<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:42:41.047595+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45055641</id><title>Some thoughts on LLMs and software development</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:31.837925+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="192b3375fcf305ad"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Some thoughts on LLMs and Software Development&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâm about to head away from looking after this site for a few weeks (part vacation, part work stuff). As I contemplate some weeks away from the daily routine, I feel an urge to share some scattered thoughts about the state of LLMs and AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâve seen a few early surveys on the effect AI is having on software development, is it really speeding folks up, does it improve or wreck code quality? One of the big problems with these surveys is that they arenât taking into account how people are using the LLMs. From what I can tell the vast majority of LLM usage is fancy auto-complete, often using co-pilot. But those I know who get the most value from LLMs reckon that auto-complete isnât very useful, preferring approaches that allow the LLM to directly read and edit source code files to carry out tasks. My concern is that surveys that ignore the different work-flows of using LLMs will produce data thatâs going to send people down the wrong paths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Another complication is the varying capabilities of different models.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâm often asked, âwhat is the future of programming?â Should people consider entering software development now? Will LLMs eliminate the need for junior engineers? Should senior engineers get out of the profession before itâs too late? My answer to all these questions is âI havenât the foggiestâ. Furthermore I think anyone who says they know what this future will be is talking from an inappropriate orifice. We are still figuring out how to use LLMs, and it will be some time before we have a decent idea of how to use them well, especially if they gain significant improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I suggest, is that people experiment with them. At the least, read about what others are doing, but pay attention to the details of their workflows. Preferably experiment yourself, and do share your experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâm also asked: âis AI a bubbleâ? To which my answer is âOF COURSE ITâS A BUBBLEâ. All major technological advances have come with economic bubbles, from canals and railroads to the internet. We know with near 100% certainty that this bubble will pop, causing lots of investments to fizzle to nothing. However what we donât know is when it will pop, and thus how big the bubble will have grown, generating some real value in the process, before that happens. It could pop next month, or not for a couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also know that when the bubble pops, many firms will go bust, but not all. When the dot-com bubble burst, it killed pets.com, it killed Webvanâ¦ but it did not kill Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I retired from public speaking a couple of years ago. But while I donât miss the stress of giving talks, I do miss hanging out with my friends in the industry. So Iâm looking forward to catching up with many of them at GOTO Copenhagen. Iâve been involved with the GOTO conference series since the 1990s (when it was called JAOO), and continue to be impressed with how they put together a fascinating program.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â â¢Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My former colleague Rebecca Parsons, has been saying for a long time that hallucinations arenât a bug of LLMs, they are a feature. Indeed they are the feature. All an LLM does is produce hallucinations, itâs just that we find some of them useful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the consequences of this is that we should always consider asking the LLM the same question more than once, perhaps with some variation in the wording. Then we can compare answers, indeed perhaps ask the LLM to compare answers for us. The difference in the answers can be as useful as the answers themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Certainly if we ever ask a hallucination engine for a numeric answer, we should ask it at least three times, so we get some sense of the variation. Furthermore we shouldnât ask an LLM to calculate an answer than we can calculate deterministically (yes, Iâve seen this). It is OK to ask an LLM to generate code to calculate an answer (but still do it more than once).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other forms of engineering have to take into account the variability of the world. A structural engineer builds in tolerance for all the factors she canât measure. (I remember being told early in my career that the unique characteristic of digital electronics was that there was no concept of tolerances.) Process engineers consider that humans are executing tasks, and will sometimes be forgetful or careless. Software Engineering is unusual in that it works with deterministic machines. Maybe LLMs mark the point where we join our engineering peers in a world on non-determinism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâve often heard, with decent reason, an LLM compared to a junior colleague. But I find LLMs are quite happy to say âall tests greenâ, yet when I run them, there are failures. If that was a junior engineerâs behavior, how long would it be before H.R. was involved?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â âÂ Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â Â â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLMs create a huge increase in the attack surface of software systems. Simon Willison described the The Lethal Trifecta for AI agents: an agent that combines access to your private data, exposure to untrusted content, and a way to externally communicate (âexfiltrationâ). That âuntrusted contentâ can come in all sorts of ways, ask it to read a web page, and an attacker can easily put instructions on the website in 1pt white-on-white font to trick the gullible LLM to obtain that private data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is particularly serious when it comes to agents acting in a browser. Read an attackerâs web page, and it could trick the agent to go to your bank account in another tab and âbuy you a presentâ by transferring your balance to the kind attacker. Willisonâs view is that âthe entire concept of an agentic browser extension is fatally flawed and cannot be built safelyâ.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/202508-ai-thoughts.html"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45056177</id><title>My startup banking story (2023)</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:31.650533+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="36308099c0e4fd45"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Mitchell Hashimoto&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;My Startup Banking Story&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a relatively new member of adult society, and an absolute infant of the business world, I didn't think much about bank choice. I figured: you put money in, you take money out, they're all the same. I also figured a local branch of a global bank is just a fungible tentacle of the giant banking machine, so also... who cares. Both incorrect assumptions, but let's relive and rediscover the effect of these assumptions as I did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I start my company. I am a 22 year old recent college graduate living in San Francisco and pursuing the startup dream. I file my incorporation paperwork and wait to receive the necessary information for one of the first steps in the life of any new business: opening a bank account.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My filing is processed and I receive my EIN while visiting my parents in a suburb of Los Angeles. I have time to kill during one of the days so I drive down to the nearest Chase bank branch and open a business banking account. We'll call the person who helped me at the local branch Alex (this will be important later). I fund that account with a $20,000 personal loan which was almost all of my savings. I get an account number, an online login, and boom, we're in business!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About 6 months later, I raise a ~$1M seed round. I supply my Chase business banking account information for the wire, and at close the funding is wired to the account. I am sitting in a cafe in downtown San Francisco and I receive a call from an unknown number -- it's Alex, the banker that helped me open my account. He is being very casual, sort of like "Hey, just wanted to check on things." "I noticed a big deposit and wanted to make sure you had everything you needed." etc. For my side, I am mostly confused: why is this person calling me? I mostly say things like "yes yes I'm fine" and end the call quickly. Some wheels have started turning in Southern California, and I just hadn't known it yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Someone out there is probably mentally screaming at me "you fool!" at this point. With hindsight, I agree, but I will remind you dear reader that I have only been legally allowed to purchase alcohol for just over a year at this point in my life in the story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two years since 2012 -- from a banking perspective -- are quiet. Alex doesn't call me again, and we have no changes in our banking setup. For two years, the company was in heads-down building mode. We had shown significant product traction and were now ready to ramp up hiring to continue building.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of 2014, we raise a $10.2M series A. I once again provide the same Chase business banking account and when the round closes, the funds are wired. Surprise surprise, Alex calls me! I'm starting to realize banks get an alert when there are major changes in account balances. Regardless, I once again brush Alex off -- "everything is good thanks! bye!" -- and continue on with my life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, I am bewildered that this guy I met at the random local branch to sign some papers is the one calling me, but didn't think much more of it at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once again, the two years since 2014 are mostly quiet from a banking perspective. Alex called more regularly to "check in" but otherwise nothing has changed. We still bank with Chase. I still have never gone back into a branch. I do everything online.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the fall of 2016, we raise a $24M series B. I once again provide the same Chase business banking account and when the round closes, the funds are wired. Again, Alex calls. Again, I brush him off. The bank is where I plant money, I don't need anyone calling me. I just want to focus on building the company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Throughout 2016, we had been building out an executive team for the company. And around the same time of the funding, we hire a Vice President of Finance. As he gets up to speed with our financial footing, he notices we have ~$35M sitting in cash in a Chase bank account. This is obviously not a smart thing to do, so he suggests some financial plans for how to better safeguard and utilize this mountain of cash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As part of these plans, he suggests moving to Silicon Valley Bank (SVB). They're local to the Bay Area, he's worked with them before, and their bankers understand startups. It'll make accounts receivables, payables, payroll, etc. easier. To me, a bank is a bank is a bank, and if it helps make his job easier, I support his plan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I log into the Chase online portal and initiate a wire for the full account balance to SVB. I have to pay something like a $30 fee to wire $35M (inconsequential to the story, but amusing nonetheless). Someone calls me for verification -- not Alex -- and the wire processes. Boom, we're done with Chase. Or so I think.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alex calls me the next day. The day we initiated the wire was his day off. He sounds slightly agitated. I wasn't rude to him, but I was short with him. I switched banks, that's all there is to it. Thanks and goodbye. I never talk to Alex ever again. A bank is a bank is a bank, you put money in, you get money out, I don't understand why I would need to talk to someone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I once again interrupt this story to appeal to the readers who are screaming at me and thank you for joining me on this story recounting my learning journey. Rest assured, at this point in the story, a professional was now in charge of the company's finances. But the decisions of the years leading up to this would have lingering effects for a few more years...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We now take a brief detour from the company, because this is where my personal life becomes relevant to the story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the prior three years, I had been living in Los Angeles. At some point during 2017, I had to go to a local Chase branch to make some changes to my personal accounts. It has been close to a year since the company stopped using Chase.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I visit the closest bank branch to my apartment. This bank branch is 20 miles north of where my parents live -- or the area with the branch where I opened the original company business bank accounts. I'm going to Chase for purely personal reasons, but this information is unfortunately relevant to the story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At my local branch, I walk up to the teller and provide some handwritten information: my name, account number, desired transaction, etc. The teller looks at the paper, then looks at me, then looks back at the paper, then asks "Are you the HashiCorp guy?" What? HashiCorp is doing well but its not at all something a random non-technical consumer would know about. What is going on?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I say yes and he acknowledges but doesn't automatically offer any more information. I have to know, so I continue "How do you know that?" His response is "Dude, everyone at Chase down here knows about HashiCorp." Huh?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Up to this point, everything in the story is what I know and experienced first hand. What follows however is now second hand information as told by this teller. I haven't verified it, but other employees (at other branches) have said similar things to me over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The teller proceeds to explain that Alex -- the guy I opened my original company account with -- became a fast rising star in the area. He had opened a business account in a small suburb that grew from $20,000 to $35,000,000 in balances in just four years! Despite the business (my business) not engaging in higher-revenue activities with the bank, the opportunity this account represented to the small business wing of the small suburban branch stirred up some excitement. It was just a matter of time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then, overnight, the account went to $0. Without talking to anyone, without any prior warning, that account was gone. I used online banking to transfer the entirety of the balance to another bank. The small suburban branch viewed this as a huge loss and Alex came into work with some tough questions and no answers. I instantly recalled feeling that Alex was agitated when he called me the day after the transfer, and I now had an idea of why.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't know what happened to Alex, the teller said he was "no longer working in the area" and said it with a noticably negative tone. I don't know what this means and I never found out. Perhaps, he just moved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following this event, Chase began an educational series to other local branches in the Los Angeles area explaining that there are these "startups" and how their financial patterns do not match those of a typical business. This series taught branches how to identify startups and how to consider their accounts. The case study they used for this presentation: HashiCorp.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has been two years since hiring our VP of Finance and our financial department is in really healthy shape. I still have certain approval rights but no longer directly manage the accounts of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given the recent events with Silicon Valley Bank, I feel it's important to mention that at this point of the company, we had already begun diversifying our balances across multiple banks. SVB will not be mentioned again for the remainder of the story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm working at my office at home in Los Angeles and I receive a phone call from our finance department. That's weird, I rarely receive phone calls. They tell me that during a routine internal audit, they realized there are a few customer accounts that are still paying their bill into the old Chase account.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I never closed that original Chase business account back in 2016. Let me explain how that happens. To close an account, I had to do it in person at any local Chase branch. Startups are busy, the account balance in 2016 was $0, and so I just put it off. Well, a couple years passed, it was still open, and a few customers were actually sending payments to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Worse, upon the realization that a few customers were paying into this account, our finance team realized that there was also fraud. For over a year, someone had been wiring thousands of dollars out every few weeks. We were short over $100,000 due to fraud. The finance team immediately called Chase and reported the fraud, locked down the account, and Chase started an investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the finance team wanted me to close the account and wire the remaining balance to our actual business bank. With the fraud actively being handled by Chase and the finance team, I take on the task of closing the account. I immediately head to the nearest local Chase branch (once again a branch I've never been to before) and explain the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After waiting for 15 minutes, a manager walks up to me. I know this can't be good. The branch manager explains that due to the actions taken to lock down the account for fraud, electronic transfers are unavailable. It doesn't matter that I'm provably the person who opened the account, electronic transfers are "impossible."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I say okay, and ask how I am supposed to close the account and transfer the remaining balance. He said I can close the account and withdraw the remaining balance only in cash. Cash? At this point, I literally asked: "like, green paper money cash?" He says yes. The balance in the account is somewhere around $1M.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I spent another two hours at the bank, juggling between calling our finance department, talking to this branch manager, and calling the Chase business phone line. We determine that instead of literal green cash, I can get a cashier's check. But there is a major problem: the amount the cashier's check is made out for has to be available at that local branch (or, whichever branch issues it). And, well, local branches I guess don't usually have $1M cash lying around. Or, if they do, its not enough to cover other business activities for the day so they're not willing to part with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bank manager gives me the phone number of another branch manager that "may be able to help me." He literally writes down a phone number on a piece of paper. This is all feeling so surreal. I call this number and its for a slightly larger branch a few miles down the road. He says "you're the HashiCorp guy right?" And I roll my eyes. My infamy in the area is still well known.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This manager is very helpful, if not a bit gruff. He explains to me that each local branch has some sort of performance metric based on inflows and outflows at the given branch. Therefore, funding a $1M cash withdrawal was not attractive to them. I'm learning a lot in a really condensed period of time at this point. I don't even know if what he's telling me is true, or legal, all I hear is "this is going to be hard to do if you want it all at once."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But we do want it all at once. And we want to close the account. Now. He is not happy, but he says he'll call me back in 24 to 48 hours. True to his word, he calls me back the next day. He says that he had to coordinate to ensure his branch had the proper funding to satisfy this transaction, and that the funding would be available at a specific date a few days hence. He said I have to do the withdrawal that day because his branch will not hold that amount in cash for any longer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He also subtly suggested I hire personal security or otherwise deposit those funds somewhere with haste. I believe his exact words were "if you lose that check, I can't help you." Again, this was a one time event, and I don't know how true that all is, but it was said to me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few days later, I walk into the branch (I did not hire personal security). I tell the teller my name and there is a flicker of immediate recognition. The teller guides me to a cubicle, the account is successfully closed, I'm issued a $1M cashier's check, and I walk out the door.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My business banking relationship with Chase is, at long last, complete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to make it clear that Chase could've been an excellent banking partner. I never gave them the chance. I never told them what my business does or what I'd use the money for. I never talked to anyone (besides saying what I needed to get off the phone). This story isn't a cautionary tale about Chase, it is rather recounting my naivete as a young, first-time startup founder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Epilogue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cashier's check was uneventfully deposited into our primary business banking account shortly after I walked out of the Chase branch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fraud investigation took a few months to complete but we were able to recover all of the lost funds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enough time has passed and employees cycled that I'm no longer recognized at any Los Angeles area Chase branches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I look back on these events and there are many places I cringe. At the same time, I can't imagine making different choices because I was acting in good faith at all times with the knowledge I had. I think the choices I made were reasonable for any new founder, and I know many founders who have made similar choices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, there was no long term negative impact of the events that transpired (except maybe for Alex, but I truly don't know) and I can now look back on it with amusement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://mitchellh.com/writing/my-startup-banking-story"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45057020</id><title>Fuck up my site – Turn any website into beautiful chaos</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:31.479448+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a9a77b49597bf6f1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DESTRUCTION LEVEL0%&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;▓&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;fuckupmysite&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some people just want to watch the web burn&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;😈Chaos Settings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 of 6 agents of chaos enabled&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;⚠️&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;IMPORTANT DISCLAIMER - FOR PARODY &amp;amp; ENTERTAINMENT ONLY&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This tool is for parody and entertainment purposes only. It temporarily applies visual chaos effects to websites for comedic effect. We do not store, collect, or transmit any personal information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NEVER enter passwords, credit card details, or any sensitive information while using this tool. The proxied sites are not secure and should not be used for any real transactions or logins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By using this tool, you acknowledge that it's purely for entertainment and you will not enter any sensitive data. Banking, financial, healthcare, and government sites are blocked for safety.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heads up: Not every site plays nice with the chaos. Got feedback or discovered something broken? Let me know on Twitter&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.fuckupmysite.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fnews.ycombinator.com&amp;torchCursor=true&amp;comicSans=true&amp;fakeCursors=true&amp;peskyFly=true"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45057322</id><title>Expert: LSP for Elixir</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:31.090646+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="24853a795d5f6fa5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expert is the official language server implementation for the Elixir programming language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can download Expert from the releases page for your operating system and architecture. Put the executable somewhere on your &lt;code&gt;$PATH&lt;/code&gt;, like &lt;code&gt;~/.local/bin/expert&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For editor specific installation instructions, please refer to the Installation Instructions&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to try out the latest features, you can download a nightly build.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the GH CLI, you can run the following command to download the latest nightly build:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gh release download nightly --pattern 'expert_linux_amd64' --repo elixir-lang/expert&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then point your editor to the downloaded binary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To build Expert from source, you need Zig &lt;code&gt;0.14.1&lt;/code&gt; installed on your system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then you can run the following command or follow the instructions in the Installation Instructions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;just release-local&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This will build the Expert binary and place it in the &lt;code&gt;apps/expert/burrito_out&lt;/code&gt; directory. You can then point your
editor to this binary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you to our corporate sponsors! If you'd like to start sponsoring the project, please read more below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For companies wanting to directly sponsor full time work on Expert, please reach out to Dan Janowski: EEF Chair of Sponsorship WG at danj@erlef.org.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Individuals can donate using GitHub sponsors. Team members are listed in the sidebar.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expert source code is released under Apache License 2.0.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check LICENSE file for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/elixir-lang/expert"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45057404</id><title>The Space Shuttle Columbia disaster and the over-reliance on PowerPoint (2019)</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:30.898500+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b789dbf4ae617ccb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve all sat in those presentations. A speaker with a stream of slides full of text, monotonously reading them off as we read along. We’re so used to it we expect it. We accept it. We even consider it ‘learning’. As an educator I push against ‘death by PowerPoint’ and I'm fascinated with how we can improve the way we present and teach. The fact is we know that PowerPoint kills. Most often the only victims are our audience’s inspiration and interest. This, however, is the story of a PowerPoint slide that actually helped kill seven people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;January 16th 2003. NASA Mission STS-107 is underway. The Space Shuttle Columbia launches carrying its crew of seven to low orbit. Their objective was to study the effects of microgravity on the human body and on ants and spiders they had with them. Columbia had been the first Space Shuttle, first launched in 1981 and had been on 27 missions prior to this one. Whereas other shuttle crews had focused on work to the Hubble Space Telescope or to the International Space Station this mission was one of pure scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The launch proceeded as normal. The crew settled into their mission. They would spend 16 days in orbit, completing 80 experiments. One day into their mission it was clear to those back on Earth that something had gone wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a matter of protocol NASA staff reviewed footage from an external camera mounted to the fuel tank. At eighty-two seconds into the launch a piece of spray on foam insulation (SOFI) fell from one of the ramps that attached the shuttle to its external fuel tank. As the crew rose at 28,968 kilometres per hour the piece of foam collided with one of the tiles on the outer edge of the shuttle’s left wing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was impossible to tell from Earth how much damage this foam, falling nine times faster than a fired bullet, would have caused when it collided with the wing. Foam falling during launch was nothing new. It had happened on four previous missions and was one of the reasons why the camera was there in the first place. But the tile the foam had struck was on the edge of the wing designed to protect the shuttle from the heat of Earth’s atmosphere during launch and re-entry. In space the shuttle was safe but NASA didn’t know how it would respond to re-entry. There were a number of options. The astronauts could perform a spacewalk and visually inspect the hull. NASA could launch another Space Shuttle to pick the crew up. Or they could risk re-entry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA officials sat down with Boeing Corporation engineers who took them through three reports; a total of 28 slides. The salient point was whilst there was data showing that the tiles on the shuttle wing could tolerate being hit by the foam this was based on test conditions using foam more than 600 times smaller than that that had struck Columbia. This is the slide the engineers chose to illustrate this point:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA managers listened to the engineers and their PowerPoint. The engineers felt they had communicated the potential risks. NASA felt the engineers didn’t know what would happen but that all data pointed to there not being enough damage to put the lives of the crew in danger. They rejected the other options and pushed ahead with Columbia re-entering Earth’s atmosphere as normal. Columbia was scheduled to land at 0916 (EST) on February 1st 2003. Just before 0900, 61,170 metres above Dallas at 18 times the speed of sound, temperature readings on the shuttle’s left wing were abnormally high and then were lost. Tyre pressures on the left side were soon lost as was communication with the crew. At 0912, as Columbia should have been approaching the runway, ground control heard reports from residents near Dallas that the shuttle had been seen disintegrating. Columbia was lost and with it her crew of seven. The oldest crew member was 48.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The shuttle programme was on lock down, grounded for two years as the investigation began. The cause of the accident became clear: a hole in a tile on the left wing caused by the foam let the wing dangerously overheat until the shuttle disintegrated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The questions to answer included a very simple one: Why, given that the foam strike had occurred at a force massively out of test conditions had NASA proceeded with re-entry?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edward Tufte, a Professor at Yale University and expert in communication reviewed the slideshow the Boeing engineers had given NASA, in particular the above slide. His findings were tragically profound.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, the slide had a misleadingly reassuring title claiming that test data pointed to the tile being able to withstand the foam strike. This was not the case but the presence of the title, centred in the largest font makes this seem the salient, summary point of this slide. This helped Boeing’s message be lost almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Secondly, the slide contains four different bullet points with no explanation of what they mean. This means that interpretation is left up to the reader. Is number 1 the main bullet point? Do the bullet points become less important or more? It’s not helped that there’s a change in font sizes as well. In all with bullet points and indents six levels of hierarchy were created. This allowed NASA managers to imply a hierarchy of importance in their head: the writing lower down and in smaller font was ignored. Actually, this had been where the contradictory (and most important) information was placed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thirdly, there is a huge amount of text, more than 100 words or figures on one screen. Two words, ‘SOFI’ and ‘ramp’ both mean the same thing: the foam. Vague terms are used. Sufficient is used once, significant or significantly, five times with little or no quantifiable data. As a result this left a lot open to audience interpretation. How much is significant? Is it statistical significance you mean or something else?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally the single most important fact, that the foam strike had occurred at forces massively out of test conditions, is hidden at the very bottom. Twelve little words which the audience would have had to wade through more than 100 to get to. If they even managed to keep reading to that point. In the middle it does say that it is possible for the foam to damage the tile. This is in the smallest font, lost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA’s subsequent report criticised technical aspects along with human factors. Their report mentioned an over-reliance on PowerPoint:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The Board views the endemic use of PowerPoint briefing slides instead of technical papers as an illustration of the problematic methods of technical communication at NASA.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edward Tufte’s full report makes for fascinating reading. Since being released in 1987 PowerPoint has grown exponentially to the point where it is now estimated than thirty million PowerPoint presentations are made every day. Yet, PowerPoint is blamed by academics for killing critical thought. Amazon’s CEO Jeff Bezos has banned it from meetings. Typing text on a screen and reading it out loud does not count as teaching. An audience reading text off the screen does not count as learning. Imagine if the engineers had put up a slide with just: “foam strike more than 600 times bigger than test data.” Maybe NASA would have listened. Maybe they wouldn’t have attempted re-entry. Next time you’re asked to give a talk remember Columbia. Don’t just jump to your laptop and write out slides of text. Think about your message. Don’t let that message be lost amongst text. Death by PowerPoint is a real thing. Sometimes literally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- Jamie&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://mcdreeamiemusings.com/blog/2019/4/13/gsux1h6bnt8lqjd7w2t2mtvfg81uhx"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45057561</id><title>Rupert's Property</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:30.844477+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="37eaebb6d330d3b1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can cut a hole in a cube that’s big enough to slide an identical cube through that hole! Think about that for a minute—it’s kind of weird.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazingly, nobody could prove any convex polyhedron doesn’t have this property! It’s called ‘Rupert’s property’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Until this week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This week Steininger and Yurkevich proved there is a convex polyhedron that you can’t cut a hole in big enough to slide the entire polyhedron through the hole. It has 90 vertices, and apparently 240 edges and 152 faces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To prove that no such hole is possible, they had to do a computer search of 18 million different holes, plus use a lot of extra math to make sure they’d checked enough possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Jakob Steininger and Sergey Yurkevich, A convex polyhedron without Rupert’s property.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To celebrate their discovery, they gave this polyhedron a silly name. Since this polyhedron lacks Rupert’s property, they called it a ‘noperthedron’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why is this property called ‘Rupert’s property’? Wikipedia explains:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In geometry, Prince Rupert’s cube is the largest cube that can pass through a hole cut through a unit cube without splitting it into separate pieces. Its side length is approximately 1.06, 6% larger than the side length 1 of the unit cube through which it passes. The problem of finding the largest square that lies entirely within a unit cube is closely related, and has the same solution.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Prince Rupert’s cube is named after Prince Rupert of the Rhine, who asked whether a cube could be passed through a hole made in another cube of the same size without splitting the cube into two pieces. A positive answer was given by John Wallis. Approximately 100 years later, Pieter Nieuwland found the largest possible cube that can pass through a hole in a unit cube.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here Greg Egan shows how Rupert’s property works for the cube:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here he shows how it works for the regular octahedron:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And finally, here’s a video by David Renshaw showing 26 polyhedra with Rupert’s property… and 5 polyhedra that might lack it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The triakis tetrahedron is an extremely close call, but it does have Rupert’s property:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2025/08/28/a-polyhedron-without-ruperts-property/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45058688</id><title>Claude Sonnet will ship in Xcode</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:30.670564+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="33a9437a9587dba1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This page requires JavaScript. Please turn on JavaScript in your browser and refresh the page to view its content.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/xcode-release-notes/xcode-26-release-notes"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45059160</id><title>Lucky 13: a look at Debian trixie</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:30.448214+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="8cefd81dd907e69e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Lucky 13: a look at Debian trixie&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;This article brought to you by LWN subscribers&lt;p&gt;Subscribers to LWN.net made this article — and everything that surrounds it — possible. If you appreciate our content, please buy a subscription and make the next set of articles possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After more than two years of development, the Debian Project has released its new stable version, Debian 13 ("trixie"). The release comes with the usual bounty of upgraded packages and more than 14,000 new packages; it also debuts Advanced Package Tool (APT) 3.0 as the default package manager and makes 64-bit RISC-V a supported architecture. There are few surprises with trixie, which is exactly what many Linux users are hoping for—a free operating system that just works as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Debian's stable releases are aptly named; the project prioritizes stability over shipping the latest software. The freeze schedule for trixie called for a soft freeze in April, which meant that (for example) the KDE Plasma 6.4 release in June was too late to make the cut—even though trixie was not released until August. Users who prefer to live on the edge will want to run another distribution or follow Debian development by running the testing release that previews the next stable version—Debian 14 ("forky"). Truly adventurous users may take their chances with the unstable ("sid") release.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, trixie is up-to-date enough for many folks; it includes GNOME 48, KDE Plasma 6.3, Xfce 4.20, GNU Emacs 30.1, GnuPG 2.4.7, LibreOffice 25.2, and more. Under the hood, it includes the most recent Linux LTS kernel (6.12.41), GNU Compiler Collection (GCC) 14.2, GNU C Library (glibc) 2.41, LLVM/Clang 19, Python 3.13, Rust 1.85, and systemd 257. The release notes have a section for well-known software that compares the version in Debian 12 against Debian 13. While some of the versions lag a bit behind the upstream, they are not woefully outdated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The project now supports six major hardware architectures: x86-64/amd64, 32-bit Arm with a hardware FPU (armhf), 64-bit Arm (arm64), IBM POWER8 or newer (ppc64el), IBM S/390 (s390x), and 64-bit RISC-V. The i386 architecture is not supported for trixie, though the project continues to build some i386 packages to run on 64-bit systems; users with i386 systems cannot upgrade to trixie. The MIPS architectures (mipsel and mis64el) have also been removed in trixie.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Arm EABI (armel) port that targets older 32-bit Arm devices prior to Arm v7 is still supported with trixie, but this release is the end of the line. There is no installation media for armel systems, but users who have bookworm installed can upgrade to trixie if they have supported hardware: the Raspberry Pi 1, Zero, and Zero W are the only devices mentioned in the release notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upgrades from bookworm are supported, of course. The release notes suggest that users convert APT source files to the DEB822 format before the upgrade. APT 3.0 includes an "apt modernize-sources" command to convert APT data source files to DEB822, but that is not available in bookworm. Users are also expected to remove all third-party packages prior to running the upgrade. I tested the upgrade on one of my servers, after taking a snapshot to roll back to if needed, and all went smoothly. Users who are considering an upgrade should read the release notes carefully before forging ahead; in particular, users should be aware that it's possible (but not certain) for network interface names to change on upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Installation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For users who want to start fresh, Debian offers a variety of installer images and download methods; users can choose a 64MB minimal ISO image with the netboot installer, all the way up to a set of Blu-ray images. The project recommends using BitTorrent or Jigsaw Download (jigdo) for the largest images. BitTorrent probably needs no introduction, but jigdo is not as well-known. Jigdo is a method of downloading all of the individual packages for an image from multiple mirrors and then assembling them into an ISO image on the user's machine. It was a bit fiddly to use jigdo to download an image, but not overly so—and the speed of the whole process was comparable to simply downloading an ISO of the same size.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Debian's network install ("netinst") image is probably the best option for server installations and for experienced Linux users; it includes the packages required for a base install and then fetches the remaining software from Debian mirrors. Unlike the tiny netboot image, it includes the option of using either the graphical installer or the text-based installer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The installer is a bit of a throwback to an earlier era when users were expected to know a lot more about the workings of a Linux system. Users who have only worked with distributions like Fedora and Ubuntu will notice that installing Debian requires many more steps than other popular distributions. For example, many desktop distributions have eliminated the step of setting a password for the root user—instead, it is generally assumed that the primary user will also be the system administrator, so the default is to give the primary user sudo privileges instead. Debian does not take that approach; &lt;del&gt;in fact, there is no way to give a user sudo privileges during installation. Setting up sudo has to be done manually after the installation is completed&lt;/del&gt; Update: Users can skip creation of a root account and the installer will then set up the regular user as an administrator with sudo permissions. Apologies for the error.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For some folks, installing Debian will be a bit of a chore and may even be confusing for users who are new to Linux. For example, the text-mode installer requires users to specify the device for GRUB boot loader installation, without providing a default. If one chooses an invalid partition, the installer tells the user that the operation has failed and drops back to a menu listing all the installation steps. Presumably if one picks the wrong partition it will happily install GRUB to that and render the system unbootable. This is not insurmountable for experienced Linux users, but it would no doubt be a hurdle for many users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More experienced Linux users are likely to appreciate the amount of control offered by the installer. For example, Fedora's recent web-based installer makes it difficult to even find the option to perform custom partitioning. Debian has a guided partitioning option for those who do not want to fuss with it, but the option to create custom partitions is not hidden from the user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Debian has a better installation option for newer Linux users, though it is easy to miss: the live install images, which use the Calamares installer. Its workflow is more akin to the installation process one finds with Fedora and Ubuntu; it also sets up the primary user with sudo privileges rather than creating a root password. Unfortunately, the live images are not listed on the main page for installer images—though they are mentioned, briefly, in the release notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Debian installer also has the option of using a Braille display and/or speech synthesizer voice for the installation. I have not tried these options, but they are available for users who need them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;X.org&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many distributions are in the process of phasing out X.org support for GNOME and KDE as the upstream projects have started doing so. For example, Fedora will remove X.org session support for GNOME in Fedora 43, and the plan is for Ubuntu to do the same in its upcoming 25.10 release. GNOME will be completely removing X.org support in GNOME 49, which is planned for September.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Much has already been said about this, of course, and there is likely little new left to be said or that needs to be said. However, for users who still need or want X.org support, Debian 13 includes X.org sessions for GNOME and KDE. In testing trixie, I've spent some time in the GNOME and KDE X.org sessions as well as the Wayland sessions; if there are any gotchas or horrible bugs, I haven't encountered them (yet). This might be a compelling reason for some folks to switch to (or stick with) Debian.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Trying trixie&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I use Debian for my personal web site and blogs, but it has been quite some time since I used it as my primary desktop operating system. Debian (and Ubuntu) derivatives, such as Linux Mint and Pop!_OS, yes—but it's been several years since I've used vanilla Debian on the desktop for more than casual tinkering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Debian release announcement boasts about the number of packages included in trixie: 64,419 packages total, with 14,100 added and more than 6,000 removed as obsolete since bookworm. That is quite a few packages, but falls short of some other distributions. For example, "dnf repoquery --repo=fedora --available" shows more than 76,000 packages available for Fedora 42.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After installing Debian, I went to install some of my preferred software, such as aerc, Ghostty, niri, and Speech Note. The aerc packages in trixie are current, but Ghostty and niri are not packaged for Debian at all. Ghostty is written in Zig, which is also not available, so users who want to build it from source will need to install Zig separately and then build Ghostty. Speech Note is packaged as a Flatpak, but Debian does not enable Flatpaks or Flathub in the GNOME Software Store by default. Users who want Flatpaks on Debian via Flathub will need to install the flatpak package and manually add the Flathub repo:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;flatpak remote-add --if-not-exists flathub \ https://dl.flathub.org/repo/flathub.flatpakrepo&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users will need to add the gnome-software-plugin-flatpak package for Flatpak support in GNOME Software, and plasma-discover-backend-flatpak to add it to KDE Discover.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trixie ships with the Firefox extended-support release (ESR) by default: Firefox 128, which was released in July 2024. Happily, Mozilla offers a Debian repository for those who want to run more current versions. Even better, there is a little-advertised utility called extrepo that has a curated list of external repositories users might want to enable for Debian. To enable the Mozilla repository, for example, a user only needs to install extrepo, run "extrepo enable mozilla" as root (or with sudo), update the package cache, and look for the regular Firefox package. In all, extrepo includes more than 160 external repositories for applications like Docker CE, Signal, and Syncthing. Unfortunately, the extrepo utility does not have a separate "list" command to show the available repositories, though running "extrepo search" with no search parameter will return all of its DEB822-formatted repository entries. Some of the software is in an external repository due to a non-free license, other software (like Firefox) just has a development cycle that outpaces Debian's.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As one might expect, the Debian desktop experience is not dramatically different from other distributions; GNOME 48 on Debian is little different than GNOME 48 on Fedora, and the same is true for KDE, Xfce, etc. The primary difference is that users can expect more or less the same desktop experience running Debian stable in two years that they have today, which is not necessarily true for other distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the features in Debian 13 is something that most users won't notice or appreciate at all: a transition to 64-bit time_t on 32-bit architectures, to avoid the Year 2038 problem. The short version is that 32-bit integers cannot hold a Unix epoch timestamp for dates after January 19, 2038. That may seem like a distant concern, even irrelevant for Debian trixie; after all, Debian 13 is only supported by the project until 2030. However, the project expects that some 32-bit embedded systems will still be running trixie in 2038, so Debian developers did the heavy lifting to complete the transition to 64-bit time_t now. LWN covered the early planning for this in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By now, most users have retired their DSA SSH keys; if not, now is the time to do so. DSA keys were disabled by default with OpenSSH in 2015, and they are entirely disabled now with the openssh-client and openssh-server packages in trixie. If there is a device that can, for some reason, only be connected to with DSA, users can install the openssh-client-ssh1 package and use ssh1 to make the connection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we covered in June 2024, Debian 13 has switched to using a tmpfs filesystem for the /tmp directory. By default, Debian allocates up to 50% of memory to /tmp, but this can be changed by following the instructions in the release notes. Note that this also applies to systems that are upgraded to trixie from bookworm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Forward to forky&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Debian Project Leader (DPL) Andreas Tille recently announced "&lt;quote&gt;Debian's 100000th birthday&lt;/quote&gt;", so clearly the project has a bit of experience with putting out solid releases. Granted, he was reporting the number in binary, but even when converted to decimal numbers (32 years), it's an impressive track record.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While testing, I installed trixie on a couple of systems, including a new Framework 12-inch laptop. My original intent was to just see whether Debian had any problems with the new hardware (it didn't), but now I'm leaning toward sticking with Debian on this system for a while to see if stability suits me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With trixie out the door, the Debian Project has already turned its attention to working on forky, which has no release date set. Debian has stuck to a loose schedule of a new stable release roughly every two years. Most likely we will see Debian 14 sometime in 2027. After the forky release, trixie will still receive updates from Debian's security team through 2028, and then from its LTS team through 2030.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As of yet, there are no major new features or changes announced for forky; it seems likely that those will be coming to light in the coming months now that the project has trixie out the door. LWN will, of course, be reporting on those developments as they happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Posted Aug 20, 2025 13:54 UTC (Wed) by bluca (subscriber, #118303) [Link] (12 responses) It's been a while, but IIRC if you skip setting a root password in the installer, then the created user will be added automatically to the sudo group Posted Aug 20, 2025 14:07 UTC (Wed) by rschroev (subscriber, #4164) [Link] (4 responses) &amp;gt; Alternatively, you can lock the root account's password by leaving this setting empty, and instead use the system's initial user account (which will be set up in the next step) to gain administrative privileges. This will be enabled for you by adding that initial user to the 'sudo' group. Admittedly it's quite a wall of text. If you do leave the root password empty (and only then) is sudo installed automatically, with a config file that grants sudo access to users in the sudo group, in addition to putting the initial user in that sudo group. Posted Aug 20, 2025 14:11 UTC (Wed) by jzb (editor, #7867) [Link] (2 responses) Posted Aug 20, 2025 14:17 UTC (Wed) by rschroev (subscriber, #4164) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Aug 21, 2025 11:40 UTC (Thu) by Karellen (subscriber, #67644) [Link] Posted Aug 20, 2025 14:14 UTC (Wed) by jzb (editor, #7867) [Link] Posted Aug 20, 2025 14:09 UTC (Wed) by jzb (editor, #7867) [Link] (4 responses) Posted Aug 20, 2025 17:48 UTC (Wed) by josh (subscriber, #17465) [Link] (3 responses) Posted Aug 21, 2025 10:55 UTC (Thu) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] (2 responses) I want a root password for login as root, Which means that with the current installer I currently am forced to set up sudo(8) after installation. Posted Aug 21, 2025 12:43 UTC (Thu) by rschroev (subscriber, #4164) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Aug 21, 2025 19:07 UTC (Thu) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] Yup, that's an alternative I always thought should be possible. I never tried it, though. Since I know my approach works, it always felt risky to try it in the other way. :) Also, I have a sudoers file that I just cp(1) into /etc/sudoers.d and it works, which is easy. (Although it is painful to install and configure sudo(8) until I actually have sudo(8).) Posted Aug 20, 2025 14:11 UTC (Wed) by smcv (subscriber, #53363) [Link] (1 responses) &amp;gt; To allow direct password-based access via the 'root' account, Posted Aug 29, 2025 9:26 UTC (Fri) by emorrp1 (guest, #99512) [Link] Posted Aug 20, 2025 16:06 UTC (Wed) by cjwatson (subscriber, #7322) [Link] Posted Aug 20, 2025 17:48 UTC (Wed) by josh (subscriber, #17465) [Link] I see what you did there. Posted Aug 21, 2025 4:17 UTC (Thu) by alison (subscriber, #63752) [Link] (5 responses) Posted Aug 21, 2025 13:59 UTC (Thu) by jzb (editor, #7867) [Link] (2 responses) If you're getting Firefox ESR from the Debian repositories, then it is updated by the Debian packagers with a number of patches applied. You can examine the patches applied to various versions here: https://sources.debian.org/patches/firefox-esr/. The new ML features postdate Firefox 128, I believe, so it's unclear right now if they'll turn those off or not. I wouldn't be surprised if they do... If you want current-ish Firefox without some of the AI-type stuff, you might check out LibreWolf or other forks. Posted Aug 22, 2025 4:52 UTC (Fri) by alison (subscriber, #63752) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Aug 29, 2025 13:17 UTC (Fri) by MKesper (subscriber, #38539) [Link] Posted Aug 22, 2025 3:04 UTC (Fri) by pabs (subscriber, #43278) [Link] Posted Aug 29, 2025 9:21 UTC (Fri) by emorrp1 (guest, #99512) [Link] https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/firefox-esr/news/?page=3 (for the exact dates we got 128.3) If you install from outside of debian (e.g. extrepo) then yes obviously it's cycle will be outside of distro control. Posted Aug 21, 2025 11:25 UTC (Thu) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] (2 responses) This is not recommended. testing is the least secure flavour of Debian, as bug fixes are applied to stable (if appropriate), and also arrive at unstable (Sid) as normal patches, but due to migration policies, they can take months to arrive at testing. See &amp;lt;https://www.debian.org/doc/manuals/debian-faq/choosing.en...&amp;gt;. Posted Aug 22, 2025 3:14 UTC (Fri) by pabs (subscriber, #43278) [Link] (1 responses) https://wiki.debian.org/DebianTesting#Best_practices_for_... I have been using this setup for years, it works great. Posted Aug 22, 2025 7:19 UTC (Fri) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] Recommending testing over unstable, saying that testing is for the bleeding edge and unstable is for the adventurous, that's at least a dangerous recommendation. Such a recommendation would need to come with a disclosure that unstable is safer (even if it might crash more often) and explains how to deal with the security issues in testing. Posted Aug 21, 2025 14:22 UTC (Thu) by tcabot (subscriber, #6656) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Aug 29, 2025 12:56 UTC (Fri) by kkremitzki (subscriber, #115703) [Link] https://packages.debian.org/trixie/all/extrepo-offline-da... &lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; and I also want sudo(8) for my primary account.&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; you can set the password for that account here.&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; .&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; Alternatively, you can lock the root account's password&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; by leaving this setting empty, and&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; instead use the system's initial user account&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; (which will be set up in the next step)&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; to gain administrative privileges.&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; This will be enabled for you&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; by adding that initial user to the 'sudo' group.&lt;head&gt;sudo user&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;64-bit time_t&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;aptly named&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;thanks for the informative article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;thanks for the informative article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;thanks for the informative article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;thanks for the informative article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; It's configurable and can also be disabled, if you decide to do so.&lt;lb/&gt; I never saw Firefox doing a restart itself, though. It displays a message to restart it myself to be able to continue browsing.&lt;head&gt;thanks for the informative article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;thanks for the informative article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;testing is for actually testing. unstable is for users who want the bleeding edge&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;testing is for actually testing. unstable is for users who want the bleeding edge&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;testing is for actually testing. unstable is for users who want the bleeding edge&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;TIL about extrepo&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;TIL about extrepo&lt;/head&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lwn.net/Articles/1033474/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45060004</id><title>PSA: Libxslt is unmaintained and has 5 unpatched security bugs</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:30.289513+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1599f515f4b7b7f2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On 6/16/25 15:12, Alan Coopersmith wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; BTW, users of libxml2 may also be using its sibling project, libxslt, which currently has no active maintainer, but has three unfixed security issues reported against it according to https://gitlab.gnome.org/Teams/Releng/security/-/wikis/2025#libxml2-and-libxslt &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;2 of the 3 have now been disclosed:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;(CVE-2025-7424) libxslt: Type confusion in xmlNode.psvi between stylesheet and source nodes&lt;lb/&gt; https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/libxslt/-/issues/139 https://project-zero.issues.chromium.org/issues/409761909&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;(CVE-2025-7425) libxslt: heap-use-after-free in xmlFreeID caused by `atype` corruption&lt;lb/&gt; https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/libxslt/-/issues/140&lt;lb/&gt;https://project-zero.issues.chromium.org/issues/410569369&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Engineers from Apple &amp;amp; Google have proposed patches in the GNOME gitlab issues, but neither has had a fix applied to the git repo since there is currently no maintainer for libxslt.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://vuxml.freebsd.org/freebsd/b0a3466f-5efc-11f0-ae84-99047d0a6bcc.html"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45060161</id><title>Strange CW Keys</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:29.750710+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7ff4f9d4ca9ca5f5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Made by OH6DC&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also use the Text-only index page (divided into useful categories).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lever arch file CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lambic pedals&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valentine's day lollipop CW paddle&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rubber stamp CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Letter scale CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clamp cootie&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Code book&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pepper mill CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lightsaber CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nutcracker CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Straight(ener) key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smoke alarm CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Teletubbygraph key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Soap dispenser CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vinyl record player CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moomin triangle CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Antiperspirant roll-on CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dual banana CW paddle&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Power twister CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Handsaw CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hole punch CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Watering can CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Toilet brush CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CW glove&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remote control CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tea bag CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eyebrow-raising CW key with optical transmitter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back scratcher CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whisk CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pliers CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Liver casserole CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Licorice pipe CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chocolate CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ski-W key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Power drill CW keyer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Six megapixel CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Suspenders CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spirit bottle cap CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speed skate CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flower CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Knee pad sideswiper CW key for portable operation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;QRP transmitter powered by a CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alarm clock CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hammer CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CW gun&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nail clipper CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ballpoint pen CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rotary dial CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hammock CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joystick CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rowing boat CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Guitar CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wallet CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radio controlled CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amaryllis telegraphiensis&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multi-function knife with CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Toilet paper roll CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Table ice hockey CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Big toe CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Waffle iron CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lego straight key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lego bug&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pogo stick CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Crutch CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smoke signal CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CCW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Necktie CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Toothbrush CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bench press CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Handshake CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chopsticks CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trailer hitch CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Typewriter CW keyboard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Refrigerator CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mobile phone CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paper cup iambic paddles&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Morsetrap CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fingertips CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vacuum cleaner semi-automatic CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Banana CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rolling pin CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Toaster CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cheese slicer CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rocking chair CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;QLF pedal for left foot CW&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cross-country ski shoe CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CW insoles&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;QRQ paddles&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Onion chopper CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beer can CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Egg slicer CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stapler CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bicycle pump CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iron bar CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Homebrew semi-automatic bug&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hacksaw blade sideswiper CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Plywood CW key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Home | Homebrew QRP&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://sites.google.com/site/oh6dccw/strangecwkeys"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45060920</id><title>The Synology End Game</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:29.532280+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="76308b4ebfbc685d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been a Synology fan for many years. I used to roll my own NAS servers for home, but eventually decided that quieter, more energy-friendly dedicated NAS solutions were a better path forward. I don’t use a lot of their on-board apps, just basic file storage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right now I’ve got a DS920, a DS418, and a DS1522…but I probably won’t be buying another Synology again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Their abusive, customer-hostile policies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Samba Limits&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started getting queasy when I read earlier this year that on some models, they limit how many concurrent connections you can make. I though this was just something setup by default in smb.conf, but in fact Synology has a proprietary wrapper around the daemon that artificially limits it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whiskey. Tango. Foxtrot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;You Must Buy Your Hard Drives From Us&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a long time, Synology has only officially supported certain hard drives. I don’t have a problem with this, for three reasons. First, it was a pretty extensive list and included all the major players (WD, Seagate, etc.). Second, it’s unreasonable to expect Synology to certify every single hard drive from every maker on the planet. And finally, it was just a support limit. In other words, you could use whatever hard drives you wanted, but if there was a problem, they wouldn’t be able to support you if the drive wasn’t on their list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I could live with that. What I can’t live with is the new policy, implemented this year, where you must buy your drives from Synology. This only affects new models from this year forward. Details still seem sketchy, but rumor is that it’s going to be along the lines of “we don’t recognize your WD Black hard drive, therefore we won’t use it.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And by the way, Synology’s hard drives aren’t all that great. My WD Blacks come with a 5 year warranty. Synology’s only come with 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Golf. Foxtrot. Yankee.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Where to Now?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I could go back to building my own, with TrueNAS. In the past, my home-build NAS boxes were hand-me-down gaming PCs (because they were big enough towers) but I have to imagine one can find a case that allows tons of drives and is still powered by something modest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or I may look at UGREEN. Or Buffalo. Or someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lowendbox.com/blog/they-used-to-be-good-but-now-theyve-turned-to-evil-the-synology-end-game/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45061689</id><title>Contrastive Representations for Temporal Reasoning</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:29.404367+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2bf0677682200a82"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key Question: Can we improve temporal reasoning by learning better representations?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Method: A novel negative sampling scheme provably enables learning temporal representations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Result: CRTR learns representations that enable solving Rubik's Cube without hand-crafted heuristics and improves the success rates overall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In classical AI, perception relies on learning spatial representations, while planning—temporal reasoning over action sequences—is typically achieved through search. We study whether such reasoning can instead emerge from representations that capture both spatial and temporal structure. We show that standard temporal contrastive learning, despite its popularity, often fails to capture temporal structure, due to reliance on spurious features. To address this, we introduce Contrastive Representations for Temporal Reasoning (CRTR), a method that uses a negative sampling scheme to provably remove these spurious features and facilitate temporal reasoning. CRTR achieves strong results on domains with complex temporal structure, such as Sokoban and Rubik’s Cube. In particular, for the Rubik’s Cube, CRTR learns representations that generalize across all initial states and allow solving the puzzle much faster than BestFS—though with longer solutions. To our knowledge, this is the first demonstration of efficiently solving arbitrary Cube states using only learned representations, without hand-crafted search heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CRTR performs well in all the evaluated domains. Success rate as a function of search budget across five domains. CRTR compared to baselines: CRL, Supervised and DeepCubeA. Results are averaged over 5 seeds; shaded regions indicate standard error. For the Rubik's Cube, both the supervised and random baselines achieve a success rate of zero for all search budgets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Distances given by CRTR representations reflect the temporal structure well. Correlation (Spearman's ρ) between the distance induced by learned embeddings and actual distance across the training, CRTR compared with CRL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CRTR solves most tasks without requiring any search. Adding BestFS results in shorter solutions. We plot the fraction of configurations solved with a solution length of at most x, while limiting the number of nodes created to 6000. Surprisingly, on the Rubik's cube CRTR achieves a higher success rate without search, solving all board configurations within the budget.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CRTR without search exhibits a block-building-like behavior. Intermediate states from solving a randomly scrambled cube, illustrating how the algorithm gradually builds partial structure. The average solve is about 400 moves, and we see similar block building behavior across solves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://princeton-rl.github.io/CRTR/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45061980</id><title>Probability of typing a wrong Bitcoin address</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:47:29.246287+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6bf701d5a06fb3fd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I heard someone say that Bitcoin is dangerous because you could easily make a typo when entering an address, sending money to the wrong person, and have no recourse. There are dangers associated with Bitcoin, such as losing a private key, but address typos are not a major concern.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Checksums&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are several kinds of Bitcoin addresses. Each is at least 20 bytes (160 bits) long, with at least 4 bytes (32 bits) of checksum. The chances of a typo resulting in a valid checksum are about 1 in 232.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Used addresses&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s ignore the checksum for this section.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because addresses are formed by cryptographic hash functions, we can assume the values are essentially randomly distributed in the space of possible addresses. The addresses are deterministic, but for modeling purposes, random is as random does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means a typo of an actual address is no more or less likely to be another actual address than an address typed at random. This is unlike, say, English words: a mistyped English word is more likely to be another English word than random keystrokes would be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There have been on the order of a billion Bitcoin addresses used, in a space of 2160 possibilities. (Actually more since some addresses have more than 160 bits.) There’s about a 1 in 1039 chance that a random 160-bit sequence corresponds to an address somewhere on the Bitcoin blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Addresses close in edit distance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Someone with the Caesarean handle Veni Vidi Vici on X asked&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;What about the odds that out of those 1B addresses, two of them are one character swap away from each other?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s an interesting question. Let’s assume the addresses are Base58-encoded strings of length 26. Addresses could be longer, but assuming the minimum length increases the probability of addresses being close.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How many addresses are within one or two character swaps of another? I addressed a similar question here a couple weeks ago. If all the characters were unique, the number of strings within k swaps of each other would be&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|S1(26, 26 − k)|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;where S1 denotes Stirling numbers of the first kind. For k = 1 this would be 325 and for k = 2 this would be 50,050. This assumes all the characters are unique; I haven’t thought through the case where characters are repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For round numbers, let’s say there are a billion addresses, and for each address there are a million other addresses that are close in some sense, plausible typos of the address. That would be 1012 addresses and typos, spread out in a space of ≈1045 (i.e. 5826) possible addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now there’s an implicit Birthday Problem here. No particular address is likely to collide with another, even when you allow typos, but what about the likelihood that some address collides?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Say we partition our space of 1045 addresses into N = 1029 addresses with a million possible typos for each address. Then as a rule of thumb, you’d need around √N random draws before you have a 50-50 chance of seeing a collision. Since 109 is a lot less than 1014.5, it’s unlikely that any two addresses collide, even when you consider each address along with a million associated typos.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/08/28/wrong-address/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45062614</id><title>Tesla said it didn't have key data in a fatal crash. Then a hacker found it</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:42:42.409049+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2025/08/29/tesla-autopilot-crashes-evidence-testimony-wrongful-death/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45062683</id><title>Anthropic reverses privacy stance, will train on Claude chats</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:42:42.349993+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.perplexity.ai/page/anthropic-reverses-privacy-sta-xH4KWU9nS3KH4Aj9F12dvQ"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45062738</id><title>If you have a Claude account, they're going to train on your data moving forward</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:42:42.298911+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://old.reddit.com/r/LocalLLaMA/comments/1n2ubjx/if_you_have_a_claude_personal_account_they_are/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45062910</id><title>Meta might be secretly scanning your phone's camera roll</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:42:41.995589+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b4b2db1208265aff"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;'ZDNET Recommends': What exactly does it mean?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ZDNET's recommendations are based on many hours of testing, research, and comparison shopping. We gather data from the best available sources, including vendor and retailer listings as well as other relevant and independent reviews sites. And we pore over customer reviews to find out what matters to real people who already own and use the products and services we’re assessing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you click through from our site to a retailer and buy a product or service, we may earn affiliate commissions. This helps support our work, but does not affect what we cover or how, and it does not affect the price you pay. Neither ZDNET nor the author are compensated for these independent reviews. Indeed, we follow strict guidelines that ensure our editorial content is never influenced by advertisers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ZDNET's editorial team writes on behalf of you, our reader. Our goal is to deliver the most accurate information and the most knowledgeable advice possible in order to help you make smarter buying decisions on tech gear and a wide array of products and services. Our editors thoroughly review and fact-check every article to ensure that our content meets the highest standards. If we have made an error or published misleading information, we will correct or clarify the article. If you see inaccuracies in our content, please report the mistake via this form.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Meta might be secretly scanning your phone's camera roll - how to check and turn it off&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow ZDNET: Add us as a preferred source on Google.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;ZDNET's key takeaways&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Meta could be scanning your camera roll right now.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It's using your photos to provide AI-powered suggestions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check Facebook settings to turn off the features.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta could be analyzing and retaining your phone's photos without your explicit consent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some Facebook users have noticed that, deep within their app settings, Meta has switched on two toggles that allow it to access their camera roll to offer AI-powered suggestions, including "personalized creative ideas, like travel highlights and collages."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also: How to delete Facebook, Messenger, or Instagram - if you want Meta out of your life&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem? The toggles for the AI suggestion features, called "camera roll sharing suggestions," appear to be turned on for users who claim they haven't seen a pop-up from Facebook asking for permission to enable them. If you get that "cloud processing" pop-up and tap "Allow" on it, you'll agree to Meta's AI Terms of Service and permit your "media and facial features" to be analyzed by AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Facebook will then use your camera roll images -- including the dates on them and the presence of people or objects -- to suggest collages, themed albums, recap posts, or AI restyled versions of your pictures. These AI suggestions are only visible to you, unless you choose to share them, and Meta says the media won't be used for ad targeting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also: How to protect your privacy from Facebook - and what doesn't work&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But, to be clear, you're still giving Meta the right to access and retain your camera roll images, and that could raise serious privacy concerns, especially for users who never knowingly opted in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ZDNET's editorial director found Meta's camera roll sharing suggestions enabled in her Facebook app without her knowledge. I also noticed they were enabled for me, although I vaguely recall seeing a pop-up from Facebook about the new features a few weeks ago. I think I dismissed it quickly, and I can't remember whether I tapped Allow or Don't allow on it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to stop Facebook from scanning your camera roll&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta said its camera roll sharing suggestions are not enabled by default. If you're worried you dismissed Facebook's pop-up, unknowingly opted-in, and gave access to your camera roll, here's how to check and turn it off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;1. Open the Facebook app&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The settings you'll want to check can be found in the Facebook mobile app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Grab your iPhone or Android phone.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Open the Facebook app. You'll need to be signed into your account.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;2. Go to the Menu &amp;gt; Settings and Privacy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Facebook hides most of its settings in the menu -- the three-line hamburger icon in the bottom corner of the app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tap the Menu icon in the bottom right corner of the screen.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Once the menu opens, look for Settings and Privacy with a gear icon. This will take you directly to Settings.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3. Select Settings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you find and tap Privacy and Settings to expand the dropdown options, tap Settings again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Under Settings and Privacy, tap Settings.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Now, scroll down and look for "Camera roll sharing suggestions."&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;4. Go to Camera roll sharing suggestions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta placed the toggles that grant it access to your camera roll under the "Camera roll sharing suggestions" setting. You'll need to go there to see if they're on and, if so, switch them off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Look for the option labeled "Camera roll sharing suggestions" and tap it.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;This will open a preference page with a couple of toggles.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;5. Turn off both toggles&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you're inside the camera roll sharing suggestions page, notice the two separate switches. If they're blue and the toggle circle is pushed to the right, they're on -- meaning Meta is already processing and retaining your phone's photos. Turn them off so the app can't automatically upload and analyze your camera roll.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Find the option labeled "Get camera roll suggestions when you're browsing Facebook." If the switch is on (blue), tap it once to turn it off (gray). This will stop Facebook from using basic camera roll data, such as which videos you've favorited and when photos were taken, to suggest sharing media you haven't yet uploaded.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Find the option labeled "Get creative ideas made for you by allowing camera roll cloud processing." If the switch is on (blue), tap it once to turn it off (gray). This will stop Facebook from continuously uploading media from your camera roll -- and using details like time, location, themes, and the presence of people or objects -- to generate personalized creative ideas such as recaps and AI restylings.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;FAQs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why is Facebook cloud-processing my device's camera roll?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta is uploading and analyzing your camera roll photos and videos, even ones you haven't posted, in its cloud in order to generate AI-powered suggestions like collages, monthly recaps, themed albums, or AI-restyled versions of your images.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Where is this feature being tested?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta has confirmed the feature is a test, saying, "We're exploring ways to make content sharing easier for people on Facebook by testing suggestions of ready-to-share and curated content from a person's camera roll."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The test is currently available in the US and Canada, but it's not available in Illinois or Texas due to those states' privacy laws.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Did Facebook ask for my consent before turning this on?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta is showing a pop-up asking users if they want to enable cloud processing, but some users claim they haven't seen it. Instead, they found the toggles in their settings already switched on by default, raising questions about whether clear consent was given.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Can I remove my photos once they've been uploaded?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ZDNET's sister site, CNET, reports that Meta pulls from your newer pictures (roughly the last 30 days) and if you disable the feature, your uploaded photos will be deleted after 30 days. The only way to confirm is by downloading your Facebook account data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why is this a potential privacy issue?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It expands Meta's reach beyond the content you've chosen to upload and share online -- into your private, unposted photos and videos. For many, that's a major red flag and a line they're not comfortable crossing, understandably so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also: What Zuckerberg's 'personal superintelligence' sales pitch leaves out&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if Meta is asking for consent to access your camera roll in order to analyze your phone's photos and provide AI-powered suggestions, the company could have done a better job of being clear and explicit about what it's trying to do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How many users, like me, simply dismissed the consent pop-up without fully realizing what they'd just agreed to?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Editor's note: This article was updated on Aug. 24, 2025 to clarify that Meta's camera roll sharing suggestions are not turned on by default and are entirely opt-in. Still, some users say they never knowingly agreed and are finding the features enabled in their settings.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/meta-might-be-secretly-scanning-your-phones-camera-roll-how-to-check-and-turn-it-off/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45062914</id><title>Deepnote (YC S19) is hiring engineers to build a better Jupyter notebook</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:42:41.830404+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b9d2255309e5a6a1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;We build tools for explorers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are here to revolutionize how data teams work together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We started Deepnote to help data teams solve the hardest problems. We don’t just need better algorithms, bigger data sets, and more computing power. We need tools that help us explore, collaborate, and share. These tools don’t exist yet. We need to invent them first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data work is as much a scientific and creative process as it is an engineering one. It involves working together, failing, learning, and going back to the drawing board. Data professionals are explorers. To make projects successful, we need tools that are both powerful and easy to use. Tools that help us collaborate and share our work in an engaging way. Tools that make working with data fun again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s why we’re building the new standard in data tooling: a notebook that brings teams together to code, query, visualize, organize, and share — all in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are building tools for explorers. Join us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read more about us on TechCrunch&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read more about us on Nature&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Build the future with us&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re building a collaborative notebook that beautifully integrates analytics and data science into every workflow and decision. But it’s not just about designing, shipping, and selling. It’s about the people who power it — and that means you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Get ready to do your best work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transforming how people work with data isn't easy. But we built a culture that allows us to do precisely that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;We move with urgency&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are a small, passionate team revolutionizing how data teams work. We give everyone the tools they need and enable them to take action.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;We keep learning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are knowledge-seekers. We invest in continuous learning across every role and encourage a culture of proactive feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;We take ownership&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are makers. We expect everyone to be a decision-maker — no politics or walls to get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;We collaborate&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are partners. We work in a fully transparent environment and put open, effective communication above all else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Backed by the best in the business&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re backed by industry leaders — and they’re as excited about reimagining the future as we are.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Y Combinator&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Index Ventures&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Accel&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Greg Brockman&lt;p&gt;CTO at OpenAI&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Elad Gil&lt;p&gt;Angel Investor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Naval Ravikant&lt;p&gt;Angel Investor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Elena Verna&lt;p&gt;Angel Investor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Explore open positions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thousands of data professionals already use Deepnote — but we’re only scratching the surface of what’s possible. We’re building out our core team, and we want kind, curious explorers to join and grow with us.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://deepnote.com/join-us"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45063431</id><title>Gun Maker Sig Sauer Citing National Security to Keep Documents from Public</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:42:41.589221+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="df1fc178385f5482"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;In the Eighth Circuit, the Fight Over Sig Sauer’s P320 FMECA Goes Public&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The secrecy battle over the Army’s Failure Modes, Effects, and Criticality Analysis (FMECA) for Sig Sauer’s P320 has followed Glasscock v. Sig Sauer to the Eighth Circuit. A media intervenor is now asking the appellate court to keep key records open—and their brief places Practical Shooting Insights (this site) squarely in the middle of the story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s new&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Trace intervenes in the appeal. The newsroom moved to intervene for the limited purpose of opposing sealed filings tied to class certification and the FMECA, arguing the public’s right of access and noting the district court cited the FMECA nine times when it certified the class.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sig Sauer says “national security” and asks for deference to the Army. In opposing intervention, Sig Sauer urges the court to leave FMECA-related material sealed and to give the Army time to weigh in, framing the dispute in terms of protecting “military secrets.”&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A second FMECA document emerges. Sig Sauer’s opposition confirms there are two FMECA records in the class-certification exhibits: a FMECA Spreadsheet and a FMECA Memorandum—the latter not previously described in public filings—raising fresh questions about what the memo contains and who authored it.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;PSI’s reporting is part of the record. The Trace’s filing tells the court the unredacted FMECA was found on CourtListener, de‑obscured, and published on Practical Shooting Insights, where it “remains available”—and it recounts Sig Sauer’s own executive discussing it on a podcast while pointing viewers to this website.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FMECA document was previously published here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Trace’s pitch: This isn’t secret anymore&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Trace walks the appellate court through how the FMECA left the bottle: it was posted on this website and then widely republished; a YouTube explainer discussing it surpassed 100,000 views. The filing quotes Sig Sauer’s VP of Consumer Affairs Phil Strader being asked on the Behind the Lens podcast why the FMECA shouldn’t be public and responding, “No, there’s not” (nothing to hide), while directing viewers to this website to see the document and describing its contents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reporting regarding Phil Strader’s interview was previously published here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How many times has the unredacted FMECA been “shared”? The filings don’t give a precise share count. What they do document is widespread republication and discussion, including the 100k‑plus video and multiple re‑posts mirroring the PSI copy. In other words, the genie is out of the bottle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Trace also points to DoD Instruction 5230.24, the policy Sig Sauer invokes, noting it does not authorize withholding unclassified information about evaluations of performance and reliability of military equipment—and that the PSI‑hosted FMECA bears no DoD distribution markings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sig Sauer’s response: Let the Army decide—and keep the lid on&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sig Sauer tells the Eighth Circuit The Trace lacks standing and that parallel briefing is already underway in the district court. Substantively, Sig Sauer leans on military‑secrets concerns, requests time for the Army to opine on release, and characterizes the FMECA as controlled technical information created under the MHS contract. (The company also recounts how the spreadsheet briefly became public in another case before being pulled down.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two details in Sig Sauer’s papers matter going forward:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1) The “FMECA Memorandum.” Sig Sauer identifies the memo alongside the previously published spreadsheet. If the memo is Sig Sauer‑authored, it could reveal how the company framed the Army analysis internally—an issue directly relevant to notice, risk mitigation, and marketing claims.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2) Ongoing Army communications. Sig Sauer’s litigation counsel filed a declaration stating he asked the Army about the FMECA’s distribution status and that key Army decision‑makers were unavailable the week of the deadline; Sig Sauer says the Army may submit information and seeks additional time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The transparency question, distilled&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Is the FMECA “national‑security” material? The Trace says no—and points to DoDI 5230.24’s carve‑out: it does not provide authority to withhold unclassified evaluations of performance and reliability—exactly what a FMECA is. It also underscores the lack of any DoD marking on the PSI copy.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Is secrecy even possible at this point? The record shows the unredacted spreadsheet is online on this website, has been reposted broadly, and has been discussed by Sig Sauer’s own executive on air—who told listeners where to find it. One video discussing it has 100,000+ views.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why this matters to the class action—and to owners&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The district court relied on the FMECA repeatedly when certifying the Missouri class, including on notice and risk‑mitigation questions—the very issues consumers care about. Keeping the heart of that analysis under seal on appeal would blunt the public’s ability to scrutinize a product‑safety fight with real‑world consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My role, plainly&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical Shooting Insights is an independent site covering the shooting‑sports and firearms industry. The Trace’s filing names PSI as the first publisher of the unredacted spreadsheet and quotes Strader pointing viewers here. I will continue to publish filings and analysis so readers can compare the arguments to the documents themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What to watch next&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1) Whether the Eighth Circuit permits intervention and applies the strong presumption of public access to class‑certification records.&lt;lb/&gt; 2) If the Army weighs in—and on what basis—regarding the FMECA’s distribution status.&lt;lb/&gt; 3) Disclosure of the FMECA Memorandum. If it’s Sig Sauer-authored, it could illuminate internal framing of hazards and fixes—material at the core of consumer‑protection claims.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://practicalshootinginsights.com/eighth-circuit-fmeca-update/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45063526</id><title>A Dark Money Group Is Funding High-Profile Democratic Influencers</title><updated>2025-08-29T13:42:41.299605+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f39b8379a58f6fd0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a private group chat in June, dozens of Democratic political influencers discussed whether to take advantage of an enticing opportunity. They were being offered $8,000 per month to take part in a secretive program aimed at bolstering Democratic messaging on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the contract sent to them from Chorus, the nonprofit arm of a liberal influencer marketing platform, came with some strings. Among other issues, it mandated extensive secrecy about disclosing their payments and had restrictions on what sort of political content the creators could produce.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In their group chat, influencers debated the details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Should we send a joint email (with all of our email addresses) … or, are we just going to send things separately and hope they change everything for everyone?” Laurenzo, a nonbinary creator in Columbus, Ohio, with over 884,000 TikTok followers, asked the group. Some joked about collective bargaining. “Any Newsies fans here?” Eliza Orlins, a public defender and reality TV star known for her appearances on Survivor, posted in the group. “‘We’re a union just by sayin’ so!’”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The influencers in the chat collectively had at least 13 million followers across social platforms. They represented some of the most well-known voices online posting in support of Democrats, and they’re key to wherever the party moves next. But ultimately, the group didn’t make much progress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Reading through this revised Chorus contract like: you win some, you lose some,” a reproductive justice influencer named Pari, who posts under the handle @womeninamerica, responded later in the thread. “I also think there’s at least 4 other things that should change 🤣but the vibe I got from their email was that there would be minimal, if any, changes.” (Laurenzo, Orlins, and Pari did not reply to requests for comment.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I don’t feel strongly about pushing tbh,” Aaron Parnas, a Gen Z news influencer who has been called the Gen Z Walter Cronkite and has been lauded in legacy media outlets, posted to the chat. “They aren’t going to modify it anymore. Seems like a take it or leave it.” (Parnas declined to comment.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I believe we are in Stage 5: Acceptance,” Pari responded. Creators began signing on to the deal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For years, Democrats have struggled to work with influencers. In 2024, President Joe Biden’s White House snubbed several prominent content creators after they lightly criticized the administration over its policies on climate change, Covid, Gaza, and the TikTok ban. Content creators who challenged Kamala Harris—including Hasan Piker, a well-known influencer on the left—were similarly unwelcome at campaign events.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the Democrats lost in November, they faced a reckoning. It was clear that the party had failed to successfully navigate the new media landscape. While Republicans spent decades building a powerful and robust independent media infrastructure, maximizing controversy to drive attention and maintaining tight relationships with creators despite their small disagreements with Trump, the Democrats have largely relied on outdated strategies and traditional media to get their message out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, Democrats hope that the secretive Chorus Creator Incubator Program, funded by a powerful liberal dark money group called The Sixteen Thirty Fund, might tip the scales. The program kicked off last month, and creators involved were told by Chorus that over 90 influencers were set to take part. Creators told WIRED that the contract stipulated they’d be kicked out and essentially cut off financially if they even so much as acknowledged that they were part of the program. Some creators also raised concerns about a slew of restrictive clauses in the contract.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Influencers included in communication about the program, and in some cases an onboarding session for those receiving payments from The Sixteen Thirty Fund, include Olivia Julianna, the centrist Gen Z influencer who spoke at the 2024 Democratic National Convention; Loren Piretra, a former Playboy executive turned political influencer who hosts a podcast for Occupy Democrats; Barrett Adair, a content creator who runs an American Girl Doll–themed pro-DNC meme account; Suzanne Lambert, who has called herself a “Regina George liberal;” Arielle Fodor, an education creator with 1.4 million followers on TikTok; Sander Jennings, a former TLC reality star and older brother of trans influencer Jazz Jennings; David Pakman, who hosts an independent progressive show on YouTube covering news and politics; Leigh McGowan, who goes by the online moniker “Politics Girl”; and dozens of others. (The first two declined to comment; the rest did not respond to requests for comment.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to copies of the contract viewed by WIRED that creators signed, the influencers are not allowed to disclose their relationship with Chorus or The Sixteen Thirty Fund—or functionally, that they’re being paid at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dozens of liberal influencers are believed to have been approached by Chorus about The Sixteen Thirty Fund financing opportunity this spring. They were told that Chorus appreciated the work they were doing online and were asked if they’d be interested in being part of the first cohort of a new program that Chorus was running to help “expand their reach and impact,” creators tell WIRED.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But following the initial outreach, many creators expressed concern about some stipulations. According to copies of the contract viewed by WIRED, creators in the program must funnel all bookings with lawmakers and political leaders through Chorus. Creators also have to loop Chorus in on any independently organized engagements with government officials or political leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“If I want to work with another politician, I have to fully collaborate with them,” said one creator who was offered the contract but ultimately declined to take it and asked not to be named. “If I get Zohran and he wants to [do an] interview with me, I don’t want to give that to them.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creators in the program are not allowed to use any funds or resources that they receive as part of the program to make content that supports or opposes any political candidate or campaign without express authorization from Chorus in advance and in writing, per the contract.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The contracts reviewed by WIRED prohibit standard partnership disclosures, declaring that creators will “not publicize” their relationship with Chorus or tell others that they’re members of the program “without Chorus’s prior express consent.” (A screenshot from a slideshow was shared with WIRED following this article's publication by Graham Wilson, a lawyer working with Chorus, that offers several talking points if a member of the cohort wanted to discuss Chorus publicly.) They also forbid creators from “disclos[ing] the identity of any Funder” and give Chorus the ability to force creators to remove or correct content based solely on the organization’s discretion if that content was made at a Chorus-organized event.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“There are some real great advantages to … housing this program in a nonprofit,” Wilson said to creators on a Zoom call reviewed by WIRED. “It gives us the ability to raise money from donors. It also, with this structure, it avoids a lot of the public disclosure or public disclaimers—you know, ‘Paid for by blah blah blah blah’—that you see on political ads. We don’t need to deal with any of that. Your names aren’t showing up on, like, reports filed with the FEC.” (Wilson did not reply to a request for comment before the article was published.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Federal Election Commission declined to comment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal of Chorus, according to a fundraising deck obtained by WIRED, is to “build new infrastructure to fund independent progressive voices online at scale.” The creators who joined the incubator are expected to attend regular advocacy trainings and daily messaging check-ins. Those messaging check-ins are led by Cohen on “rapid response days.” The creators also have to attend at least two Chorus “newsroom” events per month, which are events Chorus plans, often with lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elizabeth Dubois, an assistant professor and university research chair in politics, communication, and technology at the University of Ottawa who has researched the ways influencers are reshaping the US political system, says that “we are seeing influencers being pulled into these dark campaigns or shadow campaigns, where the legal aspect is murky at best.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Sometimes it is actually clear that influencers are being used to, for example, evade spending limits,” she says. “I think that we need to remember that for democracy to thrive, we do need transparency around who is paying for political messages.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don Heider, the chief executive of the Markkula Center for Applied Ethics at Santa Clara University, says that the outlined restrictions violate ethical norms. “If the contract for getting money from a particular interest group says you can’t disclose it, then it’s pretty simple, you can’t take the money,” he says. “We’re living in an era where a lot of powerful people have basically taken the rule book and thrown it out the window.” (Wilson maintained in a post-publication email that “creators are free to work with other groups or take on other partnerships outside the Chorus program and say whatever they want as part of that work or on their own.”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keith Edwards, a Democratic content creator who has skyrocketed to fame on YouTube since starting his channel last year, was not invited to be part of the program but believes that the way it was structured seemed “predatory.” He says that he would never agree to take part in a program that was run in secret or wouldn’t allow him to disclose funding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What I don’t understand is, why wouldn’t you just donate to creators directly who have already built something and just need to put gasoline on the fire?” says Edwards. “Democrats at least understand that the internet exists now, so that’s good. But they still think influencers are just there to do a terrible direct-to-camera interview that no one watches rather than just treating us like another form of media.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The influencers offered the funding were given just days to sign the contract, which was essentially presented on a take-it-or-leave-it basis. At least one cohort was specifically told they could not have their lawyers redline it. In the group chat formed to discuss contract negotiations, some creators discussed a clause prohibiting the disparagement of other creators. Not being able to criticize anyone else affiliated with Chorus felt restrictive to some, according to text messages posted to the chat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eventually, the creators in the group chat agreed to drop the issues they had. “I don’t think [Chorus is] out to screw us,” Orlins, a creator who was offered $8,000 per month, said in the group chat. (Some influencers for Chorus Creator Incubator Program were offered as little as $250 per month, according to one creator who declined to accept the deal, while others were offered membership into the “amplifier” cohort, which provides up to $8,000 per month.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Sixteen Thirty Fund has emerged as a powerful funder in Democratic spaces in recent years. Its website notes that issues supported by the organization include economic equity, affordable health care, climate solutions, racial justice, voter access, and other “essential social-change goals.” The organization was founded in 2009 as a liberal response to conservative dark money groups and organizations like the Koch network, and under Trump it has soared.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2018, The Sixteen Thirty Fund provided $141 million to more than 100 left-leaning causes in order to bolster Democratic support during the midterms, according to a tax filing obtained by Politico. In 2020, the fund distributed more than $400 million, according to the organization’s public tax filing, which Politico said was used in “efforts to unseat then-president Donald Trump and Republicans’ Senate majority.” In 2022, The Sixteen Thirty Fund spent $196 million backing state ballot measures on abortion rights heading into the midterms, according to NBC. Just four donors accounted for close to two-thirds of the fund’s revenue in 2023, according to its tax filing. The largest donor gave the group $50.5 million, with others donating $31.4 million, $21.8 million, and $13.6 million.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The Sixteen Thirty Fund, which is not required to disclose its contributors, has for years been a major funding source for liberal and progressive causes and groups, including those that spend in elections,” says Walker Davis, a research director for the open-government group Citizens for Responsibility and Ethics in Washington. “Though their recent tax returns indicate that they have pulled back from the eye-popping sums they raised and spent in 2020, the organization is still one of the top-spending politically oriented nonprofits in the country.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chorus, which is described in contracts reviewed by WIRED as a “project of” The Sixteen Thirty Fund that handles operations for the creator program, launched in November 2024 with ties to Good Influence, a for-profit influencer marketing agency aimed at helping content creators connect with social-good campaigns. Good Influence was founded in October 2020 by Stuart Perelmuter, the former communications director for representative John Yarmuth of Kentucky. Seeing an opportunity after Kamala Harris’ loss last November, Perelmuter cofounded Chorus with Democratic influencer Brian Tyler Cohen, who has over 4.6 million subscribers on YouTube and leads messaging check-ins for the creator cohort on “rapid response days.” According to records reviewed by WIRED, Chorus claims that its initial creator cohort has a collective audience of more than 40 million followers with more than 100 million weekly viewers and that the organization has “hundreds of creators signed up” and “ready to amplify” messaging.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I’ve spent most of my career researching right-wing media and sounding the alarms about the collapse of our old information environment,” Ellie Langford, the director of programming at Chorus, said on a Zoom call with dozens of creators in June. “Our political systems haven’t been able to figure out a real solution, and I’ve been really excited to see you all treading the path forward. I deeply, deeply believe that the work you all are doing is what’s going to make the difference in supporting and frankly resuscitating our democracy.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Already, creators in the program are creating content together. In a new weekly series titled “Good News in Politics,” six creators in the program shared a collaborative video running through political wins. “Follow these creators bringing you hope instead of doomscrolling: @sander_jennings, @eorlins, @jesscraven101, @tono.latino, @gemma_talks, @thezactivist,” they posted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While some creators have been eager to work with Chorus, others distrust the organization. This spring, Chorus faced a wave of backlash from prominent content creators whose images were included in the firm’s fundraising decks without permission. “I was included on some [of Chorus’] decks like, ‘We have access to V,’ when you do not,” said V Spehar, a liberal content creator with over 3.5 million followers on TikTok. (Following the publication of this article, Wilson said that "there is no record of V being included in any Chorus materials, nor being named as part of the effort.")&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The faces of several well-known influencers were featured prominently on the Chorus website beneath a giant DONATE button. However, users who clicked the button were taken to a fundraising page for Chorus instead of anywhere their dollars would go directly to the creators featured.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Progressive YouTuber and former Media Matters staffer Kat Abughazaleh, who’s running for Congress in Illinois, was pictured on Chorus’ website and included in fundraising decks without her consent. She asked that her image and name be removed and no longer used for fundraising purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spehar and other content creators have accused Chorus of attempting to establish themselves as a gatekeeper to Democratic political leaders. “What we need is for people to invest in independent media, and that doesn’t necessarily mean investing in a consulting group that is going to become a middleman for independent media,” says Spehar.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Several influencers who doggedly defended Chorus throughout that controversy, including Elizabeth Booker Houston, a Democratic comedian and content creator on Instagram, and Allie O’Brien, a progressive creator with more than 600,000 followers on TikTok, were involved in membership talks for the highest-paid tier in Chorus’ new creator incubator program. (Houston did not respond to requests for comment; O’Brien declined to comment.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, some creators heard about The Sixteen Thirty Fund and Chorus funding initiative and applied to join.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One creator named Chesko, who goes by @thespeechprof online, applied to join the program because he viewed it as an “opportunity to get access to people that have funding or backing and actual research that I could use,” he says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, he wasn’t accepted and received an email on June 26 rejecting his application. “We are planning to bring more creators into the Incubator program in the near future,” Chorus wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The structure of the program highlights the vast differences between how Democrats and Republicans attempt to amass online influence. Republicans have spent decades building up a powerful independent media ecosystem, though the right-wing influencer world is far from transparent. In September 2024, a federal indictment alleged that the Russian state-sponsored network RT was covertly providing millions in funding to Tenet Media, a company working with major right-wing influencers including Benny Johnson, Tim Pool, Dave Rubin, and Lauren Southern. In 2024, the National Republican Congressional Committee spent nearly $500,000 on work with Creator Grid, an influencer marketing company whose website says it “connects Republican candidates with the internet’s most powerful conservative influencers,” according to analysis of campaign finance filings from The Washington Post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Steven Buckley, a digital media sociologist at City St. George’s, University of London, says that these sorts of programs have been “happening in the right wing for ages.” But Heider said that the structure of The Sixteen Thirty Fund deal raises the question, “Is it ethical to match the tactics of your opponents?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Democrats appear to have no real counter to this system. “Democrats missed the next generation of media,” says Brendan Gahan, cofounder of influencer marketing agency Creator Authority. “Historically they owned Hollywood, but this next generation of influence is digital, and they’ve miscalculated that. I don’t think they feel comfortable in arenas where they lack control.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update: 8/28/2025, 7:00 PM EDT: Following the publication of this article, Graham Wilson of the Elias Law Group, whose participation in a Zoom call was reported upon, and who did not respond to WIRED's pre-publication email requesting comment, reached out to WIRED on several points. These include whether members of the cohort can publicly talk about working with Chorus, and Chorus's connection to Good Influence, both of which WIRED has clarified. We have also included comment from Wilson regarding Chorus placing "restrictions" on content, and whether V Spehar was included in any Chorus materials.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.wired.com/story/dark-money-group-secret-funding-democrat-influencers/"/></entry></feed>