<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:31.479167+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45292694</id><title>This map is not upside down</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:37.809396+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f00ca5471275de50"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you were to close your eyes and picture a map of the world, chances are you would imagine a conventional image: North America (including Greenland) and Europe at the top, Africa somewhere in the middle, and South America, Australia, and Antarctica at the bottom. But it does not have to be so, and it was not always so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not that our planet underwent change—it did, of course, but long before maps. Our conventions as map readers and makers have converged over time to a north-up default. What happens when that convention is challenged? Robert Simmon, a cartographer who previously developed maps for Planet Labs and NASA Earth Observatory, designed a map to address that question.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simmon’s map includes countries, major lakes, oceans, gulfs, seas, roads, and cities. It also features inset maps depicting Earth’s biosphere, global land cover, and bathymetry. All of these are familiar to most map readers. Yet the map may seem disorienting to many. Simmon’s map is geographically correct, yet purposely—and literally—turns convention on its head. What was once familiar becomes alien, challenging readers to look at Earth anew. It also encourages us to think more deeply about such conventions: Why is north almost always at the top of maps? And must it always be that way? Simmon’s map reminds us that it doesn’t have to be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simmon is not the first to create a south-up map. Others have made these maps to challenge conventions and norms. And it was only rather recently that north-up maps became so commonplace. Centuries ago, cartographers drew maps with the top being south, east, or other orientations. These alternatives reflected the limited tools, knowledge, and practices of the time. The basic idea behind a compass (which most today recognize as a device that points north) was known to the Han and Tang dynasties of China more than 2,000 years ago. Early Chinese navigators used magnetized devices as a compass, but for them south was the dominant position from which bearings were derived.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deciding to put south, or north, at the top of maps is a decision of consequence. Psychologically, we tend to view things nearer the top as ‘good’ and those lower as ‘bad.’ This can influence our interpretation of maps at both global and local scales. Still, the prominence of north-up maps did not arrive deliberately to elevate the status of some areas or their rulers. It is in part a consequence of the work of Ptolemey, who first labeled his maps with calculated lines of latitude and longitude. This made it easy for others to copy, extend, and derive new maps. Each map drawn in this way would adopt Ptolemy’s orientation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless of the reasons for a given orientation and the implications that follow, Simmon’s map reminds us to challenge tradition and consider its influence. As both a map and a philosophical prompt, this example hits the mark beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;About This Map&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Title&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;The World, South Up&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Creator&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;Robert simmon&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Data Sources&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Natural Earth, GEBCO&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;NASA/USGS MODIS Land Cover Classification&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;NOAA VIIRS NDVI&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;NOAA VIIRS Ocean Color&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This map was contributed through the Maps.com submission program. If you’d like your map to be featured, submit it for consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Tags&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.maps.com/this-map-is-not-upside-down/"/><published>2025-09-18T17:47:19+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45294058</id><title>U.S. already has the critical minerals it needs, according to new analysis</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:37.684998+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e9780551b293659e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;U.S. already has the critical minerals it needs – but they're being thrown away, new analysis shows&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In new Science article, Colorado School of Mines researchers call for more research, development and policy to increase critical mineral recovery&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the critical minerals the U.S. needs annually for energy, defense and technology applications are already being mined at existing U.S. facilities, according to a new analysis published today in the journal Science.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The catch? These minerals, such as cobalt, lithium, gallium and rare earth elements like neodymium and yttrium, are currently being discarded as tailings of other mineral streams like gold and zinc, said Elizabeth Holley, associate professor of mining engineering at Colorado School of Mines and lead author of the new paper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The challenge lies in recovery," Holley said. "It's like getting salt out of bread dough – we need to do a lot more research, development and policy to make the recovery of these critical minerals economically feasible."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To conduct the analysis, Holley and her team built a database of annual production from federally permitted metal mines in the U.S. They used a statistical resampling technique to pair these data with the geochemical concentrations of critical minerals in ores, recently compiled by the U.S. Geological Survey, Geoscience Australia and the Geologic Survey of Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using this approach, Holley’s team was able to estimate the quantities of critical minerals being mined and processed every year at U.S. metal mines but not being recovered. Instead, these valuable minerals are ending up as discarded tailings that must be stored and monitored to prevent environmental contamination.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This is a brand-new view of ‘low hanging fruit’ – we show where each critical mineral exists and the sites at which even 1 percent recovery of a particular critical mineral could make a huge difference, in many cases dramatically reducing or even eliminating the need to import that mineral,” Holley said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The analysis in Science looks at a total of 70 elements used in applications ranging from consumer electronics like cell phones to medical devices to satellites to renewable energy to fighter jets and shows that unrecovered byproducts from other U.S. mines could meet the demand for all but two – platinum and palladium.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the elements included in the analysis are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cobalt (Co): The lustrous bluish-gray metal, a key component in electric car batteries, is a byproduct of nickel and copper mining. Recovering less than 10 percent of the cobalt currently being mined and processed but not recovered would be more than enough to fuel the entire U.S. battery market.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Germanium (Ge): The brittle silvery-white semi-metal used for electronics and infrared optics, including sensors on missiles and defense satellites, is present in zinc and molybdenum mines. If the U.S. recovered less than 1 percent of the germanium currently mined and processed but not recovered from U.S. mines, it would not have to import any germanium to meet industry needs.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The benefits of enhanced recovery are not only economic and geopolitical but also environmental, Holley said – recovering these critical minerals instead of sending them to tailings piles would reduce the environmental impact of mine waste and open more opportunities for reuse in construction and other industries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Now that we know which sites are low-hanging fruit, we need to conduct detailed analyses of the minerals in which these chemical elements reside and then test the technologies suitable for recovery of those elements from those specific minerals,” Holley said. “We also need policies that incentivize mine operators to incorporate additional processing infrastructure. Although these elements are needed, their market value may not be sufficient to motivate operators to invest in new equipment and processes without the right policies in place.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Co-authors on the paper are Karlie Hadden, PhD candidate in geology; Dorit Hammerling, associate professor of applied mathematics and statistics; Rod Eggert, research professor of economics and business; Erik Spiller, research professor of mining engineering; and Priscilla Nelson, professor of mining engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read the full paper, "Byproduct recovery from US metal mines could reduce import reliance for critical minerals," on the Science website. To access the data and figures before the paper appears in print, contact Mines Media Relations Specialist Erich Kirshner at erich.kirshner@mines.edu.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.minesnewsroom.com/news/us-already-has-critical-minerals-it-needs-theyre-being-thrown-away-new-analysis-shows"/><published>2025-09-18T19:41:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45294390</id><title>Shipping 100 hardware units in under eight weeks</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:37.513228+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://farhanhossain.substack.com/p/how-we-shipped-100-hardware-units"/><published>2025-09-18T20:11:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45294440</id><title>Apple: SSH and FileVault</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:37.437030+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="201543195f03b8c1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apple_ssh_and_filevault(7)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Miscellaneous Information Manual&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apple_ssh_and_filevault(7)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;apple_ssh_and_filevault&lt;/code&gt; —
    SSH and FileVault&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When FileVault is enabled, the data volume is locked and unavailable during and after booting, until an account has been authenticated using a password. The macOS version of OpenSSH stores all of its configuration files, both system-wide and per-account, in the data volume. Therefore, the usually configured authentication methods and shell access are not available during this time. However, when Remote Login is enabled, it is possible to perform password authentication using SSH even in this situation. This can be used to unlock the data volume remotely over the network. However, it does not immediately permit an SSH session. Instead, once the data volume has been unlocked using this method, macOS will disconnect SSH briefly while it completes mounting the data volume and starting the remaining services dependent on it. Thereafter, SSH (and other enabled services) are fully available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The capability to unlock the data volume over SSH appeared in macOS 26 Tahoe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 July, 2025&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Darwin&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://keith.github.io/xcode-man-pages/apple_ssh_and_filevault.7.html"/><published>2025-09-18T20:15:45+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45295794</id><title>AI tools are making the world look weird</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:36.347412+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7adbb9070d4782bc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The images arrive already complete; there is no communication between them and myself, no reciprocal exchange. As much as we like to say that the world is opening up to us, since we can see every part of it, we can also say that the world is closing itself off – in all its openness.&lt;/p&gt;Karl Ove Knausgård&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In academia and the media, AI is often described as mirroring human psychology with humanlike reasoning, human-level performance, human-like communication. In these comparisons, “humans” are treated as the benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a provocative 2023 paper, researchers at Harvard University asked – which humans?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The diversity of human psychologies has been a hot topic since 2010, when researchers found that many accepted psychological “truths” were often confined to so-called “WEIRD people”: Western, Educated, Industrialised, Rich, Democratic. What feel like universal beliefs for people like me and no doubt many of the readers of this blog, e.g. that I am an automonous individual, are instead only true for a thin slice of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So when we say AI tools are “human-like”, what we mean is that AI is WEIRD.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact, this paper found that more than that, it thinks American. The greater the cultural distance between a country and the USA, the less accurate ChatGPT got at simulating peoples’ values. For countries like Libya and Pakistan, AI results are little better than a coin toss.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This paper showed this through an ingenious method – administering the World Values Survey (WVS) 1,000 times to ChatGPT and then comparing it to real data from other countries. The WVS measures everything from self-reported cultural values to moral principles, attitudes towards family, religion, poverty and so on.[1]&lt;lb/&gt;In this simple chart, they plotted two variables:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The eagle-eyed reader may note that ChatGPT responses are slightly more correlated to smaller Western countries such as New Zealand than the US. This likely reflects the USA’s greater cultural diversity, and the fact that ChatGPT was developed in California.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marketers and researchers in non-WEIRD countries have often struggled for budget and bandwidth. AI tools’ poorer accuracy in their markets therefore introduce a double jeopardy: the non-WEIRD countries least likely to secure research budgets also have the worst accuracy from “off the shelf” AI tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These biases could show up throughout the research process, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a real risk that increasing use of AI tools in international research will flatten out and devalue insights, as highly diverse peoples’ individual spoken and unspoken responses are fed into text-processing machines and emerge looking and sounding vaguely Californian. What looks like a living, breathing forest to us may end up being processed as just so much wood.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean we should ignore AI tools when working cross-culturally. They’re simply too useful. Instead, I’d suggest that we need to invest in the cultural fitness of our thinking and processes. Just as you don’t have to lose physical stamina when you start driving a car, your projects do not have to atrophy cultural meaning when you introduce elements of automation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As researchers we can deepen the cultural layer in our international work by:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And as AI product owners or users, it’s more a question of how we minimise the loss of cultural meaning. I remain to be convinced that AI moderation will achieve that for as long as the “moderator” is powered by an American LLM with deep-coded cultural biases. When using AI for analysis or to design research, however, there is likely to be marginal value in:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLMs process information in a WEIRD way, are psychologically WEIRD, and assume the average human is too. At the same time, the LLM space is getting ever more concentrated with US companies dominating. There is a real risk that as researchers we could get pulled into ways of working and thinking that make the world feel smaller, and much less wondrous. We must build our cultural fitness to ensure that we can introduce automation without losing sight of the many ways of being human. &lt;lb/&gt;Here at STRAT7 (and for me personally), we want to explore further:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re going to conduct a few experiments of our own with LLMs from different continents – comment below if you have any thoughts on what to look out for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[1] Separately, I recommend checking out the WVS website – it is old school but has some great data and insights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[2] The researchers released an interactive tool to compare cultural distance across a range of dimensions, worth a play around&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://strat7.com/blogs/weird-in-weird-out/"/><published>2025-09-18T22:27:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45295898</id><title>Want to piss off your IT department? Are the links not malicious looking enough?</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:36.186557+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1ee9dc214d0432b1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This tool is guaranteed to help with that!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a tool that takes any link and makes it look malicious. It works on the idea of a redirect. Much like https://tinyurl.com/ for example. Where tinyurl makes an url shorter, this site makes it look malicious.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Place any link in the below input, press the button and get back a fishy(phishy, heh...get, it?) looking link. The fishy link doesn't actually do anything, it will just redirect you to the original link you provided.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://phishyurl.com/"/><published>2025-09-18T22:40:06+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45296638</id><title>David Lynch LA House</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:35.998604+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2aa02ad177176fe2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Tour David Lynch's house as it hits the market&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;David Lynch's LA estate is for sale at $15m, and the listing pictures offer a glimpse into the late filmmaker's aesthetic and creative universe&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;David Lynch, the visionary American filmmaker behind Twin Peaks, Blue Velvet and Mulholland Dr, passed away this January, yet his creative universe endures in objects, spaces and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the most striking of these relics is his larger-than-life, meticulously designed Hollywood Hills home; a cinematic setting in its own right. Perched on a sweeping 2.3-acre hillside, David Lynch’s private compound, which is now listed for $15 million by Marc Silver of The Agency, unfolds like one of his own intricately plotted storylines. A showcase of Mid-Century modern architecture, the estate was conceived with the same care and cinematic precision that defined his work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Inside David Lynch's Los Angeles estate&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The property, set across five contiguous parcels, reads like a storyboard in relief: three main residences and several ancillary structures stepping down the hillside, each capturing a different note in Lynch’s creative oeuvre.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The story behind this compound started in 1987, when he acquired the pink-hued Beverly Johnson House designed in the early 1960s by Lloyd Wright, son of Frank Lloyd Wright. The home, in fact, was recognised by Historic Places LA as an exemplary work of Mid-Century Modern residential design. Then in 1991, he commissioned Eric Lloyd Wright (Lloyd Wright’s son) to add a pool and pool house, extending the Wright imprint on his property with a new generation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Across the years, Lynch kept expanding the plotline: in 1989, he purchased an adjoining two-bedroom Brutalist house; in 1995, a studio building; and later, more pieces of land, ultimately shaping a seven-structure sanctuary with 10 bedrooms and 11 bathrooms spread over roughly 11,000 square feet. The result was a creative campus perched above the city.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the heart of the compound lies the architectural crescendo – the approximately 2,000 square feet home where light pours through generous windows and skylights to rake across organic textures and bold geometries. The facade’s cement chevrons catch the sun; inside, simple metalwork and natural woods are drenched in material honesty that often surfaced in Lynch’s films.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two neighbouring addresses deepen the lore: 7029 Senalda served as the home of Asymmetrical Productions, while 7035 Senalda attained near-mythic status as both the Madison residence in the movie Lost Highway and Lynch’s own studio, complete with a library, screening room and editing suite – spaces where he refined major works, including Mulholland Drive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Receive our daily digest of inspiration, escapism and design stories from around the world direct to your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond the exemplary structures, Lynch left a personal handprint, collaborating on additional buildings: a sculptural two-storey guest house and a one-bedroom retreat finished in his favoured smooth grey plaster. Outdoors the terraces, courtyards and planted walkways offer a counterpoint to the intensity of production and everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a listing note from The Agency suggests, this is a 'creative sanctuary and architectural landmark,' with provenance unlike any other in Los Angeles. For admirers of Lynch, it reads as both home and archive: a lived-in factory of ideas, meticulously composed and, at last, ready for its next act.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aditi Sharma is a content specialist with 14 years of experience in the design and lifestyle space. She specialises in producing content that resonates with diverse audiences, bridging global trends with local stories, and translating complex ideas into engaging, accessible narratives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Setchu unveils minimalist fragrances that smell like river fish and tatami mats&lt;p&gt;The brand led by celebrated young designer Satoshi Kuwata unveils a range of six fragrances that combine Japanese and Western influences&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Diamond Suite Eleven is a Monegasque escape of epic proportions&lt;p&gt;Experience 195 sq m of seaside calm at this new suite atop the Monte-Carlo Bay Hotel &amp;amp; Resort&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; London Fashion Week S/S 2026: live updates from the Wallpaper* team&lt;p&gt;From 18-22 September, London Fashion Week arrives in the British capital. Follow along for a first look at the shows, presentations and other style happenings, as seen by the Wallpaper* editors&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.wallpaper.com/design-interiors/david-lynch-house-los-angeles-for-sale"/><published>2025-09-19T00:30:14+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45297066</id><title>Help Us Raise $200k to Free JavaScript from Oracle</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:35.801161+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e7214019db839d69"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Help Us Raise $200k to Free JavaScript from Oracle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After more than 27,000 people signed our open letter to Oracle about the “JavaScript” trademark, we filed a formal Cancellation Petition with the US Patent and Trademark Office. Ten months in, we’re finally reaching the crucial discovery phase.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno initiated this petition since we have legal standing as a JavaScript runtime, but it’s really on behalf of all developers. If we win, “JavaScript” becomes public domain – free for all developers, conferences, book authors, and companies to use without fear of trademark threats.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re asking for your support through our GoFundMe campaign so we can put forward the strongest case possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why $200k?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because federal litigation is expensive. Discovery is the most resource-intensive stage of litigation, where evidence is collected and arguments are built.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We don’t want to cut corners – we want to make the best case possible by funding:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Professional public surveys that carry legal weight in front of the USPTO, proving that “JavaScript” is universally recognized as the name of a language, not Oracle’s brand.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Expert witnesses from academia and industry to testify on JavaScript’s history, usage, and meaning.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Depositions and records from standards bodies, browser vendors, and industry leaders showing Oracle has no role in the language’s development.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Legal filings and responses to counter Oracle’s claims at every step.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there are leftover funds, we’ll donate them to the OpenJS to continue defending civil liberties in the digital space. None of the funds will go to Deno.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Oracle officially denies “JavaScript” is generic&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On August 6th, 2025, Oracle for the first time addressed the validity of the trademark. Their response to our petition denies that “JavaScript” is a generic term.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re a web developer, it’s self-evident that Oracle has nothing to do with JavaScript. The trademark system was never meant to let companies squat on commonly-used names and rent-seek – it was designed to protect active brands in commerce. US law makes this distinction explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We urge you to read our petition and open letter to understand our arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we don’t win discovery, Oracle locks in ownership of the word “JavaScript.” This is the decisive moment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this case is bigger than JavaScript. It’s about whether trademark law works as written, or whether billion-dollar corporations can ignore the rule that trademarks cannot be generic or abandoned. “JavaScript” is obviously both. If Oracle wins anyway, it undermines the integrity of the whole system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s make sure the law holds. Please donate. Please share and upvote this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://deno.com/blog/javascript-tm-gofundme"/><published>2025-09-19T01:40:35+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45297331</id><title>Gemini in Chrome</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:35.088702+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f852a98b3bb793b5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Meet Gemini in Chrome&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;AI assistance, right in your browser.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Intelligence that works with you, right where you are.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get key takeaways, clarify concepts, and find answers based on the context of your open tabs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Need to quickly grasp the essentials? Gemini delivers concise summaries of articles, pages, or threads directly in your browser, so you quickly grasp the main points.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a question about what you're reading? Ask Gemini. It uses the context of your open tabs to provide relevant answers and explanations, keeping you focused.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go beyond simple explanations. When you’re tackling dense topics or new concepts, ask Gemini to not only clarify confusing parts but also help you actively engage with the material.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researching products or weighing choices? Ask Gemini to pull key information, specs, or pros and cons from the page, helping you make informed choices with clarity and ease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Want to brainstorm, organize thoughts, or dive deeper into a topic? Chat naturally with Gemini Live and get spoken answers, all within Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just like on your computer, Gemini on mobile is there to answer questions about what you’re reading. On Android it works with anything on your screen—including Chrome. And coming soon to iOS, Gemini will be built right into the Chrome app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Your web, your control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini in Chrome works with you, on your terms. It assists only when you ask, putting you in control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Ready when you are&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini in Chrome activates only when you choose to use it via clicking on the Gemini icon or the keyboard shortcut you set up. It assists on your terms, stepping in only when you ask.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Get help, your way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get help your way with Gemini in Chrome. Talk or type your question naturally, and Gemini can use the page's content to help you quickly understand content or complete tedious tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Manage your activity easily&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can access your Gemini Apps Activity anytime to manage, delete and turn off your activity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The web, reimagined.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Gemini in Chrome, no tab switching is needed with AI assistance right in your browser, helping you quickly understand content or get tasks done using the context of your open tabs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Frequently asked questions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the Gemini in Chrome feature, you can get AI assistance from your browser to do things easily like get key takeaways, clarify concepts, find answers and more. To provide the most relevant responses, Gemini in Chrome uses the context of your open tabs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini in Chrome is part of the Chrome browser on desktop, and is different from visiting Gemini in any browser at gemini.google.com or starting a chat with the Gemini web app by typing @gemini in the address bar in Chrome. You can use the Gemini web app in other browsers (or the content area of Chrome), but you won’t be able to share page content or use Live mode like you can with Gemini in Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can access Gemini in Chrome through the Gemini icon in the Chrome toolbar or via a keyboard shortcut that you set up on a Windows or Mac desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also activate Gemini when using Chrome on Android, and other apps, by holding the power button. And starting soon, on iOS Gemini in Chrome will be built into the app, with access through the Chrome omnibox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini in Chrome is rolling out to all eligible Mac and Windows users in the US who have their Chrome language set to English. We look forward to bringing this feature to more people and additional languages soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini in Chrome on iOS is coming soon to eligible iPhone users in the US who have their Chrome language set to English.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check responses. Setup required. Compatibility and availability varies. 18+&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://gemini.google/overview/gemini-in-chrome/"/><published>2025-09-19T02:25:34+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45299170</id><title>Ruby Central's Attack on RubyGems [pdf]</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:34.935574+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://pup-e.com/goodbye-rubygems.pdf"/><published>2025-09-19T08:09:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45299625</id><title>Statistical Physics with R: Ising Model with Monte Carlo</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:34.434233+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d9f7ce022b3b170f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Classical Ising Model is a land mark system in statistical physics. The model explains the physics of spin glasses and magnetic materials, and cooperative phenomenon in general, for example phase transitions and neural networks. This package provides utilities to simulate one dimensional Ising Model with Metropolis and Glauber Monte Carlo with single flip dynamics in periodic boundary conditions. Utility functions for exact solutions are provided.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Effective ergodicity in single-spin-flip dynamics&lt;lb/&gt;Mehmet Suezen, Phys. Rev. E 90, 032141&lt;lb/&gt;Dataset&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anomalous diffusion in convergence to effective ergodicity, Suezen, Mehmet, arXiv:1606.08693&lt;lb/&gt;Dataset&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/msuzen/isingLenzMC"/><published>2025-09-19T09:19:04+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45300615</id><title>Dynamo AI (YC W22) Is Hiring a Senior Kubernetes Engineer</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:33.812581+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a770c0f34e35ef6a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compliant-Ready AI for the Enterprise&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dynamo AI is building the future of secure, scalable AI systems. Our platform helps enterprises safely deploy powerful AI models in production, with reliability, control, and trust at the core. We’re a team of builders working at the intersection of machine learning, infrastructure, and security.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a Senior Kubernetes Engineer, you’ll lead the full onboarding journey for our enterprise customers — from first engagement to successful production rollout. You will own the deployment of Dynamo AI clusters (Kubernetes-based) into customer environments and serve as the technical bridge between our product and the customer’s infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a deeply hands-on and customer-facing role. You’ll work with Kubernetes, Helm, and cloud-native tools to deliver secure, scalable deployments of cutting-edge AI systems. You’ll partner with engineering, product, and leadership to bring customer feedback directly into our roadmap and shape how AI is adopted across industries. Serving this role, you will grow into an expert in building the most cutting-edge enterprise-level AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This role will work with the U.S. government clients, so it requires U.S. government security clearance or US citizenship. Our company policy also requires in-office presence in San Francisco or New York office for 2-3 days per week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualifications&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The enterprise platform for enabling private, secure, and regulation-compliant Gen AI models.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/dynamo-ai/jobs/fU1oC9q-senior-kubernetes-engineer"/><published>2025-09-19T12:00:16+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45300865</id><title>Ants Seem to Defy Biology: They Lay Eggs That Hatch into Another Species</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:33.590819+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="86d0118d0e3c41d7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;These Ant Queens Seem to Defy Biology: They Lay Eggs That Hatch Into Another Species&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Iberian harvester ant queens produce offspring of their own species and of the builder harvester ant, seemingly by cloning males&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iberian harvester ant queens have a unique superpower: They can lay eggs that hatch into an entirely different species.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This discovery, described in a new paper published September 3 in the journal Nature, defies a fundamental principle of biology and may cause scientists to reconsider how they define a species.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The classic concept says that [a species] is a group of organisms with similar physical and genetic characteristics that can reproduce with each other in nature and produce fertile offspring,” says Xim Cerdá, an ecologist at Doñana Biological Station in Spain who was not involved with the research, to Miguel Ángel Criado at El País. “But it turns out that’s not the case; two species are needed here. We’re going to have to rethink the concept.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Did you know? How many ants are on the planet?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scientists estimate that 20 quadrillion ants are crawling around the Earth, according to a 2022 study.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scientists recently discovered that Iberian harvester ant queens (Messor ibericus) mate with males of another species, the builder harvester ant (Messor structor). When they do, the M. ibericus queens store the M. structor male’s sperm, then use it to fertilize some of the eggs they lay. Researchers think the M. ibericus queens remove their own genetic material from the eggs’ nuclei, so that when those eggs hatch, they effectively turn out to be M. structor male clones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The queens produce males of both M. ibericus and M. structor, and all the worker ants in M. ibericus colonies are female hybrids of the two species.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s an absolutely fantastic, bizarre story of a system that allows things to happen that seem almost unimaginable,” says Jacobus Boomsma, an evolutionary biologist at the University of Copenhagen who was not involved with the research, to Nature’s Max Kozlov.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even more perplexing is the fact that M. ibericus and M. structor are not closely related, evolutionarily speaking. The two species diverged more than five million years ago, according to the paper. For comparison, scientists think humans and chimpanzees split from a common ancestor that lived between six million and eight million years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Proving the relationship between M. ibericus and M. structor was challenging. The scientists dug up various M. ibericus colonies they found along the sides of farm roads near Lyon, France, looking for male ants. But among a colony of 10,000 ants, there might be only a few males, writes Science’s Erik Stokstad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the end, they found 132 males from 26 M. ibericus colonies. Of those, about half were nearly hairless—a hallmark of M. structor—while the others were covered in dense hair, a trait typically found in M. ibericus. DNA testing confirmed their hunch: The hairy males were M. ibericus, and the bald ones were M. structor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even more intriguing, the males of both species shared M. ibericus mitochondrial DNA, which is inherited from the mother, suggesting they had all been born from M. ibericus queens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This discovery is so novel and so unusual that the researchers had to come up with a new term to describe the behavior exhibited by M. ibericus queens: “xenoparity,” which essentially means “foreign birth.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The team also wanted to go beyond genetic evidence: They hoped to observe births of M. structor ants from an M. ibericus queen. So, they reared colonies in their laboratory. Then, they waited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It was very difficult, because in lab conditions, it’s nearly impossible to have males,” says co-author Jonathan Romiguier, an ecologist at the University of Montpellier in France, to New Scientist’s Tim Vernimmen. “We had something like 50 colonies and monitored them for two years without a single male being born. Then we got lucky.” Observing the births of M. structor males was another key piece of evidence in describing the ants’ strange biology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As for the M. ibericus males in the colony, the queens mate with them to produce the next generation of M. ibericus queens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But why do M. ibericus queens clone M. structor males? Scientists aren’t totally sure, but they say the partnership must be beneficial to both species.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For M. ibericus, this adaptation ensures they have plenty of workers, which are responsible for many important tasks in a colony, including building the nest, gathering food and raising the larvae. The arrangement also keeps M. structor males around for future M. ibericus queens to mate with, even in places without M. structor colonies. Shockingly, M. structor colonies are only found in mountainous areas across a small range. But by transporting the M. structor male clones around, M. ibericus has allowed that species to spread to new places.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the unique setup might not last forever. Because the M. structor males are clones and do not appear to be mating with members of their own species, they are probably accumulating harmful genetic mutations, which makes them more vulnerable in the long run, reports New Scientist. But, for now, the relationship seems to be working.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Every step in this coevolutionary game makes perfect sense and uses the entire toolbox of reproductive tricks that we know ants are capable of employing,” says Sara Helms Cahan, an evolutionary ecologist at the University of Vermont who was not involved with the research, to Science. “The end result is fantastical but incredibly successful, with one species carrying another in its pocket, as it were, all over southern Europe.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/these-ant-queens-seem-to-defy-biology-they-lay-eggs-that-hatch-into-another-species-180987292/"/><published>2025-09-19T12:25:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45301679</id><title>Intel Arc Celestial dGPU seems to be first casualty of Nvidia partnership</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:33.392315+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7669663fd52fd463"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Intel Arc Celestial dGPU seems to be first casualty of Nvidia partnership while Intel Arc B770 is allegedly still alive&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While we haven’t heard anything of substance regarding Intel’s high-end Arc Battlemage B770 desktop GPU for months now, the GPU is reportedly alive and coming this quarter. The information, which comes to us courtesy of Moore’s Law Is Dead, confirms a leak from back in May 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MLID’s latest leak, which also reveals the Intel x Nvidia Hammer Lake and Titan Lake APUs, delivers some noteworthy specs updates for the Arc B770. Contrary to what the leaker posted in October 2024, the Intel Arc B770 now seems to be skipping PCIe 5.0 support. Moreover, the board is also alleged to have inconsistent performance with “frame pacing issues”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, while MLID still maintains that the Arc B770 will feature 32 Xe cores, a 256-bit wide bus, and is capable of reaching RTX 4070 level, the card will reportedly suffer from choppy performance and have a limited supply. What’s even sadder, however, is that Arc B770 could be the last Intel desktop GPU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Per MLID's sources, Intel has pulled the Celestial dGPU from its roadmap. This effectively points to the desktop Arc Celestial cards being canceled. If Intel does cancel Arc Celestial and, by extension, later GPU architectures like Arc Druid, it will effectively put an end to what can only be categorized as a shaky and often rudderless business.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For what it’s worth, we do hope that Intel, somehow, keeps working on and releasing new desktop GPUs. Despite its issues, the Arc Battlemage B580 was a breath of fresh air when it launched into a crappy GPU market (Available on Amazon).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.notebookcheck.net/Intel-Arc-Celestial-dGPU-seems-to-be-first-casualty-of-Nvidia-partnership-while-Intel-Arc-B770-is-allegedly-still-alive.1118962.0.html"/><published>2025-09-19T13:51:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45301774</id><title>Court lets NSF keep swinging axe at $1B in research grants</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:33.183093+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7b5c32056cee53a5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Court lets NSF keep swinging axe at $1B in research grants&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Judge rules there’s no quick fix for 1,700+ axed grants, leaving labs scrambling for cash while the lawsuit plays out&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A US court has cleared the way for the National Science Foundation to press ahead with the cancellation of more than 1,700 research grants worth upwards of $1 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ruling, handed down this week by Judge Jia Cobb of the DC District Court, rejects a request from researchers, universities and scientific societies to reinstate the cancelled grants while the case is heard. The plaintiffs had argued that NSF's mass terminations were arbitrary, unlawful and would do irreparable harm to the country's research ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NSF began hacking away at its portfolio after publishing a "Change in Priorities" statement in April. The new policy narrowed the scope of what counts as an acceptable "broader impact," warning that taxpayer-funded projects must not "preference some groups at the expense of others." In practice, that meant hundreds of grants tied to diversity, equity and inclusion programmes, or focused on boosting participation by underrepresented groups, suddenly found themselves on the chopping block.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Between April and May, the agency fired off five waves of termination letters, citing boilerplate language that the projects "no longer effectuate program goals or agency priorities." Most awardees were given little explanation beyond that, despite their work having been peer-reviewed, approved and in many cases already underway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The legal challenge, filed in June by a coalition of educational and scientific organisations, argued that NSF's actions were arbitrary, violated grantees' due process rights, and contradicted the agency's statutory mission to broaden participation in STEM. The plaintiffs asked for a preliminary injunction that would have forced NSF to reinstate the money immediately while the case plays out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Judge Cobb said no. In her 38-page opinion, she ruled that the court lacks jurisdiction to order "retrospective relief", forcing NSF to pay out previously cancelled funds, saying those claims should be brought in the Court of Federal Claims, which handles lawsuits seeking money from the federal government. She also said that, while cancelled grants may cause serious disruption to labs, jobs and students, the plaintiffs hadn't met the high legal bar for proving "irreparable harm" needed to justify emergency relief.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In response, Democracy Forward, the coalition behind the legal challenge, said it was "deeply disappointed in the court's decision to allow the termination of grants to stand while we argue this case on the merits".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We are as united and committed as ever to ultimately winning this case and protecting these important NSF grants," it added. "The Trump-Vance administration acted unlawfully when it terminated these crucial grants. It attempted to usurp congressional authority by eliminating funding required by law. This case is not over and we are eager to defend the important role the NSF plays in the daily lives of Americans."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the decision doesn't kill the case entirely. Cobb allowed the plaintiffs' prospective claims to go forward, meaning NSF's new grantmaking policy itself can still be challenged, and future grant decisions could yet be scrutinised or overturned if the courts find the rules unlawful. But for now, the past terminations will remain in force.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scale of the purge is huge: according to data released by research lobby group COSSA, 1,752 grants worth around $1.4 billion have been terminated so far. The STEM Education Directorate was hit hardest, losing nearly half of its active grants and about two-thirds of its funding. Social, Behavioural and Economic Sciences also saw a significant share of its portfolio axed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;US science left out in the cold amid plans to retire Antarctic icebreaker&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Eggheads hold science fair on Capitol Hill to decry funding cuts&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Japan builds near $700M fund to lure foreign academic talent&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;EU tells US scientists to dump Trump for a lab in Europe&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trump wants to fire quarter of NASA budget into black hole – and not in a good way&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fight over NSF's priorities has been raging for months. As The Register reported in May, the agency's budget proposals threaten cuts of up to 80 percent in some directorates, alongside the closure of 37 divisions and the firing of probationary staff. DEI programmes and other outreach initiatives have been singled out for removal as the foundation pivots toward what it calls "neutral" science funding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For researchers on the receiving end, the court's decision means the disruption will continue. Projects are being paused or shut down mid-stream, leaving graduate students with uncertain futures due to the loss of stipends provided by those grants. Some universities have said they'll try to backfill funding to keep work alive, but warn they can't cover everything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, across the Atlantic, scientists are being offered something quite different. France's Aix-Marseille University has launched a Safe Place for Science programme, offering up to three years of funding and a "safe and stimulating environment" for American researchers seeking refuge from the disruption at home. ®&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/19/court_lets_nsf_keep_swinging/"/><published>2025-09-19T14:00:16+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45301845</id><title>As Android developer verification gets ready to go, a new reason to be worried</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:32.946015+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f2eb1338bbe2cdb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Affiliate links on Android Authority may earn us a commission. Learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;As Android developer verification gets ready to go, here's a new reason to be worried&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;September 18, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Google is putting together its framework for Android developer verification, connecting dev names to even sideloaded apps.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Recent additions to the Android SDK offer a little insight into how the system may ultimately operate.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;One variable suggests that users may not be able to sideload even verified apps without an active network connection.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Android’s approach to software openness is changing in some fundamental ways right now, and the shift has not been happening without a fair amount of controversy. While Google has always let you install Android apps from outside its managed app ecosystem, sideloading their APK files, the company will now start mandating that developers register their identity, and block the installation of apps from unverified sources.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For fans of open platforms, that’s resulted in some spicy takes (my own included), but in the weeks since the news first broke we’ve learned a little more about Google’s plans for implementing this program — and hearing about some critical workarounds, like maintaining the ability to sideload unverified apps over a connection to another device running ADB (the Android Debug Bridge).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t want to miss the best from Android Authority?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Set us as a favorite source in Google Discover to support us and make sure you never miss our latest exclusive reports, expert analysis, and much more. You can also set us as a preferred source in Google Search — find out more here.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While we’re breathing a little easier now that we know about that option, there are still plenty of headaches that this move could cause, and today we’re thinking about one that’s been brought up by Android fans on Reddit like user WesternImpression394. There, they’ve spotted some of the groundwork Google’s been laying in the Android SDK (not the AOSP, as claimed in that thread) to support developer verification.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the variables defined there is labeled in a way that immediately gets our attention: &lt;code&gt;DEVELOPER_VERIFICATION_FAILED_REASON_NETWORK_UNAVAILABLE&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you stop and think about it for a moment, that makes all the sense in the world — Google isn’t just interested in attaching someone’s name to all those anonymous APKs floating around out there, but presumably doing so in a way that allows the company to take action based on the name, like blacklisting devs who spread malware. And indeed, there’s a similar &lt;code&gt;DEVELOPER_VERIFICATION_FAILED_REASON_DEVELOPER_BLOCKED&lt;/code&gt; variable. While it’s easy enough to verify something like a cryptographic signature locally, Android might want to prevent you from installing an app if it can’t get online and check if the name is on just such a no-no list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Admittedly, this probably won’t cause a problem for most users ever, and we are looking at some kind of extreme corner case situation where you’ve already downloaded an APK, but no longer have network connectivity, nor access to a device running ADB (or an app already installed to run ADB commands locally). There could even be a cached copy of the ban list that would let you install offline up to a point. That said, Android has literally billions of users, and even rare situations will probably happen for someone eventually.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve still got a year to go before developer verification starts actually impacting any Android end-users, although devs will start signing up in the months to come. That leaves plenty of time for us to learn more about the all-too-important details behind how the system will ultimately work — and hopefully, plan ahead for how to work around it for users who genuinely need to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you for being part of our community. Read our Comment Policy before posting.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.androidauthority.com/android-sideload-offline-3598988/"/><published>2025-09-19T14:07:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45302065</id><title>I regret building this $3000 Pi AI cluster</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:32.762328+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="27f255577da246bd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I ordered a set of 10 Compute Blades in April 2023 (two years ago), and they just arrived a few weeks ago. In that time Raspberry Pi upgraded the CM4 to a CM5, so I ordered a set of 10 16GB CM5 Lite modules for my blade cluster. That should give me 160 GB of total RAM to play with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was the biggest Pi cluster I've built, and it set me back around $3,000, shipping included:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's another Pi-powered blade computer, the Xerxes Pi. It's smaller and cheaper, but it just wrapped up its own Kickstarter. Will it ship in less than two years? Who knows, but I'm a sucker for crowdfunded blade computers, so of course I backed it!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But my main question, after sinking in a substantial amount of money: are Pi clusters even worth it anymore? I There's no way this cluster could beat the $8,000, 4-node Framework Desktop cluster in performance. But what about in price per gigaflop, or in efficiency or compute density?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's only one way to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Compute Blade Cluster Build&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I made a video going over everything in this blog post—and the entire cluster build (and rebuild, and rebuild again) process. You can watch it here, or on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if you're on the blog, you're probably not the type to sit through a video anyway. So moving on...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Clustering means doing everything over n times&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the course of going from 'everything's in the box' to 'running AI and HPC benchmarks reliably', I rebuilt the cluster basically three times:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;First, my hodgepodge of random NVMe SSDs laying around the office was unreliable. Some drives wouldn't work with the Pi 5's PCIe bus, it seems, other ones were a little flaky (there's a reason these were spares sitting around the place, and not in use!)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;After replacing all the SSDs with Patriot P300s, they were more reliable, but the CM5s would throttle under load&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I put these CM heatsinks on without screwing them in... then realized they would pop off sometimes, so I took all the blades out again and screwed them into the CM5s/Blades so they were more secure for the long term.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Compute Blade Cluster HPL Top500 Test&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first benchmark I ran was my top500 High Performance Linpack cluster benchmark. This is my favorite cluster benchmark, because it's the traditional benchmark they'd run on massive supercomputers to get on the top500 supercomputer list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before I installed heatsinks, the cluster got 275 Gflops, which is an 8.5x speedup over a single 8 GB CM5. Not bad, but I noticed the cluster was only using 105 Watts of power during the run. Definitely more headroom available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After fixing the thermals, the cluster did not throttle, and used around 130W. At full power, I got 325 Gflops, which is a 10x performance improvement (for 10x 16GB CM5s) over a single 8 GB CM5.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compared to the $8,000 Framework Cluster I benchmarked last month, this cluster is about 4 times slower:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the Pi cluster is slightly more energy efficient, on a Gflops/W basis:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what about price?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Pi is a little less cost-effective for HPC applications than a Framework Desktop running a AMD's fastest APU. So discounting the fact we're only talking CPUs, I don't think any hyperscalers are looking to swap out a few thousand AMD EPYC systems for 10,000+ Raspberry Pis :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what about AI use cases?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Compute Blade Cluster AI Test&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With 160 GB of total RAM, shared by the CPU and iGPU, this could be a small, efficient AI Cluster, right? Well, you'd think.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But no: currently llama.cpp can't speed up AI using Vulkan on the Pi 5 iGPU. That means we have 160 GB of RAM, but only CPU-powered inference. On pokey Arm Cortex A76 CPU cores with 10 GB/sec or so of memory bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A small model (Llama 3.2:3B), running on a single Pi, isn't horrible; you get about 6 tokens per second. But that is pretty weak compared to even an Intel N100 (much less a single Framework Desktop):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You could have 10 nodes running 10 models, and that might be a very niche use case, but the real test would be running a larger AI model across all nodes. So I switched tracks to Llama 3.3:70B, which is a 40 GB model. It has to run across multiple Pis, since no single Pi has more than 16 GB of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just as with the Framework cluster, llama.cpp RPC was very slow, since it splits up the model layers on all the cluster members, then goes round-robin style asking each node to perform its prompt processing, then token generation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Pi cluster couldn't even make it to token generation (tg) on my default settings, so I had to dial things back and only generate 16 tokens at a time to allow it to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And after all that? Only 0.28 tokens per second, which is 25x slower than the Framework Cluster, running the same model (except on AI Max iGPUs with Vulkan).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also tried Exo and distributed-llama. Exo was having trouble even running a small 3B model on even a 2 or 3 node Pi cluster configuration, so I stopped trying to get that working.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Distributed llama worked, but only with up to 8 nodes for the 70B model. Doing that, I got a more useful 0.85 tokens/s, but that's still 5x slower than the Framework cluster (and it was a bit more fragile than llama.cpp RPC—the tokens were sometimes gibberish):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find all my AI cluster benchmarking results in the issue Test various AI clustering setups on 10 node Pi 5 cluster over on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Gatesworks and Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bottom line: this cluster's not a powerhouse. And dollar for dollar, if you're spending over $3k on a compute cluster, it's not the best value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is efficient, quiet, and compact. So if density is important, and if you need lots of small, physically separate nodes, this could actually make sense.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like the only real world use case besides learning is for CI jobs or high security edge deployments, where you're not allowed to run multiple things on one server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's what Unredacted Labs is building Pi clusters for: they're building Tor exit relays on blades, after they found the Pi was the most efficient way to run massive amounts of nodes. If your goal is efficiency and node density, this does win, ever so slightly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But for 99% of you reading this: this is not the cluster you're looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two years ago, when I originally ordered the Blades, Gateworks reached out. They were selling a souped up version of the Compute Blade, made to an industrial spec. The GBlade is around Pi 4 levels of performance, but with 10 gig networking, along with a 1 gig management interface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But... it's discontinued. It doesn't look like any type of compute blade really lit the world on fire, and like the Blade movie series, the Compute Blade is more of a cult classic than a mainstream hit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a bad cluster. Except for maybe blade 9, which dies every time I run a benchmark. But I will keep it going, knowing it's definitely easier to maintain than the 1,050 node Pi cluster at UC Santa Barbera, which to my knowledge is still the world's largest!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before I go, I just wanted to give a special thanks to everyone who supports my on Patreon, GitHub, YouTube Memberships, and Floatplane. It really helps when I take on these months- (or years!) long projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Parts Used&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might not want to replicate my cluster setup — but I always get asked what parts I used (especially the slim Ethernet cables... everyone asks about those!), so here's the parts list:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compute Blade DEV&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compute Blade Standard Fan Unit&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compute Blade 10" 3D Print Rackmount&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Raspberry Pi CM5 16GB (CM5016000)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GLOTRENDS Aluminum CM5 Heatsink&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Patriot P300 256GB NVMe SSD 10-pack&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GigaPlus 2.5 Gbps 10 port PoE+ switch&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GigaPlus 10" Rack Mount 3D Print ears&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Monoprice Cat6A SlimRun 6" Cat6 patch cables (10 pack)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ioplex SFP+ Twinax DAC patch cable&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;DeskPi RackMate TT&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Comments&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oh come on Jeff, you forgot to buy GPUs for your AI cluster. Such a beginner mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All you needed to do is buy 4x xtx 7900 used on ebay and build a four node raspberry pi cluster using the external GPU setup you've come up with in one of your previous blog posts [0].&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[0] https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2024/use-external-gpu-on-r...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heh, more to come on that soon... Nvidia is back on the table!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wonder what the 8x limitation was. Those numbers line up really well with a post from b4rtaz about "Qwen3 30B A3B Q40 hits 13.04 tok/s on 4× Raspberry Pi 5"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Working backwards from 70b to 3b active tokens getting 13.04 tok/s on 4x pi5s... with a very rough cut from 70b to 3b i would expect 23x slower so 0.5 tok/s for 4x pi5s, so with 8x it should be just around 1 tok/s but i guess with additional overhead from transfers it would be a bit under&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe the Pi cluster doesn’t have great performance, but there’s something attractive about having a small cluster of computers. I know it myself, because I’ve been thinking about using a small cluster to serve my websites, even if performance isn’t the best.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Web traffic is probably one area where something like this would be reasonable; it's not generally a huge load on the system, and having a few low power nodes would be adequate for good performance. I've run this website off a Pi cluster before, and outside of someone DDoSing it, it ran like a champ!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/i-regret-building-3000-pi-ai-cluster"/><published>2025-09-19T14:28:47+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45302220</id><title>Trevor Milton's Nikola Case Dropped by SEC Following Trump Pardon</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:32.583022+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2be08319d910f1c5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The US Securities and Exchange Comission (SEC) has dropped its fraud case against Nikola‘s founder and former CEO Trevor Milton, after Trump’s pardon six months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trevor Milton, who had been convicted of securities fraud, received a pardon from the US President Donald Trump in March, a month after the Phoenix-based electric and hydrogen truck maker Nikola filed for bankrupcy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full and unconditional presidential pardon overturned a four-year prison sentence, imposed in December 2023, for deceiving investors about the company’s progress and products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In an X post this Tuesday, the company’s founder said that “the SEC has dropped their case against me with prejudice.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“5 years of outright lies by the media, corrupt prosecutors, former Nikola executives and short sellers is finally over,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Milton added that he comes “out of this thankful to my God for one more day in this life and for such a wonderful family and wife who never backed down against the evil men behind this.” (Read the full statement below.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the company deals with the Chapter 11 plan in a Delaware bankrupcy court, Milton asked for a $69 million indemnification in legal fees against Nikola, which the company has pushed back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to Nikola, Milton’s demand is invalid, as the ex-executive acted in a “grossly negligent, reckless” behaviour, engaging in “bad faith actions” during his time at the company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, last month, he argued that the bankrupcy plan does not fully reflect the presidential pardon he received.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I don’t know him, but I was… they say it was very unfair. And they say the thing that he did wrong was he was one of the first people that supported a gentleman named Donald Trump for president,” the President said then.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The filing last month noted that “President Trump expressly decided here that Milton is factually innocent, the pardon did, contrary to the debtors’ assertions, wipe the slate clean.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In May, Nikola‘s creditors committee asked the bankrupcy court to investigate whether Milton was dissipating personal assets that should be used to satisfy his debt to the company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Milton stepped down from CEO in 2020, after allegations from Hindenburg Research that accused him of repeatedly misrepresenting Nikola‘s technological capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read Trevor Milton’s X statement below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The SEC has dropped their case against me with prejudice. 5 years of outright lies by the media, corrupt prosecutors, former Nikola executives and short sellers is finally over.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They falsely indicted me, silenced me, deleted my followers including here on X, stole my company, bankrupted my company, debanked me, targeted my friends and family, stole most my wealth and tried to put me in prison.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it’s over now and eventually our creator will make it right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I come out of this thankful to my God for one more day in this life and for such a wonderful family and wife who never backed down against the evil men behind this.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://eletric-vehicles.com/nikola/trevor-miltons-nikola-case-dropped-by-sec-following-trump-pardon/"/><published>2025-09-19T14:43:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45302222</id><title>Revamping an Old TV as a Gift (2019)</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:32.120148+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="67cc3e778305c99a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Revamping an old tv as a gift&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This entry is a summary of what I built for my dad's 50th birthday, in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The plan was to get a vintage TV to play some shows from the 70s-80s, and operation should be seamless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sacrificial lamb, found in the flea market:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the lid off&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The tuner&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attack plan:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Getting the raspberry pi to output video to the TV&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because the raspberry only outputs composite video, I needed a 'composite RF modulator' that'd convert the signal to a format that this TV can display.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These modulators output different channels at different frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These frequencies are what you 'tune' to by rotating the tuner's knob (learn more about tuners here). I left the tv tuner in a fixed channel, the same as what the modulator outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let there be video!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Software-based channels&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the Pi's output being displayed on the TV the next step was to get back the functionality of being able to rotate the knob to change channels.&lt;lb/&gt; I did this with software-based channels, controlled by a multi-polar rotary switch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Switch connected to GPIO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Powering the pi and modulator inside the TV&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The raspberry pi needs a 5v power source, and the RF modulator needed 9v.&lt;lb/&gt; I found a 12v rail and mounted an LM7809 and LM7805 to obtain the needed voltages inside the TV.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LM7809 and LM7805 placed using part of the TV as a heatsink&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Software&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially, the idea was to have a large set of shows/chapters (and advertisements) per channel, and pick from them randomly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had just recently started to get familiar with &lt;code&gt;gstreamer&lt;/code&gt; and could not get
my player to continuously play seamlessly -- either changing pads or containers
or something else would always make it get stuck after a while.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I opted to go with a massive hack: each channel is a single 8-hours long video, with the advertisements baked in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On poweroff, the timestamp of the nearest keyframe is saved and on power-on, playback resumes from there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a video reaches the end of playback, it will start again from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code can be found here, but be warned, it is very bad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First time I got it working -- the black spots are an artifact my phone's recording..&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Final version&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Extra&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also made a fake parcel-tracking website that'd display the status of the package.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Inspiration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This guy made me think about this in the first place. Our approaches are quite different, as I wanted to have the TV be 'stand alone'.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.davidv.dev/posts/revamping-an-old-tv-as-a-gift/"/><published>2025-09-19T14:43:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45303199</id><title>A shift in developer culture is impacting innovation and creativity</title><updated>2025-09-19T17:34:31.880021+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d541913a94518d5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Dev Culture Is Dying The Curious Developer Is Gone&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;When Curiosity Lead the Way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have been in software development for a while, you might remember a time when developers were launching unique and innovative products and projects just for the sake of curiosity, learning or even just because they had a particular interest in a specific topic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This curiosity and problem solving mindset gave us some of the best tools that we still use today such as VLC, Linux, Git, Apache HTTP Server, Docker(arguably), and many many more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These tools were not created by large corporations or solopreneurs looking to increase their MMR or ARR. They were created by curious developers who wanted to solve a unique problem they had or even just wanted to learn something new.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Nights Spend Chasing ideas and Tinkering&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I still remember back in the 2000s (2003-2009) the nights I spent tinkering with new technologies, frameworks, and programming languages. I would often find myself staying up late into the night, fueled by curiosity and a desire to learn more about the craft of software development. I would make the dumbest of projects and the strangest of shortcuts just because I could and just to see if it would work. Even if it would only serve me and no one else, I would still make it because it was simply fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Learning Without a Purpose&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is something to be said about learning without a clear purpose, goal or even a expected reward at the end of your journey. It allows you to explore new ideas and concepts without the pressure of having to deliver a specific outcome. It allows you to be creative and even tinker with suboptimal implementations and solutions or even some that are flat out insane or idiotic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because at the end of your journey, you will not be met with disappointment that you did not create a new product or service that will generate passive income or be used by hundreds of thousands of people. No, that was never your expectation going into it in the first place, you started the journey simply because you were curious and you wanted to create something even if your target demographic was just yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This in many ways leads to a better learning journey and a more fulfilling experience as you are not bound by the constraints of having to deliver a specific outcome or meet certain expectations. You can simply explore and learn at your own pace and in your own way. Don’t get me wrong this does not apply only to new comers to the field or junior software developers, this applies to every single developer out there even the most experienced ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Personally I’d consider myself fairly experienced in the field of software development, I started learning C++ back in 2003 and my first job as a software developer was in 2008. I’ve been in the field for a while now. In fact the longer I am in the field the more I realize that I know nothing. There is always something new to learn and explore and I find myself constantly tinkering with technologies be they new or old. Learning is not only about new and shiny tech, sometimes it’s assembly or system design, microcontrollers, embedded etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is plain and simply the tinkerers mindset and I believe that this mindset is slowly dying out in the field of software development. I find less and less like-minded people and I encounter more and more push back along the lines of “Why are you wasting your time with that? You should be focusing on X, Y or Z instead.” or “That is not going to help you in your career.” or even “You should be focusing on building products that will generate passive income or be used by hundreds of thousands of people.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Era of Metrics and Shiny Things&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I find that there has been a strong shift in developer culture over the past decade or so. A very strong and worrying shift towards metrics, revenue optimization, delivering “value” and “building for the masses”. I’m not sure this is a good shift but it is one that is happening nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems to me that the focus has shifted from curiosity, learning and a joy for creating cool things to a focus on metrics, observables, problem solving for your niche audience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I see countless developers spending their free time using their free time using technologies they do not enjoy building products they do not care about for an audience they do not understand, simply because they believe that this is what they should be doing in order to be successful as a software developer or to be taken seriously in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many who I talk to believe that this will set them apart from the rest of the pack or that they are a temporarily embarrassed startup CTO/founder or that they are building the next big thing that will paint their name in the stars and grant them the fame and respect of their fellow developers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But how can you ever hope to build something that huge if you do not even care about it? If the problem you are solving is not even a problem you yourself have or worse yet care about?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where a deeper issue shows itself, When you don’t care about what you are building you start looking elsewhere for that sense of progress, accomplishment or even identity. You become a Next.js developer, a React developer, a Rust developer etc… You start to identify yourself by the tools you use rather than the problems you solve or the things you create.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Chasing Every new Framework or Idea&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’ve identified with anything in this article so far, then take a moment and answer this to yourself honestly. How often did you find yourself working on your product or project only get think oh but this new framework/library/module/plugin is so much better, I should be using that instead of what I am doing right now, I need to improve my stack, I need to be using the latest and greatest. Because I am building something that will eventually be used by hundreds of thousands of people, so why stunt my growth, why risk being left behind?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Naturally your webapp has to use the latest version of React or Next.js with it’s latest features and optimizations, a year or so back (2023-2024) that was React server components.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or maybe you just had to switch to the newest version of Vue.js or Angular because they have some new feature that will make your life easier or your app faster or more scalable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or perhaps your utilities or backend are written in Go or Node or C# and really you should be using Rust because it’s just so damn fast and memory efficient. You can’t pass that up can you?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So you title yourself after whatever language, framework or library you are currently using. You are no longer a software developer, you are a Next.js developer, a specialist in your field.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;you chase every new shiny thing and you write a product or service in that shiny thing optimizing for MMR, ARR, DAU, MAU, SEO rankings, conversion rates and all that jazz. Wondering why your product or service is not taking off, why no one is using it, why you are not getting any traction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weird… you used all the right things, you’ve used the technology that you should have used you’ve optimized for all the right metrics, you’ve done everything by the book. So why is it not working?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What we Lost Along the Way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Constantly adopting the latest and greatest thing, not because it inspires you or because you care about it, but simply because you think you should be using it in order to be successful is a recipe for disaster. Not just for you for out entire developer culture as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t want to sound overly dramatic but I do lament the loss of the curious developer, the tinkerer, the obsessed creative that just wants to build something cool even if nobody cares about it, even if it only solves their own problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think we are slowly killing this mindset, it’s slowly disappearing from our culture wether that will be good or bad only time will tell. If you were to ask me I’d say it’s a very bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong we have occasional bright sparks of innovation and creativity HTMX, Bun, Astro, Zig and many other come to mind. But these are few and far between but they show that there are still curious developers out there, they are just harder to find and shrinking in numbers and being drowned out by the noise of metric seeking and revenue optimizations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The World Moves On, But Some of Us Remember&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t want to sound too much like a middle aged man lamenting a world that is changing around him. I understand the world moves on, you get more and more jaded and cynical as you get older. But I assure you this is not that. This is a pattern I’ve been noticing for a while and it worries me. The tools the projects that were built by curious developers are still around and still in use but compared to before we get relatively few new ones that are truly build out of curiosity and passion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are occasional sparks but not like before.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think of all the amazing software you use today, think which ones were made by insanely curious developers and think of how old that software is or when it came out and then think of more modern software and how many of those were made by massive corporations or solopreneurs or even just flat bought out or sold out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think we are losing something very important in our culture and I hope we can find it again before it’s too late. Before the curious developer is gone for good and we are left with a sea of software built with no privacy concerns, horrible monetization strategies, bloated frameworks and libraries and no ownership mindset, not for you the consumer and not by the creator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Death of Ownership is not Just for the Consumer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve all seen the shifting tide, consumers no longer own their software, you may buy the newest Adobe suite, or JetBrains IDE, latest iPhone or Android or even the latest Windows, but you do not own it. It can be taken away from you at any time, you simply rent it, you pay a monthly fee to use it. You do not own it, you simply have a license to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But do we ever take time to consider the loss of ownership for the creators? The developers, the curious tinkerers, the obsessed creatives that build these tools and software. Do they own it? Or do they simply rent it out to the highest bidder or sell it off to the largest corporation? Do people still want to build something that is uniquely their or do they simply want to build the latest and greatest SASS that they can rent out to the masses?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do they care about the software they build or do they simply care about the metrics, the revenue, the growth?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can argue that Linus Torvalds owns Linux and cares about Linux the kernel, you can argue that Jean Baptiste Kempf owns VLC and cares about VLC. Does Solomon Hykes own Docker and care about Docker? Does Daniel Ek own Spotify and care about Spotify? Does Mark Zuckerberg own Facebook and care about Facebook?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they owners, true owners of the product they built or did they simply become renters of their own creation, a slave to the metrics and revenue optimization?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again I don’t want to be overly dramatic but this is an important question we all should be asking ourselves. I know I am asking myself this question more and more often as I see the world around me change and the developer culture shift towards metrics and revenue optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Carving Space for Curiosity and Innovation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I implore you to find time in your life to be curious and creative to tinker and build something just for the sake of building it. Even if no one else cares about it, even if it only solves your own problem. Make something cool, something unique don’t care about others build it for yourself, built it because you want to and can.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t let the world tell you what you should be doing, what you should be building, what you should be using, no matter how ambitious or dumb or idiotic it may seem to others, make it because you want to, because it makes you happy, because it makes you feel alive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Software development is a unique craft, it’s equal parts creative and equal parts engineering, two opposing forces that when combined can create something truly amazing. Fight the temptation to add marketing into the mix and dilute the craft with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Build what you Can’t Ship&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a project in mind that you’ve always wanted to tackle but it never made sense to you to do it because it would never be used by anyone else or it would never make you any money? Do it anyway, build it, tinker with it, learn from it. Who cares if you can’t ship it to the masses, who cares if it’s useless. Make it, create something from nothing, just because you can.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Share the Spark&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might think this goes against my previous point, but it really does not. Share your work, share your creations, bring others into your world, if nobody responds who cares, you made it, you created something from nothing, maybe the value is in the journey and not the destination. Maybe the value is in the learning and not the outcome. Maybe the value is in the process and not the product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And who knows maybe your unique problem will be shared by others, maybe your unique solution will inspire others to create something new, something unique. Maybe your curiosity will spark a fire in someone else and they will go on to create something truly amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not impossible it happened for Linux, it happened for VLC heck it happened for Git.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just try to conceptualize what an insane idea Git was even when SVN was a well established and widely used version control system. Who in their right mind would think that a distributed version control system would be a good idea? Yet here we are, Git is the de facto standard for version control in software development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wrote this article to lament the loss of the curious spark in our developer culture, not to criticize or judge anyone. I understand the world moves on, I understand that we all have to make a living and that we all have to pay the bills. But I also believe that we should not lose sight of what makes software development such a unique and special craft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’ve made it this far, thank you, sincerely thank you. It’s one of my longer articles and I appreciate you taking the time to read it. I hope it has sparked something in you, I hope it has made you think about your own journey as a software developer and I hope it has inspired you to be curious and creative again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://dayvster.com/blog/dev-culture-is-dying-the-curious-developer-is-gone/"/><published>2025-09-19T16:02:22+00:00</published></entry></feed>