<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:22.538989+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872733</id><title>Launch HN: Modelence (YC S25) – App Builder with TypeScript / MongoDB Framework</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:30.879046+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bb22d77b01df145e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi all, Aram and Eduard here - co-founders of Modelence (&lt;/p&gt;https://modelence.com&lt;p&gt;). After spending years on scaling our previous startup’s platform, we built an open-source full-stack TypeScript + MongoDB framework to stop solving the same auth / database / API / cron job implementations every time we created an app, and we didn’t like the idea of using multiple managed platforms for each of these to run our apps either.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Here’s our prior Show HN post for reference: https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44902227)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we were excited by the whole AI app builder boom and realized that the real challenge there is the platform rather than the tool itself. Now we’re making Modelence the first full-stack framework that’s built for coding agents and humans alike:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- TypeScript is already great for AI coding because it provides guardrails and catches many errors at build time, so agents can auto-correct&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- MongoDB eliminates the schema management problem for agents, which is where they fail the most often otherwise (+ works great with TS/Node.js)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Built-in auth, database, cron jobs and else that just works together out of the box means agents only focus on your product logic and don’t fail at trying to set these things up (+ less tokens spent on boilerplate).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can now try the Modelence app builder (based on Claude Agent SDK) by just typing a prompt on our landing page ( https://modelence.com ) - watch a demo video here: https://youtu.be/BPsYvj_nGuE&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then you can check it out locally and continue working in your own IDE, while still using Modelence Cloud as your backend, with a dev cloud environment, and later deploy and run on Modelence Cloud with built-in observability around every operation running in your app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re also going to add a built-in DevOps agent that lives in the same cloud, knows the framework end-to-end, and will use all this observability data to act on errors, alerts, and incidents - closing the loop, because running in production is much harder than just building.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We launched the app builder as a quick start for developers, to demonstrate the framework and Modelence Cloud without having to manually read docs and follow the steps to set up a new app. Our main focus is still the platform itself, since we believe the real challenge in AI coding is the framework and the platform rather than the builder tool itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872733"/><published>2026-02-03T16:03:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872818</id><title>Show HN: C discrete event SIM w stackful coroutines runs 45x faster than SimPy</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:30.311078+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6a388adbeae31e0c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A fast discrete event simulation library written in C and assembly with POSIX pthreads. Simulated processes are implemented as stackful coroutines ("fibers") inside the pthreads.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Implementation status:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;x86-64: Stable, both for Linux and Windows&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apple Silicon: Planned&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ARM: Planned&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cimba models run 40-50 times faster than SimPy equivalents. The chart below shows the number of simulated events processed per second of wall clock time on a simple M/M/1 queue implemented in SimPy and Cimba. Cimba runs this scenario 45 times faster than SimPy with all CPU cores in use. Cimba runs 25 % faster (20M events/sec) on a single core than SimPy using all 64 cores (16M events/sec).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is fast, powerful, reliable, and free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Fast: The speed from multithreaded parallel execution translates to high resolution in your simulation modeling. You can run hundreds of replications and parameter variations in just a few seconds, generating tight confidence intervals in your experiments and a high density of data points along parameter variations.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In the benchmark shown above, Cimba reduces the run time by 97.8 % compared to the same model in SimPy using all CPU cores. This translates into doing your simulation experiments in seconds instead of minutes, or in minutes instead of hours.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Powerful: Cimba provides a comprehensive toolkit for discrete event simulation:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Processes implemented as asymmetric stackful coroutines. A simulated process can yield and resume control from any level of a function call stack, allowing well-structured coding of arbitrarily large simulation models. As a first-order object, a simulated process can be passed as an argument to other functions, returned from functions, and stored in data structures, allowing rich and complex interactions between processes.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Pre-packaged process interaction mechanisms like resources, resource pools, buffers, object queues, priority queues, and timeouts. Cimba also provides condition variables where your simulated processes can wait for arbitrarily complex conditions to become true – anything you can express as a function returning a binary true or false result.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;A wide range of fast, high-quality random number generators, both of academically important and more empirically oriented types. Important distributions like normal and exponential are implemented by state-of-the-art ziggurat rejection sampling for speed and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Integrated logging and data collection features that make it easy to get a model running and understand what is happening inside it, including custom asserts to pinpoint sources of errors.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;As a C library, Cimba allows easy integration with other libraries and programs. You could call CUDA routines to enhance your simulation models with GPU-powered agentic behavior or drive a fancy graphics interface like a 3D visualization of a manufacturing plant. You could even call the Cimba simulation engine from other programming languages, since the C calling convention is standard and well-documented.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reliable: Cimba is well-engineered open source. There is no mystery to the results you get. The code is written with liberal use of assertions to enforce preconditions, invariants, and postconditions in each function. The assertions act as self-enforcing documentation on expected inputs to and outputs from the Cimba functions. About 13 % of all code lines in the Cimba library are asssertions, a very high density. There are unit tests for each module. Running the unit test battery in debug mode (all assertions active) verifies the correct operation in great detail. You can do that by the one-liner&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;meson test -C build&lt;/code&gt;from the terminal command line.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Free: Cimba should fit well into the budget of most research groups.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is a general-purpose discrete event simulation library, in the spirit of a 21st century Simula67 descendant. You can use it to model, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;computer networks,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;transportation networks,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;operating system task scheduling,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;manufacturing systems and job shops,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;military command and control systems,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;hospital and emergency room patient flows,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;queuing systems like bank tellers and store checkouts,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;urban systems like public transport and garbage collection,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;and quite a few more application domains of similar kinds, where overall system complexity arises from interactions between relatively simple components.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you look under the hood, you will also find additional reusable internal components. Cimba contains stackful coroutines doing their own thing on thread-safe cactus stacks. There are fast memory pool allocators for generic small objects and hash-heaps combining a binary heap and an open addressing hash map using Fibonacci hashing. Although not part of the public Cimba API, these components can also be used in your model if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is C11/C17. As an illustration, this is the entire code for our multithreaded M/M/1 benchmark mentioned above:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;    #include &amp;lt;inttypes.h&amp;gt;
    #include &amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt;
    #include &amp;lt;stdint.h&amp;gt;
    
    #include &amp;lt;cimba.h&amp;gt;
    
    #define NUM_OBJECTS 1000000u
    #define ARRIVAL_RATE 0.9
    #define SERVICE_RATE 1.0
    #define NUM_TRIALS 100
    
    CMB_THREAD_LOCAL struct cmi_mempool objectpool = CMI_MEMPOOL_STATIC_INIT(8u, 512u);
    
    struct simulation {
        struct cmb_process *arrival;
        struct cmb_process *service;
        struct cmb_objectqueue *queue;
    };
    
    struct trial {
        double arr_mean;
        double srv_mean;
        uint64_t obj_cnt;
        double sum_wait;
        double avg_wait;
    };
    
    struct context {
        struct simulation *sim;
        struct trial *trl;
    };
    
    void *arrivalfunc(struct cmb_process *me, void *vctx)
    {
        cmb_unused(me);
        const struct context *ctx = vctx;
        struct cmb_objectqueue *qp = ctx-&amp;gt;sim-&amp;gt;queue;
        const double mean_hld = ctx-&amp;gt;trl-&amp;gt;arr_mean;
        for (uint64_t ui = 0; ui &amp;lt; NUM_OBJECTS; ui++) {
            const double t_hld = cmb_random_exponential(mean_hld);
            cmb_process_hold(t_hld);
            void *object = cmi_mempool_alloc(&amp;amp;objectpool);
            double *dblp = object;
            *dblp = cmb_time();
            cmb_objectqueue_put(qp, object);
        }
    
        return NULL;
    }
    
    void *servicefunc(struct cmb_process *me, void *vctx)
    {
        cmb_unused(me);
        const struct context *ctx = vctx;
        struct cmb_objectqueue *qp = ctx-&amp;gt;sim-&amp;gt;queue;
        const double mean_srv = ctx-&amp;gt;trl-&amp;gt;srv_mean;
        uint64_t *cnt = &amp;amp;(ctx-&amp;gt;trl-&amp;gt;obj_cnt);
        double *sum = &amp;amp;(ctx-&amp;gt;trl-&amp;gt;sum_wait);
        while (true) {
            void *object = NULL;
            cmb_objectqueue_get(qp, &amp;amp;object);
            const double *dblp = object;
            const double t_srv = cmb_random_exponential(mean_srv);
            cmb_process_hold(t_srv);
            const double t_sys = cmb_time() - *dblp;
            *sum += t_sys;
            *cnt += 1u;
            cmi_mempool_free(&amp;amp;objectpool, object);
        }
    }
    
    void run_trial(void *vtrl)
    {
        struct trial *trl = vtrl;
    
        cmb_logger_flags_off(CMB_LOGGER_INFO);
        cmb_random_initialize(cmb_random_hwseed());
        cmb_event_queue_initialize(0.0);
        struct context *ctx = malloc(sizeof(*ctx));
        ctx-&amp;gt;trl = trl;
        struct simulation *sim = malloc(sizeof(*sim));
        ctx-&amp;gt;sim = sim;
    
        sim-&amp;gt;queue = cmb_objectqueue_create();
        cmb_objectqueue_initialize(sim-&amp;gt;queue, "Queue", CMB_UNLIMITED);
    
        sim-&amp;gt;arrival = cmb_process_create();
        cmb_process_initialize(sim-&amp;gt;arrival, "Arrival", arrivalfunc, ctx, 0);
        cmb_process_start(sim-&amp;gt;arrival);
        sim-&amp;gt;service = cmb_process_create();
        cmb_process_initialize(sim-&amp;gt;service, "Service", servicefunc, ctx, 0);
        cmb_process_start(sim-&amp;gt;service);
    
        cmb_event_queue_execute();
    
        cmb_process_stop(sim-&amp;gt;service, NULL);
        cmb_process_terminate(sim-&amp;gt;arrival);
        cmb_process_terminate(sim-&amp;gt;service);
        cmb_process_destroy(sim-&amp;gt;arrival);
        cmb_process_destroy(sim-&amp;gt;service);
    
        cmb_objectqueue_destroy(sim-&amp;gt;queue);
        cmb_event_queue_terminate();
        free(sim);
        free(ctx);
    }
    
    int main(void)
    {
        struct trial *experiment = calloc(NUM_TRIALS, sizeof(*experiment));
        for (unsigned ui = 0; ui &amp;lt; NUM_TRIALS; ui++) {
            struct trial *trl = &amp;amp;experiment[ui];
            trl-&amp;gt;arr_mean = 1.0 / ARRIVAL_RATE;
            trl-&amp;gt;srv_mean = 1.0 / SERVICE_RATE;
            trl-&amp;gt;obj_cnt = 0u;
            trl-&amp;gt;sum_wait = 0.0;
        }
    
        cimba_run_experiment(experiment,
                             NUM_TRIALS,
                             sizeof(*experiment),
                             run_trial);
    
        struct cmb_datasummary summary;
        cmb_datasummary_initialize(&amp;amp;summary);
        for (unsigned ui = 0; ui &amp;lt; NUM_TRIALS; ui++) {
            const double avg_tsys = experiment[ui].sum_wait / (double)(experiment[ui].obj_cnt);
            cmb_datasummary_add(&amp;amp;summary, avg_tsys);
        }
    
        const unsigned un = cmb_datasummary_count(&amp;amp;summary);
        if (un &amp;gt; 1) {
            const double mean_tsys = cmb_datasummary_mean(&amp;amp;summary);
            const double sdev_tsys = cmb_datasummary_stddev(&amp;amp;summary);
            const double serr_tsys = sdev_tsys / sqrt((double)un);
            const double ci_w = 1.96 * serr_tsys;
            const double ci_l = mean_tsys - ci_w;
            const double ci_u = mean_tsys + ci_w;
    
            printf("Average system time %f (n %u, conf.int. %f - %f, expected %f)\n",
                   mean_tsys, un, ci_l, ci_u, 1.0 / (SERVICE_RATE - ARRIVAL_RATE));
    
            return 0;
        }
    }

&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See our tutorial at ReadTheDocs for more usage examples.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As shown above, it is some 45 times faster than SimPy in a relevant benchmark. It means getting your results almost immediately rather than after a "go brew a pot of coffee" delay breaking your line of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For another illustration of how to benefit from the sheer speed, the experiment in test_cimba.c simulates an M/G/1 queue at four different levels of service process variability. For each variability level, it tries five system utilization levels. There are ten replications for each parameter combination, in total 4 * 5 * 10 = 200 trials. Each trial lasts for one million time units, where the average service time always is 1.0 time units.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This entire simulation runs in about 1.5 seconds on an AMD Threadripper 3970X with Arch Linux and produces the chart below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Discrete event simulation fits well with an object-oriented paradigm. That is why object-oriented programming was invented in the first place for Simula67. Since OOP is not directly enforced in plain C, we provide the object-oriented characteristics (such as encapsulation, inheritance, polymorphism, and abstraction) in the Cimba software design instead. (See the ReadTheDocs explanation for more details.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The simulated processes are stackful coroutines on their own call stacks, allowing the processes to store their state at arbitrary points and resume execution from there later with minimal overhead. The context-switching code is hand-coded in assembly for each platform. (You can find more details here.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The C code is liberally sprinkled with &lt;code&gt;assert&lt;/code&gt; statements testing for preconditions,
invariants, and postconditions wherever possible, applying
Design by Contract
principles for high reliability. The Cimba library contains 958 asserts in 7132 lines of
C code, for a very high assert density of 13.4 %. These are custom-written
assert macros that will report
what trial, what process, the simulated time, the function and line number, and even the
random number seed used, if anything should go wrong. All time-consuming invariants and
postconditions are debug asserts, while the release asserts mostly check preconditions
like function argument validity. Turning off the debug asserts doubles the speed of your
model when you are ready for it, while turning off the release asserts as well gives
a small incremental improvement. (Again,
more explanation here.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is then combined with extensive unit testing of each module, ensuring that all lower level functionality works as expected before moving on to higher levels. You will find the test files corresponding to each code module in the test directory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But do read the LICENSE. We are not giving any warranties here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Long story made short: C++ exception handling is not very friendly to the stackful coroutines we need in Cimba. The stackless coroutines in C++ are entirely different from what we need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;C++ has also become a large and feature-rich language, where it will be hard to ensure compatibility with every possible combination of features.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hence (like the Linux kernel), we chose the simpler platform for speed, clarity, and reliability. If you need to call Cimba from some other language, the C calling convention is well-known and well-documented.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because it was not made public before. What retrospectively can be called Cimba 1.0 was implemented in K&amp;amp;R C at MIT in the early 1990's, followed by a parallelized version 2.0 in ANSI C and Perl around 1995–96. The present version written in C17 with POSIX pthreads is the third major rebuild, and the first public version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is right here. You clone the repository, build, and install it. You will need a C compiler and the Meson build manager. On Linux, you can use GCC or Clang, while the recommended approach on Windows is MinGW with its GCC compiler. For convenience, we recommend the CLion integrated development environment with GCC, Meson, and Ninja built-in support on both Linux and Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You will find the installation guide here: https://cimba.readthedocs.io/en/latest/installation.html&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/ambonvik/cimba"/><published>2026-02-03T16:09:07+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872894</id><title>X offices raided in France</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:30.015857+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="c9049b2d010d9784"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;X offices raided in France as prosecutors investigate child abuse images and deepfakes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;X offices raided in France as prosecutors investigate child abuse images and deepfakes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PARIS (AP) — French prosecutors raided the offices of social media platform X on Tuesday as part of a preliminary investigation into allegations including spreading child sexual abuse images and deepfakes. They have also summoned billionaire owner Elon Musk for questioning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;X and Musk’s artificial intelligence company xAI also face intensifying scrutiny from Britain’s data privacy regulator, which opened formal investigations into how they handled personal data when they developed and deployed Musk’s artificial intelligence chatbot Grok.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grok, which was built by xAI and is available through X, sparked global outrage last month after it pumped out a torrent of sexualized nonconsensual deepfake images in response to requests from X users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French investigation was opened in January last year by the prosecutors’ cybercrime unit, the Paris prosecutors’ office said in a statement. It’s looking into alleged “complicity” in possessing and spreading pornographic images of minors, sexually explicit deepfakes, denial of crimes against humanity and manipulation of an automated data processing system as part of an organized group, among other charges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prosecutors asked Musk and former CEO Linda Yaccarino to attend “voluntary interviews” on April 20. Employees of X have also been summoned that same week to be heard as witnesses, the statement said. Yaccarino was CEO from May 2023 until July 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A spokesperson for X did not respond to multiple requests for comment. X’s lawyer in France, Kami Haeri, told The Associated Press: ″We are not making any comment at this stage.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a message posted on X, the Paris prosecutors’ office announced the ongoing searches at the company’s offices in France and said it was leaving the platform while calling on followers to join it on other social media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At this stage, the conduct of the investigation is based on a constructive approach, with the aim of ultimately ensuring that the X platform complies with French law, as it operates on the national territory,” the prosecutors’ statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;European Union police agency Europol “is supporting the French authorities in this,” Europol spokesperson Jan Op Gen Oorth told the AP, without elaborating.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;French authorities opened their investigation after reports from a French lawmaker alleging that biased algorithms on X likely distorted the functioning of an automated data processing system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It expanded after Grok generated posts that allegedly denied the Holocaust, a crime in France, and spread sexually explicit deepfakes, the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grok wrote in a widely shared post in French that gas chambers at the Auschwitz-Birkenau death camp were designed for “disinfection with Zyklon B against typhus” rather than for mass murder — language long associated with Holocaust denial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In later posts on X, the chatbot reversed itself and acknowledged that its earlier reply was wrong, saying it had been deleted and pointed to historical evidence that Zyklon B was used to kill more than 1 million people in Auschwitz gas chambers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The chatbot also appeared to praise Adolf Hitler last year, in comments that X took down after complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Britain, the Information Commissioner’s Office said it’s looking into whether X and xAI followed the law when processing personal data and whether Grok had any measures in place to prevent its use to generate “harmful manipulated images.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The reports about Grok raise deeply troubling questions about how people’s personal data has been used to generate intimate or sexualised images without their knowledge or consent, and whether the necessary safeguards were put in place to prevent this,” said William Malcolm, an executive director at the watchdog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He didn’t specify what the penalty would be if the probe found the companies didn’t comply with data protection laws.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A separate investigation into Grok launched last month by the U.K. media regulator, Ofcom, is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ofcom said Tuesday it’s still gathering evidence and warned the probe could take months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;X has also been under pressure from the EU. The 27-nation bloc’s executive arm opened an investigation last month after Grok spewed nonconsensual sexualized deepfake images on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brussels has already hit X with a 120-million euro (then-$140 million) fine for shortcomings under the bloc’s sweeping digital regulations, including blue checkmarks that broke the rules on “deceptive design practices” that risked exposing users to scams and manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Monday, Musk ’s space exploration and rocket business, SpaceX, announced that it acquired xAI in a deal that will also combine Grok, X and his satellite communication company Starlink.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Associated Press writers Nicolas Vaux-Montagny in Lyon, France, Mike Corder in The Hague, Netherlands, Sylvia Hui and Kelvin Chan in London contributed to this report.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://apnews.com/article/france-x-investigation-seach-elon-musk-1116be84d84201011219086ecfd4e0bc"/><published>2026-02-03T16:14:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873133</id><title>Tadpole – A modular and extensible DSL built for web scraping</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:29.862758+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d7a2168e9b832ef8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Tadpole&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scrape the web with a language designed for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Write Declarative, Modular Scraping Code&lt;/head&gt;Section titled “Write Declarative, Modular Scraping Code”&lt;p&gt;Tadpole is built to be composable by allowing you to import modules from local files or remote repositories! All of the complexity of interacting with the browser is now completely abstracted away by the language! Building scrapers has never been easier!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://tadpolehq.com/"/><published>2026-02-03T16:29:13+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873138</id><title>Prek: A better, faster, drop-in pre-commit replacement, engineered in Rust</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:28.649518+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="28df57ddde9b6d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pre-commit is a framework to run hooks written in many languages, and it manages the language toolchain and dependencies for running the hooks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is a reimagined version of pre-commit, built in Rust. It is designed to be a faster, dependency-free and drop-in alternative for it, while also providing some additional long-requested features.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although prek is pretty new, it’s already powering real‑world projects like CPython, Apache Airflow, FastAPI, and more projects are picking it up—see Who is using prek?. If you’re looking for an alternative to &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;, please give it a try—we’d love your feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please note that some languages are not yet supported for full drop‑in parity with &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;. See Language Support for current status.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🚀 A single binary with no dependencies, does not require Python or any other runtime.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;⚡ Faster than &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;and more efficient in disk space usage.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🔄 Fully compatible with the original pre-commit configurations and hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🏗️ Built-in support for monorepos (i.e. workspace mode).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🐍 Integration with &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt;for managing Python virtual environments and dependencies.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🛠️ Improved toolchain installations for Python, Node.js, Bun, Go, Rust and Ruby, shared between hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📦 Built-in Rust-native implementation of some common hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Standalone installer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek provides a standalone installer script to download and install the tool,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Linux and macOS:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;curl --proto '=https' --tlsv1.2 -LsSf https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.sh | sh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Windows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;powershell -ExecutionPolicy ByPass -c "irm https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.ps1 | iex"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;PyPI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is published as Python binary wheel to PyPI, you can install it using &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt; (recommended), or &lt;code&gt;pipx&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Using uv (recommended)
uv tool install prek

# Using uvx (install and run in one command)
uvx prek

# Adding prek to the project dev-dependencies
uv add --dev prek

# Using pip
pip install prek

# Using pipx
pipx install prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Homebrew&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;brew install prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Cargo&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build from source using Cargo (Rust 1.89+ is required):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cargo install --locked prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;npmjs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is published as a Node.js package and can be installed with any npm-compatible package manager:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# As a dev dependency
npm add -D @j178/prek
pnpm add -D @j178/prek
bun add -D @j178/prek

# Or install globally
npm install -g @j178/prek
pnpm add -g @j178/prek
bun install -g @j178/prek

# Or run directly without installing
npx @j178/prek --version
bunx @j178/prek --version&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Nix&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is available via Nixpkgs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Choose what's appropriate for your use case.
# One-off in a shell:
nix-shell -p prek

# NixOS or non-NixOS without flakes:
nix-env -iA nixos.prek

# Non-NixOS with flakes:
nix profile install nixpkgs#prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;GitHub Releases&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-built binaries are available for download from the GitHub releases page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;GitHub Actions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek can be used in GitHub Actions via the j178/prek-action repository.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example workflow:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;name: Prek checks
on: [push, pull_request]

jobs:
  prek:
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    steps:
      - uses: actions/checkout@v6
      - uses: j178/prek-action@v1&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This action installs prek and runs &lt;code&gt;prek run --all-files&lt;/code&gt; on your repository.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is also available via &lt;code&gt;taiki-e/install-action&lt;/code&gt; for installing various tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If installed via the standalone installer, prek can update itself to the latest version:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;prek self update&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I already use pre-commit: follow the short migration checklist in the quickstart guide to swap in &lt;code&gt;prek&lt;/code&gt;safely.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I'm new to pre-commit-style tools: learn the basics—creating a config, running hooks, and installing git hooks—in the beginner quickstart walkthrough.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It is multiple times faster than &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;and takes up half the disk space.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It redesigned how hook environments and toolchains are managed, they are all shared between hooks, which reduces the disk space usage and speeds up the installation process.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Repositories are cloned in parallel, and hooks are installed in parallel if their dependencies are disjoint.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hooks can run in parallel by priority (hooks with the same &lt;code&gt;priority&lt;/code&gt;may run concurrently), reducing end-to-end runtime.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It uses &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt;for creating Python virtualenvs and installing dependencies, which is known for its speed and efficiency.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It implements some common hooks in Rust, built in prek, which are faster than their Python counterparts.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It supports &lt;code&gt;repo: builtin&lt;/code&gt;for offline, zero-setup hooks, which is not available in&lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No need to install Python or any other runtime, just download a single binary.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No hassle with your Python version or virtual environments, prek automatically installs the required Python version and creates a virtual environment for you.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Built-in support for workspaces (or monorepos), each subproject can have its own &lt;code&gt;.pre-commit-config.yaml&lt;/code&gt;file.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run&lt;/code&gt;has some nifty improvements over&lt;code&gt;pre-commit run&lt;/code&gt;, such as:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run --directory &amp;lt;dir&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;runs hooks for files in the specified directory, no need to use&lt;code&gt;git ls-files -- &amp;lt;dir&amp;gt; | xargs pre-commit run --files&lt;/code&gt;anymore.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run --last-commit&lt;/code&gt;runs hooks for files changed in the last commit.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run [HOOK] [HOOK]&lt;/code&gt;selects and runs multiple hooks.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek list&lt;/code&gt;command lists all available hooks, their ids, and descriptions, providing a better overview of the configured hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek auto-update&lt;/code&gt;supports&lt;code&gt;--cooldown-days&lt;/code&gt;to mitigate open source supply chain attacks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;prek provides shell completions for &lt;code&gt;prek run &amp;lt;hook_id&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;command, making it easier to run specific hooks without remembering their ids.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more detailed improvements prek offers, take a look at Difference from pre-commit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is pretty new, but it is already being used or recommend by some projects and organizations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;apache/airflow&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;python/cpython&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pdm-project/pdm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fastapi/fastapi&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fastapi/typer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fastapi/asyncer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;astral-sh/ruff&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;astral-sh/ty&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;openclaw/openclaw&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;home-assistant/core&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;DetachHead/basedpyright&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OpenLineage/OpenLineage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;authlib/authlib&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;django/djangoproject.com&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Future-House/paper-qa&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;requests-cache/requests-cache&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Goldziher/kreuzberg&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;python-attrs/attrs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;jlowin/fastmcp&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;apache/iceberg-python&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;apache/lucene&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;jcrist/msgspec&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;python-humanize/humanize&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MoonshotAI/kimi-cli&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;simple-icons/simple-icons&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ast-grep/ast-grep&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;commitizen-tools/commitizen&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;cocoindex-io/cocoindex&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;cachix/devenv&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is heavily inspired by the original pre-commit tool, and it wouldn't be possible without the hard work of the maintainers and contributors of that project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And a special thanks to the Astral team for their remarkable projects, particularly uv, from which I've learned a lot on how to write efficient and idiomatic Rust code.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/j178/prek"/><published>2026-02-03T16:29:34+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873294</id><title>France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:28.245539+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="af50b110b70b4885"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LONDON (AP) — In France, civil servants will ditch Zoom and Teams for a homegrown video conference system. Soldiers in Austria are using open source office software to write reports after the military dropped Microsoft Office. Bureaucrats in a German state have also turned to free software for their administrative work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Around Europe, governments and institutions are seeking to reduce their use of digital services from U.S. Big Tech companies and turning to domestic or free alternatives. The push for “digital sovereignty” is gaining attention as the Trump administration strikes an increasingly belligerent posture toward the continent, highlighted by recent tensions over Greenland that intensified fears that Silicon Valley giants could be compelled to cut off access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concerns about data privacy and worries that Europe is not doing enough to keep up with the United States and Chinese tech leadership are also fueling the drive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French government referenced some of these concerns when it announced last week that 2.5 million civil servants would stop using video conference tools from U.S. providers — including Zoom, Microsoft Teams, Webex and GoTo Meeting — by 2027 and switch to Visio, a homegrown service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The objective is “to put an end to the use of non-European solutions, to guarantee the security and confidentiality of public electronic communications by relying on a powerful and sovereign tool,” the announcement said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We cannot risk having our scientific exchanges, our sensitive data, and our strategic innovations exposed to non-European actors,” David Amiel, a civil service minister, said in a press release.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft said it continues to “partner closely with the government in France and respect the importance of security, privacy, and digital trust for public institutions.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company said it is “focused on providing customers with greater choice, stronger data protection, and resilient cloud services — ensuring data stays in Europe, under European law, with robust security and privacy protections.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zoom, Webex and GoTo Meeting did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;French President Emmanuel Macron has been pushing digital sovereignty for years. But there’s now a lot more “political momentum behind this idea now that we need to de-risk from U.S. tech,” Nick Reiners, senior geotechnology analyst at the Eurasia Group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It feels kind of like there’s a real zeitgeist shift,” Reiners said&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was a hot topic at the World Economic Forum’s annual meeting of global political and business elites last month in Davos, Switzerland. The European Commission’s official for tech sovereignty, Henna Virkkunen, told an audience that Europe’s reliance on others “can be weaponized against us.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“That’s why it’s so important that we are not dependent on one country or one company when it comes to very critical fields of our economy or society,” she said, without naming countries or companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A decisive moment came last year when the Trump administration sanctioned the International Criminal Court’s top prosecutor after the tribunal, based in The Hague, Netherlands, issued an arrest warrant for Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, an ally of President Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sanctions led Microsoft to cancel Khan’s ICC email, a move that was first reported by The Associated Press and sparked fears of a “kill switch” that Big Tech companies can use to turn off service at will.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft maintains it kept in touch with the ICC “throughout the process that resulted in the disconnection of its sanctioned official from Microsoft services. At no point did Microsoft cease or suspend its services to the ICC.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft President Brad Smith has repeatedly sought to strengthen trans-Atlantic ties, the company’s press office said, and pointed to an interview he did last month with CNN in Davos in which he said that jobs, trade and investment. as well as security, would be affected by a rift over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Europe is the American tech sector’s biggest market after the United States itself. It all depends on trust. Trust requires dialogue,” Smith said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other incidents have added to the movement. There’s a growing sense that repeated EU efforts to rein in tech giants such as Google with blockbuster antitrust fines and sweeping digital rule books haven’t done much to curb their dominance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Billionaire Elon Musk is also a factor. Officials worry about relying on his Starlink satellite internet system for communications in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Washington and Brussels wrangled for years over data transfer agreements, triggered by former National Security Agency contractor Edward Snowden’s revelations of U.S. cyber-snooping.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With online services now mainly hosted in the cloud through data centers, Europeans fear that their data is vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;U.S. cloud providers have responded by setting up so-called “sovereign cloud” operations, with data centers located in European countries, owned by European entities and with physical and remote access only for staff who are European Union residents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The idea is that “only Europeans can take decisions so that they can’t be coerced by the U.S.,” Reiners said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The German state of Schleswig-Holstein last year migrated 44,000 employee inboxes from Microsoft to an open source email program. It also switched from Microsoft’s SharePoint file sharing system to Nextcloud, an open source platform, and is even considering replacing Windows with Linux and telephones and videoconferencing with open source systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We want to become independent of large tech companies and ensure digital sovereignty,” Digitalization Minister Dirk Schrödter said in an October announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French city of Lyon said last year that it’s deploying free office software to replace Microsoft. Denmark’s government and the cities of Copenhagen and Aarhus have also been trying out open-source software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We must never make ourselves so dependent on so few that we can no longer act freely,” Digital Minister Caroline Stage Olsen wrote on LinkedIn last year. “Too much public digital infrastructure is currently tied up with very few foreign suppliers.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Austrian military said it has also switched to LibreOffice, a software package with word processor, spreadsheet and presentation programs that mirrors Microsoft 365’s Word, Excel and PowerPoint.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Document Foundation, a nonprofit based in Germany that’s behind LibreOffice, said the military’s switch “reflects a growing demand for independence from single vendors.” Reports also said the military was concerned that Microsoft was moving file storage online to the cloud — the standard version of LibreOffice is not cloud-based.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some Italian cities and regions adopted the software years ago, said Italo Vignoli, a spokesman for The Document Foundation. Back then, the appeal was not needing to pay for software licenses. Now, it’s the main reason is to avoid being locked into a proprietary system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At first, it was: we will save money and by the way, we will get freedom,” Vignoli said. “Today it is: we will be free and by the way, we will also save some money.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Associated Press writer Molly Quell in The Hague, Netherlands contributed to this report.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This version corrects the contribution line to Molly Quell instead of Molly Hague.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://apnews.com/article/europe-digital-sovereignty-big-tech-9f5388b68a0648514cebc8d92f682060"/><published>2026-02-03T16:39:18+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873308</id><title>Show HN: PII-Shield – Log Sanitization Sidecar with JSON Integrity (Go, Entropy)</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:27.750129+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a9d375110733db96"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zero-code log sanitization sidecar for Kubernetes. Prevents data leaks (GDPR/SOC2) by redacting PII from logs before they leave the pod.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developers often forget to mask sensitive data. Traditional regex filters in Fluentd/Logstash are slow, hard to maintain, and consume expensive CPU on log aggregators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PII-Shield sits right next to your app container:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;High Performance: Written in Go, designed for low-latency log processing.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Context-Aware Entropy Analysis: Detected high-entropy secrets even without keys (e.g. &lt;code&gt;Error: ... 44saCk9...&lt;/code&gt;) by analyzing context keywords.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;100% Accuracy: Verified against "Wild" stress tests including binary garbage, JSON nesting, and multilingual logs.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Deterministic Hashing: Replaces secrets with unique hashes (e.g., &lt;code&gt;[HIDDEN:a1b2c]&lt;/code&gt;), allowing QA to correlate errors without seeing the raw data.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Drop-in: No code changes required. Works with any language (Node, Python, Java, Go).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get the latest lightweight image from Docker Hub:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;docker pull thelisdeep/pii-shield:latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See CONFIGURATION.md for a full list of environment variables, including:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;PII_SALT&lt;/code&gt;: Custom HMAC salt (Required for production).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;PII_ADAPTIVE_THRESHOLD&lt;/code&gt;: Enable dynamic entropy baselines.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;PII_DISABLE_BIGRAM_CHECK&lt;/code&gt;: Optimize for non-English logs.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Test Locally (CLI) You can pipe any log output through PII-Shield to see it in action immediately:&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Emulate a log with a sensitive password
echo "Error: User password=MySecretPass123! failed login" | docker run -i --rm thelisdeep/pii-shield:latest

# Output: Error: User password=[HIDDEN:8f3a11] failed login&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Kubernetes (Sidecar Pattern) To use PII-Shield as a pipe wrapper for your application, use an &lt;code&gt;initContainer&lt;/code&gt;to copy the binary into a shared volume.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;apiVersion: v1
kind: Pod
metadata:
  name: secure-app
spec:
  volumes:
  - name: bin-dir
    emptyDir: {}
  
  # 1. Copy the PII-Shield binary to a shared volume
  initContainers:
  - name: install-shield
    image: thelisdeep/pii-shield:latest
    command: ["cp", "/bin/pii-shield", "/opt/bin/pii-shield"]
    volumeMounts:
    - name: bin-dir
      mountPath: /opt/bin

  # 2. Run your app and pipe logs through PII-Shield
  containers:
  - name: my-app
    image: my-app:1.0
    command: ["/bin/sh", "-c"]
    # Pipe stderr/stdout through the sanitizer
    args: ["./start-app.sh 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1 | /opt/bin/pii-shield"] 
    volumeMounts:
    - name: bin-dir
      mountPath: /opt/bin&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is verified with a comprehensive suite:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unit Tests: Cover edge cases, multilingual support, and JSON integrity.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fuzzing: Native Go fuzzing ensures crash safety against invalid inputs.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Stress Testing: &lt;code&gt;./full_stress_test.sh&lt;/code&gt;validates 100% detection accuracy on mixed workloads.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Distributed under the Apache 2.0 License. See &lt;code&gt;LICENSE&lt;/code&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/aragossa/pii-shield"/><published>2026-02-03T16:40:12+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873574</id><title>221 Cannon Road Is Not for Sale</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:27.527996+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ec0da09223e19cd5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like most people, I’ve had my identity stolen once or twice in my life. It’s annoying, but thankfully I’ve avoided some of the more catastrophic outcomes when criminals begin impersonating you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These days, however, it seems like someone is really trying to change that: a scammer has now tried to impersonate me multiple times in a six figure land deal in my hometown of Wilton, CT. So while I usually use this blog to write about finding weird things on the internet, it’s now time for a story about something weird on the internet finding me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The story begins with my brother Alexander and I purchasing a small parcel of vacant land at 221 Cannon Road in Wilton, Connecticut in 2015. It’s been over 10 years since we purchased it and we have never listed it for sale. Nor do we have plans to sell it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yet, three different real estate agents have now contacted us to let us know that someone has been impersonating us and attempting to sell our property out from under us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first time it happened, it was pretty upsetting, but now that it’s happened another two times, I figured it was time to write a blog post about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The First Attempt (March 2024)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In March 2024, I received an email from a real estate attorney in Wilton, asking if I was the “Fred Benenson” who co-owned property in town with an “Ed Benenson.” He explained that a realtor at a major brokerage had been working with someone claiming to be us, and that there was already an offer on the table. The attorney was doing his due diligence before representing the sellers — and something didn’t add up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I replied within minutes: Neither of us had spoken to anyone about selling the property. It was pretty concerning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The realtor had been contacted through Zillow by someone claiming to be me. They’d had a phone conversation — she noted the person had a “middle European” accent — and the scammer had provided accurate details about the property, including its exact acreage. The impostor gave her the email address &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt; and the phone number (516) 828-0305. He also provided a fake email for my brother: &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt;. Notice the subtle misspelling — “Benenson” without the second “n” in the email, and the hyphenated “out-look.com” domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She had walked the property, taken drone photos, pulled comps, and listed for a price well above what we paid for it. The property had been live on dozens of real estate websites for days before anyone caught it. A builder had already submitted a full-price cash offer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scammer had even e-signed a purchase agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the attorney requested identification before closing, the impostor provided a New York State driver’s license. It had my father’s name (which I share with him) and his correct date of birth and home address. But the photo was of a complete stranger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have no idea who that guy is in on the license, but it’s definitely not my Dad. The license wouldn’t fool anyone who knew my father, but it didn’t need to – in a transaction conducted entirely by email and text message, with a closing that the scammer would never actually attend, the ID just needed to look plausible enough to keep things moving forward. (Though if you look closely at his signature, it’s clearly not written by hand.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How It Was Caught&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attorney deserves most of the credit here. He told me this was the second time in nine months he’d encountered this exact scheme on vacant land in Wilton – his policy is that he won’t represent owners of vacant land without independently verifying ownership. That’s what led him to track me down, and that’s what stopped the sale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The realtor was an innocent victim in this too. She’d done her job by walking the property, pulling comps, etc., all in good faith. When I initially suggested (perhaps unfairly) that this felt like lead generation, the attorney took me aside and vouched for her. I’m glad I listened to him!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I apologized to her, and she graciously forwarded me all of her text message exchanges with the scammer. Reading through them was fascinating. The impostor was responsive, polite, and generally knew the right things to say. But there were tells: slightly awkward phrasing (“Hi good morning”), declining a for-sale sign (“No I don’t think that will be necessary”), and a general reluctance to engage in any way that might require showing up in person.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Going to the FBI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After gathering everything I could — the fake ID, the realtor’s text messages, the scammer’s email addresses and phone number, and the attorney’s notes from a prior similar case — I contacted the FBI field office in Connecticut. They directed me to “walk it in” to the office in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The experience was, frankly, underwhelming. The FBI wouldn’t let me submit any of our documentation. Instead, they required me to write out the entire complaint by hand on a single piece of paper and hand it to the guard. He made some calls while I waited, and by the end he seemed at least somewhat interested. He gave me the standard line: 2-3 weeks if I hear from anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I never heard from anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attorney, meanwhile, checked with his title company about recording an affidavit on the land records — something that would alert any future buyer or title searcher that the property had been targeted by fraud, and providing our verified contact information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;It’s Happening Again (February 2026)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought this was behind us. Then, this past week, nearly two years later, I was contacted by two more real estate agents, both reaching out to warn me that someone was once again trying to sell 221 Cannon Road.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first was a agent in Wilton who reached out via Instagram DM, of all places — it was the only way he could find to contact me. He explained that his team had received an inquiry to list 221 Cannon Road and had sent paperwork to “Fred and Alex” the night before to sign. But he’d done something smart: he’d noticed he had a mutual friend with my brother, and when he asked him about the situation, he flagged that the conversation with “Alex” didn’t sound right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I had a really bad feeling it wasn’t,” he told me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second agent, a woman at Berkshire Hathaway, sent a carefully worded email explaining that she’d been contacted by someone claiming to have authority to sell our property, but that “several standard verification steps raised concerns” and she chose not to proceed. She reached out purely as a courtesy to let us know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which is about when I decided I should write something about this. Not only because it’s a fascinating scam that seems to be getting more common, but because I figured this post might show up for the next broker who might be doing research on the address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Vacant Land Fraud&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This type of scam targets a very specific vulnerability: vacant land has no occupants to notice a for-sale sign, no neighbors who’d immediately recognize something is wrong, and closings often happen remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The scammer identifies vacant land through public records or Zillow. They look for parcels that are owned free and clear (no mortgage), haven’t changed hands recently, and are in desirable areas.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They contact a real estate agent through a platform like Zillow, posing as the owner. They know the property details because that information is publicly available.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They communicate primarily through text and email, avoiding in-person meetings. They provide fake identification if asked.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They agree to whatever price the agent suggests (because they don’t actually own the property, any sale is pure profit).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They push for a quick closing and attempt to direct proceeds to an account they control.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If questioned, they disappear. The scammer who targeted us in 2024 simply stopped responding once the attorney asked for an in-person closing.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If they get farther they’ll pocket the earnest money deposit which would have been significant in my case.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A similar scheme in nearby Fairfield wasn’t caught in time: someone had a $1.5 million home built on land they didn’t own without the actual owners knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What You Can Do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you own vacant land there are a couple of things you can do, but the most effective one is probably to register the address with a Fraud / No-Authority notice. This involves calling the County Recorder / Register of Deeds and ask how to record one of these (names vary by state):&lt;lb/&gt; • Owner Affidavit&lt;lb/&gt; • Affidavit of Fact&lt;lb/&gt; • Notice of Non-Authority to Convey&lt;lb/&gt; • Fraud Alert / Title Alert Notice&lt;lb/&gt; • Statement of Ownership / Anti-Fraud Notice:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You could also setup up Google Alerts for your address and you’ll be notified if it appears online.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, and this certainly isn’t for everyone, you can make yourself easily findable online. One reason the attorney was able to verify ownership quickly in 2024 was that it’s fairly easy to gooogle me. If you own property, make sure there’s some way for a diligent attorney or agent to reach the real you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Property Is Not For Sale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In case it isn’t clear, 221 Cannon Road is not for sale. It has never been for sale. If you are a real estate professional who has been contacted about listing or purchasing this property, please reach out to me directly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://fredbenenson.com/blog/2026/02/03/221-cannon-is-not-for-sale/"/><published>2026-02-03T16:56:06+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873742</id><title>Show HN: I built "AI Wattpad" to eval LLMs on fiction</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:27.267406+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="c3079dfd9fbca34b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Best AI Models for Creative Writing in 2026&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;See which AI models actually keep readers hooked—based on real data, not synthetic benchmarks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Our Architecture&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each novel uses three specialized AI models working together. Compare performance across each role to understand which models excel at different creative writing tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Brainstorming Model&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create concepts, plots, and world-building&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Writer Model&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write chapters and narrative content&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Memory Model&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maintain story context and recall information&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Want to see a specific model benchmarked? Let us know on Discord!&lt;/p&gt;Suggest New Model(opens in new tab)&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://narrator.sh/llm-leaderboard"/><published>2026-02-03T17:08:43+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873782</id><title>Show HN: Octosphere, a tool to decentralise scientific publishing</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:26.753419+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f9dc5bdd087c8698"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Octosphere&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Connecting open science with the social web&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What is Octosphere?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Octosphere bridges the gap between academic publishing and the social web. It automatically syncs your research publications from Octopus to the AT Protocol (the atmosphere) — an open, decentralized network for social apps like Bluesky.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By sharing your work on the atmosphere, you can reach broader audiences, engage with the public, and increase the visibility of your research beyond traditional academic channels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How it works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sign in with ORCID — Authenticate using your researcher identifier.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Connect to the atmosphere — Sign in with your Bluesky account (or any AT Protocol app).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Link your Octopus profile — Connect your Octopus author page.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sync your publications — Choose one-time sync or enable automatic syncing of future publications.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://octosphere.social/"/><published>2026-02-03T17:11:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873790</id><title>Defining Safe Hardware Design [pdf]</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:26.421775+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://people.csail.mit.edu/rachit/files/pubs/safe-hdls.pdf"/><published>2026-02-03T17:12:04+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873885</id><title>Migrate Wizard – IMAP Based Email Migration Tool</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:26.253317+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="8cfa0d9d71ab0df"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trusted by teams around the world&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Migrate Your Emails in&lt;lb/&gt;Minutes, Not Days&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fastest, most secure IMAP migration service. Move gigabytes of emails between any providers with zero downtime and 100% data integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No technical expertise required. No data loss. No headaches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10K+&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Successful Migrations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;99.9%&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Success Rate&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;5min&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Average Time&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;24/7&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Everything You Need for a Perfect Migration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Built for speed, security, and reliability. Trusted by businesses of all sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lightning Fast&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Optimized algorithms move gigabytes of data in minutes, not days. Parallel processing ensures maximum speed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enterprise-Grade Security&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Credentials encrypted and deleted when the migration finishes, with enterprise-grade infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;100% Data Integrity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Advanced error handling and verification ensures every email, folder, and attachment is perfectly migrated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zero Downtime&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Continue using your email during migration. No service interruption, no business disruption.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No Credential Storage&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your passwords are encrypted in memory only and deleted immediately after migration completes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incremental Sync&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep your emails synchronized after initial migration. Perfect for ongoing data consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Perfect for Every Scenario&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether you're switching providers or consolidating accounts, we've got you covered.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Provider Migration&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Switching from Gmail, Outlook, Yahoo, or any IMAP provider? We handle it seamlessly with zero data loss.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Account Consolidation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Merge multiple email accounts into one. Perfect for businesses consolidating their communication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Backup &amp;amp; Archive&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create secure backups of your entire email history. Essential for compliance and disaster recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Ready to Migrate Your Emails?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Join thousands of satisfied customers who've migrated millions of emails with Migrate Wizard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No credit card required • Free trial available • Cancel anytime&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://migratewizard.com/#features"/><published>2026-02-03T17:19:47+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874097</id><title>Deno Sandbox</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:25.410687+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="84be1f18cd2fafa2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Introducing Deno Sandbox&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past year, we’ve seen a shift in what Deno Deploy customers are building: platforms where users generate code with LLMs, and that code runs immediately without review. That code frequently calls LLMs itself, which means it needs API keys and network access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t the traditional “run untrusted plugins” problem. It’s deeper: LLM-generated code, calling external APIs with real credentials, without human review. Sandboxing the compute isn’t enough. You need to control network egress and protect secrets from exfiltration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox provides both. And when the code is ready, you can deploy it directly to Deno Deploy without rebuilding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandboxes?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t want to run untrusted code (generated by your LLMs, your users LLMs, or even hand written by users) directly on your server. It will compromise your system, steal your API keys, and call out to evil.com. You need isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox gives you lightweight Linux microVMs (running in the Deno Deploy cloud) to run untrusted code with defense-in-depth security. You create or programmatically via our JavaScript or Python SDKs, and they boot in under a second. You can also interact with them via SSH, HTTP, or even open a VS Code window directly into the sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Sandbox } from "@deno/sandbox";

await using sandbox = await Sandbox.create();
await sandbox.sh`ls -lh /`;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Secrets That Can’t Be Stolen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there is more. In Deno Sandbox, secrets never enter the environment. Code sees only a placeholder:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Sandbox } from "@deno/sandbox";

await using sandbox = await Sandbox.create({
  secrets: {
    OPENAI_API_KEY: {
      hosts: ["api.openai.com"],
      value: process.env.OPENAI_API_KEY,
    },
  },
});

await sandbox.sh`echo $OPENAI_API_KEY`;
// DENO_SECRET_PLACEHOLDER_b14043a2f578cba75ebe04791e8e2c7d4002fd0c1f825e19...&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The real key materializes only when the sandbox makes an outbound request to an approved host. If prompt-injected code tries to exfiltrate that placeholder to &lt;code&gt;evil.com&lt;/code&gt;? Useless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Network Egress Control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also restrict which hosts the sandbox can talk to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;await using sandbox = await Sandbox.create({
  allowNet: ["api.openai.com", "*.anthropic.com"],
});&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any request to an unlisted host gets blocked at the VM boundary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both features are implemented via an outbound proxy similar to coder/httpjail. This gives us a chokepoint for policy enforcement. We plan to add more capabilities here: analytics for outbound connections and programmatic hooks for trusted code to inspect or modify requests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re running untrusted JavaScript or TypeScript, combine this with Deno’s &lt;code&gt;--allow-net&lt;/code&gt; flag for defense in depth: VM-level network restrictions plus
runtime-level permissions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandbox to Production&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sandbox.deploy()&lt;/code&gt; deploys code from your sandbox directly to Deno Deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const build = await sandbox.deploy("my-app", {
  production: true,
  build: { mode: "none", entrypoint: "server.ts" },
});

const revision = await build.done;
console.log(revision.url);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One call to go from sandbox to production deployment. No rebuilding in a different CI system, no re-authenticating with a different tool. Just turn your dev environment directly into a production ready, auto-scaling serverless deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Persistence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sandboxes are ephemeral by default, but when you need state we have you covered:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Volumes: read-write storage for caches, databases, user data&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Snapshots: read-only images for pre-installed toolchains and volume base&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;apt-get install&lt;/code&gt; once, snapshot it, and every future sandbox boots with
everything already installed. Create read-write volumes from the snapshots to
create a fresh development environment in seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Technical Details&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Spec&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Value&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Regions&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Amsterdam, Chicago&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;vCPUs&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Memory&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;768 MB - 4 GB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Lifetime&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ephemeral or timeout (supports extending on demand)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Max lifetime&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 minutes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Boot time&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&amp;lt; 1 second&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perfect for AI agents executing code, vibe-coding environments, secure plugin systems, ephemeral CI runners, and customer-supplied code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pricing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox is included in your Deno Deploy plan with competitive, usage-based pricing. You pay for compute time, not wall-clock time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;$0.05/h CPU time (40h included with Pro)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;$0.016/GB-h memory (1000 GB-h included with Pro)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;$0.20/GiB-month volume storage (5 GiB included with Pro)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enterprise pricing available—contact deploy@deno.com.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Get Started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox launches in beta today, alongside the general availability of Deno Deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Landing page: deno.com/sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Docs: docs.deno.com/sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;JavaScript SDK: jsr.io/@deno/sandbox or npm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Python SDK: pypi.org/project/deno-sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re excited to see what you (or your AI agents) build with Deno Sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://deno.com/blog/introducing-deno-sandbox"/><published>2026-02-03T17:33:20+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874139</id><title>Sandboxing AI Agents in Linux</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:25.147998+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7d9ab85b0e859780"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandboxing AI agents in Linux&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like many developers, I find myself more and more using AI agents to help with software development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I currently use Claude Code, the command line interface, together with Opus 4.5 (Anthropic's top model as of this writing). I use it to distill my rough task requirements into a detailed development plan, then implement the plan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, Claude Code asks each time if it may read and write files and run software. This is sensible default configuration, but does get annoying after a time. Worse, it interrupts me often enough that I can't do much in parallel while babysitting it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's also a &lt;code&gt;--dangerously-skip-permissions&lt;/code&gt; (a.k.a. “YOLO”) mode which will happily run anything without asking. This can be risky (although I know of some people that run it like that and still haven't destroyed their dev machines).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandboxing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The standard solution is to sandbox the agent – either on a remote machine (exe.dev, sprites.dev, daytona.io), or locally via Docker or other virtualization mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lightweight alternative on Linux is bubblewrap, which uses Linux kernel features like cgroups and user namespaces to limit (jail) a process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As it turns out, bubblewrap is a good solution for lightweight sandboxing of AI agents. Here's what I personally need from such a solution:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;mimic my regular Linux dev machine setup (I don't want to manage multiple dev environment)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;minimal/no access to information outside what's required for the current project&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;write access only to the current project&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;can directly operate on the files/folders of the project so I can easily inspect or modify the same files from my IDE or run the code myself&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;network access – both to connect to AI providers and search the internet, and to be able to start a server that I can connect to&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bubblewrap and Docker are not hardened security isolation mechanisms, but that's okay with me. I'm not really concerned about the following risks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;escape via zero-day Linux kernel bug&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;covert side channel communications&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;exfiltration of data from current project (including project-specific access keys)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;screwing up the codebase (the code is managed via &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;and backed up at GitHub or elsewhere)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last bit is tricky, but even full remote sandboxes can't protect against that. In theory, we could have transparent API proxies that would inject proper access keys without the AI agent ever being aware of it, but this is really non-trivial to set up right now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An alternative is to contain potential damage by creating project-specific API keys so at least the blast area is minimal if those keys are leaked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;In practice&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's how my bubblewrap sandbox script looks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#!/usr/bin/bash

exec 3&amp;lt;$HOME/.claude.json

exec /usr/bin/bwrap \
    --tmpfs /tmp \
    --dev /dev \
    --proc /proc \
    --hostname bubblewrap --unshare-uts \
    --ro-bind /bin /bin \
    --ro-bind /lib /lib \
    --ro-bind /lib32 /lib32 \
    --ro-bind /lib64 /lib64 \
    --ro-bind /usr/bin /usr/bin \
    --ro-bind /usr/lib /usr/lib \
    --ro-bind /usr/local/bin /usr/local/bin \
    --ro-bind /usr/local/lib /usr/local/lib \
    --ro-bind /opt/node/node-v22.11.0-linux-x64/ /opt/node/node-v22.11.0-linux-x64/ \
    --ro-bind /etc/alternatives /etc/alternatives \
    --ro-bind /etc/resolv.conf /etc/resolv.conf \
    --ro-bind /etc/profile.d /etc/profile.d \
    --ro-bind /etc/bash_completion.d /etc/bash_completion.d \
    --ro-bind /etc/ssl/certs /etc/ssl/certs \
    --ro-bind /etc/ld.so.cache /etc/ld.so.cache \
    --ro-bind /etc/ld.so.conf /etc/ld.so.conf \
    --ro-bind /etc/ld.so.conf.d /etc/ld.so.conf.d \
    --ro-bind /etc/localtime /etc/localtime \
    --ro-bind /usr/share/terminfo /usr/share/terminfo \
    --ro-bind /usr/share/ca-certificates /usr/share/ca-certificates \
    --ro-bind /etc/nsswitch.conf /etc/nsswitch.conf \
    --ro-bind /etc/hosts /etc/hosts \
    --ro-bind /etc/ssl/openssl.cnf /etc/ssl/openssl.cnf \
    --ro-bind /usr/share/zoneinfo /usr/share/zoneinfo \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.bashrc $HOME/.bashrc \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.profile $HOME/.profile \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.gitconfig $HOME/.gitconfig \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.local $HOME/.local \
    --bind $HOME/.claude $HOME/.claude \
    --bind $HOME/.cache $HOME/.cache \
    --file 3 $HOME/.claude.json \
    --bind "$PWD" "$PWD" \
    claude --dangerously-skip-permissions $@
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If this looks rather idiosyncratic, it's because it is. Rather than using some generic rules, I experimented with &lt;code&gt;bwrap&lt;/code&gt; until I found minimal configuration that I need to set up for my system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some interesting stuff:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/tmp&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;/proc&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;/dev&lt;/code&gt;are automatically handled by&lt;code&gt;bwrap&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I bind-mount (ie. expose) files and directories under the same path as local machine, so there's no difference in file locations, project paths, etc&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I don't expose entire &lt;code&gt;/etc&lt;/code&gt;, just the bare minimum&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The content of &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.claude.json&lt;/code&gt;is injected into the sandbox so any changes there won't get saved to the real one&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The content of &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.claude/&lt;/code&gt;directory is mapped read-write, so Claude can save and modify files there (such as session data)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/opt/node/node-v22.11.0-linux-x64/&lt;/code&gt;is my custom&lt;code&gt;nodejs&lt;/code&gt;install location&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I change the hostname so it's easy to distinguish between the host and sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will probably be tweaking the script as needed, but this is a pretty good starting point for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to customize&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to adapt this to another AI agent or to your system, my suggestion is to tweak the script to run &lt;code&gt;bash&lt;/code&gt; instead, then run your agent manually, see what breaks and tweak as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A useful command for this is &lt;code&gt;strace&lt;/code&gt;, which can trace file access system calls so you can see what's needed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;strace -e trace=open,openat,stat,statx,access -o /tmp/strace.log codex
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inspecting the log you can spot which files are needed and bind them as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.senko.net/sandboxing-ai-agents-in-linux"/><published>2026-02-03T17:35:37+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874619</id><title>Xcode 26.3 unlocks the power of agentic coding</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:24.698294+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd64c349434690ed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; UPDATE February 3, 2026 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Xcode 26.3 unlocks the power of agentic coding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Developers can leverage coding agents, including Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex, directly in Xcode to tackle complex tasks autonomously, helping them develop apps faster than ever &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Xcode 26.3 introduces support for agentic coding, a new way in Xcode for developers to build apps using coding agents such as Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex. With agentic coding, Xcode can work with greater autonomy toward a developer’s goals — from breaking down tasks to making decisions based on the project architecture and using built-in tools. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expanding on the intelligence features introduced in Xcode 26, which brought a brand-new coding assistant for writing and editing in Swift, this release gives coding agents access to even more of Xcode’s capabilities. Agents like Claude Agent and Codex can now collaborate throughout the entire development life cycle, giving developers the power to streamline workflows, iterate faster, and bring ideas to life like never before. Agents can search documentation, explore file structures, update project settings, and verify their work visually by capturing Xcode Previews and iterating through builds and fixes. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At Apple, our goal is to make tools that put industry-leading technologies directly in developers’ hands so they can build the very best apps,” said Susan Prescott, Apple’s vice president of Worldwide Developer Relations. “Agentic coding supercharges productivity and creativity, streamlining the development workflow so developers can focus on innovation.” &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With seamless access to Claude Agent and Codex, developers can bring the advanced reasoning of these models directly into their app-building workflow.1 This connection combines the power of these agents with Xcode’s native capabilities to provide the best results when developing for Apple platforms, giving developers the flexibility to work with the model that best fits their project. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to these built-in integrations, Xcode 26.3 makes its capabilities available through the Model Context Protocol, an open standard that gives developers the flexibility to use any compatible agent or tool with Xcode. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Availability &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Xcode 26.3 is available as a release candidate for all members of the Apple Developer Program starting today, with a release coming soon on the App Store. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Share article&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Media&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Text of this article&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Images in this article&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anthropic and OpenAI’s terms of service may apply.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/"/><published>2026-02-03T18:04:08+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46875228</id><title>AliSQL: Alibaba's open-source MySQL with vector and DuckDB engines</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:24.112048+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f90b0c4553671e2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AliSQL is Alibaba's MySQL branch, forked from official MySQL and used extensively in Alibaba Group's production environment. It includes various performance optimizations, stability improvements, and features tailored for large-scale applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Quickly build your DuckDB node: How to set up a DuckDB node&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AliSQL Version: 8.0.44 (LTS)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Based on: MySQL 8.0.44&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;DuckDB Storage Engine:AliSQL integrates DuckDB as a native storage engine, allowing users to operate DuckDB with the same experience as MySQL. By leveraging AliSQL for rapid deployment of DuckDB service nodes, users can easily achieve lightweight analytical capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Vector Storage:AliSQL natively supports enterprise-grade vector processing for up to 16,383 dimensions. By integrating a highly optimized HNSW algorithm for high-performance Approximate Nearest Neighbor (ANN) search, AliSQL empowers users to build AI-driven applications—such as semantic search and recommendation systems—seamlessly using standard SQL interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;DDL Optimization (planned):AliSQL delivers a faster, safer, and lighter DDL experience through innovations such as enhanced Instant DDL, parallel B+tree construction, a non-blocking lock mechanism, and real-time DDL apply—significantly improving schema change efficiency and virtually eliminating replication lag.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;RTO Optimization (planned):AliSQL deeply optimizes the end-to-end crash recovery path to accelerate instance startup, shorten RTO, and restore service quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replication Optimization (planned): AliSQL significantly boosts replication throughput and minimizes lag by implementing Binlog Parallel Flush, Binlog in Redo, and specialized optimizations for large transactions and DDL operations.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prerequisites:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CMake 3.x or higher&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Python3&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;C++17 compliant compiler (GCC 7+ or Clang 5+)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build Instructions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Clone the repository
git clone https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL.git
cd AliSQL

# Build the project (release build)
sh build.sh -t release -d /path/to/install/dir

# For development/debugging (debug build)
sh build.sh -t debug -d /path/to/install/dir

# Install the built MySQL server
make install&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build Options:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-t release|debug&lt;/code&gt;: Build type (default: debug)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-d &amp;lt;dest_dir&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: Installation directory (default: /usr/local/alisql or $HOME/alisql)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s &amp;lt;server_suffix&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: Server suffix (default: alisql-dev)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-g asan|tsan&lt;/code&gt;: Enable sanitizer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-c&lt;/code&gt;: Enable GCC coverage (gcov)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-h, --help&lt;/code&gt;: Show help&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub Issues: https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/issues&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Alibaba Cloud RDS: DuckDB-based Analytical Instance&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For DuckDB-specific support, see the DuckDB Support Options.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AliSQL 8.0 became an open-source project in December 2025 and is actively maintained by engineers at Alibaba Group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contributions are welcome! Please:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fork the repository&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create a feature branch&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make your changes with appropriate tests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Submit a pull request&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For bug reports and feature requests, please use the GitHub Issues page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is licensed under the GPL-2.0 license. See the LICENSE file for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AliSQL is based on MySQL, which is licensed under GPL-2.0. The DuckDB integration follows the same licensing terms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL"/><published>2026-02-03T18:40:18+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46876047</id><title>China Moon Mission: Aiming for 2030 Lunar Landing</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:23.843778+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="77af907574e51d69"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Slow and steady wins the race, or so goes the fable. The China Manned Space Agency, or CMSA, has repeatedly denied any rivalry with the United States akin to the race to the moon in the 1960s. But step-by-step, one element at a time over a period of decades, it has built a human space program with goals that include landing astronauts on the moon by 2030 and starting a base there in the following years. And—partly because launch dates for NASA’s Artemis III moon landing keep slipping toward that same time frame—U.S. space leaders are ratcheting up the space race rhetoric.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We are in a great competition with a rival that has the will and means to challenge American exceptionalism across multiple domains, including in the high ground of space,” said Jared Isaacman, the new head of NASA, in December. “This is not the time for delay, but for action, because if we fall behind—if we make a mistake—we may never catch up, and the consequences could shift the balance of power here on Earth.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA’s Artemis II is almost ready to take its crew on a circumlunar test flight, and the White House has ordered that U.S. astronauts should prioritize a lunar landing by 2028—but could China slip in ahead? How would a Chinese moon flight work? Does the Chinese space program have technology that matches or beats the United States?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RELATED: Inside the Spacecraft That Will Carry Humans Around the Moon&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Nobody [in China] would argue that we are in a space race,” says Namrata Goswami, a professor at Johns Hopkins University who has written extensively about China’s space effort, “but they might be engaged in activity that showcases China as a space power, and they are very serious about getting somewhere first.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Are the Mengzhou and Lanyue Spacecraft?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;China’s lunar hardware builds on existing engineering. It is based on a multipurpose crew ship called Mengzhou, with capacity for six or seven astronauts, though as few as three may actually fly on a trip from Earth to low lunar orbit. (China watchers dispense with the word “taikonaut” for its crew members, by the way; the word was coined in 1998 and has not been used by the Chinese government itself. China generally uses the word yuhangyuan, roughly translated as “traveler of the universe.”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mengzhou, according to what the CMSA has shown, includes a crew section in the shape of a truncated cone or frustum, with a service module holding power and propulsion systems in the rear. If you squint at it, you’ll see a resemblance to the American Artemis or Apollo spacecraft, the SpaceX Crew Dragon, or the yet-to-be-flown European Nyx. Basic aerodynamics make a blunt cone a very efficient shape for safely launching a spacecraft and returning it through Earth’s atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Mengzhou command ship uses parachutes and airbags during a 2025 landing test in northwest China.Wang Heng/Xinhua/Getty Images&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mengzhou is billed as reusable, with an outer heat shield that can be replaced after flight. Landings would take place in China’s western desert. “Coupled with the landing method of airbag cushioning,” says the CMSA in a translated statement, “the spacecraft itself can be better protected from damage and allow the reuse of the spacecraft.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ship would be launched by a new heavy-lift Long March 10 booster, one of two used for a given moon mission. The Long March 10, as configured for lunar flight, would stand 92.5 meters high at launch and generate thrust of 2,678 tonnes. (The rocket for Artemis II is more powerful: 3,992 tonnes.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mengzhou would leave for the moon after another Long March 10 has launched a lunar landing craft called Lanyue. The two would rendezvous and dock in lunar orbit. Two astronauts would transfer to Lanyue and land on the moon’s surface; Mengzhou would wait for them in orbit for the trip home. Lanyue has a stated mass of 26 tonnes and could carry a 200-kilogram rover.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chinese authorities say testing of Lanyue began in 2024. Mengzhou should go on its first robotic flight in 2026; Lanyue, in 2027. The first joint test mission is planned for 2028 or 2029, with the first crew going to the moon a year after that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Is China’s Long-Term Plan for Space?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But to focus on their hardware is to miss out on a major difference between the Chinese and U.S. moon-landing efforts. Artemis is the product of a start-again stop-again debate that’s been going on in the U.S. government since Apollo ended in the 1970s. Goals have shifted repeatedly—often when new presidents took office. Conversely, the Chinese campaign is the outgrowth of a plan called Project 921, first backed by the Chinese Communist Party in 1992. There have been updates and some technical setbacks, but China has pretty much stuck to it ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What the Chinese space effort has done that others have not is integrate everything,” says Goswami. “It’s not just ‘We’re going to mount a mission.’ It’s bigger than that. They view space as an activity and not missions.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In other words, she says, each new piece of technology is part of a coordinated effort to create a sustained presence in space, which pays economic, geopolitical, and sometimes military dividends. Each part, so far, has fit together with other parts: The first orbiting capsule, called Shenzhou 1 in 1999, led to the first flight by an astronaut, Yang Lewei, on Shenzhou 5 in 2003. That led to space stations (the Tiangong series, starting in 2011), to which Shenzhou crews have been flying since in regular rotation (Shenzhou 22 launched in November). Mengzhou will eventually take over as the workhorse crew vehicle for Earth-orbiting flights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the meantime, there has been a steady cadence of robotic lunar orbiters and landers (Chang’e-6 returned the first-ever soil sample from the moon’s far side in 2024), soon to be followed, we’re now told, by Chinese astronauts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They started slowly, deliberately, with long breaks between missions, only recently picking up speed. At times they have unabashedly looked to other countries for guidance: The Shenzhou crew capsule in the 1990s borrowed heavily from the design of the Russian Soyuz. And several engineers today point out that the Mengzhou-Lanyue plan sounds in many ways like what then-administrator Michael Griffin proposed for NASA’s Constellation program back in 2005—a crewed ship launched by one rocket, a moon lander by another, with astronauts transferring to the lander once they reach lunar orbit. A crew capsule and lunar lander would be too much for one launch, as with the Apollo–Saturn V, because landings would be more ambitious than could be achieved with Apollo’s minimalist lunar module, with longer stays and equipment for a lunar base.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The Chinese are pursuing an architecture a lot like the Apollo architecture was. Which is understandable because their ambitions are to go fast, and Apollo worked,” says a former senior NASA manager who, like several others, asked not to be quoted by name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I have a lot of friends who have been watching the Chinese space program for the last couple of decades,” this person continued. “And the one hallmark that we can say is that when China announces dates for things, they typically maintain them.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;“Our Great Rival”&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that is why Jared Isaacman talks of urgency at NASA. He has so far generally avoided the word “China” in public. The Chinese, in his words, are usually “our great rival” or “a competitor.” Some NASA veterans say China may turn out to be giving the agency a helpful push to be faster and more agile. They say Apollo succeeded, in large part, because of the race to beat the Soviet Union. A Chinese challenge—even unstated, even illusory—may help Artemis move along.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We have a great competitor that is moving at absolutely impressive speeds,” Isaacman told NASA employees, “and it’s unsettling to consider the implications if we fail to maintain our technological, scientific, or economic edge in space. And the clock is running.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is part 2 of a three-part series, Back to the Moon. Part 1 is about the technology behind NASA’s Artemis II mission. Part 3 will look at how NASA reinvigorated its human spaceflight program.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The 5 Spacecraft Behind China’s Moon Rock Sample Mission ›&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;China's Moon Missions Shadow NASA Artemis's Pace - IEEE ... ›&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;China Aims for a Permanent Moon Base in the 2030s - IEEE Spectrum ›&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ned Potter is a New York writer who spent more than 25 years as an ABC News and CBS News correspondent covering science, technology, space, and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/china-moon-mission-mengzhou-artemis"/><published>2026-02-03T19:32:11+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46876347</id><title>When rust ≠ performance. a lesson in developer experience</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:23.701082+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="773d95da276f1c91"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;when rust ≠ performance. a lesson in devex.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;getting 20x speedup by removing code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;February 2, 2026 · 2 min read · tech, performance&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love working at oxen because we strive to be the fastest data versioning tool in the market. Which is why we often do multi terabyte benchmarks on each commands that we support , (add, commit, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All staged files, their location and the file hashes get stored in a rocksdb when &lt;code&gt;oxen add&lt;/code&gt; command is used, then during &lt;code&gt;oxen commit&lt;/code&gt; we create new nodes for new files/dirs and commit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was noting that our add times were pretty quick. ~1 minute for 1M files. But, commit was taking &amp;gt;50 minutes. This was interesting to me because commit is an O(n) algorithm with n = number of directories. we create n directory nodes and 1 commit node, that is all. even with a million files that is not that many directories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As is usual for all performance work. I profiled the &lt;code&gt;commit&lt;/code&gt; command with, samply
which is a wildly convenient tool to profile binaries and view it on a nice UI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you notice closely, &amp;gt;90% of the time was being spent just getting the lock on the staging RocksDB. This was because all our parallel workers are graduating the files from staged to committed by creating the respective nodes for the directories and creating a complete view of the repository at that commit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;but because we have this data (file name, etc.) passed back and forth between different layers in the code. we were doing lots of &lt;code&gt;.clone()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;db.open()&lt;/code&gt; at different layers to fetch the same data. The interesting part for me was that, this change reduced our&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final PR looked like this to improve performance by 20X&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With performance sensitive application. Often less is more and simple is better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I often think about this quote from Fabien .&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case, it was true. In good software engineering fashion, all our layers had clear separation of concerns. Which lead to repeated context retrieval for each thread / async operation leading to thread contention for the same resource. Personally this was a lesson for me on thinking about the Design and impact of the whole system even when adding a seemingly isolated feature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As an aside it is interesting that, rocksdb is not the ideal candidate for our “parallel reads” use case, because rocksdb is designed for parllel writes. which is why we see this unexpected overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://suriya.cc/tech/performance/oxen-add/"/><published>2026-02-03T19:55:44+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46876455</id><title>How Vibe Coding Is Killing Open Source</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:23.211412+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ae405269f297c5f0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does vibe coding risk destroying the Open Source ecosystem? According to a pre-print paper by a number of high-profile researchers, this might indeed be the case based on observed patterns and some modelling. Their warnings mostly center around the way that user interaction is pulled away from OSS projects, while also making starting a new OSS project significantly harder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Vibe coding” here is defined as software development that is assisted by an LLM-backed chatbot, where the developer asks the chatbot to effectively write the code for them. Arguably this turns the developer into more of a customer/client of the chatbot, with no requirement for the former to understand what the latter’s code does, just that what is generated does the thing that the chatbot was asked to create.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This also removes the typical more organic selection process of libraries and tooling, replacing it with whatever was most prevalent in the LLM’s training data. Even for popular projects visits to their website decrease as downloads and documentation are replaced by LLM chatbot interactions, reducing the possibility of promoting commercial plans, sponsorships, and community forums. Much of this is also reflected in the plummet in usage of community forums like Stack Overflow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we consider this effect of ‘AI-assisted’ software development to be effectively the delegating of the actual engineering and development to the statistical model of an LLM, then it’s easy to see the problems here. The LLM will not interact with the developers of a library or tool, nor submit usable bug reports, or be aware of any potential issues no matter how well-documented.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although the authors of this paper are still proponents of ‘AI technology’, their worries seem well-warranted, even if it’s unclear at this point how big the impact is going to be. Software ecosystems like those involving JavaScript, Python, and web technologies are likely to suffer the impact from vibe coding first, as their audiences appear to be more into such vibes, and the training sets were largest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s also a topic that is highly controversial, ever since Microsoft launched GitHub Copilot in 2021. Since then we saw reports in 2024 that ‘vibe coding’ using Copilot and similar chatbots offered no real benefits unless adding 41% more bugs is a measure of success.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the time we hit 2025, we can observe an even more negative mood, with LLM chatbots in general being accused of degrading the cognitive skills of those using them, vibe coding chatbots reducing productivity by 19%, and experienced developers who gave them a whirl subsequently burning them to the ground in scathing reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of which reinforces the notion that perhaps this ‘AI revolution’ is more of a stress test for human intelligence than an actual boost to productivity or code quality. Despite the authors pitching the idea that OpenAI or Google could toss a few cents the way of OSS projects when their code is being used, the comparison with Spotify is painfully apt, since about 80% of artists on Spotify rarely have their tracks played and thus receive basically no money for their efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With an LLM statistical model we know with extremely high likelihood that only the dependencies that are most prevalent in the training data set will realistically be used for the output, and we expect that we’ll see something similar happen with this vibe coding compensation scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even today we can already observe many negative effects from ‘AI slop’ in software development. Whether it’ll be something that’ll choke the life out of the entire OSS ecosystem remains to be seen, but it is hard to envision a bright vibe coding future.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://hackaday.com/2026/02/02/how-vibe-coding-is-killing-open-source/"/><published>2026-02-03T20:02:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46876720</id><title>Anthropic AI Tool Sparks Selloff from Software to Broader Market</title><updated>2026-02-03T20:59:23.038231+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2026-02-03/legal-software-stocks-plunge-as-anthropic-releases-new-ai-tool"/><published>2026-02-03T20:21:21+00:00</published></entry></feed>