<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:38.465762+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46805439</id><title>Questom (YC F25) is hiring an engineer</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:31:02.595464+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b5fe30170ec5bb2a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We’re looking for a Founding Engineer to help build the core systems that power Questom.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is not a framework-specialist role. It’s not about perfect abstractions on day one. It is about systems thinking, ownership, and the ability to stitch together complex infrastructure into something that works — fast.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You’ll be one of a very small group shaping not just the product, but how the company builds.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What You’ll Do&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Build systems that connect everything&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Design and build high-performance systems that connect: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Communication platforms (voice, SMS, email, chat)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Agentic workflows&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;External tools like CRMs and internal APIs&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Stitch together APIs, workflows, and agents into cohesive systems that actually run in production&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Think deeply about how these systems scale across many customers with different data sources and configurations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Build agentic workflows&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Create workflows where agents: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Handle live conversations&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Pull context from systems like Salesforce&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Log outcomes in tools like HubSpot&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Take real actions on behalf of users&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Focus on giving agents the right information at the right time and designing systems that make this repeatable across customers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Turn ambiguity into working software&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Start from half-baked ideas, rough customer conversations, or incomplete requirements&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Ship a 90% working solution quickly&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Iterate toward something more general, scalable, and high quality&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Own what you build&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Take end-to-end ownership: design → build → ship → improve&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Break things thoughtfully — and fix them yourself&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Make judgment calls without needing constant guidance&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Success Looks Like&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In the first 30 days&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Sit in a few customer conversations&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Identify a real pain point&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Propose a product or feature to solve it&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Build and ship an end-to-end solution that delivers real value&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In the first 90 days&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Take learnings from multiple customer builds&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Start shaping more general-purpose systems&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Help lay the foundation for a platform that can scale to many customers — and eventually very large companies&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How We Build&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;We use modern tools aggressively and expect you to learn quickly: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Agentic workflow frameworks&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Communication infrastructure&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;AI agent SDKs&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;We rely heavily on coding agents and automation — curiosity and systems understanding matter more than syntax mastery&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;We build fast, then make it better&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;We’re opinionated, iterative, and comfortable changing direction when a simpler solution delivers customer value&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Matters (and What Doesn’t)&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What matters a lot&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Systems thinking&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Ownership&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Comfort with ambiguity&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Curiosity and fast learning&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Product taste (what’s worth building vs not)&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Respect for how other people think&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What doesn’t matter much&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Deep expertise in any single framework or language&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Pixel-perfect UI work&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Writing perfect SQL by hand&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Knowing our exact stack on day one&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you understand how modern web systems, APIs, workflows, and agents fit together — and you’re excited to learn the rest — you’re in great shape.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How We Work&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Fast, opinionated, iterative&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Disagreements are encouraged and happen openly&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;We build first, think later — but we do think&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You won’t be micromanaged&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You will be trusted with real responsibility early&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Who You Are&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You likely describe yourself as:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Extremely curious&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Highly independent&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Comfortable operating without a map&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Someone who enjoys connecting dots across systems&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;High-EQ and collaborative&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You want to be deeply involved — not just shipping tickets, but helping build a company.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Who Should Not Apply&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;If you need clear specs and guardrails to do your best work&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;If you prefer working in isolation&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;If you’re uncomfortable with constant ambiguity&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;If you don’t enjoy discussing ideas, systems, and tradeoffs with a small team&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;If you want a narrow role instead of broad ownership&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If reading this makes you feel slightly intimidated but very excited, that’s intentional — and probably a good sign.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/questom/jobs/UBebsyO-founding-engineer"/><published>2026-01-29T03:29:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46805665</id><title>We can’t send mail farther than 500 miles (2002)</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:31:02.539070+00:00</updated><link href="https://web.mit.edu/jemorris/humor/500-miles"/><published>2026-01-29T03:58:33+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46806773</id><title>Europe’s next-generation weather satellite sends back first images</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:31:02.059217+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f28ce6731ff45f8c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Europe’s next-generation weather satellite sends back first images&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first images from the Meteosat Third Generation-Sounder satellite have been shared at the European Space Conference in Brussels, showing how the mission will provide data on temperature and humidity, for more accurate weather forecasting over Europe and northern Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The images from Meteosat Third Generation-Sounder (MTG-S) show a full-disc image of Earth as seen from geostationary orbit, about 36 000 km above Earth’s surface. These images were captured on 15 November 2025 by the satellite’s Infrared Sounder instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the ‘temperature’ image (below), the Infrared Sounder used a long-wave infrared channel, which measured Earth’s surface temperature as well as the temperature at the top of clouds. Dark red corresponds to high temperatures, mainly on the warmer land surfaces, while blue corresponds to lower temperatures, typically on the top of clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As would be expected, most of the warmest (dark red) areas in this image are on the continents of Africa and South America. In the top-centre of the image, the outline of the coast of western Africa is clearly visible in dark red, with the Cape Verde peninsula, home to Senegal’s capital Dakar, visible as among the warmest areas in this image. In the bottom-right of the image, the western coast of Namibia and South Africa are also visible in red beneath a swirl of cold cloud shown in blue, while the northeast coast of Brazil is visible in dark red on the left of the image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ‘humidity’ image (below) was captured using the Infrared Sounder’s medium-wave infrared channel, which measures humidity in Earth’s atmosphere. Blue colours correspond to regions in the atmosphere with higher humidity, while red colours correspond to lower humidity in the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The outlines of landmasses are not visible in this image. The areas of least atmospheric humidity, shown in dark red, are seen approximately over the Sahara Desert and the Middle East (top of image), while a large area of ‘dry’ atmosphere also covers part of the South Atlantic Ocean (centre of image). Numerous patches of high humidity are seen in dark blue over the eastern part of the African continent as well as in high and low latitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below we see a close-up from MTG-Sounder of the European continent and part of northern Africa. Like the first image above, here we see heat from land surfaces and temperatures at the top of clouds. The heat from the African continent is seen in red in the lower part of the image, while a dark blue weather front covers Spain and Portugal. The Italian peninsula is in the centre of the image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the animation (below) uses data from the MTG-Sounder satellite to track the eruption of Ethiopia's Hayli Gubbi volcano on 23 November 2025. The background imagery shows surface temperature changes while infrared channels highlight the developing ash plume. The satellite's timely observations enable tracking of the evolving ash plume over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Next-generation weather forecasting&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MTG is a world-class Earth observation mission developed by the European Space Agency (ESA) with European partners to address scientific and societal challenges. The mission provides game-changing data for forecasting weather and air quality over Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The satellite’s geostationary position above the equator means it maintains a fixed position relative to Earth, following the same area on the planet’s surface as we rotate. This enables it to provide coverage of Europe and part of northern Africa on a 15-minute repeat cycle. It supplies new data on temperature and humidity over Europe every 30 minutes, supplying meteorologists with a complete weather picture of the region and complementing data on cloud formation and lightning from the MTG-Imager (MTG-I) satellite.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ESA’s Director of Earth Observation Programmes, Simonetta Cheli, said, “Seeing the first Infrared Sounder images from the MTG-Sounder satellite really brings this mission and its potential to life. We expect data from this mission to change the way we forecast severe storms over Europe – and this is very exciting for communities and citizens, as well as for meteorologists and climatologists. As ever, the outstanding work done by our teams in collaboration with long-standing partners, including Eumetsat, the European Commission and dozens of European industry teams, means we now have the ability to predict extreme weather events in more accurate and timely ways than ever before.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;A hyperspectral view over Europe&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Infrared Sounder instrument on board MTG-S is the first European hyperspectral sounding instrument in geostationary orbit. It is designed to generate a completely new type of data product. It uses interferometric techniques, which analyse miniscule patterns in light waves, to capture data on temperature and humidity, as well as being able to measure wind and trace gases in the atmosphere. The data will eventually be used to generate three-dimensional maps of the atmosphere, helping to improve the accuracy of weather forecasting, especially for nowcasting rapidly evolving storms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s fantastic to see the first images from this groundbreaking mission,” said James Champion, ESA’s MTG Project Manager. “This satellite has been 15 years in development and will revolutionise weather forecasting and especially nowcasting. The ability to vertically profile the full Earth’s disk with a repeat cycle of only 30 minutes for Europe is an incredible accomplishment!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I’m excited that we can share these first images from the Infrared Sounder, which showcase just a small selection of the 1700 infrared channels continuously acquired by the instrument as it observes Earth,” said Pieter Van den Braembussche, MTG System and Payload Manager at ESA. “By combining all 1700 channels, we will soon be able to generate three dimensional maps of temperature, humidity and even trace gases in the atmosphere. This capability will offer a completely new perspective on Earth’s atmosphere, not previously available in Europe, and is expected to help forecasters predict severe storms earlier than is possible today.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;About MTG-Sounder&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The MTG mission currently has two satellites in orbit: MTG-I and MTG-S. The second Imager will be launched later in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MTG-S was launched on 1 July 2025. Thales Alenia Space is the prime contractor for the overall MTG mission, with OHB Systems responsible for the MTG-Sounder satellite. Mission control and data distribution are managed by Eumetsat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The MTG-S satellite also hosts the Copernicus Sentinel-4 mission, which consists of an ultraviolet, visible and near-infrared (UVN) imaging spectrometer. Sentinel-4 delivered its first images last year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.esa.int/Applications/Observing_the_Earth/Meteorological_missions/meteosat_third_generation/Europe_s_next-generation_weather_satellite_sends_back_first_images"/><published>2026-01-29T07:07:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46808251</id><title>Vitamin D and Omega-3 have a larger effect on depression than antidepressants</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:31:01.838168+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f5a99056fce511fe"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(content note: scientific discussion of depression &amp;amp; suicide)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; "Too Long; Didn't Read" Summary:&lt;lb/&gt; Exactly what the title says. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The "standardized effect size" of antidepressants on depression, vs placebo, is around 0.4. (On average; some people respond much better or much worse.) This is like going from a C to a C+.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In contrast: the effect size of 1500 mg/day of "≥60% EPA" Omega-3 supplements — which are cheaper &amp;amp; have fewer side effects than antidepressants — is a bit higher, around 0.6. This is like going from a C to a B–.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But, much better: the effect size of 5000 IU/day of Vitamin D is around 1.8. This is like going from a C to an A–! It works even for people who don't have a Vitamin D insufficiency, which almost half of American adults do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if you're already taking Vitamin D &amp;amp; Omega-3, you may still not be taking enough. The "official" recommendations are all several times too low, and newer research shows that the official "max safe dose" for Vitamin D is 2 times too low. Both these supplements are safe, cheap, and over-the-counter, with positive side-effects (on Covid &amp;amp; cognition).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, unless you have specific reasons to not take Vitamin D &amp;amp; Omega-3 — (kidney stones, blood thinners, etc) — please try them, for at least a month! They could save your mental health. Maybe even your life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(edit — oh hi Hacker News! also, thank you Josep for catching my terrible typo; I meant 5000 IU/day for Vitamin D, NOT 5000 mg. Jeez.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(edit 2 — I said this in the conclusion but I'll move it earlier up: you can take these supplements alongside traditional antidepressants! You can stack interventions! The research shows that they're still effective even when combined with regular meds. As always, "ask your doctor", show them the peer-reviewed papers cited in this post.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Table of Contents:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A crash course in "effect sizes" ↪&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Interpreting effect sizes on depression ↪&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Antidepressants ↪&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Omega-3 ↪&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vitamin D ↪&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Conclusion: All this time, you lacked the Vitamin? ↪&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A crash course in "effect sizes"&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Alicetown, the average person has 4 younger cousins.&lt;lb/&gt; In Bobtown, the average person has 3 younger cousins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alright, not so surprising. You may not even notice a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Alicetown, the average person has 4 limbs.&lt;lb/&gt; In Bobtown, the average person has 3 limbs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You'd definitely notice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's the same absolute difference (4 vs 3) and relative difference (3/4). So what makes limbs more surprising than cousins? Well, partly it's more dramatic &amp;amp; visible, but also because: we expect high variation in the number of someone's younger cousins, but not their number of limbs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is why scientists calculate an "effect size" or "standardized mean difference" ("mean" = average). We take the difference between two groups, then divide by the total amount of variation, to account for how surprising a difference is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(This is a health article, not a math article, so I'll skip the formulas in this post. If you're curious, : check out this 4 min video.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for laypeople, the effect size is usually just reported as a number, like "+0.74" for spacing out your studying vs cramming, or "–0.776" for sleep deprivation on attention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what's that mean? How can we make these numbers intuitive?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, a common way for data to be is a bell-shaped curve (also called a "normal distribution"). And most of us are, alas, well-acquainted with the bell curve in school grades. ("grading on a curve")&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So: school grades give us a useful way to think about standardized effect sizes! We can now convert that number into an actual letter grade:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;F: -2.0 below average&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;D: -1.0 below average&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;C: average&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;B: +1.0 above average&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A: +2.0 above average&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(see footnote for more precise ranges.[1] the units are in "standard deviations", or "sigmas". what's sigma? &lt;del&gt;sigma ba--&lt;/del&gt; just a unit of "how far away this is from average, relative to the total variation".)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example: spacing out your studying, relative to cramming, will on average lift your test scores from a C to a B–. (effect size = +0.74) And short-term sleep deprivation, relative to healthy sleep, will on average tank your ability to pay attention from a C to a D+. (effect size: –0.776)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Note — when reading about effect sizes, always remember: effect of what, on what, at what dose, for which group, relative to what? See the Data Colada post, Meaningless Means.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Note 2 — the standard way of "intuitively" describing effect sizes is Cohen's recommendations: 0.2 = small, 0.5 = medium, 0.8 = large. Personally, I prefer the "school grade letter" comparison, since it's more concrete. But hey, you do you.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it's not limited to just grades &amp;amp; academic performance. Effect sizes can also help us understand any kind of difference between groups, in observation or in experiments!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Depression!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's use our school grade analogy, to interpret effect sizes on mental health:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's an "F in mental health"? By definition of a bell curve, ~2.3% of people are below –2 sigma (an "F"). (See: this bell curve calculator.) In Canada, ~2.6% of people had suicidal ideation in 2022, while in the US, it was ~4.9% in 2019. So, it's not too far off to say: "F in mental health = literally suicidal". (Also, reminder that ~4% is 1-in-25 people. You likely know someone, or are someone, who will feel suicidal this year. Please reach out to your friends &amp;amp; loved ones!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's a "D in mental health"? ~16% of people are below –1 sigma (a "D") on a bell curve. The Keyes 2002 study estimated that ~14.1% of adults meet the DSM-III criteria for a major depressive episode. So, D = Depressed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's an average "C in mental health"? ~68% of people are within a sigma of average (a "C") on a bell curve. Same above study found that 56.6 percent had moderate mental health. They were neither "languishing" nor "flourishing". I guess C = Could Be Worse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's a "B in mental health"? ~16% of people are above +1 sigma (a "B") on a bell curve. Same above study found that 17.2% of adults are "flourishing". Good for them! B = Flourishing, life is good.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's an "A in mental health"? I don't know who these freaks are. I actually could not find any scientific studies on "the +2 sigma in well-being". In contrast, there's lots of research on suicidal ideation, the –2 sigma in well-being. In the absence of any actual data, I'll just say: A = AWESOME&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, if an intervention is found to have an effect size of +1.0, that's like going up a letter grade. If something's found to have an effect size of -2.0, that's like going down two letter grades. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, so how do we get peoples' "mental health grades" up?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's look at antidepressants, Omega-3, and Vitamin D, in turn:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Antidepressants&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The good news is they work. The bad news is they don't work as well as you'd think they may work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cipriani et al 2018 is a recent meta-analysis (a study collecting lots of previous studies) that investigated 21 different antidepressants. The most effective antidepressant, Amitriptyline, relative to placebo, had an Odds Ratio of 2.13 — which converts to a Cohen's d effect size of 0.417 — which is "small-medium" according to Cohen's recommendations. Or, by our school-letter-grade comparison: the best antidepressant would take your mental health grade from an F to F+, or C to C+.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From Figure 3 of that paper, you can see that Amitriptyline has the highest estimated effect size, while the side effects are no worse than placebo:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sure, "F to F+" can be lifesaving, but… y'know… that's not a lot. And again, this is the effect on average. Some people respond much better to antidepressants… while some respond much worse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Omega-3&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep getting confused on which fat is what? Me too. So, here's a crash course on various fats:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fatty acids are chains of carbons &amp;amp; hydrogens + two oxygens. They say "OOH" at one end, and "HHH" at the other end:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A saturated fatty acid is one where all the carbons' free spots are filled up with hydrogens. (Hence, "saturated") This makes the molecule stick straight out. This is why long saturated fatty acids — like those found in butter — tend to be solid at room temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Contrary to popular belief, saturated fats don't literally clog your arteries, like grease in plumbing pipes. What happens is {ha ha I don't actually understand this}. Something about your cholesterol levels &amp;amp; inflammation.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In contrast, unsaturated fatty acids have at least one hydrogen missing. This causes them to have a double-bond "kink" in the molecule. This makes them not stick out, which is why unsaturated fats tend to be liquid at room temperature. Mono-unsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs) — like in olive oil — only have one kink. Poly-unsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) — like in fatty fish — have two or more kinks. Let's be mature adults about this, please.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For completeness: trans fats are unsaturated fats whose "kink" is twisted around, causing them to go straight. That is the worst sentence I've written all month. The twisted kink is caused by the hydrogens being on opposite sides, hence "trans". (And yes, if they're on the same side it's "cis". Latin was a mistake.) The molecule being straight is why trans fats — which margarine used to be full of — are solid at room temperature, despite being an unsaturated fat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's neat whenever you can trace the history of something right down to its atoms! Margarine was first invented because it's cheaper, and is spreadable straight from the fridge, unlike butter. Margarine (used to be) made by taking unsaturated vegetable oils, which were cheaper than animal fats, then pumping a bunch of hydrogens into it (hence, "hydrogenated oils"). If you completely hydrogenate an oil, it becomes a saturated fat. But they only partially hydrogenated those oils, leading to trans fats, which were cheaper &amp;amp; a spreadable semi-solid at fridge temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the 1970s &amp;amp; 80s, the US Food &amp;amp; Drug Administration concluded that trans fats were not harmful to humans, and nutritionists promoted margarine over butter, because butter had "unhealthy" saturated fats. But in the early 1990s, scientists realized that trans fats were even worse for you than saturated fats. Only in the 2010's, did most Western countries start officially banning trans fats. Reminder: policy is often decades behind science.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Hey, what do you call it when you get thiccer on HRT? Trans fat! :D)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I need to stop going on infodump tangents. Anyway, Omega-3 is any fatty acid with its first kink at the 3rd carbon from the Omega end ("HHH"), though it can have more kinks later down the chain. (And yes, Omega-6 has its first kink at the 6th carbon, and Omega-9 has its first kink at the 9th carbon. There's nothing physically preventing Omega-4 or Omega-5's from existing, but due to some quirk of evolution, Omega-3, -6, and -9 are the ones biological life uses most. As far as I can tell, there's no specific reason they're all multiples of 3. Probably just a coincidence. There is a less common Omega-7.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, there's three main types of Omega-3: EPA (Eicosapentaenoic Acid), DHA (Docosahexaenoic Acid), and ALA (Alpha-Linolenic Acid). ALA is mostly found in plants like chia seeds &amp;amp; walnuts, while EPA &amp;amp; DHA mostly come from seafood, though there are algae-based vegan sources.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Figure 1.1 from Roke 2016.⤵ Thank you Kaitlin Samantha Roke for drawing this coz I'm too lazy to draw it myself. Note how the first double-bond "kink" for all these molecules is at the 3rd carbon from the Omega end — hence why they're all called Omega-3's.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EPA &amp;amp; DHA are the focus of this section. For bio-mechanical reasons I don't understand but I assume someone else does: EPA is the one associated with anti-inflammation, better brain health, and less depression... while DHA isn't. (But DHA is still needed for other stuff, like your neurons' cell walls, so don't cut them out completely!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Note: I could not find any experimental trials of ALA on depression, though an observational study in Japan (Kurotani et al 2014) finds a correlation between higher ALA and lower depression. But reminder, correlation is not necessarily causation.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the above info in a Venn (technically Euler) diagram:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, enough yap. Time for the actual data:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sublette et al 2011 is an older meta-analysis, but it's the only one I could find that tries to estimate the actual "dose-response" curve, which shows: how much effect, for how much treatment. Why is that important? Because one problem with many meta-analyses is they'll do something like: "Study 1 gave patients 1 gram of medicine and saw a +1 improvement in disease, Study 2 gave 10 grams and saw +4 improvement, Study 3 gave 100 grams and saw negative –5 improvement… the average of +1, +4, and –5 is zero... therefore the medicine's effect is zero." ...As mentioned briefly earlier, this is a meaningless mean. That's why we want to know the response at each dose.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, the Sublette meta-analysis gathered randomized trials studying Omega-3 on depression (vs placebo, of course) and got the following dose-response curve.⤵ Note that the horizontal axis is not just amount of total Omega-3, but specifically the extra amount of "unopposed" EPA, above the amount of DHA. Or in other words, "EPA minus DHA":&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The top effect size is around +0.558, which is like going from an F to D–, or C to B–. You get this maximum effect around 1 to 2 grams of extra EPA, and too much EPA gets worse results. The meta-analysis finds that Omega-3 supplements that are ~60% EPA (and the rest DHA) are optimal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This finding is roughly in line with later meta-analyses. Liao et al 2019 also finds that ~1 gram of ≥60% EPA is best, but actually found a much higher effect size: +1.03. Kelaiditis et al 2023 also finds 1 to 2g of ≥60% EPA is best, but found a lower effect size of +0.43… which is still as good as the best antidepressant!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Either way, let's boil this down to a recommendation. You want around 1 gram of EPA a day. So if your supplements are 60% EPA, you need 1 gram ÷ 0.6 ~= 1.667 grams = 1667 milligrams. Let's round this down for convenience: get 1500 mg/day of 60%-EPA Omega-3 supplements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In comparison, most official health organizations recommend "250–500 mg combined EPA and DHA each day for healthy adults." That is over three times too low, at least for optimal effects on depression. Which, as we calculated above, is probably around 1500 mg/day. (The official safe dose is 5000 mg/day)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, a (small) study directly investigating the link between suicide &amp;amp; Omega-3. Sublette et al 2006: “Low [DHA] and low Omega-3 proportions [...] predicted risk of suicidal behavior among depressed patients over the 2-year period.” Though keep in mind this is a small study, and it's observational not experimental. Also, weird that contrary to the above studies on depression, DHA predicted suicide but not EPA. Not sure what to make of that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bonus: Omega-3 may also boost cognition? Shahinfar et al 2025: “Enhancement of global cognitive abilities was observed with increasing omega-3 dosage up to 1500 mg/day. [effect size = 1.00, like going from a grade of C to B!], followed by downward trend at higher doses.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Vitamin D&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ghaemi et al 2024 is a meta-analysis on Vitamin D on depression. Again, it actually estimates a dose-response curve! Below is Figure 1 + Table 2, showing the effect of Vitamin D dosage on depression vs placebo. The solid line is the average estimated effect, dashed lines are 95% confidence interval. Note the effect size is negative in this figure, because they're measuring reduction in depressive symptoms:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The upper range of uncertainty is lowest at 5000 IU (International Units) of Vitamin D a day, with an estimated effect size of 1.82, with a 95% uncertainty range, from 0.98 to 2.66. An effect size of 1.82 is like taking your mental health from an F to a C–, or a C to an A–! And even in the most pessimistic case, 0.98, that's still over twice as effective as the top antidepressant!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(The paper's summary says 8000 IU is best, with effect size 2.04, but there's much greater uncertainty there. The paper also finds that longer studies had smaller effects than shorter studies, but this does not necessarily mean Vitamin D's effects are short-lived. Looking at Supplementary Table 4, it seems this is partly because longer studies used lower average daily doses. For example, one 52-week study only gave participants 400 IU a day.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This meta-analysis includes trials with participants who don't have Vitamin D deficiency. There's still a good effect of Vitamin D on depression for them, even if smaller! Though, you probably are lacking Vitamin D: Liu et al 2018 finds that a bit under half of all adults (41.4%) have Vitamin D Insufficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that's according to the official recommendation, of 400-800 IU a day… which is is too damn low. Even the official maximum safe dose of Vitamin D, of 4000 IU/day, is too low. McCullough et al 2019 gave over thousands of patients 5,000 to 10,000 IU/day, for seven years, and there were zero cases of serious side effects. This is in line with Billington et al 2020, a 3-year-long double-blinded randomized controlled trial, where they found "the safety profile of vitamin D supplementation is similar for doses of 400, 4000, and 10,000 IU/day." (though "mild hypercalcemia" increased from 3% to 9%. IMHO, that's a small cost for reducing the risk of major depression &amp;amp; suicide.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it makes sense that 10,000 IU a day should be safe. Your skin, exposed to the Sun's ultraviolet rays, can synthesize up to (the equivalent of) 10,000 IU a day, before plateauing out. Source is Vieth 1999: “Because vitamin D is potentially toxic, intake of [1000 IU/day] has been avoided even though the weight of evidence shows that the currently accepted [limit] of [2000 IU/day] is too low by at least 5-fold.” (So why are all the official sources still so paranoid about Vitamin D? Well, unfortunately, official/governmental policy is always a few decades behind the science in any field. See Also: the trans fat debate, everything about educational policy.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of the Sun, why take supplements instead of just getting Vitamin D from Sun exposure? Well, skin cancer. But also: because Sun-Skin D varies greatly depending on the season, your latitude, and your skin type. There's less ultraviolet rays from the Sun in winter/fall, and at latitudes further from the equator. And the darker your skin is, the less Vitamin D your skin makes for the same amount of Sun exposure. As expected from the bio-physics of skin, Black adults have the highest prevalence of Vitamin D deficiency (82.1%!!), followed by Hispanic adults (62.9%). (But hey, at least Black adults have the lowest incidence of skin cancer. You win some you lose some.) The point is: speaking as someone with Southeast Asian skin, who's currently in Canada during winter... even if I stood outside naked for hours, I'd get approximately zero IU/day of Vitamin D from the Sun. Thus: supplements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, a meta-analysis directly measuring the effect of Vitamin D on suicide rates. Yu et al 2025: “Vitamin D in patients with [suicidal behaviours] were significantly lower than in controls (standardized mean difference: –0.69, or a 'medium' difference)”. Reminder that this paper by itself only measures correlation, not causation — but combined with the above experiments of Vitamin D on depression, I think it's reasonable to guess it's partly causal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To recap:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Almost half of you have a Vitamin D deficiency according to the official recommendation (800 IU/day).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;And the official recommendation is way too low. Even the official maximum safe dose (4000 IU/day) is below the optimal Vitamin D for depression (5000 IU/day) or what your body can produce from the Sun in optimal conditions (10,000 IU/day). Recent randomized controlled trials confirm that 10,000 IU/day is, indeed, mostly safe.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Your daily reminder than official policy is often decades behind the science.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bonus: Vitamin D supplementation was found in several randomized controlled trials to reduce mortality from Covid-19! It probably helps guard against influenza too, though the evidence is small &amp;amp; early.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion: All this time, you lacked the Vitamin?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scurvy is caused by a lack of Vitamin C. It's a condition that causes your wounds to re-open up &amp;amp; teeth to fall out. Scurvy used to kill almost half(!) of all sailors on major expeditions; it's estimated millions died. It can be cured by eating lemons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rickets is mostly caused by a lack of Vitamin D. It's a condition where kids' bones go all soft and deformed. During the Industrial Revolution, up to 80% of kids suffered from it. It can be prevented with cod liver oil.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Goiters is mostly caused by a lack of Iodine. It's a condition where the thyroid gland in your neck swells up painfully, to the size of an apple. During WWI, a third of adult men had goiters. It can be prevented with iodized salt.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About 1 in 4 people are expected to have clinical depression sometime in their life. Depression is the #1 source of the global "burden from disease" in the mental health category, and that category is the #6 burden of disease in the world, above Alzheimer's, malaria, and sexually transmitted infections.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(But honestly, did you need those stats? This is likely a lived experience for a lot of you reading this.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The effective altruists are all, "woah for just $3000 you can prevent a child's death from malaria" — and that's great! save them kids! — but where's the fanfare for the accumulating evidence that, "woah with cheap daily supplements we can save millions from suicide &amp;amp; depressed lives"?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over and over again throughout history, some horrific thing that caused millions to suffer, turned out to be "yeah you were missing this one molecule lol". To be clear: not everything is gonna be that simple, and mental health is not "just" chemistry. Also, all the numbers on this page have with large error bars &amp;amp; uncertainty, more research is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But, as of right now, I feel I can at least confidently claim the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vitamin D and Omega-3 are both at least on par with antidepressants.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The evidence is much stronger for Vitamin D; it's very plausibly at least twice as good as antidepressants.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Both supplements are cheap and safe, so what's the harm of trying? (positive "expected value" for this bet)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MY SPECIFIC RECOMMENDATIONS FOR YOU TO DO A.S.A.P:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Go to a pharmacy, buy the following supplements over-the-counter, in whatever form you like: (I like the easy-to-swallow gel capsules)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vitamin D &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;🌱 By default, Vitamin D supplements are derived from… (quick web search)… the grease in sheep's wool? Huh. Also fish liver oil. Anyway, if you're vegan, make sure your bottle specifically says "vegan" or "from lichen/mushrooms". (If you're vegetarian, the sheep's-wool Vitamin D is fine, they don't kill the sheep for it.)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Omega-3 where EPA is ~60% of the Omega-3 total. For example, my 500mg Omega-3 capsules have 300mg EPA, 200mg DHA. &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;🌱 By default, Omega-3 supplements come from fish. If you're veg(etari)?an, there are plant-based sources of Omega-3, but look carefully: most vegan Omega-3 supplements provide more DHA than EPA, which the above studies suggest fully cancel out the antidepressant effect. Double check the nutritional label to make sure it's ≥60% EPA. For example, this one is 300mg EPA + 200mg DHA. (not an affiliate link)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, every day:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Take ~5000 IU of Vitamin D &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;⚠️ be cautious if you have kidney stones, or are on medications that could interact with Vitamin D. "ask your doctor".&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;4,000 IU is the "official maximum safe dose", if you understandably don't trust a random internet blogger, even though she cited peer-reviewed sources.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;10,000 IU if you're feeling daring / have darker skin / live in less sunny climates.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;bonus: may improve immune response to Covid &amp;amp; influenza?&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Take ~1500 mg of ≥60%-EPA Omega-3 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;⚠️ be cautious if you're on blood thinners, or other medications that could interact with Omega-3. again, "ask your doctor".&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;bonus: may improve cognition?&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;(Don't quit your existing antidepressants if they're net-positive for you!) &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;you may also want to ask your doctor about Amitriptyline, or those other best-effect-size antidepressants.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Can you get these doses of Vitamin D &amp;amp; Omega-3 through whole foods alone, no supplements? Probably, but it'd be expensive &amp;amp; tedious: you'd have to eat something like 2,000 calories of farmed salmon a day to get 5,000 IU/day of Vitamin D. As for Omega-3, eating mostly oily fishes would get you &amp;gt;1000mg of Omega-3, but they'd be more DHA than EPA, which the above studies suggest would cancel out the antidepressant effects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The effect sizes on depression:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The best antidepressant: +0.417 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;like your mental health grade going from F to F+, or C to C+&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1500mg of ≥60%-EPA Omega-3: +0.558 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;like your mental health grade going from F to D–, or C to B–&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;5000 IU of Vitamin D: +1.82 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;like your mental health grade going from F to C–, or C to A–&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For completeness &amp;amp; comparison, here's the effect size of other things on depression:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Any mainstream "bona-fide" psychotherapy (CBT, Psychodynamic, Humanist, Solutions-Focused): +0.35, source: Kamenov et al 2016 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;like going from C to C+&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Aerobic/Cardio Exercise: +0.79, source Ioannis et al 2018 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;like going from C to B–&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(dose: "45 minutes, at moderate intensity, three times/week" ⇒ ~20 min/day)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Good Sleep: +1.10(???), a lot of interpretation &amp;amp; calculations, see footnote[2] &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;like going from C to B&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(dose: going from moderate insomnia to healthy sleep)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bright Light Therapy: +0.487, source Menegaz de Almeida et al 2025 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(the above paper reports Odds Ratio of 2.42, which converts to Cohen's d effect size of +0.487)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;like going from C to C+&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;I went with Wirecutter's recommendation for a UV-free 10,000 lux lamp.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(dose: 10,000 lux, 30 min a day)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mindfulness Meditation: +0.42, source Breedvelt et al 2019 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;like going from C to C+&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(dose: 7 weeks, "153 min each week" ⇒ ~20 min/day)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(And remember, you can stack any of the above interventions to get an even larger effect! You can't just naively add up the effect sizes, but I'd be surprised if the effect of {vitamin d + omega-3 + bright lamps + cardio + good sleep + meditation} combined ends up being less than +2.00. Two letter grades up means going from D to B, or, theoretically, from clinically depressed to flourishing! For more papers &amp;amp; my working research notes on "best bang for buck on depression", check out this Google Doc.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, remember that all the above estimates are uncertain. And in general, when scientists replicate psychology experiments more rigorously, the effect size usually shrinks by ½. But, I think the overall qualitative picture is still strong: there exist high bang-for-buck ways to reduce depression, which are at least on par with drugs &amp;amp; therapy (possibly 2x to 4x better), that aren't (yet) common knowledge amongst policymakers &amp;amp; the public. And again, they're dirt cheap with minor-to-no adverse side effects. Moderate chance of a big win, for a known tiny cost. That's a positive "expected value" bet right there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I got onto this research rabbithole a few months ago while borrowing my housemate's ADHD meds, which I may or may not eventually collect into a "JOYMAXXING" informal meta-meta-analysis. (: See me yap about it on video as a cartoon cat.) But for this blog post, I wanted to dive deeper into Vitamin D and Omega-3, since their effect sizes are so huge, and they're insultingly cheap &amp;amp; easy, compared to therapy or regular cardio.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stay safe this winter, keep away the seasonal depression. Get your supplements, and reach out to your friends &amp;amp; loved ones!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;💖,&lt;lb/&gt; ~ Nicky Case&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I made up these ranges by requiring the standard letter grades F,D,C,B,A, to have their centers be -2,-1,0,+1,+2. Then, I made sure all in-between grades like C+ or A– had equal intervals. Each interval is +/- ⅙, or ⅓ wide:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;F---: -3.16 to -2.83&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;F--: -2.82 to -2.50&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;F–: -2.49 to -2.17&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;F: -2.16 to -1.83&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;F+: -1.82 to -1.50&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;D–: -1.49 to -1.17&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;D: -1.16 to -0.83&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;D+: -0.82 to -0.50&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;C–: -0.49 to -0.17&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;C: -0.16 to +0.17&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;C+: +0.18 to +0.50&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;B–: +0.51 to +0.83&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;B: +0.84 to +1.17&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;B+: +1.18 to +1.50&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;A–: +1.51 to +1.83&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;A: +1.84 to +2.17&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;A+: +2.18 to +2.50&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;A++: +2.51 to +2.83&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;A+++: +2.84 to +3.17&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Lee et al 2023 reports the following effect sizes. Digital therapy for Insomnia → Sleep = 0.76, and Digital therapy for Insomnia → Depression = 0.42. Assuming the therapy for insomnia specifically affects depression only through better sleep (Digital therapy for Insomnia → Sleep → Depression), we can do an "Instrumental Variable" estimate of the effect of Sleep → Depression = 0.42 / 0.76 = 0.55. To be precise: this is saying, if you improve your sleep by 1 standard deviation, on average your depression improves by 0.55 standard deviations.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;So: how many standard deviations is going from "moderate insomnia" to "healthy sleep"? The standard measure is the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI), which you can take online. A score of 0–7 means no insomnia, 8–14 is subclinical insomnia, 15–21 is clinical insomnia (moderate), 22–28 is clinical insomnia (severe). Let's be conservative and say we're just going from barely clinical to barely healthy: 15 to 7, or a reduction of 8 points. Yang et al 2009 says a 6-point reduction is 1.5 standard deviations, which means 4 points is 1 standard deviation. So a reduction of 8 points is 2 standard deviations. So, if you improve your sleep from insomniac to healthy, you improve by at least 8 points, which is 2 standard deviations, so your depression should improve by 2 × 0.55 standard deviations, or ~1.10.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Reminder that my estimate is full of assumptions upon assumptions &amp;amp; these error bars will compound. But I'd be surprised if the true causal effect of going from insomniac to healthy sleep isn't at least a "large" +0.8 effect. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.ncase.me/on-depression/"/><published>2026-01-29T10:35:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46809420</id><title>The Sovereign Tech Fund Invests in Scala</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:31:01.298201+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="47f2b49f06f2a0bf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Darja Jovanovic, Scala Center&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weâre truly excited to share that Scala has received an investment from the Sovereign Tech Fund to strengthen Scalaâs long-term security, maintenance, and developer experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The work is coordinated by the Scala Center and runs for two years, with a total investment of â¬377,300.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Sovereign Tech Fund is a program of the Sovereign Tech Agency that globally invests in open software components that build our core digital infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Sovereign Tech Agency and the Sovereign Tech Fund&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Sovereign Tech Agency is the first publicly funded organization in Europe that supports the development, improvement, and maintenance of open digital infrastructures. It is financed by the German Federal Ministry for Digital Transformation and Government Modernisation and is a subsidiary of SPRIND, the Federal Agency for Disruptive Innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Sovereign Tech Agencyâs mission is to strengthen the open source ecosystem sustainably, focusing on resilience, technological diversity, and the people behind the code as foundations for a future-ready economy and modern society.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Sovereign Tech Fund identifies and invests in open source software components that enable the creation of software, and supports key technologies with broad societal importance. Since October 2022, the Sovereign Tech Fund has invested a total of around â¬34 million in 95 critical technology projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Scala is critical digital infrastructure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scala is widely used to build and operate essential systems across multiple industries. These systems include data pipelines and distributed applications, and some are in highly regulated environments like finance and public services. In these contexts, reliability is paramount. The safety, sustainability, and evolution of the Scala language and its tooling directly impact systems that people and institutions rely on every day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is why, in 2016, the Scala Center was founded with a clear mission: to make the Scala open-source ecosystem stronger, more resilient, and sustainable over the long term. Thanks to the continued support of Scala Center industry partners (through the Advisory Board program), EPFL, and the worldwide Scala contributor community, the ecosystem continues to grow stronger every day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And today, with the Sovereign Tech Fundâs investment in Scala, this commitment is reinforced at a public-infrastructure level. We are very thankful that the Fundâs support recognizes Scala as critical digital infrastructure and enables sustained, focused work on the languageâs core foundations over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A closer look: what this investment will deliver&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;1) Security Audit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A dedicated security audit by Open Source Technology Improvement Fund (OSTIF) will uncover vulnerabilities and strengthen confidence in Scalaâs core components. This supports not only Scala users, but also the broader environments where Scala runs, for example as a component of complex software supply chains. We are super thankful to the OSTIF team and support!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2) Improvement of scoverage&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;scoverage is a key tool in the Scala ecosystem for measuring code coverage. Improving it increases the reliability of Scala codebases and helps teams detect gaps in testing earlier, especially as systems evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;3) Maintenance of the Standard Library / Core Library Modules and APIs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Long-term maintenance of core libraries and APIs is critical for stability. This includes keeping foundational modules healthy, reducing technical debt, and ensuring compatibility across versions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;4) Modernization and extension of the Standard Library / Core Library Modules and API Documentation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Scala continues to evolve, modernizing and extending core modules ensures the language remains productive and relevant, while also supporting gradual adoption and stable upgrade paths. The work also brings improvements to API documentation and Scala websites, to improve understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;5) Build tool major update: sbt 2.0&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build tools are the backbone of developer productivity. The major update to sbt 2.0 will make Scala projects easier to build, maintain, and understand. This will be impactful for new users and contributors, as well as for established projects. Among other improvements, sbt 2 adopts Scala 3 (in place of 2.12) as the language for build definitions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Scala Centerâs role&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Scala Center has been entrusted with coordinating the commissioned work, check out the team working on the projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are very thankful that this support recognizes Scalaâs importance in the broader digital landscape, and for investing in foundational work that strengthens the reliability of the systems and services built on Scala across the public sector and industries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Stay informed and get involved&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weâll share updates as work progresses, including milestones, delivered improvements, and opportunities to engage with the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scala is critical digital infrastructure, so keeping it healthy is a shared responsibility. If youâre using Scala in production, maintaining libraries, or contributing to tooling and documentation, your feedback and involvement help keep Scala strong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to occasional blog posts such as this one, weâll also post more detailed updates, progress reports, and calls for feedback on our Discourse-based contributors forum at contributors.scala-lang.org. Please follow the relevant threads to stay informed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.scala-lang.org/blog/2026/01/27/sta-invests-in-scala.html"/><published>2026-01-29T12:42:58+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46810027</id><title>A lot of population numbers are fake</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:47.346970+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e41c1f13fb30ae2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Claude Code Opus 4.5 Performance Tracker&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal of this tracker is to detect statistically significant degradations in Claude Code with Opus 4.5 performance on SWE tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;• Updated daily: Daily benchmarks on a curated subset of SWE-Bench-Pro&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;• Detect degradation: Statistical testing for degradation detection&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;• What you see is what you get: We benchmark in Claude Code CLI with the SOTA model (currently Opus 4.5) directly, no custom harnesses.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Summary&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Daily Trend&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pass rate over time&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dashed line at 58% baseline with ±14.0% significance threshold&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Weekly Trend&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aggregated 7-day pass rate&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dashed line at 58% baseline with ±5.6% significance threshold&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Change Overview&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Performance delta by period&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Methodology&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal of this tracker is to detect statistically significant degradations in Claude Code with Opus 4.5 performance on SWE tasks. We are an independent third party with no affiliation to frontier model providers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Context: In September 2025, Anthropic published a postmortem on Claude degradations. We want to offer a resource to detect such degradations in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We run a daily evaluation of Claude Code CLI on a curated, contamination-resistant subset of SWE-Bench-Pro. We always use the latest available Claude Code release and the SOTA model (currently Opus 4.5). Benchmarks run directly in Claude Code without custom harnesses, so results reflect what actual users can expect. This allows us to detect degradation related to both model changes and harness changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each daily evaluation runs on N=50 test instances, so daily variability is expected. Weekly and monthly results are aggregated for more reliable estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We model tests as Bernoulli random variables and compute 95% confidence intervals around daily, weekly, and monthly pass rates. Statistically significant differences in any of those time horizons are reported.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://davidoks.blog/p/a-lot-of-population-numbers-are-fake"/><published>2026-01-29T13:36:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46810282</id><title>Claude Code Daily Benchmarks for Degradation Tracking</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:47.246005+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e41c1f13fb30ae2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Claude Code Opus 4.5 Performance Tracker&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal of this tracker is to detect statistically significant degradations in Claude Code with Opus 4.5 performance on SWE tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;• Updated daily: Daily benchmarks on a curated subset of SWE-Bench-Pro&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;• Detect degradation: Statistical testing for degradation detection&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;• What you see is what you get: We benchmark in Claude Code CLI with the SOTA model (currently Opus 4.5) directly, no custom harnesses.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Summary&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Daily Trend&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pass rate over time&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dashed line at 58% baseline with ±14.0% significance threshold&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Weekly Trend&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aggregated 7-day pass rate&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dashed line at 58% baseline with ±5.6% significance threshold&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Change Overview&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Performance delta by period&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Methodology&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal of this tracker is to detect statistically significant degradations in Claude Code with Opus 4.5 performance on SWE tasks. We are an independent third party with no affiliation to frontier model providers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Context: In September 2025, Anthropic published a postmortem on Claude degradations. We want to offer a resource to detect such degradations in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We run a daily evaluation of Claude Code CLI on a curated, contamination-resistant subset of SWE-Bench-Pro. We always use the latest available Claude Code release and the SOTA model (currently Opus 4.5). Benchmarks run directly in Claude Code without custom harnesses, so results reflect what actual users can expect. This allows us to detect degradation related to both model changes and harness changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each daily evaluation runs on N=50 test instances, so daily variability is expected. Weekly and monthly results are aggregated for more reliable estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We model tests as Bernoulli random variables and compute 95% confidence intervals around daily, weekly, and monthly pass rates. Statistically significant differences in any of those time horizons are reported.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://marginlab.ai/trackers/claude-code/"/><published>2026-01-29T13:59:07+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46810337</id><title>Playing Board Games with Deep Convolutional Neural Network on 8bit Motorola 6809</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:43.850456+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="31777073c4324395"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;WEKO3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;アイテム&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt; Playing Board Games with a Deep Convolutional Neural Network on the Motorola 6809 8-Bit Microprocessor &lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;https://ipsj.ixsq.nii.ac.jp/records/229345&lt;/p&gt; https://ipsj.ixsq.nii.ac.jp/records/229345&lt;p&gt;9e1431e2-99f7-4d16-8f82-d7dcfa6a2045&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;名前 / ファイル&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;ライセンス&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;アクション&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt; IPSJ-GPWS2023012.pdf (275.3 kB) &lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;&lt;p&gt; Copyright (c) 2023 by the Information Processing Society of Japan &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;オープンアクセス&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Item type&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Symposium(1)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;公開日&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2023-11-10&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;タイトル&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;タイトル&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Playing Board Games with a Deep Convolutional Neural Network on the Motorola 6809 8-Bit Microprocessor&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;タイトル&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;言語&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;en&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;タイトル&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Playing Board Games with a Deep Convolutional Neural Network on the Motorola 6809 8-Bit Microprocessor&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;言語&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;言語&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;eng&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;キーワード&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;主題Scheme&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Other&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;主題&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;deep learning&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;キーワード&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;主題Scheme&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Other&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;主題&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;quantization&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;キーワード&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;主題Scheme&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Other&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;主題&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;neural networks&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;資源タイプ&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;資源タイプ識別子&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_5794&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;資源タイプ&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;conference paper&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;著者所属&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Kayufu&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;著者所属(英)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;en&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Kayufu&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;著者名&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Rémi, Coulom &lt;head&gt;× Rémi, Coulom&lt;/head&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;著者名(英)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Rémi, Coulom &lt;head&gt;× Rémi, Coulom&lt;/head&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;論文抄録&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;内容記述タイプ&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Other&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;内容記述&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;While training deep-learning neural networks often requires considerable amounts of computing power, inference is efficient, and can be run on small devices. Cell phones are a typical example, but they are still rather powerful. The research presented in this paper takes the challenge to the extreme by running a Go-playing convolutional neural network on the 6809 CPU, an 8-bit microprocessor launched by Motorola in 1978. The software was implemented on a Thomson MO5 microcomputer, and reached a playing strength on par with GNU Go.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;論文抄録(英)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;内容記述タイプ&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Other&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;内容記述&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;While training deep-learning neural networks often requires considerable amounts of computing power, inference is efficient, and can be run on small devices. Cell phones are a typical example, but they are still rather powerful. The research presented in this paper takes the challenge to the extreme by running a Go-playing convolutional neural network on the 6809 CPU, an 8-bit microprocessor launched by Motorola in 1978. The software was implemented on a Thomson MO5 microcomputer, and reached a playing strength on par with GNU Go.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;書誌情報&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; ゲームプログラミングワークショップ2023論文集 &lt;p&gt;巻 2023, p. 66-69, 発行日 2023-11-10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;出版者&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="9"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;言語&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;ja&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;出版者&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;情報処理学会&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://ipsj.ixsq.nii.ac.jp/records/229345"/><published>2026-01-29T14:03:12+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46810401</id><title>Waymo robotaxi hits a child near an elementary school in Santa Monica</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:43.092989+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="afaa845301a0f987"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Waymo robotaxi struck a child near an elementary school in Santa Monica on January 23, according to the company. Waymo told the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA) that the child — whose age and identity are not currently public — sustained minor injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The NHTSA has opened an investigation into the accident, and Waymo said in a blog post that it “will cooperate fully with them throughout the process.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Waymo said its robotaxi struck the child at 6 miles per hour, after braking “hard” from around 17 miles per hour. The young pedestrian “suddenly entered the roadway from behind a tall SUV, moving directly into our vehicle’s path,” the company said in its blog post. Waymo said its vehicle “immediately detected the individual as soon as they began to emerge from behind the stopped vehicle.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Following contact, the pedestrian stood up immediately, walked to the sidewalk, and we called 911. The vehicle remained stopped, moved to the side of the road, and stayed there until law enforcement cleared the vehicle to leave the scene,” Waymo wrote in the post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;News of the crash comes as Waymo faces dual investigations into its robotaxis illegally passing school buses. The NHTSA opened a probe into the problem in October shortly after the first report of the incident in Atlanta, Georgia, and the National Transportation Safety Board opened its own investigation last week after around 20 incidents were reported in Austin, Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to the NHTSA, the accident occurred “within two blocks” of the elementary school “during normal school drop off hours.” The safety regulator said “there were other children, a crossing guard, and several double-parked vehicles in the vicinity.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The NHTSA’s Office of Defects Investigation is investigating “whether the Waymo AV exercised appropriate caution given, among other things, its proximity to the elementary school during drop off hours, and the presence of young pedestrians and other potential vulnerable road users.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;TechCrunch Founder Summit 2026: Tickets Live&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;On June 23 in Boston, more than 1,100 founders come together at TechCrunch Founder Summit 2026 for a full day focused on growth, execution, and real-world scaling. Learn from founders and investors who have shaped the industry. Connect with peers navigating similar growth stages. Walk away with tactics you can apply immediately&lt;lb/&gt;Save up to $300 on your pass or save up to 30% with group tickets for teams of four or more.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;TechCrunch Founder Summit: Tickets Live&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;On June 23 in Boston, more than 1,100 founders come together at TechCrunch Founder Summit 2026 for a full day focused on growth, execution, and real-world scaling. Learn from founders and investors who have shaped the industry. Connect with peers navigating similar growth stages. Walk away with tactics you can apply immediately&lt;lb/&gt;Save up to $300 on your pass or save up to 30% with group tickets for teams of four or more.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Waymo said in its blog post that its “peer-reviewed model” shows a “fully attentive human driver in this same situation would have made contact with the pedestrian at approximately 14 mph.” The company did not release a specific analysis of this crash.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://techcrunch.com/2026/01/29/waymo-robotaxi-hits-a-child-near-an-elementary-school-in-santa-monica/"/><published>2026-01-29T14:08:56+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46810536</id><title>Break Me If You Can: Exploiting PKO and Relay Attacks in 3DES/AES NFC</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:42.813431+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ecf8d84918a1ebd8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Abstract&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This paper presents an in-depth analysis of vulnerabilities in MIFARE Ultralight C, MIFARE Ultralight AES, NTAG 223 DNA, NTAG 224 DNA, and widely circulated non-NXP Ultralight C compatible cards. We reveal multiple avenues to substantially weaken the security of each technology across a range of configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through relay-based man-in-the-middle techniques and partial key overwritesâoptionally combined with EEPROM tearing techniquesâan attacker can reduce the keyspace of two-key Triple DES (2TDEA) from 2112 to 228 or less in certain real-world deployments, making brute-force key recovery feasible with modest computational resources.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We further demonstrate how MIFARE Ultralight AES can be similarly affected when CMAC integrity checks are not enforced. The security of NTAG 223/224 DNA is undermined by the absence of integrity checks and the calculation of CMAC over Secure Unique NFC (SUN) messages, providing an unauthenticated ciphertext oracle that facilitates key recovery from a single tag.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Affected Products&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following NXP products and non-NXP compatible ICs are affected:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Impact Assessment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For genuine NXP Ultralight C: Using partial key overwrite across multiple tags sharing a static key, full 112-bit 2TDEA key recovery is achievable in days to weeks depending on available hardware and number of tags.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For non-NXP cards (ULCG, FJ8010, USCUID-UL): Flawed PRNGs and missing anti-tearing mechanisms enable complete key recovery from a single card in under 60 secondsâeven on a mobile phone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For NTAG 223/224 DNA: The SUNCMAC_KEY can be recovered from a single tag in under a minute via partial key overwrite combined with offline CMAC brute-force against collected SUN messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Key Contributions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Partial Key Overwrite Attack: Enables attackers with authenticated access to reduce key-recovery brute-force workload against 2TDEA and AES-128 keys given multiple source tags using the same key.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Theoretical Single-Tag Recovery: Method to recover the full 112-bit 2TDEA key from a single NXP Ultralight C tag in specific configurations, applicable even with diversified keys.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;NTAG 22x DNA Attack: Partial key overwrite and tearing techniques applied to AES-128 protected NTAG 22x DNA, enabling significantly faster offline CMAC brute-force for recovering the SUN message authentication key.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Non-NXP Card Analysis: First systematic analysis of widespread non-NXP Ultralight C compatible cards, demonstrating implementation flaws (predictable PRNGs, absent anti-tearing) allowing near-instantaneous key recovery.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Real-World Deployment Survey: Empirical data from hospitality and other deployments showing configuration lapses around key diversification, lock bytes, and integrity mechanisms.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Questions &amp;amp; Answers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This research demonstrates vulnerabilities in widely deployed NFC technologies used for access control, ticketing, and hospitality. We show that cryptographic keys protecting MIFARE Ultralight C, MIFARE Ultralight AES, and NTAG 223/224 DNA tags can be recovered through a combination of relay attacks, partial key overwrites, and EEPROM manipulation techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core issue is that these tags lack adequate post-authentication integrity protection, and many deployments fail to properly configure available security features like lock bytes and key diversification.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No. The underlying cryptographic algorithms (3DES and AES-128) remain secure. The vulnerabilities arise from:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Protocol design choices that allow unauthenticated memory writes after initial authentication&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lack of atomicity when writing cryptographic keys across multiple memory pages&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Widespread misconfiguration in real-world deployments (unlocked memory, static keys)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Non-NXP compatible chips with severely flawed random number generators&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes. We initiated contact with NXP Semiconductors in July 2025 and provided them with a complete draft of our findings. NXP confirmed the findings in August 2025 and requested additional time for product recertification. We coordinated the publication timeline with NXP, balancing their recertification needs with the importance of informing the security community and affected parties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The title comes directly from the default factory key programmed into every MIFARE Ultralight C chip by NXP. When you read the 16-byte 3DES key from a fresh Ultralight C tag, it spells out the ASCII string &lt;code&gt;BREAKMEIFYOUCAN!&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This appears to be a deliberately playful challenge left by NXP's engineers in 2008 for the security research community, and embedded directly in the Ultralight C's memory. We chose the paper's title to reflect this challenge, having demonstrated multiple practical attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, in any properly configured deployment, this default key should be replaced with a unique, securely generated key before deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The risk to individual hotel guests is generally low for opportunistic attacks. These attacks require specialized equipment and technical knowledge. However, our research did demonstrate a successful credential forgery attack against a real hospitality system using a discarded room key.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical advice:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don't leave your key card unattended for extended periods&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don't discard key cards in publicly accessible areas near the hotel&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Report lost cards immediately so they can be deactivated&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use in-room safes and additional door locks when available&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Likely yes, to some degree. Our survey found that 100% of MIFARE Ultralight C systems examined were affected by one or more issues. The severity depends on your configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;High risk: Static keys shared across all cards, unlocked key memory pages, non-NXP compatible cards in your supply chain&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Medium risk: Key diversification implemented but lock bytes not configured, CMAC not enabled on Ultralight AES&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lower risk: Proper key diversification, locked memory pages, verified genuine NXP chips, CMAC enabled (for Ultralight AES)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We strongly recommend auditing your deployment against the mitigations listed below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some transit systems use MIFARE Ultralight C for limited-use tickets. If your system uses static keys and doesn't lock key memory pages, it could be vulnerable to the multi-tag key recovery attack. However, transit systems often have backend validation that may limit the practical impact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Systems using MIFARE DESFire or other more advanced technologies are not affected by this specific research.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our sampling found that approximately 34% of cards from hospitality deployments were not genuine NXP products. Non-NXP compatible cards (like Giantec GT23SC4489 "ULCG", Feiju FJ8010, or USCUID-UL) have severely flawed random number generators that allow key recovery from a single card in under 60 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How to check:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;hf mfu info&lt;/code&gt;from the latest Proxmark3 firmware, which integrates fingerprinting for all counterfeit cards mentioned in the paper&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ULCG cards can be quickly identified by their UID suffix ending in &lt;code&gt;1589&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;See details in our paper and other fingerprinting tools available in our GitHub repository for deeper inspection&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Audit your supply chain and verify card sources&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIFARE DESFire: Not affected by this research. DESFire provides end-to-end encrypted sessions with integrity protection and is recommended as an upgrade path.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIFARE Classic and MIFARE Plus: Not in scope for this paper, but MIFARE Classic has its own well-documented vulnerabilities (Crypto1 weaknesses) which are mitigated in MIFARE Plus, provided it is properly configured.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ICODE DNA, UCODE DNA, NTAG 424 DNA: We examined these briefly. NTAG 424 DNA appears to require authentication before key modification, which mitigates the partial key overwrite attack. See the full paper for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. Audit your current deployment:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check if lock bytes are configured on key pages (Lock byte 3, bit 7 for Ultralight C)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Verify whether you're using static or diversified keys&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Test sample cards for non-NXP compatible chips&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For Ultralight AES: check if &lt;code&gt;SEC_MSG_ACT&lt;/code&gt;is enabled&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2. For new card issuance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Implement key diversification using UID and a site-specific salt&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Permanently lock key memory pages after personalization&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enable authentication attempt limits where available&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Verify genuine NXP chips before deployment&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3. For existing deployments with static keys:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If key pages can still be locked, do so immediately&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Plan migration to diversified keys or more secure technology&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Implement additional backend validation where possible&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Partially. If the key memory pages and configuration bytes are not yet locked, you can:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lock the key pages to prevent the partial key overwrite attack&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enable &lt;code&gt;AUTH_LIM&lt;/code&gt;on Ultralight AES to limit brute-force attempts&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However: If you're using static keys across your deployment, locking the pages only prevents new attacksâit doesn't change the fact that an attacker with enough cards could still recover the key through other means. Migration to diversified keys is the proper long-term solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For non-NXP compatible cards: These cannot be meaningfully secured and should be replaced with genuine NXP products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For applications requiring higher security assurance, we recommend migrating to MIFARE DESFire EV3 or similar advanced contactless smart card technologies. These provide:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;End-to-end encrypted communication sessions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mandatory integrity protection (not optional)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hardware-level countermeasures against tearing and manipulation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Secure key storage with proper atomicity guarantees&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While Ultralight AES is an improvement over Ultralight C, its security still depends heavily on proper configuration, whereas DESFire provides stronger security by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIFARE Ultralight C stores its 112-bit 2TDEA key across four 4-byte memory pages (pages 44-47). The tag's firmware doesn't enforce atomic writes across all four pagesâeach page can be written independently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After gaining authenticated access via a relay attack, an attacker can:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Overwrite three of the four key pages with known values (e.g., zeros)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Brute-force the remaining 28 bits (~228 possibilities)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Repeat on different tags, targeting different key quarters each time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Combine the four recovered segments to reconstruct the full key&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This reduces the attack complexity from 2112 to roughly 4 Ã 228, making it feasible with modest hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mutual authentication in Ultralight C does work correctlyâboth the reader and tag prove they know the shared secret. The problem is what happens after authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike MIFARE DESFire, Ultralight C has no post-authentication integrity protection. All commands after authentication are sent in plaintext without any MAC or encryption. An attacker who relays the authentication exchange can then inject their own commands to the now-authenticated tag.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Crucially, the tag has no timing constraintsâit will wait indefinitely for the reader's response during authentication, eliminating the tight timing windows that normally make relay attacks difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attacks can be performed with relatively inexpensive, commercially available hardware:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Relay attack: Two Flipper Zero devices communicating over 433 MHz, or Proxmark3 devices&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Online brute-force: Proxmark3 or Flipper Zero (~100 auth attempts/second)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Offline computation: Standard laptop (for non-NXP cards) or GPU cluster (for 2-tag variant on genuine cards)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tearing attacks: Proxmark3 with precise timing, or even Flipper Zero with busy-loop timing&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Total equipment cost is well under $500, and the techniques are within reach of moderately skilled attackers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All tools and scripts are available on GitHub at github.com/zc-public/breakme-resources. Relevant code has also been contributed to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Proxmark3 firmware repository&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Flipper Zero firmware (version 1.4.0+)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ChameleonUltra firmware&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The tools include key recovery scripts, fingerprinting utilities, and optimized brute-force implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Mitigations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enable CMAC integrity verification on all AES-protected communications (SEC_MSG_ACT for Ultralight AES)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Implement key diversification using card UID and a site-specific key or salt as input to a secure KDF&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lock critical memory pages including key pages, AUTH0, and configuration bytes to prevent modification&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enable authentication attempt counters (AUTH_LIM) where available and lock the configuration&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Verify supply chain integrity and replace non-NXP compatible cards with genuine NXP products where security is required&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Store CMAC over critical data including UID and hardware counters for technologies without secure messaging&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Consider migration to MIFARE DESFire EV3 or similar technologies with end-to-end encryption and hardware-level countermeasures&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Disclosure Timeline&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Resources&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full technical paper is available on ePrint. Proof-of-concept tools and supporting materials are published on GitHub, with relevant code contributed to the Proxmark3, Flipper Zero, and ChameleonUltra firmware repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.breakmeifyoucan.com/"/><published>2026-01-29T14:20:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46810828</id><title>Run Clawdbot/Moltbot on Cloudflare with Moltworker</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:42.604609+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd02981209b71cce"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Internet woke up this week to a flood of people buying Mac minis to run Moltbot (formerly Clawdbot), an open-source, self-hosted AI agent designed to act as a personal assistant. Moltbot runs in the background on a user's own hardware, has a sizable and growing list of integrations for chat applications, AI models, and other popular tools, and can be controlled remotely. Moltbot can help you with your finances, social media, organize your day â all through your favorite messaging app.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;But what if you donât want to buy new dedicated hardware? And what if you could still run your Moltbot efficiently and securely online? Meet Moltworker, a middleware Worker and adapted scripts that allows running Moltbot on Cloudflare's Sandbox SDK and our Developer Platform APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A personal assistant on Cloudflare â how does that work?Â &lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Firstly, Cloudflare Workers has never been so compatible with Node.js. Where in the past weÂ had to mock APIs to get some packages running, now those APIs are supported natively by the Workers Runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This has changed how we can build tools on Cloudflare Workers. When we first implemented Playwright, a popular framework for web testing and automation that runs on Browser Rendering, we had to rely on memfs. This was bad because not only is memfs a hack and an external dependency, but it also forced us to drift away from the official Playwright codebase. Thankfully, with more Node.js compatibility, we were able to start using node:fs natively, reducing complexity and maintainability, which makes upgrades to the latest versions of Playwright easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The list of Node.js APIs we support natively keeps growing. The blog post âA year of improving Node.js compatibility in Cloudflare Workersâ provides an overview of where we are and what weâre doing.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We measure this progress, too. We recently ran an experiment where we took the 1,000 most popular NPM packages, installed and let AI loose, to try to run them in Cloudflare Workers, Ralph Wiggum as a "software engineer" style, and the results were surprisingly good. Excluding the packages that are build tools, CLI tools or browser-only and donât apply, only 15 packages genuinely didnât work. That's 1.5%.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hereâs a graphic of our Node.js API support over time:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We put together a page with the results of our internal experiment on npm packages support here, so you can check for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Moltbot doesnât necessarily require a lot of Workers Node.js compatibility because most of the code runs in a container anyway, but we thought it would be important to highlight how far we got supporting so many packages using native APIs. This is because when starting a new AI agent application from scratch, we can actually run a lot of the logic in Workers, closer to the user.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The other important part of the story is that the list of products and APIs on our Developer Platform has grown to the point where anyone can build and run any kind of application â even the most complex and demanding ones â on Cloudflare. And once launched, every application running on our Developer Platform immediately benefits from our secure and scalable global network.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Those products and services gave us the ingredients we needed to get started. First, we now have Sandboxes, where you can run untrusted code securely in isolated environments, providing a place to run the service. Next, we now have Browser Rendering, where you can programmatically control and interact with headless browser instances. And finally, R2, where you can store objects persistently. With those building blocks available, we could begin work on adapting Moltbot.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How we adapted Moltbot to run on us&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Moltbot on Workers, or Moltworker, is a combination of an entrypoint Worker that acts as an API router and a proxy between our APIs and the isolated environment, both protected by Cloudflare Access. It also provides an administration UI and connects to the Sandbox container where the standard Moltbot Gateway runtime and its integrations are running, using R2 for persistent storage.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;High-level architecture diagram of Moltworker.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Let's dive in more.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare AI Gateway acts as a proxy between your AI applications and any popular AI provider, and gives our customers centralized visibility and control over the requests going through.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Recently we announced support for Bring Your Own Key (BYOK), where instead of passing your provider secrets in plain text with every request, we centrally manage the secrets for you and can use them with your gateway configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;An even better option where you donât have to manage AI providers' secrets at all end-to-end is to use Unified Billing. In this case you top up your account with credits and use AI Gateway with any of the supported providers directly, Cloudflare gets charged, and we will deduct credits from your account.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To make Moltbot use AI Gateway, first we create a new gateway instance, then we enable the Anthropic provider for it, then we either add our Claude key or purchase credits to use Unified Billing, and then all we need to do is set the ANTHROPIC_BASE_URL environment variable so Moltbot uses the AI Gateway endpoint. Thatâs it, no code changes necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Once Moltbot starts using AI Gateway, youâll have full visibility on costs and have access to logs and analytics that will help you understand how your AI agent is using the AI providers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note that Anthropic is one option; Moltbot supports other AI providers and so does AI Gateway. The advantage of using AI Gateway is that if a better model comes along from any provider, you donât have to swap keys in your AI Agent configuration and redeploy â you can simply switch the model in your gateway configuration. And more, you specify model or provider fallbacks to handle request failures and ensure reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Last year we anticipated the growing need for AI agents to run untrusted code securely in isolated environments, and we announced the Sandbox SDK. This SDK is built on top of Cloudflare Containers, but it provides a simple API for executing commands, managing files, running background processes, and exposing services â all from your Workers applications.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In short, instead of having to deal with the lower-level Container APIs, the Sandbox SDK gives you developer-friendly APIs for secure code execution and handles the complexity of container lifecycle, networking, file systems, and process management â letting you focus on building your application logic with just a few lines of TypeScript. Hereâs an example:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;import { getSandbox } from '@cloudflare/sandbox';
export { Sandbox } from '@cloudflare/sandbox';

export default {
  async fetch(request: Request, env: Env): Promise&amp;lt;Response&amp;gt; {
    const sandbox = getSandbox(env.Sandbox, 'user-123');

    // Create a project structure
    await sandbox.mkdir('/workspace/project/src', { recursive: true });

    // Check node version
    const version = await sandbox.exec('node -v');

    // Run some python code
    const ctx = await sandbox.createCodeContext({ language: 'python' });
    await sandbox.runCode('import math; radius = 5', { context: ctx });
    const result = await sandbox.runCode('math.pi * radius ** 2', { context: ctx });

    return Response.json({ version, result });
  }
};&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This fits like a glove for Moltbot. Instead of running Docker in your local Mac mini, we run Docker on Containers, use the Sandbox SDK to issue commands into the isolated environment and use callbacks to our entrypoint Worker, effectively establishing a two-way communication channel between the two systems.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;R2 for persistent storage&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The good thing about running things in your local computer or VPS is you get persistent storage for free. Containers, however, are inherently ephemeral, meaning data generated within them is lost upon deletion. Fear not, though â the Sandbox SDK provides the sandbox.mountBucket() that you can use to automatically, well, mount your R2 bucket as a filesystem partition when the container starts.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Once we have a local directory that is guaranteed to survive the container lifecycle, we can use that for Moltbot to store session memory files, conversations and other assets that are required to persist.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Browser Rendering for browser automation&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;AI agents rely heavily on browsing the sometimes not-so-structured web. Moltbot utilizes dedicated Chromium instances to perform actions, navigate the web, fill out forms, take snapshots, and handle tasks that require a web browser. Sure, we can run Chromium on Sandboxes too, but what if we could simplify and use an API instead?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;With Cloudflareâs Browser Rendering, you can programmatically control and interact with headless browser instances running at scale in our edge network. We support Puppeteer, Stagehand, Playwright and other popular packages so that developers can onboard with minimal code changes. We even support MCP for AI.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In order to get Browser Rendering to work with Moltbot we do two things:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;First we create a thin CDP proxy (CDP is the protocol that allows instrumenting Chromium-based browsers) from the Sandbox container to the Moltbot Worker, back to Browser Rendering using the Puppeteer APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Then we inject a Browser Rendering skill into the runtime when the Sandbox starts.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;From the Moltbot runtime perspective, it has a local CDP port it can connect to and perform browser tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Zero Trust Access for authentication policies&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Next up we want to protect our APIs and Admin UI from unauthorized access. Doing authentication from scratch is hard, and is typically the kind of wheel you donât want to reinvent or have to deal with. Zero Trust Access makes it incredibly easy to protect your application by defining specific policies and login methods for the endpoints.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Zero Trust Access Login methods configuration for the Moltworker application.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Once the endpoints are protected, Cloudflare will handle authentication for you and automatically include a JWT token with every request to your origin endpoints. You can then validate that JWT for extra protection, to ensure that the request came from Access and not a malicious third party.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Like with AI Gateway, once all your APIs are behind Access you get great observability on who the users are and what they are doing with your Moltbot instance.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Demo time. Weâve put up a Slack instance where we could play with our own instance of Moltbot on Workers. Here are some of the fun things weâve done with it.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We hate bad news.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hereâs a chat session where we ask Moltbot to find the shortest route between Cloudflare in London and Cloudflare in Lisbon using Google Maps and take a screenshot in a Slack channel. It goes through a sequence of steps using Browser Rendering to navigate Google Maps and does a pretty good job at it. Also look at Moltbotâs memory in action when we ask him the second time.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Weâre in the mood for some Asian food today, letâs get Moltbot to work for help.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We eat with our eyes too.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Letâs get more creative and ask Moltbot to create a video where it browses our developer documentation. As you can see, it downloads and runs ffmpeg to generate the video out of the frames it captured in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We open-sourced our implementation and made it available at https://github.com/cloudflare/moltworker, so you can deploy and run your own Moltbot on top of Workers today.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The README guides you through the necessary steps to set up everything. You will need a Cloudflare account and a minimum $5 USD Workers paid plan subscription to use Sandbox Containers, but all the other products are either free to use, like AI Gateway, or have generous free tiers you can use to get you started and run for as long as you want under reasonable limits.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note that Moltworker is a proof of concept, not a Cloudflare product. Our goal is to showcase some of the most exciting features of our Developer Platform that can be used to run AI agents and unsupervised code efficiently and securely, and get great observability while taking advantage of our global network.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Feel free to contribute to or fork our GitHub repository; we will keep an eye on it for a while for support. We are also considering contributing upstream to the official project with Cloudflare skills in parallel.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We hope you enjoyed this experiment, and we were able to convince you that Cloudflare is the perfect place to run your AI applications and agents. Weâve been working relentlessly trying to anticipate the future and release features like the Agents SDK that you can use to build your first agent in minutes, Sandboxes where you can run arbitrary code in an isolated environment without the complications of the lifecycle of a container, and AI Search, Cloudflareâs managed vector-based search service, to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare now offers a complete toolkit for AI development: inference, storage APIs, databases, durable execution for stateful workflows, and built-in AI capabilities. Together, these building blocks make it possible to build and run even the most demanding AI applications on our global edge network.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you're excited about AI and want to help us build the next generation of products and APIs, we're hiring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/moltworker-self-hosted-ai-agent/"/><published>2026-01-29T14:43:07+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46810904</id><title>How to Choose Colors for Your CLI Applications (2023)</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:42.320847+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="66a2137707fca2cf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Letâs say youâre creating a CLI tool which has to display syntax highlighted source code. You begin by choosing some colors which look nice with your chosen terminal theme:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nice! However, who knows if itâll still look good for people who use a theme different to yours? It seems sensible to try out the defaults, at least. Letâs start with the macOS Terminal.app default theme:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Youch! It seems fair to try the Tango themes next, since those are the default on e.g. Ubuntu:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hmm, better, but not by much. Finally, letâs try what is likely the most popular custom terminal theme – Solarized:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well then … Letâs take a look at each palette and investigate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sorcerer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Sorcerer, all colors are readable on the default background except for &lt;code&gt;black&lt;/code&gt;,
which is in fact darker than the background.
This is useful as the background color
for status bars and the like.
&lt;code&gt;white&lt;/code&gt; is the same color as
the default foreground,
and &lt;code&gt;brblack&lt;/code&gt; is a nice faded color.
Additionally, &lt;code&gt;brwhite&lt;/code&gt; is
even lighter than the foreground;
this allows for subtle emphasization
of important text
like error messages and titles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Basic&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Basic themes are, well, horrendous. Really owning that 90s xterm look, it seems. &lt;code&gt;bryellow&lt;/code&gt; is unreadable in light mode
(check out that function name
from the code sample earlier),
while in dark mode
both &lt;code&gt;blue&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;brblue&lt;/code&gt;
are totally illegible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That leaves us with thirteen colors we can safely use:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tango&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my opinion these did a lot better than Terminal.appâs Basic themes, but they are still far from perfect. &lt;code&gt;bryellow&lt;/code&gt; is again unreadable in the light theme,
and perhaps &lt;code&gt;brgreen&lt;/code&gt; is
a little difficult to see,
though itâs nothing that would
stop me from using &lt;code&gt;brgreen&lt;/code&gt;
in an application.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point you may have noticed how the greyscales – &lt;code&gt;black&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;brblack&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;white&lt;/code&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;code&gt;brwhite&lt;/code&gt; –
have remained consistent
between light and dark themes
for both Basic and Tango.
Of course,
this means that
&lt;code&gt;{,br}white&lt;/code&gt; is unreadable in Tango Light
(owing to the light background)
and &lt;code&gt;black&lt;/code&gt; is unreadable in Tango Dark
(owing to the dark background).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In other words: forget about that idea of mine from earlier about using &lt;code&gt;brwhite&lt;/code&gt; to emphasize content.
Unless, of course,
you donât mind if your
eminently emphasized words
are completely unreadable
for the user of your software
who deigns to use the default light theme
of A Popular Linux Distro.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, using &lt;code&gt;brblack&lt;/code&gt; to de-emphasize content
still seems fine to me.
I suppose some extra contrast
for &lt;code&gt;brblack&lt;/code&gt; in Tango Dark
would be nice,
but with text which is meant to be ignored
I donât think this matters much.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And lo, but ten colors remain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Solarized&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Solarized is a curious beast. Every color in it was chosen using L*a*b*, a perceptually-uniform color space from the 1970s. (For what itâs worth, color science has progressed significantly since then; the only reason Ethan Schoonover used L*a*b* is that itâs commonly used in photography, and he used to be a professional photographer.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Its lightnesses are perfectly symmetrical so that Solarized Light and Dark can share a set of accent colors while maintaining identical contrast. Moreover, the warm tones of the light theme and cool tones of the dark theme are complementary. (The hue gap is closer to 150Â° than 180Â° in reality. See here and here to compare hue values.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Solarized is also incredibly popular. I have no data here, but as of the date of writing itâs the most starred theme repository on GitHub I can find. Solarized has 15.4 thousand stars at the moment, while the next-closest is Gruvbox with 11.8 thousand. Solarized is available as a plugin or sometimes even as a built-in preset in damn near every popular terminal emulator and editor on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To understand Solarizedâs peculiar arrangement of the 16-color palette, we have to travel back in time to 2011 when Solarized was first released. In this dark era, terminals supporting 24-bit color didnât exist / werenât widespread. One option common among Vim themes at the time was to round every color to the nearest 256-color palette value. In Solarizedâs case, this destroys the mathematical symmetry at the heart of the theme. (Iâm not kidding, it looks awful.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The solution – rather, hack – chosen at the time was to distill all the colors used in the Vim interface down to a palette of sixteen colors. Conveniently, Solarizedâs accent colors fit nicely into the non-bright column of the 16-color palette, while Solarizedâs monotones fit into the bright column. Once the user sets their terminal to use the Solarized palette, Vim can color its entire interface using only the 16-color palette and get correct color values, no clunky color approximations needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The downside to all this is that an application which uses any of the bright colors which Solarized co-opted for itself will look strange. Users of Solarized – and, by god, thereâs so many of them – appear frequently on issue trackers asking why command-line output is inexplicably gray or even invisible as a result of CLIs using these forsaken bright colors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our beloved &lt;code&gt;brblack&lt;/code&gt;
is unreadable in Solarized Dark,
so weâll have to strike it from the table
in addition to the affected bright colors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A sad note about bold&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Far back in the past, there was no way for terminals to display bright colors. As a workaround, manufacturers (weâre talking about physical terminals here) started making all bold text bright instead of using a heavier font weight. One way or another this ended up in the default settings of many modern terminal emulators (in spite of not being in the standard), meaning that regular colorful text made bold can become bright too, depending on the userâs configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so, I present to you the final version of our table of acceptable colors:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bold: ââ boldblack ââ boldbrblack ââ boldred ââ boldbrred ââ boldgreen ââ boldbrgreen ââ boldyellow ââ boldbryellow ââ boldblue ââ boldbrblue ââ boldmagenta ââ boldbrmagenta ââ boldcyan ââ boldbrcyan ââ boldwhite ââ boldbrwhite % â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only eleven out of our thirty-two possible color settings are permissible, given that we want applications to remain readable for as many people as we can.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If youâre developing a command-line tool which will be used by anyone apart from yourself, I strongly recommend you limit your use of color to the ones Iâve identified here as being âmostly alrightâ and ânot unreadable in a common configuration used by tons of peopleâ.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Appendix&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You probably didnât notice, but I styled the âterminal windowsâ in this post to look as similar as possible to macOS Terminal.app windows through painstaking color picking and pixel counting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The dimensions in each windowâs titlebar matches as closely as I can with its actual dimensions on-screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;colortest&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;highlight&lt;/code&gt; utilities
are entirely fictional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Terminal.app doesnât actually provide individual access to the light and dark variants of Basic; they appear as a single theme, which switches seamlessly when the OS theme changes. As far as I know, this reactive functionality isnât exposed to any other theme, whether pre-installed or user-created. In order to capture this, I made the terminal windows in this post react to whether the rest of the site is in light or dark mode, except for the Basic windows. They remain fixed in either light or dark mode, since in real life youâll never see, for example, a light Basic terminal with dark window chrome.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Luna Razzaghipour&lt;lb/&gt;29 January 2023&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.xoria.org/terminal-colors/"/><published>2026-01-29T14:49:08+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46810950</id><title>Deep dive into Turso, the "SQLite rewrite in Rust"</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:41.580369+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="45c430185fd3b0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're sorry but this website doesn't work properly without JavaScript enabled. Please enable it to continue.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://kerkour.com/turso-sqlite"/><published>2026-01-29T14:51:56+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46811588</id><title>OTelBench: AI struggles with simple SRE tasks (Opus 4.5 scores only 29%)</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:41.358857+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f5885f907369ecf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Benchmarking OpenTelemetry: Can AI trace your failed login?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now on the front page of Hacker News — see the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Frontier AI models have become excellent at writing functions, but can they actually debug production systems?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To fix outages, you first need to see what’s happening. In a microservices world, this means producing structured events that track a single request as it hops from service to service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We asked 14 models to add distributed traces to existing codebases, using the standard method: OpenTelemetry instrumentation. We picked tasks that would be easy for a Site Reliability Engineer (SRE).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are releasing OTelBench as an open-source benchmark, with all tasks in QuesmaOrg/otel-bench. We use the Harbor framework (by the creators of TerminalBench), so you can easily run it yourself to reproduce results, test new models, or create benchmarks for your own use cases (we welcome contributions!).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Background: What is distributed tracing?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When an app runs on a single machine, you can often trace an error by scrolling through a log file. But when it runs across 50 microservices, that single request gets scattered into a chaotic firehose of disconnected events. Distributed tracing solves this by linking them back together, allowing you to follow a user action, like clicking Login, as it jumps from the API Gateway, to the Auth Service, to the Database, and back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make this work, you need instrumentation. This is code that you add to your app to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Start a trace when a request comes in.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pass the TraceID (context) when your app calls another service.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Send the data to a backend so you can see the graph.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenTelemetry (OTel) is the industry standard for telemetry data. Its ecosystem includes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Semantic conventions: A unified schema replaces chaotic naming (e.g., &lt;code&gt;ip_address&lt;/code&gt;vs&lt;code&gt;host.ip&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Universal SDKs: Official libraries support every major programming language.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Collector: A centralized agent processes and enriches data (e.g., adding Kubernetes tags) before export.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Auto-instrumentation: Runtime agents inject code to wrap calls, though this often results in noisy data.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, standard doesn’t mean easy. We know this firsthand from our contributions to the ecosystem, such as Go compile-time instrumentation. The process may be difficult, especially due to complexity, as 39% of respondents complained in the 2025 Observability Survey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Benchmarking OpenTelemetry instrumentation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We tested 14 frontier LLMs on 23 realistic OpenTelemetry instrumentation tasks across 11 programming languages: Go, Java, C++, Python, JavaScript, PHP, Ruby, Rust, Erlang, .NET, and Swift.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is essential to benchmark various technologies since realistic distributed systems are polyglot. To make OpenTelemetry work, the system needs to work for all of these services - if we lose track at only one service, the chain of logs gets broken.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final benchmark run cost $522 in LLM tokens across 966 runs (23 tasks × 3 attempts × 14 models).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Task&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We start with basic tasks such as adding instrumentation to a single microservice, in a single language. The AI agents get a small microservice with around 300 lines of code from a realistic application, and work in a Linux terminal, editing it, and running any commands if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, here is the prompt for go-microservices-traces:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Your task is: Add OTEL tracing to all microservices.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Requirements:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Instrumentation should match conventions and well-known good practices.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Instrumentation must match the business domain of the microservices.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Traces must be sent to the endpoint defined by a standard OTEL environment variable.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use the recent version of the OTEL SDK.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We tested if it satisfies the basic criteria of OpenTelemetry instrumentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Example&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How do LLMs fail? Let’s analyze a common failure mode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider a web service from our benchmark where a user searches and retrieves results. The test simulates two distinct user actions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Happy path: User searches, gets a token, retrieves results successfully&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Error test: User tries to retrieve results with an invalid token (gets 404)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A human engineer would immediately distinguish these as two independent events, resulting in two separate traces: one for the successful search and one for the failed request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code structure makes this clear – two separate blocks, each representing a user action:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// User Action 1: Search and get results (happy path)
{
    response := client.Post("/search", query)
    result := client.Get("/result?token=" + response.Token)
}

// User Action 2: Error test (invalid token)
{
    result := client.Get("/result?token=invalid")  // Should return 404
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We would expect:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet, sometimes models failed to recognize these as separate user actions. Instead of two traces, they produced:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core issue: Models apply instrumentation mechanically to every HTTP call without understanding the business context. They see “HTTP requests” and link them all together, rather than recognizing “these are two separate user journeys.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The models successfully instrumented the HTTP calls, but failed to propagate the Context correctly. They treated the timeline as a single flat list of events rather than two distinct hierarchical trees.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our tests don’t just check compilation. We verify correct span names, parent-child relationships, valid trace IDs, and context propagation. Many models produced compiling code that generated malformed traces – proving that “it builds” is not enough for SRE work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Observations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Models&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We were surprised that even the top models (as of Jan 2026) struggle. The tasks we proposed were trivial compared to real-world scenarios. In a typical SRE job, services are massive, legacy-ridden, and poorly documented. If models fail on 300 lines of clean Go code, they cannot handle production.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We were surprised that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Claude Opus 4.5, the best model, got just 29% of these relatively simple tasks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gemini 3 Pro (which aces at general intelligence) didn’t have an edge over the much cheaper Gemini 3 Flash.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GPT 5.2 Codex was substantially worse than GPT 5.2.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Languages&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each language has a different toolset, so it is not an apples-to-apples comparison. Our benchmark is too small to perform a comprehensive per-language comparison, yet even preliminary trends are striking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Cost and time efficiency&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In every practical application, cost and speed matter. As of Jan 2026, the Pareto frontier consists of only four models, given model performance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;19%&lt;/code&gt;Gemini 3 Flash (cost and speed) - the cheapest and fastest model in this benchmark (11x cheaper and 2x faster than Claude Opus 4.5)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;22%&lt;/code&gt;Claude Sonnet 4.5 (speed)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;26%&lt;/code&gt;GPT 5.2 (cost)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;29%&lt;/code&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 (cost and speed) — the best model in this benchmark, the most expensive but reasonably fast&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why OpenTelemetry instrumentation is hard for AI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenTelemetry has all the potential to be a perfect task for AI agents — it is long and tedious work, requiring a lot of scrutiny, but ultimately one that has clear specifications and can be easily tested.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet, even the frontier models fail miserably.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;It is a job, not a puzzle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instrumentation of even a small service involves long-horizon tasks, which remain at the frontier of the current AI model progress. It requires diligently connecting all pieces of code and testing them correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Requires polyglot backend development skills&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Realistic services use multiple languages and technologies. It is not enough to know the concept of distributed tracing, the OpenTelemetry standard, or even the APIs of SDKs. The agent must know CMake for C++, module systems for Go, or dependency management for Java - things we tested in our previous benchmark, CompileBench.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Usually, cloud environments are mixtures of the newest versions of technologies (sometimes past the training cut-off dates of AI models) and legacy systems. We cannot cherry-pick or rewrite everything, since a possible outage would be too costly. We need to support all languages and frameworks used in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lot of current AI progress focuses on the most popular languages (Python and TypeScript) and reasonably modern frameworks and build systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Less training data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although adding instrumentation is a standard engineering task, it is not common practice in open-source. The most popular applications, where reliability matters the most, are in private repositories of big tech companies such as Apple, Airbnb, or Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Key takeaways&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Best models struggle: The state-of-the-art Claude Opus 4.5 solved only 29% of tasks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Language gaps: Models failed completely on Java, Ruby, and Swift. C++ led at 37% (boosted by an easier task), Go reached 20%.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Silent failures: Many solutions compiled correctly but produced malformed traces or conflated distinct user journeys.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cost efficiency: Gemini 3 Flash exceeds Gemini 3 Pro’s performance (18%) at a fraction of the cost.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;AI SRE is still mostly hype, but there is hope&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI SRE in 2026 is what DevOps Anomaly Detection was in 2015 — bold claims backed by huge marketing budgets, but lacking independent verification. There are stories of SaaS vendors abruptly killing the observability stack. Our results mirror ClickHouse’s findings: while LLMs can assist, they lack the capabilities of a skilled SRE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Opus 4.5, GPT-5.2, and Gemini 3 models show promising signals. Some hard tasks like go-microservices-traces reached 55% pass rate. With more environments for Reinforcement Learning with Verified Rewards, this looks like a solvable problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Looking forward&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reliable software is incredibly economically valuable, but today it requires too much toil. No one wants to be woken up at 2 AM to troubleshoot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need a North Star to navigate the current AI boom. Just as SWE-Bench and TerminalBench2.0 became standards for software engineering, we need an SRE-style benchmark for distributed systems. Does the industry need newer models, or perhaps multi-agent systems? A good benchmark will tell us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We invite you to explore the full results on OTelBench and help us expand the test suite on QuesmaOrg/otel-bench. Have you tried using LLMs for observability? We are curious to hear if your experience matches our findings—or if you’ve found a workflow that actually works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Join the discussion on Hacker News, Reddit or LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But for now, the verdict is clear: if you need distributed tracing across services, expect to write that code yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for future posts and releases&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://quesma.com/blog/introducing-otel-bench/"/><published>2026-01-29T15:37:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46811762</id><title>Heating homes with the largest particle accelerator</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:40.065458+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e1e269be6278f5b1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; What if the world’s largest particle accelerator could also heat homes? CERN’s Large Hadron Collider (LHC) is doing just that, thanks to a new heat exchange system. Since mid-January, heat recovered from the LHC has been supplying a heating network for a new residential and commercial area in the nearby French town of Ferney-Voltaire. This network, inaugurated on 12 December, is expected to supply the equivalent of several thousand homes. By avoiding traditional energy sources, such as gas, the network prevents the emission of thousands of tonnes of CO2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 27-km LHC has eight surface points and Point 8 is located close to Ferney-Voltaire. The installations at Point 8, particularly the cryogenics, need to be cooled with water. As water circulates through the equipment, the equipment cools and the water heats up. “Typically, hot water would then pass through a cooling tower, releasing heat into the atmosphere so that the cooled water could be reinjected into the equipment,” explains CERN’s energy coordinator, Nicolas Bellegarde. “In the new set-up, hot water initially passes through two 5-MW heat exchangers, which transfer thermal energy to the new heating network in Ferney-Voltaire.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As one of the new network’s heat sources, CERN provides heat whenever possible, as long as it does not impact its activities. At present, Ferney-Voltaire is only using up to 5 MW from CERN but, with two heat exchangers in the system, this could theoretically be doubled, especially when CERN’s accelerators are fully operational. In summer 2026, CERN will stop the LHC for several years of maintenance and upgrades, known as Long Shutdown 3 (LS3), to prepare for the upcoming High-Luminosity LHC. Some Point 8 installations will continue to be cooled, enabling CERN to supply between 1 and 5 MW to the network during LS3, with the exception of a total of five months spread over this multi-year period.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Driven by a commitment to environmentally responsible research, CERN has implemented many initiatives to help reduce the impact of its activities on the environment. Energy recovery is a key part of CERN’s energy management strategy, in line with ISO 50001 requirements, alongside keeping energy consumption to a minimum and improving energy efficiency. Other projects include CERN’s Prévessin Data Centre, inaugurated in 2024, which is equipped with a heat-recovery system set to warm most site buildings from winter 2026/2027, and the future recovery of heat from LHC Point 1 cooling towers to supply buildings on CERN’s Meyrin site. Together, these initiatives will save 25–30 GWh per year as of 2027, marking significant progress in CERN’s responsible energy management.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://home.cern/news/news/cern/heating-homes-worlds-largest-particle-accelerator"/><published>2026-01-29T15:49:04+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46812173</id><title>US cybersecurity chief leaked sensitive government files to ChatGPT: Report</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:39.907237+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2937ce14048341f7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The acting head of the US government’s top cybersecurity agency reportedly uploaded sensitive government files into a public version of ChatGPT, triggering internal security alerts and a federal review.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Politico investigation claims Madhu Gottumukkala, the interim director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency, uploaded contracting documents marked “For Official Use Only” into ChatGPT last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The report says Gottumukkala requested a special exemption to access ChatGPT, which is blocked for other Department of Homeland Security staff.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cybersecurity monitoring systems then reportedly flagged the uploads in early August. That triggered a DHS-led damage assessment to determine whether the information had been exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Public versions of ChatGPT share user inputs with OpenAI, which raised concerns inside the federal government about sensitive data leaving internal networks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;CISA responds to ChatGPT investigation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CISA spokesperson Marci McCarthy told Politico that Gottumukkala “was granted permission to use ChatGPT with DHS controls in place,” adding that the use was “short-term and limited.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gottumukkala has served as acting director since May, while the Senate has yet to confirm Sean Plankey as permanent head of the agency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ChatGPT incident follows other reported issues during Gottumukkala’s tenure. Politico said he previously failed a counterintelligence polygraph required for access to highly sensitive intelligence. During congressional testimony last week, he rejected that characterization when questioned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The report lands as the administration of US President Donald Trump continues to push AI adoption across federal agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trump signed an executive order in December aimed at limiting state-level AI regulation, while the Pentagon has announced an “AI-first” strategy to expand the military’s use of artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.dexerto.com/entertainment/us-cybersecurity-chief-leaked-sensitive-government-files-to-chatgpt-report-3311462/"/><published>2026-01-29T16:12:19+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46812608</id><title>Launch HN: AgentMail (YC S25) – An API that gives agents their own email inboxes</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:39.721572+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3fd71f1327c4d429"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hey HN, we're Haakam, Michael, and Adi. We're building AgentMail (&lt;/p&gt;https://agentmail.to&lt;p&gt;), the email inbox API for agents. We’re not talking about AI for your email, this is email for your AI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Email is an optimal interface for long-running agents. It’s multithreaded and asynchronous with full support for rich text and files. It’s a universal protocol with identity and authentication built in. Moreover, a lot of workflow critical context already lives in email.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We wanted to build email agents that you can forward your work to and get back a completed task. The agents could act entirely autonomously as you wouldn't need to delegate your identity. If they did get stuck they could just send you, or anyone else, an email.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using Gmail, we kept getting stuck on the limitations of their API. No way to create inboxes programmatically. Rate and sending limits. OAuth for every single inbox. Keyword search that doesn't understand context. Per-seat pricing that doesn't work for agents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So we built what we wished existed: an email provider for developers. APIs for creating inboxes and configuring domains. Email parsing and threading. Text extraction from attachments. Realtime webhooks and websockets. Semantic search across inboxes. Usage-based pricing that works for agents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Developers, startups, and enterprises are already deploying email agents with AgentMail. Agents that convert conversations and documents into structured data. Agents that source quotes, negotiate prices, and get the best deals. Agents that emulate internet users for training models on end-to-end tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's demo of Clawdbots communicating using AgentMail: https://youtu.be/Y0MfUWS3LKQ&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can get started with AgentMail for free at https://agentmail.to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to hearing your thoughts and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46812608"/><published>2026-01-29T16:42:33+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46812653</id><title>Mozilla is building an AI 'rebel alliance' to take on OpenAI, Anthropic</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:39.545782+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3916017572f525e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From his small, snow-covered farm outside Toronto, home to cats and a dog, and soon some donkeys, Mark Surman has been laying the groundwork for a fierce battle with the world's leading artificial intelligence companies, located about 2,300 miles away in the San Francisco area.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bespectacled 56-year-old is president of Mozilla, a nonprofit organization best known for its Firefox browser and a pledge to keep the internet open and accessible to all. Having taken on Microsoft in the browser market in the early 2000s, and Apple and Google in the years that followed, Mozilla is right at home playing the role of underdog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These days, Surman is preoccupied with the tech industry's influence over the next big thing: AI. And it's too big of a challenge for Mozilla to tackle on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Surman is building what he's described as "a rebel alliance of sorts," using a phrase that's long been part of Mozilla's lexicon. In this case, the alliance is a loose network of tech startups, developers and public interest technologists committed to making AI more open and trustworthy and to checking the power of industry heavyweights like OpenAI and Anthropic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's that spirit that a bunch of people are banding together to create something good in the world and take on this thing that threatens us," Surman told CNBC in an interview. "It's super corny, but people totally get it."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In practice, Mozilla is focused on deploying its roughly $1.4 billion worth of reserves to support "mission driven" tech businesses and nonprofits, including its own, according to a report the organization released Tuesday. It's pursuing investments that promote AI transparency, and can potentially act as a counterforce to companies that are growing at historic rates with limited guardrails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Financially, Mozilla is at a massive disadvantage. In 2022, it launched a venture capital fund called Mozilla Ventures and pledged to invest an initial $35 million in early-stage companies. It's now exploring raising additional funds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla's cash pile is dwarfed by OpenAI, which has raised more than $60 billion from investors across the globe, and its rival Anthropic, which has raised more than $30 billion, according to PitchBook. Tech megacaps like Google and Meta are also sparing no expense, shelling out billions of dollars to hire AI researchers and tens of billions a year to build out massive data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla represents a growing swath of the AI industry that's afraid of what OpenAI has become and the power that it now wields.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When OpenAI was founded as a nonprofit AI lab in 2015, its stated goal was to "advance digital intelligence in the way that is most likely to benefit humanity as a whole, unconstrained by a need to generate financial return."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But in the decade that followed, OpenAI turned into a commercial entity with astronomical growth rates, transformed largely by the launch of ChatGPT in late 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenAI now sports a $500 billion valuation, and completed a recapitalization in October that cemented its future as a for-profit business under the umbrella of a nonprofit. It's a structure that resembles Mozilla, but the similarities end there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only a few of OpenAI's co-founders, including CEO Sam Altman, remain at the company, and a number of early employees who left have been sharply critical of what they broadly describe as a focus on growth at the expense of safety.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the loudest critics is co-founder Elon Musk, who departed in 2018, started a competitor called xAI in 2023, and then sued OpenAI and Altman for alleged breach of contract and financial damages. OpenAI has dismissed Musk's efforts as part of a "campaign of harassment," and the case is expected to head to trial in April.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenAI didn't provide a comment, and xAI returned CNBC's request for comment with an automated response.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anthropic was founded in 2021 by a group of former OpenAI executives and researchers who disagreed with the company's direction. But, even as it's taken a more pro-safety stance in AI development, Anthropic has been racing alongside AI commercially, commanding a $350 billion valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Multiple battles at once&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla's uphill battle is even steeper because of the position of the Trump administration, which is determined to stay ahead of China in the global AI race and has been quick to lash out at companies, states and lawmakers that are perceived as potential threats to that agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;David Sacks, the venture capitalist serving as the administration's AI and crypto czar, accused Anthropic of supporting "woke AI" in October due to its approach on regulation. President Donald Trump in December signed an executive order for a single regulatory framework for AI, establishing a litigation task force to challenge state AI laws, namely those led by Democratic lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An Anthropic spokesperson declined to comment, but directed CNBC to a blog post from CEO Dario Amodei in October. Amodei wrote in the post that Anthropic had increased its revenue run rate from $1 billion to $7 billion in nine months, "and we've managed to do this while deploying AI thoughtfully and responsibly."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Surman remains undeterred, and says Mozilla will be able to help "do for AI what we did for the web."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"There is an alternative that's real and is emerging, and it's a lot of small pieces that add up to that alternative," Surman said. "The people in it are hungry to look where there's weak spots in the current market and take advantage of them."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla has long viewed itself as a rebel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the 2024 "State of Mozilla" report, Surman used the phrase "rebel alliance" to describe the coalition of players that helped disrupt Microsoft's dominance over the web. In 2020, Mozilla published a report titled "Mozilla &amp;amp; the Rebel Alliance," which was dedicated to the organization's alliance of "tens of thousands of people around the globe who believe in Mozilla."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even so, Surman said it took some time to convince his colleagues that the moniker applied to the AI era.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That process actually started long before generative AI took off. In 2019, Surman shifted the philanthropic and advocacy efforts of the Mozilla Foundation to focus on "trustworthy AI."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the spring of 2023, Mozilla had launched its venture firm and its own AI company, Mozilla.ai. The following year, Surman said Mozilla's leadership agreed that keeping AI "trustworthy and open" was a fight worth picking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While its biggest priority remains growing and investing in Firefox, investing in the rebel alliance is "at the heart of who Mozilla is today," according to the report on Tuesday. Supporting startups is central to that strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla Ventures has invested in more than 55 companies to date, including dozens of AI startups, with more deals to come in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trail, a German startup that offers an AI governance solution for regulated enterprises, raised a pre-seed round in 2024, with participation from Mozilla.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anna Spitznagel, who co-founded the company the prior year, said Trail and Mozilla are exploring ways to collaborate more closely, like by building an open-source framework. Mozilla has supported open-source technology since its origin in 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Spitznagel isn't completely sold on Surman's rebel alliance concept. She said it's a "fun analogy" and wants to be aligned with the movement to enable trustworthy AI, but also wants in on the broader AI transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Rebel is a word that for me, personally, it has the wrong association," Spitznagel said in an interview. "I do think about [AI] a bit differently, but I also want to be part of the revolution that actually enables us to deploy AI and not hinder it."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tony Salomone and Ali Asaria, co-founders of Mozilla portfolio company Transformer Lab, said they're similarly on the fence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I'm not going to lie, I sometimes talk that way to get people kind of excited or engaged in our way of thinking," Salomone said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Founded in 2024, Transformer Lab is building open-source tools that developers can use to build, train and evaluate advanced AI models. The company has yet to publicly disclose any funding and, as of November, had fewer than 10 employees, mostly based in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Asaria said rebel alliance isn't a term he's used, but that there is an ecosystem of smaller AI companies that keep in touch and regularly cross paths at conferences and other events.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"There's definitely a group of folks who are interested in this idea of trying to be sustainable companies that can have an impact on the industry and have an appreciation for AI, but don't want to see just a few big companies win," Asaria said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;'Taking a lot of shortcuts'&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When it comes to the big companies in AI, Surman cautioned that a "winner-takes-all" mentality still lurks behind their open-source efforts. He said their contributions to open-source communities are welcome, but that those same companies will "eat you if you're not careful."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's an issue that resonates with Oumi CEO Manos Koukoumidis. Backed by Mozilla, Oumi operates an open-source platform that researchers and engineers can use to train, fine-tune, evaluate and deploy AI models. Koukoumidis previously spent around a decade working in AI at Microsoft, Facebook and most recently Google, where he became disillusioned with the future he was building.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While all the big tech companies contribute to a variety of open-source projects, some of which they manage, Koukoumidis said the bigger objective at the "tech mammoths" is dominance. In terms of safety, he is "very confident that they're taking a lot of shortcuts."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Koukoumidis and Surman agree that a much larger community of researchers and entrepreneurs should be collaborating to advance AI, which is one of the goals of Oumi.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Even the couple thousand people that are at OpenAI, Anthropic or anywhere else, because they're operating in a silo, they're not enough to advance this technology sufficiently, safely, cost efficiently, sustainably," Koukoumidis said in an interview. "What's happening right now, it's complete insanity. We're wasting billions, tens of billions, hundreds of billions."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Koukoumidis knows that abandoning a high-paying job at a place like Google has its drawbacks. He has substantially fewer resources at his disposal, and said his decision to leave the company was "intimidating."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the Transformer Lab team set out to raise funding in Silicon Valley and Canada, they were repeatedly told that it was going to be "technically impossible" for them to compete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"When you enter into the space of AI as a new startup, it's scary, because these few companies control so much more than just the intellectual property," Asaria said. They control funding and access to infrastructure, making it "very hard to just walk into the space without starting with $100 million or a billion dollars," he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Surman acknowledges he has to play the long game.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By 2028, he wants Mozilla to be funding a growing open-source AI ecosystem that's on its way to becoming "mainstream" for developers. And he's determined to prove that Mozilla's approach is economically viable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla is targeting a series of financial metrics over the next few years, including 20% annual growth in nonsearch revenue, according to a November report.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"For many people, the idea that open-source AI can win, or this rebel alliance, that those players can actually take a piece of the market, they find it hard to believe," Surman said. "But there's a bunch of trends that are underway."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WATCH: AI honeymoon is over and this will be its hardest year yet, says Deutsche Bank’s Adrian Cox&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/27/mozilla-building-an-ai-rebel-alliance-to-take-on-openai-anthropic-.html"/><published>2026-01-29T16:46:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46812892</id><title>Reflex (YC W23) Senior Software Engineer Infra</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:39.227450+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="75ce1aa31dcaa837"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The operating system for building mission-critical enterprise apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reflex is the operating system for building mission-critical enterprise applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today’s enterprise stack is fragmented. Shipping an app requires stitching together multiple tools and coordinating across multiple roles. Reflex replaces that complexity with a single, unified platform to build, deploy, and manage production applications end-to-end.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We empower teams to own the entire lifecycle of their apps — from idea to production — without needing specialized infrastructure, DevOps, or platform teams. We do this by providing solid, reusable abstractions at both the framework and infrastructure layers. Because we own the underlying open-source framework and the platform it runs on, we can manage the full lifecycle of the application seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Reflex, teams securely connect to company data, use AI to build standardized applications on top of our open-source framework, and deploy with a single click to share across their organization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re replacing the fragmented enterprise stack — and the organizational bottlenecks that come with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why join Reflex now?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Growth: Reflex has powered over 1 million applications, earned 28,000+ GitHub stars, and is used by 30% of Fortune 500 companies for internal tools and data-driven applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Team: Work with people who are genuinely passionate about improving the web. Our founding team consists of open source maintainers, top-ranked competitive programmers/IOI medalists, and founding team members from dev tool unicorns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Future: We are growing extremely quickly and just raised another round of funding.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/reflex/jobs/Jcwrz7A-lead-software-engineer-infra"/><published>2026-01-29T17:00:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46812933</id><title>Project Genie: Experimenting with infinite, interactive worlds</title><updated>2026-01-29T17:28:38.923772+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="18b9cbb6ad27d00d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Project Genie: Experimenting with infinite, interactive worlds&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In August, we previewed Genie 3, a general-purpose world model capable of generating diverse, interactive environments. Even in this early form, trusted testers were able to create an impressive range of fascinating worlds and experiences, and uncovered entirely new ways to use it. The next step is to broaden access through a dedicated, interactive prototype focused on immersive world creation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting today, we're rolling out access to Project Genie for Google AI Ultra subscribers in the U.S (18+). This experimental research prototype lets users create, explore and remix their own interactive worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How we’re advancing world models&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A world model simulates the dynamics of an environment, predicting how they evolve and how actions affect them. While Google DeepMind has a history of agents for specific environments like Chess or Go, building AGI requires systems that navigate the diversity of the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To meet this challenge and support our AGI mission, we developed Genie 3. Unlike explorable experiences in static 3D snapshots, Genie 3 generates the path ahead in real time as you move and interact with the world. It simulates physics and interactions for dynamic worlds, while its breakthrough consistency enables the simulation of any real-world scenario — from robotics and modelling animation and fiction, to exploring locations and historical settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on our model research with trusted testers from across industries and domains, we are taking the next step with an experimental research prototype: Project Genie.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How Project Genie works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Project Genie is a prototype web app powered by Genie 3, Nano Banana Pro and Gemini, which allows users to experiment with the immersive experiences of our world model firsthand. The experience is centred on three core capabilities:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;1. World sketching&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prompt with text and generated or uploaded images to create a living, expanding environment. Create your character, your world, and define how you want to explore it — from walking to riding, flying to driving, and anything beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more precise control, we have integrated “World Sketching” with Nano Banana Pro. This allows you to preview what your world will look like and modify your image to fine tune your world prior to jumping in. You can also define your perspective for the character — such as first-person or third-person — giving you control over how you experience the scene before you enter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2. World exploration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your world is a navigable environment that’s waiting to be explored. As you move, Project Genie generates the path ahead in real time based on the actions you take. You can also adjust the camera as you traverse through the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;3. World remixing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remix existing worlds into new interpretations, by building on top of their prompts. You can also explore curated worlds in the gallery or in the &amp;lt;randomizer icon&amp;gt; for inspiration, or build on top of them. And once you’re done, you can download videos of your worlds and your explorations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How we’re building responsibly&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Project Genie is an experimental research prototype in Google Labs, powered by Genie 3. As with all our work towards general AI systems, our mission is to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity. Since Genie 3 is an early research model, there are a few known areas for improvement:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Generated worlds might not look completely true-to-life or always adhere closely to prompts or images, or real-world physics&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Characters can sometimes be less controllable, or experience higher latency in control&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Limitations in generations to 60 seconds&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few of the Genie 3 model capabilities we announced in August, such as promptable events that change the world as you explore it, are not yet included in this prototype. You can find more details on model limitations and future updates on how we’re improving the experience, here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on the work we have been doing with trusted testers, we are excited to share this prototype with users of our most advanced AI to better understand how people will use world models in many areas of both AI research and generative media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Access to Project Genie begins rolling out today to Google AI Ultra subscribers in the U.S. (18+), expanding to more territories in due course. We look forward to seeing the infinitely diverse worlds they create, and in time, our goal is to make these experiences and technology accessible to more users.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.google/innovation-and-ai/models-and-research/google-deepmind/project-genie/"/><published>2026-01-29T17:02:39+00:00</published></entry></feed>