<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:30.183693+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46766961</id><title>There is an AI code review bubble</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:50:42.353567+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a7530c554976ccab"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we're in the hard seltzer era of AI code review: everybody's doing them. OpenAI, Anthropic, Cursor, Augment, now Cognition, and even Linear. Of course, there's also the "White Claws" of code review: pure-play code review agents like Greptile (that's us!), CodeRabbit, Macroscope, and a litter of fledgling YC startups. Then there are the adjacent Budweisers of this world:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazingly, these two were announced practically within 24 hours of each other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the proprietors of an, er, AI code review tool suddenly beset by an avalanche of competition, we're asking ourselves: what makes us different?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How does one differentiate?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on our benchmarks, we are uniquely good at catching bugs. However, if all company blogs are to be trusted, this is something we have in common with every other AI code review product. One just has to try a few, and pick the one that feels the best.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, code review performance is ephemeral and subjective, and is ultimately not an interesting way to discern the agents before trying them. It's useless for me to try to convince you that we're the best. You should just try us and make up your own mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of telling you how our product is differentiated, I am going to tell you how our viewpoint is differentiated - how we think code review will look in the long-term, and what we're doing today to prepare our customers for that future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our thesis can be distilled into three pillars: independence, autonomy, and feedback loops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Independence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We strongly believe that the review agent should be different from the coding agent. We are opinionated on the importance of independent code validation agents. In spite of multiple requests, we have never shipped codegen features. We don't write code; an auditor doesn't prepare the books, a fox doesn't guard the henhouse, and a student doesn't grade their own essays.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today's agents are better than the median human code reviewer at catching issues and enforcing standards, and they're only getting better. It's clear that in the future a large percentage of code at companies will be auto-approved by the code review agent. In other words, there will be some instances where a human writes a ticket, an agent writes the PR, and another agent validates, approves, and merges it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This might seem far-fetched but the counterfactual is Kafkaesque. A human rubber-stamping code being validated by a super intelligent machine is the equivalent of a human sitting silently in the driver's seat of a self-driving car, "supervising".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If agents are approving code, it would be quite absurd and perhaps non-compliant to have the agent that wrote the code also approve the code. Only once would you have X write a PR, then have X approve and merge it to realize the absurdity of what you just did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Autonomy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Something that Greptiles generally agree on is that everything that can be automated, will be automated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Code validation - which to us is the combination of review, test, and QA, is an excellent candidate for full automation. It's work that humans don't want to do, and aren't particularly good at. It also requires little in the way of creative expression, unlike programming. In addition, success is generally pretty well-defined. Everyone wants correct, performant, bug-free, secure code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While some other products have built out great UIs for humans to review code in an AI-assisted paradigm, we have chosen to build for what we consider to be an inevitable future - one where code validation requires vanishingly little human participation. We have no code review UI, and view ourselves as more of a background automation or "pipes" product. Human engineers should be focused only on two things - coming up with brilliant ideas for what should exist, and expressing their vision and taste to agents that do the cruft of turning it all into clean, performant code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Loops&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not long ago, we released our Claude Code plugin. It can do many things - but most notably, you can ask Claude Code to pull down and address Greptile's comments from the PR. You can ask it to keep going until there are no new comments, waiting a few minutes for a review after each push.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a step towards the future we're excited about: Human expresses intent, coding agent executes, validation/review agent finds issues and hands them back - kicking off a loop until it approves and merges. If there is ambiguity at any point, the agents Slack the human to clarify.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The question of how these things are different is important. Unlike picking IDEs and coding agents that ostensibly have low switching costs, code review products are harder to rip out, so your decision will very likely turn out to be a long-term one, especially if you're a large company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We've been around for about as long as AI code review has been around. It has gone from a fringe interest of the world's most adventurous vibecoders to a mainstream product that our enterprise users (including two of the Mag7) often describe as a "no-brainer" purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet, our guess on where this goes is about as good as anyone else's. Meanwhile, we'll keep doing what we've always done - trying to make things our users love.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.greptile.com/blog/ai-code-review-bubble"/><published>2026-01-26T15:38:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46767440</id><title>RIP Low-Code 2014-2025</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:50:42.059108+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b5503f7a49f409a8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;RIP Low-Code 2014-2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The rise of AI and particularly agentic development presents an existential threat to an entire category of low-code platforms. While the adoption of new techniques and tooling will take years to propagate through the Byzantine ranks of larger, slower-moving enterprises, the fundamental ROI case for these tools looks different in a world where the cost of shipping code now approaches zero.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This may seem like a preposterous conclusion given the substantial size and growth of the sector. Forrester, who actually gave low-code its name back in 2014, projects the category will reach $50b by 2028 and sees no current indication that things will slow down, let alone contract. However, it’s worth digging in to why these tools arose in the first place and the problems they solve to explore how much the landscape has shifted in just the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Put simply, these software platforms exist to allow users to create software with fewer developer resources. By purchasing one of these platforms, a company can enable non-technical stakeholders to ship production-ready experiences, often with little to zero actual code being written. This frees up developer bandwidth, accelerates the company, and until recently was a no-brainer investment for building internal and even customer-facing software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enable these platforms in the real world, developers spend considerable time on prerequisite and ongoing work: piping and transforming data, writing and maintaining custom components that go beyond out-of-the-box functionality, and meshing authentication systems, to name a few. This investment is in turn justified by the reduction in development scope and complexity downstream of the low-code platform—non-technical users can be left to their own devices to ship to their hearts’ content.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the emergence of AI coding, this ROI case gets inverted. It is now often faster, cheaper, and easier to ship the kind of tools you might have built with low-code tools outside these platforms. Yes, this still requires developer time, but so did enabling these low-code-platforms in the first place. Even disregarding the financial and organizational costs of low-code tools, AI affords developers the conveniences of their regular workflows without the bolt-on complexity introduced by external platforms. When you add in the total cost of ownership of these low-code tools, a return to in-house tooling becomes even more attractive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As an illustration of what’s possible, we’ve seen this play out in real-time at Cloud Capital. In the not-too-distant past, we relied heavily on a low-code platform called Retool for almost all of our internal Admin tooling. We built management dashboards, reporting, and orchestrated complex workflows that were critical to the business. The acceleration was real—our developers spent significantly less time rolling boilerplate tables, transforming data, and wiring up workflows. We even celebrated at our All Hands how much better our dashboards felt than if we’d hand-rolled them or used a pre-canned admin interface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then came the agentic tools that completely transformed the way we develop software. For our low-code tooling, the shift began with a single choice to prototype some new, self-contained functionality as a standalone internal tool instead of via our low-code platform. It was faster, easier, and leveraged our actual codebase in ways an external solution could not. That meant we shipped something safer, more robust, and more maintainable. The cherry on top is that the end product was also better—the UI looked and felt more like our in-house products, without the clunkiness required to stay on the WYSIWYG rails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It felt immediately clear that we had identified an unlock for our internal tooling velocity. All of a sudden, we found ourselves feeling constrained by the same low-code tools that until so recently were unblocking us. Changes that would have been one-liners in Cursor or automated triage tickets handled by an agent meant logging in to another platform, moving around clunky UX blocks, bashing against version management systems that weren’t quite as polished or integrated as our core development flows. All with the additional cost of maintaining this additional system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What started as a single tool quickly became a wholesale migration of all of our Admin tooling, and the inevitable sunsetting of our Retool instance. They hadn’t changed, but our culture and way of working had, and low-code couldn’t keep up. What was most shocking was the timeline of this change—for us as a small, fast-moving startup, the transition including migration played out fully in just a couple of sprints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s inevitable that incumbent low-code tools will adapt—they will need to in order to survive. In many cases, this shift is already visible in their marketing, such as Retool’s new AI-heavy positioning:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, it’s hard to say whether it’ll be enough. While it’s possible low-code platforms will survive by providing non-technical users with the kind of magical experience that’s already possible for developers with AI coding tools today, it also seems likely they will continue to cede market share to the core AI players themselves. We’re beginning to see this take shape as non-technical AI artifacts become more complex, powerful, and collaborative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For us, abandoning low-code to reclaim ownership of our internal tooling was a simple build vs buy decision with meaningful cost savings and velocity gains. It also feels like a massive upgrade in developer experience and end-user quality of life. It’s been about 6 months since we made this switch, and so far we haven’t looked back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every build vs buy decision is unique, but many ultimately boil down to ROI in terms of speed, financial cost, maintenance cost, and organizational complexity. There are of course additional considerations like vendor lock-in, ownership of core competencies, ecosystem compatibility, etc., but in this case we can reduce the decision to this: will buying this platform let my team go faster, ship more, and create more value for our customers. At least for now, that answer feels clearer every day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.zackliscio.com/posts/rip-low-code-2014-2025/"/><published>2026-01-26T16:11:28+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46768909</id><title>JuiceSSH – Give me my pro features back</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:50:41.373368+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="acb097aa1b6d154a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;JuiceSSH - Give me my pro features back&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JuiceSSH used to be, in my humble personal opinion, and for the uses I had, the best SSH client available on Android until December 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since then, the purchase made in 2019 is not recognized anymore, and the price went up by 20$. Some users complained in review, before it got unlisted from google play, that after buying it again, the application doesn't get activated. Support is unresponsive, this looks like an exit scam.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below is a way to make the application work again. This required jadx to understand smali, and will require you ApkTool and jarsigner, which is part of OpenJDK, and you that can install on Windows using &lt;code&gt;choco install openjdk&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You'll also need a JuiceSSH apk, I downloaded one from PureAPK, but feel free to dump your own from your device using adb if you cannot find it. Make sure to verify the hash using virus total/sha256sum if downloading from internet, which should be &lt;code&gt;d1ee811bcd82f25aea0bdc568896d82017ee174d9c4631c123a9d9173c748232&lt;/code&gt; for the last version available, version 3.2.2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below are powershell version of the command lines, but you get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Decompile&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first step is to decompile the dex packed code from the apk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp; "C:\Program Files\OpenJDK\jdk-25\bin\java.exe" -jar ./apktool_2.12.1.jar d juicessh.apk
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Modify smali&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You then need to modify the smali of three files, which are detailed below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;smali/com/sonelli/juicessh/models/User.smali&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this file, we'll patch the purchase validation and signature validation, done by the &lt;code&gt;public boolean H()&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the original version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;public boolean H() {
    try {
        String str = "";
        ArrayList arrayList = new ArrayList();
        for (Purchase purchase : this.purchases) {
            if (!arrayList.contains(purchase.order)) {
                str = str + purchase.product + purchase.state;
                arrayList.add(purchase.order);
            }
        }
        return vg0.b(this.signature, this.sessionIdentifier + this.name + this.email + str + this.disabled.toString());
    } catch (IllegalStateException e) {
        e.printStackTrace();
        return false;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which we'll simply change into&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;public boolean H() {
    return true;
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# virtual methods
.method public H()Z
    .locals 1

    const/4 v0, 0x1
    return v0
.end method&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;smali/com/sonelli/oi0.smali&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this one, we'll patch the &lt;code&gt;public static boolean d(Object obj)&lt;/code&gt; function, who calls the H() function we modified above, which now returns true, filters product matching JuiceSSH in purchases list, and check if it the purchase is valid. We'll simply make it return true in any case.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the original version:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;public static boolean d(Object obj) {
    if (!obj.getClass().getName().equals(User.class.getName())) {
        return false;
    }
    try {
        if (!((User) obj).H()) {
            return false;
        }
        ArrayList arrayList = new ArrayList();
        for (Purchase purchase : ((User) obj).purchases) {
            if (purchase.product.equals(a())) {
                arrayList.add(purchase);
            }
        }
        Collections.sort(arrayList, new a());
        if (arrayList.size() &amp;gt; 0) {
            if (((Purchase) arrayList.get(arrayList.size() - 1)).state.intValue() == 0) {
                return true;
            }
        }
        return false;
    } catch (NullPointerException e) {
        e.printStackTrace();
        return false;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the patched one:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;public static boolean d(Object obj) {
    return obj.getClass().getName().equals(User.class.getName());
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;.method public static d(Ljava/lang/Object;)Z
    .locals 3

    # obj.getClass()
    invoke-virtual {p0}, Ljava/lang/Object;-&amp;gt;getClass()Ljava/lang/Class;
    move-result-object v0

    # obj.getClass().getName()
    invoke-virtual {v0}, Ljava/lang/Class;-&amp;gt;getName()Ljava/lang/String;
    move-result-object v0

    # User.class
    const-class v1, Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;

    # User.class.getName()
    invoke-virtual {v1}, Ljava/lang/Class;-&amp;gt;getName()Ljava/lang/String;
    move-result-object v1

    # compare strings
    invoke-virtual {v0, v1}, Ljava/lang/String;-&amp;gt;equals(Ljava/lang/Object;)Z
    move-result v2

    if-nez v2, :cond_true

    const/4 v0, 0x0
    return v0

    :cond_true
    const/4 v0, 0x1
    return v0
.end method&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;smali/com/sonelli/pi0.smali&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, we'll patch the central part of the authentication, which is called each time a pro-feature is triggered to ensure user has valid license, the &lt;code&gt;public static void j(Context context, p pVar)&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the original version:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;public static void j(Context context, p pVar) {
    User user;
    User user2;
    String strS = User.s(context);
    if (strS == null) {
        pVar.a(context.getString(R$string.authentication_failure));
        return;
    }
    if (strS.equals("New User")) {
        pVar.a("New User");
        return;
    }
    User user3 = b;
    if (user3 != null &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !user3.disabled.booleanValue()) {
        long jCurrentTimeMillis = System.currentTimeMillis() - b.modified;
        DateUtils.getRelativeTimeSpanString(System.currentTimeMillis() + (b.w() * 1000), System.currentTimeMillis(), 0L, 0);
        DateUtils.getRelativeTimeSpanString(System.currentTimeMillis() + (3600000 - jCurrentTimeMillis), System.currentTimeMillis(), 0L, 0);
        if (b.w() &amp;lt;= 0) {
            gj0.b("API", "Cached user's API session has expired - refreshing session...");
            e(context, null, b.sessionIdentifier, pVar);
            return;
        }
        pVar.b(b);
        if (jCurrentTimeMillis &amp;lt;= 3600000 || context == null || (user2 = b) == null) {
            return;
        }
        e(context, null, user2.sessionIdentifier, null);
        return;
    }
    User userA = User.A(context);
    if (userA == null || userA.disabled.booleanValue() || !userA.H()) {
        e(context, null, null, pVar);
        return;
    }
    b = userA;
    if (userA.w() &amp;lt;= 0) {
        e(context, null, b.sessionIdentifier, pVar);
        return;
    }
    pVar.b(b);
    if (context == null || (user = b) == null) {
        return;
    }
    e(context, null, user.sessionIdentifier, null);
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pVar.b()&lt;/code&gt; is the success callback we'll call while &lt;code&gt;e()&lt;/code&gt; is called in case of error. &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; is the globally stored user we'll have to set. To patch this, we'll simply craft a User with meaningless data, a session expire always in future, save the user in &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;, and call the success callback every time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;public static void j(Context context, p pVar) {
    User user = new User();
    user.email = "myemail@google.com";
    user.name = "hello";
    user.given_name = "hello";
    user.sessionExpires = System.currentTimeMillis() + (86400000 * 365);
    user.sessionIdentifier = "";
    b = user;
    pVar.b(user);
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;.method public static j(Landroid/content/Context;Lcom/sonelli/pi0$p;)V
    .locals 8

    # User u = new User();
    new-instance v0, Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;
    invoke-direct {v0}, Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;-&amp;gt;&amp;lt;init&amp;gt;()V

    # u.email = "myemail@google.com";
    const-string v1, "myemail@google.com"
    iput-object v1, v0, Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;-&amp;gt;email:Ljava/lang/String;

    # u.name = "hello";
    const-string v1, "hello"
    iput-object v1, v0, Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;-&amp;gt;name:Ljava/lang/String;

    # u.given_name = "hello";
    iput-object v1, v0, Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;-&amp;gt;given_name:Ljava/lang/String;

    # long now = System.currentTimeMillis();
    invoke-static {}, Ljava/lang/System;-&amp;gt;currentTimeMillis()J
    move-result-wide v2

    # yearMillis = 86400000L * 365L
    const-wide/32 v4, 0x05265c00      # 86400000
    const-wide/16 v6, 0x016d          # 365
    mul-long/2addr v4, v6

    # u.sessionExpires = now + yearMillis;
    add-long/2addr v2, v4
    iput-wide v2, v0, Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;-&amp;gt;sessionExpires:J

    # u.sessionIdentifier = ""
    const-string v1, ""
    iput-object v1, v0, Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;-&amp;gt;sessionIdentifier:Ljava/lang/String;

    # pi0.b = u;
    sput-object v0, Lcom/sonelli/pi0;-&amp;gt;b:Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;

    # pVar.b(b);
    invoke-virtual {p1, v0}, Lcom/sonelli/pi0$p;-&amp;gt;b(Lcom/sonelli/juicessh/models/User;)V

    return-void
.end method&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Recompile&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp; "C:\Program Files\OpenJDK\jdk-25\bin\java.exe" -jar .\apktool_2.12.1.jar b juicessh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The built apk can then be found in &lt;code&gt;juicessh\dist\juicessh.apk&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sign the apk&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Create a keystore if needed to self sign the APK
keytool -genkey -v -keystore k.keystore -alias a -keyalg RSA -keysize 2048 -validity 50000

# Sign the APK
jarsigner -verbose -sigalg SHA1withRSA -digestalg SHA1 -keystore k.keystore ./juicessh/dist/juicessh.apk a&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Done&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can install this apk, ignore the security warning because it is self signed, and enjoy JuiceSSH with its pro features again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't think the cloud sync will ever work again, but that's a minor inconvenience, and you cannot trust a developper who act like this anyway. The plugins don't work anymore too, which is really a joke.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nproject.io/blog/juicessh-give-me-back-my-pro-features/"/><published>2026-01-26T17:46:38+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46770221</id><title>ChatGPT Containers can now run bash, pip/npm install packages and download files</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:50:41.206596+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="13184bc55a8d46c6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ChatGPT Containers can now run bash, pip/npm install packages, and download files&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;26th January 2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of my favourite features of ChatGPT is its ability to write and execute code in a container. This feature launched as ChatGPT Code Interpreter nearly three years ago, was half-heartedly rebranded to “Advanced Data Analysis” at some point and is generally really difficult to find detailed documentation about. Case in point: it appears to have had a massive upgrade at some point in the past few months, and I can’t find documentation about the new capabilities anywhere!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are the most notable new features:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ChatGPT can directly run Bash commands now. Previously it was limited to Python code only, although it could run shell commands via the Python &lt;code&gt;subprocess&lt;/code&gt;module.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It has Node.js and can run JavaScript directly in addition to Python. I also got it to run “hello world” in Ruby, Perl, PHP, Go, Java, Swift, Kotlin, C and C++. No Rust yet though!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;While the container still can’t make outbound network requests, &lt;code&gt;pip install package&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;npm install package&lt;/code&gt;both work now via a custom proxy mechanism.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ChatGPT can locate the URL for a file on the web and use a &lt;code&gt;container.download&lt;/code&gt;tool to download that file and save it to a path within the sandboxed container.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a substantial upgrade! ChatGPT can now write and then test code in 10 new languages (11 if you count Bash), can find files online and download them into the container, and can install additional packages via &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; to help it solve problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(OpenAI really need to develop better habits at keeping their release notes up-to-date!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was initially suspicious that maybe I’d stumbled into a new preview feature that wasn’t available to everyone, but I tried some experiments in a free ChatGPT account and confirmed that the new features are available there as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;container.download&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Is container.download a data exfiltration vulnerability?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bash and other languages&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Installing packages from pip and npm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adding it all together&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;container.download&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My first clue to the new features came the other day when I got curious about Los Angeles air quality, in particular has the growing number of electric vehicles there had a measurable impact?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I prompted a fresh GPT-5.2 Thinking session with:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Show me Los Angeles air quality over time for last 20 years&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the shared transcript. Annoyingly that doesn’t make the thinking trace available, so here’s a screenshot:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This bit instantly caught my eye:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[...] The URL from the error message leads to an Excel file containing air quality trends. I can use the container.download tool to fetch it. [...]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s &lt;code&gt;container.download&lt;/code&gt;? I asked ChatGPT:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Without running any searches tell me about your container.download tool&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And got back:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;container.download&lt;/code&gt;is a built-in tool I can call that fetches a file from a URL and saves it into the sandboxed container filesystem for this chat session.&lt;head&gt;What it does&lt;/head&gt;&lt;item&gt;Takes a publicly reachable URL and a destination filepath in the container.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Downloads the bytes from that URL and writes them to the given path.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;After that, I can read/process the file locally in the container (e.g., unzip it, parse it with Python, open it as an image, convert it, etc.).&lt;/item&gt;&lt;head&gt;Signature (inputs)&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s called like this (conceptually):&lt;/p&gt;{ "url": "https://example.com/somefile.zip", "filepath": "/mnt/data/somefile.zip" }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further experimentation confirmed that &lt;code&gt;container.download&lt;/code&gt; behaves as described.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had it download one file from a server with logs enabled and captured the IP address and user-agent. Here are the most interesting headers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;User-Agent: Mozilla/5.0 AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko); compatible; ChatGPT-User/1.0; +https://openai.com/bot
Accept: text/html, application/xhtml+xml, application/xml;q=0.9, image/avif, image/webp, image/apng, */*;q=0.8, application/signed-exchange;v=b3;q=0.9
Cf-Connecting-Ip: 52.230.164.178
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That &lt;code&gt;52.230.164.178&lt;/code&gt; IP address resolves to Microsoft Azure Cloud (centralus) in Des Moines, Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Is container.download a data exfiltration vulnerability?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the one hand, this is really useful! ChatGPT can navigate around websites looking for useful files, download those files to a container and then process them using Python or other languages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is this a data exfiltration vulnerability though? Could a prompt injection attack trick ChatGPT into leaking private data out to a &lt;code&gt;container.download&lt;/code&gt; call to a URL with a query string that includes sensitive information?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t think it can. I tried getting it to assemble a URL with a query string and access it using &lt;code&gt;container.download&lt;/code&gt; and it couldn’t do it. It told me that it got back this error:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;ERROR: download failed because url not viewed in conversation before. open the file or url using web.run first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This looks to me like the same safety trick used by Claude’s Web Fetch tool: only allow URL access if that URL was either directly entered by the user or if it came from search results that could not have been influenced by a prompt injection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(I poked at this a bit more and managed to get a simple constructed query string to pass through &lt;code&gt;web.run&lt;/code&gt;—a different tool entirely—but when I tried to compose a longer query string containing the previous prompt history a &lt;code&gt;web.run&lt;/code&gt; filter blocked it.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I think this is all safe, though I’m curious if it could hold firm against a more aggressive round of attacks from a seasoned security researcher.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Bash and other languages&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key lesson from coding agents like Claude Code and Codex CLI is that Bash rules everything: if an agent can run Bash commands in an environment it can do almost anything that can be achieved by typing commands into a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Anthropic added their own code interpreter feature to Claude last September they built that around Bash rather than just Python. It looks to me like OpenAI have now done the same thing for ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what ChatGPT looks like when it runs a Bash command—here my prompt was:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;npm install a fun package and demonstrate using it&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s useful to click on the “Thinking” or “Thought for 32s” links as that opens the Activity sidebar with a detailed trace of what ChatGPT did to arrive at its answer. This helps guard against cheating—ChatGPT might claim to have run Bash in the main window but it can’t fake those black and white logs in the Activity panel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had it run Hello World in various languages later in that same session.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Installing packages from pip and npm&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the previous example ChatGPT installed the &lt;code&gt;cowsay&lt;/code&gt; package from npm and used it to draw an ASCII-art cow. But how could it do that if the container can’t make outbound network requests?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In another session I challenged it to explore its environment. and figure out how that worked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the resulting Markdown report it created.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key magic appears to be a &lt;code&gt;applied-caas-gateway1.internal.api.openai.org&lt;/code&gt; proxy, available within the container and with various packaging tools configured to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following environment variables cause &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt; to install packages from that proxy instead of directly from PyPI:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;PIP_INDEX_URL=https://reader:****@packages.applied-caas-gateway1.internal.api.openai.org/.../pypi-public/simple
PIP_TRUSTED_HOST=packages.applied-caas-gateway1.internal.api.openai.org
UV_INDEX_URL=https://reader:****@packages.applied-caas-gateway1.internal.api.openai.org/.../pypi-public/simple
UV_INSECURE_HOST=https://packages.applied-caas-gateway1.internal.api.openai.org
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one appears to get &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; to work:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;NPM_CONFIG_REGISTRY=https://reader:****@packages.applied-caas-gateway1.internal.api.openai.org/.../npm-public
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it reported these suspicious looking variables as well:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_BASE_URL=packages.applied-caas-gateway1.internal.api.openai.org
CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_PYPI_REGISTRY=.../artifactory/api/pypi/pypi-public
CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_NPM_REGISTRY=.../artifactory/api/npm/npm-public
CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_GO_REGISTRY=.../artifactory/api/go/golang-main
CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_MAVEN_REGISTRY=.../artifactory/maven-public
CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_GRADLE_REGISTRY=.../artifactory/gradle-public
CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_CARGO_REGISTRY=.../artifactory/api/cargo/cargo-public/index
CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_DOCKER_REGISTRY=.../dockerhub-public
CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_READER_USERNAME=reader
CAAS_ARTIFACTORY_READER_PASSWORD=****
NETWORK=caas_packages_only
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neither Rust nor Docker are installed in the container environment, but maybe those registry references are a clue of features still to come.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Adding it all together&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result of all of this? You can tell ChatGPT to use Python or Node.js packages as part of a conversation and it will be able to install them and apply them against files you upload or that it downloads from the public web. That’s really cool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The big missing feature here should be the easiest to provide: we need official documentation! A release notes entry would be a good start, but there are a lot of subtle details to how this new stuff works, its limitations and what it can be used for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As always, I’d also encourage OpenAI to come up with a name for this set of features that properly represents how it works and what it can do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I’m going to call this ChatGPT Containers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Update: a full list of tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I decided to ask ChatGPT about other tools that were available to it in case there was anything interesting in there:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;List all tools that are available to you, with their exact names and descriptions and signatures&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what I got back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;List of ChatGPT tools according to GPT-5.2 Thinking on 26th January 2026&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below are all tools available to me in this chat, with their exact names, descriptions, and signatures (as defined in my tool interface).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;python&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;python.exec&lt;/code&gt; (FREEFORM) → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Execute Python code in a Jupyter environment for private/internal reasoning (not shown to you). Internet access is disabled.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature: &lt;code&gt;python.exec(FREEFORM) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;web&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;web.run&lt;/code&gt; (ToolCallV5 JSON) → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Access the internet and specialized lookups (search, open/click/find pages, screenshot PDFs, image search, product search, finance, weather, sports, calculator, time). Supports citations via returned &lt;code&gt;turn...&lt;/code&gt; reference IDs.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;web.run({ open?, click?, find?, screenshot?, image_query?, product_query?, sports?, finance?, weather?, calculator?, time?, search_query?, response_length? }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;automations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;automations.create&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Schedule a future/recurring task/reminder/search via iCal VEVENT.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;automations.create({ prompt: string, title: string, schedule?: string, dtstart_offset_json?: string }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;automations.update&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Modify an existing scheduled task.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;automations.update({ jawbone_id: string, schedule?: string, dtstart_offset_json?: string, prompt?: string, title?: string, is_enabled?: boolean }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;automations.list&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: List existing automations.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature: &lt;code&gt;automations.list() -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;guardian_tool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;guardian_tool.get_policy&lt;/code&gt; → str&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Retrieve policy guidance for specific categories (currently: &lt;code&gt;election_voting&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature: &lt;code&gt;guardian_tool.get_policy({ category: string }) -&amp;gt; str&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;file_search&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;file_search.msearch&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Search across available internal/connected sources (in this environment: primarily “recording_knowledge” transcripts when relevant).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;file_search.msearch({ queries?: string[], source_filter?: string[], file_type_filter?: string[], intent?: string, time_frame_filter?: { start_date?: string, end_date?: string } }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;file_search.mclick&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Expand/open previously returned search results (or connector URLs) for more context.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;file_search.mclick({ pointers?: string[], start_date?: string, end_date?: string }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;gmail (read-only)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gmail.search_email_ids&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Search Gmail message IDs by query/tags (read-only).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;gmail.search_email_ids({ query?: string, tags?: string[], max_results?: integer, next_page_token?: string }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gmail.batch_read_email&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Read a batch of Gmail messages by message IDs (read-only).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;gmail.batch_read_email({ message_ids: string[] }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;gcal (read-only)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gcal.search_events&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Search Google Calendar events in a time range and/or by keyword (read-only).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;gcal.search_events({ time_min?: string, time_max?: string, timezone_str?: string, max_results?: integer, query?: string, calendar_id?: string, next_page_token?: string }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gcal.read_event&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Read a specific calendar event by ID (read-only).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;gcal.read_event({ event_id: string, calendar_id?: string }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;gcontacts (read-only)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;gcontacts.search_contacts&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Search Google Contacts by keyword (read-only).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;gcontacts.search_contacts({ query: string, max_results?: integer }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;canmore (canvas)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;canmore.create_textdoc&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Create a new canvas text document (markdown or code).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;canmore.create_textdoc({ name: string, type: "document" | "code/bash" | "code/zsh" | "code/javascript" | "code/typescript" | "code/html" | "code/css" | "code/python" | "code/json" | "code/sql" | "code/go" | "code/yaml" | "code/java" | "code/rust" | "code/cpp" | "code/swift" | "code/php" | "code/xml" | "code/ruby" | "code/haskell" | "code/kotlin" | "code/csharp" | "code/c" | "code/objectivec" | "code/r" | "code/lua" | "code/dart" | "code/scala" | "code/perl" | "code/commonlisp" | "code/clojure" | "code/ocaml" | "code/powershell" | "code/verilog" | "code/dockerfile" | "code/vue" | "code/react" | "code/other", content: string }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;canmore.update_textdoc&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Apply regex-based edits to the current canvas textdoc.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;canmore.update_textdoc({ updates: { pattern: string, multiple?: boolean, replacement: string }[] }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;canmore.comment_textdoc&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Add actionable comments on matched regions of the current canvas textdoc.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;canmore.comment_textdoc({ comments: { pattern: string, comment: string }[] }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;python_user_visible&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;python_user_visible.exec&lt;/code&gt; (FREEFORM) → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Execute Python code that you will see (tables, plots, generated files). Internet disabled.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature: &lt;code&gt;python_user_visible.exec(FREEFORM) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;user_info&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;user_info.get_user_info&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Get your current location and local time (or UTC if unknown).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature: &lt;code&gt;user_info.get_user_info({}) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;summary_reader&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary_reader.read&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Read safe-to-share internal reasoning summaries from earlier turns (used when asked how I arrived at something).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature: &lt;code&gt;summary_reader.read({ limit?: integer, offset?: integer }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;container&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;container.exec&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Run a command inside the container and return stdout/stderr.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;container.exec({ cmd: string[], session_name?: string | null, workdir?: string | null, timeout?: integer | null, env?: object | null, user?: string | null }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;container.feed_chars&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Send input to a running interactive exec session and flush output.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;container.feed_chars({ session_name: string, chars: string, yield_time_ms?: integer }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;container.open_image&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Display an image from an absolute path in the container (jpg/jpeg/png/webp).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;container.open_image({ path: string, user?: string | null }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;container.download&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Download a file from a URL into the container filesystem.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;container.download({ url: string, filepath: string }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;bio (memory)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;bio.update&lt;/code&gt; (FREEFORM) → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Persist (or forget) user-specific info across conversations (“memory”).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature: &lt;code&gt;bio.update(FREEFORM) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;api_tool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;api_tool.list_resources&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: List available “resources” (including invokable tools) in an OP-style file tree.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;api_tool.list_resources({ path?: string, cursor?: string | null, only_tools?: boolean, refetch_tools?: boolean }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;api_tool.call_tool&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Invoke a resource as a tool (must know its full path/URI from &lt;code&gt;list_resources&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;api_tool.call_tool({ path: string, args: object }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;personal_context&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;personal_context.search&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Retrieve user-specific context from prior interactions/linked sources to maintain continuity.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;personal_context.search({ query: string }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;image_gen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;image_gen.text2im&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Generate or edit images from text instructions (and optionally referenced image IDs).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;image_gen.text2im({ prompt?: string | null, size?: string | null, n?: integer | null, transparent_background?: boolean | null, is_style_transfer?: boolean | null, referenced_image_ids?: string[] | null }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;user_settings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;user_settings.get_user_settings&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Read current settings and allowed values (personality, accent color, appearance).&lt;lb/&gt; Signature: &lt;code&gt;user_settings.get_user_settings() -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;user_settings.set_setting&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Change one setting (accent color, appearance, or personality) to an allowed value.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature:&lt;code&gt;user_settings.set_setting({ setting_name: "accent_color" | "appearance" | "personality", setting_value: string }) -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;artifact_handoff&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;&lt;code&gt;artifact_handoff.prepare_artifact_generation&lt;/code&gt; → any&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Description: Must be called immediately when the user asks for a spreadsheet or slide deck artifact.&lt;lb/&gt; Signature: &lt;code&gt;artifact_handoff.prepare_artifact_generation() -&amp;gt; any&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More recent articles&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Wilson Lin on FastRender: a browser built by thousands of parallel agents - 23rd January 2026&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;First impressions of Claude Cowork, Anthropic's general agent - 12th January 2026&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://simonwillison.net/2026/Jan/26/chatgpt-containers/"/><published>2026-01-26T19:19:40+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46770274</id><title>Dithering – Part 2: The Ordered Dithering</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:50:40.885058+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2334463359238fe7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understanding Threshold Map in Ordered Dithering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;tap/click the right side of the screen to go forward →&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hi! Welcome back to part 2 of my dithering series!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;← tap/click the left side to go back&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you missed part 1, please check it out first! I've covered how dithering simulates more colors than actually exist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;← or use arrow keys to navigate →&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This part dives into ordered dithering, a method using a threshold map to decide each pixel's final color*.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;*Note: This series covers grayscale dithering to two colors only: black &amp;amp; white. Multi-color dithering is possible, but it will not be covered here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are many ways to build a threshold map, each creating a unique visual pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'll guide you through how it works and how it forms those unique patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please note that this isn’t a technical deep-dive. It’s just a visual exploration of the logic behind ordered dithering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I personally grasp ideas much better when I can see them visually, so I hope this helps you too!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s start!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, a quick recap on quantization: the process of reducing colors in an image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grayscale images use many shades, from black to white.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, imagine our display can only show pure black and white.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must convert those gray shades into black or white. This is what quantization does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One way is by rounding: dark shades become black, and bright shades become white.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another way is by setting a threshold. Anything below it turns black; anything above it turns white.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The threshold controls the quantization output: lower thresholds can turn darker shades white, while higher ones can turn brighter shades black.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, imagine using multiple thresholds at once, each with a different value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quantizing a single color now gives us a mix of black and white pixels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result reflects the original brightness: brighter inputs get more whites, while darker inputs get more blacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is essentially how a threshold map works in ordered dithering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It converts gray shades into black &amp;amp; white patterns that mimic the original image's brightness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now let’s try to apply this map to a full image by tiling it across the entire area.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our image is now converted to black &amp;amp; white, but something is off. See those vertical line artifacts?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They are formed by the horizontal black &amp;amp; white patterns our map produces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem is that the output directly mirrors the map's layout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To fix this, we need to rearrange the threshold map.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Introducing: The Bayer matrix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thresholds are arranged in a 2x2 matrix, like this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When applied, it generates this signature cross-hatch pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pattern keeps black and white pixels apart, preventing unwanted artifacts like those vertical lines.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result is a uniform dispersion of black &amp;amp; white pixels that blend smoothly into shades of gray.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now while this looks better, we still have a problem: the transitions between shades are quite harsh.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The issue? With only 4 threshold levels, we only have 4 patterns to represent the entire grayscale shades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To improve this, we need to increase the number of our output patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a 4x4 Bayer matrix, which has 16 different threshold values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's an extension of the 2x2 matrix. Notice how the sequence is similar, just with different starting values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like the 2x2 version, it creates a cross-hatch pattern. But now with 16 distinct pattern variations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These extra patterns allow us to represent 16 unique shades of gray instead of just four.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a result, we get smoother transitions between shades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This reduces harsh transitions between shadows and highlights in the final image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that’s ordered dithering in a nutshell!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In summary, it uses a threshold map to translate shades into cleverly arranged patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now you might ask, can we use even more threshold levels? Or, can we arrange them differently?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The answer is yes! The threshold map's arrangement is what creates those unique dithering patterns. Let’s explore a few other ways to arrange them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the pattern coming from an 8x8 Bayer Matrix. With 64 levels, it’s a further extension of the versions we’ve seen so far.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It still has a similar cross-hatch pattern but offers even smoother transitions between shades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It provides a denser and more detailed gradient, although the difference is fairly subtle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now let’s look beyond the Bayer family with this pattern coming from a 8x8 Cluster Dot matrix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It consists of round dot clusters, quite different from Bayer’s cross-hatching.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It gives the image the classic, familiar feel of a printed newspaper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, my favorite method: Void and Cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;blue noise&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result is a pattern that feels less rigid than the Bayer cross-hatch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the final image, this creates a fine texture that blends into grays more naturally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s all for now! There are still some more maps to explore, but we’ll save those for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want more examples and details, here are some resources you might want to explore:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Libcaca study - 2. Halftoning&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Ditherpunk — The article I wish I had about monochrome image dithering&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Robert Ulichney's paper on void-and-cluster dithering&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoy what you read so far! In the next part, we’ll look at another dithering method that doesn't use a map at all: Error Diffusion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! See you in the next part.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;visualrambling.space is created by Damar, someone who loves to exploring new topics and rambling about them visually.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you like this, please consider following and sharing. I'll keep creating more visual articles like this!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm also open for collaborations or commissioned work. Feel free to reach out anytime.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow/contact me on:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://x.com/damarberlari&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;_blank&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://bsky.app/profile/damarberlari.bsky.social&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;_blank&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/in/damarpramudita/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;_blank&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;../rss.xml&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;_blank&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;mailto: [email protected]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;_blank&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Topics covered: Three.js, WebGL, dithering, visualization, interactive learning&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://visualrambling.space/dithering-part-2/"/><published>2026-01-26T19:23:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46772495</id><title>I let ChatGPT analyze a decade of my Apple Watch data, then I called my doctor</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:50:40.747589+00:00</updated><link href="https://www.msn.com/en-us/news/technology/i-let-chatgpt-analyze-a-decade-of-my-apple-watch-data-then-i-called-my-doctor/ar-AA1UZxip"/><published>2026-01-26T22:29:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46775135</id><title>A list of fun destinations for telnet</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:50:40.426814+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ff49aa5a6bc37ee6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Places to Telnet&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A list of fun destinations for telnet&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Overview&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The text based internet can be exciting, informative, and fun. Using telnet, you can access a variety of these resources on the internet. Below you’ll find lists of a few places to get you started.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have an interesting item to add, just send an email to us:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Various fun telnet servers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;india.colorado.edu 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Get the current time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;mapscii.me&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;A Telnet interface to a Braille/ASCII map renderer (code and info)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;horizons.jpl.nasa.gov 6775&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;NASA JPL HORIZONS solar system data (website for more details)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;telehack.com 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Telehack. Also play via the website&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;doom.w-graj.net 666&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Play Doom in the terminal (code and details)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;freechess.org 5000&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Free Internet Chess Server aka freechess.org&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;ticker.bitcointicker.co 10080&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;The live price of bitcoin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;1984.ws 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Edison Carter is…&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;telnet.wiki.gd&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Telnet Live Wikipedia with AI assistant (more info, code)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Notable, but no longer online :(&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;towel.blinkenlights.nl 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Star Wars asciimation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;towel.blinkenlights.nl 666&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;The Bofh Excuse Server&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Real classics. I especially miss the Bofh server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;rainmaker.wunderground.com 3000&lt;lb/&gt;weather via telnet!&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rainmaker was pretty great, and it lasted at least as far as 2018. I don’t recall what happened to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;nyancat.dakko.us&lt;lb/&gt;ANSI art animation of “poptart cat”, with support for many different terminals (cool screenshots!)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The telnet server is offline, but the website is still up for this one!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;mtrek.com:1701&lt;lb/&gt;mtrek (star trek themed game)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;xmltrek.com:1701&lt;lb/&gt;xmltrek (star trek themed game)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both are offline at the time of this update.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Muds, Talkers, BBS, and other systems&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;bbs.archaicbinary.net&lt;lb/&gt;Archaic Binary&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ateraan.com 4002&lt;lb/&gt;New Worlds - Ateraan&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;avalon-rpg.com 23&lt;lb/&gt;Avalon: The Legend Lives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;aardmud.org 4000&lt;lb/&gt;Aardwolf MUD&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;bbs.armageddonbbs.com 23&lt;lb/&gt;Armageddon BBS&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;52.88.68.92 1234&lt;lb/&gt;Cuban Bar&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TextMMOde.com 23&lt;lb/&gt;Sands of Time / Deep Space MMO&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;legendofthereddragon.ca 23&lt;lb/&gt;Legend of the Red Dragon (Canada)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;lord.stabs.org 23&lt;lb/&gt;Legend of the Red Dragon&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;thehatshop.mudhosting.net 3000&lt;lb/&gt;Hallowed Halls&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;eclipse.cs.pdx.edu 7680&lt;lb/&gt;New Moon&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;batmud.bat.org 23&lt;lb/&gt;BatMUD&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;forgottenkingdoms.org 4000&lt;lb/&gt;Forgotten Kingdoms&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;mush.shelteringcolorado.com 2601&lt;lb/&gt;Sheltering Sky: Colorado by Night&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;igormud.org 1701&lt;lb/&gt;Igor MUD/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;zombiemud.org 23&lt;lb/&gt;Zombie MUD&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;achaea.com 23&lt;lb/&gt;Achaea, Dreams of Divine Lands&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;gcomm.com 23&lt;lb/&gt;Galacticomm BBS&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Directories&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;http://telnetbbsguide.com&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;A large active listing of Dial-Up and Telnet accessible Bulletin Board Systems on the Internet:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;http://vintagebbs.org/bbsLookup.php&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;A bbs directory with location based searching:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;http://www.jumpjet.info/Offbeat-Internet/Public/TelNet/url.htm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Jumpjet has a nice list of telnet locations organized by category:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;http://synchro.net/sbbslist.html&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Synchronet is a nice list of bbs systems:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;http://www.mudconnect.com/&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Mudconnect keeps a good list of muds and moos:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;http://www.lights.ca/hytelnet/&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Hytelnet is an old (an now unmaintained) directory:&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://telnet.org/htm/places.htm"/><published>2026-01-27T03:24:13+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46775961</id><title>Kimi Released Kimi K2.5, Open-Source Visual SOTA-Agentic Model</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:50:39.552823+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="751fe2e9645bd4ba"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we are introducing Kimi K2.5, the most powerful open-source model to date.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kimi K2.5 builds on Kimi K2 with continued pretraining over approximately 15T mixed visual and text tokens. Built as a native multimodal model, K2.5 delivers state-of-the-art coding and vision capabilities and a self-directed agent swarm paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For complex tasks, Kimi K2.5 can self-direct an agent swarm with up to 100 sub-agents, executing parallel workflows across up to 1,500 tool calls. Compared with a single-agent setup, this reduces execution time by up to 4.5x. The agent swarm is automatically created and orchestrated by Kimi K2.5 without any predefined subagents or workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kimi K2.5 is available via Kimi.com, the Kimi App, the API, and Kimi Code. Kimi.com &amp;amp; Kimi App now supports 4 modes: K2.5 Instant, K2.5 Thinking, K2.5 Agent, and K2.5 Agent Swarm (Beta). Agent Swarm is currently in beta on Kimi.com, with free credits available for high-tier paid users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Across three agentic benchmarksâHLE, BrowseComp, and SWE-VerifiedâKimi K2.5 delivers strong performance at a fraction of the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kimi K2.5 is the strongest open-source model to date for coding, with particularly strong capabilities in front-end development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;K2.5 can turn simple conversations into complete front-end interfaces, implementing interactive layouts and rich animations such as scroll-triggered effects. Below are examples generated by K2.5 from a single prompt with image-gen tool:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond text prompts, K2.5 excels at coding with vision. By reasoning over images and video, K2.5 improves image/video-to-code generation and visual debugging, lowering the barrier for users to express intent visually.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is an example of K2.5 reconstructing a website from video:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This capability stems from massive-scale vision-text joint pre-training. At scale, the trade-off between vision and text capabilities disappears â they improve in unison.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below is an example of K2.5 reasoning over a puzzle and marking the shortest path using code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;K2.5 excels in real-world software engineering tasks. We evaluate it using Kimi Code Bench, our internal coding benchmark covering diverse end-to-end tasks â from building to debugging, refactoring, testing, and scripting â across multiple programming languages. On this benchmark, K2.5 shows consistent and meaningful improvements over K2 across task types.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To try out K2.5's agentic coding capabilities, K2.5 Agent offers a set of preconfigured tools for immediate, hands-on experiences. For software engineering use cases, we recommend pairing Kimi K2.5 with our new coding product, Kimi Code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kimi Code works in your terminal and can be integrated with various IDEs including VSCode, Cursor, Zed, etc. Kimi Code is open-sourced and supports images and videos as inputs. It also automatically discovers and migrates existing skills and MCPs into your working environment in Kimi Code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's an example using Kimi Code to translate the aesthetic of Matisse's La Danse into the Kimi App. This demo highlights a breakthrough in autonomous visual debugging. Using visual inputs and documentation lookup, K2.5 visually inspects its own output and iterates on it autonomously. It creates an art-inspired webpage created end to end:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scaling Out, Not Just Up. We release K2.5 Agent Swarm as a research preview, marking a shift from single-agent scaling to self-directed, coordinated swarm-like execution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trained with Parallel-Agent Reinforcement Learning (PARL), K2.5 learns to self-direct an agent swarm of up to 100 sub-agents, executing parallel workflows across up to 1,500 coordinated steps, without predefined roles or hand-crafted workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PARL uses a trainable orchestrator agent to decompose tasks into parallelizable subtasks, each executed by dynamically instantiated, frozen subagents. Running these subtasks concurrently significantly reduces end-to-end latency compared to sequential agent execution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Training a reliable parallel orchestrator is challenging due to delayed, sparse, and non-stationary feedback from independently running subagents. A common failure mode is serial collapse, where the orchestrator defaults to single-agent execution despite having parallel capacity. To address this, PARL employs staged reward shaping that encourages parallelism early in training and gradually shifts focus toward task success.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We define the reward as&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;where &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To further force parallel strategies to emerge, we introduce a computational bottleneck that makes sequential execution impractical. Instead of counting total steps, we evaluate performance using Critical Steps, a latency-oriented metric inspired by the critical path in parallel computation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;An agent swarm has an orchestrator that dynamically creates specialized subagents (e.g., AI Researcher, Physics Researcher, Fact Checker) and decomposes complex tasks into parallelizable subtasks for efficient distributed execution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In our parallel-agent reinforcement learning environment, the reward increases smoothly as training progresses. At the same time, the level of parallelism during training also gradually increases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;K2.5 Agent Swarm improves performance on complex tasks through parallel, specialized execution. In our internal evaluations, it leads to an 80% reduction in end-to-end runtime while enabling more complex, long-horizon workloads, as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Agent Swarm reduces the minimum critical steps required to achieve target performance by 3Ãâ4.5Ã compared to single-agent execution in wide search scenario, with savings scaling as targets riseâtranslating to up to 4.5Ã wall-clock time reduction via parallelization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are representative trajectories demonstrating K2.5 Agent Swarm in action:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kimi K2.5 brings agentic intelligence into real-world knowledge work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;K2.5 Agent can handle high-density, large-scale office work end to end. It reasons over large, high-density inputs, coordinates multi-step tool use, and delivers expert-level outputs: documents, spreadsheets, PDFs, and slide decksâdirectly through conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With a focus on real-world professional tasks, we design two internal expert productivity benchmarks. The AI Office Benchmark evaluates end-to-end Office output quality, while the General Agent Benchmark measures multi-step, production-grade workflows against human expert performance. Across both benchmarks, K2.5 shows 59.3% and 24.3% improvements over K2 Thinking, reflecting stronger end-to-end performance on real-world tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;K2.5 agent supports advanced tasks such as adding annotations in Word, constructing financial models with Pivot Tables, and writing LaTeX equations in PDFs, while scaling to long-form outputs like 10,000-word papers or 100-page documents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tasks that once took hours or days now complete in minutes. Here are some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grounded in advances in coding with vision, agent swarms, and office productivity, Kimi K2.5 represents a meaningful step toward AGI for the open-source community, demonstrating strong capability on real-world tasks under real-world constraints. Looking ahead, we will push further into the frontier of agentic intelligence, redefining the boundaries of AI in knowledge work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To reproduce official Kimi-K2.5 benchmark results, we recommend using the official API. For third-party providers, refer to Kimi Vendor Verifier (KVV) to choose high-accuracy services. Details: https://kimi.com/blog/kimi-vendor-verifier.html&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. General Testing Details&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2. Text and Reasoning&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3. Tool-Augmented / Agentic Search&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4. Vision Benchmarks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;5. Coding Tasks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;6. Long-Context Benchmarks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;7. Agent Swarm&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.kimi.com/blog/kimi-k2-5.html"/><published>2026-01-27T05:42:27+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46776454</id><title>Russia using Interpol's wanted list to target critics abroad, leak reveals</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:50:39.257736+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="fe04999e160d65d3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Russia using Interpol's wanted list to target critics abroad, leak reveals&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thousands of files provided by a whistleblower at Interpol expose for the first time the extent of Russia's apparent abuse of the international policing agency to target its critics abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The data provided to the BBC World Service and French investigative outlet, Disclose, reveals that Russia is using Interpol's wanted lists to request the arrest of people such as political opponents, businessmen and journalists, claiming that they have committed crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Analysis of data also suggests that over the past decade, Interpol's own independent complaints unit has received more complaints about Russia than anyone else - three times more than the next highest country, Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition, it indicates complaints against Moscow's requests have led to more cases being overturned than for any other country.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After Russia's full-scale invasion of Ukraine, Interpol introduced extra checks on Moscow's activity "to prevent any potential misuse of Interpol's channels in relation to the targeting of individuals within or beyond the conflict in Ukraine".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the leaked documents suggest these did not prevent Russia abusing the system and the whistleblower told us some stricter measures were quietly dropped in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In response, Interpol says that every year, thousands of the world's most serious criminals are arrested thanks to its operations and that it has a number of systems to avoid misuse which have been strengthened over the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It also says it is aware of the potential impact requests for arrest can have on individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"When you're hit with a red notice, your life changes completely," says Igor Pestrikov, a Russian businessman, whose name appears in the leaked files.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interpol is not a global police force itself, but helps police across the world to co-operate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A red notice is an alert to all of its 196 member countries, asking them to locate and arrest a person. A red diffusion is a similar request but is only sent to individual countries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pestrikov found he was named in a red diffusion after he fled Russia in June 2022 - four months after the invasion of Ukraine - and applied for asylum in France.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He felt he had two options: "Go to the police and say, 'I'm in the Interpol system,'" and risk arrest or lie low. This may mean "you can't rent an apartment, your bank accounts get blocked", which is what happened to him, he says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's constant nerves, all the time," he adds, explaining he was always looking over his shoulder. For safety, his daughter and her mother moved to another country. The police can "break into your house at any time… that's why you're like a cornered rat", he says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's the stress, the nerves, the pressure, the lawlessness inflicted on you," that breaks families apart, he adds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pestrikov had been a major shareholder in large metals companies in Russia that were privatised in the 1990s, most notably Solikamsk Magnesium Plant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the months leading up to the 2022 invasion of Ukraine, he says government ministers pressured him to stop selling his products abroad and only supply the Russian market. He believed this would mean his products could be used to make components for military hardware, such as fighter jets and tanks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He says it wasn't just that he was against "having to sell much cheaper and to whoever the ministries told me to" but that "it was a moral issue as well... no-one wanted to get involved even indirectly in the production of something used to kill people".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pestrikov believes his refusal to comply and the fact his wife at the time was Ukrainian led to his companies being nationalised and to Russia investigating him for financial crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After he fled to France, he was worried that the Kremlin might try to target him there, so he contacted Interpol and was told about the red diffusion request, which had passed the agency's checks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pestrikov decided to challenge it through Interpol's internal, independent watchdog, the Commission for the Control of Interpol's Files (CCF), arguing that Russia's request was politically motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interpol's constitution expressly states that the organisation cannot be used "to undertake any intervention or activities of a political, military, religious or racial character".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After Pestrikov had spent almost two years on the wanted list, the CCF ruled that his case was predominantly political. He showed us CCF documents that said the information Russia had provided was "generic and formulaic" and there had been an "inadequate explanation" of the alleged crime. Interpol cancelled the request for Pestrikov's detention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interpol only releases very basic data about illegitimate requests for arrests and since 2018 has not revealed which countries are the subject of complaints and inquiries. This lack of transparency makes it difficult to assess the scale of the problem, but for the first time, the leaked documents reveal a much fuller picture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One batch of files shared with the BBC contains a list of complaints sent to the CCF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The data is not complete, but it covers a broad range of countries, and where the nation requesting an arrest is listed, there are more complaints about Russia than anywhere else - this has been the case for the past 11 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The files also show that in the past decade, at least 700 people who were wanted by Russia complained to the CCF, and at least 400 of them had their red notices or diffusions overturned - that is more than for any other country, according to the data we received.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Historically it has been Russia who is one of the main perpetrators of abusive red notices," says British barrister Ben Keith, who has represented many clients wishing to have their names removed from Interpol's wanted lists.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He thinks Interpol has a particular problem with Russia and that the agency's attempts to prevent abuse have not been successful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He says that he has "a steady flow of clients who are subject to Russian red notices who are either politically connected, or often pro-Ukraine, or alternatively as a result of corporate raiding".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;International lawyer Yuriy Nemets, who specialises in Interpol matters and extradition, agrees that Interpol's extra scrutiny of Russia's requests for arrests, introduced after its full-scale invasion of Ukraine, has not proved effective.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He says he is aware of a number of cases in which Russians opposed to the war "have been targeted for speaking out against what's going on and were charged with financial… or other ordinary crimes and put into the database based on that".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's not hard to game the system," he adds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As well as information on notices and complaints, the Interpol insider also provided the BBC with thousands of messages sent between individual countries via Interpol's messaging system, revealing another, less formal route to trace people abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One message from Moscow to law enforcement agents in Abu Dhabi explained how Interpol had denied a request for a red notice, but that it still wanted help in tracing the subject's whereabouts. This goes against Interpol advice that members should not use its channels in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The leak also contains a message about Armen Aramyan, a journalist who had fled Russia after he was convicted of "engaging minors in dangerous activities" for reporting on student protests that supported the opposition leader Alexei Navalny in January 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aramyan went to Armenia and then on to Germany. The message from Russia to law enforcement entities in both countries sidestepped the more formal red notice and red diffusion process, and asked for "any useful information" about Aramyan as well as his whereabouts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The message was sent in February 2023, during the time Russia was under restrictive measures and its messages were being checked before being sent. We can't say for sure whether the message was delivered, but based on the source of the data, the whistleblower believes that it was.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the BBC showed Aramyan a copy of the message, he said he was shocked but not surprised.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I don't think they expected that Germany [would] send them my address, my phone number, and extradite me, but if they could at least get some sort of tiny bits of information it would still be valuable for them."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The leak contains other messages in which a foreign law enforcement agency responds to Moscow's request for information. It sent details about the movements of an ally of Navalny, Lyubov Sobol, and high-profile defector Gleb Karakulov. The exchange relating to Karakulov happened after Interpol announced its additional vetting of Moscow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The BBC also gained access to internal Interpol reports from 2024 and 2025 which show ongoing concern around Russia's activities from senior directors within the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In one, a senior figure expresses directly to Russian delegates "serious concerns" about the country's "wilful misuse" of Interpol systems, stating that there were instances of "flagrant violations" of Interpol rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite the extra restrictions on Russia, the reports show that approximately 90% of Russia's requests were still passing initial checks in 2024. And yet, in the same period, the CCF was overturning roughly half of all Russian requests that it received complaints about. This raises questions about whether the measures had been stringent enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One report describes how in 2024 Russia attempted to place red diffusions on judges and a prosecutor at the International Criminal Court, after the body issued arrest warrants for President Vladimir Putin and another government official for their actions in Ukraine. These requests from Moscow were rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even while concerns about Russia's misuse of Interpol's systems were being expressed inside the organisation, the reports also show that discussions were taking place in 2024 and 2025 about whether to remove additional restrictions on Russian activity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This seems to have been settled in Moscow's favour. The whistleblower told the BBC that in 2025 Interpol quietly dropped some extra measures against Russia — it is not clear how far this softening may have gone. Despite repeated requests, Interpol said it was not able to comment due to its "strict rules on the processing of data".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The BBC was unable to disclose all the details of the leak to Interpol as doing so could reveal the source. However, when asked about the issues raised in the investigation, Interpol said it was "concerned that a number of the accusations seems to come from a misunderstanding of how Interpol and CCF systems work, or factual errors about data and changes within Interpol's systems".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It is untrue to say that we prioritise police co-operation over preventing abuse – Interpol follows its constitution that expressly forbids the use of our systems on information that is of a predominantly political, military, religious or racial character."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And in the past, it has said it can do more good to prevent crimes by ensuring that lines of communication remain open.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We asked Russia's ministry of internal affairs for comment, but it did not respond.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lawyers Yuriy Nemets and Ben Keith agree that Interpol should do more to prevent misuse of its systems. "If countries are found to be significantly and persistently abusing red notices and diffusions, then they should be suspended from the system for a period of time," says Keith.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Otherwise, Igor Pestrikov fears that Russia, "with the push of a button, can enter anything, pin any crime on you - this lets them persecute you further around the world".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional reporting: Andreea Jitaru and Ned Davies&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c20gg729y1yo"/><published>2026-01-27T07:06:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46777641</id><title>We Do Not Support Opt-Out Forms (2025)</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:33.989268+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://consciousdigital.org/why-we-do-not-support-opt-out-forms/"/><published>2026-01-27T09:35:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46778123</id><title>The C-Shaped Hole in Package Management</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:33.692988+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a7b56f2f8f43a790"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;System package managers and language package managers are both called package managers. They both resolve dependencies, download code, and install software. But they evolved to solve different problems, and the overlap is where all the friction lives. If you drew a venn diagram, C libraries would sit right in the middle: needed by language packages, provided by system packages, understood by neither in a way the other can use. As Kristoffer Grönlund put it in 2017: “Why are we trying to manage packages from one package manager with a different package manager?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;apt, dnf, pacman, and the rest started as application delivery mechanisms. Users needed to install Firefox or LibreOffice, and decomposing applications into shared libraries emerged as an implementation detail. The dependency graph is there to serve patching and security updates for end users, not developers. A package like &lt;code&gt;python3-requests&lt;/code&gt; isn’t there because the Python ecosystem wanted it. It’s there because some GUI application or system tool needed it, and the distro maintainers packaged it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;System package managers generally keep only one version of each package at a time. This massively simplifies dependency resolution, but it means getting a newer or older version is hard for individual users without upgrading the whole system. It’s a stop-the-world model. Hacks like naming packages &lt;code&gt;python3&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;python2&lt;/code&gt; exist to work around this when you really need multiple versions, but they’re exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;npm, pip, cargo, and gem went the other direction. They’re dependency assembly tools that help developers build projects. They keep every version around indefinitely, letting projects pin exactly what they need. They’re also cross-platform by design: pip doesn’t know if it’s running on Debian or Fedora or macOS, so it can’t just shell out to the system package manager to install C dependencies even if it wanted to. The fact that you can &lt;code&gt;pip install httpie&lt;/code&gt; and get a working command-line tool is a side effect, not the purpose. These tools exist so you can declare &lt;code&gt;requests&amp;gt;=2.28&lt;/code&gt; in a manifest and get a working dependency tree.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The difference shows up in how they handle the same library. A distro maintainer sees a new OpenSSL release and asks: will this break existing applications? Can we backport security fixes without changing behavior? A language package manager asks: does this satisfy version constraints? Can multiple versions coexist? When you need both, the seams show.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edward Yang wrote about this in 2014: “The different communities don’t talk to each other.” They don’t need to, most of the time. But language packages that wrap C libraries have to deal with C dependencies somehow, and that’s system package manager territory. The language package manager has no vocabulary for it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The C-shaped hole&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;C never developed a canonical package registry. It predates the model of “download dependencies from the internet,” and by the time that model became standard, the ecosystem was too fragmented to converge. pkg-config exists as a partial vocabulary for discovering installed libraries, but it’s a query mechanism for what’s already on your system, not a way to declare or fetch dependencies. Conan and vcpkg exist now and are actively maintained, but neither has the cultural ubiquity of crates.io or npm. There’s no default answer to “how do I depend on libcurl” the way there is for “how do I depend on serde.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;System package managers filled this gap by default. If you need libcurl or OpenSSL or zlib, you install them through apt or dnf or brew. This makes your system package manager the de facto C package manager whether it was designed for that or not. And every distro names packages differently: libssl-dev on Debian, openssl-devel on Fedora, openssl on Alpine, openssl@3 on Homebrew. Same library, four names, no mapping between them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every language that needs C bindings solves distribution independently. Python has wheels that bundle compiled extensions. Node has node-gyp that compiles against system headers at install time. Rust has build.rs scripts that call pkg-config. Go has cgo with its own linking story. Ruby has native extensions that compile on &lt;code&gt;gem install&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;None of these mechanisms really declare C dependencies in a machine-readable way. If your Python package needs libffi, that requirement lives in a README or a Dockerfile or maybe just tribal knowledge. There’s no field in pyproject.toml that says “requires libffi &amp;gt;= 3.4” in a way that pip can act on. PEP 725 proposes adding exactly this, but it’s been in draft since 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You end up with two dependency graphs that overlap on C libraries but can’t communicate. pip knows your Python dependencies. apt knows your system dependencies. Neither knows what the other is doing, and the place where they meet is held together by humans who know which system packages to install before running pip install. Or the language package just bundles the C library inside itself: Nokogiri ships libxml2, NumPy ships OpenBLAS, and the system package manager never sees them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rust is starting to create a similar gap. Python packages that wrap Rust libraries need cargo available at build time, and the Rust dependencies don’t appear in Python’s dependency metadata. It’s not as messy as C: cargo handles its own resolution cleanly, and there’s no equivalent of the header/library version mismatch problem. But the cross-language boundary is structurally the same: two dependency graphs that can’t see each other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Containers solved the deployment side of this. As I wrote previously, Docker acts as the lockfile that system package managers never provided. Build an image and every machine running it gets identical bytes. But containers don’t solve the visibility problem. The C dependencies are still invisible to tooling, still not in any manifest that connects to vulnerability scanning or funding flows. The Dockerfile lists apt packages, but nothing maps those to the upstream projects or the language packages that need them. Tools like Syft crawl container filesystems looking for known binaries and package manifests in well-known locations. It’s a blunt instrument because it has to be: the metadata doesn’t exist, so Syft reconstructs what it can from filesystem heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Phantom dependencies&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Endor Labs coined the term “phantom dependencies” for this: dependencies bundled into packages but not represented in metadata. Vlad Harbuz covers how binary dependencies actually work at the technical level. Seth Larson, Security Developer-in-Residence at the Python Software Foundation, has been working on solutions involving standards and tooling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NumPy depends heavily on OpenBLAS, but that dependency doesn’t appear in its package metadata. The wheel bundles a compiled libopenblas.so.0 inside the package, invisible to pip and invisible to any tool that only looks at Python dependency information. If you want to know what NumPy actually depends on, you need tools like &lt;code&gt;nm&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;readelf&lt;/code&gt; to inspect the binary symbols. The pypackaging-native project documents this problem thoroughly: “The key problems are (1) not being able to express dependencies in metadata, and (2) the design of Python packaging and the wheel spec forcing vendoring dependencies.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The middle ground&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conda is probably the most successful attempt at bridging these worlds. It packages C libraries, Python, R, and other languages in a single dependency graph. You can declare dependencies on both libcurl and requests (or libcurl and an R package), and Conda understands what that means.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This took off in scientific Python, where C dependencies are a nightmare. NumPy linking against BLAS, SciPy needing LAPACK, HDF5 bindings for data science work. These projects have complex native codebases that are painful to compile from source and need careful matching between Python wrappers and underlying C libraries. Conda packages all of this with proper metadata and version constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Conda never became universal. Part of the reason is that it bundles the hard problem (managing C dependencies) with a less compelling solution for the easy problem (pure Python packages). If you don’t need compiled extensions, Conda is more than you need. And even when you do need it, conda environments are heavier than virtual environments and the resolver used to be infamously slow. Mamba exists largely because conda’s dependency resolution took forever on nontrivial environments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spack and EasyBuild occupy similar territory but for HPC, where you need fine-grained control over compiler flags, MPI implementations, and hardware-specific optimizations. Spack in particular has an exceptionally sophisticated dependency model, versioning compilers at various points in the dependency chain and recording everything involved in a build for reproducibility. It’s impressive engineering, but the complexity is justified by use cases most developers never encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nix and Guix come at it another way, with content-addressed storage and reproducibility as core design goals. They’re still system package managers, still delivering applications, but they have a better model for mapping language packages into that world. They repackage what’s on PyPI and npm, expressing C dependencies alongside Python ones in a single dependency graph. There’s a large community keeping these mappings current, encoding which Python and npm packages depend on which system libraries. It works, but it’s still one system absorbing the other rather than the two talking to each other, and the mappings live in nixpkgs, not in the upstream package metadata where other tools could use them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Making the invisible visible&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today the gap gets filled by humans. You run pip install, hit a compilation error about missing headers, google which apt package provides them. Dockerfiles accumulate RUN apt-get install lines that encode this knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vlad and I have been investigating how to automate this through ecosyste.ms: mine symbols from binaries across ecosystems, build an index that maps symbols to system libraries to upstream projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tools like &lt;code&gt;nm&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;objdump&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;readelf&lt;/code&gt; can list the symbols a library exports. Run this across apt, apk, rpm, and Homebrew packages, and you get a database: the symbol &lt;code&gt;SSL_connect&lt;/code&gt; comes from libssl, packaged as libssl3 in Debian and openssl in Alpine and openssl@3 in Homebrew. Do the same for wheels and gems and native Node modules, recording which symbols are undefined and which libraries are bundled inside the package. Then cross-reference: when a wheel has an undefined symbol, the database tells you which system library provides it. When a wheel bundles a library, you can identify the upstream project and version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The output might look like: [email protected] (PyPI) depends on libopenblas.so.0 (bundled), which is OpenBLAS 0.3.21 upstream, packaged as libopenblas0 in apt, openblas in apk, openblas in rpm, and openblas in brew. Ultimately I want to index these links into ecosyste.ms alongside the regular dependency data, so the cross-ecosystem connections become queryable like any other dependency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The motivation here is sustainability. Vlad works on the Open Source Pledge, which asks companies to pay maintainers of their dependencies. But dependencies on system libraries aren’t surfaced anywhere, which means they’re invisible to funding. NumPy depends heavily on OpenBLAS, but that relationship doesn’t show up when someone sponsors NumPy or analyzes its dependency tree. The OpenBLAS maintainers don’t get credit for the work that makes NumPy fast. Tracing these connections across package managers and languages is the first step toward fixing that. If software citation takes off in academia, the same problem applies: papers citing NumPy should propagate credit to BLAS, but only if we can trace the dependency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The same data has security applications. If a C library has a CVE, nobody can currently tell which wheels or npm packages or gems bundle an affected version. Vulnerability scanners look at language package metadata and see nothing. With a symbol database, you could trace from CVE to upstream library to every package that vendors it, across ecosystems. It also makes SBOMs more accurate: right now, generating an SBOM for a project misses all the C libraries bundled inside packages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vlad is presenting this at FOSDEM 2026 in the Package Management devroom, which I’m co-organizing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m not proposing solutions here, it’s a wicked problem. The point is that any serious attempt at a protocol for package management needs to grapple with this. Cross-ecosystem dependencies aren’t an edge case; they’re everywhere, just invisible. Making these implicit dependencies first-class is the missing layer between the two worlds, and it needs to be part of the conversation when that protocol gets investigated further.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nesbitt.io/2026/01/27/the-c-shaped-hole-in-package-management.html"/><published>2026-01-27T10:34:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46778341</id><title>I made my own Git</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:33.477271+00:00</updated><link href="https://tonystr.net/blog/git_immitation"/><published>2026-01-27T10:55:37+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46778461</id><title>Ask HN: Books to learn 6502 ASM and the Apple II</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:33.137404+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b640380132e639dc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to learn Assembly to make games on the Apple II. What are the old books to learn 6502 Assembly and the Apple II itself (memory, screen management) ? And is it absolutely necessary to learn BASIC before Assembly ?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My running joke after showing off some amazing LLM-driven work is...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;if you think this is impressive, I once opened a modal dialog on an Apple IIGS in 65C816 assembly&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't think you need to learn BASIC, if you know concepts like conditionals and looping and indexing. It is interesting to compare the higher-level language of the time with its companion assembly. And you might find yourself writing BASIC programs to complement your assembly, if you stick to that platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;lore&amp;gt; A friend dropped me a BASIC program that ran and wrote text to the Apple IIGS border. He asked me to figure it out, because it wasn't obvious what was going on. OG hacker puzzle... it was a BASIC program that jumped to hidden assembly after the apparent end of the text file (hidden chars maybe, I forget) and the assembly was changing the border at appropriate rate to "draw" on it. Those were the days... trying to find some reference to this and am failing. &amp;lt;/lore&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I certainly credit my stack-frame debugging capability to dealing with that stuff so long ago. Oddly enough, I didn't really find it helpful for computer architecture class. Just because you know registers exists and how to manipulate them, doesn't exactly map architecting modern hardware system. But being fluent in logic operations and bit-twiddling and indexing does help a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't think online tutorials are a good ressources to learn programming. We just have to look at what juniors can do nowadays (they can't even write a simple program, and I'm from that generation). That's why I asked for books.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Definitely develop some capabilities to accomplish an elementary satisfying project in BASIC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's the language that was designed for you to learn about programming and a computer language at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether or not you actually "master" the language or just barely learn a few commands, before using a few commands to make a simple finished program. One approach would surely be a lot faster than the other ;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After that then decide how much you learned about programming itself from the little project, then you can see how far that BASIC alone may be able to advance your programming abilities even after you may be very familiar with the language in detail, or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In that '80's generation of home computers with a 6502, most had built-in BASIC so a common progression for so many was to learn BASIC at the same time as learn programming, since nobody had ever had home computers before. This could be just fine for business applications. Assembly is not nearly as easy as BASIC to learn, but in some sense programming is programming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then for gaming BASIC was not nearly as fast as assembly but often BASIC performed just fine anyway for developing the logical game flow and making it a "fun" game at its core to begin with. The problem with BASIC was all the other little details like video, I/O, UI, HID, were all so dramatically slower because each BASIC command needed to be interpreted before it could be run on the hardware and that took a little extra time in between each command but it really added up when you have challenging hardware interfaces and not simply fundamental game logic (many times game logic can be so simple that it's never slow in any language).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a plain BASIC game that is "complete" but is supposed to have quick action and low latency, the next step in the learning curve would then be to find out which part of the BASIC code is the main resource bottleneck when it comes to processing time, then replace that one function with an equivalent written in assembly. It was accepted that it was a lot more work then to introduce assembly to make the game do the same thing it was before, only quicker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It may not be very clear looking back, but there were a number of good reference books and instructional approaches and so much of it was intertwined with "learn BASIC + programming at the same time" followed by "useful assembly language techniques" to speed up your programs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As crowds moved along these lines together to a degree as they emerged, it might help to look at publication dates for the books of the time, and use what's found in the earlier texts to help you with later concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I believe one of the "standard works" to learn 6502 back in the day was Programming the 6502 by Rodnay Zaks. It's out of print, but it was printed in a lot of copies so you should be able to find one second-hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This book specifically targets beginners that are new to 6502 assembly. The examples cover all of the 1980s-era computers including the Apple II. It's free on archive.org and the introductory chapters are worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They screen memory layout on the Apple II was a clever hardware hack but makes programming the machine more difficult. I think you'd be better off using a "trainer", like a KIM-1 simulator [0] to get your feet wet. (The KIM-1 was made by MOS Technologies, manufacturers of the 6502, as a demonstration and prototyping platform for the CPU.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you can do simple exercises on a machine like that and get comfortable with simple operations (loops, memory addressing modes) I think you'd have a better time grokking something more feature-filled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These two books will give you a good understanding of 6502 assembler - it is general but gives a good background and has a nice assembler with a full walk through of the code. I used these two books to learn 6502 on my Commodore 64 and they are highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are great books. I had them in paper, and they were great for understanding both how the 6502 worked, and metaphors for managing higher level constructs in ML.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and it includes a link to the documented source code for Akalabeth (also known as Ultima 0)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Somewhere, there's an article discussing the assembly-language like bit-blitting used to draw the high-res graphics in a timely fashion and the variable/memory management techniques needed to drive that which I'm sure a bit of searching will turn up (or one can derive it from the source).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm seconding the recommendation to look at Rodnay Zack's books. For example, I really enjoyed Advanced 6502 Programming. It's a project-based tutorial for a custom 6502 machine. The design and schematics are in the book.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seconded. I bought the first edition of "Programming the 6502" way back in the neolithic, and I enjoyed it greatly. I even read parts of it again now and then these days too, just because I like it. I used to write assembly on, at first, the AIM-65, and later the Apple II.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is Programming the 6502 enough to learn Assembly on the Apple II ? But it doesn't explain the memory and screen management, right ? So how can we learn that ?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Someone can correct me if I'm wrong, but I believe the screen memory of the Commodore machines (ViC-20, Commodore 64) were the most straight-forward. As opposed to the more janky Apple II memory map.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You could do a lot worse than picking up a new Commodore 64 Ultimate [1]. They're a more or less faithful remake of the Commodore 64 but have an HDMI port, SD card instead of disk drive, etc. You could learn BASIC, should be able move to assembly as well—a quick search pulled up a YouTube course on 6502 assembly for the Commodore [2].&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(I realize I am not contributing "books"—but others have done well in this regard. I did want to share what I think is a pragmatic way to learn 6502.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is the Apple II Reference Manual good for that ? Or anything specific to the Apple II, like "What's Where in the Apple" or "Understanding the Apple II" ?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learning BASIC isn't essential, but the thing is, you might as well just do it. It's not complicated, and you're not under any obligation to develop a big piece of software with it. Have fun!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check the books section and find something that compels you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, don't forget the HUGE number of resources for 6502 assembly programming that are available in the https://archive.org/ magazine and book sections:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Its not absolutely necessary to learn BASIC before Assembly, but it will definitely help you understand the resources of the machine better if you can debug BASIC ROM code. My personal 6502 platform of choice, the Oric-1/Atmos machines, has a pretty great ROM disassembly available, from which a lot of great knowledge can be obtained - but it does of course first require an undersanding of BASIC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In case you're curious, the Oric-1 ROM Disassembly:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The answer would depend on what programming experience you have? Do you have any assembly language experience ? with other targets? ie have you used an assembler ( and maybe linker ) before. Are you familiar with hex? bytes, bits etc , You will learn this and much more ...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Id look for a book that targets Assembly programming on a Apple 2, ie not a book on general 6502 programming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Such a book Id expect to discuss things like Apple 2 memory map , Apple 2 hardware and how they are used in assembler language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hopefully the book would also provide guidance using a particular assembler ( hopefully still available)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I googled phrase Apple 2 assembly language programming for beginners?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and lots of very good looking links popped up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You aim is a challenging task. Much to learn. Good luck. However entirely do able these days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My background is electronics engineer, embedded programing on in assembler (some Motorola processors and others) and C for a few years before moving on to other things ....&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I respectfully disagree, BASIC/Java/Arduino hides too much about how the CPU works from users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Getting a 6502 kit from Ben Eater, and walking though how the CPU works will implicitly show how languages abstracted away whats actually happening. And more importantly, the skills necessary to understand how to write efficient programs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I second this -- I just found the Ben Eater series a month or so ago and put together his computer clock over the holidays. It really helps you understand clock cycles, logic chips, etc, and is a good foundation for the 6502 kit you build later in the course. And learning Assembly before BASIC is the right learning path IMO, if only to understand how CPU registers work at the electron level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting with the 6502 is going to bring you up hard against its addressing modes. Better IMHO to learn about memory and how to access it using arrays in BASIC first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My opinion differs - learning how memory is accessed via assembly language will make it super easy to understand e.g. how C pointers actually work, something which can be surprisingly difficult for those who go directly to a high level (compared to assembly) language, but very easy if you come from machine code/assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have fond memories from the late 1980s of trying to get the assembler contained within this book working, typing line after line of the MLX listing in. Unfortunately I never did finish it back then.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A week or so ago I got the urge to complete this project and I literally just finished getting the source in it to a point where it can be compiled online and then within an emulator: https://github.com/jlmcgraw/LADS_DOS33&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46778461"/><published>2026-01-27T11:12:30+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46778821</id><title>India and EU announce landmark trade deal</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:32.924167+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a4b894d05ba7193c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;India and EU announce 'mother of all trade deals'&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The European Union and India have announced a landmark trade deal after nearly two decades of on-off talks, as both sides aim to deepen ties amid tensions with the US.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We did it, we delivered the mother of all deals," European Commission President Ursula von der Leyen said at a media briefing in Delhi. Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi called the pact "historic".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It will allow free trade of goods between the bloc of 27 European states and the world's most populous country, which together make up nearly 25% of global gross domestic product and a market of two billion people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The deal will see a number of huge tariff cuts across a range of goods and services, and a joint security partnership.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Von der Leyen and European Council President António Costa are in Delhi, where they met Modi at a bilateral summit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The European Commission said would eliminate tariffs on most exports of chemicals, machinery and electrical equipment, as well as aircraft and spacecraft, following phased reductions. Significantly, duties on motor vehicles, currently as high as 110%, would be cut to 10% under a quota of 250,000 vehicles. That is six times larger than the 37,000-unit quota India granted to the UK in a deal signed last July.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;India will also cut tariffs on wine, beer and olive oil from the EU. Brussels said the agreement would support investment flows, improve access to European markets and deepen supply-chain integration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Delhi said almost all of its exports would get "preferential access" into the EU, with textiles, leather, marine products, handicrafts, gems and jewellery set to see a reduction or elimination of tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While commodities such as tea, coffee, spices and processed foods will benefit from the agreement, Delhi "has prudently safeguarded sensitive sectors, including dairy, cereals, poultry, soy meal, certain fruits and vegetables, balancing export growth with domestic priorities", it said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Delhi and Brussels have also agreed on a mobility framework that eases restrictions for professionals to travel between India and the EU in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"This is India's biggest free trade agreement," Modi said. "It will make access to European markets easier for India's farmers and small business. It will also boost manufacturing and services sectors. It will boost innovative partnerships."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trade deal comes as both India and the EU contend with economic and geopolitical pressure from the US.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Delhi is grappling with 50% tariffs imposed by President Donald Trump last year amid talks aimed at securing a trade deal between India and the US that are still dragging on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last week, Trump threatened to escalate his trade war with European allies for opposing a US takeover of Greenland, before backing off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That larger geopolitical context was evident in statements made by leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, von der Leyen said: "This is the tale of two giants - the world's second and fourth largest economies. Two giants which chose partnership in a true win-win fashion. A strong message that co-operation is the best answer to global challenges."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A day before that Costa had said, without naming the US, that the trade deal would send an "important political message to the world that India and the EU believe more in trade agreements than in tariffs".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The deal with the European Union may help labour-intensive sectors in India such as shrimp farming, textiles, gems and jewellery, which were hit hard by the US tariffs, experts say.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But some analysts also predict challenges - especially when it comes to compliance with EU regulations and standards. "The EU has very strict regulations, for instance, on environment. It is one of the leaders when it comes to carbon offsetting mechanisms," says economist Mitali Nikore.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She says India's manufacturing sector "might not be fully prepared" for this and that it is critical that it takes steps to fix this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It is an opportunity more than a challenge," she says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the EU, the deal is aimed at providing some certainty, even security, in a time of economic coercion and global turbulence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Germany and France are projected to be among the biggest beneficiaries even if this isn't the "super maximally ambitious" version of a trade deal once envisioned, says Andrew Small, Asia director at the European Council on Foreign Relations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, he says, the agreement is seen as a building block rather than a final destination as the EU looks to tap into a massive, fast-growing economy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It really is understood as a floor for what is possible for the bilateral relationship."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The formal signing is likely to take place only later this year, after the agreement is approved by the European Parliament and member states.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There may be some concerns around this after another major trade deal the EU struck with the Mercosur bloc of South American countries was recently derailed in the European Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the India agreement is regarded as less contentious as it "cuts around sensitives on both sides," says Small.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alongside the trade agreement, India and the European Union are also advancing separate talks on security and defence co-operation, and climate action.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, India's Defence Minister Rajnath Singh said he had discussed a range of bilateral security and defence issues with the European Commission's vice-president Kaja Kallas, including opportunities to integrate supply chains to build trusted defence ecosystems and develop future-ready capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two sides are working on a draft security and defence partnership covering areas such as maritime security, cyber threats and defence dialogue, Reuters news agency reported.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EU is India's largest trading partner in goods, with bilateral merchandise trade reaching $136bn (£99.4bn) in 2024-25, nearly doubling over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Talks for a deal started in 2007 but stalled in 2013 over roadblocks in market access and regulatory demands. Discussions were formally restarted in July 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trump's tariffs proved to be a "useful tailwind in the homestretch" to get the deal over the line, one EU diplomat told the BBC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the past seven months, India has signed major trade agreements with the UK, Oman and New Zealand, and a 2024 pact signed with the four-nation European Free Trade Association bloc of Switzerland, Norway, Iceland and Liechtenstein came into effect last year. It signed a trade pact with Australia in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow BBC News India on Instagram, YouTube, Twitter and Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/crrnee01r9jo"/><published>2026-01-27T11:58:07+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46778846</id><title>Trayd (YC S23) is hiring senior engineers in NYC</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:32.613853+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b50dc15d5663cc54"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Trayd (YCS23) is building construction payroll + back office software. Payroll is one of the few domains where 99% accuracy is an F, so we obsess over correctness, reliability, and observability.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We recently hit a major growth milestone (57% month-over-month revenue growth, among other things), and we’re hiring senior engineers in NYC (on-site) to help scale the product and the systems behind it as volume ramps. You would be joining a small but mighty eng team, all based in NYC.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Stack: TypeScript, Node, Postgres, Prisma, React &amp;amp; React Native.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;URL: https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/trayd/jobs/1Ez3l4b-sen...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46778846"/><published>2026-01-27T12:00:22+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46779136</id><title>9 Mothers (YC X26, Defense Tech) Is Hiring</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:32.319614+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e10fcdab2cdf53e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need to enable JavaScript to run this app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/9-mothers?utm_source=x8pZ4B3P3Q"/><published>2026-01-27T12:31:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46779645</id><title>Xfwl4 – The Roadmap for a Xfce Wayland Compositor</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:32.195332+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9f1261d108f93af0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We, the Xfce team are excited to share some great news!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After careful consideration, we’ve decided on a meaningful way to use the generous donations from our community: funding longtime Xfce core developer Brian Tarricone to create xfwl4, a brand-new Wayland compositor for Xfce.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This initiative will utilize a significant portion of the project’s donated funds, but we believe it’s an important investment in Xfce’s future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal is, that xfwl4 will offer the same functionality and behavior as xfwm4 does, or as much as possible considering the differences between X11 and Wayland. Using xfwl4 should feel just like using xfwm4 on X11. We even plan to reuse the existing xfwm4 configuration dialogs and xfconf settings to ensure a seamless transition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Xfwl4 will not be based on the existing xfwm4 code. Instead, it will be written from scratch in rust, using smithay building blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first attempt at creating an Xfce Wayland compositor involved modifying the existing xfwm4 code to support both X11 and Wayland in parallel. However, this approach turned out to be the wrong path forward for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the decision to write a compositor from scratch was done, the next major question was: Which Wayland support library to use as a base? In order to find an answer on that question Brian evaluated wlroots and smithay. The decision to use smithay as a base was done for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Besides getting feature parity with xfwm4, the xfwl4 project scope includes as well some other related tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brian has already started work on the project, so stay tuned for the first development release of xfwl4, which we hope to share around mid-year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in the detailed reasoning behind the project or want to explore all the technical details, check out the issues and the work in progress source code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For any questions related to xfwl4, please visit our Matrix channel #xfce-dev.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’d like to extend our heartfelt thanks to our generous supporters on Open Collective US and Open Collective EU for making this project possible!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Best regards,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Xfce development team&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://alexxcons.github.io/blogpost_15.html"/><published>2026-01-27T13:25:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46779809</id><title>TikTok users can't upload anti-ICE videos. The company blames tech issues</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:31.902633+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f59ddc90a060ae91"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The comedian Megan Stalter, who posts absurd character skits to an audience in the high hundreds of thousands across Instagram and TikTok, tried sharing a different kind of video on Saturday night. Driven by the death of Alex Pretti, the nurse shot by a federal immigration agent or agents that day, she had recorded herself urging her fellow Christians to speak out against ICE raids in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We have to abolish ICE,” Stalter said in the video. “I truly, truly believe that is exactly what Jesus would do.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Instagram, the video was reposted more than 12,000 times. But her plea never made it to TikTok. In a follow-up post on Instagram, she said she had attempted to upload the video to TikTok several times with no success, then had given up and deleted her TikTok account entirely, believing her content was being censored because it was about ICE. (CNN has reached out to Stalter for comment.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other users reported the same combination of events, drawing a circumstantial connection between their efforts to make videos about ICE and the difficulties they had posting them over the weekend. The controversy caught the attention of Connecticut Democratic Sen. Chris Murphy, who said that among “threats to democracy,” the purported censorship on TikTok was “at the top of the list.” (CNN has reached out to Murphy’s office for comment.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TikTok said in a statement that glitches on the app were due to a power outage at a US data center. As a result, a spokesperson for TikTok US Joint Venture told CNN, it’s taking longer for videos to be uploaded and recommended to other users. The tech issues are ongoing, TikTok said, and are “unrelated to last week’s news.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last week, a majority American-owned joint venture took control of TikTok’s assets in the US, in a deal shepherded by the Trump administration under a 2024 law requiring the app to move out from under its previous Chinese ownership or face a ban in the United States. Among its new investors is the tech company Oracle, whose executive chair Larry Ellison is a close affiliate of President Donald Trump. Oracle will store US TikTok users’ data in a “secure US cloud environment,” according to TikTok, and the new joint venture will “have decision-making authority for trust and safety policies and content moderation.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a private platform, TikTok is free to exert influence on what users can upload or see. Even if accusations of TikTok’s censorship are unprovable, it’s understandable that US users would be increasingly skeptical of the platform in this moment, said Casey Fiesler, an associate professor of technology ethics and internet law at the University of Colorado, Boulder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“There’s not a lot of trust in the leadership of social media platforms in general,” Fiesler told CNN. “And given the connection of the new ownership of TikTok to the Trump administration, which is so wrapped up in what is happening with ICE in Minnesota, it’s not surprising that there’s a significant lack of trust.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;TikTok users are concerned&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fiesler said she was “unsurprised” about censorship concerns on TikTok, given the timing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Almost immediately after oversight of TikTok’s US operations changed, misinformation started to spread about changes to the app’s new terms of service, including those that applied to location sharing and data collection, Fiesler said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“A lot of TikTok users are concerned about what this new ownership means, both with respect to who has access to their data, and how content recommendation might change or could change,” Fiesler said. “I think those are valid concerns.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few days ago, Fiesler posted some videos aiming to debunk those rumors about the changes to the terms of service, and those were uploaded without issue. She has attempted to upload two videos since Sunday afternoon, one of which she says is still “under review” by TikTok and can’t be viewed publicly. While both generally alluded to ongoing ICE action in Minneapolis, she used it as a framing device to discuss media literacy. One of the videos did successfully upload on Monday, though its captions and view counter weren’t working for several hours, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Even if this isn’t purposeful censorship, does it matter? In terms of perception and trust, maybe,” Fiesler said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jen Hamilton, a nurse and author with more than 4.5 million TikTok followers, says she became suspicious of TikTok on January 22, the day of the announced change in control in the US, when a video she made about 5-year-old Liam Conejo Ramos being taken by federal agents wouldn’t upload.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It was very ironic for that very first day of this takeover, for me to post something about ICE and then it not be viewable to the public,” Hamilton told CNN, adding that the video still can’t be seen by her followers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After she posted a still about Pretti, her next four videos couldn’t be uploaded, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Something has shifted in the way that content is getting put on the platform, or allowed to be on the platform,” she said, while noting that she didn’t have proof of being personally censored. “And I just find it very ironic that it’s the same day that it takes over that people are not being able to post their stuff.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;An opaque algorithm&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It would be incredibly difficult to prove TikTok is censoring content about ICE because the platform’s content recommendation process is so opaque, said Jeffrey Blevins, a professor at the University of Cincinnati who studies media law and ethics, among other subjects. Plus, if TikTok were intentionally censoring content about ICE, it would be within its legal right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“They’re a private platform. They have a First Amendment right to do that,” he said. “A lot of times it’s easy for us to think of social media as a public square, but it’s not public in a way that matters under the law.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some users, like Stalter, are deleting their accounts and leaving the app altogether (though some have also had trouble deleting their accounts, Fiesler noted). The daily average of TikTok uninstalls are up nearly 150% in the last five days compared to the last three months, market firm SensorTower told CNBC on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“If people leave TikTok now, I suspect it’s a combination of things, not just because some videos weren’t posted on one day. It’s also concerns about what this means for the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hamilton said while she’s exploring options like Substack and Patreon, where followers can pay to hear her unvarnished thoughts, she won’t fully abandon TikTok.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This whole thing is intended to dissuade people, especially who are sharing a narrative that is not similar to what the government is wanting people to hear,” she said she suspects. “I think the purpose of having those people feel like their content is not safe on this platform is to get them to stop speaking out, or use the platform differently, or play by the rules.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She’s already figured out ways to continue to talk about ICE, she said. In a video that did make it through TikTok’s uploading process, she calls herself a “fashion influencer” and speaks in code about her trouble uploading an earlier video about Liam.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Fashion influencing is in my blood,” she said in the video, with a photo of Liam behind her. “And even a company with bad customer service won’t keep me from doing my fashion review.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/01/26/tech/tiktok-ice-censorship-glitch-cec"/><published>2026-01-27T13:44:24+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46779994</id><title>Show HN: We Built the 1. EU-Sovereignty Audit for Websites</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:30.843133+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="91b5b4e9f9bc27b3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check in seconds how dependent your website is on Non-EU services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EU Independence Audit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Â· &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our free scanner analyzes Google Fonts, Analytics, CDNs, video embeds and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What gets checked?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hosting â Where is your server located?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fonts â Google Fonts, Adobe Fonts or EU alternatives?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Analytics â Google Analytics or privacy-friendly solutions?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CDN â Cloudflare, AWS or European providers?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Video â YouTube embeds or self-hosted?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chat â Intercom, Drift or EU tools?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Social â Facebook Pixel, Twitter widgets?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Maps â Google Maps or OpenStreetMap?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why does this matter?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EU-US Data Privacy Framework can be invalidated at any time â just like Safe Harbor (2015) and Privacy Shield (2020). Websites with 100% EU score are future-proof.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lightwaves.io/en/eu-audit/"/><published>2026-01-27T14:00:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46780065</id><title>The age of Pump and Dump software</title><updated>2026-01-27T15:48:30.629282+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2b5c91524b2567bd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Age of Pump and Dump Software&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A new worrying amalgamation of crypto scams and vibe coding emerges from the bowels of the internet in 2026&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025 was the breakthrough year when software creation became easy. AI models became much better and even doing a “ralph loop” on a simple prompt in a few hours could produce copious amount of working code. As a result you would have burned through thousands of dollars of tokens to get some barely working “product” and you would have no idea who or why would use it. In order to develop it into proper offering you would have to learn how to code, product development, marketing and so on. But what if there was an easy way to “dump it” on unsuspecting masses?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The initial software Pump and Dump event could be considered when Cursor burned through millions of dollars to build a barely working browser. Naturally there was no way to finish such a monstrous heap of software into a working product and why would anybody use a vibe coded browser anyway? The “dump” on their end was to use this as marketing bait and a way to inflate their valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the start of 2026 “gastown” project attracted my attention. What initially looked as a schizoprenic vibe coded fever dream was touted by multiple tech blogs as possibly a “new thing”, maybe revolution of some sort. Later a blog post by project author announced that he had taken a donation from crypto bros and the things started to click together for me. That is how a new unholy frankenstein of vibe coding and crypto is born. This is how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fame hungry tech bro vibe codes (prompts) an unholy blob of “software”. To do that he does initial investment of several thousand dollars into AI tokens.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Since the product is a monstrosity and it can not be commercialized it does not sell and probably does not generate fame either&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A tech person is approached by crypto bros and is offered a stake in some shitcoin. The deal is accepted because developer does not want to be holding the ‘bags’ for his initial investent in AI software pump&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Crypto scammers and bots hype and astroturf the new project in all possible platforms to raise awareness of the project and associated COIN&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unsuspecting software developers start actually trying out this new software tool and help to amplify the promotion message (because of the FOMO happening in tech space due to rapid evolution of AI tools).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;After a few months the software dump happens. The coin is dumped on the market and every developer moves on to the next shiny software thing.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The author kills the project because it is an unmaintainable mountain of code that could be only further developed with AI tools, but that does not come cheap.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few days ago I started being bombarded with hype posts about Clawdbot. I sincerely believe this is another instance of software “pump and dump”. Today after opening Linkedin the first three posts are #lookingforwork CTOs hyping Clawdbot as the next big thing. After taking a quick look at the project I have concluded that it is an unsecure mess and a vibecoded software blob that will be forgotten in a few months (or acquired by AI-rabid corporation if they get lucky!). What is important is that CLAWD coin tokens are kicking off right now and people are being lured into buying them as the hype grows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So please look at these projects with a critical mindset. Keep in mind that many posts hyping them could be paid astroturfing by crypto and don’t fall for the vibe coded software FOMO hype. Otherwise you might be the one holding the bags in the end!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://tautvilas.medium.com/software-pump-and-dump-c8a9a73d313b"/><published>2026-01-27T14:05:48+00:00</published></entry></feed>