<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:44.632970+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45960852</id><title>Unofficial "Tier 4" Rust Target for older Windows versions</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:55.127214+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ac60d61a319bb854"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the main source code repository for Rust. It contains the compiler, standard library, and documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Performance: Fast and memory-efficient, suitable for critical services, embedded devices, and easily integrated with other languages.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Reliability: Our rich type system and ownership model ensure memory and thread safety, reducing bugs at compile-time.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Productivity: Comprehensive documentation, a compiler committed to providing great diagnostics, and advanced tooling including package manager and build tool (Cargo), auto-formatter (rustfmt), linter (Clippy) and editor support (rust-analyzer).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read "Installation" from The Book.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you really want to install from source (though this is not recommended), see INSTALL.md.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See https://www.rust-lang.org/community for a list of chat platforms and forums.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See CONTRIBUTING.md.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rust is primarily distributed under the terms of both the MIT license and the Apache License (Version 2.0), with portions covered by various BSD-like licenses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See LICENSE-APACHE, LICENSE-MIT, and COPYRIGHT for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Rust Foundation owns and protects the Rust and Cargo trademarks and logos (the "Rust Trademarks").&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to use these names or brands, please read the media guide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Third-party logos may be subject to third-party copyrights and trademarks. See Licenses for details.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/rust9x/rust"/><published>2025-11-18T02:46:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45961481</id><title>The surprising benefits of giving up</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:55.041125+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="37f482b945538782"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might’ve been told to “hang in there” throughout your childhood, as illustrated by a kitten dangling from a rope. But it turns out that quitting might often be your healthiest option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers have long sought to understand how persistence is linked to personal well-being and human evolution more broadly. One poorly supported theory posited that our ancestors were so determined to catch prey that they ran for long stretches in hot, dry environments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Newer evidence suggests that ditching tough-to-attain goals can actually be good for us. According to a review of more than 230 studies recently published in the journal Nature Human Behaviour, adjusting our goals in response to stress or challenges, rather than grinding on, is often “a more appropriate and beneficial response.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The authors of the sweeping meta-analysis examined 235 studies spanning various fields, including psychology, health, and social sciences, that detailed how people shift their goals after encountering obstacles to success. The researchers wanted to consolidate this “fragmented” information and observe how adjusting goals relates not only to psychological well-being but also physical health, social functioning, and future ambitions. This allowed them to chart a goal “roadmap.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read more: “We Can Be Heroes”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Sticking with impossible goals can take a real toll, with previous research suggesting it can lead to higher stress, poorer well-being, and even physical health costs such as illness,” said study author Hugh Riddell, a professor at the School of Population Health at Curtin University in Australia, in a statement. “But letting go and—crucially—reengaging with new goals, was found to restore purpose and well-being.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The team employed statistical analysis to illuminate what causes people to ditch, adjust, or re-engage with goals. Disengagement from goals, for example, was most strongly linked to negative feedback on these ideas and an “action crisis” stemming from one’s failure to overcome related obstacles. Our personalities might also play a major role in these types of decisions: Optimism tended to be strongly linked to one’s openness to revise a goal to better fit their skills and resources. “These findings indicate that goal-striving flexibility is more likely to emerge when individuals feel secure, exhibit stable regulation, and possess emotional resilience,” the paper notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scientists also analyzed the impacts of these decisions. Giving up on goals was significantly linked to reduced stress, anxiety, and depression, for instance. And adopting new ones was strongly associated with high social and physical functioning. Finding new goals also came with moderate to large benefits to psychological functioning, feeling a sense of purpose in life, satisfaction, and personal growth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This analysis comes with limitations, the authors acknowledge, due to observational data collected at specific points in time and risks of bias in individual papers. The next step, they write, is to pinpoint the specific moment that people should rethink their dreams or keep on chugging. “Finding out when exactly people should stick with their goals or change course, without giving up too early, is really the next piece of the puzzle,” Riddell said in the statement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So whether you’re the type to stick with it to the bitter end or change course when you sense trouble up ahead, there may be an optimal method to help you achieve—or alter—your goals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enjoying Nautilus? Subscribe to our free newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lead image: eamesBot / Shutterstock&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nautil.us/the-surprising-benefits-of-giving-up-1248362/"/><published>2025-11-18T04:44:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45962178</id><title>Langfuse (YC W23) Hiring OSS Support Engineers in Berlin and SF</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:54.856749+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e10fcdab2cdf53e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need to enable JavaScript to run this app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/langfuse/5ff18d4d-9066-4c67-8ecc-ffc0e295fee6"/><published>2025-11-18T07:00:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45962654</id><title>How Quake.exe got its TCP/IP stack</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:54.350623+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2eea993caa203e87"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Released in June 1996, Quake had to ride three technological shock-waves during its lifetime. Besides the emergence of 3D hardware accelerator cards and the growth of the Internet, an operating system shift put game developers in a tough position.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With its push for Windows 95 and Windows NT, Microsoft was replacing its legacy PC operating system, MS-DOS. From 1996 to 1997, the market share of DOS dropped by 50%. Some developers, like Blizzard North, took the leap of faith and wrote Windows 95–exclusive titles such as Diablo. id Software on the other hand went through the effort of producing a single binary, &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt;, able to run on both DOS and Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is even more impressive is that id managed to make Quake better when Windows 95 TCP/IP stack was available. Here is how they did it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; is a DOS executable. id Software had used &lt;code&gt;Watcom&lt;/code&gt; compiler for DOOM but they switched to a GCC port named &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt;[1] to cross-compile Quake on Alpha servers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ file quake.exe quake.exe: MS-DOS executable, COFF for MS-DOS, DJGPP go32 DOS extender&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alike &lt;code&gt;watcom&lt;/code&gt;'s &lt;code&gt;DOS/4GW&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt; offered to developers an extender allowing to write programs with flat 32-bit addressing instead of the dreaded 16-bit near/far hellish real-mode otherwise mandated by DOS. An extender works with a client and a server. In the case of Quake the extender client is embedded in &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; while the server is in &lt;code&gt;cwsdpmi.exe&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the beginning of the development, id had requested from &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt; engineers that their DPMI client would be able to run on &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt;'s DPMI server but also Windows 95 DPMI server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It may not be apparent how much of a tour-de-force it was for &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt; to make their DPMI client work with another DPMI server but knowing a little about how it works, it blows me away. Raymond Chen, Microsoft kernel engineer at the time, had the best description of how to perceive this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;The client application was written with the assumption that it is using the MS-DOS extender that is included with the application, but in reality it is talking to the DPMI host that comes with Windows.&lt;lb/&gt;The fact that programs seem to run mostly okay in spite of running under a foreign extender is either completely astonishing or totally obvious, depending on your point of view.&lt;lb/&gt;It’s completely astonishing because, well, you’re taking a program written to be run in one environment, and running it in a different environment. Or it’s totally obvious because they are using the same DPMI interface, and as long as the interface has the same behavior, then naturally the program will continue to work, because that’s why we have interfaces!&lt;lb/&gt;- Raymond Chen[2]&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being able to run with Windows 95 DPMI server was how &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; pulled off the ability to run under both DOS and Windows 95.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DOOM only needed two files to run, &lt;code&gt;doom.exe&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;doom.wad&lt;/code&gt; but there are many files that came with Quake.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ find quake ./mgenvxd.vxd ./genvxd.dll ./qlaunch.exe ./id1/pak0.pak ./pdipx.com ./cwsdpmi.exe ./q95.bat ./id1/config.cfg ./quake.exe ./quakeudp.dll&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It looks like a mess at first sight but running Quake under DOS only requires four files. Namely, the game engine &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt;, the config file &lt;code&gt;config.cfg&lt;/code&gt;, the asset file &lt;code&gt;pak0.pak&lt;/code&gt;, and the DOS extender server &lt;code&gt;cwsdpmi.exe&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;./mgenvxd.vxd ./genvxd.dll ./qlaunch.exe ./id1/pak0.pak ./pdipx.com ./cwsdpmi.exe ./q95.bat ./id1/config.cfg ./quake.exe ./quakeudp.dll&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quake supported four types of multiplayer protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two modes allowed gamers to enter a duel (1v1). Both modes expected a device plugged into the COM port of the PC. A modem allowed to call an opponent's phone number (hello $$$) while a NullModem cable (called here "Direct Connect") required both computers to be a few feet apart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both IPX and TCP/IP allowed a much more interesting deathmatch featuring up to 16 players. IPX technology was intended for LAN where all machines were a few feet apart, while TCP/IP allowed to reach anybody worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice how, under DOS, by default, both IPX and TCP modes were disabled (greyed out).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quake came with PDIPX.EXE which loaded an IPX DOS TSR. That TSR communicated with a packet driver which in turn hit the network card. Quake was able to probe for that DOS TSR and upon detection allowed players to select IPX.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using TCP/IP was nearly impossible. DOS did not come with a TCP/IP stack and it was something complex enough that only a single vendor provided a TSR for it on DOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The TSR name was BWNFS. Made by Beame &amp;amp; Whiteside, its cost $395 in 1996 ($830 in 2025!)[3]. It is reasonable to say that few gamers ever used TCP/IP on DOS to play QUAKE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; from Windows 95 works like a charm. The executable is loaded into a Windows 95 "dos-box"[4] that virtualizes memory, interrupts, and signals[5]. The game ran exactly like under DOS with the same multiplayer choices available. It was convenient since users did not have to load any mouse driver or set up the &lt;code&gt;BLASTER&lt;/code&gt; environment variable to make the sound card work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Much less convenient however, this way to run Quake requires 16 MiB RAM. Quake only needs 8 MiB but Windows 95 adds quite a bit of overhead! The same files used when running from DOS are used here as well, except for &lt;code&gt;cwsdpmi.exe&lt;/code&gt;, since the DJGPP client detects and uses Windows’ built-in DPMI server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;./mgenvxd.vxd ./genvxd.dll ./qlaunch.exe ./id1/pak0.pak ./pdipx.com ./cwsdpmi.exe ./q95.bat ./id1/config.cfg ./quake.exe ./quakeudp.dll&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is impressive to see Quake run at full speed knowing that Windows 95 runs DOS executable in a virtual machine. My guess is that, in full screen, memory writes and reads to the VGA are given direct access to the hardware to preserve performances.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; from DOS or Windows are not the only two options to run Quake. There is a third one which is to launch &lt;code&gt;q95.bat&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case, a window "Launching Quake" briefly pops up on Windows 95 desktop.&lt;lb/&gt; The text gives a clue about what is happening. Quake is loaded with a tunnel to Winsock, Microsoft's TCP/IP stack. There is further indication of what is doing that, "Powered by Mpath". But not much more to explain how this all works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mpath Interactive was a company dedicated to online gaming. They provided subscription services to help gamers find each other but also operated as an ISP reseller.[6]. It was in their interest to help gaming companies to release titles allowing Internet play as Larry Hastings, an Mpath employee at the time, recalls.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Back then in the primordial ooze that was the mid-90s internet, online multiplayer was still in its infancy. If you wanted to play a multiplayer game on the internet, either you needed to have explicit host &amp;amp; port information, or you needed to use an online multiplayer gaming service. And in 1995 there were only two: us, and Total Entertainment Network. You might think game creators would come to us and say "please put my game on your service!", but... nope! Not only did we have a licensing team that went out and got contracts to license games for our service, but we had to pay the vendor for the right to license their game, which was often an exclusive. So, we had Quake and Unreal; TEN got Duke Nukem 3D and NASCAR.&lt;lb/&gt;The user experience for Mplayer was like this. First, you'd run the "Gizmo", which was a Windows program that acted as a sort of game browser. It knew which compatible games you had installed, and it'd let you browse the multiplayer games on offer for each game; the metaphor we used for this was a "room". Quake was drop-in, so you could simply find a game in progress and hop right in--not a feature of very many games back then. Alternatively, you could find a "room" where someone was proposing to launch a game soon. Or you could create your own. You'd set the name of the room, and the Mplayer Gizmo had some per-game UI that let you set the settings for the game (what map, what features, etc). The room featured text and audio chat, and even a shared "whiteboard", a simple paint program. Once the owner of the "room" "launched" the game, everyone's Gizmos would automatically start the game for them, and the game would automatically join that online game and start playing.&lt;lb/&gt;In order for a game to run on Mplayer, it had to integrate with the Mplayer software stack. Mostly this integration work was done by Mpath engineers; we'd get source code from the game developer and "porting engineers" would get it to run on Mplayer. This often included modifying both the client and the server, so that both could talk via Mplayer's servers.&lt;lb/&gt;The early version of Quake was DOS only, and used the Chunnel to talk to the Windows 95 TCP/IP stack. (Which in retrospect makes the "Chunnel" a type of "thunk", like Microsoft's "Win32s".) I think the deal was, we licensed the Chunnel to id, and in return for that we got to have Quake on Mplayer. So, DOS Quake supported running on Mplayer via the Chunnel, in addition to connecting to open game servers on the Internet via host and port.&lt;lb/&gt;- Larry Hastings (Email conversation)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Larry was kind enough to share some Quake anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;One afternoon shortly after we got our first build of the game, we played a round of deathmatch with the id team over the internet. We were in Cupertino, CA, in a building on Bandley Drive (now a "Fitness Center" for Apple employees). They of course were in Mesquite TX. Yup, it was deathmatch over the internet--very exciting!&lt;lb/&gt;The only id employee I remember for sure being in the game was Tim Willits. He owned us, both because he was way more used to Quake, but also because he knew where all the secrets were. At one point I spotted him coming out of a secret doorway with a rocket launcher. And either he didn't see me, or I died shortly thereafter.&lt;lb/&gt;- Larry Hastings (Email conversation)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As for explaining how the Chunnel worked, I was out of luck.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;I didn't work on the Chunnel. That was mainly a British guy named Henry but I don't remember his last name, it was thirty years ago. All I remember about him is what he looked like, and the fact that he drove a cool car, a white Merkur XR4Ti.&lt;lb/&gt;- Larry Hastings (Email conversation)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When everything else fails, we still have Ghidra and doomworld's amazing community (thanks xttl[7]). After much decompiling and talking, it turned out all files previously ignored were part of Mpath's "Chunnel".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;./mgenvxd.vxd ./genvxd.dll ./qlaunch.exe ./id1/pak0.pak ./pdipx.com ./cwsdpmi.exe ./q95.bat ./id1/config.cfg ./quake.exe ./quakeudp.dll&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;q95.bat&lt;/code&gt; is just a small script to launch mpath's main program. &lt;code&gt;qlauncher.exe&lt;/code&gt; contains all the MPlayer functions. However the role of this executable is limited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It merely loads &lt;code&gt;quakeudp.dll&lt;/code&gt;. Despite its confusing name, this DLL is the heart of Quake Chunnel. It is the bridge to Microsoft TCP/UDP/IP stack (&lt;code&gt;wsock32.dll&lt;/code&gt;). It also starts Quake with &lt;code&gt;-path&lt;/code&gt; parameter to make it load a BSD network socket API &lt;code&gt;sys/socket.h&lt;/code&gt;. Finally, it also loads the virtual device driver manager &lt;code&gt;genvxd.dll&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The virtual device is the trick that allows a DOS executable running inside a Windows 95 dos box to communicate with win32. The &lt;code&gt;genvxd.dll&lt;/code&gt; dynamic library loads a virtual device driver[8] named &lt;code&gt;GENVXD.VXD&lt;/code&gt; which installs itself to respond on interrupt &lt;code&gt;0x48&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last piece of the puzzle is on Quake side. The implementation of BSD &lt;code&gt;sys/socket.h&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mpplc.c&lt;/code&gt;, is code provided by Mpath. It takes care of marshaling every BSD socket function call, then use the DPMI client to trigger a software interrupt that is received in win32 land. Data is passed up the pipeline we previously described until it is unmarshalled by &lt;code&gt;genvxd.dll&lt;/code&gt; and routed towards &lt;code&gt;wsock32.dll&lt;/code&gt;. Notice the symmetry of functions found in &lt;code&gt;mplib.c&lt;/code&gt; marshalling and the symbols found in &lt;code&gt;genvxd.dll&lt;/code&gt; unmarshalling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems John Cash was involved in compiling Mpath's stuff. We can find his name in the symbols of &lt;code&gt;mgenvxd.vxd&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;F:\cashcode\GENVXD\bin\Mgenvxd.pdb&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The source code of mgenvxd.vxd, genvxd.dll, qlaunch.exe and quakeudp.dll was never released. It was a proprietary, patented technology from Mpath. It is likely id only got permission to release the client side of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as I understood it, that is how Quake was able to send TCP and UDP packets over IP. This convoluted construct became obsolete when id stopped shipping DOS executable (the last one being &lt;code&gt;vquake.exe&lt;/code&gt;). After Dec 1996, &lt;code&gt;winquake.exe&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;glquake.exe&lt;/code&gt;, and all QuakeWorld binaries were win32 exclusive with direct access to &lt;code&gt;wsock32.dll&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://fabiensanglard.net/quake_chunnel/index.html"/><published>2025-11-18T08:18:35+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45963583</id><title>The Miracle of Wörgl</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:53.011301+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2681901966d72d90"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Story of Wörgl and others&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Miracle of Wörgl&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wörgl was the first in town in Austria that effectively managed to eliminate the extreme unemployment caused by the Great Depression. Its local currency experiment was such a success that it gained worldwide attention. That effort became known as the “Miracle of Wörgl .” For the full details, go here. Here is the summary of that story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On July 5th 1932, in the middle of the Great Depression, the Austrian town of Wörgl made economic history by introducing a remarkable complimentary currency. Wörgl was in trouble, and was prepared to try anything. Of its population of 4,500, a total of 1,500 people were without a job, and 200 families were penniless. The mayor, Michael Unterguggenberger, had a long list of projects he wanted to accomplish, but there was hardly any money with which to carry them out. These included repaving the roads, streetlights, extending water distribution across the whole town, and planting trees along the streets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rather than spending the 40,000 Austrian schillings in the town’s coffers to start these projects off, he deposited them in a local savings bank as a guarantee to back the issue of a type of complimentary currency known as ‘stamp scrip’. The Mayor then proceeded to hire people to do infrastructure projects for the town and the community quickly went from an unemployment rate of over 30% to near zero, as that money began to circulate very rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of all the business in town, only the railway station and the post office refused to accept the local money. When people ran out of spending ideas, they would pay their taxes early using scrip, resulting in a huge increase in town revenues. Over the 13-month period the project ran, the council not only carried out all the intended works projects, but also built new houses, a reservoir, a ski jump, and a bridge. The people also used scrip to replant forests, in anticipation of the future cash flow they would receive from the trees.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Six neighbouring villages copied the system successfully. The French Prime Minister, Eduoard Dalladier, made a special visit to see the ‘miracle of Wörgl’. In January 1933, the project was replicated in the neighbouring city of Kirchbuhl, and in June 1933, Unterguggenburger addressed a meeting with representatives from 170 different towns and villages. Two hundred Austrian townships were interested in adopting the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, the central bank panicked, and decided to assert its monopoly rights by banning complimentary currencies. The people unsuccessfully sued the bank, and later lost in the Austrian Supreme Court. It then became a criminal offence to issue ’emergency currency’. The town went back to 30% unemployment. In 1934, social unrest exploded across Austria. In 1938, when Hitler annexed Austria, he was welcomed by many people as their economic and political saviour.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the success of Wörgl attracted the attention of one of the leading economists in the U.S. at the time, Professor Irving Fisher, who informed the FDR administration he thought that idea could be used to end the Great Depression. That story is next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Irving Fisher, the Great Depression and FDR&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Professor Irving Fisher learned of the success of Wörgl and other European experiments, he determined that “The correct application of stamp scrip would solve the Depression crisis in the U.S. in three weeks.” He presented his findings to Dean Acheson, then under-secretary of the Treasury under FDR. Acheson sought input from Harvard economics professor Russell Sprague, who told him that this approach could indeed succeed in bringing America out of the Depression, but cautioned him to check with the President.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He did so. Unfortunately, fearing decentralization, President Roosevelt denounced complementary currencies soon afterwards and they were prohibited. He did so in probably his most famous address, the one including the phrase “The only thing we need to fear is fear itself.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In that speech he also announced that by “executive decree” he would henceforth prohibit ‘emergency currencies’. This was the code name for all the complementary currencies already in existence, and all those in preparation around the country. That prohibition lasted for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Imagine if Fisher’s recommendation had held the day. The Great Depression would have ended well before World War II and a great deal of suffering would have been avoided. Fortunately, complementary currencies are now legal in just about every country, as evidenced by the popularity of cryptocurrencies, one form of a complementary currency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Central Middle Ages and Cathedrals&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We now come to one of the most prolonged and significant times where the use of complementary currencies had a profound and widespread positive impact on the communities that adopted them. Here we find a sustained period of 250 years (1040-1290) of financial success based on local currencies spread throughout Western Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chapter 6 from the book, New Money for a New World by Bernard Lietaer (co-architect of the Euro) and Stephen Belgin details that period of widespread abundance throughout Western Europe that can be directly attributed to the extensive use of local currencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The authors note that, “There was work for all, with favorable working conditions and abundant time for family, community, and personal pursuits. This epoch was also characterized by significant advancements in science, technology, education, literature, music, arts, craftsmanship, and more.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It all commenced when communities like Paris decided they wanted to build a local cathedral like Notre Dame, each a massive infrastructure project that lasted on average between 50 and 100 years. Those communities printed their own money and hired architects, stone masons, carpenters, lead workers, glass workers and more to build those magnificent edifices and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What most people don’t know is that those citizens were directly responsible for building more than 1,000 cathedrals in Western Europe, alongside 350,000 churches and several thousand large abbeys. That means over 1,000 European communities adopted their own complementary currency program, yielding a building phase rarely matched throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Month after month those communities paid those workers “new money” they printed up which in turn was injected into the local economy. That money was spent on food, clothing, shelter and all the necessities of life, which stimulated all manner of new local merchants and the jobs they produced.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This medieval building phenomenon is more remarkable still,” say the authors, “given that there was no central authority, church or otherwise, in charge of initiating or funding the construction of these cathedrals. Contrary to popular belief today, these structures were neither built by nor belonged to the church or nobility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Local nobility and royalty customarily did make contributions, but these monuments were typically owned and financed by the citizens of the municipalities where they were built.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those efforts initiated over 800 years ago are still providing financial returns today. Tourists flock to those cathedrals bringing with them money that they leave in the communities they visit. Almost nothing in history has provided a greater return on investment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More examples&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See this document, Complementary Currencies in Use for more examples of complementary currencies and the positive impact they had on the communities that adopted them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://scf.green/story-of-worgl-and-others/"/><published>2025-11-18T10:59:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45963780</id><title>Cloudflare Global Network experiencing issues</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:52.229458+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e73fa6963d75d83"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Ahmedabad, India - (AMD) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Almaty, Kazakhstan - (ALA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Bangalore, India - (BLR) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Bangkok, Thailand - (BKK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Bandar Seri Begawan, Brunei - (BWN) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Cebu, Philippines - (CEB) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chandigarh, India - (IXC) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Changde, China - (CGD) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chennai, India - (MAA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chittagong, Bangladesh - (CGP) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Colombo, Sri Lanka - (CMB) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Dhaka, Bangladesh - (DAC) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Foshan, China - (FUO) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Fukuoka, Japan - (FUK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Fuzhou, China - (FOC) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Guangzhou, China - (CAN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Haikou, China - (HAK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Hanoi, Vietnam - (HAN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Hengshui, China - (SJW) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam - (SGN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Hong Kong - (HKG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Hyderabad, India - (HYD) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Islamabad, Pakistan - (ISB) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Jakarta, Indonesia - (CGK) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Jinan, China - (TNA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Johor Bahru, Malaysia - (JHB) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kanpur, India - (KNU) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kaohsiung City, Taiwan - (KHH) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Karachi, Pakistan - (KHI) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kathmandu, Nepal - (KTM) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kolkata, India - (CCU) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Krasnoyarsk, Russia - (KJA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia - (KUL) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Langfang, China - (PKX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Macau - (MFM) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Malé, Maldives - (MLE) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Manila, Philippines - (MNL) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Mumbai, India - (BOM) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Nagpur, India - (NAG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Naha, Japan - (OKA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; New Delhi, India - (DEL) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Osaka, Japan - (KIX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Patna, India - (PAT) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Phnom Penh, Cambodia - (PNH) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Qingdao, China - (TAO) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Seoul, South Korea - (ICN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Shanghai, China - (SHA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Singapore, Singapore - (SIN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Surat Thani, Thailand - (URT) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Taipei - (TPE) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Tokyo, Japan - (NRT) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Ulaanbaatar, Mongolia - (ULN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Vientiane, Laos - (VTE) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Xinyu, China - (KHN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Yerevan, Armenia - (EVN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Yogyakarta, Indonesia - (JOG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Cagayan de Oro, Philippines - (CGY) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kochi, India - (COK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Denpasar, Indonesia - (DPS) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kannur, India - (CNN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Shenzhen, China - (SZX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Guiyang, China - (KWE) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Shaoxing, China - (HGH) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Changzhou, China - (CZX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kunming, China - (KMG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chiang Mai, Thailand - (CNX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Zhengzhou, China - (CGO) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Yangquan, China - (TYN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Changsha, China - (CSX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Dalian, China - (DLC) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Beihai, China - (BHY) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chongqing, China - (CKG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Xiangyang, China - (XFN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Da Nang, Vietnam - (DAD) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Jiaxing, China - (JXG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Tarlac City, Philippines - (CRK) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Thimphu, Bhutan - (PBH) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Baoji, China - (XIY) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Astana, Kazakhstan - (NQZ) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Nanning, China - (NNG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Zibo, China - (TNA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kuching, Malaysia - (KCH) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Aktobe, Kazakhstan - (AKX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chengmai, China - (HAK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Nanchang, China - (KHN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Male, Maldives - (MLE) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Tongren, China - (TEN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Taizhou, China - (HYN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Shijiazhuang, China - (SJW) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Xining, China - (XNN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan - (FRU) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Malang, Indonesia - (MLG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.cloudflarestatus.com/?t=1"/><published>2025-11-18T11:35:10+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45963836</id><title>Gemini 3 Pro Model Card</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:51.855612+00:00</updated><link href="https://pixeldrain.com/u/hwgaNKeH"/><published>2025-11-18T11:40:01+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45964816</id><title>Mathematics and Computation (2019) [pdf]</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:49.741291+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.math.ias.edu/files/Book-online-Aug0619.pdf"/><published>2025-11-18T12:35:13+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45964835</id><title>GoSign Desktop RCE flaws affecting users in Italy</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:48.655568+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="359ee30e981be4d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pasquale "sid" Fiorillo discovered a critical vulnerability in GoSign Desktop &amp;lt;= 2.4.0 that allows an attacker to execute arbitrary code on the system through insecure updates and a TLS bypass. The exploit leverages the deactivation of TLS certificate verification when a proxy is configured, together with an update mechanism based on unsigned manifests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vendor, Tinexta InfoCert, initially cooperative, ceased all communication after receiving the technical details, ignoring follow?up requests and releasing version 2.4.1 without any public notice or acknowledgment of the researchers. Due to this opaque behavior, which does not align with responsible disclosure best practices, a forced disclosure was carried out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Multiple Vulnerabilities in GoSign Desktop leads to Remote Code Execution Name TLS Verification Bypass and Insecure Update in GoSign Desktop Systems Affected GoSign Desktop &amp;lt;= 2.4.0 Severity High 8.2/10 Impact CVSS:3.1/AV:L/AC:L/PR:L/UI:R/S:C/C:H/I:H/A:H Vendor https://www.infocert.it/ Advisory https://www.ush.it/team/ush/hack-gosign-desktop_240/gosign-desktop-exec.txt Authors Pasquale "sid" Fiorillo (sid AT ush DOT it) Francesco "ascii" Ongaro (ascii AT ush DOT it) Marco Lunardi Date 20251003 I. BACKGROUND GoSign is an advanced and qualified electronic signature solution developed by Tinexta InfoCert S.p.A., used by public administrations, businesses, and professionals to manage approval workflows with traceability and security. The SaaS/web version of the product has received the "QC2" qualification from the Italian National Cybersecurity Agency (ACN). The QC2 qualification certifies a service's ability to securely handle critical data, including data processed by public administrations. Under ACN's regulation effective from August 1, 2024, cloud service providers for public entities must meet strict security and resilience requirements. This qualification enables public administrations to adopt certified solutions for safeguarding sensitive data and ensuring continuity of essential services. GoSign Desktop, subject of this advisory, is the on-premise version released for Microsoft Windows, Linux Ubuntu, and Apple macOS. II. DESCRIPTION We have identified a critical vulnerability in the GoSign Desktop software, developed by Tinexta InfoCert. The platform is widely used for signing, verifying, and managing electronic documents. In 2021 alone, it was used by 1.6 million people to perform over 830 million signing transactions, confirming its central role in the Italian and European digital ecosystem. GoSign Desktop disables TLS certificate validation (`SSL_VERIFY_NONE`) in the `libdgsapi.so` and `libcurl.so` modules when configured to use a proxy server, removing any assurance regarding server identity during encrypted communications. This compromises the security of TLS connections and opens the door to Man-in-the-Middle (MitM) attacks. Additionally, the update mechanism relies on an unsigned manifest, meaning security depends entirely on the TLS layer. We verified three attack scenarios that severely impact the security of GoSign Desktop users: Malicious software installation (Critical): A network attacker can deceive the client into installing fake updates, taking control of the machine with the privileges of the user running GoSign Desktop (Windows, macOS) or with administrative privileges (Linux). Credential theft (High): Access information (tokens, temporary passwords) can be intercepted because the application does not verify the server's identity. Privilege escalation (High): A local attacker with the same privileges as the GoSign Desktop user can enable proxy settings and inject a malicious update to gain full control of the system (Linux). III. ANALYSIS 1) TLS verification bypass The `GoSignDesktop` process, through `libdgsapi.so` and `libcurl.so`, disables TLS certificate verification by invoking `SSL_CTX_set_verify(mode=SSL_VERIFY_NONE)` when configured to use a proxy server. This setting completely disables certificate validation during the TLS handshake, effectively nullifying the authenticity and confidentiality guarantees of the TLS channel. As a result, a remote attacker can perform Man-in-the-Middle (MitM) attacks to intercept and manipulate traffic. Neither the authenticity of the InfoCert server nor the proxy server is verified. The vulnerability was confirmed in methods related to update checks (`UpdateManager::get_manifest`, `UpdateManager::check_and_download`) and OAuth renewal and authentication operations (`ISACBinder::refresh` and `UpdateManager::getIdentity`). However, it is plausible that any request originating from `libdgsapi.so` is affected by the same certificate validation issue. Tested and vulnerable versions due to lack of TLS certificate validation: - GoSign Desktop 2.4.0 (standard) Windows - GoSign Desktop 2.4.0 (standard) Linux The vendor confirms that the macOS version is also affected: - GoSign Desktop 2.4.0 (standard) macOS 1.1) Insecure Update The GoSign Desktop update mechanism relies on an unsigned manifest containing the package URL and its SHA-256 hash. A MitM attacker can provide a malicious manifest with a matching hash, tricking the client into downloading and installing a tampered package, resulting in remote code execution. Effectively, the update manifest's authentication is entirely delegated to the TLS layer, which is not validated-thus rendering all authenticity guarantees ineffective. This architecture is conceptually flawed: since the manifest is not digitally signed, it protects at most against accidental integrity issues (e.g., corrupted files) but offers no defense against active attacks. Without valid TLS and manifest signing, an attacker can replace both the package and its hash, fully bypassing the security mechanism. Instead of adopting established solutions for secure software distribution, a custom mechanism was implemented that reintroduces well-known, extensively documented risks. This design choice was avoidable given the availability of reliable, industry-standard approaches that would have ensured update integrity and authenticity. 1.2) Verified Security Impacts We have confirmed three concrete attack scenarios that severely compromise the security of GoSign Desktop: - OAuth Secrets Information Disclosure - Remote Code Execution - Privilege Escalation It is likely that additional attack vectors exist but have not yet been identified. Given the severity of the confirmed impacts, we immediately alerted the relevant authorities (ACN/CSIRT Italia) to ensure responsible and timely incident handling. 1.3) CVSS 3.1 CVSS Base Score: 8.2 CVSS Vector: AV:L/AC:L/PR:L/UI:R/S:C/C:H/I:H/A:H 1.4) CWE Mappings CWE-295: Improper Certificate Validation - use of SSL_VERIFY_NONE / disabled TLS verification CWE-347: Improper Verification of Cryptographic Signature - absence of signature validation on manifests/metadata CWE-200: Exposure of Sensitive Information to an Unauthorized Actor - OAuth secrets exposed over an unverified channel 2) Attack scenarios 2.1) MitM In a typical Man-in-the-Middle (MitM) attack scenario, an attacker positioned to intercept network traffic can respond to TLS requests initiated by GoSign Desktop by presenting a self-signed certificate. Since GoSign Desktop disables certificate validation when configured to use a proxy, the client establishes the connection without verifying the server's identity. The attacker can thus intercept and read sensitive requests and responses-specifically, OAuth calls may disclose secrets such as client_secret, JWT tokens, or refresh tokens. Simultaneously, the attacker can respond to update requests by providing a tampered manifest that points to a compromised package and includes the SHA-256 hash of the malicious payload. Because the client has neither TLS verification enabled nor a digital signature on the manifest, it downloads the update and executes the attacker's code with administrative (root) privileges if running on Linux, or with the privileges of the user running GoSign on Windows or macOS. 2.2) Privilege Escalation A second exploitation vector involves the preliminary compromise of the unprivileged user account running GoSign Desktop. A local attacker can independently modify the HTTP-PROXY settings in the configuration file ~/.gosign/dike.conf, causing the client to download a malicious update and thereby escalate privileges to root. Proof of Concept Video: https://www.ush.it/team/ush/hack-gosign-desktop_240/gosigndesktop_mitm_poc.mp4 Proof of Concept Exploit: https://www.ush.it/team/ush/hack-gosign-desktop_240/ IV. WORKAROUND Fix in GoSign Desktop 2.4.1 In version 2.4.1 of GoSign Desktop, released on 2025-11-04, a fix was introduced to verify the digital signature of the update manifest. However, the lack of TLS certificate validation when the application is configured to use a proxy remains unaddressed. - Information Disclosure of OAuth secrets â€“ NOT FIXED - Remote Code Execution â€“ FIXED - Privilege Escalation â€“ FIXED VI. VENDOR RESPONSE Handling of Responsible Disclosure by Vendor Tinexta InfoCert Following the initial contact, the vendor was provided with all technical details of the vulnerability, the Proof of Concept (PoC), and mitigation suggestions-both via encrypted email and during a Teams call requested by the vendor and held on 2025-10-16 at 15:00. Present at the call were the InfoCert security officer and the product manager for GoSign Desktop. During the call, the vendor confirmed the vulnerability and agreed that October 31, 2025, was a reasonable deadline for releasing a fix. After this call, the vendor ceased all communication, failed to provide any further updates, and did not respond to subsequent contact attempts. On 2025-11-04, the fix was released publicly without any announcement from the vendor and without honoring the request to include a changelog acknowledgment. ACN/CSIRT Italia was notified about the vendor's improper handling of responsible disclosure best practices. VII. CVE INFORMATION Mitre is unresponsive. VIII. DISCLOSURE TIMELINE 2025-10-03: Vulnerability discovered 2025-10-04: Proof of Concept developed 2025-10-04: Initial contact attempt to InfoCert S.p.A. 2025-10-04: Concurrent notification sent to ACN/CSIRT Italia 2025-10-04: Response from ACN/CSIRT Italia acknowledging receipt and awaiting further developments 2025-10-07: Response from InfoCert Cyber Security Operation 2025-10-07: Technical details and evidence shared with the vendor 2025-10-09: InfoCert acknowledges the report and states the issue is under investigation 2025-10-16: Technical call with InfoCert; vulnerability confirmed; over 1 million users affected. Full technical details and remediation suggestions shared during the call 2025-10-26: Follow-up request for update sent to vendor; no response received 2025-11-04: Version 2.4.1 released; no communication or changelog from the vendor 2025-11-08: Further request for explanation and update sent to the vendor; no response 2025-11-14: Report submitted to ACN/CSIRT Italia regarding vendor's mishandling of disclosure process 2025-11-14: Advisory published IX. TECHNICAL DETAILS Collected evidence indicates that the disabling of TLS certificate verification is not an isolated anomaly: the `SSL_VERIFY_NONE` behavior is systematically applied during the initialization of TLS connections by GoSign Desktop when the proxy setting is enabled. To demonstrate this, a dynamic runtime instrumentation approach was used, intercepting OpenSSL APIs responsible for certificate verification configuration. The findings confirm that the application's default behavior sets the `SSL_VERIFY_NONE` flag and that certificate checks are explicitly disabled. In its current configuration, GoSign effectively functions as a backdoor installed on a vast number of systems used by major public administrations, ministries, and Italian enterprises. To observe this behavior at runtime, a hook library (LD_PRELOAD) was developed to intercept calls to `SSL_CTX_set_verify()` and `SSL_set_verify()` functions exported by the cryptographic libraries. --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- /* gcc -shared -fPIC -o log_ssl_verify.so log_ssl_verify.c -ldl -rdynamic */ #define _GNU_SOURCE #include &amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt; #include &amp;lt;dlfcn.h&amp;gt; #include &amp;lt;stdlib.h&amp;gt; #include &amp;lt;execinfo.h&amp;gt; #include &amp;lt;stdint.h&amp;gt; typedef void (*ssl_ctx_set_verify_t)(void*, int, void*); typedef void (*ssl_set_verify_t)(void*, int); static ssl_ctx_set_verify_t real_SSL_CTX_set_verify = NULL; static ssl_set_verify_t real_SSL_set_verify = NULL; static void dump_backtrace(FILE *f) { void *buffer[50]; int nptrs = backtrace(buffer, 50); char **strings = backtrace_symbols(buffer, nptrs); if (strings != NULL) { for (int i = 0; i &amp;lt; nptrs; ++i) { fprintf(f, " %s\n", strings[i]); } free(strings); } else { fprintf(f, " &amp;lt;no backtrace available&amp;gt;\n"); } } void SSL_CTX_set_verify(void *ctx, int mode, void *cb) { if (!real_SSL_CTX_set_verify) { real_SSL_CTX_set_verify = (ssl_ctx_set_verify_t)dlsym(RTLD_NEXT, "SSL_CTX_set_verify"); } FILE *f = fopen("/tmp/gosign_ssl_verify.log", "a"); if (f) { fprintf(f, "PID %d: SSL_CTX_set_verify called with mode=%d\n", getpid(), mode); dump_backtrace(f); fclose(f); } if (real_SSL_CTX_set_verify) real_SSL_CTX_set_verify(ctx, mode, cb); } void SSL_set_verify(void *ssl, int mode) { if (!real_SSL_set_verify) { real_SSL_set_verify = (ssl_set_verify_t)dlsym(RTLD_NEXT, "SSL_set_verify"); } FILE *f = fopen("/tmp/gosign_ssl_verify.log", "a"); if (f) { fprintf(f, "PID %d: SSL_set_verify called with mode=%d\n", getpid(), mode); dump_backtrace(f); fclose(f); } if (real_SSL_set_verify) real_SSL_set_verify(ssl, mode); } --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- Process launch and log capture in `gosign_ssl_verify.log`: --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- export LD_PRELOAD=./log_ssl_verify.so /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop &amp;amp; disown --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- Startup log: --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- $ export LD_PRELOAD=./log_ssl_verify.so $ /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop &amp;amp; disown [1] 282062 $ Profile verified! Using @ffi-napi 2025-10-03 21:21:22.977 [info] info LoggerElectron initialized 2025-10-03 21:21:22.978 [info] Current log level: { verbose: false, defaultLogLevel: 'info' } 2025-10-03 21:21:23.191 [info] (main) homeDir is '/home/sid/.gosign' Creating certificate store: {"filename":"/home/sid/.gosign/certificates.db","autoload":true} Creating option store: {"filename":"/home/sid/.gosign/options.db","autoload":true} ~ Analytics ~ currentCustomization standard Native module: @ice/dike-core-linux x64 2025-10-03 21:21:23.200 [info] (DikeClients) Loading profile from: /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/current-customization/profile.jwt 2025-10-03 21:21:23.200 [info] (DikeClients) Homepath for core library is '/home/sid/.gosign' HOME_PATH: /home/sid/.gosign 2025-10-03 21:21:23.201 [warn] (DikeClients) LIBRARY PATH __dirname IS STILL BROKEN, PLEASE CHECK ISSUE ON GITHUB!!! https://github.com/electron/electron/issues/8206 2025-10-03 21:21:23.201 [info] (DikeClients) ======================= PRODUCTION ENV ======================= Native module: @ice/dike-core-linux x64 Profile verified! 2025:10:03 21:21:23 (0xfd27cd80)[INFO][dgs] (prepare_tempdir): Removing session dir /home/sid/.gosign/sessiondir_7cb271e1 Scheduler -&amp;gt; getMessages Registering channel get-version Registering channel jobs-channel Registering channel add-jobs-channel Registering channel test-pin Registering channel set-configuration Registering channel get-session-params Registering channel device-list Registering channel change-pin Registering channel unlock-pin Registering channel unlock-ce-pin [..] --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- Contents of `gosign_ssl_verify.log` showing evidence of `SSL_CTX_set_verify(mode=0)` and the corresponding backtrace: --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- PID 282062: SSL_CTX_set_verify called with mode=0 ./log_ssl_verify.so(+0x1272) [0x796e00465272] ./log_ssl_verify.so(SSL_CTX_set_verify+0x9b) [0x796e004653e2] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x734f4) [0x796dfcabb4f4] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x7419f) [0x796dfcabc19f] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x74b09) [0x796dfcabcb09] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x1a8ef) [0x796dfca628ef] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x14ca5) [0x796dfca5cca5] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x189bf) [0x796dfca609bf] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x483e9) [0x796dfca903e9] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_multi_perform+0xea) [0x796dfca9195a] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_easy_perform+0x14b) [0x796dfca6c7eb] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs14NetworkRequest7executeEv+0x54e) [0x796df3d8dc9e] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs10ISACBinder7refreshERNS_12IdentityDataE+0x450) [0x796df3d733e0] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs10ISACBinder11getIdentityERNS_12IdentityDataEb+0x55d) [0x796df3d7ab5d] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(dgs_oauth_get_identity+0x1b7) [0x796df3c2efc7] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x7b16) [0x796dfe7efb16] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x43ef) [0x796dfe7ec3ef] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(ffi_call+0x12e) [0x796dfe7ef0be] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/ffi-napi/build/Release/ffi_bindings.node(_ZN3FFI3FFI12AsyncFFICallEP9uv_work_s+0x23) [0x796dfcaef533] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop(+0x18f14d4) [0x59e78df734d4] PID 282062: SSL_CTX_set_verify called with mode=0 ./log_ssl_verify.so(+0x1272) [0x796e00465272] ./log_ssl_verify.so(SSL_CTX_set_verify+0x9b) [0x796e004653e2] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x734f4) [0x796dfcabb4f4] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x7419f) [0x796dfcabc19f] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x74b09) [0x796dfcabcb09] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x1a8ef) [0x796dfca628ef] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x14ca5) [0x796dfca5cca5] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x189bf) [0x796dfca609bf] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x483e9) [0x796dfca903e9] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_multi_perform+0xea) [0x796dfca9195a] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_easy_perform+0x14b) [0x796dfca6c7eb] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs14NetworkRequest7executeEv+0x54e) [0x796df3d8dc9e] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs13UpdateManager12get_manifestERNS0_14UpdateManifestE+0x2bb) [0x796df3e2dc5b] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs13UpdateManager18check_and_downloadERNS_17UpdateManagerDataEb+0x178) [0x796df3e30bd8] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN5boost10statechart12simple_stateIN3dgs16WaitCheckRequestENS2_10UpdaterFSMENS_3mpl4listIN4mpl_2naES8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_S8_EELNS0_12history_modeE0EE10react_implERKNS0_10event_baseEPKv+0x1e5) [0x796df3d0cb25] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs10UpdaterFSM18process_event_jsonE14DGS_FLOW_EVENTRKN8nlohmann10basic_jsonISt3mapSt6vectorNSt7__cxx1112basic_stringIcSt11char_traitsIcESaIcEEEblmdSaNS2_14adl_serializerES5_IhSaIhEEEE+0x43a) [0x796df3d0171a] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs7FlowFSM12processeventE14DGS_FLOW_EVENTRKN8nlohmann10basic_jsonISt3mapSt6vectorNSt7__cxx1112basic_stringIcSt11char_traitsIcESaIcEEEblmdSaNS2_14adl_serializerES5_IhSaIhEEEE+0x53) [0x796df3cccb73] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(dgs_flow_post_event+0xc5) [0x796df3c30085] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x7b16) [0x796dfe7efb16] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x43ef) [0x796dfe7ec3ef] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(ffi_call+0x12e) [0x796dfe7ef0be] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/ffi-napi/build/Release/ffi_bindings.node(_ZN3FFI3FFI12AsyncFFICallEP9uv_work_s+0x23) [0x796dfcaef533] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop(+0x18f14d4) [0x59e78df734d4] PID 282062: SSL_CTX_set_verify called with mode=0 ./log_ssl_verify.so(+0x1272) [0x796e00465272] ./log_ssl_verify.so(SSL_CTX_set_verify+0x9b) [0x796e004653e2] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x734f4) [0x796dfcabb4f4] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x7419f) [0x796dfcabc19f] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x74b09) [0x796dfcabcb09] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x1a8ef) [0x796dfca628ef] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x14ca5) [0x796dfca5cca5] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x189bf) [0x796dfca609bf] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x483e9) [0x796dfca903e9] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_multi_perform+0xea) [0x796dfca9195a] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_easy_perform+0x14b) [0x796dfca6c7eb] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcaCRLCache.so(+0x5873e) [0x796df2ae673e] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcaCRLCache.so(+0x59e85) [0x796df2ae7e85] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcaCRLCache.so(+0x2f884) [0x796df2abd884] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libdeSign.so(_Z9loadEUTSLv+0x26) [0x796df2098386] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs6Design13isTSLToUpdateE16DGS_COUNTRY_CODE+0x4a) [0x796df3c116fa] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs10TSLManager18check_TSLs_updatesEv+0xa7) [0x796df3e2bc07] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs4Core16tsl_checkupdatesERNS_7TSLDataE+0x2c) [0x796df3bb865c] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(dgs_tsl_checkupdates+0x87) [0x796df3c2f357] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x7b16) [0x796dfe7efb16] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x43ef) [0x796dfe7ec3ef] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(ffi_call+0x12e) [0x796dfe7ef0be] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/ffi-napi/build/Release/ffi_bindings.node(_ZN3FFI3FFI12AsyncFFICallEP9uv_work_s+0x23) [0x796dfcaef533] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop(+0x18f14d4) [0x59e78df734d4] PID 282062: SSL_CTX_set_verify called with mode=0 ./log_ssl_verify.so(+0x1272) [0x796e00465272] ./log_ssl_verify.so(SSL_CTX_set_verify+0x9b) [0x796e004653e2] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x734f4) [0x796dfcabb4f4] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x7419f) [0x796dfcabc19f] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x74b09) [0x796dfcabcb09] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x1a8ef) [0x796dfca628ef] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x14ca5) [0x796dfca5cca5] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x189bf) [0x796dfca609bf] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x483e9) [0x796dfca903e9] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_multi_perform+0xea) [0x796dfca9195a] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_easy_perform+0x14b) [0x796dfca6c7eb] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcaCRLCache.so(+0x5873e) [0x796df2ae673e] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcaCRLCache.so(+0x59e85) [0x796df2ae7e85] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcaCRLCache.so(+0x31007) [0x796df2abf007] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libdeSign.so(_Z26checkCountryCACertsUpdatesPc+0x2d) [0x796df20987bd] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs6Design13isTSLToUpdateE16DGS_COUNTRY_CODE+0xd0) [0x796df3c11780] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs10TSLManager18check_TSLs_updatesEv+0xa7) [0x796df3e2bc07] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs4Core16tsl_checkupdatesERNS_7TSLDataE+0x2c) [0x796df3bb865c] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(dgs_tsl_checkupdates+0x87) [0x796df3c2f357] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x7b16) [0x796dfe7efb16] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x43ef) [0x796dfe7ec3ef] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(ffi_call+0x12e) [0x796dfe7ef0be] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/ffi-napi/build/Release/ffi_bindings.node(_ZN3FFI3FFI12AsyncFFICallEP9uv_work_s+0x23) [0x796dfcaef533] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop(+0x18f14d4) [0x59e78df734d4] PID 282062: SSL_CTX_set_verify called with mode=0 ./log_ssl_verify.so(+0x1272) [0x796e00465272] ./log_ssl_verify.so(SSL_CTX_set_verify+0x9b) [0x796e004653e2] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x734f4) [0x796dfcabb4f4] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x7419f) [0x796dfcabc19f] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x74b09) [0x796dfcabcb09] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x1a8ef) [0x796dfca628ef] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x14ca5) [0x796dfca5cca5] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x189bf) [0x796dfca609bf] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(+0x483e9) [0x796dfca903e9] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_multi_perform+0xea) [0x796dfca9195a] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/lib/libcurl.so.4(curl_easy_perform+0x14b) [0x796dfca6c7eb] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs14NetworkRequest7executeEv+0x54e) [0x796df3d8dc9e] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(_ZN3dgs14NetworkManager15checkConnectionEv+0xd2) [0x796df3d8ec92] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-js/node_modules/@ice/dike-core-linux/native/libdgsapi.so(dgs_check_connection+0x2b) [0x796df3c27e2b] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x7b16) [0x796dfe7efb16] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(+0x43ef) [0x796dfe7ec3ef] /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libffi.so.8(ffi_call+0x12e) [0x796dfe7ef0be] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/node_modules/ffi-napi/build/Release/ffi_bindings.node(_ZN3FFI3FFI12AsyncFFICallEP9uv_work_s+0x23) [0x796dfcaef533] /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop(+0x18f14d4) [0x59e78df734d4] --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- Static analysis of the binary `/usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop` returned a series of strings suggesting the existence of flags and parameters intended to disable TLS checks or log cryptographic information. These occurrences indicate that the code includes mechanisms (or supports parameters) which, if enabled, can alter certificate verification behavior or activate sensitive TLS key logging. --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- $ strings -n 1 /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop | grep -i -E 'ignore-certificate-errors|certificate-error|ignore-urlfetcher-cert-requests|ssl-key-log-file' &amp;gt; binary_relevant_strings.txt' $ cat binary_relevant_strings.txt certificate-error ssl-key-log-file argument missing ignore-urlfetcher-cert-requests ignore-certificate-errors-spki-list ssl-key-log-file ignore-certificate-errors [..] --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- To verify whether these parameters were passed to the running process, the command line of all GoSignDesktop processes was checked by reading their respective `/proc/&amp;lt;pid&amp;gt;/cmdline`. On the analyzed systems, the binary's execution shows that child processes use various `--type` arguments (zygote, gpu-process, renderer, etc.) and internal options typical of Chromium/Electron-based runtimes, but no flags explicitly disabling TLS verification were found. --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- $ for p in $( pgrep -f GoSignDesktop ); do echo "=== PID $p ===" &amp;gt;&amp;gt; proc_cmdlines.txt; cat /proc/$p/cmdline 2&amp;gt;/dev/null | tr '\0' ' ' &amp;gt;&amp;gt; proc_cmdlines.txt || echo "no /proc/$p/cmdline" &amp;gt;&amp;gt; proc_cmdlines.txt; echo &amp;gt;&amp;gt; proc_cmdlines.txt; done $ cat proc_cmdlines.txt === PID 282062 === /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop === PID 282065 === /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop --type=zygote --no-zygote-sandbox === PID 282066 === /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/chrome-sandbox /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop --type=zygote === PID 282067 === /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop --type=zygote === PID 282069 === /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop --type=zygote === PID 282106 === /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop --type=gpu-process --field-trial-handle=13821780690570354888,7554827926380561664,131072 --enable-features=WebComponentsV0Enabled --disable-features=CookiesWithoutSameSiteMustBeSecure,SameSiteByDefaultCookies,SpareRendererForSitePerProcess --gpu-preferences=OAAAAAAAAAAgAAAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABgAAAAAAAYAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIAAAAAAAAAA== --shared-files === PID 282114 === /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop --type=utility --utility-sub-type=network.mojom.NetworkService --field-trial-handle=13821780690570354888,7554827926380561664,131072 --enable-features=WebComponentsV0Enabled --disable-features=CookiesWithoutSameSiteMustBeSecure,SameSiteByDefaultCookies,SpareRendererForSitePerProcess --lang=en-US --service-sandbox-type=network --standard-schemes=file --secure-schemes=file --bypasscsp-schemes --cors-schemes --fetch-schemes --service-worker-schemes --streaming-schemes --shared-files=v8_context_snapshot_data:100 === PID 282279 === /usr/lib/gosigndesktop/GoSignDesktop --type=renderer --field-trial-handle=13821780690570354888,7554827926380561664,131072 --enable-features=WebComponentsV0Enabled --disable-features=CookiesWithoutSameSiteMustBeSecure,SameSiteByDefaultCookies,SpareRendererForSitePerProcess --lang=en-US --standard-schemes=file --secure-schemes=file --bypasscsp-schemes --cors-schemes --fetch-schemes --service-worker-schemes --streaming-schemes --app-path=/usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app --node-integration-in-worker --no-sandbox --no-zygote --preload=/usr/lib/gosigndesktop/resources/app/preload.js --context-isolation --background-color=#fff --enable-spellcheck --enable-websql --disable-electron-site-instance-overrides --num-raster-threads=4 --enable-main-frame-before-activation --renderer-client-id=4 --no-v8-untrusted-code-mitigations --shared-files=v8_context_snapshot_data:100 --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- HTTP traffic demonstrating the lack of a digital signature on the update manifest: --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- GET /gosign/download/update HTTP/1.1 Host: rinnovofirma.infocert.it Cookie: Accept: application/json Cache-Control: no-cache Connection: keep-alive HTTP/1.1 200 OK Date: Fri, 03 Oct 2025 21:44:39 GMT Server: Apache Content-Security-Policy: upgrade-insecure-requests; frame-ancestors none; object-src none X-Frame-Options: SAMEORIGIN Last-Modified: Thu, 04 Sep 2025 10:16:23 GMT ETag: "453-63df703669aaa" Accept-Ranges: bytes Content-Length: 1107 Vary: Accept-Encoding Keep-Alive: timeout=15, max=100 Connection: Keep-Alive Content-Type: application/json { "control":{ "probability": 100 }, "darwin": { "2.3.7": { "packages": { "dmg": { "any": { "url": "https://gosignupdates.infocert.it/gosign/standard/GoSignDesktop-standard-2.3.7-8aa7cbe.dmg", "sha256": "05ae06770253f2dadc9cce36b44d1198781eb874bb19fd10a10d8311749e4b84", "size": 163804666 , "releaseDate": "2025-05-26" } } }, "type": "MANDATORY" } }, "linux": { "2.4.0": { "packages": { "deb": { "64": { "url": "https://gosignupdates.infocert.it/gosign/standard/gosigndesktop_2.4.0_amd64.deb", "sha256": "02b7bc38365f3e456c4f41ef7ccd4bfa2134e54868345aad323823aabe740576", "size": 102522536, "releaseDate": "2025-04-04" } } }, "type": "MANDATORY" } } } --8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;--8&amp;lt;-- X. PoC The provided Proof of Concept targets a GoSign Desktop installation on Debian/Ubuntu Linux with amd64 architecture and simulates a local privilege escalation to root by a local attacker. After the exploit, you will need to reinstall GoSign Desktop by downloading it again from the official website, as it is replaced by the fake update package. The GoSign Desktop configuration is preserved. https://www.ush.it/team/ush/hack-gosign-desktop_240/gosigndesktop_mitm_poc.mp4 1) Build Compile the fake .deb update package and create the Python virtual environment with the dependencies required for the exploit: `make` 2) Run Configure the exploit to act as a proxy for GoSign Desktop in order to simulate the attack: `make run` 3) PoC Evidence After installing the fake .deb update package, you can verify the impact by checking the file: `cat /tmp/gosigndesktop_mitm_poc.log` 4) Cleanup You can remove the proxy configuration, the .deb file, and the virtual environment: `make clean` XI. REFERENCES No references. XII. CREDIT Pasquale "Sid" Fiorillo is credited with the discovery of this vulnerability with the contribution of Francesco "ascii" Ongaro and Marco Lunardi. Pasquale "sid" Fiorillo web site: http://www.ush.it/ mail: sid AT ush DOT it Francesco "ascii" Ongaro web site: http://www.ush.it/ mail: ascii AT ush DOT it XIII. LEGAL NOTICES Copyright (c) 2025 Pasquale "Sid" Fiorillo Permission is granted for the redistribution of this alert electronically. It may not be edited in any way without mine express written consent. If you wish to reprint the whole or any part of this alert in any other medium other than electronically, please email me for permission. Disclaimer: The information in the advisory is believed to be accurate at the time of publishing based on currently available information. Use of the information constitutes acceptance for use in an AS IS condition. There are no warranties with regard to this information. Neither the author nor the publisher accepts any liability for any direct, indirect, or consequential loss or damage arising from use of, or reliance on, this information.&lt;/quote&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ush.it/2025/11/14/multiple-vulnerabilities-gosign-desktop-remote-code-execution/"/><published>2025-11-18T12:36:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45964987</id><title>Multiple Digital Ocean services down</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:48.523154+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3576af652540de2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our Engineering team is actively investigating an issue impacting multiple DigitalOcean services caused by an upstream provider incident. This disruption affects a subset of Gen AI tools, the App Platform, Load Balancer, Spaces and provisioning or management actions for new clusters. Existing clusters are not affected. Users may experience degraded performance or intermittent failures within these services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We acknowledge the inconvenience this may cause and are working diligently to restore normal operations. Signs of recovery are starting to appear, with most requests beginning to succeed. We will continue to monitor the situation closely and provide timely updates as more information becomes available. Thank you for your patience as we work towards full service restoration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posted Nov 18, 2025 - 13:40 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Investigating&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our Engineering team is actively investigating an issue impacting multiple DigitalOcean services caused by an upstream provider incident. This disruption affects a subset of Gen AI tools, the App Platform, Load Balancer, and Spaces. Users may experience degraded performance or intermittent failures within these services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We acknowledge the inconvenience this may cause and are working diligently to restore normal operations. Signs of recovery are starting to appear, with most requests beginning to succeed. We will continue to monitor the situation closely and provide timely updates as more information becomes available. Thank you for your patience as we work towards full service restoration&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posted Nov 18, 2025 - 12:26 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This incident affects: API, GenAI Platform, App Platform (Global), Managed Databases (Global), Load Balancers (Global), and Spaces (Global).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://status.digitalocean.com/incidents/lgt5xs2843rx"/><published>2025-11-18T12:48:45+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45965060</id><title>Do Not Put Your Site Behind Cloudflare If You Don't Need To</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:47.988860+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b3c3cd1b9c4a48d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Do Not Put Your Site Behind Cloudflare if You Don't Need To&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the time of writing 12:43 UTC on Tue 18 Nov, Cloudflare has taken many sites down. I'm trying to browse the web, but about half of the sites show an error:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of these sites are not even that big. I expect maybe a few thousand visitors per month.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This demonstrates again a simple fact: if you put your site behind a centralized service, then this service is a single point of failure. Even large established companies make mistakes and can go down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most people use Cloudflare because they have been scared into the idea that you need DDoS protection. Well, maybe you do, but probably you don't.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As they say in security, "no one will burn a zero day on you!". For your small blog with one hundred visitors per month, it's probably the same: "no one will burn their DDoS capabilities on you!"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't know how else to say it. Many people keep talking about the importance of a decentralized web, and then continue putting their site behind Cloudflare.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you really want to be safe in case your server goes down, then setup a second version of your site at another location and point to that server via the A and AAAA records, see "round-robin DNS".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe that's the core of this message. Face your fears. Put your service on the internet. Maybe it goes down, but at least not by yet another Cloudflare outage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://huijzer.xyz/posts/123/do-not-put-your-site-behind-cloudflare-if-you-dont"/><published>2025-11-18T12:54:49+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45965664</id><title>Ruby 4.0.0 Preview2 Released</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:47.771485+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7c00b14b9620b6d5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posted by naruse on 17 Nov 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce the release of Ruby 4.0.0-preview2. Ruby 4.0 updates its Unicode version to 17,0.0, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Language changes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;*nil&lt;/code&gt;no longer calls&lt;code&gt;nil.to_a&lt;/code&gt;, similar to how&lt;code&gt;**nil&lt;/code&gt;does not call&lt;code&gt;nil.to_hash&lt;/code&gt;. [[Feature #21047]]&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Core classes updates&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: We’re only listing notable updates of Core class.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Binding&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Binding#local_variables&lt;/code&gt;does no longer include numbered parameters. Also,&lt;code&gt;Binding#local_variable_get&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;Binding#local_variable_set&lt;/code&gt;reject to handle numbered parameters. [[Bug #21049]]&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;IO&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;IO.select&lt;/code&gt;accepts +Float::INFINITY+ as a timeout argument. [[Feature #20610]]&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;String&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Update Unicode to Version 17.0.0 and Emoji Version 17.0. [[Feature #19908]][[Feature #20724]][[Feature #21275]] (also applies to Regexp)&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Standard Library updates&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: We’re only listing notable updates of Standard librarires.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ostruct 0.6.1&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pstore 0.2.0&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;benchmark 0.4.0&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;logger 1.7.0&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;rdoc 6.13.1&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;win32ole 1.9.2&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;irb 1.15.2&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;reline 0.6.1&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;readline 0.0.4&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fiddle 1.1.6&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Compatibility issues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: Excluding feature bug fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Standard library compatibility issues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;C API updates&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;JIT&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;YJIT &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;YJIT stats &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;ratio_in_yjit&lt;/code&gt;no longer works in the default build. Use&lt;code&gt;--enable-yjit=stats&lt;/code&gt;on&lt;code&gt;configure&lt;/code&gt;to enable it on&lt;code&gt;--yjit-stats&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;invalidate_everything&lt;/code&gt;to default stats, which is incremented when every code is invalidated by TracePoint.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;mem_size:&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;call_threshold:&lt;/code&gt;options to&lt;code&gt;RubyVM::YJIT.enable&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;YJIT stats &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ZJIT &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Add an experimental method-based JIT compiler. Use &lt;code&gt;--enable-zjit&lt;/code&gt;on&lt;code&gt;configure&lt;/code&gt;to enable the&lt;code&gt;--zjit&lt;/code&gt;support.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;As of Ruby 4.0.0-preview2, ZJIT is not yet ready for speeding up most benchmarks. Please refrain from evaluating ZJIT just yet. Stay tuned for the Ruby 4.0 release.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add an experimental method-based JIT compiler. Use &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;RJIT &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;--rjit&lt;/code&gt;is removed. We will move the implementation of the third-party JIT API to the ruby/rjit repository.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Miscellaneous changes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See NEWS or commit logs for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With those changes, 3607 files changed, 197451 insertions(+), 285607 deletions(-) since Ruby 3.4.0!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Download&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://cache.ruby-lang.org/pub/ruby/4.0/ruby-4.0.0-preview2.tar.gz&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;SIZE: 23444451 SHA1: 132e450bbee3f61ed0b463ed1e2bd3a3a324339c SHA256: 0a3330dae710302e11f7f0323e83219ab3c6517984691a312c662f329c5120e1 SHA512: b5e681cc84be59148485b9a2212dcf54d61cfee27431ceddb49bedc8baa913ec8b36da43242cb4f1791b25e4bfc1dcf72b5527288a0656f2933da898d0e0b40f&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://cache.ruby-lang.org/pub/ruby/4.0/ruby-4.0.0-preview2.tar.xz&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;SIZE: 17554228 SHA1: f8e8b98ea85ac82610ab601a21dc9a90c5c56a97 SHA256: 0b92b15466d77a9d7e59e4a75f050d42cd50fe96c951d2b3b9f8029394cd9a43 SHA512: 7afaa8d8e832ef0ded28f1caf874da69f16105e1b3aad5947c6911364159b4c6ebd3d7ea5d7d86708e9f2f06a047921b8302ca6e75ec429a3da846845f896976&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://cache.ruby-lang.org/pub/ruby/4.0/ruby-4.0.0-preview2.zip&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;SIZE: 28933540 SHA1: 48a235cfbfd4252dce81da870c792e32309e62b9 SHA256: f5c68ee44dfcb76b61c07c437fa945814dfc516570b1c921506ac886960160ca SHA512: 508c685e46a641c74e2968daf650559503ce2bcaac3403654713adb2345c3ede2bace929294a1367afecac5edd6b2c42fa833f5313456f78c79151d310c860cf&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What is Ruby&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ruby was first developed by Matz (Yukihiro Matsumoto) in 1993, and is now developed as Open Source. It runs on multiple platforms and is used all over the world especially for web development.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/news/2025/11/17/ruby-4-0-0-preview2-released/"/><published>2025-11-18T13:34:44+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45966018</id><title>Experiment: Making TypeScript Immutable-by-Default</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:47.370510+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="eadcf3715b288ba1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Experiment: making TypeScript immutable-by-default&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I like programming languages where variables are immutable by default. For example, in Rust, &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; declares an immutable variable and &lt;code&gt;let mut&lt;/code&gt; declares a mutable one. I’ve long wanted this in other languages, like TypeScript, which is mutable by default—the opposite of what I want!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wondered: is it possible to make TypeScript values immutable by default?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My goal was to do this purely with TypeScript, without changing TypeScript itself. That meant no lint rules or other tools. I chose this because I wanted this solution to be as “pure” as possible…and it also sounded more fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I spent an evening trying to do this. I failed but made progress! I made arrays and &lt;code&gt;Record&lt;/code&gt;s immutable by default, but I couldn’t get it working for regular objects. If you figure out how to do this completely, please contact me—I must know!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Step 1: obliterate the built-in libraries&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TypeScript has built-in type definitions for JavaScript APIs like &lt;code&gt;Array&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;. If you’ve ever changed the &lt;code&gt;target&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;lib&lt;/code&gt; options in your TSConfig, you’ve tweaked which of these definitions are included. For example, you might add the “ES2024” library if you’re targeting a newer runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My goal was to swap the built-in libraries with an immutable-by-default replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first step was to stop using any of the built-in libraries. I set the &lt;code&gt;noLib&lt;/code&gt; flag in my TSConfig, like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "compilerOptions": {
    "noLib": true
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then I wrote a very simple script and put it in &lt;code&gt;test.ts&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;console.log("Hello world!");
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I ran &lt;code&gt;tsc&lt;/code&gt;, it gave a bunch of errors:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Cannot find global type 'Array'.
Cannot find global type 'Boolean'.
Cannot find global type 'Function'.
Cannot find global type 'IArguments'.
Cannot find global type 'Number'.
Cannot find global type 'Object'.
Cannot find global type 'RegExp'.
Cannot find global type 'String'.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Progress! I had successfully obliterated any default TypeScript libraries, which I could tell because it couldn’t find core types like &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Boolean&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time to write the replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Step 2: a skeleton standard library&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project was a prototype. Therefore, I started with a minimal solution that would type-check. I didn’t need it to be good!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I created &lt;code&gt;lib.d.ts&lt;/code&gt; and put the following inside:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// In lib.d.ts:
declare var console: any;

interface Boolean {}
interface Function {}
interface IArguments {}
interface Number {}
interface RegExp {}
interface String {}
interface Object {}

// TODO: We'll update this soon.
interface Array&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; {}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, when I ran &lt;code&gt;tsc&lt;/code&gt;, I got no errors! I’d defined all the built-in types that TypeScript needs, and a dummy &lt;code&gt;console&lt;/code&gt; object.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you can see, this solution is impractical for production. For one, none of these interfaces have any properties! &lt;code&gt;"foo".toUpperCase()&lt;/code&gt; isn’t defined, for example. That’s okay because this is only a prototype. A production-ready version would need to define all of those things—tedious, but should be straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Step 3: making arrays immutable&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I decided to tackle this with a test-driven development style. I’d write some code that I want to type-check, watch it fail to type-check, then fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I updated &lt;code&gt;test.ts&lt;/code&gt; to contain the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// In test.ts:
const arr = [1, 2, 3];

// Non-mutation should be allowed.
console.log(arr[1]);
console.log(arr.map((n) =&amp;gt; n + 1));

// @ts-expect-error Mutation should not be allowed.
arr[0] = 9;
// @ts-expect-error Mutation should not be allowed.
arr.push(4);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This tests three things:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Creating arrays with array literals is possible.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Non-mutating operations, like &lt;code&gt;arr[1]&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;arr.map()&lt;/code&gt;, are allowed.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Operations that mutate the array, like &lt;code&gt;arr[1] = 9&lt;/code&gt;, are disallowed.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I ran &lt;code&gt;tsc&lt;/code&gt;, I saw two errors:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;arr[0] = 9&lt;/code&gt;is allowed. There’s an unused&lt;code&gt;@ts-expect-error&lt;/code&gt;there.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;arr.map&lt;/code&gt;doesn’t exist.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I updated the &lt;code&gt;Array&lt;/code&gt; type in &lt;code&gt;lib.d.ts&lt;/code&gt; with the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// In lib.d.ts:
interface Array&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; {
  readonly [n: number]: T;

  map&amp;lt;U&amp;gt;(
    callbackfn: (value: T, index: number, array: readonly T[]) =&amp;gt; U,
    thisArg?: any
  ): U[];
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The property accessor—the &lt;code&gt;readonly [n: number]: T&lt;/code&gt; line—tells TypeScript that you can access array properties by numeric index, but they’re read-only. That should make &lt;code&gt;arr[1]&lt;/code&gt; possible but &lt;code&gt;arr[1] = 9&lt;/code&gt; impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; method definition is copied from the TypeScript source code with no changes (other than some auto-formatting). That should make it possible to call &lt;code&gt;arr.map()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice that I did not define &lt;code&gt;push&lt;/code&gt;. We shouldn’t be calling that on an immutable array!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I ran &lt;code&gt;tsc&lt;/code&gt; again and…success! No errors! We now have immutable arrays!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this stage, I’ve shown that it’s possible to configure TypeScript to make all arrays immutable with no extra annotations. No need for &lt;code&gt;readonly string[]&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;ReadonlyArray&amp;lt;number&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;! In other words, we have some immutability by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This code, like everything in this post, is simplistic. There are lots of other array methods, like &lt;code&gt;filter()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;join()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;forEach()&lt;/code&gt;! If this were made production-ready, I’d make sure to define all the read-only array methods.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But for now, I was ready to move on to mutable arrays.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Step 4: mutable arrays&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I prefer immutability, but I want to be able to define a mutable array sometimes. So I made another test case:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// In test.ts:
const arr = [1, 2, 3] as MutableArray&amp;lt;number&amp;gt;;
arr[0] = 9;
arr.push(4);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice that this requires a little extra work to make the array mutable. In other words, it’s not the default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TypeScript complained that it can’t find &lt;code&gt;MutableArray&lt;/code&gt;, so I defined it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// In lib.d.ts:
interface MutableArray&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; extends Array&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; {
  [n: number]: T;
  push(...items: T[]): number;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And again, type-checks passed!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, I had mutable and immutable arrays, with immutability as the default. Again, this is simplistic, but good enough for this proof-of-concept!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was exciting to me. It was possible to configure TypeScript to be immutable by default, for arrays at least. I didn’t have to fork the language or use any other tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could I make more things immutable?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Step 5: the same for &lt;code&gt;Record&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wanted to see if I could go beyond arrays. My next target was the &lt;code&gt;Record&lt;/code&gt; type, which is a TypeScript utility type. So I defined another pair of test cases similar to the ones I made for arrays:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// In test.ts:

// Immutable records
const obj1: Record&amp;lt;string, string&amp;gt; = { foo: "bar" };
console.log(obj1.foo);
// @ts-expect-error Mutation should not be allowed.
obj1.foo = "baz";

// Mutable records
const obj2: MutableRecord&amp;lt;string, string&amp;gt; = { foo: "bar" };
obj2.foo = "baz";
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TypeScript complained that it couldn’t find &lt;code&gt;Record&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;MutableRecord&lt;/code&gt;. It also complained about an unused &lt;code&gt;@ts-expect-error&lt;/code&gt;, which meant that mutation was allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I rolled up my sleeves and fixed those errors like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// In lib.d.ts:
declare type PropertyKey = string | number | symbol;
type Record&amp;lt;KeyT extends PropertyKey, ValueT&amp;gt; = {
  readonly [key in KeyT]: ValueT;
};
type MutableRecord&amp;lt;KeyT extends PropertyKey, ValueT&amp;gt; = {
  [key in KeyT]: ValueT;
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, we have &lt;code&gt;Record&lt;/code&gt;, which is an immutable key-value pair, and the mutable version too. Just like arrays!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can imagine extending this idea to other built-in types, like &lt;code&gt;Set&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Map&lt;/code&gt;. I think it’d be pretty easy to do this the same way I did arrays and records. I’ll leave that as an exercise to the reader.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Failed step 6: plain objects&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My final test was to make regular objects (not records or arrays) immutable. Unfortunately for me, I could not figure this out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the test case I wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// In test.ts:
const obj = { foo: "bar" };
console.log(obj.foo);
// @ts-expect-error Mutation should not be allowed.
obj.foo = "baz";
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This stumped me. No matter what I did, I could not write a type that would disallow this mutation. I tried modifying the &lt;code&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt; type every way I could think of, but came up short!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are ways to annotate &lt;code&gt;obj&lt;/code&gt; to make it immutable, but that’s not in the spirit of my goal. I want it to be immutable by default!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alas, this is where I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Can you figure this out?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wanted to make TypeScript immutable by default. I was able to do this with arrays, &lt;code&gt;Record&lt;/code&gt;s, and other types like &lt;code&gt;Map&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Set&lt;/code&gt;. Unfortunately, I couldn’t make it work for plain object definitions like &lt;code&gt;obj = { foo: "bar" }&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s probably a way to enforce this with lint rules, either by disallowing mutation operations or by requiring &lt;code&gt;Readonly&lt;/code&gt; annotations everywhere. I’d like to see what that looks like.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you figure out how to make TypeScript immutable by default with no other tools, I would love to know, and I’ll update my post. I hope my failed attempt will lead someone else to something successful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, please contact me if you figure this out, or have any other thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://evanhahn.com/typescript-immutability-experiment/"/><published>2025-11-18T13:56:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45966251</id><title>Nearly all UK drivers say headlights are too bright</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:47.068396+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="24df8d635d03762d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Nearly all drivers say headlights are too bright&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nearly all UK drivers said they thought headlights were too bright and that they have been dazzled by oncoming vehicles, according to a major study.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government said last week that it will take a closer look at the design of cars and headlamps after concerns about lights dazzling drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A study commissioned by the Department for Transport (DfT) found 97% of people surveyed found they were regularly or sometimes distracted by oncoming vehicles and 96% thought most or some headlights were too bright.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dr Shaun Helman, who led the research for Berkshire-based Transport Research Laboratory (TRL), said it provides "compelling evidence" that lights' glare is a "genuine issue for UK drivers".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New measures will be included in the government's upcoming Road Safety Strategy, reflecting what is becoming an increasingly fraught issue for road users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TRL's data suggests that LED and whiter headlamps may be linked to glare and that drivers might find their whiteness harder to cope with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of those surveyed, 33% said they had either stopped driving or are driving less at night because of lights, while another 22% said they would like to drive less at night but have no choice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A total of 1,850 drivers, matched to the age and gender split of the country's licence holding population, were surveyed for their views.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TRL said LED lights used in vehicles are brighter, more concentrated and emit more blue light, which human eyes struggle with more at night.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The RAC's senior policy officer Rod Dennis said: "Having campaigned hard for this study, we welcome its findings which independently confirm what drivers have been telling us – that rather than being an imagined phenomenon, some bright headlights do cause a glare problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"While drivers clearly benefit from high-performing headlights, it's important this doesn't lead to others suffering the effects of dazzle, so a balance needs to be struck," he added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mr Dennis said that it is "vital" TRL's report is "reviewed carefully to put us on a path towards changes that ultimately benefit all road users."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Denise Voon, a clinical advisor at The College of Optometrists, said the DfT should "take immediate, actionable steps to support drivers and commission more detailed research, specifically into how headlight regulations need to change".&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c1j8ewy1p86o"/><published>2025-11-18T14:11:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45966435</id><title>Short Little Difficult Books</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:47.006032+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://countercraft.substack.com/p/short-little-difficult-books"/><published>2025-11-18T14:23:18+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45967211</id><title>Gemini 3 Pro Preview Live in AI Studio</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:46.284685+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="c5bbe5cda930f6e1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sign in Use your Google Account Email or phone Forgot email? Type the text you hear or see Not your computer? Use a Private Window to sign in. Learn more about using Guest mode Next Create account&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://aistudio.google.com/prompts/new_chat?model=gemini-3-pro-preview"/><published>2025-11-18T15:09:38+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45967814</id><title>Google Antigravity</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:45.949529+00:00</updated><link href="https://antigravity.google/"/><published>2025-11-18T15:47:38+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45967999</id><title>Gemini 3</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:45.661653+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f9d7a1cf9b3f9a95"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;A new era of intelligence with Gemini 3&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;A note from Google and Alphabet CEO Sundar Pichai:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nearly two years ago we kicked off the Gemini era, one of our biggest scientific and product endeavors ever undertaken as a company. Since then, it’s been incredible to see how much people love it. AI Overviews now have 2 billion users every month. The Gemini app surpasses 650 million users per month, more than 70% of our Cloud customers use our AI, 13 million developers have built with our generative models, and that is just a snippet of the impact we’re seeing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And we’re able to get advanced capabilities to the world faster than ever, thanks to our differentiated full stack approach to AI innovation — from our leading infrastructure to our world-class research and models and tooling, to products that reach billions of people around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every generation of Gemini has built on the last, enabling you to do more. Gemini 1’s breakthroughs in native multimodality and long context window expanded the kinds of information that could be processed — and how much of it. Gemini 2 laid the foundation for agentic capabilities and pushed the frontiers on reasoning and thinking, helping with more complex tasks and ideas, leading to Gemini 2.5 Pro topping LMArena for over six months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And now we’re introducing Gemini 3, our most intelligent model, that combines all of Gemini’s capabilities together so you can bring any idea to life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s state-of-the-art in reasoning, built to grasp depth and nuance — whether it’s perceiving the subtle clues in a creative idea, or peeling apart the overlapping layers of a difficult problem. Gemini 3 is also much better at figuring out the context and intent behind your request, so you get what you need with less prompting. It’s amazing to think that in just two years, AI has evolved from simply reading text and images to reading the room.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And starting today, we’re shipping Gemini at the scale of Google. That includes Gemini 3 in AI Mode in Search with more complex reasoning and new dynamic experiences. This is the first time we are shipping Gemini in Search on day one. Gemini 3 is also coming today to the Gemini app, to developers in AI Studio and Vertex AI, and in our new agentic development platform, Google Antigravity — more below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like the generations before it, Gemini 3 is once again advancing the state of the art. In this new chapter, we’ll continue to push the frontiers of intelligence, agents, and personalization to make AI truly helpful for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We hope you like Gemini 3, we'll keep improving it, and look forward to seeing what you build with it. Much more to come!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Introducing Gemini 3: our most intelligent model that helps you bring any idea to life&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Demis Hassabis, CEO of Google DeepMind and Koray Kavukcuoglu, CTO of Google DeepMind and Chief AI Architect, Google, on behalf of the Gemini team&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today we’re taking another big step on the path toward AGI and releasing Gemini 3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s the best model in the world for multimodal understanding and our most powerful agentic and vibe coding model yet, delivering richer visualizations and deeper interactivity — all built on a foundation of state-of-the-art reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re beginning the Gemini 3 era by releasing Gemini 3 Pro in preview and making it available today across a suite of Google products so you can use it in your daily life to learn, build and plan anything. We’re also introducing Gemini 3 Deep Think — our enhanced reasoning mode that pushes Gemini 3 performance even further — and giving access to safety testers before making it available to Google AI Ultra subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;State-of-the-art reasoning with unprecedented depth and nuance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro can bring any idea to life with its state-of-the-art reasoning and multimodal capabilities. It significantly outperforms 2.5 Pro on every major AI benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It tops the LMArena Leaderboard with a breakthrough score of 1501 Elo. It demonstrates PhD-level reasoning with top scores on Humanity’s Last Exam (37.5% without the usage of any tools) and GPQA Diamond (91.9%). It also sets a new standard for frontier models in mathematics, achieving a new state-of-the-art of 23.4% on MathArena Apex.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond text, Gemini 3 Pro redefines multimodal reasoning with 81% on MMMU-Pro and 87.6% on Video-MMMU. It also scores a state-of-the-art 72.1% on SimpleQA Verified, showing great progress on factual accuracy. This means Gemini 3 Pro is highly capable at solving complex problems across a vast array of topics like science and mathematics with a high degree of reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 is state-of-the-art across a range of key AI benchmarks. See details on our evaluation methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro also brings a new level of depth and nuance to every interaction. Its responses are smart, concise and direct, trading cliché and flattery for genuine insight — telling you what you need to hear, not just what you want to hear. It acts as a true thought partner that gives you new ways to understand information and express yourself, from translating dense scientific concepts by generating code for high-fidelity visualizations to creative brainstorming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 can code a visualization of plasma flow in a tokamak and write a poem capturing the physics of fusion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Gemini 3 Deep Think&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Deep Think mode pushes the boundaries of intelligence even further, delivering a step-change in Gemini 3’s reasoning and multimodal understanding capabilities to help you solve even more complex problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In testing, Gemini 3 Deep Think outperforms Gemini 3 Pro’s already impressive performance on Humanity’s Last Exam (41.0% without the use of tools) and GPQA Diamond (93.8%). It also achieves an unprecedented 45.1% on ARC-AGI-2 (with code execution, ARC Prize Verified), demonstrating its ability to solve novel challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Deep Think mode excels on some of the most challenging AI benchmarks. See details on our evaluation methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Gemini 3 helps you learn, build and plan anything&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Learn anything&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini was built from the start to seamlessly synthesize information about any topic across multiple modalities, including text, images, video, audio and code. Gemini 3 pushes the frontier of multimodal reasoning to help you learn in ways that make sense for you by combining its state-of-the-art reasoning, vision and spatial understanding, leading multilingual performance, and 1 million-token context window.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, if you want to learn how to cook in your family tradition, Gemini 3 can decipher and translate handwritten recipes in different languages into a shareable family cookbook. Or if you want to learn about a new topic, you can give it academic papers, long video lectures or tutorials and it can generate code for interactive flashcards, visualizations or other formats that will help you master the material. It can even analyze videos of your pickleball match, identify areas where you can improve and generate a training plan for overall form improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 can help you learn and preserve family cooking traditions. Try it in Gemini Canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 can help you analyze complex information like research papers and can generate code for an interactive guide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get expert-level sports analysis on your pickleball match to help improve your game.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To help you make better sense of information on the web, AI Mode in Search now uses Gemini 3 to enable new generative UI experiences like immersive visual layouts and interactive tools and simulations, all generated completely on the fly based on your query.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learn a complex topic like how RNA polymerase works with generative UI in AI Mode in Search.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Build anything&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on the success of 2.5 Pro, Gemini 3 delivers on the promise of bringing any idea to life for developers. It’s exceptional at zero-shot generation and handles complex prompts and instructions to render richer, more interactive web UI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 is the best vibe coding and agentic coding model we’ve ever built – making our products more autonomous and boosting developer productivity. It tops the WebDev Arena leaderboard by scoring an impressive 1487 Elo. It also scores 54.2% on Terminal-Bench 2.0, which tests a model’s tool use ability to operate a computer via terminal and it greatly outperforms 2.5 Pro on SWE-bench Verified (76.2%), a benchmark that measures coding agents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can now build with Gemini 3 in Google AI Studio, Vertex AI, Gemini CLI and our new agentic development platform, Google Antigravity. It’s also available in third-party platforms like Cursor, GitHub, JetBrains, Manus, Replit and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Code a retro 3D spaceship game with richer visualizations and improved interactivity. Try it in AI Studio.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bring your imagination to life by building, deconstructing and remixing detailed 3D voxel art using code. Try it in AI Studio.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build a playable sci-fi world with shaders using Gemini 3. Try it in AI Studio.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can vibe code richer, more interactive web UI and apps with Gemini 3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Introducing a new agent-first development experience&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As model intelligence accelerates with Gemini 3, we have the opportunity to reimagine the entire developer experience. Today we’re releasing Google Antigravity, our new agentic development platform that enables developers to operate at a higher, task-oriented level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using Gemini 3’s advanced reasoning, tool use and agentic coding capabilities, Google Antigravity transforms AI assistance from a tool in a developer’s toolkit into an active partner. While the core of Google Antigravity is a familiar AI IDE experience, its agents have been elevated to a dedicated surface and given direct access to the editor, terminal and browser. Now, agents can autonomously plan and execute complex, end-to-end software tasks simultaneously on your behalf while validating their own code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to Gemini 3 Pro, Google Antigravity also comes tightly coupled with our latest Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model for browser control and our top-rated image editing model Nano Banana (Gemini 2.5 Image).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google Antigravity uses Gemini 3 to drive an end-to-end agentic workflow for a flight tracker app. The agent independently plans, codes the application and validates its execution through browser-based computer use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Plan anything&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since introducing the agentic era with Gemini 2, we’ve made a lot of progress, not only advancing Gemini’s coding agent abilities, but also improving its ability to reliably plan ahead over longer horizons. Gemini 3 demonstrates this by topping the leaderboard on Vending-Bench 2, which tests longer horizon planning by managing a simulated vending machine business. Gemini 3 Pro maintains consistent tool usage and decision-making for a full simulated year of operation, driving higher returns without drifting off task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro demonstrates better long-horizon planning to generate significantly higher returns compared to other frontier models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means Gemini 3 can better help you get things done in everyday life. By combining deeper reasoning with improved, more consistent tool use, Gemini 3 can take action on your behalf by navigating more complex, multi-step workflows from start to finish — like booking local services or organizing your inbox — all while under your control and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google AI Ultra subscribers can try these agentic capabilities in the Gemini app with Gemini Agent today. We’ve learned a lot improving Gemini’s agentic capabilities, and we’re excited to see how you use it as we expand to more Google products soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini Agent can help you organize your Gmail inbox. Try it now in the Gemini app for Google AI Ultra subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building Gemini 3 responsibly&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 is our most secure model yet, and has undergone the most comprehensive set of safety evaluations of any Google AI model to date. The model shows reduced sycophancy, increased resistance to prompt injections and improved protection against misuse via cyberattacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to our in-house testing for the critical domains in our Frontier Safety Framework, we've also partnered on evaluations with world-leading subject matter experts, provided early access to bodies like the UK AISI, and obtained independent assessments from industry experts like Apollo, Vaultis, Dreadnode and more. For more information, see the Gemini 3 model card.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The next era of Gemini&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is just the start of the Gemini 3 era. As of today, Gemini 3 starts rolling out:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For everyone in the Gemini app and for Google AI Pro and Ultra subscribers in AI Mode in Search&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For developers in the Gemini API in AI Studio, our new agentic development platform, Google Antigravity; and Gemini CLI&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For enterprises in Vertex AI and Gemini Enterprise&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Gemini 3 Deep Think mode, we’re taking extra time for safety evaluations and input from safety testers before making it available to Google AI Ultra subscribers in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We plan to release additional models to the Gemini 3 series soon so you can do more with AI. We look forward to getting your feedback and seeing what you learn, build and plan with Gemini.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.google/products/gemini/gemini-3/"/><published>2025-11-18T16:00:33+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45968043</id><title>Gemini 3 for developers: New reasoning, agentic capabilities</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:45.390383+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d57a34d93b79a8d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Start building with Gemini 3&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today we are introducing Gemini 3, our most intelligent model that can help bring any idea to life. Built on a foundation of state-of-the-art reasoning, Gemini 3 Pro delivers unparalleled results across every major AI benchmark compared to previous versions. It also surpasses 2.5 Pro at coding, mastering both agentic workflows and complex zero-shot tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro fits right into existing production agent and coding workflows, while also enabling new use cases not previously possible. It’s available in preview at $2/million input tokens and $12/million output tokens for prompts 200k tokens or less through the Gemini API in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI for enterprises (see pricing for rate limits and full pricing details). Additionally, it can be utilized via your favorite developer tools within the broader ecosystem and is available, with rate limits, free of charge in Google AI Studio.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Agentic coding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developers are spending more and more time creating software with AI at their side. Building on the momentum of Gemini 2.5 Pro and all the feedback, Gemini 3 Pro serves as a new foundation of intelligence for what’s possible with an agentic coding model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro scores 54.2% points on Terminal-Bench 2.0, which tests a model’s tool use ability to operate a computer via terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can feel the power of this model come to life in Google Antigravity, our new agentic development platform, in addition to Gemini CLI, Android Studio, and other coding products like Cursor, GitHub, JetBrains, Manus, Cline and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Google Antigravity&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To advance how the model and IDE work together, we’re introducing Google Antigravity to showcase what’s possible with Gemini 3. It’s an agentic development platform that enables developers to operate at a higher, task-oriented level by managing agents across workspaces, while retaining a familiar AI IDE experience at its core.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a faster way to develop: you act as the architect, collaborating with intelligent agents that operate autonomously across the editor, terminal, and browser. These agents plan and execute complex software tasks, communicating their work with the user via detailed artifacts. This elevates all aspects of development, from building features, UI iteration, and fixing bugs to researching and generating reports. Visit the Google Antigravity website to download the public preview at no charge, now available for MacOS, Windows and Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Gemini API&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Gemini 3, we are releasing a client-side bash tool that empowers the model to propose shell commands as part of agentic workflows for tasks such as navigating your local filesystem, driving development processes, and automating system operations. We’re pairing this with a hosted server-side bash tool for multi language code generation and secure prototyping. Available now in the Gemini API for early access partners, with general availability coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additionally, Gemini hosted tools Grounding with Google Search and URL context can now be combined with structured outputs. This is especially powerful for building agentic use cases which involve fetching and extracting data and then outputting them in a specific format for downstream agentic tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Vibe coding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro unlocks the true potential of “vibe coding”, where natural language is the only syntax you need. By significantly improving complex instruction following and deep tool use, the model can translate a high-level idea into a fully interactive app with a single prompt. It handles the heavy lifting of multi-step planning and coding details delivering richer visuals and deeper interactivity, allowing you to focus on the creative vision.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro tops the WebDev Arena leaderboard by scoring an impressive 1487 Elo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Google AI Studio&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether it’s building a game with a single prompt, an interactive landing page from unstructured voice notes, or a full on app from a napkin sketch, developers can bring their idea to life with Gemini 3. With this model, we pushed single prompt generation capabilities further than ever, meaning you can go from idea to AI-powered app with a single prompt, like this retro game built in Google AI Studio.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve built Google AI Studio to be your fastest path from a prompt to an AI-native app. Build mode lets you add AI capabilities faster than ever, automatically wiring up the right models and APIs, while features like annotations enable fast and intuitive iteration. You can start building with Gemini 3 in Google AI Studio today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Multimodal understanding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 is the best model in the world for complex multimodal understanding and sets new highs on MMMU-Pro for complex image reasoning and Video MMMU for video understanding. Combining its intelligence and a 1 million-token context window, developers can see significant improvements while building key multimodal use cases. To give you more control over latency and cost, you can now configure multimodal vision processing with more granularity in the Gemini API based on the visual fidelity required for your application.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Visual reasoning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro is best-in-class for document understanding, going beyond simple OCR (Object Character Recognition) to intelligently handle complex document understanding and reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can see the model’s vision understanding, reasoning and coding capabilities in our demo app that brings any idea to life in Google AI Studio.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Spatial reasoning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The model’s improved spatial understanding also drives strong performance in embodied reasoning tasks like pointing, trajectory prediction and task progression, unlocking new use cases across autonomous vehicles, XR devices and robotics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Its spatial reasoning also powers intelligent screen understanding of desktop, mobile and OS screens delivering significant performance improvement for computer use agents. The model also understands the intent of user actions based on mouse movements and screen annotations unlocking novel experiences like this Visual Computer demo app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Video reasoning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro captures rapid action with high-frame-rate understanding, ensuring developers never miss a critical moment in fast-moving scenes. Beyond speed, long-context recall allows for synthesizing narratives and pinpointing specific details across hours of continuous footage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Build what’s next, today&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 Pro is now integrated into many developer products and tools to seamlessly fit into your existing workflows and unlock entirely new ways to code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Build with the Gemini API: You can integrate Gemini 3 Pro immediately into your applications via Google AI Studio and Vertex AI for Enterprise. To support the model's deeper reasoning capabilities, we’re introducing a new thinking level and more granular media resolution parameters in the API, along with stricter validation for thought signatures. This update is critical for preserving the model’s thoughts across multi-turn conversations. Check out the Developer Guide for the technical breakdown and our Prompting Guide to learn how to build with Gemini 3 Pro.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Experience the model’s agentic capabilities: Whether you are adding AI-native features to an Android app, automating workflows through Gemini CLI or managing a fleet of autonomous agents in Google Antigravity, Gemini 3 Pro provides the reliability needed for complex, agentic architectures.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vibe code with Gemini 3 Pro: Google AI Studio is your fastest path to bring any idea to life. Get started in Build mode to generate a fully functional app with a single prompt. And if you need a little inspiration, click “I’m feeling lucky” and let Gemini 3 Pro handle the creative spark and the code implementation simultaneously.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The software landscape is shifting. As AI changes who builds and how they build, we are committed to meeting you where you are — giving you the tools to push the boundaries of what’s possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is just the start of the Gemini 3 era but we can’t wait to see what you build with Gemini 3 Pro!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.google/technology/developers/gemini-3-developers/"/><published>2025-11-18T16:04:12+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45968059</id><title>How long can it take to become a US citizen?</title><updated>2025-11-18T16:13:45.249272+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6ee8c55d43e04c79"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How long can it take to become a US citizen?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For some immigrants, becoming a US citizen takes a few years. For others, limited visa availability and annual country caps mean waiting decades before even applying.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s no single timeline for becoming a US citizen. For some, the journey is a few years; for others, it spans decades. Processing times, federally mandated annual visa limits, and mandatory waiting periods mean that the same goal — citizenship — is obtained in very different ways depending on where a person is from and how they begin their journey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;For some applicants, becoming a naturalized US citizen can take decades&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time to citizenship by visa category and applicant’s country of citizenship, FY 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are either born into US citizenship, or you follow the lengthy process to become one. That process first requires becoming a lawful permanent resident, better known as a “green card holder.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Citizenship and Immigration Services (USCIS) only issues green cards to people who meet certain criteria, most often through sponsorship by a family member or employer. The timeline for getting a green card is anything but predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why is the wait for a green card so unpredictable?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To gain permanent residence, aka a green card, a person must first be approved for an immigrant visa. There are several types of these visas, and some, like those for the spouses, children, and parents of US citizens, are always available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Others are limited, with only a certain number issued each year, and no more than 7% of those issued visas can go to applicants from any one country. When demand outpaces supply, applicants are placed in a queue to await an available visa.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each new applicant joins the line behind others seeking the same type of visa and their families. Because spouses and children can also be included on a visa application, each family may receive more than one visa within the annual limit. For applicants from countries with especially high demand, like India, China, Mexico, and the Philippines, that can mean waiting decades to reach the front of the line.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The main paths to a green card&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each green card path follows the same basic steps, but the pace varies. Some of the wait comes from how long it takes officials to review and approve paperwork. The rest comes from waiting for a visa to become available, since only a set number are issued each year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The family path to a green card&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Family ties are the most common path to a green card. In FY 2023, nearly 65% of new green card holders qualified through a US citizen or lawful permanent resident relative. But how long the process takes depends entirely on who that relative is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For immediate family of US citizens, such as spouses, parents, and unmarried children under 21, the process is relatively fast. These applicants are not subject to annual visa limits, so once their petition is approved, they can move straight into green card processing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other family members face a queue. The US uses a preference system for extended family, with caps that can stretch wait times into decades:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;First preference: Unmarried adult children of US citizens&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Second preference: Spouses and children of lawful permanent residents&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Third preference: Married children of US citizens&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fourth preference: Siblings of US citizens&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those final categories can take the longest. Mexican siblings of US citizens who applied in 2001 – the year that George W. Bush entered the White House – started to become eligible for green cards in September 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Spouses of US citizens can become citizens themselves decades before siblings receive green cards&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time to citizenship by applicant’s country of citizenship and relationship to a US citizen, FY 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The employment path to a green card&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Employment is the second most common path to a green card. In FY 2023, 16.7% of new green cards were issued through jobs or job offers in the US, though roughly half of those went to the workers’ spouses and children rather than the employees themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The employment route to a green card requires more steps than the family-sponsored route. Most applicants need a US employer to sponsor them. In many cases, the employer first completes a permanent labor certification, known as a PERM application, through the Labor Department to prove that hiring a foreign worker will not displace qualified US workers. That process includes confirming a government-set wage for the position, advertising the job to US candidates, and documenting the results. Once the Labor Department certifies the application, the employer can petition USCIS for the worker’s green card.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Employment-based visas are divided into three preference categories, each of which is subject to annual visa limits:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;First preference: Individuals with extraordinary ability, outstanding professors, or multinational executives. Applicants in this category do not need a PERM labor certification and may self-petition in some cases.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Second preference: Professionals with advanced degrees or exceptional ability. Most require a PERM labor certification, though some may qualify for a national interest waiver (NIW) that allows them to self-petition without an employer.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Third preference: Skilled workers, professionals, and certain other workers. These applicants typically require a PERM labor certification.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The wait time for any of these visas depends on demand and country of origin. Because of the high number of applicants and the annual and per-country limits, applicants from India and China often face waits of 10 years or more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some applicants can pay for premium processing to expedite review of initial paperwork, but that does not shorten the overall wait for a visa number. As of 2025, Indian professionals who applied for Second Preference employment visas in 2013 were only just becoming eligible for green cards because of the annual visa limits. For context, that means they applied when Barack Obama was beginning his second presidential term.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Many employment-based paths can lead to citizenship in less than 13 years, but for some Indian applicants, it can take over 20&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time to citizenship by visa category and applicant’s country of citizenship, FY 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The humanitarian aid path to a green card&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Refugees and asylees make up a smaller share of new green card holders, and their path to citizenship is among the least predictable. In FY 2023, roughly 8.5% of new green cards were granted through humanitarian protections to people who first arrived as refugees or were granted asylum after reaching the US.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both groups can apply for a green card one year after receiving refugee or asylum status, but the time it takes to reach that point may vary. The federal government does not publish comprehensive data on how long asylum or refugee cases take from application to approval, making this part of the citizenship journey difficult to measure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Becoming a naturalized citizen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Green card holders aren’t automatically placed on a path to citizenship. Some choose not to apply even when eligible, but those who do pursue it follow a relatively consistent process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;maintain permanent resident status for up to five years&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;meet physical presence and other eligibility requirements&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pass the required civics and English language tests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;take the oath of allegiance&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on FY 2025 processing times, the full journey from receiving a green card to becoming a US citizen can take three to six years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;One goal, many timelines&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s no single clock for becoming a US citizen. Each path runs on its own timeline shaped by law, policy, paperwork, and chance. The data shown here reflects how long each step in the process took under FY 2025 conditions. But those figures only describe how the system operates now, not how long it will take for those beginning the process today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Government processing capacity, policy changes, and individual circumstances all affect how long the process takes. For those subject to annual visa caps, the longest wait typically stems from the limits set by law.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s no limit on how many people can join the line awaiting a capped visa each year, so those applying now may be entering a much longer queue than those who applied years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://usafacts.org/articles/how-long-can-it-take-to-become-a-us-citizen/"/><published>2025-11-18T16:06:03+00:00</published></entry></feed>