<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:36.422122+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45902898</id><title>Project Euler</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:44.931684+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="8438e19922bbe329"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;About Project Euler&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What is Project Euler?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Project Euler is a series of challenging mathematical/computer programming problems that will require more than just mathematical insights to solve. Although mathematics will help you arrive at elegant and efficient methods, the use of a computer and programming skills will be required to solve most problems.&lt;lb/&gt; The motivation for starting Project Euler, and its continuation, is to provide a platform for the inquiring mind to delve into unfamiliar areas and learn new concepts in a fun and recreational context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Who are the problems aimed at?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The intended audience include students for whom the basic curriculum is not feeding their hunger to learn, adults whose background was not primarily mathematics but had an interest in things mathematical, and professionals who want to keep their problem solving and mathematics on the cutting edge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently we have 1365127 registered members who have solved at least one problem, representing 220 locations throughout the world, and collectively using 113 different programming languages to solve the problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Can anyone solve the problems?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problems range in difficulty and for many the experience is inductive chain learning. That is, by solving one problem it will expose you to a new concept that may allow you to undertake a previously inaccessible problem. So determined participants will be able to slowly but surely work their way through the problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What next?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order to track your progress it is necessary to setup an account and have Cookies enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you already have an account, then Sign In. Otherwise, please Register – it's completely free!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, as the problems are challenging, you may wish to view the Problems before registering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Project Euler exists to encourage, challenge, and develop the skills and enjoyment of anyone with an interest in the fascinating world of mathematics."&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://projecteuler.net"/><published>2025-11-12T17:24:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45903161</id><title>Launch HN: JSX Tool (YC F25) – A Browser Dev-Panel IDE for React</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:44.443820+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ae4ab77c7123cd5c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi HN, We’re Jamie &amp;amp; Dan, building JSX Tool (&lt;/p&gt;https://jsxtool.com&lt;p&gt;) a new inspector/dev panel IDE that allows you to navigate to any line of your React project’s JSX with just a click and a command click to explore your render stack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demo video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JIIXvN7vhrs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve been writing React code for nearly a decade. Since I first saw source maps in the days of Babel and Redux, I’ve always wanted to be able to edit my code from the source maps. I’ve also always wanted to be able to inspect my JSX like it was HTML.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year, I found my first real use of AI was taking ad-hoc CSS changes in the Chrome element inspector, pasting them into ChatGPT, and asking for the equivalent in Tailwind. I’d then paste those changes into my React TSX files.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wanted to streamline this process but came to the conclusion that to do so I needed to build a JSX inspector. I had to write a custom AST parser to create a mapping between the JSX and HTML. So I hacked on an inspector for a couple of months that connected JSX to the DOM in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next feature was adding a CSS editor, like the one in the browser inspectors but for JSX. Unlike styling a piece of HTML I decided that any in memory style edits to a React fiber should be globally applied, as if you had tweaked that line of code in your codebase.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, I was able to add the two AI features I really wanted: (1) prompt for in-memory styles for when I was pixel tweaking, and (2) save those temporary changes back to my codebase in the convention of the codebase I was working in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To accomplish talking to the filesystem from the Chrome extension I built a little local server that mounts from the root of your project and allows the extension to send file-system commands back to your project root. We named this the “Dev Server”. (Note: You can fully use us as a JSX inspector without this server installed.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After all that, I found that to convert myself as a user I needed it to be a pretty fully functional IDE. I needed vim bindings, I needed a typechecker, I needed auto-complete, I needed a linter, I needed code search and I needed a proper file explorer. Fortunately we were able to take advantage of the dev-server architecture we had stumbled onto in order to add an LSP server and Rip Grep. At this point, after months of dog fooding, I use JSX Tool for almost all of my website edits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re still rough around the edges for mobile but we’re working on that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of the IDE stuff not involving AI is free and works fine without AI. We let you get a taste of the prompting stuff for free but apply some rate limits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The extension itself is not open source but the dev server with the LSP is. It’s a great foundation if you want to build any sort of in-browser IDE and it's nearly React agnostic. Building the dev server was a big undertaking so I’d love to see someone fork it and find value in it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the future we want to start adding things that we are in a position to take advantage of over something like Cursor, such as letting AI give you code suggestions for runtime exceptions or work with the network logs. We think that the convenience of having your IDE in the dev panel gives us a leg up in convenience and workflow context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, regardless of how you feel about AI coding, I wanted to make something that was useful with or without AI. We’d love it if you gave it a spin and we want to share anything we can about the technical side of the product that you might find interesting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45903161"/><published>2025-11-12T17:43:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45903325</id><title>Steam Frame</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:43.799464+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="97fc7fa59f8fbace"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt; Install Steam &lt;/p&gt; login | language &lt;p&gt; 简体中文 (Simplified Chinese) 繁體中文 (Traditional Chinese) 日本語 (Japanese) 한국어 (Korean) ไทย (Thai) Български (Bulgarian) Čeština (Czech) Dansk (Danish) Deutsch (German) Español - España (Spanish - Spain) Español - Latinoamérica (Spanish - Latin America) Ελληνικά (Greek) Français (French) Italiano (Italian) Bahasa Indonesia (Indonesian) Magyar (Hungarian) Nederlands (Dutch) Norsk (Norwegian) Polski (Polish) Português (Portuguese - Portugal) Português - Brasil (Portuguese - Brazil) Română (Romanian) Русский (Russian) Suomi (Finnish) Svenska (Swedish) Türkçe (Turkish) Tiếng Việt (Vietnamese) Українська (Ukrainian) Report a translation problem &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://store.steampowered.com/sale/steamframe"/><published>2025-11-12T17:54:58+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45903404</id><title>Steam Machine</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:43.269061+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="97fc7fa59f8fbace"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt; Install Steam &lt;/p&gt; login | language &lt;p&gt; 简体中文 (Simplified Chinese) 繁體中文 (Traditional Chinese) 日本語 (Japanese) 한국어 (Korean) ไทย (Thai) Български (Bulgarian) Čeština (Czech) Dansk (Danish) Deutsch (German) Español - España (Spanish - Spain) Español - Latinoamérica (Spanish - Latin America) Ελληνικά (Greek) Français (French) Italiano (Italian) Bahasa Indonesia (Indonesian) Magyar (Hungarian) Nederlands (Dutch) Norsk (Norwegian) Polski (Polish) Português (Portuguese - Portugal) Português - Brasil (Portuguese - Brazil) Română (Romanian) Русский (Russian) Suomi (Finnish) Svenska (Swedish) Türkçe (Turkish) Tiếng Việt (Vietnamese) Українська (Ukrainian) Report a translation problem &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://store.steampowered.com/sale/steammachine"/><published>2025-11-12T17:59:43+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45903995</id><title>How Tube Amplifiers Work</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:42.206103+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a0721267a80a378a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell/&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;How Tube Amplifiers Work&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;By Rob Robinette&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Have you ever looked at the guts of a guitar amplifier and wondered what all those parts do? Well, I'll walk you through the signal flow and discuss the components in this very simple but great sounding 1950's Fender 5F1 Champ guitar amplifier. Once you understand the simple 5F1 you'll be able to understand more complicated amps. 5F1 was Fender's internal model code for the 1950's tweed Champ. Although this page discusses Guitar tube amps everything here applies to audio stereo tube amplifiers too with the goal of distortion prevention in audio amps being the biggest difference.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;5F1 Champ Amplifier&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;5F1 Chassis&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Volume control on top, Circuit Board inside, tubes on bottom: V1 Preamp Tube on right, V2 Power Tube in center, V3 Rectifier Tube on left. The Power Transformer and Output Transformer are attached to the other side of the chassis.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;WARNING: A tube amplifier chassis contains lethal high voltage even when unplugged--sometimes over 700 volts AC and 500 volts DC. If you have not been trained to work with high voltage then have an amp technician service your amp. See more tube amplifier safety info here.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;We'll start with the amplifier layout diagram. If things get too cluttered you can refer back up to this clean diagram. The guitar input jacks are at the upper right, the circuit board is in the center, the power transformer (PT) is on the left and the tubes and speaker jack are at the bottom. The output transformer (OT) is not shown but "OT In" are the output transformer primary wires and "OT Out" are the secondary wires.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;5F1 Champ Guitar Amplifier Layout Diagram&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;I added component numbers to this layout that match the schematic diagram below. Compare this to the picture of the chassis above. I have had questions about the grounding scheme shown in this layout. Grounding the V2 power tube grid leak (R9) and the power tube cathode resistor (R8) and cathode bypass cap (C6) to the first filter capacitor's ground (C3) is best practice and should result in a quieter amp. Click the image to download the pdf.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Annotated Layout With Signal Flow and Component Function&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Tracing the signal path on this layout diagram and the schematic below will help you understand how this amp works.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Signal Flow Overview&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Signal flow is shown above and below (orange arrows above, fat red line below). Signal from the guitar enters at upper right guitar Input Jack 1 or 2 and flows down to the circuit board and then to the preamp tube V1A at bottom right where the signal goes through its first stage of amplification. The signal then goes up to the circuit board and on to the volume control at top center, then back down to tube V1B (the second half of the first tube) for its second stage of amplification. From there the audio signal goes back to the circuit board then down to the power tube V2 for the third stage of amplification. V2's output goes out the blue wire to the output transformer (not shown) for a current boost, then from the output transformer via the green wire to the speaker jack (to the right of V2) and on to the speaker. I have added component numbers to the layout diagram above that match the schematic below.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Annotated Weber 5F1 Schematic&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The signal flow in red seems much simpler on the amp's schematic. Component numbers match the Layout diagram above. V1A is one half of tube V1, V1B is the other half. Voltages shown are approximate. Click the image for the full size schematic. Click here for the clean schematic.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;These are pretty much all the symbols you'll need to know to read tube amp schematics.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;How Cathode Bypass Capacitors Work&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Long Tail Pair Phase Inverter&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ultra-Linear Output Transformers&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Impedance Mismatch Between the Power Tube and Speaker&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Magnatone 280 Amp With Stereo Harmonic Pitch-Shift Tremolo&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;How Humbucking Guitar Pickups Work&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Transistor Equivalent Circuits&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Calculating Parallel Resistance&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;How Voltage Dividers and Pots Work&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Measuring In Circuit Resistance&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Your Calculator's Engineering Mode&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;How Amps Work&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The next few paragraphs will help you visualize the flow of electrons through simple circuits. Learning to visualize the flow of individual electrons was a breakthrough for me in understating tube amplifier electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Electric guitars generate an alternating current (AC) audio signal. The guitar's pickups are small electric generators. Pickups have magnets (poles) that magnetize the metal guitar strings. The movement of the magnetic field surrounding the magnetized strings generates electricity in the pickup's coil. The coil is simply a thin insulated wire wrapped around a spool and when a magnetic field cuts through a coil of wire it generates an electric voltage (electronic pressure) and current (electron flow) in the coil's wire.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Guitar Pickup&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The black and white wires leaving the guitar pickup are the two ends of one long coil wire. A humbucker pickup is simply two of these coils connected end-to-end (in series).&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Standard Guitar Circuit&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Pickup on the left is a wire coil that generates the guitar signal. The Tone Control bleeds high frequencies to ground. The Volume Pot is wired as a variable voltage divider. The Volume Pot bleeds guitar signal to ground to lower the guitar's output volume.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;I've been asked many times, "What is voltage?" It's pretty simple really. Like electrical charges repel the same way like magnetic poles repel. So if you cram a bunch of negatively charged electrons together onto the metal plates of a battery their negative charges repel one other--they want elbow room. The tighter they are packed together the higher the pressure so I like to think of negative voltage as electron pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A quick note about 'Conventional Current Flow.' In electric circuits negatively charged electrons actually flow from the negative '-' battery terminal to the positive '+' terminal. That's right, the electricity in your car flows from the battery's - terminal through the ground wire, through the car's body, through the radio's ground wire to the radio and then through the positive power wire back to the battery. The problem is that Benjamin Franklin guessed wrong on the polarity and direction of electrical flow so conventionally we think of electricity as flowing from + to -. People say electric current flows + to - (conventional current flow) but electrons flow - to +. With tube electronics it's easier to think in terms of how the electrons are really moving in order to understand them.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;If you connect a wire across a battery's terminals the jammed together electrons in the negative terminal see the wire as a pipe with lots of room so they flow down the wire. When you have an 'excess' of electrons tightly packed together you have negative voltage. When you have a 'scarcity' of electrons, or electrons are pulled apart from one another, you have a positive voltage.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When I think about a wire with very high positive voltage on it I imagine the wire as an empty pipe with very few electrons in it with lots of 'elbow room' so electrons really want to flow into that wire. Ground or earth represents an unlimited supply of electrons at zero volts (or neutral voltage). Touch that high voltage wire wire to a ground and the electrons hanging out there will rush in to fill the void of electrons in the wire. Voltage is the force of electrons wanting to move from a conductor crowded with electrons to a conductor with fewer electrons and more elbow room. Current is the measure of how many electrons are flowing through a conductor--the more electrons flowing, the higher the current. Keep this in mind when thinking about amp circuits, high voltage is an extreme scarcity of electrons and ground represents an unlimited supply of electrons.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;As a guitar string vibrates it moves one way and generates a positive voltage in the pickup coil, then as the string reverses direction the voltage is reversed and a negative voltage is generated. This occurs with every string vibration so an alternating current (positive-negative-positive-negative. . .) makes up the audio signal put out by the guitar. I'll repeat that because it's a very important concept, as the guitar string moves one direction over the guitar pickup coil it generates a negative voltage (excess electrons), then as the string reverses direction the electron pressure (voltage) and electron flow (current) reverses too and a positive voltage is generated (scarcity of electrons) and this repeats with every vibration of the string creating an Alternating Current (AC) electrical signal. This is why guitar audio signals are AC, or alternating current--as the strings alternate their direction of travel the signal voltage alternates between + and -. This tiny little AC signal is what the guitar amp will amplify until it's strong enough to move a speaker cone in and out. The speaker cone alternates in and out with the alternating current from the guitar's pickup coil. For every guitar string movement there is a corresponding speaker cone movement.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;An AC guitar audio signal on a wire alternates between positive and negative voltage. A negative signal voltage packs electrons closer together (excess of electrons = negative voltage). The positive half of the AC guitar signal pulls electrons apart and creates a scarcity of electrons. Remember, voltage = electron pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;If you graph a guitar audio signal the pitch of the guitar string's sound is expressed as wave spacing (frequency) and loudness is expressed as wave height (amplitude). A high frequency sound will have tight wave spacing and a low frequency sound will have wide wave spacing. In the graph below the high E string is on the left and the low E is on the right. A quiet sound will have short waves and a loud sound will have tall waves.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The direct relationship between string movement and electricity generated in the pickup coil is the key to understanding guitar amplification. Our guitar amplifier will simply make the electric audio waves taller to boost their loudness.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When multiple strings are played the multiple electric waves are summed into complex waves. See my short youtube video to see guitar audio on an oscilloscope.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Guitar AC Voltage Audio Signal&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Fender Stratocaster connected directly to an oscilloscope. Each 'wave' on the oscilloscope is caused by one string vibration. The highest voltage (peak of wave) is created by the fastest string speed when it's moving directly over the pickup. The zero voltage point (center of graph) is when the string stops moving and reverses its direction. The left side of the graph shows a high open E string pluck followed by a pluck of the low open E. Voltage is on the left scale and time runs along the bottom. The top half of the signal is positive voltage and the bottom half is negative. The signal's voltage and current alternate between positive and negative. The tight wave spacing on the left is an indication of high frequency and pitch. The wave height is an indication of power and loudness. The high open E + low open E strings' signal on the right is a summation of the two strings' signals combined into a complex wave--the high open E wave is 'written' onto the large low open E wave. The speaker cone will move just like this graph. Every little twitch on that line makes the speaker cone twitch. When the graph goes high with a positive voltage the speaker cone moves outward, when the graph goes low with a negative voltage the cone moves inward.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;WARNING&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Amplifiers have large capacitors that store enough electricity to kill even when the amplifier is unplugged. If you open an amplifier you MUST verify no voltage remains in the capacitors before working inside it.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Guitar Audio Signal Input&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The guitar cable's tip conductor connects to the input jack's "T" tip terminal. The cable's sleeve connects to the "G" ground terminal. The guitar signal travels down the wire and through grid stopper resistor R3.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The guitar's alternating current audio signal enters the amplifier at guitar input jack 1 or 2. 1 is the Hi input and 2 is the Lo, -6dB quieter input. Resistor R1 on jack 1 is the 'input resistor.' It sets the amp's input impedance to 1,000,000 ohms (1M) to boost the signal voltage from the guitar. [Bonus info: R1 also functions as the 'grid leak' resistor for Tube V1A's grid. A grid leak drains off unwanted DC voltage to keep the tube's control grid near 0 DC volts.] The '1M' written on R1 is its rating of 1 megaohm. See more on impedance here and see this web page for grad school level information on how Fender multiple input jacks and jumpering channels works.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The signal moves from the guitar jacks down the yellow wires to resistors R2 or R3, which are 'grid stopper' resistors. They help stabilize the amplifier by removing much of the audio signal above human hearing. The "68K" written on the resistor refers to its resistance value of 68,000 ohms or 68 kilohms. [Bonus info: R2 and R3 also act as 'mixing resistors' and prevent interaction between two simultaneous inputs like two guitars or a guitar and microphone. Sometimes you will see resistor values written as 1K5 which simply means 1.5 kilohms.]&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Preamp Stage&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Signal from resistor R3 travels down the wire to tube V1A's grid (pin 2) then out the plate to coupling capacitor C1. Tube V1 is split into two identical halves, A &amp;amp; B.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;After going through grid stopper resistor R3 the audio signal flows down the wire to the preamp tube's control grid, which is the entry to the 'A' half of the preamp tube (V1A). It's called V1A because tubes were called 'Valves' and this is tube number 1 and we're using the 'A' half of the tube. 12AX7 is the type of tube which happens to be the most popular preamp tube in use and it's really two tubes in one.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;I recommend you now read How Tubes Work and come back here when finished.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The preamp tube amplifies the guitar audio signal then sends it out pin 1 (plate) up the yellow wire to capacitor C1, which is a 'coupling capacitor' or 'cap.' Coupling caps are sometimes also called 'blocking caps' because they block DC voltage but allow the AC guitar signal to pass. The 0.022uF written on the cap is it's rating of 0.022 microfarads (0.000,000,022 Farads). In some old documents you'll see "micro-micro" or "uu" which means pico Farad.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Use this chart to help convert capacitor size such as: .1uF = 100nF and 1nF = 1000pF.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Capacitors are made of two conductive plates separated by an insulator or dielectric. Common dielectrics are mica, polypropylene, ceramic and even paper and oil.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;How capacitors block DC but let AC pass: Caps are made with sandwiched but separated conductive plates. The separated plates cannot flow DC current but AC fluctuates between positive and negative voltage. When the AC guitar signal negative voltage (excess electrons) is applied to the input plate the electrons repel electrons on the output plate so they move off the plate and flow out of the capacitor. When a positive voltage is applied (scarcity of electrons) to the input plate the output plate attracts electrons so electrons flow into the capacitor.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;That's how capacitors really work but I like to visualize them as having a stretchable rubber membrane inside that blocks the flow of electricity. When voltage is applied to a capacitor the 'rubber membrane' stretches and bulges as electrons try to flow through it. The higher the voltage the more the membrane bulges. If you quickly reverse the capacitor's voltage polarity it will go from bulging one way to bulging the other way. This is what a small AC signal does--it stretches the 'membrane' back and forth as the voltage alternates which allows electrons on both sides of the capacitor to move back and forth (alternate) but a constant DC voltage that is trying to flow in one direction will be blocked by the membrane.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;If you are familiar with hydraulics a coupling capacitor is like a piston in a hydraulic line. Small alternating pressure changes will make the piston move back and forth so fluid is moved on both sides of the piston -- this is how small alternating current signals move through a capacitor.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;High voltage DC (direct current) power used by the tube is brought in through resistor R5, which is a 'load resistor.' We'll discuss the function of the load resistor later. The wire between tube pin 1 (plate) and R5 carries up to 250 volts DC. That wire carries both the AC audio signal out and the high voltage DC power the tube needs in. Coupling capacitor C1 allows the AC audio signal to pass through but blocks the DC on the wire and keeps it out of the volume pot.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Volume and Output Stage Driver&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Signal flows from capacitor C1 to the Volume pot then down the orange wire to tube V1B's grid (pin 7) then out the plate (pin 6) to capacitor C2, then to a fork in the road--resistor R9 one way and the other way down the yellow wire to the power tube V2.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;After going through capacitor C1 the audio signal flows up the yellow wire to the volume potentiometer (pot) which acts as a variable voltage divider. Volume knob left = more signal bled to ground and lower volume. Volume knob right = less signal bled to ground and higher volume. [Bonus info: The volume pot also functions as V1B's grid leak resistor] For more info see voltage dividers and potentiometers.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The signal then flows from the volume pot down the orange wire all the way to tube V1B's pin 7 (grid). V1B is the second half of the preamp tube. This second gain stage is called the output stage driver because it boosts the signal to the level needed by the power tube. The audio signal leaves tube V1B via pin 6 (plate) and flows up the yellow wire to capacitor C2, another coupling cap that blocks DC. High voltage DC is fed to the tube via load resistor R7. After C2 the signal flows down the yellow wire to the power tube's pin 5 (grid). Resistor R9 has a dual function. It adds input impedance to the power tube amplifier circuit and acts as the tube's 'grid leak' resistor which keeps the grid at 0 volts DC.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Power Tube to Output Transformer to Speaker Jack&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Signal leaves V2's pin 3 and flows out the blue wire to the Output Transformer's primary winding then out the secondary winding to the speaker jack.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The power tube, V2 is sometimes referred to as the output tube. V2 is the final stage of amplification and its purpose is to amplify for power (voltage x current) where V1A and V1B were focused on voltage amplification. The signal enters the power tube at pin 5 (grid) and leaves via pin 3 (plate). It then goes to the output transformer (OT) which is mounted on the backside of the chassis and is not shown on the layout diagram.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Like we saw with the guitar's pickup, magnetism can be used to generate electricity in a coil. You can also do the reverse and pass electricity through a coil and generate magnetism. The amplifier's output transformer uses both of these principles to pass alternating current (AC) from its primary (input) winding to the iron core as magnetic flux and on to the secondary (output) winding as alternating current.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The output transformer's windings are really just two wire coils wrapped around an iron core. The input, or primary winding uses electric current flowing through it to generate a magnetic field or flux. This magnetic field fluctuates with the guitar AC signal voltage and is captured by the transformer's iron core. The captured magnetic flux flowing through the core generates a voltage and current in the secondary winding. You can alter the voltage and current from primary to secondary by changing the ratio of coil wraps from primary coil to secondary.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Transformers&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Current flowing into the primary winding (above left) induces magnetic flux flow around the transformer iron core which in turn induces an electric voltage and current in the secondary winding. Put fewer wire wraps on the secondary (output) winding and its voltage will decrease (step down) but its current will increase. Most guitar amp transformers are of the 'double window' type (bottom of left diagram) and made with laminated iron magnetic cores. 5F1 transformers are shown on the right. The Power Transformer is lying on its side while the Output Transformer is standing vertically. Positioning transformers 90º out of phase with one another like this reduces interference hum.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Example: The primary winding has 200 wraps of wire in its coil and the secondary has 100 wraps. If a 10 volt alternating current is applied to the primary winding the secondary will generate 1/2 of the input or 5 volts. The current will change proportionally in the opposite direction. If 1 ampere of AC current is applied to the primary the secondary will generate 2 amps. This is what an amplifier's output transformer does, it steps down the signal's voltage but steps up the current because the speaker's voice coil needs current to generate a magnetic field to move the speaker cone.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The output transformer's primary takes in a high voltage, low current signal (high impedance signal) and puts out a low voltage, high current signal (low impedance signal) through the green wire to the speaker jack and on to the speaker. For you mechanical types you can think of the output transformer as a gearbox that alters speed (voltage) and torque (current). The power tubes send large voltage swing into the output transformer and you can think of this as high speed from an "engine". The transformer gears this high speed (high speed, low torque=high voltage, low current) down for much less speed (less voltage swing) but much more torque (current).&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The alternating current audio signal flows through the speaker's voice coil which generates a magnetic field. The voice coil is simply a single wire wrapped into a coil as shown below. The magnetic field created by the voice coil is either attracted to or repelled by the speaker's magnet. Positive voltage generates a repulsive magnetic force and the speaker coil and cone moves outward away from the speaker magnet, negative voltage generates an attractive magnetic force and pulls the speaker cone inward. The speaker cone alternates between moving outward and inward as the signal voltage alternates between positive and negative. For every guitar string movement there is a corresponding speaker cone movement.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Speaker Voice Coil is an Electromagnet&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Electric current flowing through the speaker's voice coil generates a magnetic field. When the electric current in the voice coil reverses, the magnetic field also reverses causing attraction and repulsion to the speaker magnet.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;This magnetic attraction and repulsion moves the voice coil and speaker cone back and forth to create air pressure waves that our ears perceive as sound--the sweet sound of electric guitar. When the speaker cone moves outward a positive air pressure wave is created and when the cone moves inward a negative (low pressure) wave trough is generated. These air pressure waves move our ear drums in and out. The ear drum movement is translated into neuron activity which is sent to the brain where pleasure is created, thus electric guitar + amp = pleasure ;)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Bonus Info: You can determine the ohm rating of a guitar speaker by measuring the DC ohms (resistance) between the speaker terminals (while disconnected from the amp) and then multiply by 1.2. Example: You measure 6.5 ohms: 6.5 x 1.2 = 7.8 ohms = 8 ohm speaker.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Speaker&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The 'voice coil' is an electromagnet that interacts with the speaker magnet. The 'spider' supports the voice coil but allows it to move in and out freely. This excellent DIY speaker recone video shows speaker parts and function in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Bonus Info: How Microphones Work&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dynamic microphones work exactly in reverse of how a speaker works. They have a diaphragm like a speaker cone that gets moved by sound (air pressure waves). The diaphragm moves a coil of wire wrapped around a magnet. The coil moving through the magnetic field creates electricity in the coil wire--an alternating current signal voltage.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Microphone&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When the microphone diaphragm moves the coil, electricity is generated.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When a singer sings a note her vocal chords vibrate like a guitar string. The movement of the vocal chords create air pressure waves that strike the microphone diaphragm and cause it to move. Speaking of diaphragms, our ear drums are diaphragms that when moved by sound waves cause neurons to fire to communicate with our brain. Yea, our ears are biological dynamic microphones.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When a positive, high pressure sound wave hits the microphone diaphragm it is pushed inward and a positive electrical current and voltage are created. When the low pressure wave trough hits the diaphragm it is pulled outward and a negative current and voltage are created in the coil. The microphone creates an alternating current voltage signal similar to an electric guitar AC voltage signal.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Negative Feedback&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The 5F1 amplifier uses negative feedback (NFB) to reduce distortion, increase headroom, decrease damping factor and improve stability but a drawback is it also reduces overall amplifier gain. Negative feedback works by taking the speaker output voltage and feeding it back into the amp's signal stream before the driver or phase inverter circuit. A feedback resistor reduces the voltage to a suitable level before it joins the amp's signal stream. It's negative feedback because the signal is out of phase so when it's injected into the amp's signal stream it reduces the amp's signal voltage.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A green wire running from the 5F1's speaker jack carries the amplified audio signal through resistor R13 and injects the feedback at V1B's pin 8 (cathode). Resistor R13 is the Feedback Resistor and controls the level of feedback voltage passed to the cathode. Adding a switch to the NFB circuit is a common modification. Removing feedback makes an amp more aggressive with earlier break up and distortion at lower volume levels.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;So the main purpose of a guitar amplifier is to take the tiny AC electrical signal generated by the guitar's pickup coil and make it strong enough to push and pull a speaker cone. The guitar amp is also used to shape the tone and control signal distortion giving us the clean, mellow sound of jazz guitar or the animal growl of hard rock. Distortion is an important part of guitar amplifier design and this is the primary difference between guitar and audio amplifiers. Audio amps are usually designed for absolute minimum distortion.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Power Supply&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Now that we've covered the signal flow I'll go back and cover the other amplifier components that I didn't mention. Wall plug power of 120 volts AC (USA or 100, 220 or 240 volts AC in other countries) runs to the fuse F1. Fender guitar amp fuses are MDL type "slow blow" or "time delay", size 3AG, 1/4 inch (6mm) wide by 1 1/4 inch (30mm) long. The fuse is a 250 volt, 2 amp slow blow fuse. Slow blow means it won't blow instantaneously when the turn-on power surge runs through it. Sustained current greater than 2 amps is required to blow the fuse. Next the power flows to the power switch S1, which is located on the volume pot.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;120 AC volts RMS (average) wall power equals 169.7 volts peak (Vp) and 339.4 volts peak-to-peak (Vpp).&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Bonus Info: Alternating Current (AC) voltage is normally given in volts RMS (root-mean-square), which is a form of voltage averaging equal to a DC voltage. Always consider AC voltage as RMS unless it is specified as peak Vp or peak-to-peak Vpp. Multimeters show voltage in RMS. Our standard 120 volts AC wall power is RMS. You can convert RMS voltage to peak voltage by multiplying RMS by 1.414, so 120 volts AC at the wall is actually 169.7 volts measured from the + wave peak to 0. You can convert peak voltage to RMS by multiplying by 0.707. To convert RMS voltage to peak-to-peak voltage you multiply RMS by 2.828, so 120 volts AC at the wall is actually 339.4 volts measured from the + wave peak to the - wave peak. You can convert peak-to-peak to RMS by multiplying by 0.354.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;AC voltage in the United States runs at 60 cycles per second, which is called Hertz (Hz). 120 volt wall power goes from zero to +169.7 volts, then down through zero to -169.7 volts, then back up to zero 60 times per second. This is why AC electrical noise picked up by guitar amps is often described as a 60 Hertz hum. Why is our wall power 60 cycles per second? Because power company electrical generators in the US turn at 60 revolutions per second (3600 revolutions per minute or RPM).&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Bonus Bonus Info: Visualizing Alternating Current. One way to visualize how AC electricity flows is to think of the amplifier's power system as a rope and pulley system. Think of the wall power plug and the amplifier's power transformer as pulleys. A loop of rope representing the hot and neutral wires would be wrapped tightly around the wall power and transformer pulleys.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The power company's AC generator is like a hand grabbing the power rope (hot wire) and pushing it forward a few feet then stopping the rope movement and pulling the rope back, then pushing the rope again, then pulling it in this alternating pattern (doing one push-pull cycle 60 times per second). Electrons actually alternate their movement forward and backward, reversing course through AC wires and circuits like this rope movement.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Bonus Bonus Bonus Info: 240 volt circuits in the United States use two 120 volt hot wires instead of 120 volt's single hot wire and ground (called neutral). For 240 volts one wire pushes at +120 volts while the other pulls at -120 volts (like using two hands, one hand on each of the two ropes in the analogy above), then they alternate the pushing and pulling at the same 60 cycles per second for 240 volts of power. Alright, back to the amplifier. . .&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;After the amp's fuse and On/Off switch the 120v AC RMS runs to the power transformer (PT), through its primary winding, then back to the wall plug via the white Neutral wire. The white Neutral wire is a ground wire and is connected to the same ground as the Safety Ground wire at the building's electrical service entrance.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The 5F1's power transformer high voltage winding is rated at 325-0-325v. This means the transformer has a grounded 0 volt center tap and simultaneously puts out +325 volts AC RMS on one secondary winding wire and -325v on the other for a 650 volt AC RMS wire-to-wire voltage (650 volts AC RMS = 1,838 volts peak-to-peak :O ). Yes, that's high voltage that can kill you. At this very high voltage the 5F1 power transformer only needs to be rated for a paltry 70 milliamps (0.070 amp) max AC current to run the amp circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The power transformer has three secondary windings. The first winding as discussed above steps the 120v RMS AC wall power up to 325 volts RMS AC. Two other small secondary windings step the 120v AC down to 6.3 volts RMS AC and 5 volts RMS AC. Notice all voltages in transformer secondaries are always AC because a transformer can't pass DC from primary to secondary. The 6.3 volts are used to power the pilot light and heat the preamp and power tubes' heater filaments which heat the tubes' cathodes. The 5 volts are used to directly heat the rectifier tube's cathode.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Bonus Info: When I first learned that the power transformer primary coil was made up of one long wire that directly connects the 120v hot wire to the neutral (ground) wire I wondered why it didn't short out. The reason is the primary and secondary coils are coupled together by the transformer's iron core. Alternating current in the primary coil creates a magnetic field or flux that is captured by the core. That flux in the core creates an AC voltage in the secondary coil. The load (impedance) placed on the secondary winding by the amplifier is transferred through the core to the primary coil. That impedance keeps the primary coil from "shorting out."&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Power Cord Wiring&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Modern U.S. wall cords and sockets have a narrow blade for Hot (black wire 120v), a wide blade for Neutral (white wire ground), and a round or 'D' shaped prong for the chassis Safety Ground (green wire ground). Power cord wire colors are sometimes non-standard so use a multimeter to identify Hot and Neutral. Europeans sometimes use the letters E: Earth (safety ground), L: Line (hot) and N: Neutral to describe the three plug wires.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The 325 volts AC power from the power transformer is fed directly into V3, the rectifier tube. V3 is a full wave dual plate rectifier tube that converts alternating current (AC) into direct current (DC). The power transformer and rectifier work together as an electron pump which pulls electrons out of the amp circuit creating a positive voltage (electron scarcity = positive voltage). The amplifier's electronics need DC to amplify. The amp is powered by DC but the guitar signal moving through the amp is AC.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The flow of power starts at the power transformer at far left. 325V AC on each high voltage secondary wire powers the V3 rectifier tube. V3 puts out 360V of DC. Note the yellow wires running to V1's pins 1 &amp;amp; 6 carry both high voltage DC power into the tube and the AC signal out (orange arrows). This diagram shows "conventional" current flow but the actual electrons flow in the opposite direction.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;360 volts of DC flows out of V3's pin 8 (cathode) and is referred to as B+ voltage (from old Battery Positive designation). Tube rectifiers are popular in guitar amps due to their dynamic power sag which adds to the amp's playing dynamics and note "bloom". Audio stereo tube amps usually use solid state rectifiers to reduce voltage sag that would be seen as distortion to the Hi Fi listener.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The B+ DC voltage flows to the output transformer's primary winding and to the circuit board's three large filter/reservoir capacitors, C3, C4 and C5 and two voltage dropping resistors, R10 &amp;amp; R11. These resistors and capacitors form RC (resistance capacitance) low pass filters that take the lumpy, pulsing DC output of the rectifier tube and smooth it out--the smoother the better. Any waves or ripples left over in the DC power would be added to our audio signal and heard as hum in the preamp and power tubes. These big capacitors also function as current reservoirs that help feed the amp during high demand. The hydraulic equivalent of a filter capacitor is a hydraulic accumulator. The '16µF 475V' written on the cap is its rating of 16 micro Farads and 475 volts. The '10K 2W' written on resistor R10 is its rating of 10,000 ohms and 2 watts. Here's an online RC Ripple Filter Calculator.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The voltage dropping resistors separate the amp's power into three power supply nodes, B+1, B+2 and B+3. The 360 volts DC from the rectifier is B+1 then it's stepped down to 325 volts DC (B+2) then to 250 volts DC (B+3). The 360 volts DC B+1 direct from the rectifier is fed to the output transformer's primary input which flows on to the power tube plates. The 325 volts DC B+2 is connected to the power tube pin 4--the screen grid. The 250 volts DC B+3 is used to power the preamp tube. The filter capacitors and voltage dropping resistors also decouple the three B+ power nodes to prevent interaction, feedback and oscillation between the preamp stages and power tube. With no guitar signal present the 'idle' voltage at the V1 preamp tube's plate pins 1 and 6 will be around 170 volts DC after flowing through the Load Resistors R5 and R7.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;How Chokes Work&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Although the Champ does not use a choke many amps do use them to filter the power supply. Typically the choke is placed between the power tube plate and power tube screen power nodes. This is done as a cost savings measure. A choke would have to be very large and expensive to filter the entire power supply for a 50 or 100 watt amplifier.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When electrical current flows through a wire it creates a magnetic field around the wire. Chokes are inductors that use this magnetic field to reduce changes in voltage and current. When no current flows through a wire (you can have voltage but no current) there is no magnetic field generated around the wire. When current increases some of the current will be used to grow a magnetic field around the wire. When current decreases the magnetic field shrinks and the magnetic energy is converted into electrical current. These inductor properties "fight" current changes.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A choke is simply one long wire wound in many loops. A choke will have two leads which are simply the two ends of the one long wire. The wire is usually looped around an iron core which makes it work better. Looping the wire increases the effect of the induced magnetic field ("inductor" comes from the word "induced").&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When power supply voltage ripple flows through a choke, the choke "fights" the ripple. As ripple voltage increases, ripple current increases through the choke. The choke will convert some of the current increase into a magnetic field. The choke's magnetic field is stored energy. As the power supply ripple voltage decreases the choke's magnetic field collapses and converts into current. So increasing voltage and current are cut, and decreasing voltage and current are reinforced which reduces the amplitude of voltage ripple.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;This simple looped wire is a small air core inductor.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Inductors in AC circuits work the same way. Inductance "fights" changes in current and AC audio signals are made up of voltage and current changes. A small inductor can remove high frequencies. A larger value inductor can remove medium and high frequencies. A very high value inductor, like the choke in power supplies, can remove all audio frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Amp Total Power Usage&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;How is it that the 5F1 Champ uses 0.75 amps of 6.3 volt current, 2 amps of 5 volt current and 42ma of high voltage current and yet it uses a 2 amp fuse? It's due to power conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;This is the power conversion for the 5F1 Champ&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;First we will convert the current from amps to watts:&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Champ's 5Y3 rectifier tube datasheet shows it uses 2 amps of 5v heater current: 2a x 5v = 10 watts (this is also be called 10 VA)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The 6V6GT power tube datasheet shows it 0.45 amps of 6.3v heater current: 0.45a x 6.3v = 2.835 watts&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The 12AX7 datasheet shows it uses 0.3 amps of 6.3v heater current: 0.3a x 6.3v = 1.89 watts&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The amp uses 42ma of high voltage DC.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;We have a typical 19v drop across the 470 ohm power tube cathode resistor: 19v / 470 = 40ma&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;We have a 1.5v drop across both of the 12AX7 cathode resistors: 1.5v / 1.5k = 1ma each, 2ma total&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;42ma x 370v = 15.5 watts&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Total the watts: 10w + 2.835w + 1.89w + 15.5w = 30.225 watts of power used by the power transformer secondaries.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Now we convert the secondary watts to primary watts:&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;If our mains voltage is 125 volts then 30.225w / 125v = 0.24 amps of mains current. We can estimate that the transformer looses about 10% for a total of 0.26 amps, so a 2 amp fuse has a lot of headroom for turn-on power surge.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;If our mains voltage is 240 volts then 30.225w / 240v = 0.13 amps + 0.01 amp efficiency loss for a total of 0.14 amps, so a 1 amp fuse could be used.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Well that's it for the 5F1 Champ. It's a great sounding but simple guitar amp. The signal flow is very similar to most other Fender amps, they just have more parts. Really understanding the 5F1 will help you understand other more complex amps.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Fender Original 5F1 Layout and Schematic&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;5E3 Tweed Deluxe Annotated Schematic&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The 5E3 Deluxe is the most common tube amp kit available. It uses two 6V6GT power tubes in a Class AB push-pull configuration. Click the image to view the full size (readable) annotated schematic.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;5E3 Layout with Signal Flow and Annotations&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Notice how convoluted the signal path is compared to the schematic. Input jacks are at top right and the speaker jack is bottom center. Click the image to view the full size (readable) annotated layout.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;The Pinnacle of tweed Amps, the 1959 5F6-A Bassman with Annotations&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;My 5F6-A Bassman amp is the sweetest amp I have ever heard. See this for an explanation of How the Bassman Works.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Bonus Info: How Fender multiple guitar input jacks and channel jumpering works&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell/&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://robrobinette.com/How_Amps_Work.htm"/><published>2025-11-12T18:35:59+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45904551</id><title>GPT-5.1: A smarter, more conversational ChatGPT</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:42.005782+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9d1fea781db6c8bf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GPT-5.1: A smarter, more conversational ChatGPT&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re upgrading GPT‑5 while making it easier to customize ChatGPT. Starting to roll out today to everyone, beginning with paid users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today we’re upgrading the GPT‑5 series with the release of:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GPT‑5.1 Instant: our most-used model, now warmer, more intelligent, and better at following your instructions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GPT‑5.1 Thinking: our advanced reasoning model, now easier to understand and faster on simple tasks, more persistent on complex ones.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We heard clearly from users that great AI should not only be smart, but also enjoyable to talk to. GPT‑5.1 improves meaningfully on both intelligence and communication style.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re also making it easier for you to shape ChatGPT’s tone. Preferences on chat style vary—from person to person and even from conversation to conversation—so we’re introducing more intuitive and effective controls so ChatGPT can better match the tone you want in responses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPT‑5.1 Instant, ChatGPT’s most used model, is now warmer by default and more conversational. Based on early testing, it often surprises people with its playfulness while remaining clear and useful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GPT-5&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GPT-5.1 Instant&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve also improved instruction following, so the model more reliably answers the question you actually asked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GPT-5&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GPT-5.1 Instant&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the first time, GPT‑5.1 Instant can use adaptive reasoning to decide when to think before responding to more challenging questions, resulting in more thorough and accurate answers, while still responding quickly. This is reflected in significant improvements on math and coding evaluations like AIME 2025 and Codeforces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re also upgrading GPT‑5 Thinking to make it more efficient and easier to understand in everyday use. It now adapts its thinking time more precisely to the question—spending more time on complex problems while responding more quickly to simpler ones. In practice, that means more thorough answers for difficult requests and less waiting for simpler ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPT‑5.1 Thinking’s responses are also clearer, with less jargon and fewer undefined terms. This makes our most capable model more approachable and easily understandable, especially for complex tasks at work and explaining technical concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GPT-5&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GPT-5.1 Thinking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPT‑5.1 Thinking’s default tone is also warmer and more empathetic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GPT-5&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GPT-5.1 Thinking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This release is a step forward in both capability and usability across the models. GPT‑5.1 Auto will continue to route each query to the model best suited for it, so in most cases, you won’t need to choose a model at all. What you will notice is that answers across GPT‑5.1 feel both smarter and more natural in tone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPT‑5.1 Instant and Thinking begin rolling out today, starting with paid (Pro, Plus, Go, Business) users and then to free and logged-out users. Enterprise and Edu plans get a seven-day early-access toggle (off by default). After that window, GPT‑5.1 will become the sole default model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you check ChatGPT today, you may not see GPT‑5.1 available immediately. We plan to roll it out gradually over the next few days to help keep performance stable for everyone. We will also update GPT‑5 Pro to GPT‑5.1 Pro soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re bringing both GPT‑5.1 Instant and GPT‑5.1 Thinking to the API later this week. GPT‑5.1 Instant will be added as gpt-5.1-chat-latest, and GPT‑5.1 Thinking will be released as GPT‑5.1 in the API, both with adaptive reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPT‑5 (Instant and Thinking) will remain available in ChatGPT under the legacy models dropdown for paid subscribers for three months, so people have time to compare and adapt at their own pace. The GPT‑5 sunset period does not affect the availability of other legacy models. Going forward, when we introduce new ChatGPT models, our approach is to give people ample space to evaluate what’s changed and share feedback, allowing us to continue innovating our frontier models while transitioning smoothly. Sunset periods will be communicated clearly and with plenty of advance notice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPT‑5.1 is more capable and useful, and we encourage you to try it and see the difference. Our system card addendum includes more information on our safety approach for GPT‑5.1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And a note on naming: this update is called GPT‑5.1 to reflect meaningful improvements, while remaining within the GPT‑5 generation. Future iterative upgrades to GPT‑5 will follow the same pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alongside these model improvements, we’re making it easier to customize ChatGPT’s tone and style. People have strong and varied preferences in how ChatGPT should respond, and tailoring its tone to what sounds right for you should feel effortless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, we added preset options to tailor the tone of how ChatGPT responds. Today, we’re refining those options to better reflect the most common ways people use ChatGPT. Default, Friendly (formerly Listener), and Efficient (formerly Robot) remain (with updates), and we’re adding Professional, Candid, and Quirky. These options are designed to align with what we’ve learned about how people naturally steer the model, making it quick and intuitive to choose a personality that feels uniquely right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These personality settings apply across all models. The original Cynical (formerly Cynic) and Nerdy (formerly Nerd) options we introduced earlier this year will remain available unchanged under the same dropdown in personalization settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond these presets, for users who want more granular control over how ChatGPT responds, we’re also experimenting with the ability to tune ChatGPT’s characteristics directly from personalization settings—including how concise, warm, or scannable its responses are, and how frequently it uses emojis. ChatGPT can also proactively offer to update these preferences during conversations when it notices you asking for a certain tone or style, without requiring you to navigate into settings. You can adjust or remove any of these preferences at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The updated styles and tone options are rolling out today, and the ability to finetune specific characteristics is starting to roll out gradually later this week as an experiment, starting with a limited number of users. Both will continue to improve over time. Additionally, the updated GPT‑5.1 models are also better at adhering to custom instructions, giving you even more precise control over tone and behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Updates you make in personalization settings now take effect across all chats right away, including ongoing conversations, so your experience stays consistent. Before, changes to base style and tone or custom instructions only applied to conversations started afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today’s GPT‑5.1 updates and new customization options are a step toward a ChatGPT that feels like it fits you—smarter, more enjoyable to talk to, and more adaptable to your preferences. Going forward, we’ll continue improving along these dimensions—there’s much more to come.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://openai.com/index/gpt-5-1/"/><published>2025-11-12T19:05:41+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45905408</id><title>GLP-1 drugs linked to lower death rates in colon cancer patients</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:41.532092+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f6fa41ae60c98de2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GLP-1 Drugs Linked to Dramatically Lower Death Rates in Colon Cancer Patients&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Story by:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Published Date&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Story by:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Topics covered:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Share This:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Article Content&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A new University of California San Diego study offers compelling evidence that GLP-1 receptor agonists — the class of drugs behind Ozempic, Wegovy and Mounjaro, for example — may do more than regulate blood sugar and weight. In an analysis of more than 6,800 colon cancer patients across all University of California Health sites, researchers found that those taking glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) medications were less than half as likely to die within five years compared to those who weren’t on the drugs (15.5% vs. 37.1%).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study, led by Raphael Cuomo, Ph.D., associate professor in the Department of Anesthesiology at UC San Diego School of Medicine and member of UC San Diego Moores Cancer Center, used real-world clinical data from the University of California Health Data Warehouse to assess outcomes across the state’s academic medical centers. After adjusting for age, body mass index (BMI), disease severity and other health factors, GLP-1 users still showed significantly lower odds of death, suggesting a strong and independent protective effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The survival benefit appeared most pronounced in patients with very high BMI (over 35), hinting that GLP-1 drugs may help counteract the inflammatory and metabolic conditions that worsen colon cancer prognosis. Researchers believe several biological mechanisms could explain the link. Beyond regulating blood sugar, GLP-1 receptor agonists reduce systemic inflammation, improve insulin sensitivity and promote weight loss — all factors that can dampen tumor-promoting pathways. Laboratory studies also suggest that GLP-1 drugs may directly prevent cancer cell growth, trigger cancer cell death and reshape the tumor microenvironment. However, the study authors emphasize that more research is needed to confirm these mechanisms and determine whether the survival benefit observed in this real-world analysis represents a direct anti-cancer effect or an indirect result of improved metabolic health.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cuomo notes that while these results are observational, they underscore an urgent need for clinical trials to test whether GLP-1 drugs can improve cancer survival rates, especially for patients with obesity-related cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study appeared in Cancer Investigation on Nov. 11, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;You May Also Like&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Stay in the Know&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep up with all the latest from UC San Diego. Subscribe to the newsletter today.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://today.ucsd.edu/story/glp-1-drugs-linked-to-dramatically-lower-death-rates-in-colon-cancer-patients"/><published>2025-11-12T19:50:32+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45907259</id><title>Homebrew no longer allows bypassing Gatekeeper for unsigned/unnotarized software</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:40.726050+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="760419b45cb6b368"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Notifications &lt;tool-tip&gt;You must be signed in to change notification settings&lt;/tool-tip&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fork 10.7k&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Description&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Verification&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; This issue's title and/or description do not reference a single formula e.g. &lt;code&gt;brew install wget&lt;/code&gt;. If they do, open an issue at https://github.com/Homebrew/homebrew-core/issues/new/choose instead.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Provide a detailed description of the proposed feature&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;--no-quarantine&lt;/code&gt; is used to forcibly bypass Gatekeeper, which is a built-in macOS security mechanism. This is used to run unsigned/unnotarized applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;macOS Tahoe is the final release to support Intel systems, and last year Apple updated macOS runtime protection to make it harder to override Gatekeeper. Macs with Apple silicon also don't "permit native arm64 code to execute unless a valid signature is attached". Finally, we are ending support for all casks that fail Gatekeeper checks on September 1st, 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the above in mind, it's time to deprecate the &lt;code&gt;--no-quarantine&lt;/code&gt; flag from &lt;code&gt;brew&lt;/code&gt;. It intentionally bypasses macOS security mechanisms, which we already actively discourage. Deprecating now will give a decent lead time for users using it to come up with another solution or adjust their workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What is the motivation for the feature?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intel support is coming to an end from both Apple and Homebrew. This flag is primarily used to override a macOS security mechanism, which we do not want to encourage. Since we are requiring casks fulfill Gatekeeper checks next year, there is no reason to keep this flag.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How will the feature be relevant to at least 90% of Homebrew users?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We will provide a safer experience for our users, and stop making it easier to bypass OS-level security.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What alternatives to the feature have been considered?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;None. Macs with Apple silicon are the platform that will be supported in the future, and Apple is making it harder to bypass Gatekeeper as is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/Homebrew/brew/issues/20755"/><published>2025-11-12T21:50:14+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45907541</id><title>Marble: A Multimodal World Model</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:40.120977+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1815cb1fadd45c6f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;November 12, 2025Marble, our frontier multimodal world model, is available to everyone starting today&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Marble: A Multimodal World Model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spatial intelligence is the next frontier in AI, demanding powerful world models to realize its full potential. World models should reconstruct, generate, and simulate 3D worlds; and allow both humans and agents to interact with them. Spatially intelligent world models will transform a wide variety of industries over the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two months ago we shared a preview of Marble, our World Model that creates 3D worlds from image or text prompts. Since then, Marble has been available to an early set of beta users to create 3D worlds for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today we are making Marble, a first-in-class generative multimodal world model, generally available for anyone to use. We have also drastically expanded Marble's capabilities, and are excited to highlight them here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multimodal Marble: Marble is now massively multimodal. Marble can create 3D worlds from text, images, video, or coarse 3D layouts; Marble also lets you interactively edit, expand, and combine worlds. Once generated, 3D worlds can be exported as Gaussian splats, meshes, or videos. These new capabilities let users create and edit worlds with fine-grained control; and makes those worlds more useful than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble Labs: We are launching Marble Labs, a creative hub where imagination meets experimentation. It is where artists, engineers, and designers push the boundaries of world models, showcasing bold ideas, real-world workflows, and new possibilities across gaming, VFX, design, robotics, and beyond. Marble Labs is also home to in-depth case studies, tutorials, and documentation that give anyone the tools to learn, build, and share their own 3D worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sign up at marble.worldlabs.ai and start creating worlds for yourself!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Marble World Model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our human experience of the world is inherently multimodal: we use all of our senses to make sense of the world around us. We integrate sight, sound, touch, and language to build up a mental model of the outside world; these different representations work together, enriching and reinforcing each other to let us reason about the world and act within it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;World models should work similarly. They should be massively multimodal, able to lift whatever input signals are available into a full 3D world, and they should be able to iteratively update their understanding of the world as new information becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble is the first of its kind - a next-generation world model making strides toward this vision. It can now create 3D worlds from a wide variety of input types, and lets users iteratively edit or expand worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble's new capabilities let you dive as deep as you want in controlling your generated worlds. You can quickly create full 3D worlds from a simple image or text prompt or interactively edit worlds in both 2D and 3D, bringing to life a precise vision of a world in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Text and Image to World&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To start, Marble can create a full 3D world from a single image or a short text prompt. This is the simplest and easiest way to create worlds. Marble can generate worlds with a wide variety of scene types and artistic styles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Image prompts make it easy to combine Marble with other AI tools. You can generate images with your favorite image generation model, then bring it to Marble to lift it to a full 3D world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Text and image prompts are intuitive and powerful, but limited in creative control: Marble must invent all the details of the world that are not present in the input text or image prompt. This is often magical; but sometimes you may want to steer Marble more directly toward a desired world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Multi-Image and Video to World&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An easy way to create worlds with more creative control is multi-image prompting. Marble can accept different prompt images for different parts of the world, stitching them together into a unified 3D world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multi-image prompts let you create worlds with more precision. Unlike text or single-image prompts where Marble must invent all parts of the world not present in the prompt, with multi-image prompts you can control what the generated world will look like from different angles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This leads to a brand-new workflow for generating worlds. You can use your favorite image generation tool to iterate separately on the input views, and Marble will lift them into full 3D worlds while also adding seamless transitions between the input views.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multi-image prompts can also be used to create worlds inspired by real-world spaces. Marble can input a few photos or a short video depicting a real-world location from different angles, and it will combine them to generate a 3D world with elements of the real-world space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;World Editing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The creative process is highly iterative for many users. Often, generating a world is only the start of a creative journey. Seeing a generated 3D world often kicks off a dozen more ideas for changing it or improving it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble includes AI-native world editing tools. Edits can be small and local: remove an object, touch up an area. They can also be more drastic: swap objects, change the visual style, or re-structure large parts of the world. This gives a new level of fine-grained control to the world creation process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edited&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edited&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edited&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;World editing lets you re-imagine the same space in endless different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edited&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edited&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edited&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edited&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edited&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Chisel: Sculpting Worlds in 3D&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble's multimodal inputs and editing features give a lot of control over your generated 3D worlds. But sometimes, creating the world exactly as you see it in your mind's eye requires finer-grained control over the scene layout or exact sizes and positions of objects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For these situations we are introducing Chisel, an AI-native tool to sculpt Marble worlds directly in 3D.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chisel is a new experimental editing mode for advanced users to create 3D worlds. It lets you lay out the coarse structure of your world in 3D using coarse 3D shapes like boxes or planes, or importing existing 3D assets into the scene.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After laying out the coarse 3D scene, you can add a text prompt to describe the visual style of the scene, or additional elements not present in the coarse layout. Marble will combine these inputs to give you a fully detailed 3D world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chisel decouples structure from style. The coarse 3D scene determines the world's structure, while the text prompt controls its overall style. The two can be mixed in any combination, adding a whole new dimension of control to world generation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generated World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coarse 3D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coarse 3D After&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coarse 3D Before&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generated World After&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generated World Before&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The coarse 3D scene can be as simple or complex as you want. In addition to building the coarse 3D scene out of basic blocks and walls, you can import existing 3D assets of objects. Objects will be restyled based on the text prompt to give a cohesive 3D world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Varying the text prompt can give rise to 3D worlds with drastically different visual styles and appearances that all share a common structure determined by the coarse 3D scene.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generated World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coarse 3D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generated World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coarse 3D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generated World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coarse 3D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generated World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coarse 3D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generated World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coarse 3D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generated World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coarse 3D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building Large Worlds by Expanding and Composing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes bigger really is better. Larger worlds give more possibilities, more space, more room for your creativity to shine. Marble offers two ways to make bigger worlds than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After a world has been generated, Marble allows one-step expansion to make it larger. You are in control of this process: you can select a region of the world to be expanded, and Marble will create more content to fill the selected region.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expansion can make worlds larger. Regions of the world that previously broke down into artifacts can become crisp and clean after expansion. Expansion can also be used to add detail to targeted regions of a world. Sometimes the back of a table or the far corner of a room is not a crisp as the room's center; expanding the world in that region can improve it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expanded World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initial World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expanded World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initial World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expanded World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initial World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expanded World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initial World&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to generating individual worlds, you can compose any number of worlds to build out extremely large spaces with Marble's composer mode. This composition is entirely under your control: you can choose exactly which worlds to compose, and exactly how to lay them out relative to each other. Composing is yet another way to build worlds that follow your creative vision.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Exporting Worlds to 3D and Video&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After creating a world with Marble you have many options to export it for incorporation into downstream projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gaussian splats are the highest-fidelity representation for Marble worlds. They represent 3D scenes as a large set of semitransparent particles. You can render Gaussian splats in the browser using Spark, our open-source cross-platform renderer integrated with THREE.js.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble worlds can also be exported as triangle meshes. Marble can generate both collider meshes, which are low-fidelity meshes intended for coarse physics simulation; and high-quality meshes which are intended to match the visual fidelity of Gaussian splats as closely as possible. Exporting worlds as meshes lets them interoperate with many industry-standard tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mesh&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Splats&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mesh with lighting&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mesh with lighting&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble worlds exist in full 3D, but sometimes a video is the best way to share a world. You can use Marble to render generated worlds to videos with pixel-accurate camera control, letting you frame every shot just as you imagine it. In fact, nearly all the videos in this post were generated directly from Marble.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble can also enhance exported videos. Enhanced videos can add detail, remove artifacts, and add dynamic elements to the scene, while maintaining pixel-perfect camera control and adhering to the structure of the generated 3D world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enhanced Video&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original Video&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enhanced Video&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original Video&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enhanced Video&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original Video&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Marble Labs: A Glimpse of Future Possibilities&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While flexing your creativity in Marble, Marble Labs may further inspire your imagination. This is where artists, engineers, and designers are already shaping what comes next. From cinematic filmmaking and interactive worlds to robotics simulations and therapeutic environments, these projects show how Marble is transforming imagination into reality. Each one reflects a new way of building with world models, both creative and technical. Explore Marble Labs to see what others are creating and discover how you can start building your own worlds today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;From Marble to Spatial Intelligence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble is a state-of-the-art generative world model. Today it lets you create worlds from diverse input types, edit them, expand them, and export them. These capabilities give you unprecedented levels of control when creating worlds, and are already enabling a wide variety of creative use cases across industries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Marble is just a step on our journey toward spatial intelligence. Going forward, a key opportunity is interactivity. Future world models will let humans and agents alike interact with generated worlds in new ways, unlocking even more use cases in simulation, robotics, and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Try Marble Today&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marble is available today at marble.worldlabs.ai. Sign up now and start creating worlds!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are excited about this vision and want to help us build it, join us!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Read More&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;November 10, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;From Words to Worlds: Spatial Intelligence is AI’s Next Frontier&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A manifesto piece explaining what spatial intelligence is, why it matters, and how we’re building the world models that will unlock it—with impact that will reshape creativity, embodied intelligence, and human progress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;October 16, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;RTFM: A Real-Time Frame Model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A research preview of RTFM, a new generative world model that generates video in real-time as you interact with it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.worldlabs.ai/blog/marble-world-model"/><published>2025-11-12T22:11:14+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45908464</id><title>Valve is about to win the console generation</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:39.788691+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="4e7e82b81462420f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Making sure you're not a bot! Loading... Please wait a moment while we ensure the security of your connection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://xeiaso.net/blog/2025/valve-is-about-to-win-the-console-generation/"/><published>2025-11-12T23:35:41+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45908483</id><title>Voyager 1 is a light-day away by November 2026</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:39.608838+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1ea2c1731caca3bf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the first time in humanity's long history, a human-made object will soon be a full light-day away from our home planet.&lt;/p&gt;The rest of this article is behind a paywall. Please sign in or subscribe to access the full content.&lt;p&gt;Space, as they say, is pretty big, and human-made objects are slow. The record speed any human has ever traveled was set by Apollo 10 back in 1969, and has not been broken since. The fastest human spaceflight remains 39,937.7 kilometers per hour (24,816.1 miles per hour), and at those speeds, it would take 3,730 hours to travel just 1 astronomical unit (AU), the distance between the Earth and the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At around 155 days, that's an unacceptable travel time to (for example) slam into the Sun. And while it takes you 155 days to get wherever it is you went, light and communications from Earth would reach you in about 8 minutes and 20 seconds, really rubbing it in how great it is to be massless.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But we will get a real reminder of the vast distance and incredible speed of light in late 2026, when Voyager 1 becomes the first human-made object to reach one light-day away from Earth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This spacecraft was launched in 1977 and has been traveling ever since. At the time of writing, it is around 169.5 AU from the Earth, having become the first spacecraft to go beyond the heliosphere, cross the heliopause, and enter interstellar space. At its current position, it takes 23 hours, 29 minutes, and 27 seconds for signals from Earth to reach the spacecraft. At its current speed of about 61,198 kilometers per hour (38,027 miles per hour), it will still take over a year to widen that light-distance to a full 24 hours.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it does reach 25.9 billion kilometers (16 billion miles) from Earth, a journey that took nearly 50 years, it will finally be the distance that light can travel in a day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to calculations from IFLScience's resident astronomer, Dr Alfredo Carpineti, using data from NASA's Eyes on the Solar System, this will occur on November 13, 2026. After this date, the probe will not fall within 24 light-hours from Earth again, despite the Earth-to-Voyager distance changing as we orbit the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After that, it will continue on its course, guided by NASA until it runs out of power, likely in the early 2030s. But its journey will be far from over. First, it will leave the Solar System, passing through the Oort cloud, before having at least one close encounter with another star, Gliese 445, in the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The distant Oort cloud marks the gravitational edge of the Solar System, in a vast region of undiscovered objects," NASA explains of the Oort cloud, first hypothesized by Dutch astronomer Jan Oort in 1950. "Short-period comets may originate in the scattered disk, inner, part of the Oort cloud, while long-period comets likely come from the spherical, outer portion of the Oort cloud. These comets only pass the Sun on rare occasions, possibly when disturbed by distant passing stars or galactic tides. There is speculation of other large planets in this region that may disturb comets in their vicinity, but none have yet been discovered."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the lower range of estimates, the Oort cloud could begin around 1,000 AU from the Sun. If the Oort cloud does begin here, Voyager could reach it in just a few centuries. However, given the sheer scale of the cloud, it will be there for tens of thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Much of interstellar space is actually inside our Solar System," NASA explains. "It will take about 300 years for Voyager 1 to reach the inner edge of the Oort Cloud and possibly about 30,000 years to fly beyond it."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assuming that the Voyager probes make it through the cloud undamaged (a likely outcome, given that space is not the asteroid-dodging exercise sci-fi would have us believe), they could go on relatively unscathed for many, many years beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a long time, Voyager will not be near any astronomical objects, drifting on its own through the cosmos, far from sources of heat and light. But in 40,000 years, it will get a brief close encounter with another star, coming closer to it than home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It took 35 years to reach interstellar space, but it will take 40,000 years for Voyager 1 to be closer to the star AC +79 3888 than our sun," NASA explains. "Alpha Centauri is the closest star to our own right now, but because stars are moving, Voyager 1 will actually get within 1.7 light years of AC +79 3888 (aka Gliese 445) in 40,000 years."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A paper examining the future stellar flybys of probes on an escape velocity from the Solar System puts the figure at more like 44,000 years. Gliese 445 is an M-type main-sequence star with around a third of the mass of our Sun. At the moment, it is around 17,000 light-years from Earth, but by the time the encounter with Voyager happens, it will be around 3.5 light-years away from us. It will not be the spacecraft's final encounter with another star.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Statistically, a spacecraft will encounter stars within a given distance at approximately the same rate as the Sun does, which Bailer-Jones et al. [...] inferred to be one star within 1 pc every 50 kyr," the study explains, adding that more-distant encounters are difficult to predict due to uncertainty in the data. "This rate scales quadratically with encounter distance (i.e. one star within 0.1 pc every 5 Myr [million years]). As the spacecraft are not leaving the Galaxy, it is inevitable that the spacecraft will pass much closer to some stars on longer timescales."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the team was able to predict the closest approach that Voyager will have in the not-too-distant future, astronomically speaking. They found that the spacecraft will encounter TYC 3135-52-1, a main-sequence star, in around 303,000 years. At this point, it will be around 0.965 light-years from the star, so still quite wide of it. Looking at the data, it is unlikely Voyager 1 will be captured by a star any time soon, and will continue to drift through the cosmos with only the Golden Records for company.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The timescale for the collision of a spacecraft with a star is of order 1020 years," the team concludes, "so the spacecraft have a long future ahead of them."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An earlier version of this article was published in June 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.iflscience.com/on-november-13-2026-voyager-will-reach-one-full-light-day-away-from-earth-81432"/><published>2025-11-12T23:38:56+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45908938</id><title>Google will allow users to sideload Android apps without verification</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:39.391517+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="89b03251d8d5e4b8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;12 November 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posted by Matthew Forsythe Director - Product Management, Android App Safety&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We recently announced new developer verification requirements, which serve as an additional layer of defense in our ongoing effort to keep Android users safe. We know that security works best when it accounts for the diverse ways people use our tools. This is why we announced this change early: to gather input and ensure our solutions are balanced. We appreciate the community's engagement and have heard the early feedback – specifically from students and hobbyists who need an accessible path to learn, and from power users who are more comfortable with security risks. We are making changes to address the needs of both groups.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To understand how these updates fit into our broader mission, it is important to first look at the specific threats we are tackling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why verification is important&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keeping users safe on Android is our top priority. Combating scams and digital fraud is not new for us — it has been a central focus of our work for years. From Scam Detection in Google Messages to Google Play Protect and real-time alerts for scam calls, we have consistently acted to keep our ecosystem safe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, online scams and malware campaigns are becoming more aggressive. At the global scale of Android, this translates to real harm for people around the world – especially in rapidly digitizing regions where many are coming online for the first time. Technical safeguards are critical, but they cannot solve for every scenario where a user is manipulated. Scammers use high-pressure social engineering tactics to trick users into bypassing the very warnings designed to protect them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, a common attack we track in Southeast Asia illustrates this threat clearly. A scammer calls a victim claiming their bank account is compromised and uses fear and urgency to direct them to sideload a "verification app" to secure their funds, often coaching them to ignore standard security warnings. Once installed, this app — actually malware — intercepts the victim's notifications. When the user logs into their real banking app, the malware captures their two-factor authentication codes, giving the scammer everything they need to drain the account.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While we have advanced safeguards and protections to detect and take down bad apps, without verification, bad actors can spin up new harmful apps instantly. It becomes an endless game of whack-a-mole. Verification changes the math by forcing them to use a real identity to distribute malware, making attacks significantly harder and more costly to scale. We have already seen how effective this is on Google Play, and we are now applying those lessons to the broader Android ecosystem to ensure there is a real, accountable identity behind the software you install.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supporting students and hobbyists&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We heard from developers who were concerned about the barrier to entry when building apps intended only for a small group, like family or friends. We are using your input to shape a dedicated account type for students and hobbyists. This will allow you to distribute your creations to a limited number of devices without going through the full verification requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Empowering experienced users&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While security is crucial, we’ve also heard from developers and power users who have a higher risk tolerance and want the ability to download unverified apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on this feedback and our ongoing conversations with the community, we are building a new advanced flow that allows experienced users to accept the risks of installing software that isn't verified. We are designing this flow specifically to resist coercion, ensuring that users aren't tricked into bypassing these safety checks while under pressure from a scammer. It will also include clear warnings to ensure users fully understand the risks involved, but ultimately, it puts the choice in their hands. We are gathering early feedback on the design of this feature now and will share more details in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Getting started with early access&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we’re excited to start inviting developers to the early access for developer verification in Android Developer Console for developers that distribute exclusively outside of Play, and will share invites to the Play Console experience soon for Play developers. We are looking forward to your questions and feedback on streamlining the experience for all developers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Watch our video below for a walkthrough of the new Android Developer Console experience and see our guides for more details and FAQs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are committed to working with you to keep the ecosystem safe while getting this right.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://android-developers.googleblog.com/2025/11/android-developer-verification-early.html"/><published>2025-11-13T00:33:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45909059</id><title>Human Fovea Detector</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:39.239617+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.shadertoy.com/view/4dsXzM"/><published>2025-11-13T00:48:45+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45909667</id><title>My dad could still be alive, but he's not</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:38.966656+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6f3f3a01d7ae1eb7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;my dad could still be alive, but he's not.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;cw: death&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;dad died this summer, from his first heart attack, barely a week after his 57th birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;i get the first call at 11:30pm from mom, who lived in toronto with him and my brother. she says to not worry, but dad's in the hospital, and i should plan to visit first thing tomorrow morning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;she calls again, 15 minutes later, and says that i should try to head back that night.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;she calls a final time at midnight, asking me where i was. i just got in the cab, i say. i think you might be too late, she says vaguely. but you should still try to make it back. i tell the driver to please speed a bit on the highway if he's comfortable doing so, and he does, and im grateful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;i get to the hospital at 1:30 am. the nurse gives me a long, hard stare after i tell them who i'm here to see. she asks if my mom told me the news, and that's the moment when i know for sure (except it still doesn't quite feel real). i lie and say yes, and she stares at me a little longer, scrutinizing. then she leads me to the room with my dad's body and the rest of my family. when i press one last kiss to his forehead, he is still not quite cool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;i learn the story afterwards. dad went upstairs for a lie-down after dinner, but was awoken by severe chest pain. he vomits, which is a thing he never does, and asks mom to call 911 immediately. she does and provides all the symptoms, the dispatcher tells her that they've sent for an ambulance, and they should get ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;so they get ready, and then they wait. they wait for 15 long minutes, my dad in an extreme amount of pain, and nothing happens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;mom calls 911 again and asks if they have an ETA. the dispatcher responds that don't have visibility on that. she asks if she should just drive my dad to the hospital and is advised that the best thing to do is to keep waiting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;so they wait another 15 long minutes, and still no one shows up. the house is in a car-oriented suburb, 5 minutes away from a major highway, a ten minute drive from the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;mom decides that they should not keep waiting. she and my brother help dad into the car, and they drive him to the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(my brother drives us back the next day to collect his things. at one intersection, he says, "he told me to be careful when doing the left turn. those were his last words to me." they were, in all likelihood, his very last words.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;they arrive at the emergency room entrance. dad gets out of the car, takes two steps, lurches forwards, and dies on the front steps of the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;every time i think about this sequence of events, i feel a sense of vertigo. i don't understand it, except i understand the workings of moloch all too well. i don't understand why this was allowed, but of course this is a thing that happens every day. i don't understand why the dispatcher didn't say to my mom, "if you have a car, use that, it's faster", but i can feel the weight of all the incentives behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;i don't understand why the common narrative that i was told, that we were all told growing up, is that one should wait for an ambulance, when this is the way it ends, except i know that institutions do not see themselves clearly and they often do not know what they do. i don't understand why afterwards, everyone we explained this to nodded at us sagely and said "oh, of course, we all know that ambulances are slow and terrible and actually the transport of last resort, it's understandable but a shame that you didn't get this update". except of course i understand that too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;now i have updated. and now it is too late.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;my dad is dead, because his family members were too naive to know that the thing they were instructed to do by the state was a false thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;i don't know if you should update on this, if you don't live in toronto, or if things are only this bad because of the chronic emt shortage and it will get better in some indeterminate amount of time, or if we just caught them on a bad night, or what.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;all i know is that my family waited 30 minutes for an ambulance that didn't come, and now my dad is dead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.jenn.site/my-dad-could-still-be-alive-but-hes-not/"/><published>2025-11-13T02:17:30+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45910009</id><title>A Commentary on the Sixth Edition Unix Operating System</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:38.823659+00:00</updated><link href="https://warsus.github.io/lions-/"/><published>2025-11-13T03:01:47+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45910257</id><title>Large integer precision error in Bash command output rendering</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:38.246219+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="562887f54d8fd799"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Notifications &lt;tool-tip&gt;You must be signed in to change notification settings&lt;/tool-tip&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fork 2.8k&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Labels&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;area:toolsbugSomething isn't workingSomething isn't workinghas reproHas detailed reproduction stepsHas detailed reproduction stepsplatform:macosIssue specifically occurs on macOSIssue specifically occurs on macOS&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Description&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Code incorrectly displays large integers in bash command output, showing a different value than what was actually output by the command.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Steps to Reproduce&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Run the following command in Claude Code:&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;echo '348555896224571969'&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or with jq:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;echo '{"value": 348555896224571969}' | jq -c .value&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Expected Behavior&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Code should display: &lt;code&gt;348555896224571969&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Actual Behavior&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Code displays: &lt;code&gt;348555896224571970&lt;/code&gt; (off by 1)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Verification&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running the same command in a native terminal correctly outputs: &lt;code&gt;348555896224571969&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Environment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Claude Code version: v2.0.37&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Model: Sonnet 4.5 (Claude Max)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Platform: macOS (Darwin 24.3.0)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Screenshots&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;sammcj, jeffreygray, notque, brainkim and rrwrightbrainkim and bboutkov&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Metadata&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Metadata&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Assignees&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Labels&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;area:toolsbugSomething isn't workingSomething isn't workinghas reproHas detailed reproduction stepsHas detailed reproduction stepsplatform:macosIssue specifically occurs on macOSIssue specifically occurs on macOS&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/anthropics/claude-code/issues/11506"/><published>2025-11-13T03:34:02+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45910305</id><title>Bitcoin's big secret: How cryptocurrency became law enforcement's secret weapon</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:38.136923+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3846912202753f9a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the 2025 Bitwarden Open Source Security Summit, WIRED's Andy Greenberg sat down for a fireside chat with GigaOm analyst Paul Stringfellow to discuss a revelation that turned his decades-long reporting on its head: Bitcoin became a criminal's worst nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2011, Greenberg thought he'd discovered the story of a lifetime: digital cash that promised complete anonymity. A decade later, that story flipped entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;"I had this slow-motion epiphany that I was entirely wrong about Bitcoin. It was, in fact, the opposite of untraceable."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How law enforcement cracked the blockchain code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting around 2014, law enforcement discovered something remarkable: Bitcoin's blockchain was a permanent, traceable record.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enter Tigran Gambaryan, an IRS criminal investigator who would become the hero of Greenberg's book Tracers in the Dark. The same IRS unit that brought down Al Capone for tax evasion now had a new weapon: blockchain forensics. Working alongside cryptocurrency tracing startup Chainalysis, Gambaryan developed techniques that offered even greater transparency than traditional financial systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;"They could follow the money with even greater financial forensic power than in the traditional finance system."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scale of what followed was staggering. Greenberg walked through several landmark cases that reshaped how law enforcement thinks about cryptocurrency:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Silk Road's corruption: Corrupt DEA and Secret Service agents received Bitcoin payments from the site's kingpin. Blockchain analysis proved these weren't personal investments — they were payments to moles selling law enforcement secrets.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Mt. Gox heist: Investigators traced 650,000 stolen Bitcoins to Russian cybercriminals, leading to arrests when one vacationed in Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;AlphaBay: Federal agents dismantled this dark web drug marketplace after cryptocurrency tracing identified kingpin Alexandre Cazes operating from Bangkok. Advanced crypto techniques revealed the secret server's location in Lithuania.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Welcome to Video: Blockchain analysis exposed a dark web marketplace for child sexual abuse materials (CSAM). Investigators identified 337 perpetrators worldwide and rescued 23 children.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;"The first, second, and third biggest seizures of money in US Justice Department history — billions of dollars."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gambaryan and his colleagues carried out the first, second, and third largest financial seizures in U.S. Justice Department history. Not just in cryptocurrency — in any crime category, period.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The uncomfortable reality: Why crime continues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But here's the paradox: if cryptocurrency tracing is so powerful, why do ransomware attacks, pig butchering scams, and North Korean hackers continue to steal billions?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The answer: identifiability isn't the same as accountability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Law enforcement can identify perpetrators with incredible accuracy through blockchain analysis&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;But criminals operating from Russia, North Korea, or lawless Southeast Asian zones remain out of reach&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ransomware profits dropped significantly last year when federal investigators seized websites and cryptocurrency — even without arrests&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Pig butchering scams steal tens of billions annually through forced labor compounds, yet Chinese crime bosses face minimal consequences&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The gap: law enforcement hasn't prioritized crypto tracing investigations against scam operations at scale&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;"You can identify perpetrators with incredible accuracy thanks to the blockchain, but if they're beyond the reach of Western law enforcement, they can still be beyond accountability."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Blockchain analysis: The privacy trade-off&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the discussion wrapped up, Stringfellow highlighted a provocative tension: while blockchain analysis empowers law enforcement, it also raises profound privacy concerns for everyone else. The same technology that catches criminals can potentially track law-abiding citizens, making this book more than just a true crime thriller.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;"When you read this book, you realize how cool accountants are."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Forensic accountants power the most exciting detective work of the digital age. They analyze blockchain transactions, where hackers and traditional law enforcement often hit dead ends.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Watch the replay&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tracers in the Dark is now available and offers a comprehensive deep dive into these cases and the forensic techniques that led to their resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For anyone interested in cybersecurity, cryptocurrency, or the intersection of technology and crime, the full fireside chat delivers cases that read like spy novels but are entirely real. Hear directly from Greenberg about covert operations, international manhunts, and the complete reversal of what criminals thought they knew about staying anonymous online.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://bitwarden.com/blog/how-cryptocurrency-became-law-enforcements-secret-weapon/"/><published>2025-11-13T03:39:56+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45910347</id><title>Meta replaces WhatsApp for Windows with web wrapper that uses 1 GB RAM when idle</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:37.909251+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6c47977bf3754df"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WhatsApp on Windows 11 has just got a ‘major’ upgrade, and you’re probably going to hate it because it simply loads web.whatsapp.com in a WebView2 container. This means WhatsApp on Windows 11 is cooked, and it’s back to being absolute garbage in terms of performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WhatsApp is one of those Windows apps that went from being a web wrapper to a native app and then back to the web again after all these years of investment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WhatsApp for Windows was originally an Electron app, and it was eventually replaced with UWP after years of investment. Four years later, WhatsApp is going back to WebView2, abandoning the original WinUI/UWP native idea.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;I blame the layoffs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My understanding is that the recent layoffs at Mark Zuckerberg-headed Meta likely disbanded the entire team behind the native WhatsApp. I don’t see any other reason why Meta would abandon its native app for Windows. Meta will save costs by maintaining the web app codebase on Windows, but you’re going to hate the experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How bad is the new WhatsApp for Windows 11?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our tests showed that new Chromium/WebView2-based WhatsApp for Windows 11 uses up to 300MB of RAM when you are on the login screen and doing nothing. On the other hand, the old/native WhatsApp uses just 18MB of RAM and even slips to less than 10MB when left idle on the login screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After logging in, WhatsApp (new) memory usage increased to 2GB while trying to load all my chats. On average, it used 1.2GB when left idle in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’d realise how bad this is when I tell you the benchmarks for the native WhatsApp for comparison. I tested the old/native WhatsApp, and it uses just 190MB most of the time, dropping to less than 100MB when it’s completely idle. At worst, it would reach 300MB, which can happen only when the chat is really active.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the looks of things, this new WhatsApp for Windows 11 can touch 3GB RAM if you have too many active conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s absolutely garbage, and it should not be allowed inside the Microsoft Store. You’re better off using WhatsApp on the web (Edge/Chrome) than updating/downloading this new WebView2-based app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact, it appears that WhatsApp web (web.whatsapp.com) in any browser is less terrible than this WebView2 container.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;New WhatsApp is a performance nightmare&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An app can use a lot of memory, and it does not necessarily mean it’s a performance nightmare, but the issue with the new WhatsApp is that it feels sluggish. You’re going to notice sluggish performance, long loading time, and other performance issues when browsing different conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also noticed that it does not work well with Windows notifications. It also struggles with Windows 11’s Do Not Disturb mode or Active Hours. And there are delayed notifications problems as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Can you avoid this new WhatsApp upgrade on Windows 11? Yes, but not for a very long time&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Windows Latest found that WhatsApp version 2.2584.3.0 replaces the native (WinUI/UWP) app and is rolling out in all regions via the Microsoft Store. Do not download it, and you might still be allowed to use the native app for the next days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, Windows Latest has learned that all users will be logged out eventually and forced to use the WebView2-based WhatsApp.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This ‘upgrade’ ships as the WhatsApp native experience rolls out on Apple Watch, which has 115 million consumers, while Windows has over one billion active monthly devices. Clearly, numbers are not always enough, and I am not sure if I can really blame Meta when Microsoft also does not make native apps for Windows anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.windowslatest.com/2025/11/12/meta-just-killed-native-whatsapp-on-windows-11-now-it-opens-webview-uses-1gb-ram-all-the-time/"/><published>2025-11-13T03:44:37+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45910381</id><title>Android 16 QPR1 is being pushed to the Android Open Source Project</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:37.236665+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f8eb8f2f2d953eed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To use the Mastodon web application, please enable JavaScript. Alternatively, try one of the native apps for Mastodon for your platform.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://grapheneos.social/@GrapheneOS/115533432439509433"/><published>2025-11-13T03:49:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45910625</id><title>CollectWise (YC F24) Is Hiring</title><updated>2025-11-13T05:11:36.720091+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1778b25df8afe5d4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Automating consumer debt collection with AI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Us&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CollectWise is a fast growing and well funded Y Combinator-backed startup. We’re using generative AI to automate debt collection, a $35B market in the US alone. Our AI agents are already outperforming human collectors by 2X, and we’re doing so at a fraction of the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With a team of three, we scaled to a $1 million annualized run rate in just a few months, and we are now hiring a forward deployed engineer to help us reach $10 million within the next year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Role&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are hiring a Forward Deployed Engineer to lead customer implementations end-to-end. You’ll work at the intersection of engineering and operations, building the integrations and technical systems that bring clients into production.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This role blends software engineering with hands-on customer work. You’ll thrive here if you enjoy ambiguity, love shipping quickly, and can translate business requirements into robust, testable systems. This is a highly visible, high-ownership role working closely with the founder and clients.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Desired Qualifications&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compensation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CollectWise is revolutionizing debt recovery with autonomous AI agents and an integrated legal network. We boost recovery rates, reduce costs, and maintain a positive brand image through respectful, data-driven interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/collectwise/jobs/tv3ufcc-forward-deployed-engineer"/><published>2025-11-13T04:26:56+00:00</published></entry></feed>