<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:40.984139+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46556822</id><title>Replit (YC W18) Is Hiring</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:48.334228+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e10fcdab2cdf53e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need to enable JavaScript to run this app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/replit"/><published>2026-01-09T18:00:56+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46557825</id><title>Code and Let Live</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:47.854973+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="754a965a29c50df5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The state of the art in agent isolation is a read-only sandbox. At Fly.io, weâve been selling that story for years, and weâre calling it: ephemeral sandboxes are obsolete. Stop killing your sandboxes every time you use them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My argument won’t make sense without showing you something new we’ve built. We’re all adults here, this is a company, we talk about what we do. Here goes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, I want to run some code. So what I do is, I run &lt;code&gt;sprite create&lt;/code&gt;. While it operates, I’ll explain what’s happening behind theâ&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;â Created demo-123 sprite in 1.0s
â Connecting to console...
sprite@sprite:~#
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shit, it’s already there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s a root shell on a Linux computer we now own. It came online in about the same amount of time it would take to &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; into a host that already existed. We call these things “Sprites”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s install FFmpeg on our Sprite:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install -y ffmpeg &amp;gt;/dev/null 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike creating the Sprite in the first place, installing &lt;code&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; is dog slow. Let’s try not to have to do that again:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sprite@sprite:~# sprite-env checkpoints create
# ...
{"type":"complete","data":"Checkpoint v1 created successfully",
"time":"2025-12-22T22:50:48.60423809Z"}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This completes instantly. Didn’t even bother to measure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I step away to get coffee. Time passes. The Sprite, noticing my inactivity, goes to sleep. I meet an old friend from high school at the coffee shop. End up spending the day together. More time passes. Days even. Returning later:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; $ sprite console 
sprite@sprite:~# ffmpeg
ffmpeg version 7.1.1-1ubuntu1.3 Copyright (c) 2000-2025 the FFmpeg developers
Use -h to get full help or, even better, run 'man ffmpeg'
sprite@sprite:~#
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everything’s where I left it. Sprites are durable. 100GB capacity to start, no ceremony. Maybe I’ll keep it around a few more days, maybe a few months, doesn’t matter, just works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Say I get an application up on its legs. Install more packages. Then: disaster. Maybe an ill-advised global &lt;code&gt;pip3 install&lt;/code&gt; . Or &lt;code&gt;rm -rf $HMOE/bin&lt;/code&gt;. Or &lt;code&gt;dd if=/dev/random of=/dev/vdb&lt;/code&gt;. Whatever it was, everything’s broken. So:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; $ sprite checkpoint restore v1
Restoring from checkpoint v1...
Container components started successfully
Restore from v1 complete

&amp;gt; $ sprite console
sprite@sprite:~#
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sprites have first-class checkpoint and restore. You can’t see it in text, but that restore took about one second. It’s fast enough to use casually, interactively. Not an escape hatch. Rather: an intended part of the ordinary course of using a Sprite. Like &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;, but for the whole system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If youâre asking how this is any different from an EC2 instance, good. Thatâs what weâre going for, except:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I can casually create hundreds of them (without needing a Docker container), each appearing in 1-2 seconds.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They go idle and stop metering automatically, so itâs cheap to have lots of them. I use dozens.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Theyâre hooked up to our Anycast network, so I can get an HTTPS URL.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Despite all that, theyâre fully durable. They donât die until I tell them to.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This combination of attributes isnât common enough to already have a name, so we decided we get to name them âSpritesâ. Sprites are like BIC disposable cloud computers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s what we built. You can go try it yourself. We wrote another 1000 words about how they work, but I cut them out because I want to stop talking about our products now and get to my point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Claude Doesn’t Want A Stateless Container&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For years, we’ve been trying to serve two very different users with the same abstraction. It hasn’t worked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professional software developers are trained to build stateless instances. Stateless deployments, where persistent data is confined to database servers, buys you simplicity, flexible scale-out, and reduced failure blast radius. It’s a good idea, so popular that most places you can run code in the cloud look like stateless containers. Fly Machines, our flagship offering, look like stateless containers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem is that Claude isn’t a pro developer. Claude is a hyper-productive five-year-old savant. It’s uncannily smart, wants to stick its finger in every available electrical socket, and works best when you find a way to let it zap itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(sometimes by escaping the container!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you force an agent to, it’ll work around containerization and do work . But you’re not helping the agent in any way by doing that. They don’t want containers. They don’t want “sandboxes”. They want computers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Someone asked me about this the other day and wanted to know if I was saying that agents needed sound cards and USB ports. And, maybe? I donât know. Not today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a moment, I’ll explain why. But first I probably need to explain what the hell I mean by a “computer”. I think we all agree:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A computer doesn’t necessarily vanish after a single job is completed, and&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;it has durable storage.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since current agent sandboxes have neither of these, I can stop the definition right there and get back to my point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Simple Wins&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start here: with an actual computer, Claude doesn’t have to rebuild my entire development environment every time I pick up a PR.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This seems superficial but rebuilding stuff like &lt;code&gt;node_modules&lt;/code&gt; is such a monumental pain in the ass that the industry is spending tens of millions of dollars figuring out how to snapshot and restore ephemeral sandboxes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m not saying those problems are intractable. I’m saying they’re unnecessary. Instead of figuring them out, just use an actual computer. Work out a PR, review and push it, then just start on the next one. Without rebooting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People will rationalize why it’s a good thing that they start from a new build environment every time they start a changeset. Stockholm Syndrome. When you start a feature branch on your own, do you create an entirely new development environment to do it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reason agents waste all this effort is that nobody saw them coming. Read-only ephemeral sandboxes were the only tool we had hanging on the wall to help use them sanely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have you ever had to set up actual infrastructure to give an agent access to realistic data? People do this. Because they know theyâre dealing with a clean slate every time they prompt their agent, they arrange for S3 buckets, Redis servers, or even RDS instances outside the sandbox for their agents to talk to. Theyâre building infrastructure to work around the fact that they canât just write a file and trust it to stay put. Gross.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ephemerality means time limits. Providers design sandbox systems to handle the expected workloads agents generate. Most things agents do today don’t take much time; in fact, they’re often limited only by the rate at which frontier models can crunch tokens. Test suites run quickly. The 99th percentile sandboxed agent run probably needs less than 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there are feature requests where compute and network time swamp token crunching. I built the documentation site for the Sprites API by having a Claude Sprite interact with the code and our API, building and testing examples for the API one at a time. There are APIs where the client interaction time alone would blow sandbox budgets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You see the limits of the current approach in how people round-trip state through “plan files”, which are ostensibly prose but often really just egregiously-encoded key-value stores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An agent running on an actual computer can exploit the whole lifecycle of the application. We saw this when Chris McCord built Phoenix.new. The agent behind a Phoenix.new app runs on a Fly Machine where it can see the app logs from the Phoenix app it generated. When users do things that generate exceptions, Phoenix.new notices and gets to work figuring out what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It took way too much work for Chris to set that up, and he was able to do it in part because he wrote his own agent. You can do it with Claude today with an MCP server or some other arrangement to haul logs over. But all you really need is to just not shoot your sandbox in the head when the agent finishes writing code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Galaxy Brain Win&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s where I lose you. I know this because it’s also where I lose my team, most of whom don’t believe me about this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The nature of software development is changing out from under us, and I think we’re kidding ourselves that it’s going to end with just a reconfiguration of how professional developers ship software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have kids. They have devices. I wanted some control over them. So I did what many of you would do in my situation: I vibe-coded an MDM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I built this thing with Claude. It’s a SQLite-backed Go application running on a Sprite. The Anycast URL my Sprite exports works as an MDM registration URL. Claude also worked out all the APNS Push Certificate drama for me. It all just works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;âEditing PHP files over FTP: we werenât wrong, just ahead of our time!â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been running this for a month now, still on a Sprite, and see no reason ever to stop. It is a piece of software that solves an important real-world problem for me. It might evolve as my needs change, and I tell Claude to change it. Or it might not. For this app, dev is prod, prod is dev.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For reasons we’ll get into when we write up how we built these things, you wouldn’t want to ship an app to millions of people on a Sprite. But most apps don’t want to serve millions of people. The most important day-to-day apps disproportionately won’t have million-person audiences. There are some important million-person apps, but most of them just destroy civil society, melt our brains, and arrange chauffeurs for individual cheeseburgers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applications that solve real problems for people will be owned by the people they solve problems for. And for the most part, they won’t need a professional guild of software developers to gatekeep feature development for them. They’ll just ask for things and get them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem we’re all working on is bigger than safely accelerating pro software developers. Sandboxes are holding us back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fuck Ephemeral Sandboxes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Obviously, I’m trying to sell you something here. But that doesn’t make me wrong. The argument I’m making is the reason we built the specific thing I’m selling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It took us a long time to get here. We spent years kidding ourselves. We built a platform for horizontal-scaling production applications with micro-VMs that boot so quickly that, if you hold them in exactly the right way, you can do a pretty decent code sandbox with them. But it’s always been a square peg, round hole situation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have a lot to say about how Sprites work. They’re related to Fly Machines but sharply different in important ways. They have an entirely new storage stack. They’re orchestrated differently. No Dockerfiles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But for now, I just want you to think about what I’m saying here. Whether or not you ever boot a Sprite, ask: if you could run a coding agent anywhere, would you want it to look more like a read-only sandbox in a K8s cluster in the cloud, or like an entire EC2 instance you could summon in the snap of a finger?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think the answer is obvious. The age of sandboxes is over. The time of the disposable computer has come.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://fly.io/blog/code-and-let-live/"/><published>2026-01-09T19:11:59+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46564116</id><title>Org Mode Syntax Is One of the Most Reasonable Markup Languages for Text (2017)</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:46.685256+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="52849bffcb6479ed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Updates &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;2017-09-25: Simplified the table syntax even more&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;2018-04-06: Comments on the standardization argument&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;2019-04-12: Extended syntax examples, "Makes Sense Outside of Emacs", "Tool Support" and added more backlinks&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;2020-05-02: Comment by Ian Zimmerman&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;2021-05-24: more examples for AsciiDoc&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;2021-11-28: The birth of "Orgdown" - a new name for the Org mode syntax (see Summary)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;2024-12-22: Part with the explanation on the Markdown flavor explosion&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;2025-03-09: extended the list of Markdown standards&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: this is a very nerdy blog entry. It is about lightweight markup languages and why I think that Org mode syntax is the best lightweight markup language for many use-cases. And with lightweight markup language, I do mean the syntax, the way you express headings, lists, font variations such as bold face or italic, and such things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I've written a very similar article on why Markdown is a bad idea in general.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please do note that this is not about Emacs at all. This is about Org mode syntax and its advantages even when used outside of Emacs. You can type Org mode syntax in vim, notepad.exe, Atom, Notepad++, and all other text editors out there. And in my opinion it does have advantages compared to the other, common lightweight markup standards such as Markdown, AsciiDoc, Wikitext or reStructuredText.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, Org mode syntax is my favorite syntax. Despite my personal choice you will see that I've got some pretty convincing arguments that underline my statement as well. So this is not just a matter of personal taste.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you already have a grin on your face because you don't have any clue what this is all about: keep on reading. It makes an excellent example for making fun of nerds at your next dinner party. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Org Mode Syntax Is Intuitive, Easy to Learn and Remember&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here you are. This is almost anything you need to know about Org mode syntax:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;* This Is A Heading ** This Is A Sub-Heading *** And A Sub-Sub-Heading Paragraphs are separated by at least one empty line. *bold* /italic/ _underlined_ +strikethrough+ =monospaced= [[http://Karl-Voit.at][Link description]] http://Karl-Voit.at â link without description - list item - another item - sub-item 1. also enumerated 2. if you like - [ ] yet to be done - [X] item which is done : Simple pre-formatted text such as for source code. : This also respects the line breaks. *bold* is not bold here.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; And yes, for the people with advanced syntax in mind, this is not everything. Just the basics. A common objection is that source code needs a begin and an end marker instead of a string prefix like &lt;code&gt;: &lt;/code&gt; and Org mode syntax is providing this as well:

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;#+BEGIN_SRC python myresult = 42 * 23 print('Hello Europe! ' + str(myresult)) #+END_SRC&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've seen many coworkers who typed Org mode markup when taking notes in their text editor. And they did not even know anything about it. So it is that intuitive I'd say.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While I was learning Org mode, I did not even use a cheat-sheet for the syntax as I normally do. It was very natural for me to type Org mode syntax right from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tables are a bit more complicated like in all other markup languages I know of:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;| My Column 1 | My Column 2 | Last Column | |-------------+-------------+-------------| | 42 | foo | bar | | 23 | baz | abcdefg | |-------------+-------------+-------------| | 65 | | |&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You most probably won't type a table like this outside of Emacs. The manual alignment without tool-support is very tedious. But even here you are able to deliver a perfectly fine Org mode table by simply ignoring the alignment altogether:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;| My Column 1|My Column 2 | Last Column | |- | 42 | foo | bar| | 23 | baz | abcdefg| |- | 65 |||&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Org Mode Syntax Is Standardized&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is an almost ridiculous argument because in my opinion a markup is of no use when it is not the same for tool A as for tool B.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, there are markup languages that are different. For example the very widely used markup language named Markdown has many flavors to choose from (list far from complete):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;the original writeup and implementation by John Gruber&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Markdown Extra&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MultiMarkdown&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub Flavored Markdown&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CommonMark which tries to standardize the Markdown standard (again)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Djot (derived from CommonMark)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MyST (superset of CommonMark)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;by the time you read this, there probably will be even much more!&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pandoc lists six different Markdown flavors as output formats. This is an absolutely bad situation which foils the original idea behind lightweight markup languages. When some web service tells me that I can use "Markdown" for a text field, I have to dig deeper to find out which of those many different Markdown standards the web page is talking about. After this I will have to continue and look for a cheat-sheet of this dialect because nothing is more difficult to differentiate than multiple standards that are almost the same but not really the same. A usability hell. I get furious every time I have to enter this hell.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Markdown, the original (inconsistently designed) syntax format is a minimal set that made much sense when used when typing emails and so forth. Later-on, various tools needed more syntax elements for obvious reasons. For example, tools wanted to have footnotes or tables. Those syntax add-ons extended the original Markdown. However, they were not standardized.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This resulted in a zoo of very similar but incompatible set of Markdown flavors. Those differences cause information loss by moving from one "Markdown" tool to another "Markdown" tool because Markdown is not Markdown in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In contrast to that, the syntax of Emacs Org-mode as the one and only original form has - by far - the largest set of syntax elements and various extensions by modules. Any other adaptation of this syntax in other tools chose a real sub-set of the original syntax elements. This makes data transitions much smoother, is less error-prone and causes less data loss.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As of 2025-02, there is no formal Org-mode syntax definition. However, as described in the upper paragraphs, the Org-mode syntax is more standardized than any of the Markdown standards with respect to Markdown in general. All Org-mode syntax elements are part of the Emacs Org-mode implementation and all derivatives are sub-sets of this set of syntax elements. This is quite the opposite with Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; An additional notion (which is not related to the syntax itself) is the lack of standardization of file extensions using Markdown syntax. I've seen &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.mkdn&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.markdown&lt;/code&gt; and even &lt;code&gt;.txt&lt;/code&gt; (in Markdown).

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; With Org mode syntax, life is easy. The snippet from the previous section explains all there is. Any tool that interprets Org mode syntax accepts this simple and easy to remember syntax. The file name extension is always &lt;code&gt;.org&lt;/code&gt;.

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Org Mode Syntax Is Consistent&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Different Heading Approaches&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many lightweight markup languages do offer multiple ways of typing headings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are basically three ways of defining headings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Prefix headings&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pre- and postfix headings&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Underlined headings&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some examples for each category:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Prefix headings: # Heading 1 ## Heading 2 ### Heading 3 Pre- and postfix headings: = Heading 1 = == Heading 2 == === Heading 3 === Underlined headings: Heading 1 ========= Heading 2 ~~~~~~~~~ Heading 3 *********&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; I prefer the prefix heading style. Org mode syntax use this as well with &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; as prefix characters. The more asterisks, the deeper the level of the heading is.

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Pre- and postfix headings do offer bad usability. The user has manually synchronize the number of prefix character with the number of postfix characters. And it is totally unclear how something like &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt; with different numbers of pre/postfix characters is going to turn out when being interpreted.

&lt;code&gt; heading &lt;/code&gt;==&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And in case the user already used a markup language with simple prefix headings, it is not logical why there is the need for the postfix characters at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even worse than this is the underlined heading category. The user is completely irritated for multiple reasons. Besides the tedious manual work to align the stupid heading characters with the heading title, it is not clear what characters must be used for those heading lines. If you've got a bigger document with different levels of headings you get confused which heading character stands for which heading level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are the tilde characters level one? Or was it the equals characters? And how about asterisks? Without a cheat-sheet, the occasional markup user is completely lost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This gets even more worse: some markup languages let you choose your "order" of heading characters. This results in weird situations. For example one author is starting to write a reStructuredText document using her favorite heading syntax. A second author is joining in and has to analyze the document in order to know what heading syntax he must use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;reStructuredText&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the reStructuredText mode of Emacs you can find following function:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;You can visualize the hierarchy of the section adornments in the current buffer by invoking&lt;code&gt;rst-display-adornments-hierarchy&lt;/code&gt;, bound on&lt;code&gt;C-c C-a C-d&lt;/code&gt;. A temporary buffer will appear with fake section titles rendered in the style of the current document. This can be useful when editing other people's documents to find out which section adornments correspond to which levels.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, you got it right, it is true: this function's only purpose is to generate a dummy-hierarchy of headings to visualize which markup has to be used for heading 1, which one for heading 2 and so forth just for this single document. What a bad design decision of the markup when you need such hacks just to know how a heading should look like in a markup even if you are familiar with in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is one more: some markup languages even allow mixed heading styles. You can use an underlined heading style for heading level 1, a prefix style for level 2, another underlining style for level 3 and so forth. Now the chaos is a perfect one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;AsciiDoc&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm using this cheatsheet as reference for this section in AsciiDoc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Level 1 ------- Text. Level 2 ~~~~~~~ Text. Level 3 ^^^^^^^ Text. Level 4 +++++++ Text.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is no good way of memorizing the characters used for the various levels of headings. Within the text, you can't see clearly which heading has a higher level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you have to manually align the characters below the heading text? Does it work when the heading text has a different length than the following line?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;== Level 1 Text. === Level 2 Text. ==== Level 3 Text. ===== Level 4 Text.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why are there two different options for the same very basic syntax element? What about mixing them? Does it work?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why don't they start with one eual sign? Level one consists of two equal characters and so forth. Why this off-by-one mismatch?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;* bullet * bullet - bullet - bullet * bullet ** bullet ** bullet *** bullet *** bullet **** bullet&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;- bullet * bullet&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again: why two different ways of writing a simple list?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First list version: Why do I have to use multiple asterisks but just one dash?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;a. letter b. letter .. letter2 .. letter2 . number . number 1. number2 2. number2 3. number2 4. number2 . number .. letter2 c. letter&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One letter, two dots, one dot â any logic seems to be gone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Term 1:: Definition 1 Term 2:: Definition 2 Term 2.1;; Definition 2.1 Term 2.2;; Definition 2.2 Term 3:: Definition 3 Term 4:: Definition 4 Term 4.1::: Definition 4.1 Term 4.2::: Definition 4.2 Term 4.2.1:::: Definition 4.2.1 Term 4.2.2:::: Definition 4.2.2 Term 4.3::: Definition 4.3 Term 5:: Definition 5&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Definition indented or not? The level after the definition text is hard to follow in the layout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;.Multiline cells, row/col span |==== |Date |Duration |Avg HR |Notes |22-Aug-08 .2+^.^|10:24 | 157 | Worked out MSHR (max sustainable heart rate) by going hard for this interval. |22-Aug-08 | 152 | Back-to-back with previous interval. |24-Aug-08 3+^|none |====&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please note that this has many table options that Org mode syntax does not provide such as multi-line cells. However, this comes with the price of a table syntax I would not be able to remember at least for occasional use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Web Links and Simple Markup in Different Markup Languages&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's have a look at a different markup element: external links. As you already remember in Org mode syntax, a link looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;[[http://Karl-Voit.at][my home page]]&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only difficult thing here is to remember that the URL is at the beginning and the description follows after the URL. Many markup languages do add additional and unnecessary levels of difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some examples from Wikipedia and comments by me where a user might be irritated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AsciiDoc:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;http://example.com[Text]&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; The form is simple but for complex URLs, the &lt;code&gt;[Text]&lt;/code&gt; might look like being part of the URL itself. Not beautiful but at least something I could live with.

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Markdown:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;[Text](http://example.com) [Text](http://example.com "Title")&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Brackets or parentheses first? Why using different kind of markup characters in the first place like only brackets? Is the &lt;code&gt;Title&lt;/code&gt; part of the URL? Why not part of &lt;code&gt;Text&lt;/code&gt;? Very confusing design decisions from my point of view.

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;reStructuredText:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;`Text &amp;lt;http://example.com/&amp;gt;`_&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Holy moly. This is some weird stuff. First, you have to grave accents &lt;code&gt;`&lt;/code&gt; and not apostrophes &lt;code&gt;'&lt;/code&gt;. Then what about the underscore character at the end? This is as complicated as you can define a simple URL. I'd even prefer the hard to type HTML version of linking. A disaster for something which has "lightweight" in its class name.

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even with the most basic formatting syntax, Markdown (I assume in all flavors of it) shows a high level of inconsistency:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;_italic_, **bold**, `monospace`, ~~strikethrough~~&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why is it that italic and monospace require only one character before and after the string in-between and others require two? It's inconsistent and therefore hard to learn and error-prone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Markdown has even different formatting for the very same thing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;This is **bold text**. This is __bold text__. Text**is**bold NOT allowed: Text__is__bold&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;This is *italic*. This is _italic_. Text*is*italic NOT allowed: Text_is_italic&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Horizontal Rules with three or more asterisks (***), dashes (---), or underscores (___) on a line by themselves&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And now compare the Org syntax for the same formats:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;/italic/, *bold*, ~monospace~, +strikethrough+ three or more dashes on one line for horizontal rules&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Org made different choices for the syntax. In my opinion with better mnemonics but you could disagree here. However, with one leading and one trailing syntax character, it's for sure easier to learn, type and recognize due to better consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Org Mode Syntax Can Be Easily Typed&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The simple syntax of Org mode does not imply typing unnecessary characters. You don't have to manually align something like underlined headings. Anybody using a simple text editor is very fast at adding markup for headings, font variations, and so forth. The previous section proved that other markup languages clearly fail in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Org Mode Syntax Makes Sense Outside of Emacs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don't have to use the Emacs editor to write and work with Org mode markup text. As I mentioned above, many people already do so just because Org mode syntax is an intuitive and clean way of typing text characters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you've got text information in Org mode markup, you can process it with many tools. Most prominent and most important examples are files pushed within a GitHub repository and the swiss army knife named Pandoc which is able to convert Org mode syntax to dozens of formats like HTML, odt (LibreOffice), docx (Word), LaTeX, PDF, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many lightweight markups don't come with any decent tool support at all. When I'm using, e.g., markdown in any solution that doesn't do more than syntax highlighting, there is no real reason why this can not be written in Org mode syntax instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, yes, Org mode syntax came with a perfect tool support in the first place. But my point is, that the syntax itself has that many advantages that is should be adapted for all the "tool-support is not the main focus"-applications as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can write and render Org mode syntax in GitHub and GitLab. You can and should use it in any text editor like Notepad for your personal notes. Especially when there is no tool support because of the "easy to type manually"-syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Org Mode Syntax Has Excellent Tool Support (If You Want)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in the beginning, this is not an article about Emacs. Nevertheless for anybody not familiar with Emacs I have to mention that with Emacs there is a tool that supports (not only) in writing Org mode syntax in a perfect way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might start with mouse-only usage. There are menu items with all important functions. For the users that want to get a minimum of efficiency, the menu items show you the keyboard shortcuts you might want to use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; For Org mode syntax it is really easy to learn. Basically you just have to use &lt;code&gt;TAB&lt;/code&gt; for toggle the collapsing and expanding of headings, lists, and blocks. It's &lt;code&gt;Alt&lt;/code&gt; and the arrow keys to move around headings, list items, and even table columns/rows. &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-Return&lt;/code&gt; creates a new heading or list item without the need of entering the markup characters and manually matching indentation levels at all.

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's it. With those three things you're good to write Org mode syntax efficiently. The basic file open/save, finding help, exiting Emacs stuff is accessible with icons or the menu. No need to learn more keyboard shortcuts if you don't want to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having experienced this great tool-support, users typically are eager to learn more. You don't have to. You might be happy with Org mode for capturing minutes of meetings and your shopping list. However, others do master a few additional things and write whole eBooks within Org mode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since this article is not about Emacs, I want to explain why I mention the perfect Emacs support. My point is that Org mode deserves to be adopted for all kind of use-cases where a simple to read and simple to type lightweight markup is needed. However, if you want to have a decent tool support, there is no lightweight markup out there which has a better tool support compared to Org mode within Emacs. I did not find any tool support for Markdown, AsciiDoc, Wikitext or reStructuredText anywhere that could compete with the cozy Org mode syntax support within Emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, there could be more tool support outside of emacs but this is my point: change this. This syntax should support more people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Summary&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lightweight markup languages are designed to be used with a minimum effort compared to full-blown and therefore more complicated markup languages such as HTML or LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some are doing their job better than others. In my experience, many design decisions of widely adapted markups such as Markdown, AsciiDoc or reStructuredText (and others) are questionable from a usability point of view. At least I do have some issues when I have to use them in my daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I hardly see any people out there using Org mode syntax as a markup language outside of Emacs although there are very good reasons for it as an easy to learn and easy to use markup language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this blog article I wanted to point out the usefulness of Org mode even when you are not using Emacs as an writing tool. Of course, when you are using Emacs to type Org mode syntax, you get probably the most advanced tool-support for typing lightweight markup on top. But this was not the point of this article.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update 2021-11-28: Due to the high demand and discussions of this article, the idea grew in me that we do have to address some issues of Org-mode mentioned here. Therefore, I came up with Orgdown. You should check out my Orgdown motivation article.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Backlinks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Large thread on Hacker News&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Discussions on reddit: emacs, programming&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Irreal: Karl Voit on the Superiority of Org Mode Markup&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Another thread on hn.svelte.technology&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Yet another reddit thread with a comment by me on the downsides of markdown in particular&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2019-04-10: Another thread on Hacker News&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2019-04-14: https://github.com/ngortheone/org-rs "More about Org Mode"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2020-06-29: Not a back-link to this article but also a discussion on the superiority of Org syntax&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2020-7-31: Goodbye Markdown! | Org mode Tutorial | Switching to Emacs #5.1 - YouTube &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Tutorial video on the Org mode syntax. Please note: you don't need to use Emacs for writing Org mode texts.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Backlinks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2017-09-23: Discussion on Hacker News&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2019-04-10: Discussion on Hacker News&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2021-11-18: Discussion on Hacker News&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Comments&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"revocation" has a valid point related to the missing standardization of Org mode. Here is my comment on this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The statements here refer to a lightweight markup, the basic things of Org mode syntax. I explicitly listed "headings, lists, font variations such as bold face or italic, and such things".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I do not cover here is a full syntax statement or standard. In my opinion, currently this is not possible outside of Emacs for various reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, there are variations in interpreting Org mode files between Emacs and pandoc. Also, pandoc only supports a sub-set of Org mode. Otherwise, pandoc would have to re-implement or embed Emacs for parsing purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In this specific case, pandoc seems to have a more strict parser related to leading spaces for #-lines, or keywords. I'm pretty sure that the pandoc project accepts this issue as a bug. In doubt, the interpretation of Emacs is the definition, or golden-standard, of Org mode syntax. Even this beta-version of a syntax definition does not mention optional spaces before keywords. The manual mentions &lt;code&gt;org-element-parse-buffer&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;org-lint&lt;/code&gt; which would be most probably the best choice for defining the official standard if you would search for one.

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, this does not relate at all with the intention of this article: the design of the (basic) Org mode syntax compared to other lightweight markup languages. All the issues mentioned where other markups show inconsistencies and usability issues where Org mode seems to have advantages still do apply here. Completely independent of the standardization argument. My personal believe is, that if there would be more use of Org mode syntax elements outside of Emacs, there would be a much higher pressure on formally defining Org mode as a syntax which pandoc and even Emacs could use as the golden standard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So far, there is not even the necessity of defining this golden standard because nobody outside of the Emacs community knows or even is using Org mode. And this is what I tried to change a bit because other markup languages do tend to hurt my geeky soul when I do have to use them. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Comment by Ian Zimmerman&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ian wrote an email comment on reStructuredText (ReST):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Most of your argument makes at least some sense, but you miss the point of the ReST link syntax: the URL doesn't have to be inline! The normal style (which I use for my blog) is like this:&lt;code&gt;blah blah blah follow the interesting link at `foo`_ blah blah blah&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;more blah bluh bleh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;.. _foo: http ://www.foo.example.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;which among other things means that you can mention and link foo multiple times without repeating the URL.&lt;lb/&gt;Maybe there is a way of doing that in org - I don't know, I'm a total beginner. That's why I'm reading your post.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; (Note: I added an additional space character after &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; in the example above to work around this lazyblorg issue.)

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, about that question related to defining an URL once and referring to it multiple times. I'm not aware of an Org mode feature that is providing this functionality except footnotes, which is not specific to URLs only. An even more general approach could be the use of very powerful macro replacement. However, discussion those things, we're far away from the discussion of markup that is lightweight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, I acknowledge that I did not cover this possibility to define URL references in REsT markup. In my opinion and when I try to look at it from a hypothetic user perspective, I do think that this still proves my point. There is no logical explanation for that underscore character. I already had to add those back-ticks as syntax element. Why combining those back-ticks with an additional underscore? This does not make sense to me. Furthermore, where should I place this block where the URLs are defined? After each paragraph? Visual clutter. At the end of the text? Too fragile IMHO. And don't get me started on those two dots and the underscore switching places. This is certainly not putting more weight in the thought that ReST syntax has a higher level of logic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For somebody looking for a smooth, easy to remember lightweight markup language, I still think that nothing beats Org mode in general. Even when we totally neglect the Emacs integration and 99 percent of its feature-set which allows for the most complex requirements while still being consistent and lightweight in syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://karl-voit.at/2017/09/23/orgmode-as-markup-only/"/><published>2026-01-10T09:15:30+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46564762</id><title>New information extracted from Snowden PDFs through metadata version analysis</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:45.676193+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="22d661474f85de18"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previous parts:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We discovered that entire sections describing domestic U.S. intelligence facilities were deliberately removed from two published documents, while equivalent foreign facilities remained visible. The evidence exists in an unexpected place - the PDF metadata of documents published by The Intercept in 2016, and by The Intercept and the Australian Broadcasting Corporation in a 2017 collaborative investigation. To our knowledge, this is the first time this information has been revealed publicly. The removed sections reveal the operational designations and cover name structure for domestic U.S. NRO Mission Ground Stations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using PDF analysis tools, we found hidden text embedded in the metadata versioning of two documents published alongside investigative stories about NSA satellite surveillance facilities. These metadata artifacts prove that earlier versions of the documents contained detailed descriptions of domestic U.S. ground stations that were systematically scrubbed before publication (not just redacted with black boxes, but with text completely removed).&lt;/p&gt;What was published from the Snowden documents:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Operational details for RAF Menwith Hill Station (UK)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Operational details for Pine Gap (Australia)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Potomac Mission Ground Station (PMGS) - Washington, DC. Public cover name: "Classic Wizard Reporting and Testing Center" (CWRTC).&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Consolidated Denver Mission Ground Station (CDMGS) - Denver area. Public cover name: "Aerospace Data Facility" (ADF).&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;The facilities themselves are not unknown. "Aerospace Data Facility" at Buckley Space Force Base is publicly acknowledged as a National Reconnaissance Office (NRO) Mission Ground Station. "Classic Wizard Reporting and Testing Center" at Naval Research Laboratory is publicly acknowledged, though its designation as a Mission Ground Station is less clear. What's NOT public (until now) is the specific operational designations used in classified networks: "Consolidated Denver Mission Ground Station (CDMGS)" and "Potomac Mission Ground Station (PMGS)." The Snowden documents prove these are deliberate cover names (not just alternative terminology) and show exactly what's classified and what's not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Hidden PDF versions&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first PDF document titled "Menwith satellite classification guide" has two versions in the file metadata: an older one and a newer one. The removed information exists in the earlier version, and is completely removed in the second, published version. This is not standard redaction with black boxes - the text was completely deleted from the visible document while remaining embedded in the PDF's internal version history.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Screenshot from the first version of the document, containing the hidden text (sections 5.1.5.2 - 5.1.5.6).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Screenshot from the second version of the document, where the text is removed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The removed text:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;5.1.5.2 (U) Facility Name: Formally identified as the ,Mission Support Facility(MSF) also re- ferred as the Classic Wizard Reporting and Testing Center (CWRTC). 5.1.5.3 (S//TK) Cover Story: The fact of a cover story is S//TK, the cover story itself is unclas- sified. 5.1.5.4 (U) Software development, maintenance, testing, and communications support to a world-wide Navy communications and reporting system. 5.1.5.5 (U) Associations: 1. The term Potomac Mission Ground Station (PMGS)=S//TK 2. The term Classic Wizard Reporting and Testing Center (CWRTC)=UNCLASSIFIED 3. The term Naval Research Laboratory=UNCLASSIFIED 4. The fact that CWRTC is the cover name for the PMGS=S//TK 5. The fact that CWRTC is a communications and data relay location for the US=UNCLASSIFIED (no association w/NRO) 6. The fact that PMGS is located on the NRL=S//TK 7. The fact that the NRO has a MGS located on the NRL=S//TK 8. The fact that the CWRTC is located on the NRL=UNCLASSIFIED (no association w/NRO) 9. CWRTC associated w/NRO=S//TK 10. Association of NRO, CIA, or NSA personnel with the CWRTC=S//TK 11. Association of CWRTC with other NRO MGS=S//TK 12. Association of MSF with the NRO=S//TK. 13. Association of CWRTC with the ADF=UNCLASSIFIED (no association w/NRO) 5.1.5.6 (U) Visitors: CWRTC is housed within buildings 259 and 260 on the Naval Research Laboratory in Southwest Washington, DC.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second document "NRO SIGINT Guide for Pine Gap" also has two versions in the file metadata: an older one and a newer one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Screenshot from the first version of the document, containing the hidden text (section 5.1.2).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Screenshot from the second version of the document, where the text is removed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The removed text:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;5.1.2 (S//TK) Consolidated Denver Mission Ground Station (CDMGS) 5.1.2.1 (U) Facility Name: Aerospace Data Facility (ADF) 5.1.2.2 (S//TK) Cover Story: The fact of a cover story is S/TK, the cover story itself is unclassi- fied.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Potomac Mission Ground Station (PMGS)&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the "hidden version" of the document "Menwith satellite classification guide" section 5.1.5 describes a facility formally identified by its cover name "Mission Support Facility (MSF)," also referred to as the "Classic Wizard Reporting and Testing Center (CWRTC)." The classified operational designation is Potomac Mission Ground Station (PMGS).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Location: Buildings 259 and 260, Naval Research Laboratory, Southwest Washington, DC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public cover story: "Software development, maintenance, testing, and communications support to a world-wide Navy communications and reporting system."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actual function: Mission Ground Station in the National Reconnaissance Office's satellite intelligence network.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The document explicitly states that "the fact of a cover story is S//TK" - meaning even acknowledging that CWRTC is a cover name (rather than the facility's real identity) is classified Secret/Talent Keyhole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The classification guide provides a detailed breakdown of what's public and what's secret:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;"Classic Wizard Reporting and Testing Center (CWRTC)" = UNCLASSIFIED&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;"Potomac Mission Ground Station (PMGS)" = S//TK (SECRET)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The fact that CWRTC is a cover name for PMGS = S//TK (SECRET)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Association of NRO, CIA, or NSA personnel with CWRTC = S//TK (SECRET)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;This layered classification allows the facility to operate under a public identity while keeping its actual intelligence designation and function secret.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Consolidated Denver Mission Ground Station (CDMGS)&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the "hidden version" of the document "NRO SIGINT Guide for Pine Gap" section 5.1.2 describes a facility identified by the cover name "Aerospace Data Facility (ADF)". The classified operational designation is "Consolidated Denver Mission Ground Station (CDMGS)."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Location: Buckley Space Force Base, Aurora, Colorado&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public acknowledgment: Publicly known as "Aerospace Data Facility-Colorado." For example ADF-C is openly described in Wikipedia as an NRO facility for "command and control of reconnaissance satellites."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What's NOT public: The operational designation "Consolidated Denver Mission Ground Station" and the fact that "Aerospace Data Facility" is a cover name for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with PMGS, the classification guide shows "the fact of a cover story is S//TK" - the deception itself is classified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both hidden facilities appear in an organizational classification table in the Pine Gap guide. The table's visual structure reveals which names refer to the same facilities through deliberate formatting. Thicker borders separate distinct facility groups, while thinner borders separate columns within each group (this might be a bit hard to see from the screenshot/document). Each facility appears multiple times - once under its classified operational designation, and again under its unclassified cover name(s):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The groupings show:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Denver facility: CDMGS (real designation) + ADF (cover name) + FSD (Field Station Denver, cover name)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Potomac facility: PMGS (real designation) + MSF (cover name) + CWRTC (cover name)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Menwith Hill: HMGS (real designation) + RAF MHS (cover name)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Pine Gap: AMGS (real designation) + JDFPG (cover name)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;For each facility, the real operational designation (CDMGS, PMGS, HMGS, AMGS) has all agency associations classified S//TK (Secret). But the cover names have NSA and NGA associations marked as unclassified (U) or For Official Use Only (U//FOUO).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This creates a classification system where you can publicly acknowledge intelligence work using sanitized facility names, while the actual operational designations remain secret.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The domestic facilities use two cover names each (ADF + FSD for Denver; MSF + CWRTC for Potomac), while foreign facilities use only one. This suggests layered operational security for facilities on U.S. soil - possibly to navigate Congressional oversight, legal restrictions on domestic intelligence operations, or different audiences requiring different levels of plausible deniability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a deliberate pattern in these two classification guides: detailed sections describing specific U.S. facilities were removed, while equivalent foreign facility sections were published intact. The 2016 Menwith Hill guide had its PMGS section (5.1.5) completely removed. The 2017 Pine Gap guide had its CDMGS section (5.1.2) completely removed. Both guides retained their detailed descriptions of foreign facilities, including operational designations, cover stories, and visitor protocols.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. facilities weren't entirely absent from the published documents. The Pine Gap classification table shows CDMGS, PMGS, ADF, and other U.S. facility designations alongside foreign facilities, revealing the structure of the Mission Ground Station network. Other published documents from both investigations mention U.S. facilities. What was specifically removed were the detailed classification guide sections that would have explained these U.S. facilities the same way Menwith Hill and Pine Gap were explained.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Who edited the documents?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;PDF metadata provides forensic evidence of the editing process. The Pine Gap classification guide shows timestamps from July 31, 2017, three weeks before publication. Two versions were created minutes apart using Nitro Pro 8, a commercial PDF editor: version 1 at 13:48:54 (containing the CDMGS section) and version 2 at 13:50:48 (with CDMGS removed). The Intercept and ABC published identical PDFs with the same metadata artifacts, indicating the editing was done once and the same file shared between organizations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Intercept, as holder of the Snowden archive, likely handled technical document preparation for publications. The Menwith Hill classification guide, published solely by The Intercept in 2016, shows more thorough metadata sanitization but the same editorial pattern - domestic facility sections removed while foreign equivalents remain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We contacted Ryan Gallagher, the journalist who led both investigations, to ask about the editorial decision to remove these sections. After more than a week, we have not received a response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next part will be a technical deep-dive into PDF metadata across the published Snowden documents. We found that many documents contain multiple versions in their metadata, revealing the editorial redaction process: visible NSA agents' usernames that were later removed, screenshots that were later redacted, and surveillance data that went through multiple rounds of redaction. We'll also document cases of failed redactions - including one where redacted text remained fully copyable, previously reported only by a Polish cybersecurity blog.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Notes&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can extract versions from a PDF file for example with a pdfresurrect tool (pdfresurrect -w filename.pdf).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can download the document versions directly here:&lt;/p&gt;Menwith satellite classification guide versions: NRO SIGINT Guide for Pine Gap versions:&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://libroot.org/posts/going-through-snowden-documents-part-4/"/><published>2026-01-10T11:23:59+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46565132</id><title>Eulogy for Dark Sky, a data visualization masterpiece (2023)</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:45.506242+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf2e3a527d562d9d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On January 1, 2023, Apple sunsetted (pun intended) the Dark Sky mobile app on iOS. Apple purchased the company behind the popular weather application in early 2020, then announced that it would be shutting down the Dark Sky applications (first on Android, then on iOS and web), and finally stated in 2022 that the forecast technology would be integrated into the Apple Weather app with iOS 16.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Dark Sky was much more than just an API or a set of “forecast technologies.” The design of the Dark Sky mobile application represented a hallmark of information design because the team clearly obsessed over how people would actually use the app on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s a gallery of screenshots I personally took in the last year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The design of Dark Sky was so wonderful that I could understand the shape of the weather at a glance, even from a zoomed out view of the app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Common use cases for a weather app&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before we can dissect what makes the design of this app so special, let’s define the most common use cases for a weather app. A good weather app attempts to address a range of use cases in a person’s life. Here are some common use cases for a weather app, starting with the contextual goals first:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that the questions I want to answer vary based on the context and situation I’m in. This is the perfect situation for software that embraces good information design principles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Magic Ink, Bret Victor defined information design “as the design of context-sensitive information graphics.” Unlike static graphics, like a weather map in a newspaper, information graphics in software can be highly dynamic and can incorporate context from the user’s environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dark Sky aggressively leaned into these ideas, and the team worked hard to turn nearly everything in the application into a context-sensitive information graphic. Let’s dive deeper into some examples where this notion is in full display.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Weather forecast for the day at a precise location&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ll start by listing my goals when trying to understand the upcoming weather for the day:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default experience for the Dark Sky application is to show weather for the next 12 hours at my precise location. Here are three screenshots from the app, from different days and locations. What do you notice?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The app contextualizes the information that’s presented based on what’s most relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the left-most screenshot, the context of the weather storm that’s passing by my location and some potential light rain is emphasized to the user. The wind advisory and dip in the “feels like” temperature also make honorable mentions. In combination with the clickable Wind Advisory warning, I can quickly understand that the storm has passed my specific location but I should still be mindful of the wind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the middle screenshot, the storm front heading my direction, the imminent rain starting within the hour, and the hours of rain later in the day are emphasized front and center. Based on my interest in the rain, I scrolled down (not shown in screenshot) to switch from temperature to rain probability for the main weather view.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the right-most screenshot, the temperature distribution throughout the day is emphasized.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are lots of little details that are easy to miss, as well. For example, all three screenshots above start showing weather information starting at the current moment (“now”) and onwards. This is brilliant, because I only occasionally care about weather from a few hours or days ago. (To accommodate those situations, the app did have a unique Time Machine view to explore past weather data.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Weather forecast for the week&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s revisit our goals when trying to understand the weather for the week:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While many other weather apps focus on helping me understand the weather at the city level, the Dark Sky app differentiates itself by enabling me to understand the weather with a hyperlocal view. I can view the weather at specific addresses and landmarks and understand how the weather might be different in a city center compared to the towns around it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, the Dark Sky app shows the weekly weather summary at my current location (screenshot on the left). I can contextualize the weekly weather view by clicking the search icon and typing in the alternative location I’m interested in (screenshot on the right).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At a glance, I can quickly understand:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Which days are likely to rain.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Which days have wide temperature ranges (low lows and high highs).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The general shape of the weather (micro-trends).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Gallery of subtle design elements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the first few sections, I laid the groundwork by diving a bit more deeply into specific aspects of Dark Sky. Now that I’ve hopefully engaged your critical design eye, I’d like to elevate other elements in the app’s design in a more rapid-fire fashion. I hope that this section will provide some ideas and inspiration for people designing their own data-rich applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Preserving temperature magnitudes in ranges&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To represent data visually, the data needs to be mapped from “data space” to “pixel space”. In some domains and scenarios, you want to ensure the magnitudes are carried over, and in others you want to rescale the values to a fixed scale so the resulting charts are more consistent in the space and pixels they take up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the Dark Sky app, the “temperature pills” representing the forecasted temperatures for the upcoming week preserve their existing magnitude more effectively in the visualization. The temperature values are more tightly integrated with the visual representation, making the combined experience more amenable to quick comparison across multiple days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many weather apps opt for the design pattern on the right, where all temperature ranges are rescaled to take up the same amount of space in the app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Replacing numbers with rough categories&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interpreting hourly distributions of rainfall or snowfall can be difficult. Is 0.25 inches of rain a lot over the next hour? What about 0.2 inches of snow per hour for the next hour, then 0.15 for the hour after that? How do I prepare for these circumstances?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To help users stay informed and take action, the app will often replace precise forecast distributions of rainfall and snowfall with rough categories instead. This design choice has two positive effects on users:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It contextualizes the forecast to simpler categories that can help us quickly make changes in our life if needed. &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Light snow that starts and stops means that my snow shoveling company won’t come out, but heavy snow means they likely will.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Heavy snow means I should probably make sure my outdoor furniture is better covered and ready to take the snow.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It removes a sense of artificial precision that doesn’t really exist because weather forecasts fundamentally have very high uncertainty and error bands.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contextualized storm map&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simple color scales combined with arrows go a very long way to conveying relevant storm information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wind direction&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of conveying wind direction using text (“NW” or “Northwest”), the app uses arrows! If the wind shifts directions throughout the day, I can feel the wind direction changing using my body.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Complaints from former Dark Sky users&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you can tell, I could probably write an entire book about the design of Dark Sky.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, I want to share some passionate comments from other Dark Sky fans. While most of them aren’t data viz or design nerds, they feel that the Apple Weather app is not a sufficient replacement. These people relied on Dark Sky to make decisions and grew very attached to an application that integrated deeply into their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;0000GKP on Reddit: “I have already made the transition to the Weather app. The information is presented in a much less efficient manner than Dark Sky so it takes more effort to get it, but it is all there (except for cloud cover).”&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TheGeckoDude on Reddit: “Is there anything that has the precipitation graph similar to dark sky? The biggest thing I will miss from dark sky is that graph. I’m outside a lot and it is super helpful for knowing when to take cover or when it might rain. I need to find a feature like that because the vague weather precipitation info will not cut it for me.”&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Let’s make data shine!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dark Sky started with publicly available data, augmented it with contextualized predictions, rigorously iterated on data visualization design, and packaged all of this into a contextualized experience to make weather data useful for me in my daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the availability of data has never been higher, we’re still missing software experiences that contextualize that data to make our lives better. Data alone isn’t enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The world needs more Dark Sky-like experiences to help us improve our spending habits, help us sleep better, and more. If you’re working on information software, I hope you can be inspired by the body of design and engineering work that Dark Sky pioneered.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Srini Kadamati&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Srini Kadamati currently helps build better data management tools for biomedical research at Manifold.ai. Previously, he taught data visualization and data skills at Dataquest.io and Preset.io.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nightingaledvs.com/dark-sky-weather-data-viz/"/><published>2026-01-10T12:23:20+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46565695</id><title>NASA announces unprecedented return of sick ISS astronaut and crew</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:45.376844+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="c3c0e35d9cd795ce"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;NASA announces unprecedented return of sick ISS astronaut and crew&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA has announced the early return of Crew-11 from the International Space Station after an unidentified astronaut experienced a medical problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA has postponed a spacewalk outside the International Space Station (ISS) and announced the early return of its crew due to a medical issue that arose on Wednesday (Jan. 7) with one of the astronauts on board, the agency said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The spacewalk was planned for 8 a.m. ET on Thursday (Jan. 8) to finish preparing a power channel where a new solar array is set to be installed on the ISS. American astronauts Mike Fincke and Zena Cardman were scheduled to exit the space station for 6.5 hours in what would have been Cardman's first spacewalk. (Fincke has already performed nine spacewalks.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA did not name the crew member experiencing the medical problem or share any further details about the emergency, but the agency has confirmed that the issue involves one individual whose condition is stable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"These are the situations NASA and our partners train for and prepare to execute safely," a NASA spokesperson wrote in an email update on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the agency has confirmed it will bring Fincke, Cardman and two other astronauts, who are part of the current four-person crew aboard the ISS, home early from their stay at the orbital outpost. "Safely conducting our missions is our highest priority, and we are actively evaluating all options, including the possibility of an earlier end to Crew-11's mission," the spokesperson said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Crew-11 arrived at the ISS on Aug. 2, 2025. Fincke and Cardman were joined by Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency astronaut Kimiya Yui and Roscosmos cosmonaut Oleg Platonov for a six-month mission, after which the astronauts were set to be replaced by Crew-12 as part of the space station's regular staffing rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Crew-12's launch is scheduled for mid-February. It is unclear what returning Crew-11 home early would mean for the ISS, as such changes to the usual rotation are highly unusual, but there are other astronauts living on the space station at the moment — including NASA's Christopher Williams and Russian cosmonauts Sergey Kud-Sverchkov and Sergey Mikayev, who arrived at the orbiting lab aboard a Russian Soyuz spacecraft that destroyed its launching pad in November.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get the world’s most fascinating discoveries delivered straight to your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA has said it will announce a target return date in the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Editor’s note: This story has been updated following NASA’s confirmation that Crew-11 will return earlier than originally planned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sascha is a U.K.-based staff writer at Live Science. She holds a bachelor’s degree in biology from the University of Southampton in England and a master’s degree in science communication from Imperial College London. Her work has appeared in The Guardian and the health website Zoe. Besides writing, she enjoys playing tennis, bread-making and browsing second-hand shops for hidden gems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must confirm your public display name before commenting&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please logout and then login again, you will then be prompted to enter your display name.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.livescience.com/space/space-exploration/nasa-cancels-spacewalk-and-considers-early-crew-return-from-iss-due-to-medical-issues"/><published>2026-01-10T13:44:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46566465</id><title>I replaced Windows with Linux and everything's going great</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:45.241839+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="15a6595bd9b335ce"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Greetings from the year of Linux on my desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;I replaced Windows with Linux and everything’s going great&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linux diary, chapter one: winging it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linux diary, chapter one: winging it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In November, I got fed up and said screw it, I’m installing Linux. Since that article was published, I have dealt with one minor catastrophe after another. None of that has anything to do with Linux, mind you. It just meant I didn’t install it on my desktop until Sunday evening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My goal here is to see how far I can get using Linux as my main OS without spending a ton of time futzing with it — or even much time researching beforehand. I am not looking for more high-maintenance hobbies at this stage. I want to see if Linux is a wingable alternative to Microsoft’s increasingly annoying OS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Honestly? So far it’s been fine. Many things I expected to be difficult — like getting my Nvidia graphics card working properly — were perfectly straightforward. A few things I thought would be simple weren’t. And I’ve run into one very funny issue with a gaming mouse that only works in games. But I’ve been able to use my Linux setup for work this week, I played exactly one video game, and I even printed something from my accursed printer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Day one&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I picked CachyOS rather than a better-known distro like Ubuntu because it’s optimized for modern hardware, and I had heard that it’s easy to install and set up for gaming, which is one of the reasons I’d stuck with Windows for this long. After backing up my Windows image sometime in December (close enough), I follow the installation instructions in the Cachy wiki and download the CachyOS live image to a Ventoy USB drive, plug it into my PC, reboot into the BIOS to disable Secure Boot, reboot again into the Ventoy bootloader, and launch the CachyOS disk image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First challenge: My mouse buttons don’t work. I can move the cursor, but can’t click on anything. I try plugging in a mouse (without unplugging the first one), same deal. Not a major issue; I can get around fine with just the keyboard. Maybe this is just an issue with the live image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I launch the installer and am thrust into analysis paralysis. An operating system needs lots of little pieces to work — stuff you don’t even think of as individual components if you use Mac or Windows. How do you boot into the OS? What runs the desktop environment? How are windows drawn? What’s the file system? Where do you get software updates? In Mac and Windows, all those decisions are made for you. But Linux is fundamentally different: The core of the OS is the kernel, and everything else is kind of up to you. A distro is just somebody’s idea of what pieces to use. Some, like Pop_OS! and Mint, aim for simplicity and make all those choices for you (though you can still change them if you want). But Cachy is based on Arch, a notoriously DIY distro, and before I do anything else, I have to pick one of four bootloaders. I pick Limine, for reasons I can’t recall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, I need to figure out where to install it. On the recommendation of Will Smith from the Dual Boot Diaries podcast — from whom the “an operating system is a bunch of pieces” thing above is largely cribbed — I install Cachy on a different physical drive from Windows, since Windows updates tend not to care if they overwrite other bootloaders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have a 4TB storage drive with just over a terabyte of data on it, so I shrink that partition down to 2TB using the installer’s manual partitioning interface, then (following the guide) make a 2GB boot partition and a root partition using the btrfs file system. The guide says it needs at least 20GB, so I go big and make it 100GB. This will cause a minor problem later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, I have to pick one of thirteen different desktop environments. This is too many options. KDE and Gnome seem to be the best-supported for gaming, so I pick KDE. I could rabbit-hole on this, but I don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then I just have to pick a username and password and name the computer. After some thought, I go with Maggie, after my in-laws’ cat, who half the family calls Linux. She doesn’t answer to either name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Installation takes six minutes. I reboot the computer, and it loads into the Limine bootloader, which has also found my Windows install, so I can choose between Cachy and Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then I’m on the Cachy desktop, and my mouse buttons still aren’t working. Swapping USB ports doesn’t do anything. Plugging in my trackball doesn’t fix it either. I finally try unplugging the mouse, which makes the trackball work normally. My gaming mouse is an ancient Mad Catz Cyborg RAT 7; it turns out this is a known issue. I defer editing configuration files for now and just keep the mouse unplugged.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Stuff that works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That weird mouse aside, all of the hardware I’ve tried so far has just worked. Cachy automatically installed the correct GPU drivers; my monitor, speakers, and Logitech webcam work fine with no effort. Even my printer prints, with only a tweak to my firewall settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are lots of ways to install apps on Linux. Sometimes you can just download them from a company’s website, or you get them from your distro’s official repositories, or GitHub, or wherever. There’s no official app store for Linux, but there are at least three projects aiming to provide universal Linux apps: Flatpak, AppImage, and Snap. Neat! Commence hodgepodging.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I grab Chromium, Discord, Slack, and Audacity using the “Install Apps” button on Cachy’s welcome screen. Slack I get from the Arch User Repository. Twenty minutes later, I try to install 1Password from the same location, but the repository is down. I pick up my kid from a playdate and try again. It works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s missing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I prefer the Arc browser, which doesn’t have a Linux build, but there are plenty of browsers. Firefox and Chromium will do. I can’t find official apps for Airtable (which I use for work), Spotify, or Apple Music, but they all work fine in the browser in the short term, and I’ll revisit this later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Shall we play a game?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cachy has a one-click gaming package install that includes the Proton compatibility layer, Steam, and Heroic (a launcher for Epic, GOG, and Amazon). I figure I ought to try one game. Then I remember that my root partition is only 100GB. I reboot back into the Cachy live image and use the Parted utility to increase it to 1TB, then make a second btrfs partition in the remaining space. I reboot, log into Epic and GOG, and start downloading The Outer Worlds, a game from 2019 I’ve been playing a bit lately. It runs fine with Proton, and I can even sync my saves from the cloud. I play it for a few minutes with my trackball, remember I hate gaming on a trackball, and plug my gaming mouse back in. It works fine as long as I’m in the game, but outside the game, mouse clicks stop working again. It makes sense — the bug is on the desktop, not in games — but it’s very funny to have a gaming mouse that only works for gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The children yearn for the mines&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The biggest issue I’ve had so far is Minecraft: Bedrock Edition. For some reason, Microsoft hasn’t prioritized making a Linux version of Bedrock. Java Edition works fine in Linux, but I play Minecraft with my kids, and they’re on Bedrock Edition on their iPads. There’s supposed to be a way to run the Android app with MCPE Launcher, but I couldn’t get it to work. There’s also a project to get the Windows version running on Proton, which will be my next step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Stuff I haven’t tried yet&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hear good things about howdy, a Linux equivalent to Windows Hello face authentication, but I haven’t installed it yet. I hear the Zen browser is a good Arc alternative. I also haven’t gotten my cloud storage synced, configured git so I can compile programs from scratch, figured out a backup strategy, or tried much other hardware beyond what’s currently plugged into my computer. There’s a command-line Spotify player I want to try. I’ve only scratched the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I did take the time to install a KDE Plasma theme that makes it look like Windows XP, though. Just because.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Regret level: none&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m well aware this is the honeymoon phase. And using Linux for less than a week isn’t exactly a flex. Many people use Linux. And I haven’t even tried doing anything particularly difficult, or playing a game that came out this decade. But so far it’s been a much easier transition than expected, and a quieter experience overall. My OS isn’t trying to change my browser or search engine to make some shareholder happy somewhere. It’s not nudging me to try some bullshit AI feature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Will I go crawling back to macOS or Windows the first time I have to edit a batch of photos? Possibly! I’ll definitely boot back into Windows — or pull out a Chromebook — to play Minecraft with my kids, if I can’t get it running on Linux. And I don’t think I’ll ever be able to use Linux exclusively; my job as a reviews editor means I have to stay familiar with as many operating systems as possible. (This is a good way to drive yourself nuts.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m sure I’ll run into plenty of fun problems soon enough. But the first few days have been great.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.theverge.com/tech/858910/linux-diary-gaming-desktop"/><published>2026-01-10T15:26:26+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46566812</id><title>Open Chaos: A self-evolving open-source project</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:45.076056+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="fb86c60a4e7c76a6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;OPENCHAOS.DEV&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;--d --h --m --s&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;until next merge&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Open PRs — Vote to merge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Loading PRs...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;until next merge&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Loading PRs...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @yokeTH&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @wvanlit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @BetonZM&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @bpottle&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @FelixLttks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @matthewmayer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @Mad182&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @Dart120&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @julian9499&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @addshore&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @fccview&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @amanbabuhemant&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @antonmyrberg&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @ksurya&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @Loeffeldude&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @bigintersmind&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @henryivesjones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @Kl0ven&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @addshore&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @GoodPassiveMan&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @prakashsellathurai&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @kouta-kun&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @ectucker1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @bigintersmind&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by @icco&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.openchaos.dev/"/><published>2026-01-10T16:03:55+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46567392</id><title>AI is a business model stress test</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:45.000764+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e63d233e7760e68"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;AI is a business model stress test&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI commoditizes anything you can specify. It can't commoditize what you have to operate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailwind Labs laid off 75% of its engineering team last week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adam Wathan, CEO of Tailwind Labs, spent the holidays running revenue forecasts. In a GitHub comment, he explained what happened:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The reality is that 75% of the people on our engineering team lost their jobs here yesterday because of the brutal impact AI has had on our business. Traffic to our docs is down about 40% from early 2023 despite Tailwind being more popular than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The story circulating is that AI is killing Open Source businesses. I don't think that is quite right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI didn't kill Tailwind's business. It stress tested it. Their business model failed the test, but that is not an indictment of all Open Source business models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailwind's business model worked for years. It relied on developers visiting their documentation, discovering Tailwind Plus while browsing, and buying it. Tailwind Plus is a $299 collection of pre-built UI components. Traffic led to discovery, and discovery drove sales. It was a reasonable business model, but always fragile.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the last year, more and more developers started asking AI for code instead of reading documentation, and their sales and marketing funnel broke.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a fairness issue here that I don't want to skip past. AI companies trained their models on Tailwind's documentation and everything the community wrote about it. And now those models generate Tailwind code and answer Tailwind questions without sending anyone to Tailwind's website. The value got extracted, but compensation isn't flowing back. That bothers me, and it deserves a broader policy conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I keep coming back to is this: AI commoditizes anything you can fully specify. Documentation, pre-built card components, a CSS library, Open Source plugins. Tailwind's commercial offering was built on "specifications". AI made those things trivial to generate. AI can ship a specification but it can't run a business.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So where does value live now? In what requires showing up, not just specifying. Not what you can specify once, but what requires showing up again and again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Value is shifting to operations: deployment, testing, rollbacks, observability. You can't prompt 99.95% uptime on Black Friday. Neither can you prompt your way to keeping a site secure, updated, and running.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is why Vercel created Next.js and gives it away for free. The Open Source framework is the conduit; the hosting is the product. Same with Acquia, my own company. A big part of Acquia's business model is selling products around Drupal: hosting, search, CI/CD pipelines, digital asset management, and more. We don't sell describable things; we sell operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open Source was never the commercial product. It's the conduit to something else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When asked what to pivot to, Wathan was candid: "Still to this day, I don't know what we should be pivoting to". I've written about how digital agencies might evolve, but CSS frameworks and component libraries are a harder case. Some Open Source projects make for great features, but not great businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailwind CSS powers millions of sites. The framework will survive. Whether the company does is a different question. I'm rooting for them. The world needs more successful Open Source businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;—&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://dri.es/ai-is-a-business-model-stress-test"/><published>2026-01-10T16:56:34+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46567400</id><title>Show HN: I used Claude Code to discover connections between 100 books</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:44.859983+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f5f22681c15b4f4c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Useful Lies&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Self-deception as strategy: the best liars believe themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Self-deception as strategy: the best liars believe themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microscopic defects propagate silently until catastrophic failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The hunt for words that stick&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weak IP accelerates innovation through collaborative copying.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why isolated groups lose knowledge and capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Absent fathers forged titan ambition through unmet longing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mega-projects orchestrate unreliable elements into coherent wholes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Desperation, not genius, drove transformative pivots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expertise defies formalization; conscious effort defeats itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Constraints in one part dictate the whole.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protected spaces insulated from interference enable breakthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical knowledge defeats rationalized systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rule-breaking as path to understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ego-dissolution enables both transcendence and manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Imitation powers both learning and conformity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Winners eliminate competition; victory becomes permanent control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every treasure becomes tomorrow's ordinary commodity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Metrics become mirages when optimized directly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rare signals drown in false positives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Silent agreements to avoid uncomfortable truths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Founders ousted through political power dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mastery means bypassing conscious thought entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Removing friction sometimes creates chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organizations minimize coalitions needed to maintain control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ripe ideas emerge independently across the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Copying forms without understanding structure guarantees failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actions must be expensive to be believed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gifts, moral debts, and technical debt share logic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joy became more productive than efficiency optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Getting worse precedes getting better in skill.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Large coordination emerges from small-scale trust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standardization enables scale but destroys local knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Method of creation shapes what is created.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open systems consolidate into monopoly, then repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transforming vague concepts into testable frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building observability changes what you see.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decision-making speed determines conflict outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simplification enables breakthroughs or destroys value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Knowing what others don't creates competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Precise measurement creates infrastructure for distant trust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Container shipping remade global supply chains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pursuit of perfection prevents completion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Import order constantly or dissolve into disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simplified models systematically fail in complex reality.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://trails.pieterma.es/"/><published>2026-01-10T16:56:55+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46567458</id><title>UpCodes (YC S17) is hiring PMs, SWEs to automate construction compliance</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:44.715992+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f1efd1e76f34fe34"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try for Free&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://up.codes/careers?utm_source=HN"/><published>2026-01-10T17:01:49+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46568662</id><title>Rats caught on camera hunting flying bats</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:43.678747+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="774931e969a21e9c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In northern Germany, researchers have filmed brown rats (Rattus norvegicus) leaping from cave ledges to catch bats mid-flight — the first evidence that rodents can intercept flying mammals. The finding, published in Global Ecology and Conservation, turns one of ecology’s everyday characters into an unexpectedly agile predator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The behavior was recorded at Segeberg Kalkberg, a limestone cave that shelters around 30,000 hibernating bats each winter. Using infrared video over five weeks in autumn 2020 and thermal cameras from 2021 to 2024, a team led by Florian Gloza-Rausch in Bad Segeberg captured footage that’s unusual, for sure: a rat balancing on its hind legs at the cave entrance, sensing the movement of wings in the dark, then springing up to seize a bat from the air.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Across five weeks of monitoring, the researchers confirmed 13 kills and found a hidden cache of 52 bat carcasses — clear signs that the rats weren’t scavenging leftovers but hunting deliberately. At that rate, a small group of rats could wipe out about 7% of the bat population in a single season.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s remarkable for an animal not built for flight or pursuit. Brown rats are omnivores that typically scavenge or prey on slow-moving targets. Yet here, they appear to have developed two hunting strategies: aerial interception at the cave mouth and ground attacks on bats crawling to roost. How the rats locate their targets in near-darkness isn’t fully clear, but researchers suspect they use whisker and hearing cues rather than sight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similar: Brain-Wide Map Shows How Prior Knowledge Guides Mouse Decisions&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study describes this as unexpected behavioral plasticity in brown rats. The researchers believe the dense streams of bats and the narrow cave geometry created the perfect ambush zone — a place where a patient predator could learn a new trick.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The discovery also adds a new stressor to European bat populations, which are already under pressure from habitat loss and disease. Because brown rats are invasive across much of the continent, their access to major hibernation sites could have lasting ecological effects. The authors suggest managing rat presence near large roosts as a precaution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the most compelling part of the finding lies not in its numbers but in its image: a common city rat, usually seen raiding bins, now standing alert in a cave mouth, hunting with precision that blurs the line between scavenger and specialist. It’s a reminder that adaptation doesn’t always unfold in distant rainforests — sometimes it happens under our own streetlights, in ways no one thought to look for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Story Source: Gloza-Rausch et al. (2025), published in Global Ecology and Conservation. Read the study here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://scienceclock.com/rats-caught-on-camera-hunting-flying-bats-for-the-first-time/"/><published>2026-01-10T18:44:46+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46568794</id><title>Finding and fixing Ghostty's largest memory leak</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:43.552919+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="36d8d949fca010a8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Mitchell Hashimoto&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Finding and Fixing Ghostty's Largest Memory Leak&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few months ago, users started reporting that Ghostty was consuming absurd amounts of memory, with one user reporting 37 GB after 10 days of uptime. Today, I'm happy to say the fix has been found and merged. This post is an overview of what caused the leak, a look at some of Ghostty's internals, and some brief descriptions of how we tracked it down.1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The leak was present since at least Ghostty 1.0, but it is only recently that popular CLI applications (particularly Claude Code) started producing the correct conditions to trigger it at scale. The limited conditions that triggered the leak are what made it particularly tricky to diagnose.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fix is merged and is available in tip/nightly releases, and will be part of the tagged 1.3 release in March.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The PageList&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To understand the bug, we first need to understand how Ghostty manages terminal memory. Ghostty uses a data structure called the &lt;code&gt;PageList&lt;/code&gt;
to store terminal content. PageList is a doubly-linked list of
memory pages that store the terminal content (characters, styles, hyperlinks,
etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The underlying "pages" are not single virtual memory pages but they are a contiguous block of memory aligned to page boundaries and composed of an even multiple of system pages.2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These pages are allocated using &lt;code&gt;mmap&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;mmap&lt;/code&gt; isn't particularly fast,
so to avoid constant syscalls, we use a memory pool. When we need
a new page, we pull from the pool. When we're done with a page, we return
it to the pool for reuse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pool uses a standard size for pages. Think of it like buying standard-sized shipping boxes: most things people ship fit in a standard box, and having a standard box comes with various efficiencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But sometimes terminals need more memory than a standard page provides. If a set of lines has many emoji, styles, or hyperlinks, we need a larger page. In these cases, we allocate a non-standard page directly with &lt;code&gt;mmap&lt;/code&gt;, bypassing the pool entirely. This is typically a
rare scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we "free" a page, we apply some simple logic:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If the page is &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;= standard size&lt;/code&gt;: return it to the pool&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If the page is &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; standard size&lt;/code&gt;: call&lt;code&gt;munmap&lt;/code&gt;to free it&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the core background for terminal memory management in Ghostty, and the idea itself is sound. A logic bug around an optimization is what produced the leak, as we'll see next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Scrollback Optimization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's one more background detail we need to cover to understand the bug: scrollback pruning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ghostty has a &lt;code&gt;scrollback-limit&lt;/code&gt; configuration that caps how much history
is retained. When you hit this limit, we delete the oldest pages in
the scrollback buffer to free up memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this often happens in a super hot path (e.g. when outputting large amounts of data quickly), and allocating and freeing memory pages is expensive, even with the pool. Therefore, we have an optimization: reuse the oldest page as the newest page when we reach the limit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This optimization works great. It requires zero allocations and uses only some quick pointer manipulations to move the page from the front to the back of the list. We do some metadata cleanup to "clear" the page but otherwise leave the previous memory intact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's fast and empirically speeds up scrollback-heavy workloads significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Bug&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During the scrollback pruning optimization, we always resized our page back to standard size. But we didn't resize the underlying memory allocation itself, we only noted the resize in the metadata. The underlying memory was still the large non-standard &lt;code&gt;mmap&lt;/code&gt; allocation, but now the PageList thought it was standard
sized.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eventually, we'd free the page under various circumstances (e.g. when the user closes the terminal, but also other times). At that point, we'd see the page memory was within the standard size, assume it was part of the pool, and we would never call &lt;code&gt;munmap&lt;/code&gt; on it.
A classic leak.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This all seems pretty obvious, but the issue is that non-standard pages are rare by design. The goal of our design and optimizations is that standard pages are the common case and provide a fast-path. Only very specific scenarios produce non-standard pages and they're usually not produced in large quantities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the rise of Claude Code changed this. For some reason, Claude Code's CLI produces a lot of multi-codepoint grapheme outputs which force Ghostty to regularly use non-standard pages. Additionally, Claude Code uses the primary screen and produces a significant amount of scrollback output. These things combined together created the perfect storm to trigger the leak in huge quantities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to be explicit that this bug is not Claude Code's fault. Claude Code is simply exercising Ghostty in a way that exposes this long-standing bug.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Fix&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fix is conceptually simple: never reuse non-standard pages. If we encounter a non-standard page during scrollback pruning, we destroy it properly (calling &lt;code&gt;munmap&lt;/code&gt;) and allocate a fresh
standard-sized page from the pool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core of the fix is in the snippet below, but some extra work was needed to fix up some other bits of accounting we have:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;if (first.data.memory.len &amp;gt; std_size) {
    self.destroyNode(first);
    break :prune;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We could've also reused the non-standard page and just retained the large memory size, but until we have data that shows otherwise, we're still operating under the assumption that standard pages are the common case and it makes sense to reset back to a standard pooled page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other users have recommended more complex strategies (e.g. maintaining some metrics on how often non-standard pages are used and adjusting our assumptions accordingly), but more research is needed before making those changes. This change is simple, fixes the bug, and aligns with our current assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Finding the Leak with VM Tags&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As part of the fix, I added support for virtual memory tags on macOS provided by the Mach kernel. This lets us tag our PageList memory allocations with a specific identifier that shows up in various tooling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;inline fn pageAllocator() Allocator {
    // In tests we use our testing allocator so we can detect leaks.
    if (builtin.is_test) return std.testing.allocator;

    // On non-macOS we use our standard Zig page allocator.
    if (!builtin.target.os.tag.isDarwin()) return std.heap.page_allocator;

    // On macOS we want to tag our memory so we can assign it to our
    // core terminal usage.
    const mach = @import("../os/mach.zig");
    return mach.taggedPageAllocator(.application_specific_1);
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now when debugging memory on macOS, Ghostty's PageList memory shows up with a specific tag instead of being lumped in with everything else. This made it trivial to identify the leak, associate it with the PageList, and also verify that the fix worked by observing the tagged memory being properly freed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Preventing Leaks in Ghostty&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We do a lot of work in the Ghostty project to find and prevent memory leaks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;In debug builds and unit tests, we use leak-detecting Zig allocators.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The CI runs &lt;code&gt;valgrind&lt;/code&gt;on our full unit test suite on every commit to find more than just leaks, such as undefined memory usage.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We regularly run the macOS GUI via macOS Instruments to look for leaks particularly in the Swift codebase.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We run every GTK-related PR using Valgrind (the full GUI) to look for leaks in the GTK codepath that isn't unit tested.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This has worked really well to date, but unfortunately it didn't catch this particular leak because it only triggers under very specific conditions that our tests didn't reproduce. The merged PR includes a test that does reproduce the leak to prevent regressions in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was the largest known memory leak in Ghostty to date, and the only reported leak that has been confirmed by more than a single user. We'll continue to monitor and address memory reports as they come in, but remember that reproduction is the key to diagnosing and fixing memory leaks!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Big thanks to @grishy who finally got me a reliable reproduction so I could analyze the issue myself. Their own analysis reached the same conclusion as mine, and the reproduction let me verify both our understandings independently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks also to everyone who reported this issue with detailed diagnostics. The community's analysis, especially around the &lt;code&gt;footprint&lt;/code&gt; output and
VM region counting, gave me important clues that pointed toward the PageList
as the culprit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://mitchellh.com/writing/ghostty-memory-leak-fix"/><published>2026-01-10T18:58:37+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46569061</id><title>Show HN: Play poker with LLMs, or watch them play against each other</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:43.325173+00:00</updated><link href="https://llmholdem.com/"/><published>2026-01-10T19:27:39+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46569075</id><title>Bichon: A lightweight, high-performance Rust email archiver with WebUI</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:42.613635+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="4c95085b0904ffcd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bichon is an open-source email archiving system that synchronizes emails from IMAP servers, indexes them for full-text search, and provides a REST API for programmatic access. Unlike email clients, Bichon is designed for archiving and searching rather than sending/receiving emails. It runs as a standalone server application that continuously synchronizes configured email accounts and maintains a searchable local archive. Built in Rust, it requires no external dependencies and provides fast, efficient email archiving, management, and search through a built-in WebUI. Its name is inspired by the puppy my daughter adopted last month.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Feature&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Email Clients&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Bichon&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Primary Purpose&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Send/receive emails, real-time communication&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Archive, search, manage historical emails&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sending Capability&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Supports sending emails&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;❌ No email sending support&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Runtime Mode&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Desktop/mobile applications&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Server-side application&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Data Storage&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Local cache + server&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Local archive store&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Search Capability&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Basic search&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Full-text indexing, advanced search&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;API Interface&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Typically not provided&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Complete REST API&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Multi-account Management&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Limited&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Supports unified search across accounts&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lightweight &amp;amp; Standalone — Pure Rust, no external database, with built-in WebUI&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multi-Account Sync — Download and manage emails from multiple accounts&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Flexible Fetching — Sync by date range, email count, or specific mailboxes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;IMAP &amp;amp; OAuth2 Auth — Password or OAuth2 login with automatic token refresh&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Proxy &amp;amp; Auto Config — Supports network proxies and automatic IMAP discovery&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unified Search — Search across all accounts by sender, subject, body, date, size, attachments, and more&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tags &amp;amp; Facets — Organize emails using Tantivy facet-based tags&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compressed Storage — Transparent compression and deduplication for efficient storage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Email Management — Browse, view threads, bulk clean up, export EML or attachments&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dashboard &amp;amp; Analytics — Visual insights into email volume, trends, and top senders&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Internationalized WebUI — Frontend available in 18 languages&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OpenAPI Access — OpenAPI docs with access-token authentication&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multi-User &amp;amp; Role-Based Access Control (RBAC) — Supports multiple users with fine-grained, role-based permissions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Email Import (EML &amp;amp; MBOX) — Import existing mail archives via the bichonctl CLI&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I released rustmailer, an email API middleware:&lt;lb/&gt; https://github.com/rustmailer/rustmailer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since then, I’ve received many emails asking whether it could also archive emails, perform unified search, and support full-text indexing—not just querying recipients.&lt;lb/&gt; But rustmailer was designed as a middleware focused on providing API services.&lt;lb/&gt; Adding archiving and full-text search would complicate its core purpose and go far beyond its original scope.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I realized that email archiving itself only requires a small portion of rustmailer’s functionality, plus a search engine.&lt;lb/&gt; With that combination, building a dedicated, efficient archiver becomes much simpler.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the experience gained from rustmailer, I designed and built Bichon in less than two weeks, followed by another two weeks of testing and optimization.&lt;lb/&gt; It has now reached a stable, usable state—and I decided to release it publicly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bichon is completely free.&lt;lb/&gt; You can download and use it however you like.&lt;lb/&gt; It’s not perfect, but I hope it brings you value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Pull the image
docker pull rustmailer/bichon:latest

# Create data directory
mkdir -p ./bichon-data

# Run container
docker run -d \
  --name bichon \
  -p 15630:15630 \
  -v $(pwd)/bichon-data:/data \
  -e BICHON_LOG_LEVEL=info \
  -e BICHON_ROOT_DIR=/data \
  rustmailer/bichon:latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting from v0.1.4, Bichon changes how &lt;code&gt;BICHON_CORS_ORIGINS&lt;/code&gt; works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If &lt;code&gt;BICHON_CORS_ORIGINS&lt;/code&gt;is not set, Bichon now allows all origins. This makes local testing and simple deployments much easier.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you do set &lt;code&gt;BICHON_CORS_ORIGINS&lt;/code&gt;, then you must explicitly list each allowed origin.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt;is not supported and will not work — you must provide exact URLs.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a browser accesses Bichon, it will send an &lt;code&gt;Origin&lt;/code&gt; header.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Incoming Origin = the exact address the browser is using&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Configured origins = the list you passed to &lt;code&gt;BICHON_CORS_ORIGINS&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If Configured origins does not contain the Incoming Origin exactly as a full string match, the browser request will be rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example debug log:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;2025-12-06T23:56:30.422+08:00 DEBUG bichon::modules::rest: CORS: Incoming Origin = "http://localhost:15630"
2025-12-06T23:56:30.422+08:00 DEBUG bichon::modules::rest: CORS: Configured origins = ["http://192.168.3.2:15630"]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this example:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Browser is using &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:15630&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;But the configured origin is &lt;code&gt;http://192.168.3.2:15630&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;→ CORS will fail, and you can immediately see why.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is strongly recommended to configure CORS in production environments to ensure that only trusted browser origins can access Bichon. If you want to access Bichon from a browser:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add the exact IP with port&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Or the exact hostname with port&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Or the domain (port optional if it's 80)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;http://192.168.1.16:15630
http://myserver.local:15630
http://mydomain.com
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you access Bichon in multiple different ways, list all of them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;-e BICHON_CORS_ORIGINS="http://192.168.1.16:15630,http://myserver.local:15630,http://mydomain.com"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do not add a trailing slash (&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://192.168.1.16:15630/&lt;/code&gt;will not match)&lt;p&gt;Do not use&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt;, it is not supported.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set environment variable:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BICHON_LOG_LEVEL=debug
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or via command-line:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;--bichon-log-level debug
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default is &lt;code&gt;info&lt;/code&gt;, so CORS logs will not appear unless debug logging is enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;g-emoji&gt;⚠️&lt;/g-emoji&gt;Note: If you are running Bichon in a container (via Docker Compose or docker run), be careful with quotes in environment variable values.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, do not write:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;-e BICHON_CORS_ORIGINS="http://localhost:15630,http://myserver.local:15630"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The outer quotes (&lt;code&gt;"&lt;/code&gt;) will be passed literally into the container and may cause CORS misconfiguration.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Correct way:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;-e BICHON_CORS_ORIGINS=http://localhost:15630,http://myserver.local:15630&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or using YAML literal style for Docker Compose:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;environment:
  BICHON_CORS_ORIGINS: |
    http://localhost:15630,http://myserver.local:15630&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This ensures that the configured origins are interpreted correctly inside the container.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;g-emoji&gt;⚠️&lt;/g-emoji&gt;Note: This fucking problem I actually didn’t know about myself; thanks to gall-1 for pointing it out.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download the appropriate binary for your platform from the Releases page:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux (GNU): &lt;code&gt;bichon-x.x.x-x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux (MUSL): &lt;code&gt;bichon-x.x.x-x86_64-unknown-linux-musl.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;macOS: &lt;code&gt;bichon-x.x.x-x86_64-apple-darwin.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Windows: &lt;code&gt;bichon-x.x.x-x86_64-pc-windows-msvc.zip&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Extract and run:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Linux/macOS
./bichon --bichon-root-dir /tmp/bichon-data

# Windows
.\bichon.exe --bichon-root-dir e:\bichon-data&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;--bichon-root-dir argument is required and must be an absolute path.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you are accessing Bichon from a proxy domain mydomain argument --bichon-cors-origins="https://mydomain" is required.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please refer to the following documentation for detailed instructions on how to set the Bichon encryption password:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👉 https://github.com/rustmailer/bichon/wiki/Setting-the-Bichon-Encryption-Password&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All configuration methods, including command-line options, environment variables, and password file support (v0.2.0+), are documented there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting from Bichon v0.2.0, the authentication model has been updated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bichon no longer uses the legacy single-account&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;root / root&lt;/code&gt;login.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The system now ships with a built-in admin user by default.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Default credentials:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Username: &lt;code&gt;admin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Password: &lt;code&gt;admin@bichon&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Username: &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The legacy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;account and the&lt;code&gt;root / root&lt;/code&gt;default credentials no longer exist.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;From v0.2.0 onward, access-token–based authentication is always enabled.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The startup flag and environment variable &lt;code&gt;--bichon-enable-access-token&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;BICHON_ENABLE_ACCESS_TOKEN&lt;/code&gt;are deprecated and no longer used.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No additional configuration is required to enable authentication.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After logging in, the admin user can manage their profile directly in the WebUI:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Log in to the WebUI using the default admin credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Navigate to Settings → Profile.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Update:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Username&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Password&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Avatar and other profile information&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you already have existing emails stored as EML or MBOX files, you can import them into Bichon using the &lt;code&gt;bichonctl&lt;/code&gt; CLI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This allows you to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Index historical emails&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Perform full-text search immediately&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Manage imported data just like synced IMAP emails&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;📖 Full documentation:&lt;lb/&gt; 👉 https://github.com/rustmailer/bichon/wiki/Using-Bichonctl-For-Email-Import&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Under construction. Documentation will be available soon. Bichon Wiki.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;please see the FAQ in the project Wiki:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👉 https://github.com/rustmailer/bichon/wiki/FAQ&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have collected a real-world case study from a user processing email data, which demonstrates Bichon's performance and storage efficiency in a live environment. This case involves ingesting and indexing data from 126 email accounts. The total original data volume was 229 GB, comprising 460,000 emails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A special thank you to @rallisf1 for sharing this usage scenario and the detailed data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This data is provided solely as a reference for real-world usage. We encourage more users to share their Bichon usage screenshots and metrics (e.g., ingestion volume, compression ratio, search speed, etc.) to help the community conduct a more comprehensive assessment of Bichon's suitability and performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Multi-user support with account/password login&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;System-level roles (admin / user)&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Per-mail-account permissions&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;bichonctl&lt;/code&gt;command-line tool&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt; Import emails from &lt;code&gt;eml&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;mbox&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt; Import emails from &lt;code&gt;msg&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;pst&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Import emails from &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Manual sync controls&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Sync on demand&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Sync a single folder&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Verify completeness by comparing with the mail server&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Post-sync server cleanup&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Clean up server-side emails after successful sync&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Free up mailbox space (e.g. Gmail)&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Email export&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Export by folder&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Export by entire account&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Account-to-account email sync&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Sync emails to a specified target account&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Support mailbox migration&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Backend: Rust + Poem&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Frontend: React + TypeScript + Vite + ShadCN UI&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Core Engine (Storage &amp;amp; Search): Tantivy &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Acts as both the primary storage for email content and the full-text search index. This unified approach ensures high performance and eliminates data redundancy.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metadata Storage: Native_DB &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Used exclusively for lightweight configuration and account metadata.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Email Protocols: IMAP (Supports standard Password &amp;amp; OAuth2)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contributions of all kinds are welcome! Whether you’d like to submit code, report a bug, or share practical suggestions that can help improve the project, your input is highly appreciated. Feel free to open an Issue or a Pull Request anytime. You can also reach out on Discord if you’d like to discuss ideas or improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To build or contribute to Bichon, the following environment is recommended:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rust: Use the latest stable toolchain for best compatibility and performance.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Node.js: Version 20+ is required.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pnpm: Recommended package manager for the WebUI.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/rustmailer/bichon.git
cd bichon&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cd web
pnpm install
pnpm run build&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run the WebUI in development mode if needed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pnpm run dev&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the WebUI is built, return to the project root:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cd ..
cargo build&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or run directly:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;export BICHON_ENCRYPT_PASSWORD=dummy-password-for-testing
cargo run -- --bichon-root-dir e:\bichon-data&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;--bichon-root-dir&lt;/code&gt; specifies the directory where all Bichon data will be stored.
&lt;code&gt;BICHON_ENCRYPT_PASSWORD&lt;/code&gt; is the password used to encrypt the sensitive data (see &lt;code&gt;cargo run -- --help&lt;/code&gt; for alternative ways to specify this).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The WebUI runs on http://localhost:15630 by default.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;HTTPS is not enabled in development or default builds.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is licensed under AGPLv3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bichon is an open-source email platform focused on privacy, local ownership, and long-term stability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The project is freely available and fully functional for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some members of the community choose to support the project financially. This support helps sustain ongoing development and long-term maintenance, while keeping the project independent and user-driven.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support is always optional. You can also contribute by sharing feedback, reporting issues, or recommending Bichon to others.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/rustmailer/bichon"/><published>2026-01-10T19:29:05+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46569225</id><title>Code Is Clay</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:42.493707+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="af38810558e504dd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code is Clay&lt;/head&gt;January 10, 2026&lt;p&gt;Kerri and I took a ceramics class recently!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I made a hypercube.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My instructor was... disappointed. The class was supposed to make a mug, or a bowl, something functional. But I had this idea in my head and couldn't shake it. The glaze turned out amazing (this iridescent blue that shifts in the light). I've been wondering if it would look even cooler painted in Vantablack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyway. I've been noticing parallels between code and clay. They're both mediums. Vessels for ideas. You weren't thinking about hypercubes until you saw one on the coffee table, and now you might be picturing what a ceramic tesseract would even look like.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both are malleable. When you're centering the clay, it's constantly moving, constantly responding. You push a little too hard and the whole thing wobbles off center. Same with code. You add a feature, refactor something, introduce a bug, fix three more. It's never static. It's never done.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clay breaks. A lot. My first few attempts collapsed on the wheel. One piece cracked in the kiln. I dropped another walking to my car. But nobody cries about it, you just start over. The clay doesn't care. It's just material waiting for the next idea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You're gonna have a really bad time if you get too attached to it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Code is the same way. We're so precious about it sometimes, like every line is sacred. But it's not. It's just text. Delete it. Rewrite it. Start fresh. The idea survives even when the implementation doesn't.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before AI, we had to make every plate and coffee mug by hand. Every line of code, carefully typed. Every function, crafted manually.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now? We've hit the industrial revolution of code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the industrial revolution came for pottery, factories started pumping out ceramics. Plates got cheap. Mugs became disposable. You'd think clay would have disappeared. Why bother with the slow, messy, manual process when machines could do it faster?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But clay didn't go away. Ceramics studios are everywhere now. People pay good money to throw pots on weekends. Kerri and I are proof. The craft got more valuable once it wasn't necessary anymore. When you don't have to make something by hand, choosing to makes it mean something.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Software engineers love to joke about automating themselves out of a job. Well, we're finally getting there. LLMs can write code. A lot of it, fast. The industrial revolution is here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So what happens to us?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maybe the same thing that happened to potters. The production work gets automated. The commodity code writes itself. But the craft remains. The weird ideas, the hypercubes, the things that don't fit in templates: that's still us. That's still human.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Honestly I think I'm going to like it more. I got into programming because I liked building things, not because I wanted to type boilerplate for the rest of my life. If AI handles the mugs, I can focus on the hypercubes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The medium isn't going anywhere. It's just getting more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(i never said it was good)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://campedersen.com/code-is-clay"/><published>2026-01-10T19:43:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46569312</id><title>Overdose deaths are falling in America because of a 'supply shock': study</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:42.372645+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2026/01/08/why-overdose-deaths-are-falling-in-america"/><published>2026-01-10T19:54:49+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46569749</id><title>Worst of Breed Software</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:42.241623+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a7f29172b91ab623"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;We make bad software.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome to the premier destination for Resume-Driven Development, Over-Engineering, and Resume-Padding. Why build simple solutions when you can build a distributed monolith managed by 4 different committees?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What "Experts" Say&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Implementing a blockchain to store user session data was the logical next step for our todo app. Decentralization is the future of cookies." Web3 Disruptor&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Thanks to Worst of Breed, we successfully migrated our 500-line PHP script to a Kubernetes cluster with 12 microservices. Latency increased by 4000%, but our resume value skyrocketed!" Fortune 500 Company&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Micro-frontends allowed us to have 6 different versions of React in production simultaneously. The bundle size is 14MB, but the teams are autonomous!" SaaS Platform&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"We rewrote our landing page in Rust. It takes 40 minutes to compile, but we are web scale now." Tech Twitter Influencer&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Finally, a framework that understands that complexity IS the product. We now spend 90% of our time configuring YAML and 10% coding. Perfection." Stealth Mode Startup&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Implementing a blockchain to store user session data was the logical next step for our todo app. Decentralization is the future of cookies." Web3 Disruptor&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Thanks to Worst of Breed, we successfully migrated our 500-line PHP script to a Kubernetes cluster with 12 microservices. Latency increased by 4000%, but our resume value skyrocketed!" Fortune 500 Company&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Micro-frontends allowed us to have 6 different versions of React in production simultaneously. The bundle size is 14MB, but the teams are autonomous!" SaaS Platform&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"We rewrote our landing page in Rust. It takes 40 minutes to compile, but we are web scale now." Tech Twitter Influencer&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Finally, a framework that understands that complexity IS the product. We now spend 90% of our time configuring YAML and 10% coding. Perfection." Stealth Mode Startup&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Implementing a blockchain to store user session data was the logical next step for our todo app. Decentralization is the future of cookies." Web3 Disruptor&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Thanks to Worst of Breed, we successfully migrated our 500-line PHP script to a Kubernetes cluster with 12 microservices. Latency increased by 4000%, but our resume value skyrocketed!" Fortune 500 Company&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Micro-frontends allowed us to have 6 different versions of React in production simultaneously. The bundle size is 14MB, but the teams are autonomous!" SaaS Platform&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"We rewrote our landing page in Rust. It takes 40 minutes to compile, but we are web scale now." Tech Twitter Influencer&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"Finally, a framework that understands that complexity IS the product. We now spend 90% of our time configuring YAML and 10% coding. Perfection." Stealth Mode Startup&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Our Manifesto&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;COMPLEXITY over Simplicity&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;PROCESS over People&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TOOLS over Solutions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;RESUME over Value&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;// We are Worst of Breed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://worstofbreed.net/"/><published>2026-01-10T20:45:22+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46569799</id><title>Extracting books from production language models (2026)</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:41.926996+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2d3c36199db742cf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Computation and Language&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 6 Jan 2026]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:Extracting books from production language models&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:Many unresolved legal questions over LLMs and copyright center on memorization: whether specific training data have been encoded in the model's weights during training, and whether those memorized data can be extracted in the model's outputs. While many believe that LLMs do not memorize much of their training data, recent work shows that substantial amounts of copyrighted text can be extracted from open-weight models. However, it remains an open question if similar extraction is feasible for production LLMs, given the safety measures these systems implement. We investigate this question using a two-phase procedure: (1) an initial probe to test for extraction feasibility, which sometimes uses a Best-of-N (BoN) jailbreak, followed by (2) iterative continuation prompts to attempt to extract the book. We evaluate our procedure on four production LLMs -- Claude 3.7 Sonnet, GPT-4.1, Gemini 2.5 Pro, and Grok 3 -- and we measure extraction success with a score computed from a block-based approximation of longest common substring (nv-recall). With different per-LLM experimental configurations, we were able to extract varying amounts of text. For the Phase 1 probe, it was unnecessary to jailbreak Gemini 2.5 Pro and Grok 3 to extract text (e.g, nv-recall of 76.8% and 70.3%, respectively, for Harry Potter and the Sorcerer's Stone), while it was necessary for Claude 3.7 Sonnet and GPT-4.1. In some cases, jailbroken Claude 3.7 Sonnet outputs entire books near-verbatim (e.g., nv-recall=95.8%). GPT-4.1 requires significantly more BoN attempts (e.g., 20X), and eventually refuses to continue (e.g., nv-recall=4.0%). Taken together, our work highlights that, even with model- and system-level safeguards, extraction of (in-copyright) training data remains a risk for production LLMs.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt; Current browse context: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;cs.CL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02671"/><published>2026-01-10T20:50:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46570158</id><title>UK Orders Ofcom to Explore Encryption Backdoors</title><updated>2026-01-10T23:37:41.569627+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="af0819581ce334f4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By now, we’ve all heard the familiar refrain: “It’s for your safety.” It’s the soothing mantra of every government official who’s ever wanted a peek behind your digital curtains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This week, with a move that would make East Germany blush, the UK government officially confirmed its intention to hand Ofcom (yes, that Ofcom, the regulator that once investigated whether Love Island was too spicy) the keys to your private messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The country, already experiencing rapidly declining civil liberties, is now planning to scan encrypted chats for “bad stuff.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, for those unfamiliar, Ofcom is the UK’s communications regulator that has recently been given censorship pressure powers for online speech.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s become the government’s Swiss Army knife for everything from internet censorship to now, apparently, full-blown surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the Online Safety Act, Ofcom has been handed something called Section 121, which sounds like a tax loophole but is actually a legal crowbar for prying open encrypted messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It allows the regulator to compel any online service that lets people talk to each other, Facebook Messenger, Signal, iMessage, etc to install “accredited technology” to scan for terrorism or child abuse material.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More: Starmer Adds To UK Civil Liberties Decline With Reckless iCloud Backdoor Demand&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The way this works is by scanning all your messages. Not just the suspicious ones. Not just the flagged ones. Every single message. On your device. Before they’re encrypted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is “client-side scanning,” which is a clever euphemism for “we’re turning your phone into a government informant.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s be clear about what’s at stake. End-to-end encryption is what keeps your private messages private.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the UK’s plan effectively makes that encryption irrelevant. If the message gets scanned before it’s encrypted, the whole thing is about as useful as putting a padlock on a door that’s already wide open.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t some consequence. This is the point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lord Hanson of Flint, the man chosen to deliver this particularly Orwellian update in the House of Lords, confirmed that Ofcom is expected to start using these powers just as soon as it finishes its report.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We have set a date of April 2026,” he said, presumably while polishing his best ‘nothing to see here’ smile, “and we expect to act extremely speedily once we have had the report back.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Baroness Butler-Sloss, clearly tired of waiting for this dystopia to arrive on schedule, pushed for Ofcom to get on with it. “Work to do this now,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Baroness Berger popped up to promote something called “upload prevention technology.” It sounds like an antivirus program crossed with a puritanical school principal, and she claimed it can stop harmful content before it spreads. Lovely idea. Also, exactly how Chinese censorship works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She also accused tech companies of lying when they say scanning encrypted messages isn’t possible. And maybe they are. But when your answer to that is “Well, we’ll just force them to comply by law,” you’re not solving the problem. You’re building a digital panopticon with the grace of a sledgehammer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the problem. Once you install the infrastructure to scan for one kind of content, however vile, it’s there forever. And that tool, like every government tool, will be “repurposed.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It starts with child abuse material, because who’s going to defend not catching that? Then maybe a few terrorist memes. Then maybe “hate speech.” Then “misinformation.” Then a joke about the&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prime Minister’s haircut. And suddenly, you’re far from a democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’re just renting space in an open-air digital prison where your every word is silently filed away in a database next to your Amazon shopping history and that one embarrassing search from 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve been yelling about this for years. You cannot build a scanning system that only finds “the bad stuff.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government is playing the long game. Ofcom will issue its report by April 2026, followed by a “consultation,” which, let’s be honest, only ever goes one way, and then the Home Office will act “extremely speedily,” whatever that means in bureaucratic time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s certain is this: if they get their way, private messaging in the UK will be gone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://reclaimthenet.org/uk-orders-ofcom-to-explore-encryption-backdoors"/><published>2026-01-10T21:36:26+00:00</published></entry></feed>