<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:00.272734+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46155085</id><title>Trick users and bypass warnings – Modern SVG Clickjacking attacks</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:06.782782+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="120802a0bcc92fb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;SVG Filters - Clickjacking 2.0&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clickjacking is a classic attack that consists of covering up an iframe of some other website in an attempt to trick the user into unintentionally interacting with it. It works great if you need to trick someone into pressing a button or two, but for anything more complicated it’s kind of unrealistic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve discovered a new technique that turns classic clickjacking on its head and enables the creation of complex interactive clickjacking attacks, as well as multiple forms of data exfiltration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I call this technique “SVG clickjacking”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Liquid SVGs&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The day Apple announced its new Liquid Glass redesign was pretty chaotic. You couldn’t go on social media without every other post being about the new design, whether it was critique over how inaccessible it seemed, or awe at how realistic the refraction effects were.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drowning in the flurry of posts, a thought came to mind - how hard would it be to re-create this effect? Could I do this, on the web, without resorting to canvas and shaders? I got to work, and about an hour later I had a pretty accurate CSS/SVG recreation of the effect1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;EMERGENCY!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Girls Rituals&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Won't Be The Last Time&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;acloudyskye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SOUND BANDIT FUCKING LIVES&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sound Bandit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Love &amp;amp; Ponystep&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vylet Pony&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I Love My Computer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ninajirachi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can drag around the effect with the bottom-right circle control thing in the demo above (chrome/firefox desktop, chrome mobile).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My little tech demo made quite a splash online, and even resulted in a news article with what is probably the wildest quote about me to date: “Samsung and others have nothing on her”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few days passed, and another thought came to mind - would this SVG effect work on top of an iframe?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like, surely not? The way the effect “refracts light”2 is way too complex to work on a cross-origin document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, to my surprise, it did.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reason this was so interesting to me is that my liquid glass effect uses the &lt;code&gt;feColorMatrix&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;feDisplacementMap&lt;/code&gt; SVG filters - changing the colors of pixels, and moving them, respectively. And I could do that on a cross-origin document?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This got me wondering - do any of the other filters work on iframes, and could we turn that into an attack somehow? It turns out that it’s all of them, and yes!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building blocks&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got to work, going through every &amp;lt;fe*&amp;gt; SVG element and figuring out which ones can be combined to build our own attack primitives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These filter elements take in one or more input images, apply operations to them, and output a new image. You can chain a bunch of them together within a single SVG filter, and refer to the output of any of the previous filter elements in the chain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at some of the more useful base elements we can play with:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feImage&amp;gt; - load an image file;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feFlood&amp;gt; - draw a rectangle;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feOffset&amp;gt; - move stuff around;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feDisplacementMap&amp;gt; - move pixels according to a map;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feGaussianBlur&amp;gt; - blur stuff;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feTile&amp;gt; - tiling and cropping utility;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feMorphology&amp;gt; - expand/grow light or dark areas;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feBlend&amp;gt; - blend two inputs according to the mode;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feComposite&amp;gt; - compositing utilities, can be used to apply an alpha matte, or do various arithmetics on one or two inputs;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feColorMatrix&amp;gt; - apply a color matrix, this allows moving colors between channels and converting between alpha and luma mattes;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s quite a selection of utilities!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re a demoscener3 you’re probably feeling right at home. These are the fundamental building blocks for many kinds of computer graphics, and they can be combined into many useful primitives of our own. So let’s see some examples.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Fake captcha&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ll start off with an example of basic data exfiltration. Suppose you’re targeting an iframe that contains some sort of sensitive code. You could ask the user to retype it by itself, but that’d probably seem suspicious.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What we can do instead is make use of &lt;code&gt;feDisplacementMap&lt;/code&gt; to make the text seem like a captcha! This way, the user is far more likely to retype the code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is your secret code:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;6c79 7261 706f 6e79&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don't share it with anyone!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is your secret code:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;6c79 7261 706f 6e79&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don't share it with anyone!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(tapclick to edit if you're not a girl)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: Only the part inside the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;filter&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; block is relevant, the rest is just an example of using filters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add to this some color effects and random lines, and you’ve got a pretty convincing cap-tcha!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Out of all the attack primitives I’ll be sharing, this one is probably the least useful as sites rarely allow you to frame pages giving out magic secret codes. I wanted to show it though, as it’s a pretty simple introduction to the attack technique.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still, it could come in handy because often times you’re allowed to frame read-only API endpoints, so maybe there’s an attack there to discover.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Grey text hiding&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next example is for situations where you want to trick someone into, for example, interacting with a text input. Oftentimes the inputs have stuff like grey placeholder text in them, so showing the input box by itself won’t cut it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at our example target (try typing in the box).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this example we want to trick the user into setting an attacker-known password, so we want them to be able to see the text they’re entering, but not the grey placeholder text, nor the red “too short” text.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s start off by using &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt; with arithmetics to make the grey text disappear. The &lt;code&gt;arithmetic&lt;/code&gt; operation takes in two images, &lt;code&gt;i1&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;in=...&lt;/code&gt;) and &lt;code&gt;i2&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;in2=...&lt;/code&gt;), and lets us do per-pixel maths with &lt;code&gt;k1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;k2&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;k3&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;k4&lt;/code&gt; as the arguments according to this formula: 4.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tip! You can leave out the in/in2 parameters if you just want it to be the previous output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s getting there - by multiplying the brightness of the input we’ve made the grey text disappear, but now the black text looks a little suspicious and hard to read, especially on 1x scaling displays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We could play around with the arguments to find the perfect balance between hiding the grey text and showing the black one, but ideally we’d still have the black text look the way usually does, just without any grey text. Is that possible?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So here’s where a really cool technique comes into play - masking. We’re going to create a matte to “cut out” the black text and cover up everything else. It’s going to take us quite a few steps to get to the desired result, so lets go through it bit-by-bit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We start off by cropping the result of our black text filter with &lt;code&gt;feTile&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: Safari seems to be having some trouble with &lt;code&gt;feTile&lt;/code&gt;, so if the examples flicker or look blank, read this post in a browser such as Firefox or Chrome. If you're writing an attack for Safari, you can also achieve cropping by making a luma matte with &lt;code&gt;feFlood&lt;/code&gt; and then applying it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then we use &lt;code&gt;feMorphology&lt;/code&gt; to increase the thickness of the text.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now we have to increase the contrast of the mask. I’m going to do it by first using &lt;code&gt;feFlood&lt;/code&gt; to create a solid white image, which we can then &lt;code&gt;feBlend&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;difference&lt;/code&gt; to invert our mask. And then we can use &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt; to multiply5 the mask for better contrast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have a luma matte now! All that’s left is to convert it into an alpha matte with &lt;code&gt;feColorMatrix&lt;/code&gt;, apply it to the source image with &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt;, and make the background white with &lt;code&gt;feBlend&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looks pretty good, doesn’t it! If you empty out the box (try it!) you might notice some artifacts that give away what we’ve done, but apart from that it’s a pretty good way to sort of sculpt and form various inputs around a bit for an attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are all sorts of other effects you can add to make the input seem just right. Let’s combine everything together into a complete example of an attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can see how the textbox is entirely recontextualized now to fit a different design while still being fully functional.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Pixel reading&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;And now we come to what is most likely the most useful attack primitive - pixel reading. That’s right, you can use SVG filters to read color data off of images and perform all sorts of logic on them to create really advanced and convincing attacks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The catch is of course, that you’ll have to do everything within SVG filters - there is no way to get the data out6. Despite that, it is very powerful if you get creative with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a higher level, what this lets us do is make everything in a clickjacking attack responsive - fake buttons can have hover effects, pressing them can show fake dropdowns and dialogs, and we can even have fake form validation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s start off with a simple example - detecting if a pixel is pure black, and using it to turn another filter on or off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this target, we want to detect when the user clicks on the box to change its color, and use that to toggle a blur effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s start off by using two copies of the &lt;code&gt;feTile&lt;/code&gt; filter to first crop out the few pixels we’re interested in and then tile those pixels across the entire image.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The result is that we now have the entire screen filled with the color of the area we are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can turn this result into a binary on/off value by using &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt;’s arithmetic the same way as in the last section, but with a way larger &lt;code&gt;k2&lt;/code&gt; value. This makes it so that the output image is either completely black or completely white.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And just as before, this can be used as a mask. We once again convert it into an alpha matte, but this time apply it to the blur filter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So that’s how you can find out whether a pixel is black and use that to toggle a filter!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uh oh! It seems that somebody has changed the target to have a pride-themed button instead!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How can we adapt this technique to work with arbitrary colors and textures?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The solution is pretty simple - we can simply use &lt;code&gt;feBlend&lt;/code&gt;’s difference combined with a &lt;code&gt;feColorMatrix&lt;/code&gt; to join the color channels to turn the image into a similar black/white matte as before. For textures we can use &lt;code&gt;feImage&lt;/code&gt;, and for non-exact colors we can use a bit of &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt;’s arithmetic to make the matching threshold more lenient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And that’s it, a simple example of how we can read a pixel value and use it to toggle a filter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Logic gates&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;But here’s the part where it gets fun! We can repeat the pixel-reading process to read out multiple pixels, and then run logic on them to program an attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By using &lt;code&gt;feBlend&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt;, we can recreate all logic gates and make SVG filters functionally complete. This means that we can program anything we want, as long as it is not timing-based7 and doesn’t take up too many resources8.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Input: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; NOT: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feBlend mode=difference in2=white /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; AND: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feComposite operator=arithmetic k1=1 /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; OR: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feComposite operator=arithmetic k2=1 k3=1 /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; XOR: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feBlend mode=difference in=a in2=b /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; NAND: &lt;code&gt;(AND + NOT)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; NOR: &lt;code&gt;(OR + NOT)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; XNOR: &lt;code&gt;(XOR + NOT)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These logic gates are what modern computers are made of. You could build a computer within an SVG filter if you wanted to. In fact, here’s a basic calculator I made:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SVG Adder&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a full adder circuit. This filter implements the logic gates for the output and for the carry bit using the logic gates described above. There are more efficient ways to implement an adder in SVG filters, but this is meant to serve as proof of the ability to implement arbitrary logic circuits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyways, for an attacker, what all of this means is that you can make a multi-step clickjacking attack with lots of conditions and interactivity. And you can run logic on data from cross-origin frames.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Securify&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this secure application!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hack confirmation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are you sure you'd like to get hacked?&lt;/p&gt;⌛&lt;p&gt;This is an example target where we want to trick the user into marking themselves as hacked, which requires a few steps:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Clicking a button to open a dialog&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Waiting for the dialog to load&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Clicking a checkbox within the dialog&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Clicking another button in the dialog&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Checking for the red text that appeared&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Securify&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this secure application!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hack confirmation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are you sure you'd like to get hacked?&lt;/p&gt;⌛&lt;p&gt;Win free iPod by following the steps below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A traditional clickjacking attack against this target would be difficult to pull off. You’d need to have the user click on multiple buttons in a row with no feedback in the UI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are some tricks you could do to make a traditional attack more convincing than what you see above, but it’s still gonna look sketch af. And the moment you throw something like a text input into the mix, it’s just not gonna work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyways, let’s build out a logic tree for a filter-based attack:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Is the dialog open? &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Is the red text present? &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Make the user press the button&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(Yes) Show the end screen&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(Yes) Is the dialog loaded? &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Show loading screen&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(Yes) Is the checkbox checked? &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Make the user check the checkbox&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(Yes) Make the user click the button&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Is the red text present? &lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which can be expressed in logic gates9 as:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Inputs &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;D (dialog visible) = check for background dim&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;L (dialog loaded) = check for the button in dialog&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;C (checkbox checked) = check whether the button is blue or grey&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;R (red text visible) = &lt;code&gt;feMorphology&lt;/code&gt;and check for red pixels&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Outputs &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(¬D) ∧ (¬R) =&amp;gt; button1.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;D ∧ (¬L) =&amp;gt; loading.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;D ∧ L ∧ (¬C) =&amp;gt; checkbox.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;D ∧ L ∧ C =&amp;gt; button2.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(¬D) ∧ R =&amp;gt; end.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;And this is how we would implement it in SVG:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Securify&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this secure application!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hack confirmation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are you sure you'd like to get hacked?&lt;/p&gt;⌛&lt;p&gt;Play around with this and see just how much more convincing it is as an attack. And we could easily make it better by, for example, adding some extra logic to also add hover visuals to the buttons. The demo has debug visuals for the four inputs (D, L, C, R) in the bottom left as squares to make it easier to understand what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But yeah, that’s how you can make complex and long clickjacking attacks that have not been realistic with the traditional clickjacking methods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I kept this example here pretty short and simple, but real-world attacks can be a lot more involved and polished.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Docs bug&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve actually managed to pull off this attack against Google Docs!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the demo videos here (alt links: bsky, twitter).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What this attack does is:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Makes the user click on the “Generate Document” button&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Once pressed, detects the popup and shows a textbox for the user to type a “captcha” into &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;The textbox starts off with a gradient animation, which must be handled&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The textbox has focus states, which must also be present in the attack visuals, so they must be detected by the background color of the textbox&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The textbox has grey text for both a placeholder AND suggestions, which must be hidden with the technique discussed earlier&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Once the captcha is typed, makes the user seemingly click on a button (or press enter), which causes a suggested Docs item to be added into the textbox &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;This item must be detected by looking for its background color in the textbox&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Once the item is detected, the textbox must be hidden and another button must be shown instead &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Once that button is clicked, a loading screen appears, which must be detected&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;If the loading screen is present, or the dialog is not visible and the “Generate Document” button is not present, the attack is over and the final screen must be shown&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the past, individual parts of such an attack could’ve been pulled off through traditional clickjacking and some basic CSS, but the entire attack would’ve been way too long and complex to be realistic. With this new technique of running logic inside SVG filters, such attacks become realistic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Google VRP awarded me $3133.70 for the find. That was, of course, right before they introduced a novelty bonus for new vulnerability classes. Hmph!10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The QR attack&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something I see in online discussions often is the insistence on QR codes being dangerous. It kind of rubs me the wrong way because QR codes are not any more dangerous than links.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t usually comment on this too much because it’s best to avoid suspicious links, and the same goes for QR codes, but it does nag me to see people make QR codes out to be this evil thing that can somehow immediately hack you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I turns out though, that my SVG filters attack technique can be applied to QR codes as well!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The example from earlier in the blog with retyping a code becomes impractical once the user realizes they’re typing something they shouldn’t. We can’t stuff the data we exfiltrate into a link either, because an SVG filter cannot create a link.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But since an SVG filter can run logic and provide visual output, perhaps we could generate a QR code with a link instead?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Creating the QR&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating a QR code within an SVG filter is easier said than done however. We can shape binary data into the shape of a QR code by using &lt;code&gt;feDisplacementMap&lt;/code&gt;, but for a QR code to be scannable it also needs error correction data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QR codes use Reed-Solomon error correction, which is some fun math stuff that’s a bit more advanced than a simple checksum. It does math with polynomials and stuff and that is a bit annoying to reimplement in an SVG.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luckily for us, I’ve faced the same problem before! Back in 2021 I was the first person11 to make a QR code generator in Minecraft, so I’ve already figured out the things necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my build I pre-calculated some lookup tables for the error correction, and used those instead to make the build simpler - and we can do the same with the SVG filter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is already getting pretty long, so I’ll leave figuring out how this filter works as an exercise to the reader ;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a demo that displays a QR code telling you how many seconds you’ve been on this page for. It’s a bit fiddly, so if it doesn’t work make sure that you aren’t using any &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This demo &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Similarly, in a real attack, the scaling and color profile issues could be worked around using some JavaScript tricks or simply by implementing the filter a bit differently - this here is just a proof of concept that’s a bit rough around the edges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But yeah, that’s a QR code generator built inside an SVG filter!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Took me a while to make, but I didn’t want to write about it just being “theoretically possible”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Attack scenario&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;So the attack scenario with the QR code is that you’d read pixels from a frame, process them to extract the data you want, encode them into a URL that looks something like https://lyra.horse/?ref=c3VwZXIgc2VjcmV0IGluZm8 and render it as a QR code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, you prompt the user to scan the QR code for whatever reason (eg anti-bot check). To them, the URL will seem like just a normal URL with a tracking ID or something in it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once the user opens the URL, your server gets the request and receives the data from the URL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;And so on..&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are so many ways to make use of this technique I won’t have time to go over them all in this post. Some examples would be reading text by using the difference blend mode, or exfiltrating data by making the user click on certain parts of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You could even insert data from the outside to have a fake mouse cursor inside the SVG that shows the pointer cursor and reacts to fake buttons inside your SVG to make the exfiltration more realistic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or you could code up attacks with CSS and SVG where CSP doesn’t allow for any JS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyways, this post is long as is, so I’ll leave figuring out these techniques as homework.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Novel technique&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first time in my security research I’ve found a completely new technique!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I introduced it briefly at my BSides talk in September, and this post here is a more in-depth overview of the technique and how it can be used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can never know 100% for sure that a specific type of attack has never been found by anyone else, but my extensive search of existing security research has come up with nothing, so I suppose I can crown myself as the researcher who discovered it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s some previous research I’ve found:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;You click, I steal: analyzing and detecting click hijacking attacks in web pages,&lt;lb/&gt;On the fragility and limitations of current Browser-provided Clickjacking protection schemes&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;The papers mention SVG filters in clickjacking attacks, but only in the context of obscuring the underlying elements, not running logic.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Pixel Perfect Timing - Attacks with HTML5,&lt;lb/&gt;Security: SVG Filter Timing Attack&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Research on reading pixels through SVG filter timing attacks, which is a technique that is mitigated in modern browsers.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The Human Side Channel &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Some pretty cool clickjacking techniques, though no multi-step attacks or SVG logic.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;SVG is turing-complete-ish &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Another example of logic gates in SVG I found after writing my blog. It’s fun because it comes with reddit and hn threads - I particularly like the comment asking about whether this turing completeness is useful or just a fun fact, which got a reply confirming the latter. I like turning fun facts into vulnerabilities ^^.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Note that whether SVG filters are actually turing complete is questionable because filters are implemented in constant-time and can’t run in a loop. This doesn’t mean they can’t be turing complete, but it also doesn’t prove that they are.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t think me discovering this technique was just luck though. I have a history of seeing things such as CSS as programming languages to exploit and be creative with. It wasn’t a stretch for me to see SVG filters as a programming language either.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That, and my overlap between security research and creative projects - I often blur the lines between the two, which is what Antonymph was born out of.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any case, &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;afterword&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;whoa this post took such a long time for me to get done!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;i started work on it in july, and was expecting to release it alongside my CSS talk in september, but it has taken me so much longer than expected to actually finish this thing. i wanted to make sure it was a good in-depth post, rather than something i just get out as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;unlike my previous posts, i did unfortunately have to break my trend of using no images, since i needed a few data URIs within the SVG filters for demos. still, no images anywhere else in the post, no javascript, and just 42kB (gzip) of handcrafted html/css/svg.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;also, i usually hide a bunch of easter eggs in my post that link to stuff i’ve enjoyed recently, but i have a couple links i didn’t want to include without content warnings. finding responsibility is a pretty dark talk about the ethics of making sure your work won’t end up killing people, and youre the one ive always wanted is slightly nsfw doggyhell vent art.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;btw i’ll soon be giving talks at 39c3 and disobey 2026! the 39c3 one is titled “css clicker training” and will be about css crimes and making games in css. and the disobey one is the same talk as the bsides one about using css to hack stuff and get bug bounties, but i’ll make sure to throw some extra content in there to keep it fun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;see y’all around!!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: I you’re making content (articles, videos etc) based on this post, feel free to reach out to me to ask for questions or feedback.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discuss this post on: twitter, mastodon, lobsters&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I actually had after an hour was this, the Codepen link is an updated version that I added controls to later on. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a fancy way of saying it does a basic displacement of pixels. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;…or After Effects/Blender/Fusion etc user. Or anything else computer graphics. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;result = k1*i1*i2 + k2*i1 + k3*i2 + k4 in programmer language (I just couldn’t resist trying out the &amp;lt;math&amp;gt; tag for fun). ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The multiplication in this case is kind of the opposite of what you’d expect from the “multiply” blend mode - things will get lighter, not darker. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s not possible to get the pixel data out of a SVG filter as they’re implemented in constant-time. If you can find a way to retrieve the data then it’s a browser bug and you can most likely get bounty for it. Happy to collaborate if you’d like to turn such a finding into a working proof of concept for a report :). ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can actually pass the current time into an SVG filter, but we can’t do attacks such as “if a pixel changes, wait 1 second and then show a dialog” unless we can piggyback off an animation in the source frame. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since SVG filters are implemented in constant-time, they become pretty resource-intensive for complex filters on high-resolution targets. One optimization would be to have a full-resolution filter just for picking out the pixels, then a tiny-resolution backdrop-filter to run all the logic, and then another full-resolution filter to display the attack. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;¬ - NOT, ∧ - AND, ∨ - OR, ⊕ - XOR etc, see List of logic symbols. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is kind of similar to how I reported the Docs/YouTube/Slides chain right before they 5x’d the VRP rewards. I seem to have the worst luck with timing my reports… ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;I released my QR code generator in 2021, making it the earliest publicly released Minecraft QR code generator. I know, however, that DavidJR was independently working on a QR code generator at the same time as I was, eventually releasing it in 2023. Then there’s one from Sep 2024 by 37meliodas, and lastly there’s the probably most well-known one by mattbatwings from Dec 2024. The latter has an awesome video explaining everything in-depth, so I definitely recommend checking it out if you’re interested in Minecraft redstone. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lyra.horse/blog/2025/12/svg-clickjacking/"/><published>2025-12-05T00:03:36+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46155135</id><title>Netflix’s AV1 Journey: From Android to TVs and Beyond</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:06.547684+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://netflixtechblog.com/av1-now-powering-30-of-netflix-streaming-02f592242d80"/><published>2025-12-05T00:09:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46155619</id><title>BMW PHEV: Safety fuse replacement is extremely expensive</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:06.403832+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://evclinic.eu/2025/12/04/2021-phev-bmw-ibmucp-21f37e-post-crash-recovery-when-eu-engineering-becomes-a-synonym-for-unrepairable-generating-waste/"/><published>2025-12-05T01:05:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46157594</id><title>UniFi 5G</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:06.163115+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e818a12e14516a1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UniFi 5G Max lineup was created with a clear goal in mind: deliver a sleek, versatile, and exceptionally powerful 5G internet experience that works effortlessly in any environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UniFi 5G Max lineup was created with a clear goal in mind: deliver a sleek, versatile, and exceptionally powerful 5G internet experience that works effortlessly in any environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UniFi 5G Max makes deployment easy, whether installed locally or at a remote site. Plug it into any PoE port and it instantly appears as a ready to use WAN interface, no matter whether plugged directly into your UniFi gateway or into your office switch. No new cable runs needed! It sits neatly on a desk, but you can reposition it for the best possible signal using the included wall or window mount.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 5G Max delivers downlink speeds up to 2 Gbps with ultra low latency that makes it reliable as a primary connection and seamless as a backup WAN. UniFi routing policies and SLAs let you choose exactly how and when 5G is used, and for which clients and VLANs. Easily set per-SIM usage limits to avoid overage costs with just a few clicks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For tougher environments or deployments with poor indoor cellular coverage, the outdoor model maintains the same high performance cellular connectivity with improved antenna performance in a durable IP67 rated enclosure. It is built for rooftop installs, off site locations, and mobile deployments where reliability is critical. Just like its indoor counterpart, you can also connect it via any PoE port, anywhere on your network, greatly simplifying cabling requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want everything UniFi in one device, the DreamRouter 5G Max combines 5G connectivity with WiFi 7, local storage, and full UniFi OS application support. Deploy it anywhere 5G is available and run an entire high-performance and scalable network stack instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every device in the UniFi 5G lineup supports both physical SIMs and eSIM, giving you the freedom to choose your carrier and switch whenever needed with zero friction. All are equipped with dual SIM slots, with one SIM replaceable by eSIM, and are fully unlocked: any major carrier, any type of deployment, with one piece of hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UniFi 5G lineup brings sleek design, powerful performance, easy installation, and genuine WAN flexibility to every deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.ui.com/article/introducing-unifi-5g"/><published>2025-12-05T07:06:38+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46158578</id><title>Kenyan court declares law banning seed sharing unconstitutional</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:05.902520+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d8e624ea1bbbd655"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Kenyan court declares law banning seed sharing unconstitutional&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;KISUMU, Kenya (AP) — A high court in Kenya on Thursday declared unconstitutional sections of a seed law that prevented farmers from sharing and selling indigenous seeds in what food campaigners have called a landmark win for food security.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Farmers in Kenya could face up to two years’ imprisonment and a fine of 1 million Kenya shillings ($7,700) for sharing seeds through their community seed banks, according to a seed law signed in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Justice Rhoda Rutto on Thursday said sections of the seed law that gave government officials powers to raid seed banks and seize seeds were also unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The law was introduced as a measure to curb growing sale of counterfeit seeds that were causing loses in the agricultural sector and gave sole seed trading rights to licensed companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The case had been filed by 15 smallholder farmers, who are members of community seed banks that have been in operation for years, preserving and sharing seeds among colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A farmer, Samuel Wathome, who was among the 15, said the old farming practices had been vindicated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“My grandmother saved seeds, and today the court has said I can do the same for my grandchildren without fear of the police or of prison,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elizabeth Atieno, a food campaigner at Greenpeace Africa, called the win a “victory for our culture, our resilience, and our future.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“By validating indigenous seeds, the court has struck a blow against the corporate capture of our food system. We can finally say that in Kenya, feeding your community with climate-resilient, locally adapted seeds is no longer a crime,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Food campaigners have in the past encouraged governments to work with farmers to preserve indigenous seeds as a way of ensuring food security by offering farmers more plant varieties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indigenous seeds are believed to be drought resistant and adaptable to the climate conditions of their native areas, and hence often outperform hybrid seeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kenya has a national seed bank based near the capital Nairobi where indigenous seeds are stored in cold rooms, but farmers say community seed banks are equally important for variety and proximity to the farmer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The country has faced challenges in the seed sector where counterfeit seeds were sold to farmers, leading to losses amounting to millions of shillings in a country that relies on rain-fed agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://apnews.com/article/kenya-seed-sharing-law-ruling-ad4df5a364299b3a9f8515c0f52d5f80"/><published>2025-12-05T09:09:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46160315</id><title>Netflix to Acquire Warner Bros</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:05.811967+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://about.netflix.com/en/news/netflix-to-acquire-warner-bros"/><published>2025-12-05T12:21:19+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46160698</id><title>Making RSS More Fun</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:05.144900+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2b4893113586319f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't like RSS readers. I know, this is blasphemous especially on a website where I'm actively encouraging you to subscribe through RSS. As someone writing stuff, RSS is great for me. I don't have to think about it, the requests are pretty light weight, I don't need to think about your personal data or what client you are using. So as a protocol RSS is great, no notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However as something I'm going to consume, it's frankly a giant chore. I feel pressured by RSS readers, where there is this endlessly growing backlog of things I haven't read. I rarely want to read all of a websites content from beginning to end, instead I like to jump between them. I also don't really care if the content is chronological, like an old post about something interesting isn't less compelling to me than a newer post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I want, as a user experience, is something akin to TikTok. The whole appeal of TikTok, for those who haven't wasted hours of their lives on it, is that I get served content based on an algorithm that determines what I might think is useful or fun. However what I would like is to go through content from random small websites. I want to sit somewhere and passively consume random small creators content, then upvote some of that content and the service should show that more often to other users. That's it. No advertising, no collecting tons of user data about me, just a very simple "I have 15 minutes to kill before the next meeting, show me some random stuff."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case the "algorithm" is pretty simple: if more people like a thing, more people see it. But with Google on its way to replacing search results with LLM generated content, I just wanted to have something that let me play around with the small web the way that I used to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There actually used to be a service like this called StumbleUpon which was more focused on pushing users towards popular sites. It has been taken down, presumably because there was no money in a browser plugin that sent users to other websites whose advertising you didn't control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;TL;DR&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can go download the Firefox extension now and try this out and skip the rest of this if you want. https://timewasterpro.xyz/ If you hate it or find problems, let me know on Mastodon. https://c.im/@matdevdug&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Functionality&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I wanted to do something pretty basic. You hit a button, get served a new website. If you like the website, upvote it, otherwise downvote it. If you think it has objectionable content then hit report. You have to make an account (because I couldn't think of another way to do it) and then if you submit links and other people like it, you climb a Leaderboard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the backend I want to (very slowly so I don't cost anyone a bunch of money) crawl a bunch of RSS feeds, stick the pages in a database and then serve them up to users. Then I want to track what sites get upvotes and return those more often to other users so that "high quality" content shows up more often. "High quality" would be defined by the community or just me if I'm the only user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's pretty basic stuff, most of it copied from tutorials scattered around the Internet. However I really want to drive home to users that this is not a Serious Thing. I'm not a company, this isn't a new social media network, there are no plans to "grow" this concept beyond the original idea unless people smarter than me ping with me ideas. So I found this amazing CSS library: https://sakofchit.github.io/system.css/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Apple's System OS design from the late-80s to the early 90s was one of my personal favorites and I think would send a strong signal to a user that this is not a professional, modern service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Great, the basic layout works. Let's move on!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Backend&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I ended up doing FastAPI because it's very easy to write. I didn't want to spend a ton of time writing the API because I doubt I nailed the API design on the first round. I use sqlalchemy for the database. The basic API layout is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;admin - mostly just generating read-only reports of like "how many websites are there"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;leaderboard - So this is my first attempt at trying to get users involved. Submit a website that other people like? Get points, climb leaderboard.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The source for the RSS feeds came from the (very cool) Kagi small web Github. https://github.com/kagisearch/smallweb. Basically I assume that websites that have submitted their RSS feeds here are cool with me (very rarely) checking for new posts and adding them to my database. If you want the same thing as this does, but as an iFrame, that's the Kagi small web service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scraping work is straightforward. We make a background worker, they grab 5 feeds every 600 seconds, they check for new content on each feed and then wait until the 600 seconds has elapsed to grab 5 more from the smallweb list of RSS feeds. Since we have a lot of feeds, this ends up look like we're checking for new content less than once a day which is the interval that I want.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then we write it out to a sqlite database and basically track "has this URL been reported", if so, put it into a review queue and then how many times this URL has been liked or disliked. I considered a "real" database but honestly sqlite is getting more and more scalable every day and its impossible to beat the immediate start up and functionality. Plus very easy to back up to encrypted object storage which is super nice for a hobby project where you might wipe the prod database at any moment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In terms of user onboarding I ended up doing the "make an account with an email, I send a link to verify the email". I actually hate this flow and I don't really want to know a users email. I never need to contact you and there's not a lot associated with your account, which makes this especially silly. I have a ton of email addresses and no real "purpose" in having them. I'd switch to Login with Apple, which is great from a security perspective but not everybody has an Apple ID.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also did a passkey version, which worked fine but the OSS passkey handling was pretty rough still and most people seem to be using a commercial service that handled the "do you have the passkey? Great, if not, fall back to email" flow. I don't really want to do a big commercial login service for a hobby application.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Auth is a JWT, which actually was a pain and I regret doing it. I don't know why I keep reaching for JWTs, they're a bad user experience and I should stop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Can I just have the source code?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm more than happy to release the source code once I feel like the product is in a somewhat stable shape. I'm still ripping down and rewriting relatively large chunks of it as I find weird behavior I don't like or just decide to do things a different way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the end it does seem to do whats on the label. We have over 600,000 individual pages indexed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;So how is it to use?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Honestly I've been pretty pleased. But there are some problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First I couldn't find a reliable way of switching the keyboard shortcuts to be Mac/Windows specific. I found some options for querying platform but they didn't seem to work, so I ended up just hardcoding them as Alt which is not great.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other issue is that when you are making an extension, you spend a long time working with these manifests.json. The specific part I really wasn't sure about was:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;"browser_specific_settings": {
    "gecko": {
      "id": "[email protected]",
      "strict_min_version": "80.0",
      "data_collection_permissions": {
        "required": ["authenticationInfo"]
      }
    }
  }&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm not entirely sure if that's all I'm doing? I think so from reading the docs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway I built this mostly for me. I have no idea if anybody else will enjoy it. But if you are bored I encourage you to give it a try. It should be pretty light weight and straight-forward if you crack open the extension and look at it. I'm not loading any analytics into the extension so basically until people complain about it, I don't really know if its going well or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Future stuff&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I need to sort stuff into categories so that you get more stuff in genres you like. I don't 100% know how to do that, maybe there is a way to scan a website to determine the "types" of content that is on there with machine learning? I'm still looking into it.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There's a lot of junk in there. I think if we reach a certain number of downvotes I might put it into a special "queue".&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I want to ensure new users see the "best stuff" early on but there isn't enough data to determine "best vs worst".&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I wish there were more independent photography and science websites. Also more crafts. That's not really a "future thing", just me putting a hope out into the universe. Non-technical beta testers get overwhelmed by technical content.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://matduggan.com/making-rss-more-fun/"/><published>2025-12-05T13:00:28+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46160773</id><title>Most technical problems are people problems</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:04.899945+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2ed1d053672c65da"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I once worked at a company which had an enormous amount of technical debt - millions of lines of code, no unit tests, based on frameworks that were well over a decade out of date. On one specific project, we had a market need to get some Windows-only modules running on Linux, and rather than cross-compiling, another team had simply copied &amp;amp; pasted a few hundred thousand lines of code, swapping Windows-specific components for Linux-specific.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the non-technical reader, this is an enormous problem because now two versions of the code exist. So, all features &amp;amp; bug fixes must be solved in two separate codebases that will grow apart over time. When I heard about this, a young &amp;amp; naive version of me set out to fix the situation....&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;People Problems&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tech debt projects are always a hard sell to management, because even if everything goes flawlessly, the code just does roughly what it did before. This project was no exception, and the optics weren't great. I did as many engineers do and "ignored the politics", put my head down, and got it done. But, the project went long, and I lost a lot of clout in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I realized I was essentially trying to solve a people problem with a technical solution. Most of the developers at this company were happy doing the same thing today that they did yesterday...and five years ago. As Andrew Harmel-Law points out, code tends to follow the personalities of the people that wrote it. The code was calcified because the developers were also. Personality types who dislike change tend not to design their code with future change in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most technical problems are really people problems. Think about it. Why does technical debt exist? Because requirements weren't properly clarified before work began. Because a salesperson promised an unrealistic deadline to a customer. Because a developer chose an outdated technology because it was comfortable. Because management was too reactive and cancelled a project mid-flight. Because someone's ego wouldn't let them see a better way of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core issue with the project was that admitting the need for refactoring was also to admit that the way the company was building software was broken and that individual skillsets were sorely out of date. My small team was trying to fix one module of many, while other developers were writing code as they had been for decades. I had one developer openly tell me, "I don't want to learn anything new." I realized that you'll never clean up tech debt faster than others create it. It is like triage in an emergency room, you must stop the bleeding first, then you can fix whatever is broken.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;An Ideal World&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The project also disabused me of the engineer's ideal of a world in which engineering problems can be solved in a vacuum - staying out of "politics" and letting the work speak for itself - a world where deadlines don't exist...and let's be honest, neither do customers. This ideal world rarely exists. The vast majority of projects have non-technical stakeholders, and telling them "just trust me; we're working on it" doesn't cut it. I realized that the perception that your team is getting a lot done is just as important as getting a lot done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Non-technical people do not intuitively understand the level of effort required or the need for tech debt cleanup; it must be communicated effectively by engineering - in both initial estimates &amp;amp; project updates. Unless leadership has an engineering background, the value of the technical debt work likely needs to be quantified and shown as business value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Heads Up&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps these are the lessons that prep one for more senior positions. In my opinion, anyone above senior engineer level needs to know how to collaborate cross-functionally, regardless of whether they choose a technical or management track. Schools teach Computer Science, not navigating personalities, egos, and personal blindspots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have worked with some incredible engineers, better than myself - the type that have deep technical knowledge on just about any technology you bring up. When I was younger, I wanted to be that engineer - the "engineer's engineer". But I realize now, that is not my personality. I'm too ADD for that. :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For all of their (considerable) strengths, more often than not, those engineers shy away from the interpersonal. The tragedy is that they are incredibly productive ICs, but may fail with bigger initiatives because they are only one person - a single processor core can only go so fast. Perhaps equally valuable is the "heads up coder" - the person who is deeply technical, but also able to pick their head up &amp;amp; see project risks coming (technical &amp;amp; otherwise) and steer the team around them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.joeschrag.com/2023/11/most-technical-problems-are-really.html"/><published>2025-12-05T13:07:59+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46160824</id><title>Show HN: Pbnj – A minimal, self-hosted pastebin you can deploy in 60 seconds</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:04.568448+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="aa4b2d5ddfbc6a08"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# API Reference

## Authentication

All write operations require a Bearer token:
```
Authorization: Bearer YOUR_AUTH_KEY
```

## Endpoints

### Create Paste

POST /api

#### JSON Request
```bash
curl &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 05_api.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 11 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# CLI Reference

## Installation

```bash
npm install -g @pbnjs/cli
```

## Configuration

Run the setup wizard:
```bash
pbnj --init
```

This creates ~/.pbnj with your configuration:
```
PBNJ_HOST=ht&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 04_cli.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 11 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Cost Breakdown

"This is deployed on Cloudflare, they might charge us eventually!"

Don't worry. Let's do the math.

## Cloudflare D1 Free Tier

- 500 MB storage
- 5 million reads/day
- 100,000 writ&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 03_cost.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 11 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Deployment Guide

## One-Click Deploy (Recommended)

Click the "Deploy to Cloudflare" button on the GitHub repo â that's it!

The deploy button automatically:
- Forks the repo to your GitHub account&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 02_deployment.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 11 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Welcome to pbnj

pbnj is a simple, minimal self-hosted pastebin solution.

## What is pbnj?

pbnj lets you share code snippets and text files with a simple URL.
No accounts, no bloat - just paste an&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 01_welcome.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 11 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Web Interface

pbnj includes a web interface for creating and managing pastes directly from your browser.

## Authentication

The web interface uses the same `AUTH_KEY` as the CLI and API. Authentic&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 07_web_interface.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 11 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Configuration

pbnj is configured through a single `pbnj.config.js` file in the project root.

## Default Configuration

```js
export default {
  name: 'pbnj',
  logo: '/logo.png',
  idStyle: 'sandw&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 06_configuration.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 11 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://pbnj.sh/"/><published>2025-12-05T13:13:03+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46161125</id><title>Influential study on glyphosate safety retracted 25 years after publication</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:04.378152+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="364059ff18954fcc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A quarter-century after its publication, one of the most influential research articles on the potential carcinogenicity of glyphosate has been retracted for "several critical issues that are considered to undermine the academic integrity of this article and its conclusions." In a retraction notice dated Friday, November 28, the journal Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology announced that the study, published in April 2000 and concluding the herbicide was safe, has been removed from its archives. The disavowal comes 25 years after publication and eight years after thousands of internal Monsanto documents were made public during US court proceedings (the "Monsanto Papers"), revealing that the actual authors of the article were not the listed scientists – Gary M. Williams (New York Medical College), Robert Kroes (Ritox, Utrecht University, Netherlands), and Ian C. Munro (Intertek Cantox, Canada) – but rather Monsanto employees.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Known as "ghostwriting," this practice is considered a form of scientific fraud. It involves companies paying researchers to sign their names to research articles they did not write. The motivation is clear: When a study supports the safety of a pesticide or drug, it appears far more credible if not authored by scientists employed by the company marketing the product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have 73.89% of this article left to read. The rest is for subscribers only.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/environment/article/2025/12/03/influential-study-on-glyphosate-safety-retracted-25-years-after-publication_6748114_114.html"/><published>2025-12-05T13:39:04+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46162262</id><title>Covid-19 mRNA Vaccination and 4-Year All-Cause Mortality</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:04.238702+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2842305"/><published>2025-12-05T15:07:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46162656</id><title>Cloudflare outage on December 5, 2025</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:03.596964+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e418bb5fc591a8cb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On December 5, 2025, at 08:47 UTC (all times in this blog are UTC), a portion of Cloudflareâs network began experiencing significant failures. The incident was resolved at 09:12 (~25 minutes total impact), when all services were fully restored.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A subset of customers were impacted, accounting for approximately 28% of all HTTP traffic served by Cloudflare. Several factors needed to combine for an individual customer to be affected as described below.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The issue was not caused, directly or indirectly, by a cyber attack on Cloudflareâs systems or malicious activity of any kind. Instead, it was triggered by changes being made to our body parsing logic while attempting to detect and mitigate an industry-wide vulnerability disclosed this week in React Server Components.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Any outage of our systems is unacceptable, and we know we have let the Internet down again following the incident on November 18. We will be publishing details next week about the work we are doing to stop these types of incidents from occurring.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The graph below shows HTTP 500 errors served by our network during the incident timeframe (red line at the bottom), compared to unaffected total Cloudflare traffic (green line at the top).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare's Web Application Firewall (WAF) provides customers with protection against malicious payloads, allowing them to be detected and blocked. To do this, Cloudflareâs proxy buffers HTTP request body content in memory for analysis. Before today, the buffer size was set to 128KB.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As part of our ongoing work to protect customers using React against a critical vulnerability, CVE-2025-55182, we started rolling out an increase to our buffer size to 1MB, the default limit allowed by Next.js applications. We wanted to make sure as many customers as possible were protected.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This change was being rolled out using our gradual deployment system, and, as part of this rollout, we identified an increase in errors in one of our internal tools which we use to test and improve new WAF rules. As this was an internal tool, and the fix being rolled out was a security improvement, we decided to disable the tool for the time being as it was not required to serve or protect customer traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Disabling this was done using our global configuration system. This system does not use gradual rollouts but rather propagates changes within seconds to the entire network and is under review following the outage we recently experienced on November 18.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In our FL1 version of our proxy under certain circumstances, this latter change caused an error state that resulted in 500 HTTP error codes to be served from our network.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As soon as the change propagated to our network, code execution in our FL1 proxy reached a bug in our rules module which led to the following LUA exception:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;[lua] Failed to run module rulesets callback late_routing: /usr/local/nginx-fl/lua/modules/init.lua:314: attempt to index field 'execute' (a nil value)&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;resulting in HTTP code 500 errors being issued.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The issue was identified shortly after the change was applied, and was reverted at 09:12, after which all traffic was served correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Customers that have their web assets served by our older FL1 proxy AND had the Cloudflare Managed Ruleset deployed were impacted. All requests for websites in this state returned an HTTP 500 error, with the small exception of some test endpoints such as &lt;code&gt;/cdn-cgi/trace&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Customers that did not have the configuration above applied were not impacted. Customer traffic served by our China network was also not impacted.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cloudflareâs rulesets system consists of sets of rules which are evaluated for each request entering our system. A rule consists of a filter, which selects some traffic, and an action which applies an effect to that traffic. Typical actions are â&lt;code&gt;block&lt;/code&gt;â, â&lt;code&gt;log&lt;/code&gt;â, or â&lt;code&gt;skip&lt;/code&gt;â. Another type of action is â&lt;code&gt;execute&lt;/code&gt;â, which is used to trigger evaluation of another ruleset.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our internal logging system uses this feature to evaluate new rules before we make them available to the public. A top level ruleset will execute another ruleset containing test rules. It was these test rules that we were attempting to disable.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We have a killswitch subsystem as part of the rulesets system which is intended to allow a rule which is misbehaving to be disabled quickly. This killswitch system receives information from our global configuration system mentioned in the prior sections. We have used this killswitch system on a number of occasions in the past to mitigate incidents and have a well-defined Standard Operating Procedure, which was followed in this incident.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;However, we have never before applied a killswitch to a rule with an action of â&lt;code&gt;execute&lt;/code&gt;â. When the killswitch was applied, the code correctly skipped the evaluation of the execute action, and didnât evaluate the sub-ruleset pointed to by it. However, an error was then encountered while processing the overall results of evaluating the ruleset:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;if rule_result.action == "execute" then
  rule_result.execute.results = ruleset_results[tonumber(rule_result.execute.results_index)]
end&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This code expects that, if the ruleset has action=âexecuteâ, the ârule_result.executeâ object will exist. However, because the rule had been skipped, the rule_result.execute object did not exist, and Lua returned an error due to attempting to look up a value in a nil value.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is a straightforward error in the code, which had existed undetected for many years. This type of code error is prevented by languages with strong type systems. In our replacement for this code in our new FL2 proxy, which is written in Rust, the error did not occur.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What about the changes being made after the incident on November 18, 2025?&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We made an unrelated change that caused a similar, longer availability incident two weeks ago on November 18, 2025. In both cases, a deployment to help mitigate a security issue for our customers propagated to our entire network and led to errors for nearly all of our customer base.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We have spoken directly with hundreds of customers following that incident and shared our plans to make changes to prevent single updates from causing widespread impact like this. We believe these changes would have helped prevent the impact of todayâs incident but, unfortunately, we have not finished deploying them yet.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We know it is disappointing that this work has not been completed yet. It remains our first priority across the organization. In particular, the projects outlined below should help contain the impact of these kinds of changes:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Enhanced Rollouts &amp;amp; Versioning: Similar to how we slowly deploy software with strict health validation, data used for rapid threat response and general configuration needs to have the same safety and blast mitigation features. This includes health validation and quick rollback capabilities among other things.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Streamlined break glass capabilities: Ensure that critical operations can still be achieved in the face of additional types of failures. This applies to internal services as well as all standard methods of interaction with the Cloudflare control plane used by all Cloudflare customers.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;"Fail-Open" Error Handling: As part of the resilience effort, we are replacing the incorrectly applied hard-fail logic across all critical Cloudflare data-plane components. If a configuration file is corrupt or out-of-range (e.g., exceeding feature caps), the system will log the error and default to a known-good state or pass traffic without scoring, rather than dropping requests. Some services will likely give the customer the option to fail open or closed in certain scenarios. This will include drift-prevention capabilities to ensure this is enforced continuously.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Before the end of next week we will publish a detailed breakdown of all the resiliency projects underway, including the ones listed above. While that work is underway, we are locking down all changes to our network in order to ensure we have better mitigation and rollback systems before we begin again.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;These kinds of incidents, and how closely they are clustered together, are not acceptable for a network like ours. On behalf of the team at Cloudflare we want to apologize for the impact and pain this has caused again to our customers and the Internet as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Time (UTC)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Status&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Description&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;08:47&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;INCIDENT start&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Configuration change deployed and propagated to the network&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;08:48&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Full impact&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Change fully propagated&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;08:50&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;INCIDENT declared&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Automated alerts&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;09:11&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Change reverted&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Configuration change reverted and propagation start&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;09:12&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;INCIDENT end&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Revert fully propagated, all traffic restored&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/5-december-2025-outage/"/><published>2025-12-05T15:35:43+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46162872</id><title>Framework Laptop 13 gets ARM processor with 12 cores via upgrade kit</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:03.326914+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f36d19f305b9d557"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Framework Laptop 13 gets ARM processor with 12 cores via upgrade kit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Qualcomm Snapdragon X Plus and Snapdragon X Elite have proven that ARM processors have earned a place in the laptop market, as devices like the Lenovo IdeaPad Slim 5 stand out with their long battery life and an affordable price point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MetaComputing is now offering an alternative to Intel, AMD and the Snapdragon X series. Specifically, the company has introduced a mainboard that can be installe in the Framework Laptop 13 or in a mini PC case. This mainboard is equipped with a CIX CP8180 ARM chipset, which is also found inside the Minisforum MS-R1. This processor has a total of eight ARM Cortex-A720 performance cores, the two fastest can hit boost clock speeds of up to 2.6 GHz. Moreover, there are four Cortex-A520 efficiency cores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additionally, there’s an ARM Immortalis-G720 GPU with ten cores and an AI accelerator with a performance of 30 TOPS. This chipset is likely slower than the Snapdragon X Elite or a current flagship smartphone chip, but it should still provide enough performance for many everyday tasks. Either way, this mainboard upgrade might only be interesting for developers for the most part, because early tests show that the SoC already draws about 16 watts at idle, which means battery life will likely be fairly short when combined with the 55Wh battery of the Framework Laptop 13.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Price and availability&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The MetaComputing ARM AI PC Kit is available now at the manufacturer’s official online shop. The base model with 16GB RAM, 1TB SSD and a mini PC case costs $549. The mainboard can be installed in a previously purchased Framework Laptop 13. Users who don’t own a Framework Laptop can order a bundle including the notebook for $999. MetaComputing charges an additional $100 for 32GB RAM. Shipping is free worldwide, but these list prices do not include import fees or taxes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Source(s)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MetaComputing (press release | product page)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.notebookcheck.net/Framework-Laptop-13-gets-ARM-processor-with-12-cores-via-upgrade-kit.1177930.0.html"/><published>2025-12-05T15:49:56+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46163121</id><title>I'm Peter Roberts, immigration attorney who does work for YC and startups. AMA</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:02.851254+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ff3190150160ebd7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As usual, there are countless immigration topics and I'll be guided by whatever you're concerned with. Please remember that I can't provide legal advice on specific cases for obvious liability reasons because I won't have access to all the facts. Please stick to a factual discussion in your questions and comments and I'll do the same in my answers!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I work for an American company and I am based in Europe. I visit the US for work every now and then. I heard a lot of horror stories regarding border entries. If I am ever in a situation where the border police asks for access to my personal phone and pin code, what are my options? Can I refuse and what happens then?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Border Patrol can wait longer than you want to wait at the airport, you should not bring your personal phone if you don't want them going through all the contents, they can hold your device for an inconvenient amount of time if you are an American citizen. If you say no and are not an American citizen you can be denied entry at the airport and sent home.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could you please help with any insights about the social media vetting rules? This has been a blackbox to the visa applications - started with student visas, now being forced on work visas too from Dec 15th.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's right, both before US Consulates when applying for visas, before CBP when applying for admission, and before USCIS when applying for a benefit (H-1B, O-1, green card, etc.), social media is being reviewed, not across-the-board but more and more. And there's really no option to keep social media as private if asked to turn to public by a Consular Officer or CBP Officer. The review is broad and not limited to social media that is critical of US policy but extends to a review of an individual's entire background to make sure there were no violations of US immigration law, including unauthorized employment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CBP actually made me give them my facebook password when entering on a J1 visa in 2017, so I'm surprised to hear so much talk about this. Is it more that the practice of checking social media is more widespread now?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If one didn’t have an account with meta they just wouldn’t get the visa then or how does it work?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does the government have any direct link to meta re what accounts people actually have. I’m surprised people aren’t up in arms about this, I guess it affects mostly visitors and immigrants but the fact that the government needs to see your activity on a private company’s web app is wild to me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Someone studied in the US under a F1 visa and a scholarship. No other substantial income other than that. This person while in the U.S. had to file tax forms, although there was no tax to be paid because this person had no income outside the scholarships. The student finished the studies in, say, October last year and then left the country for his home country. The student graduated and does not intend to return to the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The educational institution sent the student's home address some tax form that he had to file by April 15, but the former student forgot to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The question is: would the student have problems getting a U.S. visa as a tourist and entering the U.S. several years after that? If yes, how could that be fixed? Thanks in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A question about TN status for a Canadian living in the US. There are some income-generating things I'd like to do outside of my work visa (play a music gig, upload music to Spotify, act in a movie). My understanding is that I can't do these things in the US. Am I able to do these things if I do them outside of the country, or is there any way to make them work? For example, if I went to Canada, recorded an album, uploaded it, then came back to the US.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In your view, who are the winners and losers of the recent H1B changes? And any changes on your perspective for YC harboring international talent in SF Bay Area?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the end, the new requirements - really, just the $100K payment for now - are manageable/avoidable and absent this requirement, the rules and their application haven't really changed. The bigger change, which hasn't happened yet, is the across-the-board increase in prevailing wages. And this will have a profound effect on H-1B employment since the increases will be significant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hi Peter, thanks as always. It seems that i-131 Reentry Permit processing times are greater than 12 months these days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If an i-131 is pending, would you advise that person to return briefly to USA before their 1 year date of exit (ensuring that they are never out of USA for greater than 1 year prior to approved i-131)?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or does a reentry permit allow them to remain out of country for longer than that even if pending (presuming it gets approved)?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have recently taken a job with an American based company and will need to complete a few weeks training in Miami. Based on the information they have given me I need a B1 visa and maybe an ESTA since I'm in the UK, and a C-1/D for moving through the US.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However they keep flip flopping between me needing a B1 and me just using my ESTA for the training, and their communication hasn't been the most straight forward. Which visa do I need to get to enter the US for the training?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether you present a B-1 visa or ESTA for admission, you will be seeking admission as a business visitor. Under these circumstances, my advice is almost always not to risk a denial of a B-1 visa application (which happens all the time) and to travel on ESTA. The only relative downside is that ESTA limits admission to 90 days. But of course run this all by the company's immigration counsel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the end, it's largely put a stop to H-1B sponsorship of workers outside the U.S. That doesn't mean that all these workers can't get visas to work in the U.S. but other - tougher visas - have to be explored.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How does the Supreme Court’s elimination of Chevron deference affect USCIS’s ability to narrowly interpret the EB-1A regulatory framework, particularly at Step 1 of the Kazarian analysis? I am specifically interested in two areas: (1) whether, under a strict textual reading of the judging the work of others criterion in 8 C.F.R. § 204.5(h)(3), participation in code review where the beneficiary evaluates and approves the technical work of others in the same field should qualify without USCIS applying extra regulatory limitations, and (2) whether USCIS can continue using its historically restrictive approach to comparable evidence under 8 C.F.R. § 204.5(h)(4) now that courts are no longer required to defer to agency interpretations. I understand that even if these issues favor the petitioner at Step 1 they may not change the outcome of the final merits determination under Step 2, and I am trying to determine how a post Chevron, strictly textual approach might influence Step 1 outcomes for petitioners whose achievements do not align neatly with the ten listed criteria.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm living in the US on TN status and I'm interested in starting a startup, a subscription-based mobile app. But I have a pending PERM application and leaving my company would mean abandoning the whole thing, which I'm not eager to do. Is there any legal way I could start a startup without having to do that?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Assuming a US startup is considering engineering hires outside the United States, how does one currently assess the likelihood of getting them a visa to work in the USA? And what timeline and cost would be involved?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hi Peter, thanks for doing the AMA! I have a Delaware registered LLC (10 years old), I managed to get even an EIN remotely. However, I can't open a bank account remotely and so I have just been paying the registered agent fees and Delaware gov taxes for the LLC all these years. I however, genuinely want to come to the states to open the bank account and actually expand my business into the US. The LLC hasn't really had any annual meetings/etc. but taxes are always paid on time. How do I use my LLC to apply for a B1/B2 to visit the US?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OR should I just close it and try the normal route? Thanks in advance!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My understanding of the B-1 visa is all you really need is a letter of employment. Might get tricky with you providing the letter of employment to yourself however.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In October, the state department introduced a new policy:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; Applicants for U.S. nonimmigrant visas (NIV) should schedule their visa interview appointments at the U.S. Embassy or Consulate in their country of nationality or residence&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; Applicants must be able to demonstrate residence in the country where they are applying, if the place of application is based on their residency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What sort of proof is required to demonstrate residence? What about cases where an applicant legally has residency in a particular country (e.g. PR card or work visa) but in practice lives in the US as an H-1B/TN/L-1/O-1/etc. worker or H-4/TD/L-2/O-3/etc. dependant? Especially for the dual intent visas?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hi Peter, have you been seeing either a slowdown or increased denial rates to N-400 applications (5 year rule)? Just curious if it's more or less business as usual or if there is any impact on N-400 applications (we've heard of the neighborhood checks etc.) Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's not business as usual anymore. Clients have shared that interviewing officers have shared that flexibility and leniency in adjudicating N-400 (and green card) applications is over. So officers are taking a much tougher stance on criminal records and extended absences from the US. That being said, applications without any issues are being approved although the approvals are taking longer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just a high level question. My youngest son was adopted. He isn't white. He is naturalized. Should we go ahead and renew his passport so he can carry around a passport card at this point(we never got one in the past because they seemed like a waste). It seems crazy but with people being grabbed off the street for being brown, it seems prudent have a quick way to prove citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My H-1B with my current employer expires on Jan 10, 2026 and can’t be extended because I don’t have an I-140. Another startup plans to file my O-1A at the end of December. Can I remain in the U.S. while the O-1A petition is pending?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you think H1B visa holders looking to move to a Green Card (in coordination with their employer) should be concerned about rejected applications or other issues?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46163121"/><published>2025-12-05T16:04:20+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46163609</id><title>Patterns for Defensive Programming in Rust</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:02.490382+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2c79df8a6ea533d8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have a hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whenever I see the comment &lt;code&gt;// this should never happen&lt;/code&gt; in code, I try to find out the exact conditions under which it could happen.
And in 90% of cases, I find a way to do just that.
More often than not, the developer just hasn’t considered all edge cases or future code changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact, the reason why I like this comment so much is that it often marks the exact spot where strong guarantees fall apart. Often, violating implicit invariants that aren’t enforced by the compiler are the root cause.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, the compiler prevents memory safety issues, and the standard library is best-in-class. But even the standard library has its warts and bugs in business logic can still happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All we can work with are hard-learned patterns to write more defensive Rust code, learned throughout years of shipping Rust code to production. I’m not talking about design patterns here, but rather small idioms, which are rarely documented, but make a big difference in the overall code quality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Code Smell: Indexing Into a Vector&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s some innocent-looking code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;if !matching_users.is_empty   
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if you refactor it and forget to keep the &lt;code&gt;is_empty()&lt;/code&gt; check?
The problem is that the vector indexing is decoupled from checking the length.
So &lt;code&gt;matching_users[0]&lt;/code&gt; can panic at runtime if the vector is empty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Checking the length and indexing are two separate operations, which can be changed independently. That’s our first implicit invariant that’s not enforced by the compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we use slice pattern matching instead, we’ll only get access to the element if the correct &lt;code&gt;match&lt;/code&gt; arm is executed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;match matching_users.as_slice   
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note how this automatically uncovered one more edge case: what if the list is empty? We hadn’t explicitly considered this case before. The compiler-enforced pattern matching requires us to think about all possible states! This is a common pattern in all robust Rust code: putting the compiler in charge of enforcing invariants.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Code Smell: Lazy use of &lt;code&gt;Default&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When initializing an object with many fields, it’s tempting to use &lt;code&gt;..Default::default()&lt;/code&gt; to fill in the rest.
In practice, this is a common source of bugs.
You might forget to explicitly set a new field later when you add it to the struct (thus using the default value instead, which might not be what you want), or you might not be aware of all the fields that are being set to default values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let foo = Foo ;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let foo = Foo ;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, it’s slightly more verbose, but what you gain is that the compiler will force you to handle all fields explicitly. Now when you add a new field to &lt;code&gt;Foo&lt;/code&gt;, the compiler will remind you to set it here as well and reflect on which value makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you still prefer to use &lt;code&gt;Default&lt;/code&gt; but don’t want to lose compiler checks, you can also destructure the default instance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let Foo   =  default;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This way, you get all the default values assigned to local variables and you can still override what you need:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let foo = Foo ;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pattern gives you the best of both worlds:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You get default values without duplicating default logic&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The compiler will complain when new fields are added to the struct&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Your code automatically adapts when default values change&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It’s clear which fields use defaults and which have custom values&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Code Smell: Fragile Trait Implementations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Completely destructuring a struct into its components can also be a defensive strategy for API adherence. For example, let’s say you’re building a pizza ordering system and have an order type like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For your order tracking system, you want to compare orders based on what’s actually on the pizza - the &lt;code&gt;size&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;toppings&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;crust_type&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;ordered_at&lt;/code&gt; timestamp shouldn’t affect whether two orders are considered the same.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the problem with the obvious approach:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now imagine your team adds a field for customization options:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your &lt;code&gt;PartialEq&lt;/code&gt; implementation still compiles, but is it correct?
Should &lt;code&gt;extra_cheese&lt;/code&gt; be part of the equality check?
Probably yes - a pizza with extra cheese is a different order!
But you’ll never know because the compiler won’t remind you to think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the defensive approach using destructuring:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now when someone adds the &lt;code&gt;extra_cheese&lt;/code&gt; field, this code won’t compile anymore.
The compiler forces you to decide: should &lt;code&gt;extra_cheese&lt;/code&gt; be included in the comparison or explicitly ignored with &lt;code&gt;extra_cheese: _&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pattern works for any trait implementation where you need to handle struct fields: &lt;code&gt;Hash&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Debug&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Clone&lt;/code&gt;, etc.
It’s especially valuable in codebases where structs evolve frequently as requirements change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Code Smell: &lt;code&gt;From&lt;/code&gt; Impls That Are Really &lt;code&gt;TryFrom&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes there’s no conversion that will work 100% of the time. That’s fine. When that’s the case, resist the temptation to offer a &lt;code&gt;From&lt;/code&gt; implementation out of habit; use &lt;code&gt;TryFrom&lt;/code&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of &lt;code&gt;TryFrom&lt;/code&gt; in disguise:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;unwrap_or_else&lt;/code&gt; is a hint that this conversion can fail in some way.
We set a default value instead, but is it really the right thing to do for all callers?
This should be a &lt;code&gt;TryFrom&lt;/code&gt; implementation instead, making the fallible nature explicit.
We fail fast instead of continuing with a potentially flawed business logic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Code Smell: Non-Exhaustive Matches&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s tempting to use &lt;code&gt;match&lt;/code&gt; in combination with a catch-all pattern like &lt;code&gt;_ =&amp;gt; {}&lt;/code&gt;, but this can haunt you later.
The problem is that you might forget to handle a new case that was added later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;match self  
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;match self  
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By spelling out all variants explicitly, the compiler will warn you when a new variant is added, forcing you to handle it. Another case of putting the compiler to work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the code for two variants is the same, you can group them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;match self  
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Code Smell: &lt;code&gt;_&lt;/code&gt; Placeholders for Unused Variables&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;_&lt;/code&gt; as a placeholder for unused variables can lead to confusion.
For example, you might get confused about which variable was skipped.
That’s especially true for boolean flags:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;match self  
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the above example, it’s not clear which variables were skipped and why. Better to use descriptive names for the variables that are not used:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;match self  
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if you don’t use the variables, it’s clear what they represent and the code becomes more readable and easier to review without inline type hints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pattern: Temporary Mutability&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you only want your data to be mutable temporarily, make that explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let mut data = get_vec;
data.sort;
let data = data;  // Shadow to make immutable

// Here `data` is immutable.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pattern is often called “temporary mutability” and helps prevent accidental modifications after initialization. See the Rust unofficial patterns book for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can go one step further and do the initialization part in a scope block:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let data = ;
// Here `data` is immutable
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This way, the mutable variable is confined to the inner scope, making it clear that it’s only used for initialization. In case you use any temporary variables during initialization, they won’t leak into the outer scope. In our case above, there were none, but imagine if we had a temporary vector to hold intermediate results:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let data = ;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;code&gt;temp&lt;/code&gt; is only accessible within the inner scope, which prevents it from accidental use later on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is especially useful when you have multiple temporary variables during initialization that you don’t want accessible in the rest of the function. The scope makes it crystal clear that these variables are only meant for initialization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pattern: Defensively Handle Constructors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip for libraries&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following pattern is only truly helpful for libraries and APIs that need to be robust against future changes. In such a case, you want to ensure that all instances of a type are created through a constructor function that enforces validation logic. Because without that, future refactorings can easily lead to invalid states.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For application code, it’s probably best to keep things simple. You typically have all the call sites under control and can ensure that validation logic is always called.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s say you have a simple type like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now you want to add validation logic to ensure invalid states are never created. One pattern is to return a &lt;code&gt;Result&lt;/code&gt; from the constructor:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But nothing stops someone from bypassing your validation by creating an instance directly:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let s = S ;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This should not be possible! It is our implicit invariant that’s not enforced by the compiler: the validation logic is decoupled from struct construction. These are two separate operations, which can be changed independently and the compiler won’t complain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To force external code to go through your constructor, add a private field:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now code outside your module cannot construct &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; directly because it cannot access the &lt;code&gt;_private&lt;/code&gt; field.
The compiler enforces that all construction must go through your &lt;code&gt;new()&lt;/code&gt; method, which includes your validation logic!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why the underscore in &lt;code&gt;_private&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that the underscore prefix is just a naming convention to indicate the field is intentionally unused; it’s the lack of &lt;code&gt;pub&lt;/code&gt; that makes it private and prevents external construction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For libraries that need to evolve over time, you can also use the &lt;code&gt;#[non_exhaustive]&lt;/code&gt; attribute instead:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This has the same effect of preventing construction outside your crate, but also signals to users that you might add more fields in the future. The compiler will prevent them from using struct literal syntax, forcing them to use your constructor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Should you use #[non_exhaustive]&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;_private&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a big difference between these two approaches:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;#[non_exhaustive]&lt;/code&gt;only works across crate boundaries. It prevents construction outside your crate.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;_private&lt;/code&gt;works at the module boundary. It prevents construction outside the module, but within the same crate.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On top of that, some developers find &lt;code&gt;_private: ()&lt;/code&gt; more explicit about intent: “this struct has a private field that prevents construction.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With &lt;code&gt;#[non_exhaustive]&lt;/code&gt;, the primary intent is signaling that fields might be added in the future, and preventing construction is more of a side effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what about code within the same module? With the patterns above, code in the same module can still bypass your validation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Still compiles in the same module!
let s = S ;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rust’s privacy works at the module level, not the type level. Anything in the same module can access private items.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you need to enforce constructor usage even within your own module, you need a more defensive approach using nested private modules:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt; 

// Re-export for public use
pub use  S;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now even code in your outer module cannot construct &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; directly because &lt;code&gt;Seal&lt;/code&gt; is trapped in the private &lt;code&gt;inner&lt;/code&gt; module.
Only the &lt;code&gt;new()&lt;/code&gt; method, which lives in the same module as &lt;code&gt;Seal&lt;/code&gt;, can construct it.
The compiler guarantees that all construction, even internal construction, goes through your validation logic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You could still access the public fields directly, though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let s =  new.unwrap;
s.field1 = "".to_string; // Still possible to mutate fields directly
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To prevent that, you can make the fields private and provide getter methods instead:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now the only way to create an instance of &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; is through the &lt;code&gt;new()&lt;/code&gt; method, and the only way to access its fields is through the getter methods.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;When to Use Each&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enforce validation through constructors:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For external code: Add a private field like &lt;code&gt;_private: ()&lt;/code&gt;or use&lt;code&gt;#[non_exhaustive]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For internal code: Use nested private modules with a private “seal” type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Choose based on your needs: Most code only needs to prevent external construction; forcing internal construction is more defensive but also more complex&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key insight is that by making construction impossible without access to a private type, you turn your validation logic from a convention into a guarantee enforced by the compiler. So let’s put that compiler to work!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pattern: Use &lt;code&gt;#[must_use]&lt;/code&gt; on Important Types&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;#[must_use]&lt;/code&gt; attribute is often neglected.
That’s sad, because it’s such a simple yet powerful mechanism to prevent callers from accidentally ignoring important return values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now if someone creates a &lt;code&gt;Config&lt;/code&gt; but forgets to use it, the compiler will warn them
(even with a custom message!):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let config =  new;
// Warning: Configuration must be applied to take effect
config.with_timeout; 

// Correct usage:
let config =  new 
    .with_timeout;
apply_config;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is especially useful for guard types that need to be held for their lifetime and results from operations that must be checked. The standard library uses this extensively. For example, &lt;code&gt;Result&lt;/code&gt; is marked with &lt;code&gt;#[must_use]&lt;/code&gt;, which is why you get warnings if you don’t handle errors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Code Smell: Boolean Parameters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Boolean parameters make code hard to read at the call site and are error-prone. We all know the scenario where we’re sure this will be the last boolean parameter we’ll ever add to a function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Too many boolean parameters
 

// At the call site, what do these booleans mean?
process_data;  // What does this do?
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s impossible to understand what this code does without looking at the function signature. Even worse, it’s easy to accidentally swap the boolean values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, use enums to make the intent explicit:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt; 

 

 

 

// Now the call site is self-documenting
process_data;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is much more readable and the compiler will catch mistakes if you pass the wrong enum type. You will notice that the enum variants can be more descriptive than just &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;.
And more often than not, there are more than two meaningful options; especially for programs which grow over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For functions with many options, you can configure them using a parameter struct:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt; 

 

 

// Usage with preset configurations
process_data;

// Or customize for specific needs
process_data;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This approach scales much better as your function evolves. Adding new parameters doesn’t break existing call sites, and you can easily add defaults or make certain fields optional. The preset methods also document common use cases and make it easy to use the right configuration for different scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rust is often criticized for not having named parameters, but using a parameter struct is arguably even better for larger functions with many options.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Clippy Lints for Defensive Programming&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many of these patterns can be enforced automatically using Clippy lints. Here are the most relevant ones:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Lint&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;clippy::indexing_slicing&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Prevents direct indexing into slices and vectors&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;clippy::fallible_impl_from&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Warns about &lt;code&gt;From&lt;/code&gt; implementations that can panic and should be &lt;code&gt;TryFrom&lt;/code&gt; instead.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;clippy::wildcard_enum_match_arm&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Disallows wildcard &lt;code&gt;_&lt;/code&gt; patterns.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;clippy::unneeded_field_pattern&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Identifies when you’re ignoring too many struct fields with &lt;code&gt;..&lt;/code&gt; unnecessarily.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;clippy::fn_params_excessive_bools&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Warns when a function has too many boolean parameters (4 or more by default).&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;clippy::must_use_candidate&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Suggests adding &lt;code&gt;#[must_use]&lt;/code&gt; to types that are good candidates for it.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can enable these in your project by adding them at the top of your crate, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or in your &lt;code&gt;Cargo.toml&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;[]
= "deny"
  = "deny"
  = "deny"
  = "deny"
  = "deny"
  = "deny"
  &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Defensive programming in Rust is about leveraging the type system and compiler to catch bugs before they happen. By following these patterns, you can:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make implicit invariants explicit and compiler-checked&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Future-proof your code against refactoring mistakes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reduce the surface area for bugs&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a skill that doesn’t come naturally and it’s not covered in most Rust books, but knowing these patterns can make the difference between code that works but is brittle, and code that is robust and maintainable for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remember: if you find yourself writing &lt;code&gt;// this should never happen&lt;/code&gt;, take a step back and ask how the compiler could enforce that invariant for you instead.
The best bug is the one that never compiles in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://corrode.dev/blog/defensive-programming/"/><published>2025-12-05T16:34:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46163671</id><title>Synadia and TigerBeetle Pledge $512,000 to the Zig Software Foundation</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:02.101698+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf70d8bf88a3ab96"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Synadia and TigerBeetle Pledge $512,000 to the Zig Software Foundation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synadia and TigerBeetle have together pledged $512,000 to the Zig Software Foundation over the next two years in support of the language, leadership, and communities building the future of simpler systems software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I first saw Zig in 2018, seven years ago. Two years later, I chose Zig over C or Rust for TigerBeetle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2020, I was following Rust closely. At the time, Rustâs default memory philosophy was to crash when out of memory (OOM). However, for TigerBeetle, I wanted explicit static allocation, following NASAâs Power of Ten Rules for Safety-Critical Code, which would become a part of TigerStyle, a methodology for creating safer software in less time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I learned is that if you could centralize resource allocation in time and space (the dimensions that prove tricky for humans writing software) then this could not only simplify memory management, to design away some of the need for a borrow checker in the first place, but, more importantly, also be a forcing function for propagating good design, to encourage teams to think through the explicit limits or physics of the software (you have no choice).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From a performance perspective, I didnât want TigerBeetle to be fearlessly multithreaded. Transaction processing workloads tend to have inherent contention, even to the point of power law, precluding partitioning and necessitating a single-threaded architecture. Therefore, Rustâs borrow checker, while a phenomenal tool for the class of problems it targets, made less sense for TigerBeetle. TigerBeetle never frees memory and never runs multithreaded, instead using explicit submission/completion queue interfaces by design.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, while the borrow checker could achieve local memory safety, TigerBeetle needed more correctness properties. TigerBeetle needed to be always correct, and across literally thousands of invariants. As matklad would say, this is a harder problem! I had also spent enough time in memory safe languages to know that local memory safety is no guarantee of local correctness, let alone distributed system correctness. Per systems thinking, I believe that total correctness is a design problem, not a language problem. Language is valuable. But no human language can guarantee the next Hemingway or Nabokov. For this you need philosophy. Even then itâs not a guarantee but a probability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Rust off the table, the choice fell to C or Zig. A language of the past or future?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zig was early, which gave me pause, but I felt that the quality of Andrew Kelleyâs design decisions in the language, the standard library (e.g. the unmanaged hashmap interface) and the cross-compilation toolchain, even five years ago, was already exceptional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrewsâs philosophy resonated with what I wanted to explore in TigerStyle. No hidden memory allocations. No hidden control flow. No preprocessor. No macros. And then you get things like comptime, reducing the grammar and dimensionality of the language, while simultaneously multiplying its power. The primary benefit of Zig is the favorable ratio of expressivity to language complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a replacement for C, Zig fixed not only the small cuts, such as explicit alignment in the type system for Direct I/O, or safer casts, but the showstoppers of spatial memory safety through bounds checking, and, to a lesser degree (but not guarantee), temporal memory safety through the debug allocator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zig also enabled checked arithmetic by default in safe builds, which is something I believe only Ada and Swift do (remarkably, Rust disables checked arithmetic by default in safe buildsâa default I would love to see changed). TigerBeetle separates the data plane from the control plane by design, through batching, so the runtime cost of these safety checks was not material, being amortized in the data plane across bigger buffers. While a borrow checker or static allocation can simplify memory management, getting logic and arithmetic correct remains hard. Of course, you can enable checked arithmetic in other languages, but I appreciated Andrewâs concern for checked arithmetic and stricter operands by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In all these things, what impressed me most was Zigâs approach to safety when working with the metal. Not in terms of an on/off decision, but as a spectrum. Not aiming for 100% guarantees across 1 or 2 categories, but 90% and then across more categories. Not eliminating classes of bugs, but downgrading their probability. All while preserving the power-to-weight ratio of the language, to keep the language beautifully simple.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many languages start simple and grow complex as features are added. Zigâs simplicity is unusual in that it comes from a subtractive discipline (e.g. no private fields) rather than a deferred complexity; minimizing surface area is part of the ethos of the language. The simplicity of Zig meant that we could hire great programmers from any language backgroundâthey could pick up Zig in a weekend. Indeed, Iâve never had to talk to a new hire about learning Zig.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, there was the timing. Recognizing that TigerBeetle would take time to reach production (we shipped production in 2024, after 3.5 years of development), giving Zig time to mature, for our trajectories to intersect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Investing in creating a database like TigerBeetle is a long term effort. Databases tend to have a long half life (e.g. Postgres is 30 years old). And so, while Zig being early in 2020 did give me pause, nevertheless Zigâs quality, philosophy and simplicity made sense for a multi-decade horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How has the decision for Zig panned out?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TigerBeetle is tested end-to-end under some pretty extreme fuzzing. We did have three bugs that would have been prevented by the borrow checker, but these were caught by our fuzzers and online verification. We run a fuzzing fleet of 1,000 dedicated CPU cores 24/7. We invest in deterministic simulation testing (e.g. VOPR), as well as non-deterministic fault-injection harnesses (e.g. VÃ¶rtex). We engaged Kyle Kingsbury in one of the longest Jepsen audits to dateâfour times the typical duration. Through all this, Zigâs quality held up flawlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zig has also been a huge part of our success as a company. TigerBeetle is only 5 years old but is already migrating some of the largest brokerages, exchanges and wealth managements in their respective jurisdictions. Several of our key enterprise contracts were thanks to the CTOs and even CEOs of these companies also following Zig and seeing the quality we wanted to achieve with it. I donât think we could have written TigerBeetle as it is, in any other language, at least not to the same tight tolerances, let alone with the same velocity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zigâs language specification will only reach 1.0 when all experimental areas of the language (e.g. async I/O) are finally done. For TigerBeetle, we care only about the stable language features we use, testing our binaries end to end, as we would for any language. Nevertheless, upgrading to new versions, even with breaking changes, has only been a pleasure for us as a team. The upgrade work is usually fully paid for by compilation time reduction. For example, the upgrade from Zig 0.14.1 to Zig 0.15.2 (with the native x86_64 backend) makes debug builds 2x faster, and even LLVM release builds become 1.6x faster. With each release, you can literally feel the sheer amount of effort that the entire Zig core team put into making Zig the worldâs most powerful programming languageâand toolchain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back in 2020, from a production perspective, Zig was more or less a frontend to LLVM, the same compiler used by Rust, Swift and other languages. However, by not shying away from also investing in its own independent compiler backends and toolchain, by appreciating the value of replacing LLVM long term, Zig is becoming well positioned to gain a low-level precision and compilation speed that generic LLVM wonât always be able to match.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We want Andrew to take his time, to get these things right for the long term. Fred Brooks once said that conceptual integrity is âthe most important considerationâ in system design, that the design must proceed from one mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this spirit, I am grateful for Andrewâs remarkably strong leadership (and taste) in the design of the language and toolchain. There can be thankless pressure on an open source project to give in to the tragedy of the commons. But if anything, in hindsight I think this is what Iâve most appreciated about choosing Zig for TigerBeetle, that Zig has a strong BDFL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, some may hear âBDFLâ and see governance risk. But I fear the opposite: conceptual risk, the harder problem. Brooks was rightâconceptual integrity is almost certainly doomed by committee. Whereas governance is easier solved: put it in the hands, not of the corporates, but of the people. The individuals who choose each day to continue to donate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is why our pledge today, along with all other ZSF donors, is a simple donation with no strings attached. The Zig Software Foundation is well managed, transparent and independent. We want it to remain this way. The last thing we want is some kind of foundation âseatâ. Andrew is Chef. We want to let him cook, and pay his core team sustainably (e.g. 92% percent of budget goes to directly paying contributors).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If cooking is one metaphor, then surfing is another. I believe that technology moves in waves. The art is not in paddling to the wave with a thousand surfers on it. But in spotting the swell before it breaks. And then enjoying the ride with the early adopters who did the same. River, Ghostty, Bun, Mach and many fellow surfers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact, it was through Zig that I met Derek Collison, who like me had been sponsoring the language in his personal capacity since 2018. As a former CTO at VMware, Derek was responsible for backing antirez to work full time on Redis. Derek later went on to create NATS, founding Synadia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we were about to increase TigerBeetleâs yearly donation to Zig, I reached out to Derek, and we decided to do a joint announcement, following Mitchell Hashimotoâs lead. For each of our companies to donate $256,000 in monthly installments over the next two years, with Synadia matching TigerBeetle, for a total of $512,000âthe first installment already made.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please consider donating or increasing your donation if you can. And if you are a CEO or CTO, please team up with another company to outmatch us! Thanks Andrew for creating something special, and to all who code for the joy of the craft:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Together we serve the users.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://tigerbeetle.com/blog/2025-10-25-synadia-and-tigerbeetle-pledge-512k-to-the-zig-software-foundation/"/><published>2025-12-05T16:38:30+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46163804</id><title>Jony Ive's OpenAI Device Barred from Using 'Io' Name</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:01.827569+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b4064b0d10aa71f0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Jony Ive's OpenAI Device Barred From Using 'io' Name&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A U.S. appeals court has upheld a temporary restraining order that prevents OpenAI and Jony Ive's new hardware venture from using the name "io" for products similar to those planned by AI audio startup iyO, Bloomberg Law reports.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;iyO sued OpenAI earlier this year after the latter announced its partnership with Ive's new firm, arguing that OpenAI's planned "io" branding was too close to its own name and related to similar AI-driven hardware. Court filings later showed that Ive and Sam Altman chose the name io in mid-2023, and that iyO CEO Jason Rugolo had approached Altman in early 2025 seeking funding for a project about "the future of human-computer interface." Altman declined, saying he was already working on "something competitive."&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;OpenAI countered that io's first product would not be a wearable device, and that Rugolo had voluntarily disclosed details about iyO while suggesting OpenAI acquire his company for $200 million. Despite this, a district court issued a temporary restraining order blocking OpenAI, Altman, Ive, and IO Products, Inc. from using the io mark in connection with products deemed sufficiently similar to iyO's planned AI-audio computer. OpenAI removed its io branding shortly after.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Ninth Circuit affirmed the order earlier this week. The court agreed there was a likelihood of confusion between "IO" and "iyO," that reverse confusion was a significant risk given OpenAI's size, and that iyO could face irreparable harm to its brand and fundraising. However, the ruling does not bar all uses of the io name, only marketing and selling hardware similar to iyO's.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The case now returns to the district court for a preliminary injunction hearing in April 2026, with the broader litigation expected to extend into 2027 and 2028. OpenAI's first hardware device is expected to launch next year.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Popular Stories&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;We're getting closer to the launch of the final major iOS update of the year, with Apple set to release iOS 26.2 in December. We've had three betas so far and are expecting a fourth beta or a release candidate this week, so a launch could follow as soon as next week. Past Launch Dates Apple's past iOS x.2 updates from the last few years have all happened right around the middle of the...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple is encouraging iPhone users who are still running iOS 18 to upgrade to iOS 26 by making the iOS 26 software upgrade option more prominent. Since iOS 26 launched in September, it has been displayed as an optional upgrade at the bottom of the Software Update interface in the Settings app. iOS 18 has been the default operating system option, and users running iOS 18 have seen iOS 18...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple is expected to launch a new foldable iPhone next year, based on multiple rumors and credible sources. The long-awaited device has been rumored for years now, but signs increasingly suggest that 2026 could indeed be the year that Apple releases its first foldable device. Subscribe to the MacRumors YouTube channel for more videos. Below, we've collated an updated set of key details that ...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple today seeded the release candidate versions of upcoming iOS 26.2 and iPadOS 26.2 updates to developers and public beta testers, with the software coming two weeks after Apple seeded the third betas. The release candidates represent the final versions of iOS 26.2 and iPadOS 26.2 that will be provided to the public if no further bugs are found during this final week of testing....&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;In a statement shared with Bloomberg on Wednesday, Apple confirmed that its software design chief Alan Dye will be leaving. Apple said Dye will be succeeded by Stephen Lemay, who has been a software designer at the company since 1999. Meta CEO Mark Zuckerberg announced that Dye will lead a new creative studio within the company's AR/VR division Reality Labs. On his blog Daring Fireball,...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple's iPhone 17 lineup is selling well enough that Apple is on track to ship more than 247.4 million total iPhones in 2025, according to a new report from IDC. Total 2025 shipments are forecast to grow 6.1 percent year over year due to iPhone 17 demand and increased sales in China, a major market for Apple. Overall worldwide smartphone shipments across Android and iOS are forecast to...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;2026 could be a bumper year for Apple's Mac lineup, with the company expected to announce as many as four separate MacBook launches. Rumors suggest Apple will court both ends of the consumer spectrum, with more affordable options for students and feature-rich premium lines for users that seek the highest specifications from a laptop. Below is a breakdown of what we're expecting over the next ...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The iPhone Air has recorded the steepest early resale value drop of any iPhone model in years, with new data showing that several configurations have lost almost 50% of their value within ten weeks of launch. According to a ten-week analysis published by SellCell, Apple's latest lineup is showing a pronounced split in resale performance between the iPhone 17 models and the iPhone Air....&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;iPhone 17 Pro models, it turns out, can't take photos in Night mode when Portrait mode is selected in the Camera app – a capability that's been available on Apple's Pro devices since the iPhone 12 Pro in 2020. If you're an iPhone 17 Pro or iPhone 17 Pro Max owner, try it for yourself: Open the Camera app with Photo selected in the carousel, then cover the rear lenses with your hand to...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple's iPhone development roadmap runs several years into the future and the company is continually working with suppliers on several successive iPhone models at the same time, which is why we often get rumored features months ahead of launch. The iPhone 18 series is no different, and we already have a good idea of what to expect for the iPhone 18 Pro and iPhone 18 Pro Max. One thing worth...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/05/openai-device-barred-from-io-name/"/><published>2025-12-05T16:48:44+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46163977</id><title>Onlook (YC W25) the Cursor for Designers Is Hiring a Founding Fullstack Engineer</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:01.417632+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="be519058de7ce427"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hey HN! I'm Daniel, building Onlook, the Cursor for Designers. We built an open-source collaborative canvas for code that lets designers and developers craft incredible web experiences together.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Since launching, Onlook hit #1 on Hacker News, was the #1 trending repo on GitHub—above DeepSeek + Anthropic—and has earned over 23,000 GitHub stars. We’re looking to bring on Onlook’s first Founding Engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This role requires autonomy - you’ll be setting standards for one of the fastest-growing open source projects backed by YC ever. You’ll help design and build an uncompromising visual IDE loved by tens of thousands of designers and engineers around the world, and you'll have a heavy influence on the direction of where we take the company.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You’re a full-stack engineer based in the U.S. who is ultra comfortable in Typescript, NextJS, React, and Tailwind, and ready to jump-in and build.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The most important things we look for:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;• Olympic-level dedication – you want to be the best in the world at what you do.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;• Ownership – you like autonomy and control over the destiny of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;• Speed – you’re comfortable shipping and iterating quickly with feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;• Craft – you’re opinionated and are willing to defend your opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ideally, you:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;• Are looking for a fast-paced, early startup environment.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;• Are willing to put in long hours and go the extra mile.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;• Are comfortable with any part of the stack, front-end, back-end, or database.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;• Believe in open source and are ok with your work being very public.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The comp range for this role is $130k-200k, 1-5% equity, great healthcare + other perks, and an awesome office if you happen to be in SF. We're open to remote / hybrid candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you’d like to stand out, please share a project or piece of work that you’re most proud of. We love seeing people’s work. If you have a personal website, please include that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you're interested, email daniel@onlook.com with your Github / LinkedIn / Website or work samples and why you'd be a great addition to the team, or apply here: https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/onlook/jobs/e4gHv1n-fo...&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Excited to meet, and build alongside you!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46163977"/><published>2025-12-05T17:00:10+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46164419</id><title>The AI Backlash Is Here: Why Public Patience with Tech Giants Is Running Out</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:01.170183+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a914a61d2f0a43a9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On OpenAI’s new social app, Sora 2, a popular video shows a disturbingly lifelike Sam Altman sprinting out of a Target store with stolen computer chips, begging police not to take his “precious technology.” The clip is absurdist, a parody of the company’s own CEO, but it also speaks to a larger conversation playing out in dinner conversations, group chats and public spaces around the country: What, exactly, is this technology for?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From ads scrawled with graffiti to online comment sections filled with mockery, the public’s patience with AI-generated media is starting to wear thin. Whether it's YouTube comments deriding synthetic ad campaigns or scribbled in Sharpie across New York City subway posters for AI startups, the public's discontent with the AI boom is growing louder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What began in 2022 as broad optimism about the power of generative AI to make peoples' lives easier has instead shifted toward a sense of deep cynicism that the technology being heralded as a game changer is, in fact, only changing the game for the richest technologists in Silicon Valley who are benefiting from what appears to be an almost endless supply of money to build their various AI projects — many of which don't appear to solve any actual problems. Three years ago, as OpenAI's ChatGPT was making its splashy debut, a Pew Research center survey found that nearly one in five Americans saw AI as a benefit rather than a threat. But by 2025, 43 percent of U.S. adults now believe AI is more likely to harm them than help them in the future, according to Pew. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Slop as a Service&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As AI spreads, public skepticism is turning into into open hostility toward its products and ads. Campaigns made with generative AI are mocked online and vandalized in public. Friend, a startup that spent $1 million on a sprawling campaign in the New York City subway with more than 11,000 advertisements on subway cars, 1,000 platform posters, and 130 urban panels, has been hit especially hard. Most of its ads were defaced with graffiti calling the product “surveillance capitalism” and urging people to “get real friends.”&lt;lb/&gt;"AI doesn't care if you live or die," reads one tag on a Friend ad in Brooklyn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other brands like Skechers are seeing similar backlash for an AI-generated campaign showing a distorted woman in sneakers, dismissed as lazy and unprofessional. Many of the Skechers subway posters were quickly defaced — some tagged with “slop,” the memeified shorthand for AI’s cheap, joyless flood of content, now embodied by the Altman deepfakes flooding Sora.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The idea of authenticity has long been at the center of the social media promise, for audiences and content creators alike. But a lot of AI-generated content is not following that logic,” said Natalia Stanusch, a researcher at AI Forensics, a nonprofit that investigates the impact of artificial intelligence on digital ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“With this flood of content made using generative AI, there is a threat of social media becoming less social and users are noticing this trend,” she told Newsweek.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;'Wildly Oversold'&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In an era where the boundaries between the digital and physical worlds are becoming nearly indistinguishable, one thing is becoming increasingly clear: the skepticism toward generative artificial intelligence is rising on both sides of the political divide. What once held the promise of innovation in the arts—an AI that could generate art, compose music or write coherent, even beautiful, prose—has begun to feel more like saturation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The friction isn’t just about quality—it’s about what the ubiquity of these tools signals. In entertainment, backlash has mounted as high-profile artists find themselves cloned without consent. After an AI-generated song mimicking his voice went viral on TikTok, rapper Bad Bunny lashed out on WhatsApp, telling his 19 million followers that, if they enjoyed the track, “you don’t deserve to be my friends.” Similar complaints came from Drake and The Weeknd whose own AI replicas were pulled from streaming platforms after public outcry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The public is finally starting to catch on,” said Gary Marcus, a professor emeritus at NYU and one of the field’s most vocal critics. “Generative AI itself may be a fad and certainly has been wildly oversold.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That saturation, according to Marcus and others, has less to do with AI’s breakthroughs and more to do with the way companies have stripped out human labor under the guise of innovation. It's a shift that has turned into backlash—one fueled not only by developers and ethicists but by cultural figures, creators and the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alex Hanna, director of research at the Distributed AI Research Institute (DAIR) and co-author of The A.I. Con: How to Fight Big Tech’s Hype and Create the Future We Want—a critique of large language models (LLMs), the technology behind AI systems like ChatGPT and Sora—told Newsweek that public opinion is increasingly aligning with his criticism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We’re seeing this narrative that AI is this inevitable future and it's being used to shut down questions about whether people actually want these tools or benefit from them,” Hanna said. “It becomes an excuse to displace workers, to automate without accountability, and with serious questions about its impact on the environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Companies want to make it look like AI is magic,” Hanna added. “But behind that magic is a labor force, data that’s been extracted without consent and an entire system built on exploitation.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One telling example: Meta’s recent launch of Vibes, a TikTok-style video app featuring only AI-generated content, was met with widespread mockery. “No one asked for this,” one viral post read. Stanusch, of AI Forensics, agreed: “For the near future, we don’t expect this adoption to slow down but rather increase,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even as capital flows into AI infrastructure buildouts, the cultural effect of so much "slop" is creating its own language of resistance. The term “clanker”—borrowed from Star Wars and repurposed by Gen Z—has exploded in popularity on TikTok as a meme-slur for robots and AI systems replacing human jobs. The term, while satirical, reflects deeper anxieties about labor displacement, particularly among younger workers entering an economy being transformed by AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, some see a long-term upside. “The robots are coming, and they’re coming for everyone’s jobs," said Adam Dorr, director of research at RethinkX, in an interview with Newsweek. “But in the longer term, AI could take over the dangerous, miserable jobs we’ve never wanted to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dorr, like others, urges caution—not rejection. “The challenge is: how do we make this transformation safely?” he said. “People are right to be scared. We’re already on the train—and the destination may be great but the journey will be chaotic.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Bubble Threat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From mental health chatbots and short-form video apps to corporate ad campaigns and toilet cameras that can analyze feces, AI is everywhere, and billions of dollars are still pouring in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But saturation breeds doubt: what might look like cutting-edge innovation to investors is starting to look like a bubble to everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In just the first half of 2025, global investment in AI infrastructure topped $320 billion, with $225 billion coming from U.S. hyperscalers and sovereign-backed funds, according to IDC. Microsoft alone committed over $50 billion to data center expansion this year. Meta, Amazon, OpenAI and others are backing the $500 billion Stargate AI initiative — championed by the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since returning to office, Donald Trump has made AI central to his economic agenda, fast-tracking permitting for AI infrastructure and declaring in a recent speech: “We will win the AI race just like we did the space race.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But many experts are unconvinced the numbers add up. “AI spending outpacing current real economic returns is not a problem—that’s what many innovative technologies call for,” Andrew Odlyzko, professor emeritus at the University of Minnesota, told Newsweek. “The problem is that current (and especially projected) AI spending appears to be outpacing plausible future real economic returns.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Odlyzko warned that much of the sector is propped up by “circular investment patterns,” in which AI companies fund one another without enough real customer demand. In one such example, Nvidia recently said it would invest $100 billion in OpenAI to help it build massive data centers, essentially backstopping its own customer. “If there was a big rush of regular non-AI companies paying a lot for AI services, that would be different," Odlyzko said. "But there is no sign of it.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other experts like British technology entrepreneur Azeem Azhar have compared the current capex boom to past busts. “The trillions pouring into servers and power lines may be essential,” he wrote on his Substack, “but history suggests they are not where enduring profits accumulate.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And while lawsuits over AI training data have begun piling up—including one filed by The New York Times against OpenAI—others center on how generative tools imitate distinct styles. A viral 2025 trend saw ChatGPT produce Studio Ghibli-style images so convincingly that it appeared the beloved Japanese animation studio had endorsed the platform. They had not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the meantime, so far, AI remains deeply unprofitable at scale. Last month, the consulting firm Bain predicted the AI industry would need to be making $2 trillion in combined annual revenues by 2030 to meet expected data center demand — a shortfall of roughly $800 billion.&lt;lb/&gt; “There is a lack of deep value,” the tech columnist and AI critic Ed Zitron told Newsweek. “The model is unsustainable.” And yet, with billions of dollars and the weight of national policy behind it, even skeptics agree: if and when the AI bubble bursts, its impact will ripple far beyond Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.newsweek.com/ai-backlash-openai-meta-friend-10807425"/><published>2025-12-05T17:29:47+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46164646</id><title>Shingles vaccination prevented or delayed dementia</title><updated>2025-12-05T18:14:00.776918+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.cell.com/cell/fulltext/S0092-8674(25)01256-5"/><published>2025-12-05T17:47:16+00:00</published></entry></feed>