<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:09.376905+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45789424</id><title>Using FreeBSD to make self-hosting fun again</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:19.358381+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f1431577be6acd1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Using FreeBSD to make self-hosting fun again&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025-11-01 - Feeling like a kid in a candy store, once more&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As evident by my last blog post "A prison of my own making", I needed to change something about my relationship with technology. How I was doing things didn't work anymore, but I also felt unable to change anything about it, as the way I was doing things seemed like the way that I was supposed to use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I needed was a fresh start. And I managed to find that fresh start in the BSD family of operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had already given FreeBSD and OpenBSD a try at the time and I liked what I saw. OpenBSD had already established itself in my workflow as an easy to use and reliable router and general OS for single-purpose VMs. But it isn't able to fullfill my needs for a multi-purpose system, where I'd want to run multiple separated workloads in something like a container or VM. But FreeBSD could.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know that I generally operate best by just committing to using a thing and then figuring out what I need, as I need it. So I committed to using FreeBSD and found a really nice server to do just that on the Hetzner server auction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started setting it up with BastilleBSD for jails and vm-bhyve for VMs. I didn't know how to do most things and felt kinda lost. But there it was again, that feeling of excitement to learn something new, which got my into self-hosting in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After some trial and error I managed to find a setup that works for me. As per usual, it deviates a bit from what might be the most common setup, but it's undoubtedly me (I'll probably explain more about it in the future, when things have settled).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I've come to appreciate about FreeBSD, and the BSD operating systems in general, is their simplicity and good documentation. Most tasks are just a few commands to run via SSH and if that isn't the case, someone has probably written a decent wrapper around it. If I need to find a piece of information, I still instinctively search online for it, just to be greeted by an online version of the corresponding man page. So I could also have just gathered that information on the CLI, oh well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also love the focus on long-term compatibility. I can find a solution to a problem in a forum post from 2008 and not even for a second do I have to doubt whether it will work, because it always does. At the same time, that doesn't mean there are no new features. The system doesn't feel old.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sure, not everything was all roses and some of that was probably due to my way of just jumping into a problem and digging myself through it one step at a time, instead of reading up on it a lot beforehand. For example I was confused for a long time about the release cycle of the base system and whether that somehow related to pkg and ports (It does not). And I was not able to properly phrase the question in a way that would result in a helpful result while searching. Luckily the BSD community has been nothing but kind and helpful so far. I've had multiple people on the Fediverse offer their help and when I had a specific question, I would always get multiple solid answers explaining it to me. Thanks to everyone that replied, it's genuinely a blast to feel like a newbie again!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't know whether I will actually stick with all of what I'm doing right now, in the long term. But that's not important. What is important is that I'm having fun, learning a new thing, right now. I'll see what sticks long-term.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;@Joel: See? I wrote a blog post! :D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://jsteuernagel.de/posts/using-freebsd-to-make-self-hosting-fun-again/"/><published>2025-11-02T11:01:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45789474</id><title>URLs are state containers</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:18.785505+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="abc21e28a1a26d89"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Couple of weeks ago when I was publishing The Hidden Cost of URL Design I needed to add SQL syntax highlighting. I headed to PrismJS website trying to remember if it should be added as a plugin or what. I was overwhelmed with the amount of options in the download page so I headed back to my code. I checked the file for PrismJS and at the top of the file, I found a comment containing a URL:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;/* https://prismjs.com/download.html#themes=prism&amp;amp;languages=markup+css+clike+javascript+bash+css-extras+markdown+scss+sql&amp;amp;plugins=line-highlight+line-numbers+autolinker */
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had completely forgotten about this. I clicked the URL, and it was the PrismJS download page with every checkbox, dropdown, and option pre-selected to match my exact configuration. Themes chosen. Languages selected. Plugins enabled. Everything, perfectly reconstructed from that single URL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was one of those moments where something you once knew suddenly clicks again with fresh significance. Here was a URL doing far more than just pointing to a page. It was storing state, encoding intent, and making my entire setup shareable and recoverable. No database. No cookies. No localStorage. Just a URL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This got me thinking: how often do we, as frontend engineers, overlook the URL as a state management tool? We reach for all sorts of abstractions to manage state such as global stores, contexts, and caches while ignoring one of the webâs most elegant and oldest features: the humble URL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my previous article, I wrote about the hidden costs of bad URL design. Today, I want to flip that perspective and talk about the immense value of good URL design. Specifically, how URLs can be treated as first-class state containers in modern web applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Overlooked Power of URLs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scott Hanselman famously said âURLs are UIâ and heâs absolutely right. URLs arenât just technical addresses that browsers use to fetch resources. Theyâre interfaces. Theyâre part of the user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But URLs are more than UI. Theyâre state containers. Every time you craft a URL, youâre making decisions about what information to preserve, what to make shareable, and what to make bookmarkable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think about what URLs give us for free:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Shareability: Send someone a link, and they see exactly what you see&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bookmarkability: Save a URL, and youâve saved a moment in time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Browser history: The back button just works&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Deep linking: Jump directly into a specific application state&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs make web applications resilient and predictable. Theyâre the webâs original state management solution, and theyâve been working reliably since 1991. The question isnât whether URLs can store state. Itâs whether weâre using them to their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before we dive into examples, letâs break down how URLs encode state. Hereâs a typical stateful URL:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For many years, these were considered the only components of a URL. That changed with the introduction of Text Fragments, a feature that allows linking directly to a specific piece of text within a page. You can read more about it in my article Smarter than âCtrl+Fâ: Linking Directly to Web Page Content.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Different parts of the URL encode different types of state:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Path Segments (&lt;code&gt;/path/to/myfile.html&lt;/code&gt;). Best used for hierarchical resource navigation:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/users/123/posts&lt;/code&gt;- User 123âs posts&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/docs/api/authentication&lt;/code&gt;- Documentation structure&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/dashboard/analytics&lt;/code&gt;- Application sections&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Query Parameters (&lt;code&gt;?key1=value1&amp;amp;key2=value2&lt;/code&gt;). Perfect for filters, options, and configuration:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;?theme=dark&amp;amp;lang=en&lt;/code&gt;- UI preferences&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;?page=2&amp;amp;limit=20&lt;/code&gt;- Pagination&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;?status=active&amp;amp;sort=date&lt;/code&gt;- Data filtering&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;?from=2025-01-01&amp;amp;to=2025-12-31&lt;/code&gt;- Date ranges&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;del rend="overstrike"&gt;Anchor&lt;/del&gt;Fragment (&lt;code&gt;#SomewhereInTheDocument&lt;/code&gt;). Ideal for client-side navigation and page sections:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;#L20-L35&lt;/code&gt;- GitHub line highlighting&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;#features&lt;/code&gt;- Scroll to section&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;#/dashboard&lt;/code&gt;- Single-page app routing (though itâs rarely used these days)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Common Patterns That Work for Query Parameters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Multiple values with delimiters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes youâll see multiple values packed into a single key using delimiters like commas or plus signs. Itâs compact and human-readable, though it requires manual parsing on the server side.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;?languages=javascript+typescript+python
?tags=frontend,react,hooks
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Nested or structured data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developers often encode complex filters or configuration objects into a single query string. A simple convention uses keyâvalue pairs separated by commas, while others serialize JSON or even Base64-encode it for safety.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;?filters=status:active,owner:me,priority:high
?config=eyJyaWNrIjoicm9sbCJ9==  (base64-encoded JSON)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Boolean flags&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For flags or toggles, itâs common to pass booleans explicitly or to rely on the keyâs presence as truthy. This keeps URLs shorter and makes toggling features easy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;?debug=true&amp;amp;analytics=false
?mobile  (presence = true)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Arrays (Bracket notation)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;?tags[]=frontend&amp;amp;tags[]=react&amp;amp;tags[]=hooks
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another old pattern is bracket notation, which represents arrays in query parameters. It originated from early web frameworks like PHP where appending &lt;code&gt;[]&lt;/code&gt; to a parameter name signals that multiple values should be grouped together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;?tags[]=frontend&amp;amp;tags[]=react&amp;amp;tags[]=hooks
?ids[0]=42&amp;amp;ids[1]=73
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many modern frameworks and parsers (like Nodeâs &lt;code&gt;qs&lt;/code&gt; library or Express middleware) still recognize this pattern automatically. However, itâs not officially standardized in the URL specification, so behavior can vary depending on the server or client implementation. Notice how it even breaks the syntax highlighting on my website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key is consistency. Pick patterns that make sense for your application and stick with them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;State via URL Parameters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Letâs look at real-world examples of URLs as state containers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PrismJS Configuration&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;https://prismjs.com/download.html#themes=prism&amp;amp;languages=markup+css+clike+javascript&amp;amp;plugins=line-numbers
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The entire syntax highlighter configuration encoded in the URL. Change anything in the UI, and the URL updates. Share the URL, and someone else gets your exact setup. This one uses anchor and not query parameters, but the concept is the same.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GitHub Line Highlighting&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;https://github.com/zepouet/Xee-xCode-4.5/blob/master/XeePhotoshopLoader.m#L108-L136
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It links to a specific file while highlighting lines 108 through 136. Click this link anywhere, and youâll land on the exact code section being discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google Maps&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;https://www.google.com/maps/@22.443842,-74.220744,19z
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coordinates, zoom level, and map type all in the URL. Share this link, and anyone can see the exact same view of the map.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figma and Design Tools&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;https://www.figma.com/file/abc123/MyDesign?node-id=123:456&amp;amp;viewport=100,200,0.5
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before shareable design links, finding an updated screen or component in a large file was a chore. Someone had to literally show you where it lived, scrolling and zooming across layers. Today, a Figma link carries all that context like canvas position, zoom level, selected element. Literally everything needed to drop you right into the workspace.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;E-commerce Filters&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;https://store.com/laptops?brand=dell+hp&amp;amp;price=500-1500&amp;amp;rating=4&amp;amp;sort=price-asc
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is one of the most common real-world patterns youâll encounter. Every filter, sort option, and price range preserved. Users can bookmark their exact search criteria and return to it anytime. Most importantly, they can come back to it after navigating away or refreshing the page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Frontend Engineering Patterns&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before we discuss implementation details, we need to establish a clear guideline for what should go into the URL. Not all state belongs in URLs. Hereâs a simple heuristic:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good candidates for URL state:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Search queries and filters&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pagination and sorting&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;View modes (list/grid, dark/light)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Date ranges and time periods&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Selected items or active tabs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UI configuration that affects content&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Feature flags and A/B test variants&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Poor candidates for URL state:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sensitive information (passwords, tokens, PII)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Temporary UI states (modal open/closed, dropdown expanded)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Form input in progress (unsaved changes)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Extremely large or complex nested data&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;High-frequency transient states (mouse position, scroll position)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are not sure if a piece of state belongs in the URL, ask yourself: If someone else clicking this URL, should they see the same state? If so, it belongs in the URL. If not, use a different state management approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Implementation using Plain JavaScript&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The modern &lt;code&gt;URLSearchParams&lt;/code&gt; API makes URL state management straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Reading URL parameters
const params = new URLSearchParams(window.location.search);
const view = params.get('view') || 'grid';
const page = params.get('page') || 1;

// Updating URL parameters
function updateFilters(filters) {
  const params = new URLSearchParams(window.location.search);

  // Update individual parameters
  params.set('status', filters.status);
  params.set('sort', filters.sort);

  // Update URL without page reload
  const newUrl = `${window.location.pathname}?${params.toString()}`;
  window.history.pushState({}, '', newUrl);

  // Now update your UI based on the new filters
  renderContent(filters);
}

// Handling back/forward buttons
window.addEventListener('popstate', () =&amp;gt; {
  const params = new URLSearchParams(window.location.search);
  const filters = {
    status: params.get('status') || 'all',
    sort: params.get('sort') || 'date'
  };
  renderContent(filters);
});
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;popstate&lt;/code&gt; event fires when the user navigates with the browserâs Back or Forward buttons. It lets you restore the UI to match the URL, which is essential for keeping your appâs state and history in sync. Usually your frameworkâs router handles this for you, but itâs good to know how it works under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Implementation using React&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;React Router and Next.js provide hooks that make this even cleaner:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { useSearchParams } from 'react-router-dom';
// or for Next.js 13+: import { useSearchParams } from 'next/navigation';

function ProductList() {
  const [searchParams, setSearchParams] = useSearchParams();

  // Read from URL (with defaults)
  const color = searchParams.get('color') || 'all';
  const sort = searchParams.get('sort') || 'price';

  // Update URL
  const handleColorChange = (newColor) =&amp;gt; {
    setSearchParams(prev =&amp;gt; {
      const params = new URLSearchParams(prev);
      params.set('color', newColor);
      return params;
    });
  };

  return (
    &amp;lt;div&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;select value={color} onChange={e =&amp;gt; handleColorChange(e.target.value)}&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;option value="all"&amp;gt;All Colors&amp;lt;/option&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;option value="silver"&amp;gt;Silver&amp;lt;/option&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;option value="black"&amp;gt;Black&amp;lt;/option&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/select&amp;gt;

      {/* Your filtered products render here */}
    &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  );
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Best Practices for URL State Management&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that weâve seen how URLs can hold application state, letâs look at a few best practices that keep them clean, predictable, and user-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Handling Defaults Gracefully&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donât pollute URLs with default values:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Bad: URL gets cluttered with defaults
?theme=light&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;sort=date

// Good: Only non-default values in URL
?theme=dark  // light is default, so omit it
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use defaults in your code when reading parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;function getTheme(params) {
  return params.get('theme') || 'light'; // Default handled in code
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Debouncing URL Updates&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For high-frequency updates (like search-as-you-type), debounce URL changes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { debounce } from 'lodash';

const updateSearchParam = debounce((value) =&amp;gt; {
  const params = new URLSearchParams(window.location.search);
  if (value) {
    params.set('q', value);
  } else {
    params.delete('q');
  }
  window.history.replaceState({}, '', `?${params.toString()}`);
}, 300);

// Use replaceState instead of pushState to avoid flooding history
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;pushState vs. replaceState&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When deciding between &lt;code&gt;pushState&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;replaceState&lt;/code&gt;, think about how you want the browser history to behave. &lt;code&gt;pushState&lt;/code&gt; creates a new history entry, which makes sense for distinct navigation actions like changing filters, pagination, or navigating to a new view â users can then use the Back button to return to the previous state. On the other hand, &lt;code&gt;replaceState&lt;/code&gt; updates the current entry without adding a new one, making it ideal for refinements such as search-as-you-type or minor UI adjustments where you donât want to flood the history with every keystroke.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;URLs as Contracts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When designed thoughtfully, URLs become more than just state containers. They become contracts between your application and its consumers. A good URL defines expectations for humans, developers, and machines alike&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Clear Boundaries&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A well-structured URL draws the line between whatâs public and whatâs private, client and server, shareable and session-specific. It clarifies where state lives and how it should behave. Developers know whatâs safe to persist, users know what they can bookmark, and machines know whats worth indexing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs, in that sense, act as interfaces: visible, predictable, and stable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Communicating Meaning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Readable URLs explain themselves. Consider the difference between the two URLs below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;https://example.com/p?id=x7f2k&amp;amp;v=3
https://example.com/products/laptop?color=silver&amp;amp;sort=price
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first one hides intent. The second tells a story. A human can read it and understand what theyâre looking at. A machine can parse it and extract meaningful structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jim Nielsen calls these âexamples of great URLsâ. URLs that explain themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Caching and Performance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs are cache keys. Well-designed URLs enable better caching strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Same URL = same resource = cache hit&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Query params define cache variations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CDNs can cache intelligently based on URL patterns&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can even visualize a userâs journey without any extra tracking code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;graph LR A["/products"] --&amp;gt; |selects category| B["/products?category=laptops"] B --&amp;gt; |adds price filter| C["/products?category=laptops&amp;amp;price=500-1000"] style A fill:#e9edf7,stroke:#455d8d,stroke-width:2px; style B fill:#e9edf7,stroke:#455d8d,stroke-width:2px; style C fill:#e9edf7,stroke:#455d8d,stroke-width:2px;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your analytics tools can track this flow without additional instrumentation. Every URL parameter becomes a dimension you can analyze.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Versioning and Evolution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs can communicate API versions, feature flags, and experiments:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;?v=2                   // API version
?beta=true             // Beta features
?experiment=new-ui     // A/B test variant
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This makes gradual rollouts and backwards compatibility much more manageable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Anti-Patterns to Avoid&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even with the best intentions, itâs easy to misuse URL state. Here are common pitfalls:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;âState Only in Memoryâ SPAs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The classic single-page app mistake:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// User hits refresh and loses everything
const [filters, setFilters] = useState({});
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your app forgets its state on refresh, youâre breaking one of the webâs fundamental features. Users expect URLs to preserve context. I remember a viral video from years ago where a Reddit user vented about an e-commerce site: every time she hit âBack,â all her filters disappeared. Her frustration summed it up perfectly. If users lose context, they lose patience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Sensitive Data in URLs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one seems obvious, but itâs worth repeating:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// NEVER DO THIS
?password=secret123
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs are logged everywhere: browser history, server logs, analytics, referrer headers. Treat them as public.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Inconsistent or Opaque Naming&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Unclear and inconsistent
?foo=true&amp;amp;bar=2&amp;amp;x=dark

// Self-documenting and consistent
?mobile=true&amp;amp;page=2&amp;amp;theme=dark
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Choose parameter names that make sense. Future you (and your team) will thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Overloading URLs with Complex State&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;?config=eyJtZXNzYWdlIjoiZGlkIHlvdSByZWFsbHkgdHJpZWQgdG8gZGVjb2RlIHRoYXQ_IiwiZmlsdGVycyI6eyJzdGF0dXMiOlsiYWN0aXZlIiwicGVuZGluZyJdLCJwcmlvcml0eSI6WyJoaWdoIiwibWVkaXVtIl0sInRhZ3MiOlsiZnJvbnRlbmQiLCJyZWFjdCIsImhvb2tzIl0sInJhbmdlIjp7ImZyb20iOiIyMDI0LTAxLTAxIiwidG8iOiIyMDI0LTEyLTMxIn19LCJzb3J0Ijp7ImZpZWxkIjoiY3JlYXRlZEF0Iiwib3JkZXIiOiJkZXNjIn0sInBhZ2luYXRpb24iOnsicGFnZSI6MSwibGltaXQiOjIwfX0==
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you need to base64-encode a massive JSON object, the URL probably isnât the right place for that state.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;URL Length Limits&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Browsers and servers impose practical limits on URL length (usually between 2,000 and 8,000 characters) but the reality is more nuanced. As this detailed Stack Overflow answer explains, limits come from a mix of browser behavior, server configurations, CDNs, and even search engine constraints. If youâre bumping against them, itâs a sign you need to rethink your approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Breaking the Back Button&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Replacing state incorrectly
history.replaceState({}, '', newUrl); // Used when pushState was needed
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Respect browser history. If a user action should be âundoableâ via the back button, use &lt;code&gt;pushState&lt;/code&gt;. If itâs a refinement, use &lt;code&gt;replaceState&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Closing Thought&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That PrismJS URL reminded me of something important: good URLs donât just point to content. They describe a conversation between the user and the application. They capture intent, preserve context, and enable sharing in ways that no other state management solution can match.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weâve built increasingly sophisticated state management libraries like Redux, MobX, Zustand, Recoil and others. They all have their place but sometimes the best solution is the one thatâs been there all along.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my previous article, I wrote about the hidden costs of bad URL design. Today, weâve explored the flip side: the immense value of good URL design. URLs arenât just addresses. Theyâre state containers, user interfaces, and contracts all rolled into one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your app forgets its state when you hit refresh, youâre missing one of the webâs oldest and most elegant features.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://alfy.blog/2025/10/31/your-url-is-your-state.html"/><published>2025-11-02T11:12:58+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45789602</id><title>Tongyi DeepResearch – open-source 30B MoE Model that rivals OpenAI DeepResearch</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:18.661472+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="efd86393ad1b861a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GITHUB HUGGINGFACE MODELSCOPE SHOWCASE&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;From Chatbot to Autonomous Agent&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are proud to present Tongyi DeepResearch, the first fully open‑source Web Agent to achieve performance on par with OpenAI’s DeepResearch across a comprehensive suite of benchmarks. Tongyi DeepResearch demonstrates state‑of‑the‑art results, scoring 32.9 on the academic reasoning task Humanity’s Last Exam (HLE), 43.4 on BrowseComp and 46.7 on BrowseComp‑ZH in extremely complex information‑seeking tasks, and achieving a score of 75 on the user‑centric xbench‑DeepSearch benchmark, systematically outperforming all existing proprietary and open‑source Deep Research agents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond the model, we share a complete and battle‑tested methodology for creating such advanced agents. Our contribution details a novel data synthesis solution applied across the entire training pipeline, from Agentic Continual Pre‑training (CPT) and Supervised Fine‑Tuning (SFT) for cold‑starting, to the final Reinforcement Learning (RL) stage. For RL, we provide a full‑stack solution, including algorithmic innovations, automated data curation, and robust infrastructure. For inference, the vanilla ReAct framework showcases the model’s powerful intrinsic capabilities without any prompt engineering, while the advanced Heavy Mode (test‑time‑scaling) demonstrates the upper limits of its complex reasoning and planning potential.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Continual Pre‑training and Post‑training Empowered by Fully Synthetic Data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Continual Pre‑training Data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We introduce Agentic CPT to deep research agent training, creating powerful agentic foundation models for post‑training. We propose AgentFounder, a systematic and scalable solution for large‑scale data synthesis that creates a data flywheel with data from the post‑training pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data Reorganization and Question Construction. We continuously collect data from various sources, including documents, publicly available crawled data, knowledge graphs, and historical trajectories and tool invocation records (e.g., search results with links). As shown in the figure, these diverse data sources are restructured into an entity‑anchored open‑world knowledge memory. Based on randomly sampled entities and their corresponding knowledge, we generate multi‑style (question,answer) pairs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Action Synthesis. Based on diverse problems and historical trajectories, we construct first‑order action synthesis data and higher‑order action synthesis data. Our method enables large‑scale and comprehensive exploration of the potential reasoning‑action space within offline environments, thereby thereby eliminating the need for additional commercial tool API calls. Specifically, for the higher‑order action synthesis, we remodel trajectories as multi‑step decision‑making processes to enhance the model’s decision‑making capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Post-training Data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;High-quality synthetic QA pairs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We develop an end‑to‑end solution for synthetic data generation. This fully automated process requires no human intervention to construct super‑human quality datasets, designed to push the boundaries of AI agent performance. Through long‑term exploration and iteration‑from early methods like reverse‑engineering QA pairs from clickstreams (WebWalker) to the more systematic graph‑based synthesis (WebSailor and WebSailor‑V2), then the formalized task modeling (WebShaper)‑our approach ensures both exceptional data quality and massive scalability, breaking through the upper limits of model capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To address complex, high‑uncertainty questions, we synthesize web‑based QA data through a novel pipeline. The process begins by constructing a highly interconnected knowledge graph via random walks and isomorphic tables towards tabular data fusion from real‑world websites , ensuring a realistic information structure. We then sample subgraphs and subtables to generate initial questions and answers. The crucial step involves intentionally increasing difficulty by strategically obfuscating or blurring information within the question. This practical approach is grounded in a complete theoretical framework, where we formally model QA difficulty as a series of controllable “atomic operations” (e.g., merging entities with similar attributes) on entity relationships, allowing us to systematically increase complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To further reduce inconsistencies between the organized information structure and the reasoning structure of QA, enable more controllable difficulty and structure scaling of reasoning, we proposed a formal modeling of the information‑seeking problem based on set theory. With this formalization, we developed agents that expands the problem in a controlled manner, and minimizes reasoning shortcuts and structural redundancy, leading to further improved QA quality. Moreover, this formal modeling also allows for efficient verification of QA correctness, effectively addressing the challenge of validating synthetic information‑seeking data for post‑training.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we have developed an automated data engine to scale up the creation of PhD‑level research questions. This engine begins with a multi‑disciplinary knowledge base, generating “seed” QA pairs that require multi‑source reasoning. Each seed then enters a self‑guided loop of “iterative complexity upgrades”, where a question‑crafting agent is equipped with a powerful toolset including web search, academic retrieval, and a Python execution environment. In each iteration, the agent expands knowledge boundaries, deepens conceptual abstraction, and even constructs computational tasks, creating a virtuous cycle where the output of one round becomes the more complex input for the next, ensuring a controllable and systematic escalation of task difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unleashing Agent Capabilities with Diverse Reasoning Pattern&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To bootstrap the model’s initial capabilities, we constructed a set of trajectories via rejection sampling, based on the ReAct and IterResearch frameworks (for details, see below). On one hand, ReAct, as a classic and foundational multi-turn reasoning format, instills rich reasoning behaviors and reinforces the model’s ability to adhere to structured formats.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, we introduce IterResearch, an innovative agent paradigm (detailed below). It unleashes the model’s full reasoning potential by dynamically reconstructing a streamlined workspace in each turn, ensuring that every decision is deliberate and well-considered. Leveraging IterResearch, we constructed a set of trajectories that integrate reasoning, planning, and tool-use, thereby strengthening the model’s capacity for sustained planning when confronted with Long-Horizon tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Rollout Mode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have conducted extensive exploration into the rollout paradigms for DeepResearch‑type agents. As a result, our final model supports multiple rollout formats, including the native ReAct Mode and the context‑managing Heavy Mode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Native ReAct Mode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our model demonstrates excellent performance using the native ReAct reasoning paradigm without any prompt engineering. It strictly adheres to the Thought‑Action‑Observation cycle, performing multiple iterations to solve problems. With a model context length of 128K, it can handle a large number of interaction rounds, fully achieving scaling in its interaction with the environment. ReAct’s simplicity and universality provide the clearest benchmark for a model’s intrinsic capabilities and the efficacy of our training pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our choice of ReAct is heavily informed by “The Bitter Lesson”, which posits that general methods leveraging scalable computation ultimately outperform approaches that rely on complex, human‑engineered knowledge and intricate designs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Heavy Mode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to the native ReAct mode, we have developed a “Heavy Mode” for complex, multi‑step research tasks. This mode is built on our new IterResearch paradigm, designed to push the agent’s capabilities to their limit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The IterResearch paradigm was created to solve the “cognitive suffocation” and “noise pollution” that occurs when agents accumulate all information into a single, ever‑expanding context. Instead, IterResearch deconstructs a task into a series of “research rounds”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In each round, the agent reconstructs a streamlined workspace using only the most essential outputs from the previous round. Within this focused workspace, the agent analyzes the problem, integrates key findings into a continuously evolving central report, and then decides its next action‑either gathering more information or providing a final answer. This iterative process of “synthesis and reconstruction” allows the agent to maintain a clear “cognitive focus” and high reasoning quality throughout long tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on this, we propose the Research‑Synthesis framework. In this model, multiple Research Agents use the IterResearch process to explore a problem in parallel. A final Synthesis Agent then integrates their refined reports and conclusions to produce a more comprehensive final answer. This parallel structure enables the model to consider a wider range of research paths within a limited context window, pushing its performance to the limit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;End-to‑End Agent Training Pipeline&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Training an agentic model like this required us to rethink the entire model training pipeline, from pre‑training to fine‑tuning to reinforcement learning. We established a new paradigm for agent model training that connects Agentic CPT → Agentic SFT → Agentic RL, creating a seamless end‑to‑end training loop for an AI agent. Here’s how we tackled the final stage with reinforcement learning, which was crucial for aligning the agent’s behavior with high‑level goals:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;On‑Policy Agent Reinforcement Learning (RL)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Constructing a high‑quality agent through RL is a complex system engineering challenge; if this entire development process is viewed as a “reinforcement learning” loop, any instability or lack of robustness in its components can lead to erroneous “reward” signals. We will now share our practices in RL, covering both the algorithmic and infrastructure sides.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For RL algorithm, we made several algorithmic breakthroughs, using a customized on‑policy Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO). We employ a strictly on‑policy training regimen, ensuring that the learning signal is always relevant to the model’s current capabilities. The training objective is optimized using a token‑level policy gradient loss. Second, to further reduce variance in the advantage estimation, we adopt a leave‑one‑out strategy. Furthermore, we employ a conservative strategy for negative samples, having observed that an unfiltered set of negative trajectories significantly degrades training stability. This can manifest as a “format collapse” phenomenon after extended training. To mitigate this, we selectively exclude certain negative samples from the loss calculation, for instance, those that do not yield a final answer because they exceed a length limit. For the sake of efficiency, we do not employ dynamic sampling. We instead leverage larger batch and group sizes, which serve to maintain smaller variance and provide adequate supervision.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The training dynamics demonstrate effective learning, with a consistent upward trend in reward. Meanwhile, policy entropy remains consistently high, indicating sustained exploration and preventing premature convergence. We attribute this to the non‑stationary nature of the web environment, which naturally fosters a robust, adaptive policy and obviates the need for explicit entropy regularization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We consider that the algorithm is important but not the only decisive factor in the success of Agentic RL. We have experimented with many different algorithms and tricks, and find that data and stability of the training environment are likely the more critical components in determining whether the RL works. Interestingly, we have tested to train the model directly on the BrowseComp testing set, but the results are substantially poorer than when using our synthetic data. We hypothesize that this disparity arises because the synthetic data offers a more consistent distribution, which allows the model to be more effectively tailored. Conversely, the human‑annotated data (such as BrowseComp) is inherently noisier. Given its limited scale, it is difficult to approximate a learnable underlying distribution, which consequently hinders the model to learn and generalize from it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the infrastructure side, training an agent with tools required us to develop a highly stable and efficient environment:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Synthetic Training Environment: Relying on live web APIs for development is expensive, slow, and inconsistent. We addressed this by creating a simulated training environment using an offline Wikipedia database and a custom tool suite. By adapting our data pipeline to generate high‑quality, complex tasks for this environment, we created a cost‑effective, fast, and controllable platform that dramatically accelerates our research and iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Stable &amp;amp; Efficient Tool Sandbox: To ensure reliable tool use during agent training and evaluation, we developed a unified sandbox. The sandbox handles concurrency and failure gracefully by caching results, retrying failed calls, and using redundant providers as fallbacks (e.g., a backup search API). This provides the agent with a fast and deterministic experience, which is crucial for preventing tool errors from corrupting its learning trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Automatic Data Curation: Data is the core driver of model capability enhancement; its importance even surpasses that of the algorithm. The quality of the data directly determines the upper bound on the model’s ability to generalize to out‑of‑distribution scenarios through self‑exploration. To address this challenge, we optimize data in real time, guided by training dynamics. This optimization is achieved through a fully automated data synthesis and filtering pipeline that dynamically adjusts the training set. By closing the loop between data generation and model training, this approach not only ensures training stability but also delivers substantial performance gains.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;On‑Policy Asynchronous Framework: We implemented a custom step‑level asynchronous RL training loop on top of rLLM. Multiple agent instances interact with the (simulated or real) environment in parallel, each producing trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through these measures, we “closed the loop” on agent training. Starting from a raw model, we did Agentic pre‑training to initialize tool‑use skills, then supervised finetuning on expert‑like data to cold start, and finally on‑policy RL to let the model conduct self‑evolution. This full‑stack approach ‑ now proven with Tongyi DeepResearch ‑ presents a new paradigm for training AI agents that can robustly solve complex tasks in dynamic environments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Our RL approach is inspired by several past work from Agentica. We adapt their rLLM framework and extend it to train our web agents.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Real‑World Applications and Impact&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tongyi DeepResearch is not just a research showcase; it’s already powering real applications within Alibaba and beyond, demonstrating its value in practical scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gaode Mate (Map &amp;amp; Navigation Agent): Collaborating with Amap (Gaode) Team, we co‑developed “Xiao Gao,” an AI copilot that leverages the app’s rich toolset. It can execute complex travel planning commands, like creating a multi‑day driving tour that includes specific scenic spots and pet‑friendly hotels. Through multi‑step reasoning, Xiao Gao autonomously researches and integrates information to produce a detailed, personalized itinerary, offering an intelligent planning experience that far surpasses standard navigation.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tongyi FaRui (Legal Research Agent): Empowered by our DeepResearch architecture, FaRui now functions as a true legal agent. It autonomously executes complex, multi‑step research tasks that mirror a junior attorney’s workflow‑systematically retrieving case law, cross‑referencing statutes, and synthesizing analysis. Crucially, all conclusions are grounded in verifiable judicial sources and delivered with precise case and statute citations, ensuring professional‑grade accuracy and credibility.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Limitations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our future work will address three key limitations. First, the current 128k context length is still insufficient for the most complex long‑horizon tasks, requiring us to explore expanded context windows and more sophisticated information management. Second, our training pipeline’s scalability remains unproven on foundation models significantly larger than our 30B‑scale MoE, and we plan to validate our methods on larger‑scale models. Lastly, we aim to improve the efficiency of our reinforcement learning framework by investigating techniques like partial rollouts, which will necessitate solving the challenges of off‑policy training, such as distributional shift.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Series Work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tongyi DeepResearch also has an extensive deep research agent family. You can find more information in the following papers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[1] WebWalker: Benchmarking LLMs in Web Traversal&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[2] WebDancer: Towards Autonomous Information Seeking Agency&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[3] WebSailor: Navigating Super‑human Reasoning for Web Agent&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[4] WebShaper: Agentically Data Synthesizing via Information‑Seeking Formalization&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[5] WebWatcher: Breaking New Frontier of Vision‑Language Deep Research Agent&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[6] WebResearch: Unleashing reasoning capability in Long‑Horizon Agents&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[7] ReSum: Unlocking Long‑Horizon Search Intelligence via Context Summarization&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[8] WebWeaver: Structuring Web‑Scale Evidence with Dynamic Outlines for Open‑Ended Deep Research&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[10] Scaling Agents via Continual Pre‑training&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[11] Towards General Agentic Intelligence via Environment Scaling&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our team has a long‑standing commitment to the research and development of deep research agents. Over the past six months, we have consistently published one technical report per month, totaling five to date. Today, we are excited to simultaneously release six new reports and share our Tongyi DeepResearch‑30B‑A3B model with the community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for our next generation of agentic models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@misc{tongyidr,
  author={Tongyi DeepResearch Team},
  title={Tongyi DeepResearch: A New Era of Open-Source AI Researchers},
  year={2025},
  howpublished={\url{https://github.com/Alibaba-NLP/DeepResearch}}
}
&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://tongyi-agent.github.io/blog/introducing-tongyi-deep-research/"/><published>2025-11-02T11:43:26+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45790015</id><title>X.org Security Advisory: multiple security issues X.Org X server and Xwayland</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:16.794103+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="981a9199600a0298"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;X.Org Security Advisory: multiple security issues X.Org X server and Xwayland&lt;/head&gt; Olivier Fourdan ofourdan at redhat.com &lt;lb/&gt;Tue Oct 28 13:22:18 UTC 2025&lt;quote&gt;====================================================================== X.Org Security Advisory: October 28, 2025 Issues in X.Org X server prior to 21.1.18 and Xwayland prior to 24.1.8 ====================================================================== Multiple issues have been found in the X server and Xwayland implementations published by X.Org for which we are releasing security fixes for in xorg-server-21.1.19 and xwayland-24.1.9. 1) CVE-2025-62229: Use-after-free in XPresentNotify structures creation Using the X11 Present extension, when processing and adding the notifications after presenting a pixmap, if an error occurs, a dangling pointer may be left in the error code path of the function causing a use-after-free when eventually destroying the notification structures later. Introduced in: Xorg 1.15 Fixed in: xorg-server-21.1.19 and xwayland-24.1.9 Fix: https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/5a4286b1 Found by: Jan-Niklas Sohn working with Trend Micro Zero Day Initiative. 2) CVE-2025-62230: Use-after-free in Xkb client resource removal When removing the Xkb resources for a client, the function XkbRemoveResourceClient() will free the XkbInterest data associated with the device, but not the resource associated with it. As a result, when the client terminates, the resource delete function triggers a use-after-free. Introduced in: X11R6 Fixed in: xorg-server-21.1.19 and xwayland-24.1.9 Fix: https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/99790a2c https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/10c94238 Found by: Jan-Niklas Sohn working with Trend Micro Zero Day Initiative. 3) CVE-2025-62231: Value overflow in Xkb extension XkbSetCompatMap() The XkbCompatMap structure stores some of its values using an unsigned short, but fails to check whether the sum of the input data might overflow the maximum unsigned short value. Introduced in: X11R6 Fixed in: xorg-server-21.1.19 and xwayland-24.1.9 Fix: https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/-/commit/475d9f49 Found by: Jan-Niklas Sohn working with Trend Micro Zero Day Initiative. ------------------------------------------------------------------------ X.Org thanks all of those who reported and fixed these issues, and those who helped with the review and release of this advisory and these fixes. -------------- next part -------------- A non-text attachment was scrubbed... Name: OpenPGP_0x14706DBE1E4B4540.asc Type: application/pgp-keys Size: 2988 bytes Desc: OpenPGP public key URL: &amp;lt;https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/attachments/20251028/ff11c77e/attachment.key&amp;gt; -------------- next part -------------- A non-text attachment was scrubbed... Name: OpenPGP_signature.asc Type: application/pgp-signature Size: 203 bytes Desc: OpenPGP digital signature URL: &amp;lt;https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/attachments/20251028/ff11c77e/attachment.sig&amp;gt; &lt;/quote&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;More information about the xorg-announce
mailing list&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-announce/2025-October/003635.html"/><published>2025-11-02T13:07:31+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45790827</id><title>Why don't you use dependent types?</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:16.670764+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a748029f0d0bb7f0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;"Why don't you use dependent types?"&lt;/head&gt;[&lt;code&gt;&lt;nobr&gt;memories&lt;/nobr&gt;&lt;/code&gt; 
  
    
    &lt;code&gt;&lt;nobr&gt;AUTOMATH&lt;/nobr&gt;&lt;/code&gt; 
  
    
    &lt;code&gt;&lt;nobr&gt;LCF&lt;/nobr&gt;&lt;/code&gt; 
  
    
    &lt;code&gt;&lt;nobr&gt;type theory&lt;/nobr&gt;&lt;/code&gt; 
  
    
    &lt;code&gt;&lt;nobr&gt;Martin-Löf type theory&lt;/nobr&gt;&lt;/code&gt; 
  
    
    &lt;code&gt;&lt;nobr&gt;NG de Bruijn&lt;/nobr&gt;&lt;/code&gt; 
  
    
    &lt;code&gt;&lt;nobr&gt;ALEXANDRIA&lt;/nobr&gt;&lt;/code&gt; 
  
]

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, nobody asks me this exact question. But people have regularly asked why Isabelle dispenses with proof objects. The two questions are essentially the same, because proof objects are intrinsic to all the usual type theories. They are also completely unnecessary and a huge waste of space. As described in an earlier post, type checking in the implementation language (rather than in the logic) can ensure that only legitimate proof steps are executed. Robin Milner had this fundamental insight 50 years ago, giving us the LCF architecture with its proof kernel. But the best answer to the original question is simply this: I did use dependent types, for years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;My time with AUTOMATH&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to get some personal time with N G de Bruijn when he came to Caltech in 1977 to lecture about AUTOMATH. I never actually got to use this system. Back then, researchers used the nascent Internet (the ARPAnet) not to download software so much as to run software directly on the host computer, since most software was not portable. But Eindhoven University was not on the ARPAnet, and AUTOMATH was configured to run on a computer we did not have:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until September 1973, the computer was the Electrologica X8, after that Burroughs 6700. In both cases the available multiprogranming systems required the use of ALGOL 60.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I did however read many of the research reports, including the PhD dissertation by LS Jutting, where he presents his translation of Landau’s text Grundlagen der Analysis (described last time) from German into AUTOMATH. It is no coincidence that many of my papers, from the earliest to the latest, copied the idea of formalising a text and attempting to be faithful to it, if possible line by line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an aside, note that while AUTOMATH was a system of dependent types, it did not embody the Curry–Howard correspondence (sometimes wrongly called the Curry–Howard–de Bruijn correspondence). That correspondence involves having a type theory strong enough to represent the predicate calculus directly in the form of types. In AUTOMATH you had to introduce the symbols and inference rules of your desired calculus in the form of axioms, much as you do with Isabelle. In short, AUTOMATH was a logical framework:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;like a big restaurant that serves all sorts of food: vegetarian, kosher, or anything else the customer wants&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;De Bruijn did not approve of the increasingly powerful type theories being developed in the 1990s. AUTOMATH was a weak language, a form of λ-calculus including a general product construction just powerful enough to express the inference rules of a variety of formalisms and to make simple definitions, again clearly the inspiration for Isabelle. Isabelle aims to be generic, like the big AUTOMATH restaurant. Only these days everybody prefers the same cuisine, higher-order logic, so Isabelle/HOL has become dominant. Unfortunately, I last spoke to Dick (as he was known to friends) when I was putting all my effort into Isabelle/ZF. He simply loathed set theory and saw mathematics as essentially typed. He never lived to see the enormous amount of advanced mathematics that would be formalised using types in Isabelle/HOL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I annoyed him in another way. I kept asking, AUTOMATH looks natural, but how do we know that it is right? He eventually sent me a 300 page volume entitled The Language Theory of Automath. It describes AUTOMATH’s formal properties such as strong normalisation and Church–Rosser properties, but this was not the answer I wanted at all. I got that answer for a quite different type theory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Martin-Löf type theory&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to kind invitations from Bengt Nordström and Kent Petersson, I paid a number of visits to Chalmers University in Gothenburg to learn about Martin-Löf type theory. I was particularly impressed by its promise of a systematic and formal approach to program synthesis. I had already encountered intuitionism through a course on the philosophy of mathematics at Stanford University, as I recall taught by Ian Hacking. The “rightness” of Martin-Löf type theory was obvious, because it directly embodied the principles of intuition truth as outlined by Heyting: for example, that a proof of $A\land B$ consists of a proof of $A$ paired with a proof of $B$.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I devoted several years of research to Martin-Löf type theory. This included a whole year of intricate hand derivations to produce a paper that I once thought would be important, and the very first version of Isabelle. Yes: Isabelle began as an implementation of Martin-Löf type theory, which is still included in the distribution even today as Isabelle/CTT. But eventually I tired of what seemed to me a doctrinaire attitude bordering on a cult of personality around Per Martin-Löf. The sudden switch to intensional equality (everyone was expected to adopt the new approach) wrecked most of my work. Screw that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might ask, what about the calculus of constructions, which arose during that time and eventually gave us Rocq and Lean? (Not to mention LEGO.) To me they raised, and continue to raise, the same question I had put to de Bruijn. Gérard Huet said something like “it is nothing but function application”, which did not convince me. It’s clear that I am being fussy,1 because thousands of people find these formalisms perfectly natural and believable. But it is also true that the calculus of constructions underwent numerous changes over the past four decades. There seem to be several optional axioms that people sometimes adopt while attempting to minimise their use, like dieters enjoying an occasional croissant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Decisions, decisions&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can see all this as an example of the choices we make in research. People were developing new formalisms. This specific fact was the impetus for making Isabelle generic in the first place. But we have to choose whether to spend our time developing formalisms or instead to choose a fixed formalism and see how far you can push it. Both are legitimate research goals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, already in 1985, Mike Gordon was using higher-order logic to verify hardware. He was not distracted by the idea that some dependent type theory might work better for n-bit words and the like. The formalism that he implemented was essentially the same as the simple theory of types outlined by Alonzo Church in 1940. He made verification history using this venerable formalism, and John Harrison later found a clever way to encode the dimension of vector types including words. Isabelle/HOL also implements Church’s simple type theory, with one extension: axiomatic type classes. Isabella users also derive much power from the locale concept, a kind of module sysstem that lies outside any particular logic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During all this time, both Martin-Löf type theory and the calculus of constructions went through several stages of evolution. It’s remarkable how the Lean community, by running with a certain version of the calculus, quickly formalised a vast amount of mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Pushing higher-order logic to its limit&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I felt exceptionally lucky to win funding from the European Research Council for the advanced grant ALEXANDRIA. When I applied, homotopy type theory was still all the rage, so the proposal emphasised Isabelle’s specific advantages: its automation, its huge libraries and the legibility of its proofs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The team started work with enthusiasm. Nevertheless, I fully expected that we would hit a wall, reaching mathematical material that could not easily be formalised in higher-order logic. Too much of Isabelle’s analysis library identified topological spaces with types. Isabelle’s abstract algebra library was old and crufty. A number of my research colleagues were convinced that higher-logic was not adequate for serious mathematics. But Anthony Bordg took up the challenge, leading a subproject to formalise Grothendieck schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For some reason I had a particular fear of the field extension $F[a]$, which extends the field $F$ with some $a$ postulated to be a root of some polynomial over $F$. (For example, the field of complex numbers is precisely $\mathbb{R}[i]$, where $i$ is postulated to be a root of $x^2+1=0$.) And yet an early outcome of ALEXANDRIA was a proof, by Paulo Emílio de Vilhena and Martin Baillon, that every field admits an algebraically closed extension. This was the first proof of that theorem in any proof assistant, and its proof involves an infinite series of field extensions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We never hit any wall. As our group went on to formalise more and more advanced results, such as the Balog–Szemerédi–Gowers theorem, people stopped saying “you can’t formalise mathematics without dependent types” and switched to saying “dependent types give you nicer proofs”. But they never proved this claim.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that dependent type theory has attained maturity and has an excellent tool in the form of Lean, shall I go back to dependent types? I am not tempted. The only aspects of Lean that I envy are its huge community and the Blueprint tool. I hear too many complaints about Lean’s performance. I’ve heard of too many cases where dependent types played badly with intensional equality – I sat through an entire talk on this topic – or otherwise made life difficult. Quite a few people have told me that the secret of dependent types is knowing when not to use them. And so, to me, they have too much in common with Tesla’s Full Self-Driving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Addendum: somebody commented on Hacker News that higher-order logic is too weak (in terms of proof-theoretic strength) to formalise post-WWII mathematics. This is not quite right. It is true that higher-order logic is much, much weaker than ZF set theory. But one of the most striking findings of ALEXANDRIA is that this is no obstacle to doing advanced mathematics, say to formalise Grothendieck schemes. Such elaborate towers of definitions do not seem to ascend especially high in the set-theoretic hierarchy. I can only recall a couple of proofs (this one, and that one) that required strengthening higher-order logic with the ZF axioms (which is easily done). These were theorems that referred to ZF entities in their very statements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Especially as regards constructive mathematics. To its founders, intuitionism is a philosophy suspicious of language, which it relegates to the purpose of recording and communicating mathematical thoughts. This is the opposite of today’s “constructive mathematics”, which refers the use of a formalism satisfying certain syntactic properties. ↩&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lawrencecpaulson.github.io//2025/11/02/Why-not-dependent.html"/><published>2025-11-02T15:06:36+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45792166</id><title>Is Your Bluetooth Chip Leaking Secrets via RF Signals?</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:16.227640+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9fb01c14c0e0095a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Is Your Bluetooth Chip Leaking Secrets via RF Signals?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;@article{Ji2025IsYB, title={Is Your Bluetooth Chip Leaking Secrets via RF Signals?}, author={Yanning Ji and Elena Dubrova and Ruize Wang}, journal={IACR Cryptol. ePrint Arch.}, year={2025}, volume={2025}, pages={559}, url={https://api.semanticscholar.org/CorpusID:278151312} }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A machine learning-assisted side-channel attack on the hardware AES accelerator of a Bluetooth chip used in millions of devices worldwide, ranging from wearables and smart home products to industrial IoT, can recover the full encryption key from 90,000 traces captured at a one-meter distance from the target device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;One Citation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Probabilistic Skipping-Based Data Structures with Robust Efficiency Guarantees&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer Science&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work presents adaptive attacks on all three aforementioned data structures that, in the case of hash tables and skip lists, cause exponential degradation compared to the input-independent setting, and proposes simple and efficient modifications to the original designs of these data structures to provide provable security against adaptive adversaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;27 References&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Screaming Channels: When Electromagnetic Side Channels Meet Radio Transceivers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2018&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Engineering, Physics&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This paper presents a new side channel that affects mixed-signal chips used in widespread wireless communication protocols, such as Bluetooth and WiFi and argues that protections against side channels (such as masking or hiding) need to be used on this class of devices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Understanding Screaming Channels: From a Detailed Analysis to Improved Attacks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2020&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer Science, Engineering&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work conducts a thorough experimental analysis of the peculiar properties of Screaming Channels, and provides a broader security evaluation of the leaks, helping the defender and radio designers to evaluate risk, and the need of countermeasures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Far Field EM Side-Channel Attack on AES Using Deep Learning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2020&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer Science, Engineering&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work presents the first deep learning-based side-channel attack on AES-128 using far field electromagnetic emissions as a side channel and can recover the key from less than 10K traces captured in an office environment at 15 m distance to target even if the measurement for each encryption is taken only once.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Advanced Far Field EM Side-Channel Attack on AES&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2021&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer Science, Engineering&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deep learning models are trained on "clean" traces, captured through a coaxial cable and the resulting models can extract the AES key from less than 500 traces on average captured at 15 m from the victim device without repeating each encryption more than once.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Attacking at non-harmonic frequencies in screaming-channel attacks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2023&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Engineering, Physics&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work demonstrates that compromising signals appear not only at the harmonics and that leakage at non-harmonics can be exploited for successful attacks, and proposes two methodologies to locate frequencies that contain leakage and demonstrates that it appears atNon-harmonic frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Machine learning in side-channel analysis: a first study&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2011&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer Science, Engineering&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work comprehensively investigates the application of a machine learning technique in SCA, a powerful kernel-based learning algorithm: the Least Squares Support Vector Machine (LS-SVM) and the target is a software implementation of the Advanced Encryption Standard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Power Analysis Attacks Against IEEE 802.15.4 Nodes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2016&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer Science, Engineering&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work measures the leakage characteristics of the AES accelerator on the Atmel ATMega128RFA1, and demonstrates how this allows recovery of the encryption key from nodes running an IEEE 802.15.4 stack.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Screaming Channels Revisited: Encryption Key Recovery from AES-CCM Accelerator&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer Science, Engineering&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This paper demonstrates the first successful extraction of the encryption key from the hardware AES accelerator in the nRF52832 Bluetooth Low Energy system-on-chip operating in Counter with CBC-MAC (CCM) mode using side-channel information recovered from RF signals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Power analysis attacks - revealing the secrets of smart cards&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2007&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer Science&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This volume explains how power analysis attacks work and provides an extensive discussion of countermeasures like shuffling, masking, and DPA-resistant logic styles to decide how to protect smart cards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Non-Profiled Deep Learning-Based Side-Channel Attacks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2018&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer Science&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This paper introduces a new method to apply Deep Learning techniques in a Non-Profiled context, where an attacker can only collect a limited number of side-channel traces for a fixed unknown key value from a closed device and introduces metrics based on Sensitivity Analysis that can reveal both the secret key value and points of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Is-Your-Bluetooth-Chip-Leaking-Secrets-via-RF-Ji-Dubrova/c1d3ceb47ea6f9cc4f29929e2f97d36862a260a2"/><published>2025-11-02T18:06:15+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45792373</id><title>Reproducing the AWS Outage Race Condition with a Model Checker</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:16.103763+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2d1cd20b79028601"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Reproducing the AWS Outage Race Condition with a Model Checker&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oct 30, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS published a post-mortem about a recent outage [1]. Big systems like theirs are complex, and when you operate at that scale, things sometimes go wrong. Still, AWS has an impressive record of reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The post-mortem mentioned a race condition, which caught my eye. I don’t know all the details of AWS’s internal setup, but using the information in the post-mortem and a few assumptions, we can try to reproduce a simplified version of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a small experiment, we’ll use a model checker to see how such a race could happen. Formal verification can’t prevent every failure, but it helps us think more clearly about correctness and reason about subtle concurrency bugs. Of course, writing about it after the incident benefits from hindsight, we already know what went wrong. For this experiment, we’ll use the Spin model checker, which uses the Promela language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of detail in the post-mortem, but for simplicity we’ll focus only on the race-condition aspect. The incident was triggered by a defect in DynamoDB’s automated DNS management system. The components of this system involved in the incident were the DNS Planner, DNS Enactor, and Amazon Route 53 service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The DNS Planner creates DNS plans, and the DNS Enactors look for new DNS plans and apply them to the Amazon Route 53 service. Three Enactors operate independently in three different availability zones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is an illustration showing these components (if the images appear small, please open them in a new browser tab):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My understanding of how the DNS Enactor works is as follows: it picks up the latest plan and, before applying it, performs a one-time check to ensure the plan is newer than the previously applied one. It then applies the plan and invokes a clean-up process. During the clean-up, it identifies plans significantly older than the one it just applied and deletes them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the details from the incident report, we could sketch an interleaving that could explain the race condition. Two Enactors running side by side: Enactor 2 applies a new plan and starts cleaning up, while the other, running just a little behind, applies an older plan, making it an active one. When the Enactor 2 finishes its cleanup, it deletes that plan, and the DNS entries disappear. Here’s what that sequence looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s try to uncover this interleaving using a model checker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Promela, you can model each part of the system as its own process. Spin then takes those processes, starts from the initial state, and systematically applies every possible transition, exploring all interleavings to build the set of reachable states [2]. It checks that your invariants hold in each one, and if it finds a violation, it reports a counterexample.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll create a DNS Planner process that produces plans, and DNS Enactor processes that pick them up. The Enactor will check whether the plan it’s about to apply is newer than the previous one, update the state of certain variables to simulate changes in Route 53, and finally clean up the older plans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In our simplified model, we’ll run one DNS Planner process and two concurrent DNS Enactor processes. (AWS appears to run three across zones; we abstract that detail here.) The Planner generates plans, and through Promela channels, these plans are sent to the Enactors for processing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inside each DNS Enactor, we track the key aspects of system state. The Enactor keeps the current plan in current_plan, and it represents DNS health using dns_valid. It also records the highest plan applied so far in highest_plan_applied. The incident report also notes that the clean-up process deletes plans that are “significantly older than the one it just applied.” In our model, we capture this by allowing an Enactor to remove only those plans that are much older than its current plan. To simulate the deletion of an active plan, the Enactor’s clean-up process checks whether current_plan equals the plan being deleted. If it does, we simulate the resulting DNS failure by setting dns_valid to false.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the code for the DNS Planner:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;active proctype Planner() {
    byte plan = 1;
    
    do
    :: (plan &amp;lt;= MAX_PLAN) -&amp;gt;
        latest_plan = plan;
        plan_channel ! plan; 
        printf("Planner: Generated Plan v%d\n", plan);
        plan++;
    :: (plan &amp;gt; MAX_PLAN) -&amp;gt; break;
    od;
    
    printf("Planner: Completed\n");
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It creates plans and sends them over a channel (plan is being sent to the channel plan_channel) to be picked up later by the DNS Enactor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We start two concurrent DNS Enactor processes by specifying the number of enactors after the active keyword.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;active [NUM_ENACTORS] proctype Enactor() 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The DNS Enactor waits for plans and receives them (? opertaor receives a plan from the channel plan_channel). It then performs a staleness check, updates the state of certain variables to simulate changes in Route 53, and finally cleans up the older plans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;:: plan_channel ? my_plan -&amp;gt;
    snapshot_current = current_plan;

    // staleness check    
    if
    :: (my_plan &amp;gt; snapshot_current || snapshot_current == 0) -&amp;gt;

        if
            :: !plan_deleted[my_plan] -&amp;gt;
                /* Apply the plan to Route53 */
                
                current_plan = my_plan;
                dns_valid = true;
                initialized = true;
               /* Track highest plan applied for regression detection */
                if 
                :: (my_plan &amp;gt; highest_plan_applied) -&amp;gt;
                    highest_plan_applied = my_plan;
                fi 
            
            // runs the clean-up process (omitted for brevity, included in the 
            // code linked below)
        fi
    fi

&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How do we discover the race condition? The idea is this: we express as an invariant what must always be true of the system, and then ask the model checker to confirm that it holds in every possible state. In this case, we can set up an invariant stating that the DNS should never be deleted once a newer plan has been applied. (With more information about the real system, we could simplify or refine this rule further.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We specify this invariant formally as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;/*

A quick note on some of the keywords used in the invariant below:

ltl - keyword that declares a temporal property to verify (ltl: linear temporal logic lets you specify properties about all possible executions of your program.)

[] - "always" operator (this must be true at every step forever)

-&amp;gt; - "implies" (if left side is true, then right side must be true)

*/

ltl no_dns_deletion_on_regression {
    [] ( (initialized &amp;amp;&amp;amp; highest_plan_applied &amp;gt; current_plan 
            &amp;amp;&amp;amp; current_plan &amp;gt; 0) -&amp;gt; dns_valid )
}



&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we start the model checker, one DNS Planner process begins generating plans and sending them through channels to the DNS Enactors. Two Enactors receive these plans, perform their checks, apply updates, and run their cleanup routines. As these processes interleave, the model checker systematically builds the set of reachable states, allowing the invariant to be checked in each one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we run the model with this invariant in the model checker, it reports a violation. Spin reports one error and writes a trail file that shows, step by step, how the system reached the bad state.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
$ spin -a aws-dns-race.pml
$ gcc -O2 -o pan pan.c                                                       
$ ./pan -a -N no_dns_deletion_on_regression  

pan: wrote aws-dns-race.pml.trail

(Spin Version 6.5.2 -- 6 December 2019)

State-vector 64 byte, depth reached 285, errors: 1
    23201 states, stored
    11239 states, matched
    34440 transitions (= stored+matched)
  (truncated for brevity....)

&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trail file in the repository below shows how the race happens. The trail file shows that two Enactors operate side by side: the faster one applies plan 4 and starts cleaning up. Because cleanup only removes plans much older than the one just applied, it deletes 1 and 2 but skips 3. The slower Enactor then applies plan 3 and makes it active, and when the faster Enactor picks up cleanup again, it deletes 3 and the DNS goes down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s an illustration of the interleaving reconstructed from the trail:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before publishing, I reread the incident report and noted: “Additionally, because the active plan was deleted, the system was left in an inconsistent state…”. This suggests a direct invariant: the active plan must never be deleted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ltl never_delete_active {
    [] ( current_plan &amp;gt; 0 -&amp;gt; !plan_deleted[current_plan] )
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running the model checker with this invariant produces essentially the same counterexample as before: one Enactor advances to newer plans while the other lags and applies an older plan, thereby making it active. When control returns to the faster Enactor, its cleanup deletes that now-active plan, violating the invariant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Invariants are invaluable for establishing correctness. If we can show that an invariant holds in the initial state, in every state reachable from it, and in the final state as well, we gain confidence that the system’s logic is sound.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To fix the code, we execute the problematic statements atomically. You can find both versions of the code, the one with the race and the fixed one, along with the interleaving trail in the accompanying repository [3]. I’ve included detailed comments to make it self-explanatory, as well as instructions on how to run the model and explore the trail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the assumptions in this model are necessarily simplified, since I don’t have access to AWS’s internal design details. Without that context, there will naturally be gaps between this abstraction and the real system. This model was created in a short time frame for experimental purposes. With more time and context, one could certainly build a more accurate and refined version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please keep in mind that I’m only human, and there’s a chance this post contains errors. If you notice anything off, I’d appreciate a correction. Please feel free to send me an email.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;References&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AWS Post-Incident Summary — October 2025 Outage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How concurrency works: A visual guide&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Source code repository&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Spin model checker&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://wyounas.github.io/aws/concurrency/2025/10/30/reproducing-the-aws-outage-race-condition-with-model-checker/"/><published>2025-11-02T18:37:38+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45792579</id><title>Lisp: Notes on its Past and Future (1980)</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:15.786178+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9449101996ab135c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; John McCarthy &lt;lb/&gt; Computer Science Department &lt;lb/&gt; Stanford University &lt;lb/&gt; Stanford, CA 94305 &lt;lb/&gt; jmc@cs.stanford.edu &lt;lb/&gt; http://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; JanFebMarAprMayJun JulAugSepOctNovDec , :&amp;lt; 10 0 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LISP has survived for 21 years because it is an approximate local optimum in the space of programming languages. However, it has accumulated some barnacles that should be scraped off, and some long-standing opportunities for improvement have been neglected. It would benefit from some co-operative maintenance especially in creating and maintaining program libraries. Computer checked proofs of program correctness are now possible for pure LISP and some extensions, but more theory and some smoothing of the language itself are required before we can take full advantage of LISP's mathematical basis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1999 note: This article was included in the 1980 Lisp conference held at Stanford. Since it almost entirely corresponds to my present opinions, I should have asked to have it reprinted in the 1998 Lisp users conference proceedings at which I gave a talk with the same title.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/lisp20th/lisp20th.html"/><published>2025-11-02T19:05:32+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45793244</id><title>Alleged Jabber Zeus Coder 'MrICQ' in U.S. Custody</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:15.223231+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="62a059d43823868d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Ukrainian man indicted in 2012 for conspiring with a prolific hacking group to steal tens of millions of dollars from U.S. businesses was arrested in Italy and is now in custody in the United States, KrebsOnSecurity has learned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sources close to the investigation say Yuriy Igorevich Rybtsov, a 41-year-old from the Russia-controlled city of Donetsk, Ukraine, was previously referenced in U.S. federal charging documents only by his online handle “MrICQ.” According to a 13-year-old indictment (PDF) filed by prosecutors in Nebraska, MrICQ was a developer for a cybercrime group known as “Jabber Zeus.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Jabber Zeus name is derived from the malware they used — a custom version of the ZeuS banking trojan — that stole banking login credentials and would send the group a Jabber instant message each time a new victim entered a one-time passcode at a financial institution website. The gang targeted mostly small to mid-sized businesses, and they were an early pioneer of so-called “man-in-the-browser” attacks, malware that can silently intercept any data that victims submit in a web-based form.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once inside a victim company’s accounts, the Jabber Zeus crew would modify the firm’s payroll to add dozens of “money mules,” people recruited through elaborate work-at-home schemes to handle bank transfers. The mules in turn would forward any stolen payroll deposits — minus their commissions — via wire transfers to other mules in Ukraine and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 2012 indictment targeting the Jabber Zeus crew named MrICQ as “John Doe #3,” and said this person handled incoming notifications of newly compromised victims. The Department of Justice (DOJ) said MrICQ also helped the group launder the proceeds of their heists through electronic currency exchange services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two sources familiar with the Jabber Zeus investigation said Rybtsov was arrested in Italy, although the exact date and circumstances of his arrest remain unclear. A summary of recent decisions (PDF) published by the Italian Supreme Court states that in April 2025, Rybtsov lost a final appeal to avoid extradition to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to the mugshot website lockedup[.]wtf, Rybtsov arrived in Nebraska on October 9, and was being held under an arrest warrant from the U.S. Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The data breach tracking service Constella Intelligence found breached records from the business profiling site bvdinfo[.]com showing that a 41-year-old Yuriy Igorevich Rybtsov worked in a building at 59 Barnaulska St. in Donetsk. Further searching on this address in Constella finds the same apartment building was shared by a business registered to Vyacheslav “Tank” Penchukov, the leader of the Jabber Zeus crew in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Penchukov was arrested in 2022 while traveling to meet his wife in Switzerland. Last year, a federal court in Nebraska sentenced Penchukov to 18 years in prison and ordered him to pay more than $73 million in restitution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lawrence Baldwin is founder of myNetWatchman, a threat intelligence company based in Georgia that began tracking and disrupting the Jabber Zeus gang in 2009. myNetWatchman had secretly gained access to the Jabber chat server used by the Ukrainian hackers, allowing Baldwin to eavesdrop on the daily conversations between MrICQ and other Jabber Zeus members.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Baldwin shared those real-time chat records with multiple state and federal law enforcement agencies, and with this reporter. Between 2010 and 2013, I spent several hours each day alerting small businesses across the country that their payroll accounts were about to be drained by these cybercriminals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those notifications, and Baldwin’s tireless efforts, saved countless would-be victims a great deal of money. In most cases, however, we were already too late. Nevertheless, the pilfered Jabber Zeus group chats provided the basis for dozens of stories published here about small businesses fighting their banks in court over six- and seven-figure financial losses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Baldwin said the Jabber Zeus crew was far ahead of its peers in several respects. For starters, their intercepted chats showed they worked to create a highly customized botnet directly with the author of the original Zeus Trojan — Evgeniy Mikhailovich Bogachev, a Russian man who has long been on the FBI’s “Most Wanted” list. The feds have a standing $3 million reward for information leading to Bogachev’s arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core innovation of Jabber Zeus was an alert that MrICQ would receive each time a new victim entered a one-time password code into a phishing page mimicking their financial institution. The gang’s internal name for this component was “Leprechaun,” (the video below from myNetWatchman shows it in action). Jabber Zeus would actually re-write the HTML code as displayed in the victim’s browser, allowing them to intercept any passcodes sent by the victim’s bank for multi-factor authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“These guys had compromised such a large number of victims that they were getting buried in a tsunami of stolen banking credentials,” Baldwin told KrebsOnSecurity. “But the whole point of Leprechaun was to isolate the highest-value credentials — the commercial bank accounts with two-factor authentication turned on. They knew these were far juicier targets because they clearly had a lot more money to protect.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Baldwin said the Jabber Zeus trojan also included a custom “backconnect” component that allowed the hackers to relay their bank account takeovers through the victim’s own infected PC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The Jabber Zeus crew were literally connecting to the victim’s bank account from the victim’s IP address, or from the remote control function and by fully emulating the device,” he said. “That trojan was like a hot knife through butter of what everyone thought was state-of-the-art secure online banking at the time.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although the Jabber Zeus crew was in direct contact with the Zeus author, the chats intercepted by myNetWatchman show Bogachev frequently ignored the group’s pleas for help. The government says the real leader of the Jabber Zeus crew was Maksim Yakubets, a 38-year Ukrainian man with Russian citizenship who went by the hacker handle “Aqua.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Jabber chats intercepted by Baldwin show that Aqua interacted almost daily with MrICQ, Tank and other members of the hacking team, often facilitating the group’s money mule and cashout activities remotely from Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The government says Yakubets/Aqua would later emerge as the leader of an elite cybercrime ring of at least 17 hackers that referred to themselves internally as “Evil Corp.” Members of Evil Corp developed and used the Dridex (a.k.a. Bugat) trojan, which helped them siphon more than $100 million from hundreds of victim companies in the United States and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This 2019 story about the government’s $5 million bounty for information leading to Yakubets’s arrest includes excerpts of conversations between Aqua, Tank, Bogachev and other Jabber Zeus crew members discussing stories I’d written about their victims. Both Baldwin and I were interviewed at length for a new weekly six-part podcast by the BBC that delves deep into the history of Evil Corp. Episode One focuses on the evolution of Zeus, while the second episode centers on an investigation into the group by former FBI agent Jim Craig.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/11/alleged-jabber-zeus-coder-mricq-in-u-s-custody/"/><published>2025-11-02T20:40:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45793466</id><title>Paris had a moving sidewalk in 1900, and a Thomas Edison film captured it (2020)</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:14.966426+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6f8a1d567f3f91af"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s fair to say that few of us now marvel at moving walkways, those standard infrastructural elements of such utilitarian spaces as airport terminals, subway stations, and big-box stores. But there was a time when they astounded even residents of one of the most cosmopolitan cities in the world. The innovation of the moving sidewalk demonstrated at the Paris Exposition of 1900 (previously seen here on Open Culture when we featured Lumière Brothers footage of that period) commanded even Thomas Edison’s attention. As Paleofuture’s Matt Novak tells it at Smithsonian magazine, “Thomas Edison sent one of his producers, James Henry White, to the Exposition and Mr. White shot at least 16 movies,” a clip of which footage you can see above.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;White “had brought along a new panning-head tripod that gave his films a newfound sense of freedom and flow. Watching the film, you can see children jumping into frame and even a man doffing his cap to the camera, possibly aware that he was being captured by an exciting new technology while a fun novelty of the future chugs along under his feet.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Novak also includes hand-colored photographs from the Paris Exhibition and quotes a New York Observer correspondent describing the moving sidewalk as a “novelty” consisting of “three elevated platforms, the first being stationary, the second moving at a moderate rate of speed, and the third at the rate of about six miles an hour.” Thus “the circuit of the Exposition can be made with rapidity and ease by this contrivance. It also affords a good deal of fun, for most of the visitors are unfamiliar with this mode of transit, and are awkward in its use.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Novak features contemporary images of the Paris Exhibition’s moving sidewalk at Paleofuture, found in the book Paris Exposition Reproduced From the Official Photographs. Its authors describe the trottoir roulant as “a detached structure like a railway train, arriving at and passing certain points at stated times” without a break. “In engineers’ language, it is an ‘endless floor’ raised thirty feet above the level of the ground, ever and ever gliding along the four sides of the square — a wooden serpent with its tail in its mouth.” But the history of the moving walkway didn’t start in Paris: “In 1871 inventor Alfred Speer patented a system of moving sidewalks that he thought would revolutionize pedestrian travel in New York City,” as Novak notes, and the first one actually built was built for Chicago’s 1893 Columbian Exposition — but it cost a nickel to ride and “was undependable and prone to breaking down,” making Paris’ version the more impressive spectacle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, the Columbian Exposition’s visitors must have got a kick out of gliding down the pier without having to do the walking themselves. You can learn more about this first moving walkway and its successors, the one at the Paris Exhibition included, from the Little Car video above. However much these early models may look like quaint turn-of-the century novelties, some still see in the technology genuine promise for the future of public transit. Moving walkways work well, writes Treehugger’s Lloyd Alter, “when the walking distance and time is just a bit too long.” And they remind us that “transportation should be about more than just getting from A to B; it should be a pleasure as well.” Parisians “kept the Eiffel Tower from the exhibition” — it had been built for the 1889 World’s Fair — but “it is too bad they didn’t keep this, a sort of moving High Line that is both transportation and entertainment.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you would like to sign up for Open Culture’s free email newsletter, please find it here. It’s a great way to see our new posts, all bundled in one email, each day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you would like to support the mission of Open Culture, consider making a donation to our site. It’s hard to rely 100% on ads, and your contributions will help us continue providing the best free cultural and educational materials to learners everywhere. You can contribute through PayPal, Patreon, and Venmo (@openculture). Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Related Content:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How French Artists in 1899 Envisioned Life in the Year 2000: Drawing the Future&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based in Seoul, Colin Marshall writes and broadcasts on cities, language, and culture. His projects include the book The Stateless City: a Walk through 21st-Century Los Angeles and the video series The City in Cinema. Follow him on Twitter at @colinmarshall or on Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.openculture.com/2020/03/paris-had-a-moving-sidewalk-in-1900.html"/><published>2025-11-02T21:08:15+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45793652</id><title>FurtherAI (YC W24) Is Hiring Across Software and AI</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:14.679987+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ad5c709c2efe2c46"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;FurtherAI (Series A, a16z + YC) is hiring Software Engineers, AI Engineers, and Forward-Deployed Engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We're building AI Agents for the insurance industry and are already post-PMF with strong enterprise adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;  - $25M Series A led by Andreessen Horowitz (a16z)
  - &amp;gt;10× revenue growth this year
  - Seed -&amp;gt; Series A in under a year
  - Small, talent-dense team - 6/15 are founders (incl. 4 YC founders)
  - Team backgrounds include staff engineers and researchers from Apple, Microsoft, Amazon
&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Hiring strong engineers based in SF who want high ownership, fast shipping, and real impact.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you/someone you know is interested, feel free to reach out directly to Sashank (CTO) - sg+hn@furtherai.com&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Jobs link - https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/furtherai&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;PS: We also have a $10k referral bonus per hire, so plz share it across!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45793652"/><published>2025-11-02T21:35:02+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45794032</id><title>Facts about throwing good parties</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:14.415889+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ae81d25b166581bc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;21 Facts About Throwing Good Parties&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For New York’s No 1 Socialite, Angela.&lt;lb/&gt;1) Prioritize your ease of being over any other consideration: parties are like babies, if you’re stressed while holding them they’ll get stressed too. Every other decision is downstream of your serenity: e.g. it's better to have mediocre pizza from a happy host than fabulous hors d'oeuvres from a frazzled one.&lt;lb/&gt;2) Advertise your start time as a quarter-to the hour. If you start an event at 2:00, people won't arrive till 2:30; if you make it 1:45, people will arrive at 2:00.&lt;lb/&gt;3) Invite a few close friends to come 30-60 mins earlier to set up / eat dinner with you / hang out / whatever, so that when the start time approaches you’re already having fun instead of stressing that nobody will come.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4) Most people will only go to a party where they expect to know 3+ others already.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;5) Use an app like Partiful or Luma that shows the guest list to invitees. Start by inviting your closest friends, get some yesses, then expand from there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;6) Send the invites in chat groups (or visibly cc’ed emails) to clusters of 4-5 people who know each other, so they can see that their friends are also going.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;7) When inviting people individually, namedrop mutual friends who are invited or coming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;8) In a small group, the quality of the experience will depend a lot on whether the various friends blend together well. Follow your instinct on this, even if your instinct feels rude. It’s like cooking a dish, two ingredients can each be fabulous and still not go well together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;9) A large party is more like an Everything Soup: you mainly need to avoid ingredients that ruin the flavor for everyone else; beyond that you can mostly throw in whatever and see what works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10) Regardless, try not to feel bad about not-inviting someone if your heart says they would make the party less-fun for others. Make peace with gatekeeping because if you don't exclude a small % of people you will ultimately lose everyone else. Someone can be a good person and a bad fit for your party, so don't think of it as a judgement on their soul. All of this is easier in theory than in practice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;11) Most events are better when roughly gender-balanced. Prioritize inviting people of the gender you’d likely have fewer of, then top up invites with the other. Once an event crosses a threshold (maybe 70%?) of male-or-female dominance, most people of the other gender are likely to decline (or just not-come to your next party) as a result. So there's ultimately two equilibria, "roughly gender balanced" and "extremely uncomfortably unbalanced," and you need to stay in the attraction basin for balance. To do this, keep your invite ratio at worst 60-40 in either direction, in order to prevent a downward spiral.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;12) Co-host parties with someone you like a lot but who isn't in your exact social circle, so that your two friend-sets can intermingle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;13) Figure out the flake rate in your social circles (the % of people who will RSVP yes and flake on the day), and set your invite numbers with that in mind. In my circles, consistently 1/3rd of people who say they will be there will actually not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;14) Couples often flake together. This changes the probability distribution of attendees considerably, and so your chance of losing a quorum in a small-group setting. Small-group couple-events (e.g. 3-4 couple dinner parties) are very hard to manage in a high-flake society, as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;15) Create as much circulation at your party as you can. People circulate more when standing than when sitting, so try to encourage standing for those who can e.g. by having high-top tables, or taking away chairs from around tables, or leaving shelves and counter-tops open for people to rest their plates and drinks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;16) Put the food in one part of the room and the drinks in another, or spread the food and drinks out around the space, so that people have lots of excuses to move around the room.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;17) If someone arrives at your party and doesn’t know anybody, welcome them and then place them with another group or person. Ideally you can pick someone they’d specifically get along well with, at second-best just someone who’s friendly and easy to talk to, but ultimately you can just insert them in any group that’s nearby and open. The main point is to prevent them having to butt in on strangers themselves, which for many people is mortifying, while your Host Privilege allows you to do it for them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;18) To leave a group conversation, just slowly step back and then step away. Don't draw attention to your leaving or you’ll be pulled back in. It feels mildly weird to do this but it’s worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;19) Throughout the party, prioritize introducing people to each other and hosting the people who are new or shy, even at the cost of getting less time hanging out with your best friends yourself. Parties are a public service, and the guests will (hopefully) pay you back for this by inviting you to parties of their own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;20) Let me repeat that: Parties are a public service, you’re doing people a favor by throwing them. Someone might meet their new best friend or future lover at your gathering. In the short term, lovely people may feel less lonely, and that's thanks to you. In the long term, whole new children may ultimately exist in the world because you bothered to throw a party. Throwing parties is stressful for most people, but a great kindness to the community, so genuinely pat yourself on the back for doing this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;21) The biggest problem at many parties is an endless escalation of volume. If you know how to fix this, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.atvbt.com/21-facts-about-throwing-good-parties/"/><published>2025-11-02T22:32:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45794245</id><title>New prompt injection papers: Agents rule of two and the attacker moves second</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:14.237572+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f52930f49b4d725"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;New prompt injection papers: Agents Rule of Two and The Attacker Moves Second&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2nd November 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two interesting new papers regarding LLM security and prompt injection came to my attention this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Agents Rule of Two: A Practical Approach to AI Agent Security&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first is Agents Rule of Two: A Practical Approach to AI Agent Security, published on October 31st on the Meta AI blog. It doesn’t list authors but it was shared on Twitter by Meta AI security researcher Mick Ayzenberg.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It proposes a “Rule of Two” that’s inspired by both my own lethal trifecta concept and the Google Chrome team’s Rule Of 2 for writing code that works with untrustworthy inputs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At a high level, the Agents Rule of Two states that until robustness research allows us to reliably detect and refuse prompt injection, agents must satisfy no more than two of the following three properties within a session to avoid the highest impact consequences of prompt injection.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[A] An agent can process untrustworthy inputs&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[B] An agent can have access to sensitive systems or private data&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[C] An agent can change state or communicate externally&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s still possible that all three properties are necessary to carry out a request. If an agent requires all three without starting a new session (i.e., with a fresh context window), then the agent should not be permitted to operate autonomously and at a minimum requires supervision --- via human-in-the-loop approval or another reliable means of validation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s accompanied by this handy diagram:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I like this a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve spent several years now trying to find clear ways to explain the risks of prompt injection attacks to developers who are building on top of LLMs. It’s frustratingly difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve had the most success with the lethal trifecta, which boils one particular class of prompt injection attack down to a simple-enough model: if your system has access to private data, exposure to untrusted content and a way to communicate externally then it’s vulnerable to private data being stolen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The one problem with the lethal trifecta is that it only covers the risk of data exfiltration: there are plenty of other, even nastier risks that arise from prompt injection attacks against LLM-powered agents with access to tools which the lethal trifecta doesn’t cover.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Agents Rule of Two neatly solves this, through the addition of “changing state” as a property to consider. This brings other forms of tool usage into the picture: anything that can change state triggered by untrustworthy inputs is something to be very cautious about.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s also refreshing to see another major research lab concluding that prompt injection remains an unsolved problem, and attempts to block or filter them have not proven reliable enough to depend on. The current solution is to design systems with this in mind, and the Rule of Two is a solid way to think about that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update: On thinking about this further there’s one aspect of the Rule of Two model that doesn’t work for me: the Venn diagram above marks the combination of untrustworthy inputs and the ability to change state as “safe”, but that’s not right. Even without access to private systems or sensitive data that pairing can still produce harmful results. Unfortunately adding an exception for that pair undermines the simplicity of the “Rule of Two” framing!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which brings me to the second paper...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The Attacker Moves Second: Stronger Adaptive Attacks Bypass Defenses Against LLM Jailbreaks and Prompt Injections&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This paper is dated 10th October 2025 on Arxiv and comes from a heavy-hitting team of 14 authors—Milad Nasr, Nicholas Carlini, Chawin Sitawarin, Sander V. Schulhoff, Jamie Hayes, Michael Ilie, Juliette Pluto, Shuang Song, Harsh Chaudhari, Ilia Shumailov, Abhradeep Thakurta, Kai Yuanqing Xiao, Andreas Terzis, Florian Tramèr—including representatives from OpenAI, Anthropic, and Google DeepMind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The paper looks at 12 published defenses against prompt injection and jailbreaking and subjects them to a range of “adaptive attacks”—attacks that are allowed to expend considerable effort iterating multiple times to try and find a way through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The defenses did not fare well:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;By systematically tuning and scaling general optimization techniques—gradient descent, reinforcement learning, random search, and human-guided exploration—we bypass 12 recent defenses (based on a diverse set of techniques) with attack success rate above 90% for most; importantly, the majority of defenses originally reported near-zero attack success rates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably the “Human red-teaming setting” scored 100%, defeating all defenses. That red-team consisted of 500 participants in an online competition they ran with a $20,000 prize fund.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key point of the paper is that static example attacks—single string prompts designed to bypass systems—are an almost useless way to evaluate these defenses. Adaptive attacks are far more powerful, as shown by this chart:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The three automated adaptive attack techniques used by the paper are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gradient-based methods—these were the least effective, using the technique described in the legendary Universal and Transferable Adversarial Attacks on Aligned Language Models paper from 2023.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reinforcement learning methods—particularly effective against black-box models: “we allowed the attacker model to interact directly with the defended system and observe its outputs”, using 32 sessions of 5 rounds each.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Search-based methods—generate candidates with an LLM, then evaluate and further modify them using LLM-as-judge and other classifiers.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The paper concludes somewhat optimistically:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[...] Adaptive evaluations are therefore more challenging to perform, making it all the more important that they are performed. We again urge defense authors to release simple, easy-to-prompt defenses that are amenable to human analysis. [...] Finally, we hope that our analysis here will increase the standard for defense evaluations, and in so doing, increase the likelihood that reliable jailbreak and prompt injection defenses will be developed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given how totally the defenses were defeated, I do not share their optimism that reliable defenses will be developed any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a review of how far we still have to go this paper packs a powerful punch. I think it makes a strong case for Meta’s Agents Rule of Two as the best practical advice for building secure LLM-powered agent systems today in the absence of prompt injection defenses we can rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More recent articles&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hacking the WiFi-enabled color screen GitHub Universe conference badge - 28th October 2025&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Video: Building a tool to copy-paste share terminal sessions using Claude Code for web - 23rd October 2025&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/2/new-prompt-injection-papers/"/><published>2025-11-02T23:11:22+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45795036</id><title>Simple trick to increase coverage: Lying to users about signal strength</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:11.538769+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3c2aa11d56340649"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Poking around in Android the other day I found this nugget in Carrier Config manager; a flag (KEY_INFLATE_SIGNAL_STRENGTH_BOOL) to always report the signal strength to the user as one bar higher than it really is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not documented in the Android docs, but it’s there in the source available for any operator to use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably both AT&amp;amp;T and Verizon have this flag enabled on their networks, I’m not sure who was responsible for requesting this to be added to Android, nor could I find it in the &lt;code&gt;git-blame&lt;/code&gt;, but we can see it in the CarrierConfig which contains all the network settings for each of these operators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operators are always claiming to have the biggest coverage or the best network, but stuff like this, along with the fake 5G flags, don’t help build trust, especially considering the magic mobile phone antennas which negate the need for all this deception anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nickvsnetworking.com/simple-trick-to-increase-coverage-lying-to-users-about-signal-strength/"/><published>2025-11-03T01:27:48+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45795186</id><title>Syllabi – Open-source agentic AI with tools, RAG, and multi-channel deploy</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:11.251530+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f7c22e69c0a7aeba"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Create Custom AIChatbots That Deploy Everywhere&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build intelligent chatbots with knowledge bases, multi-app integrations, and omnichannel deployment. Open-source, customizable, and ready to scale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Features&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Build from Your Knowledge&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transform your documents, websites, and data into an intelligent knowledge base. Your chatbot retrieves accurate information with citations and source highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Multi-Format Support&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Import PDFs, videos, websites, Google Drive, Notion, and more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Smart Retrieval (RAG)&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advanced retrieval technology finds the most relevant information instantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Source Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Highlights exact passages from documents with clickable references.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Deploy Across Channels&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;One chatbot, multiple channels. Deploy to web, embed in your website, or connect to Slack and Discord for team collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Web &amp;amp; Embedded Widget&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add AI-powered chat to any website with customizable widgets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Slack &amp;amp; Discord&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Integrate with team messaging platforms for instant access to knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;API Access&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build custom integrations with our REST API.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Extend with Skills&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make your chatbot agentic by adding custom skills and tools. Connect to external services, trigger actions, or create custom API integrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Custom Tools &amp;amp; Webhooks&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create custom actions via webhooks and API integrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Integration Skills&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Send Slack messages, trigger workflows, and connect external services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Agentic Behavior&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your chatbot intelligently decides when and how to use available tools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More Than Just Text&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rich, interactive conversations that go beyond simple Q&amp;amp;A. Documents, diagrams, code, and multimedia—all in one place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Document Highlighting&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click on citations to see the exact source highlighted in the original document. Navigate directly to relevant passages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Diagrams &amp;amp; Visualizations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generate Mermaid diagrams, flowcharts, and visual explanations to make complex concepts easier to understand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Native Code Execution&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run Python and R code directly in the browser using Pyodide and WebR. Generate, execute, and visualize results instantly—no server needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Multimedia Support&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Embed and play videos, display images, and share rich media content directly in conversations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Built for Every Team and Use Case&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;From education to customer support, Syllabi adapts to your needs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Course Assistant for Students&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Teachers create chatbots from course materials. Students get instant answers with source citations, making learning interactive and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Document upload&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Citation tracking&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Q&amp;amp;A support&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Embedded Website Support&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add AI-powered support to your website. Automatically answer questions from your docs, reducing support tickets and improving customer satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Embedded widget&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;24/7 availability&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Brand customization&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Team Knowledge via Slack/Discord&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Connect your team's knowledge base to Slack or Discord. Get instant answers from company docs without leaving your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Slack/Discord integration&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Private data&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Team collaboration&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;API &amp;amp; Code Documentation&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Help developers find answers in technical documentation. Generate code examples and explain complex concepts with diagrams.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Code generation&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Diagram support&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Technical docs&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Full Control Over Behavior &amp;amp; Appearance&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Customize every aspect of your chatbot to match your brand and business needs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Brand Customization&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Match your brand with custom themes, colors, and styling. Choose from pre-built themes or create your own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Model Configuration&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Choose OpenAI models (GPT-4, GPT-3.5) and configure temperature, personality, and behavior. More model providers coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Conversation Design&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set custom welcome messages, suggested questions, and conversation flows to guide user interactions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Analytics &amp;amp; Insights&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Track conversations, measure engagement, and understand user needs with detailed analytics dashboards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Integrate with Tools You Already Use&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Connect Syllabi to your favorite apps. Use them as knowledge sources, deployment channels, or to automate actions and workflows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Knowledge Sources&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Google Drive&lt;/head&gt;Knowledge Source&lt;p&gt;Sync Google Drive files and docs as knowledge sources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Notion&lt;/head&gt;Knowledge Source&lt;p&gt;Sync Notion pages and databases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Website URLs&lt;/head&gt;Knowledge Source&lt;p&gt;Feed in direct website URLs and web pages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Deploy Channels&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Discord&lt;/head&gt;Deploy Channel&lt;p&gt;Deploy chatbot to Discord servers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Web Widget&lt;/head&gt;Deploy Channel&lt;p&gt;Embed on any website with a chat widget.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Standalone App&lt;/head&gt;Deploy Channel&lt;p&gt;Deploy as a standalone chat app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Actions &amp;amp; Extensions&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Gmail&lt;/head&gt;Action/Workflow&lt;p&gt;Send emails based on chatbot interactions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Google Calendar&lt;/head&gt;Action/Workflow&lt;p&gt;Create and manage calendar events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Custom APIs&lt;/head&gt;Action/Workflow&lt;p&gt;Connect to any custom API or webhook.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Powerhouse Integrations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multi-purpose integrations that work as knowledge sources, channels, AND actions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Slack&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build knowledge base from Slack, deploy chatbot, trigger Slack actions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Google Workspace&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Connect Google Drive, Gmail, Calendar, and Docs as knowledge sources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coming soon: Zapier, Make (Integromat), GitHub, Microsoft Teams, Stripe, Zendesk, HubSpot, and many more. Plus, custom API integrations for unlimited possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Open Source. Self-Hosted. Your Data, Your Control.&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Built for developers and teams who value transparency, privacy, and full control over their AI infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;MIT Licensed&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Free to use, modify, and deploy. No vendor lock-in, no hidden costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Self-Hosted&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run on your infrastructure with full data control and privacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Extensible&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build custom integrations, skills, and features to match your needs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Community-Driven&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Active development with contributions from developers worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Privacy-First&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your data never leaves your servers. Complete control over security.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐ Star us on GitHub&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Open Source&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;MIT licensed and community-driven. Self-host and customize freely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Multi-Channel&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deploy to Web, Embedded, Slack, and Discord.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Agentic &amp;amp; Extensible&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add custom skills and tools to extend chatbot capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Advanced RAG&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Powered by retrieval-augmented generation for accurate, cited responses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Start Building Your Custom Chatbot Today&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Join developers and businesses creating intelligent chatbots with Syllabi. Open-source, free, and ready to deploy everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.syllabi-ai.com/"/><published>2025-11-03T01:59:07+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45795511</id><title>Oxy is Cloudflare's Rust-based next generation proxy framework (2023)</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:10.869066+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b5fad91d343278d3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In this blog post, we are proud to introduce Oxy - our modern proxy framework, developed using the Rust programming language. Oxy is a foundation of several Cloudflare projects, including the Zero Trust Gateway, the iCloud Private Relay second hop proxy, and the internal egress routing service.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxy leverages our years of experience building high-load proxies to implement the latest communication protocols, enabling us to effortlessly build sophisticated services that can accommodate massive amounts of daily traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We will be exploring Oxy in greater detail in upcoming technical blog posts, providing a comprehensive and in-depth look at its capabilities and potential applications. For now, let us embark on this journey and discover what Oxy is and how we built it.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We refer to Oxy as our "next-generation proxy framework". But what do we really mean by âproxy frameworkâ? Picture a server (like NGINX, that reader might be familiar with) that can proxy traffic with an array of protocols, including various predefined common traffic flow scenarios that enable you to route traffic to specific destinations or even egress with a different protocol than the one used for ingress. This server can be configured in many ways for specific flows and boasts tight integration with the surrounding infrastructure, whether telemetry consumers or networking services.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Now, take all of that and add in the ability to programmatically control every aspect of the proxying: protocol decapsulation, traffic analysis, routing, tunneling logic, DNS resolution, and so much more. And this is what Oxy proxy framework is: a feature-rich proxy server tightly integrated with our internal infrastructure that's customizable to meet application requirements, allowing engineers to tweak every component.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This design is in line with our belief in an iterative approach to development, where a basic solution is built first and then gradually improved over time. With Oxy, you can start with a basic solution that can be deployed to our servers and then add additional features as needed, taking advantage of the many extensibility points offered by Oxy. In fact, you can avoid writing any code, besides a few lines of bootstrap boilerplate and get a production-ready server with a wide variety of startup configuration options and traffic flow scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;High-level Oxy architecture&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For example, suppose you'd like to implement an HTTP firewall. With Oxy, you can proxy HTTP(S) requests right out of the box, eliminating the need to write any code related to production services, such as request metrics and logs. You simply need to implement an Oxy hook handler for HTTP requests and responses. If you've used Cloudflare Workers before, then you should be familiar with this extensibility model.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Similarly, you can implement a layer 4 firewall by providing application hooks that handle ingress and egress connections. This goes beyond a simple block/accept scenario, as you can build authentication functionality or a traffic router that sends traffic to different destinations based on the geographical information of the ingress connection. The capabilities are incredibly rich, and we've made the extensibility model as ergonomic and flexible as possible. As an example, if information obtained from layer 4 is insufficient to make an informed firewall decision, the app can simply ask Oxy to decapsulate the traffic and process it with HTTP firewall.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The aforementioned scenarios are prevalent in many products we build at Cloudflare, so having a foundation that incorporates ready solutions is incredibly useful. This foundation has absorbed lots of experience we've gained over the years, taking care of many sharp and dark corners of high-load service programming. As a result, application implementers can stay focused on the business logic of their application with Oxy taking care of the rest. In fact, we've been able to create a few privacy proxy applications using Oxy that now serve massive amounts of traffic in production with less than a couple of hundred lines of code. This is something that would have taken multiple orders of magnitude more time and lines of code before.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As previously mentioned, we'll dive deeper into the technical aspects in future blog posts. However, for now, we'd like to provide a brief overview of Oxy's capabilities. This will give you a glimpse of the many ways in which Oxy can be customized and used.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On-ramp defines a combination of transport layer socket type and protocols that server listeners can use for ingress traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxy supports a wide variety of traffic on-ramps:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;HTTP 1/2/3 (including various CONNECT protocols for layer 3 and 4 traffic)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;TCP and UDP traffic over Proxy Protocol&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;general purpose IP traffic, including ICMP&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;With Oxy, you have the ability to analyze and manipulate traffic at multiple layers of the OSI model - from layer 3 to layer 7. This allows for a wide range of possibilities in terms of how you handle incoming traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;One of the most notable and powerful features of Oxy is the ability for applications to force decapsulation. This means that an application can analyze traffic at a higher level, even if it originally arrived at a lower level. For example, if an application receives IP traffic, it can choose to analyze the UDP traffic encapsulated within the IP packets. With just a few lines of code, the application can tell Oxy to upgrade the IP flow to a UDP tunnel, effectively allowing the same code to be used for different on-ramps.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The application can even go further and ask Oxy to sniff UDP packets and check if they contain HTTP/3 traffic. In this case, Oxy can upgrade the UDP traffic to HTTP and handle HTTP/3 requests that were originally received as raw IP packets. This allows for the simultaneous processing of traffic at all three layers (L3, L4, L7), enabling applications to analyze, filter, and manipulate the traffic flow from multiple perspectives. This provides a robust toolset for developing advanced traffic processing applications.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Multi-layer traffic processing in Oxy applications&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Off-ramp defines a combination of transport layer socket type and protocols that proxy server connectors can use for egress traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxy offers versatility in its egress methods, supporting a range of protocols including HTTP 1 and 2, UDP, TCP, and IP. It is equipped with internal DNS resolution and caching, as well as customizable resolvers, with automatic fallback options for maximum system reliability. Oxy implements happy eyeballs for TCP, advanced tunnel timeout logic and has the ability to route traffic to internal services with accompanying metadata.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Additionally, through collaboration with one of our internal services (which is an Oxy application itself!) Oxy is able to offer geographical egress â allowing applications to route traffic to the public Internet from various locations in our extensive network covering numerous cities worldwide. This complex and powerful feature can be easily utilized by Oxy application developers at no extra cost, simply by adjusting configuration settings.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Tunneling and request handling&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We've discussed Oxy's communication capabilities with the outside world through on-ramps and off-ramps. In the middle, Oxy handles efficient stateful tunneling of various traffic types including TCP, UDP, QUIC, and IP, while giving applications full control over traffic blocking and redirection.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Additionally, Oxy effectively handles HTTP traffic, providing full control over requests and responses, and allowing it to serve as a direct HTTP or API service. With built-in tools for streaming analysis of HTTP bodies, Oxy makes it easy to extract and process data, such as form data from uploads and downloads.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In addition to its multi-layer traffic processing capabilities, Oxy also supports advanced HTTP tunneling methods, such as CONNECT-UDP and CONNECT-IP, using the latest extensions to HTTP 3 and 2 protocols. It can even process HTTP CONNECT request payloads on layer 4 and recursively process the payload as HTTP if the encapsulated traffic is HTTP.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Recursive processing of HTTP CONNECT body payload in HTTP pipeline&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The modern Internet is unimaginable without traffic encryption, and Oxy, of course, provides this essential aspect. Oxy's cryptography and TLS are based on BoringSSL, providing both a FIPS-compliant version with a limited set of certified features and the latest version that supports all the currently available TLS features. Oxy also allows applications to switch between the two versions in real-time, on a per-request or per-connection basis.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxy's TLS client is designed to make HTTPS requests to upstream servers, with the functionality and security of a browser-grade client. This includes the reconstruction of certificate chains, certificate revocation checks, and more. In addition, Oxy applications can be secured with TLS v1.3, and optionally mTLS, allowing for the extraction of client authentication information from x509 certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxy has the ability to inspect and filter HTTPS traffic, including HTTP/3, and provides the means for dynamically generating certificates, serving as a foundation for implementing data loss prevention (DLP) products. Additionally, Oxy's internal fork of BoringSSL, which is not FIPS-compliant, supports the use of raw public keys as an alternative to WebPKI, making it ideal for internal service communication. This allows for all the benefits of TLS without the hassle of managing root certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Gluing everything together&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxy is more than just a set of building blocks for network applications. It acts as a cohesive glue, handling the bootstrapping of the entire proxy application with ease, including parsing and applying configurations, setting up an asynchronous runtime, applying seccomp hardening and providing automated graceful restarts functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;With built-in support for panic reporting to Sentry, Prometheus metrics with a Rust-macro based API, Kibana logging, distributed tracing, memory and runtime profiling, Oxy offers comprehensive monitoring and analysis capabilities. It can also generate detailed audit logs for layer 4 traffic, useful for billing and network analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To top it off, Oxy includes an integration testing framework, allowing for easy testing of application interactions using TypeScript-based tests.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To take full advantage of Oxy's capabilities, one must understand how to extend and configure its features. Oxy applications are configured using YAML configuration files, offering numerous options for each feature. Additionally, application developers can extend these options by leveraging the convenient macros provided by the framework, making customization a breeze.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Suppose the Oxy application uses a key-value database to retrieve user information. In that case, it would be beneficial to expose a YAML configuration settings section for this purpose. With Oxy, defining a structure and annotating it with the &lt;code&gt;#[oxy_app_settings]&lt;/code&gt; attribute is all it takes to accomplish this:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;///Applicationâs key-value (KV) database settings
#[oxy_app_settings]
pub struct MyAppKVSettings {
    /// Key prefix.
    pub prefix: Option&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;,
    /// Path to the UNIX domain socket for the appropriate KV 
    /// server instance.
    pub socket: Option&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;,
}&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxy can then generate a default YAML configuration file listing available options and their default values, including those extended by the application. The configuration options are automatically documented in the generated file from the Rust doc comments, following best Rust practices.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Moreover, Oxy supports multi-tenancy, allowing a single application instance to expose multiple on-ramp endpoints, each with a unique configuration. But, sometimes even a YAML configuration file is not enough to build a desired application, this is where Oxy's comprehensive set of hooks comes in handy. These hooks can be used to extend the application with Rust code and cover almost all aspects of the traffic processing.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To give you an idea of how easy it is to write an Oxy application, here is an example of basic Oxy code:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;struct MyApp;

// Defines types for various application extensions to Oxy's
// data types. Contexts provide information and control knobs for
// the different parts of the traffic flow and applications can extend // all of them with their custom data. As was mentioned before,
// applications could also define their custom configuration.
// Itâs just a matter of defining a configuration object with
// `#[oxy_app_settings]` attribute and providing the object type here.
impl OxyExt for MyApp {
    type AppSettings = MyAppKVSettings;
    type EndpointAppSettings = ();
    type EndpointContext = ();
    type IngressConnectionContext = MyAppIngressConnectionContext;
    type RequestContext = ();
    type IpTunnelContext = ();
    type DnsCacheItem = ();

}
   
#[async_trait]
impl OxyApp for MyApp {
    fn name() -&amp;gt; &amp;amp;'static str {
        "My app"
    }

    fn version() -&amp;gt; &amp;amp;'static str {
        env!("CARGO_PKG_VERSION")
    }

    fn description() -&amp;gt; &amp;amp;'static str {
        "This is an example of Oxy application"
    }

    async fn start(
        settings: ServerSettings&amp;lt;MyAppSettings, ()&amp;gt;
    ) -&amp;gt; anyhow::Result&amp;lt;Hooks&amp;lt;Self&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {
        // Here the application initializes various hooks, with each
        // hook being a trait implementation containing multiple
        // optional callbacks invoked during the lifecycle of the
        // traffic processing.
        let ingress_hook = create_ingress_hook(&amp;amp;settings);
        let egress_hook = create_egress_hook(&amp;amp;settings);
        let tunnel_hook = create_tunnel_hook(&amp;amp;settings);
        let http_request_hook = create_http_request_hook(&amp;amp;settings);
        let ip_flow_hook = create_ip_flow_hook(&amp;amp;settings);

        Ok(Hooks {
            ingress: Some(ingress_hook),
            egress: Some(egress_hook),
            tunnel: Some(tunnel_hook),
            http_request: Some(http_request_hook),
            ip_flow: Some(ip_flow_hook),
            ..Default::default()
        })
    }
}

// The entry point of the application
fn main() -&amp;gt; OxyResult&amp;lt;()&amp;gt; {
    oxy::bootstrap::&amp;lt;MyApp&amp;gt;()
}&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxy leverages the safety and performance benefits of Rust as its implementation language. At Cloudflare, Rust has emerged as a popular choice for new product development, and there are ongoing efforts to migrate some of the existing products to the language as well.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rust offers memory and concurrency safety through its ownership and borrowing system, preventing issues like null pointers and data races. This safety is achieved without sacrificing performance, as Rust provides low-level control and the ability to write code with minimal runtime overhead. Rust's balance of safety and performance has made it popular for building safe performance-critical applications, like proxies.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We intentionally tried to stand on the shoulders of the giants with this project and avoid reinventing the wheel. Oxy heavily relies on open-source dependencies, with hyper and tokio being the backbone of the framework. Our philosophy is that we should pull from existing solutions as much as we can, allowing for faster iteration, but also use widely battle-tested code. If something doesn't work for us, we try to collaborate with maintainers and contribute back our fixes and improvements. In fact, we now have two team members who are core team members of tokio and hyper projects.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Even though Oxy is a proprietary project, we try to give back some love to the open-source community without which the project wouldnât be possible by open-sourcing some of the building blocks such as https://github.com/cloudflare/boring and https://github.com/cloudflare/quiche.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The road to implementation&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At the beginning of our journey, we set out to implement a proof-of-concept Â for an HTTP firewall using Rust for what would eventually become Zero Trust Gateway product. This project was originally part of the WARP service repository. However, as the PoC rapidly advanced, it became clear that it needed to be separated into its own Gateway proxy for both technical and operational reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Later on, when tasked with implementing a relay proxy for iCloud Private Relay, we saw the opportunity to reuse much of the code from the Gateway proxy. The Gateway project could also benefit from the HTTP/3 support that was being added for the Private Relay project. In fact, early iterations of the relay service were forks of the Gateway server.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It was then that we realized we could extract common elements from both projects to create a new framework, Oxy. The history of Oxy can be traced back to its origins in the commit history of the Gateway and Private Relay projects, up until its separation as a standalone framework.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Since our inception, we have leveraged the power of Oxy to efficiently roll out multiple projects that would have required a significant amount of time and effort without it. Our iterative development approach has been a strength of the project, as we have been able to identify common, reusable components through hands-on testing and implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our small core team is supplemented by internal contributors from across the company, ensuring that the best subject-matter experts are working on the relevant parts of the project. This contribution model also allows us to shape the framework's API to meet the functional and ergonomic needs of its users, while the core team ensures that the project stays on track.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Although Pingora, another proxy server developed by us in Rust, shares some similarities with Oxy, it was intentionally designed as a separate proxy server with a different objective. Pingora was created to serve traffic from millions of our clientâs upstream servers, including those with ancient and unusual configurations. Non-UTF 8 URLs or TLS settings that are not supported by most TLS libraries being just a few such quirks among many others. This focus on handling technically challenging unusual configurations sets Pingora apart from other proxy servers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The concept of Pingora came about during the same period when we were beginning to develop Oxy, and we initially considered merging the two projects. However, we quickly realized that their objectives were too different to do that. Pingora is specifically designed to establish Cloudflareâs HTTP connectivity with the Internet, even in its most technically obscure corners. On the other hand, Oxy is a multipurpose platform that supports a wide variety of communication protocols and aims to provide a simple way to develop high-performance proxy applications with business logic.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxy is a proxy framework that we have developed to meet the demanding needs of modern services. It has been designed Â to provide a flexible and scalable solution that can be adapted to meet the unique requirements of each project and by leveraging the power of Rust, we made it both safe and fast.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Looking forward, Oxy is poised to play one of the critical roles in our company's larger effort to modernize and improve our architecture. It provides a solid block in foundation on which we can keep building the better Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As the framework continues to evolve and grow, we remain committed to our iterative approach to development, constantly seeking out new opportunities to reuse existing solutions and improve our codebase. This collaborative, community-driven approach has already yielded impressive results, and we are confident that it will continue to drive the future success of Oxy.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for more tech savvy blog posts on the subject!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/introducing-oxy/"/><published>2025-11-03T03:13:46+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45796351</id><title>ECL Runs Maxima in a Browser</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:10.238732+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6673f6864c066aa3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 27 Jan 2025 27 Jan '25 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 4:06 p.m. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thought you would be interested to know that Marius Gerbershagen has used ecl to compile Maxima to wasm to run in a browser. I believe it's a pretty complete implementation with fancy TeX display of formulas and nice graphics via gnuplot compiled to wasm. See it at http://maxima-on-wasm.pages.dev/ -- Ray&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 280 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Age (days ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 280 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Last active (days ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 0 comments &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 1 participants &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;participants (1)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Raymond Toy&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://mailman3.common-lisp.net/hyperkitty/list/ecl-devel@common-lisp.net/thread/T64S5EMVV6WHDPKWZ3AQHEPO3EQE2K5M/"/><published>2025-11-03T06:21:20+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45796421</id><title>First recording of a dying human brain shows waves similar to memory flashbacks</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:10.111573+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="315792a5e8f2cdea"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;First-ever recording of a dying human brain shows waves similar to memory flashbacks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Imagine reliving your entire life in the space of seconds. Like a flash of lightning, you are outside of your body, watching memorable moments you lived through. This process, known as “life recall,” can be similar to what it is like to have a near-death experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What happens inside your brain during these experiences and after death are questions that have puzzled neuroscientists for centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, a new study from Dr. Ajmal Zemmar of the University of Louisville and colleagues throughout the world, “Enhanced Interplay of Neuronal Coherence and Coupling in the Dying Human Brain,” published in Frontiers in Aging Neuroscience, suggests that your brain may remain active and coordinated during and even after the transition to death, and be programmed to orchestrate the whole ordeal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When an 87-year-old patient developed epilepsy, Dr. Raul Vicente of the University of Tartu, Estonia, and colleagues used continuous electroencephalography to detect the seizures and treat the patient. During these recordings, the patient had a heart attack and passed away.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This unexpected event allowed the scientists to record the activity of a dying human brain for the first time ever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What did they find?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We measured 900 seconds of brain activity around the time of death and set a specific focus to investigate what happened in the 30 seconds before and after the heart stopped beating,” said Zemmar, a neurosurgeon at the University of Louisville, who organized the study.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Just before and after the heart stopped working, we saw changes in a specific band of neural oscillations, so-called gamma oscillations, but also in others such as delta, theta, alpha and beta oscillations.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brain oscillations are more commonly known as brain waves. They are patterns of rhythmic brain activity normally present in living human brains. The different types of oscillations, including gamma, are involved in high-cognitive functions, such as concentrating, dreaming, meditation, memory retrieval, information processing and conscious perception, just like those associated with memory flashbacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Through generating brain oscillations involved in memory retrieval, the brain may be playing a last recall of important life events just before we die, similar to the ones reported in near-death experiences,” Zemmar speculated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The findings question what we believe we know about the moment of death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“These findings challenge our understanding of when exactly life ends and generate important subsequent questions, such as those related to the timing of organ donation,” Zemmar said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Every human alive has at some point an encounter when they lose a loved one and every one of us someday will go death themselves, so the interest obviously has been there. I've lost my grandfather. I've lost my grandmother with whom I was very, very close,” Zemmar said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“And you ask yourself, what does the brain do? As a Ph.D. in neuroscience and a neurosurgeon, you think about these things.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What do the findings tell us?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“You could probably categorize it in in three different categories to say what can we take from this,” Zemmar said. “One is scientific, one is metaphysical and philosophical and one is spiritual.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Scientifically, it's very difficult to interpret the data because the brain had suffered bleeding, seizures, swelling – and then it's just one case. So we can't make very big assumptions and claims based on this case.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“On the metaphysical side, if you have these things, it is intriguing to speculate to say that these mechanisms – these brain activity patterns that occur when we have memory recall and dreaming and meditative states – they recall just before we go to die. So maybe they're letting us have a replay of life in the last seconds when we die.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“On the spiritual side, I think it is somewhat calming. I face this at times when you have patients that pass away and you talk their families; you have to be the bearer of bad news. Right now, we don't know anything about what happens to their loved one’s brain when they're dying. I think if we know that there is something happening in their brain, that they are remembering nice moments, we can tell these families and it builds a feeling of warmth that in that moment when they are falling, this can help a little bit to catch them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It opens an interesting question to me on when you define death. That plays a big role for questions such as, when do you go ahead with organ donation? When are we dead? When the heart stops beating because the brain keeps going. Should we record EEG activity in addition to EKG to declare death? This is a very, very interesting question for me. When is exactly the time when we die? We may have tapped the door open now to start a discussion about that exact time onset.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://louisville.edu/medicine/news/first-ever-recording-of-a-dying-human-brain-shows-waves-similar-to-memory-flashbacks"/><published>2025-11-03T06:39:13+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45796907</id><title>China intimidated UK university to ditch human rights research, documents show</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:09.884420+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7bb0119d27e1d4ec"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;China intimidated UK university to ditch human rights research, documents show&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;China waged a campaign of harassment and intimidation directed at a UK university to get it to shut down sensitive research into alleged human rights abuses, documents seen by the BBC show.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sheffield Hallam University staff in China were threatened by individuals described by them as being from China's National Security Service who demanded the research being done in Sheffield be halted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And access to the university's websites from China was blocked, impeding its ability to recruit Chinese students, in a campaign of threats and intimidation lasting more than two years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In an internal email from July 2024, university officials said "attempting to retain the business in China and publication of the research are now untenable bedfellows".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the UK government learned of the case, the then Foreign Secretary David Lammy issued a warning to his Chinese counterpart that it would not tolerate attempts to suppress academic freedoms at UK universities, the BBC understands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The issue was also raised with China's most senior education minister.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;China was seeking to halt research by Laura Murphy, professor of human rights and contemporary slavery at Sheffield Hallam, into allegations Uyghur Muslims in the north-western region of Xinjiang were subject to forced labour.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;China has faced accusations – always firmly denied – that it has committed crimes against humanity and possibly genocide against the Uyghur population.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In late 2024, following pressure from the Chinese state and a separate defamation law suit against the university, Sheffield Hallam decided not to publish a final piece of research by Prof Murphy and her team into forced labour.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And in early 2025, university administrators told her that she could "not continue with her research into supply chains and forced labour in China".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She initiated legal action against the university for failing in its duty to protect her academic freedom and she submitted a "subject access request" demanding Sheffield Hallam hand over any relevant internal documents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The documents she obtained showed the university "had negotiated directly with a foreign intelligence service to trade my academic freedom for access to the Chinese student market," she told the BBC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She added: "I'd never seen anything quite so patently explicit about the extent to which a university would go to ensure that they have Chinese student income."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sheffield Hallam has now apologised to Prof Murphy and said she can resume her work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A spokesperson said "the university's decision to not continue with Professor Laura Murphy's research was taken based on our understanding of a complex set of circumstances at the time, including being unable to secure the necessary professional indemnity insurance".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They said the university wished to "make clear our commitment to supporting her research and to securing and promoting freedom of speech and academic freedom within the law".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the general secretary of the University and College Union, Jo Grady, said "it is incredibly worrying that Sheffield Hallam appears to have attempted to silence its own professor on behalf of a foreign government".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She added: "Given the censorship Hallam has seemingly engaged in, it now needs to set out how it will ensure its academics will be supported to research freely and protected from overreach by foreign powers."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A government spokesperson told the BBC "any attempt by a foreign state to intimidate, harass or harm individuals in the UK will not be tolerated, and the government has made this clear to Beijing after learning of this case".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It all began so differently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When, in 2021, Prof Murphy published a major report into Uhygur forced labour in the solar panel industry, the director of the Helena Kennedy Centre (HKC), the department in which her unit was based, wrote to congratulate her.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"This is an exceptional moment in the history of the HKC... we are all exceptionally proud of this body of work which rightly shines light on the blatant abuse of Uyghur tights (sic) in China.. Well done Laura!"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the following months her unit published four reports, including into car parts and cotton for clothing, trying to trace supply chains and highlight where goods reaching western consumers may have been produced with inputs made with forced labour in Xinjiang.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;China denies such practices occur.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chinese Embassy in London told the BBC "the Helena Kennedy Centre at the Sheffield Hallam University has released multiple fake reports on Xinjiang that are seriously flawed".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It has been revealed that some authors of these reports received funding from certain US agencies," the Embassy added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prof Murphy told the BBC she has received funding over the course of her career from the US National Endowment for Humanities for work on slave narratives, the US Department of Justice for work on human trafficking in New Orleans, and more recently from USAID, the US State Department and the UK Foreign Office for her work on China.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chinese Embassy said the allegations of "forced labor" in her reports "cannot withstand basic fact-check".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"While presenting itself as an academic body, the Centre has in practice acted as a vehicle for politicised and disinformation-driven narratives deployed by anti-China forces," the embassy added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The university realised it was coming in for criticism from China as far back as 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An internal university email from August of that year, seen by the BBC, said China's foreign ministry had issued a statement "denouncing us as being in the 'disreputable vanguard of anti-China rhetoric'".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The email said the university had admitted 500 Chinese students in 2018, but numbers had collapsed in the pandemic and had not bounced back like it had in other markets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It expressed concern that the Chinese government's criticisms could result in a "boycott" by prospective students and recruitment agents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, the documents show Sheffield had earned £3.8m in 2021/22 from China and Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later in August 2022 the university's English language testing website used by Chinese students to take tests before coming to Sheffield had been "shut down in China temporarily".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the next two years the pressure escalated dramatically leading university officials to write in an email in May 2024 that "the continuation of the university's scholarly activity with and in China and Hong Kong has been placed at risk because of the research activities, led by Professor Laura Murphy, in relation to alleged persecution of Uyghur Muslims in Xinjiang, China".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An internal "risk summary," dated 9 December 2024, detailed what had happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In August 2022, China had blocked access to the university's websites. All email communication from and to the university was disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It meant students in China due to study at Sheffield Hallam were unable to access the enrolment website, arrange their welcome or airport pick up in the UK, or course information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The university said this had "undoubtedly had a negative impact on recruitment" in 23/24, with "anticipated further decline in 24/25".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And, in 2024, the intimidation began.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Things in Beijing have kicked off," an internal email from 18 April 2024 said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The risk summary detailed that "three officers of the National Security Service" visited Sheffield Hallam's office in China.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A local staff member was "questioned for two hours regarding the HKC research and future publications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The tone was threatening and message to cease the research activity was made clear."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At another visit, security officers said the internet issues were because the Uyghur research was available on the university website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, in September 2024, the document states "a decision by the university not to publish a final phase of the research on forced labour in China was communicated to the National Security Service .. immediately relations improved and the threat to staff wellbeing appears to be removed".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sheffield Hallam says these internal communications need to be seen in context and do not represent university policy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Complicating things for Sheffield Hallam had been a report by its Forced Labour Lab published December 2023 into clothing supply chains connected to Xinjiang.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smart Shirts Ltd, a Hong Kong supplier of garments with customers in the UK, brought a claim for libel, alleging it had been defamed as its name was included.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A preliminary ruling at the High Court in London in December 2024 found that report had been "defamatory".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A full trial in that case is yet to take place at which Sheffield Hallam will be able to put forward its defence to the company's claim, but the university was told by its insurers that "any defamation, libel or slander" claims linked to its entire Social and Economic Research Institute were no longer covered.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professor Murphy had, meanwhile, built an international profile.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Her work had been cited in the UK parliament, in Canada and in Australia. She had taken a career break in late 2023 to work for the US Department of Homeland Security, helping it with the implementation of their Uyghur Forced Labour Prevention Act.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In her absence, and amid the pressure from China and the lawsuit, Sheffield Hallam decided her unit would close in early 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Despite significant offers of continued funding we have decided it is in our best interests to terminate the research," an email of August 2024 said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It added that by not publishing the final report under the university's auspices it hoped "we can minimise the possibility of any further scrutiny of our operations .. thereby attending to related duty of care issues".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But failing to publish the report was a breach of the terms agreed with the external groups who had agreed to fund the research.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So the university decided to close the unit and not use any outstanding funds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sheffield Hallam said it was normal practice for research groups to stand down at the end of an external contract.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Prof Murphy returned from her career break in early 2025, the university told her of its "decision not to continue with her research into supply chains and forced labour in China due to .. the corporate insurance position .. and our duty of care to colleagues working in both China and the UK".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any other work or public engagements outside the university would also have to be checked for "conflict of interest".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seeking to continue her work, Prof Murphy began her legal action and made a subject access request to the university requiring it to turn over relevant internal documents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"What about the duty of care to me and the duty of care to the rest of my research team?," Prof Murphy told the BBC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"They laid off my entire research team. Sent them away. They sent back all of our research funding, and they shuttered the entire programme without regard for the people who worked with us on that project, so many of them Uyghur folks."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She added: "As long as the university system in the UK is so wildly underfunded as it is now, universities will be vulnerable to attacks like this."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After receiving her apology from the university and a pledge to protect her academic freedom, she is not currently pursuing her legal action.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Her case had been built on the Higher Education (Freedom of Speech) Act 2023, which places on universities a duty to promote freedom of speech and academic freedom for their staff.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Her solicitors, Leigh Day, had argued that a lack of insurance and "unspecified" concerns about staff safety do not provide universities carte blanche to restrict freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The law firm believes refusing to authorise any research on a particular country would be unlawful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sheffield Hallam's spokesperson said: "For the avoidance of doubt, the decision was not based on commercial interests in China.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Regardless, China is not a significant international student market for the university."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The university only enrolled 73 students from China in 2024/25.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chinese Embassy said "there are over 200,000 Chinese students in the UK, making China the largest source of international students in the UK," adding "educational cooperation has become a driving force in bilateral ties".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Baroness Helena Kennedy KC, patron of the centre that bears her name, said UK universities were "vulnerable" to pressure from China because "bringing in Chinese students is one of the ways of dealing with the financial crises that universities are facing".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"If we see limitations being made on the kind of research that goes on in these universities, I think we should be alarmed," added the Labour peer, who has herself been sanctioned by China for speaking out about issues related to Xinjiang.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sign up for our Politics Essential newsletter to keep up with the inner workings of Westminster and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cq50j5vwny6o"/><published>2025-11-03T08:15:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45797242</id><title>Tiny electric motor outperforms record holder by 40%</title><updated>2025-11-03T10:44:09.687445+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b5e8d0560977a510"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Tiny electric motor is as powerful as four Tesla motors put together and outperforms record holder by 40%&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Published on Nov 02, 2025 at 1:48 AM (UTC+4)&lt;lb/&gt; by Jason Fan&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last updated on Oct 29, 2025 at 10:11 PM (UTC+4)&lt;lb/&gt; Edited by Mason Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UK-based YASA has just built a tiny electric motor that makes Tesla motors look like slackers, and this invention could potentially reshape the future of EVs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company has unveiled a new prototype that’s breaking records for power and performance density.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s smaller and lighter than traditional motors, yet it’s somehow more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps the best part is that it’s a fully functional motor, rather than some lab-only concept.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SBX CARS – View live supercar auctions powered by Supercar Blondie&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;This tiny electric motor can produce more than 1,000 horsepower&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new YASA axial flux motor weighs just 28 pounds, or about the same as a small dog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, it delivers a jaw-dropping 750 kilowatts of power, which is the equivalent of 1,005 horsepower.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s about the same as two Tesla Model 3 Performance cars combined, or four individual Tesla motors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In comparison, the previous record holder, which was also produced by the same company, weighed 28.8 pounds, and achieved a peak power of 550 kilowatts (737 horsepower).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This makes the current electric motor 40 percent better than the previous edition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It can also sustain between 350 and 400 kilowatts (469–536 horsepower) continuously, meaning it’s not just built for short bursts, as it can deliver massive power all day long.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to YASA, this is achieved without using exotic or expensive materials, so the design could actually be scalable once the demand kicks in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This record demonstrates what makes YASA unique,” said CEO Joerg Miska.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“With three times the performance density of today’s leading radial flux motors, we’re redefining what’s possible in electric motor design.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In simpler terms, the company has made a motor that is small, light, and ridiculously powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;YASA already produces motors for many expensive cars&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s a big deal for EVs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lighter motor means a lighter car, which means better efficiency, faster acceleration, and longer range from the same battery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For EVs, every pound matters, so saving weight without compromising performance could be a gamechanger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;YASA, which is a wholly owned subsidiary of Mercedes-Benz, already produces motors that power some of the world’s fastest and most expensive cars.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These include the Mercedes-AMG GT XX concept, and the Ferrari 296 GTB.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps as production scales and prices drop, these ultra-efficient motors could find their way into everyday EVs, like the Nissan Leaf EV, which is the cheapest EV in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For now, the company’s tiny electric motor proves that big things can come in small packages, and that performance need not be sacrificed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DISCOVER SBX CARS: The global premium car auction platform powered by Supercar Blondie&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Fan is an experienced content creator who graduated from Nanyang Technological University in Singapore with a degree in communications. He then relocated to Australia during a millennial mid-life crisis. A fan of luxury travel and high-performance machines, he politely thanks chatbots just in case the AI apocalypse ever arrives. Jason covers a wide variety of topics, with a special focus on technology, planes and luxury.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://supercarblondie.com/electric-motor-yasa-more-powerful-tesla-mercedes/"/><published>2025-11-03T09:20:01+00:00</published></entry></feed>