<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:19.857522+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45617948</id><title>Show HN: I'm making a detective game built on Wikipedia</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:26.579026+00:00</updated><link href="https://detective.wiki/"/><published>2025-10-17T15:34:04+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45621557</id><title>Code from MIT's 1986 SICP video lectures</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:26.117868+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a5619a2afc97f391"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT lectures on Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs, as taught in 1986 by Gerald Sussman and Harold Abelson, are available online in youtube and MIT OCW's website. The videos are available in 240p/360p: very poor quality for visualizing the code in the slides. In addition to that, the camera won't fixate on the board for long, making it extremely difficult to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project's intent is to make the lectures' code and content readable (unlike the slide below) and available in digital format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried to maintain consistency of notation, comments and indentation throughout the lectures. Much of the original indentation on the slides was maintained, except for when I was able to improve readability by changing it. Lecture breaks are also noted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every &lt;code&gt;SLIDE&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;TERMINAL&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;BOARD&lt;/code&gt; content is marked with the time of appearance. E.g.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;;# SLIDE 0:00:00
    ... slide content
;# END SLIDE
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I have added comments and remarks throughout the code to help comprehension.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Though all files have extension .scm, their content represent a literal transcription of the slides, some of which isn't code. They're expected to fail to compile in all Scheme interpreters.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I have fixed the code on a few, rare occasions. In all of them I've noted the correction using a colon followed by an exclamation mark. Notice that ';!' was also used, once or twice, in the lecture slides.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;it's clearly readable&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;it's not code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;its content isn't "textable"&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Standardize syntax and style across the transcription files.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/felipap/sicp-code"/><published>2025-10-17T20:18:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45623509</id><title>Results from blood test for 50 cancers</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:25.873392+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bfeba1279a839e42"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Exciting results from blood test for 50 cancers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A blood test for more than 50 types of cancer could help speed up diagnosis, according to a new study.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Results of a trial in North America show that the test was able to identify a wide range of cancers, of which three-quarters don't have any form of screening programme.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More than half the cancers were detected at an early stage, where they are easier to treat and potentially curable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Galleri test, made by American pharmaceutical firm Grail, can detect fragments of cancerous DNA that have broken off a tumour and are circulating in the blood. It is currently being trialled by the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trial followed 25,000 adults from the US and Canada over a year, with nearly one in 100 getting a positive result. For 62% of these cases, cancer was later confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lead researcher Dr Nima Nabavizadeh, associate professor of radiation medicine at Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University, said the data showed that the test could "fundamentally change" their approach to cancer screening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He explained that it could help detect many types of cancer "earlier, when the chance of successful treatment or even cure are the greatest".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The test correctly ruled out cancer in over 99% of those who tested negative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When combined with breast, bowel, lung and cervical screening it increased the number of cancers detected overall seven-fold.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Crucially, three-quarters of cancers detected were those which have no screening programme such as ovarian, liver, stomach, bladder and pancreatic cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The blood test correctly identified the origin of the cancer in nine out of 10 cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These impressive results suggest the blood test could eventually have a major role to play in diagnosing cancer earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But scientists not involved in the research say more evidence is needed to show whether the blood test reduces deaths from cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clare Turnbull, professor of translational cancer genetics at The Institute of Cancer Research, London, said: "Data from randomised studies, with mortality as an endpoint, will be absolutely essential to establish whether seemingly earlier-stage detection by Galleri translates into benefits in mortality."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The topline results are to be released at the European Society for Medical Oncology congress in Berlin on Saturday, but the full details have yet to be published in a peer-reviewed journal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Much will depend on the results of a three-year trial involving 140,000 NHS patients in England, which will be published next year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The NHS has previously said that if the results are successful, it would extend the tests to a further one million people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sir Harpal Kumar, president of biopharma at Grail called the results "very compelling".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking to BBC Radio 4's Today programme, he said: "The vast majority of people who die from cancer do so because we find their cancers too late."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many cancers are found when they are "already very advanced" he added, explaining that the aim is to "shift to earlier detection, when we have the chance to use treatments that are much more effective and potentially curative".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Naser Turabi of Cancer Research UK cautioned that further research is needed to "avoid overdiagnosing cancers that may not have caused harm".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The UK National Screening Committee will "play a critical role in reviewing the evidence and determining whether these tests should be adopted by the NHS," he added.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c205g21n1zzo"/><published>2025-10-17T23:54:40+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45632429</id><title>A laser pointer at 2B FPS [video]</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:25.091427+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7055905545553646"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Press Copyright Contact us Creators Advertise Developers Terms Privacy Policy &amp;amp; Safety How YouTube works Test new features NFL Sunday Ticket © 2025 Google LLC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o4TdHrMi6do"/><published>2025-10-19T06:42:19+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45640226</id><title>Space Elevator</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:24.870160+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://neal.fun/space-elevator/"/><published>2025-10-20T04:42:08+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45640594</id><title>DeepSeek OCR</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:24.428974+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d0978f309aa0d982"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;📥 Model Download | 📄 Paper Link | 📄 Arxiv Paper Link |&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Explore the boundaries of visual-text compression.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;[2025/10/20]🚀🚀🚀 We release DeepSeek-OCR, a model to investigate the role of vision encoders from an LLM-centric viewpoint.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our environment is cuda11.8+torch2.6.0.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clone this repository and navigate to the DeepSeek-OCR folder&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-OCR.git&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Conda&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;conda create -n deepseek-ocr python=3.12.9 -y
conda activate deepseek-ocr&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Packages&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;download the vllm-0.8.5 whl&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pip install torch==2.6.0 torchvision==0.21.0 torchaudio==2.6.0 --index-url https://download.pytorch.org/whl/cu118
pip install vllm-0.8.5+cu118-cp38-abi3-manylinux1_x86_64.whl
pip install -r requirements.txt
pip install flash-attn==2.7.3 --no-build-isolation&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: if you want vLLM and transformers codes to run in the same environment, you don't need to worry about this installation error like: vllm 0.8.5+cu118 requires transformers&amp;gt;=4.51.1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;VLLM:&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note: change the INPUT_PATH/OUTPUT_PATH and other settings in the DeepSeek-OCR-master/DeepSeek-OCR-vllm/config.py&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cd DeepSeek-OCR-master/DeepSeek-OCR-vllm&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;image: streaming output&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;python run_dpsk_ocr_image.py&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pdf: concurrency ~2500tokens/s(an A100-40G)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;python run_dpsk_ocr_pdf.py&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;batch eval for benchmarks&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;python run_dpsk_ocr_eval_batch.py&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Transformers&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from transformers import AutoModel, AutoTokenizer
import torch
import os
os.environ["CUDA_VISIBLE_DEVICES"] = '0'
model_name = 'deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-OCR'

tokenizer = AutoTokenizer.from_pretrained(model_name, trust_remote_code=True)
model = AutoModel.from_pretrained(model_name, _attn_implementation='flash_attention_2', trust_remote_code=True, use_safetensors=True)
model = model.eval().cuda().to(torch.bfloat16)

# prompt = "&amp;lt;image&amp;gt;\nFree OCR. "
prompt = "&amp;lt;image&amp;gt;\n&amp;lt;|grounding|&amp;gt;Convert the document to markdown. "
image_file = 'your_image.jpg'
output_path = 'your/output/dir'

res = model.infer(tokenizer, prompt=prompt, image_file=image_file, output_path = output_path, base_size = 1024, image_size = 640, crop_mode=True, save_results = True, test_compress = True)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;or you can&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cd DeepSeek-OCR-master/DeepSeek-OCR-hf
python run_dpsk_ocr.py&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The current open-source model supports the following modes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Native resolution: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Tiny: 512×512 （64 vision tokens）✅&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Small: 640×640 （100 vision tokens）✅&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Base: 1024×1024 （256 vision tokens）✅&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Large: 1280×1280 （400 vision tokens）✅&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dynamic resolution &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Gundam: n×640×640 + 1×1024×1024 ✅&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# document: &amp;lt;image&amp;gt;\n&amp;lt;|grounding|&amp;gt;Convert the document to markdown.
# other image: &amp;lt;image&amp;gt;\n&amp;lt;|grounding|&amp;gt;OCR this image.
# without layouts: &amp;lt;image&amp;gt;\nFree OCR.
# figures in document: &amp;lt;image&amp;gt;\nParse the figure.
# general: &amp;lt;image&amp;gt;\nDescribe this image in detail.
# rec: &amp;lt;image&amp;gt;\nLocate &amp;lt;|ref|&amp;gt;xxxx&amp;lt;|/ref|&amp;gt; in the image.
# '先天下之忧而忧'&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We would like to thank Vary, GOT-OCR2.0, MinerU, PaddleOCR, OneChart, Slow Perception for their valuable models and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also appreciate the benchmarks: Fox, OminiDocBench.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;coming soon！&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-OCR"/><published>2025-10-20T06:26:33+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45640838</id><title>AWS multiple services outage in us-east-1</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:24.119864+00:00</updated><link href="https://health.aws.amazon.com/health/status?ts=20251020"/><published>2025-10-20T07:22:28+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45643163</id><title>Alibaba Cloud says it cut Nvidia AI GPU use by 82% with new pooling system</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:23.937052+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="799894bc8f16d6d1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Alibaba Cloud says it cut Nvidia AI GPU use by 82% with new pooling system— up to 9x increase in output lets 213 GPUs perform like 1,192&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A paper presented at SOSP 2025 details how token-level scheduling helped one GPU serve multiple LLMs, reducing demand from 1,192 to 213 H20s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alibaba Cloud claims its new Aegaeon pooling system reduces the number of Nvidia GPUs required to serve large language models by 82% during a multi-month beta test inside its Model Studio marketplace. The result, published in a peer-reviewed paper presented at the 2025 ACM Symposium on Operating Systems (SOSP) in Seoul, suggests that cloud providers may be able to extract significantly more inference capacity from existing silicon, especially in constrained markets like China, where the supply of Nvidia's latest H20s remains limited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike training-time breakthroughs that chase model quality or speed, Aegaeon is an inference-time scheduler designed to maximize GPU utilization across many models with bursty or unpredictable demand. Instead of pinning one accelerator to one model, Aegaeon virtualizes GPU access at the token level, allowing it to schedule tiny slices of work across a shared pool. This means one H20 could serve several different models simultaneously, with system-wide “goodput” — a measure of effective output — rising by as much as nine times compared to older serverless systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The system was tested in production over several months, according to the paper, which lists authors from both Peking University and Alibaba’s infrastructure division, including CTO Jingren Zhou. During that window, the number of GPUs needed to support dozens of different LLMs — ranging in size up to 72 billion parameters — fell from 1,192 to just 213.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the paper does not break down which models contributed most to the savings, reporting by the South China Morning Post says the tests were conducted using Nvidia’s H20, one of the few accelerators still legally available to Chinese buyers under current U.S. export controls.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alibaba says the gains came from two main techniques: Packing multiple models per GPU, and using a token-level autoscaler to dynamically allocate compute as output is generated, rather than reserving resources at the request level. In benchmarks, Aegaeon beat the goodput of ServerlessLLM and MuxServe by margins ranging from 1.5 times to 9 times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether those savings translate outside Alibaba’s stack remains to be seen. Alibaba Cloud’s paper does not specify the exact network fabric used in the beta test, but we know the company offers its own eRDMA elastic RDMA network and has a record of building highly‑integrated GPU serving stacks, suggesting the results may depend on an optimized, vertically integrated environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless, the result is likely to attract interest from other hyperscalers looking to stretch scarce accelerator fleets as inference demand continues to spike.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get Tom's Hardware's best news and in-depth reviews, straight to your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow Tom's Hardware on Google News, or add us as a preferred source, to get our latest news, analysis, &amp;amp; reviews in your feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Luke James is a freelance writer and journalist. Although his background is in legal, he has a personal interest in all things tech, especially hardware and microelectronics, and anything regulatory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;zsydeepsky&lt;/header&gt;Reply&lt;quote/&gt;There are plenty of H20s currently selling on China's used e-market.pug_s said:Does that mean that there will be used H20's in the Chinese market?&lt;lb/&gt;Just checked, half of them have their price dropped(3-19%).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.tomshardware.com/tech-industry/semiconductors/alibaba-says-new-pooling-system-cut-nvidia-gpu-use-by-82-percent"/><published>2025-10-20T12:31:22+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45644328</id><title>BERT is just a single text diffusion step</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:23.801873+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="35106edd82bc1c52"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A while back, Google DeepMind unveiled Gemini Diffusion, an experimental language model that generates text using diffusion. Unlike traditional GPT-style models that generate one word at a time, Gemini Diffusion creates whole blocks of text by refining random noise step-by-step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I read the paper Large Language Diffusion Models and was surprised to find that discrete language diffusion is just a generalization of masked language modeling (MLM), something we’ve been doing since 2018. The first thought I had was, “can we finetune a BERT-like model to do text generation?” I decided to try a quick proof of concept out of curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;NOTE: After I wrote the article I stumbled upon the paper DiffusionBERT which does essentially the same thing but with more rigorous testing! Check it out if this post interested you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Short History of Transformers#&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The original Transformer architecture, introduced in 2017, was an encoder-decoder model. In 2018, researchers realized that the encoder and decoder components of the model could be separated (with the advent of BERT and GPT), and two distinct families of models were created:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Encoder-only models (BERT-style, bidirectional)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Encoder models used masked language modeling (MLM) as a training objective: randomly mask out a subset of tokens of each input and train the encoder to reconstruct the missing tokens (fill in the blanks). The model sees the entire (partially masked) context at once and learns bidirectional representations. This architecture excelled at tasks requiring a full‐sentence (or paragraph) representation (e.g., classification and retrieval).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Decoder-only models (GPT-style, autoregressive)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decoder models used next‐token prediction as a training objective: at each position $t$, predict the token at position $t + 1$ given all tokens up to $t$ as context. Only the left context is used to predict future values (unidirectional). This architecture excelled at generative tasks where you produce text one token at a time, such as open‐ended generation, summarization, and translation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originally, BERT saw immediate use in tasks such as classification, whereas GPT-style models didn’t become popular until later (due to initial limited capabilities). Eventually, the generation capabilities of autoregressive (decoder) transformers vastly improved. The general training objective of “next token prediction” means a much larger space of use cases when compared to encoder models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Discrete Language Diffusion Models#&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Diffusion models were first popularized in image generation. In image generation, diffusion models gradually add Gaussian noise to an image (forward process) and then train a neural network to iteratively denoise it (reverse process). A high‐level summary of continuous diffusion with images is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Forward process: Start from a clean image x₀, then add small amounts of (usually Gaussian) noise at each timestep until you end up with near‐pure noise.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reverse process: Train a model (often a U‐Net) to predict the noise at each timestep, gradually recovering the original image in discrete denoising steps.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applying this idea to language means we need a way to add noise to text and then remove it in stages. The simplest way to do this is a masking‐based noise process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Forward (masking) process:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;At timestep t = 0, you have a fully uncorrupted text sequence.&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;At each subsequent timestep t &amp;gt; 0, randomly replace a fraction of tokens with a special &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;token according to a pre‐defined schedule (e.g., gradually increasing the masked proportion from 0% to 100%).&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;By the final timestep T, the entire sequence may be masked (all tokens are &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Reverse (denoising) process:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Train a model (often a standard Transformer encoder) to predict the original token IDs given a partially masked sequence at timestep t.&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;This is akin to performing masked language modeling at varying mask rates: at early timesteps, only a few tokens are masked (easy to predict); at later timesteps, many tokens are masked (harder).&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;By chaining together predictions from high‐mask‐rate back down to zero, you can recover (or generate) a full sequence.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this discrete text diffusion framework, the model learns a likelihood bound on the data distribution by optimizing a sum of denoising losses over all timesteps, rather than a single MLM objective at a fixed mask probability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we can see, BERT’s masked language modeling objective is the same training objective as text diffusion, but just for a subset of masking rates. By introducing variable masking rates (from 0 to 1) and a scheduled sequence of denoising steps (inspired by diffusion theory), we can transform BERT’s masked language modeling objective into a full generative procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;RoBERTa Diffusion#&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2019, RoBERTa was released. It was essentially just an enhancement of the original BERT model, with better hyperparameters, data training size, and a more simple training objective (MLM only, removed next sentence prediction).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here we use the HuggingFace &lt;code&gt;transformers&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dataset&lt;/code&gt; libraries to pull in the original RoBERTa weights, tokenizer, and the Trainer class to easily finetune the model on the WikiText dataset.
The main code (full code here) looks like this below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Load and tokenize dataset and instantiate the model
dataset = load_dataset("wikitext", "wikitext-2-raw-v1")
tokenizer = RobertaTokenizerFast.from_pretrained("roberta-base")
model = RobertaForMaskedLM.from_pretrained("roberta-base")

# Create the training args and Trainer instance
training_args = TrainingArguments(
    output_dir="finetuned-roberta-diffusion",
    overwrite_output_dir=True,
    num_train_epochs=NUM_EPOCHS,
    per_device_train_batch_size=BATCH_SIZE,
    save_strategy="epoch",
    save_total_limit=1,
    logging_steps=200,
)

trainer = Trainer(
    model=model,
    args=training_args,
    train_dataset=tokenized["train"],
    eval_dataset=tokenized["validation"],
    data_collator=diffusion_collator, # custom implementation
    tokenizer=tokenizer,
)

# Train &amp;amp; save
trainer.train()
trainer.save_model("finetuned-roberta-diffusion")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently we have 10 diffusion steps, so we randomly sample a percentage $p$ out of &lt;code&gt;mask_probs&lt;/code&gt; (1.0, 0.9, 0.9, &amp;amp;mldr;, 0.1) and mask that percent of the tokens each batch.
The custom &lt;code&gt;diffusion_collator&lt;/code&gt; function (see code here) samples one mask-probability &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;mask_probs&lt;/code&gt; per batch and sets each token to &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; probability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be able to condition the generation on a “prompt”, we currently never mask the first 16 tokens. That means that during training, each step will always have the first 16 tokens as context for generation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simplified code for the &lt;code&gt;diffusion_collator&lt;/code&gt; looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;  def diffusion_collator(examples):
      batch = tokenizer.pad(examples, return_tensors="pt")

      # Randomly select masking probability for this batch
      mask_prob = random.choice([1.0, 0.9, 0.8, 0.7, 0.6, 0.5, 0.4, 0.3, 0.2, 0.1])

      # Never mask the first PREFIX_LEN tokens (preserved context)
      maskable_positions = batch.input_ids[:, PREFIX_LEN:]

      # Create random mask for the chosen probability
      mask = torch.rand(maskable_positions.shape) &amp;lt; mask_prob

      # Apply masking
      batch.input_ids[:, PREFIX_LEN:][mask] = tokenizer.mask_token_id
      batch.labels = batch.input_ids.clone()

      return batch&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For inference, we start with an input which is a tensor of size 256 (since we are generating blocks of 256 tokens). The first 16 positions are the token ids that correspond to the prompt, and the last 240 are just &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tokens. We iterate through the denoising schedule and each step, we generate a prediction and then remask the sequence again. The process looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Step 0: [PREFIX] &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; ...     (100% masked)
Step 1: [PREFIX] will &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; over &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; control ...        (90% masked)
Step 2: [PREFIX] will begin &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; greater control ...      (80% masked)
...
Step 10: [PREFIX] will begin to assert greater control ...  (0% masked - DONE)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simplified code for generation looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Generate text through iterative denoising
for step, mask_prob in enumerate(mask_probs):
    # Forward pass: predict masked tokens
    with torch.no_grad():
        outputs = model(input_ids=input_ids, attention_mask=attention_mask)
        predictions = outputs.logits  # shape: (1, MAX_LEN, vocab_size)

    # For each masked position, sample from top-k/top-p filtered distribution
    for pos in range(PREFIX_LEN, MAX_LEN):
        if input_ids[0, pos] == tokenizer.mask_token_id:
            logits = predictions[0, pos, :]
            # Apply top-k and top-p filtering
            filtered_logits = top_k_top_p_filtering(logits, top_k=TOP_K, top_p=TOP_P)
            probs = F.softmax(filtered_logits, dim=-1)
            # Sample token
            sampled_token = torch.multinomial(probs, 1)
            input_ids[0, pos] = sampled_token

    # Re-mask a portion of non-prefix tokens for next iteration
    if mask_prob &amp;gt; 0:
        mask_indices = torch.rand(MAX_LEN - PREFIX_LEN) &amp;lt; mask_prob
        input_ids[0, PREFIX_LEN:][mask_indices] = tokenizer.mask_token_id&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is an example output generation of the fine-tuned model after training on an H200 for 30 minutes (the first line is the initial prompt):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Following their victory in the French and Indian War, Britain began to assert
greater...

...dominion over Europe beginning about the early 19th. There conflict took
place on the island, between British and Irish Ireland. British officials 
administered British Ireland, a Celtic empire under the control of the Irish 
nationalist authorities, defined as a dominion of Britain. As the newly Fortic 
states acquired independent and powerful status, many former English colonies
played their part in this new, British @-@ controlled colonial system. Following
this period the Non @-@ Parliamentaryist Party won its influence in Britain in 
1890, led by the support of settlers from the Irish colonies. Looking inwards, 
Sinclair, Lewis questioned, and debated the need to describe " The New Britain "&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The output looks surprisingly coherent! Most of the quirks present are actually just quirks from the formatting of WikiText (spaces around punctuation &lt;code&gt;"&lt;/code&gt;, turning hyphens &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt; into &lt;code&gt;@-@&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below is a comparison between our diffusion model and GPT-2:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We see GPT-2’s output is more coherent and slightly faster (~9 seconds vs ~13) but I’m pleasantly surprised with how good my simple implementation was. It is a good proof of concept, and with new approaches like AR-Diffusion and Skip-Step Diffusion (and a more optimized implementation), the quality and speed can be drastically improved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion#&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve seen that masked language models like RoBERTa, originally designed for fill-in-the-blank tasks, can be repurposed into fully generative engines by interpreting variable-rate masking as a discrete diffusion process. By gradually corrupting text with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tokens and training the model to iteratively denoise at increasing mask intensities, we effectively turn the standard MLM objective into a step-by-step generation procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even without architectural changes, a fine-tuned RoBERTa can generate coherent looking text after slightly modifying the training objective, validating the idea that BERT-style models are essentially just text diffusion models trained on one masking rate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nathan.rs/posts/roberta-diffusion/"/><published>2025-10-20T14:31:16+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45645120</id><title>Show HN: I created a cross-platform GUI for the JJ VCS (Git compatible)</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:23.666558+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://judojj.com"/><published>2025-10-20T15:35:19+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45645349</id><title>Production RAG: what I learned from processing 5M+ documents</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:23.325791+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9bf95f134d9a6771"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've spent the last 8 months in the RAG trenches, I want to share what actually worked vs. wasted our time. We built RAG for Usul AI (9M pages) and an unnamed legal AI enterprise (4M pages).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Langchain + Llamaindex&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We started out with youtube tutorials. First Langchain → Llamaindex. Got to a working prototype in a couple of days and were optimistic with the progress. We run tests on subset of the data (100 documents) and the results looked great. We spent the next few days running the pipeline on the production dataset and got everything working in a week — incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Except it wasn't, the results were subpar and only the end users could tell. We spent the following few months rewriting pieces of the system, one at a time, until the performance was at the level we wanted. Here are things we did ranked by ROI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What moved the needle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Query Generation: not all context can be captured by the user's last query. We had an LLM review the thread and generate a number of semantic + keyword queries. We processed all of those queries in parallel, and passed them to a reranker. This made us cover a larger surface area and not be dependent on a computed score for hybrid search.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reranking: the highest value 5 lines of code you'll add. The chunk ranking shifted a lot. More than you'd expect. Reranking can many times make up for a bad setup if you pass in enough chunks. We found the ideal reranker set-up to be 50 chunk input -&amp;gt; 15 output.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chunking Strategy: this takes a lot of effort, you'll probably be spending most of your time on it. We built a custom flow for both enterprises, make sure to understand the data, review the chunks, and check that a) chunks are not getting cut mid-word or sentence b) ~each chunk is a logical unit and captures information on its own&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metadata to LLM: we started by passing the chunk text to the LLM, we ran an experiment and found that injecting relevant metadata as well (title, author, etc.) improves context and answers by a lot.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Query routing: many users asked questions that can't be answered by RAG (e.g. summarize the article, who wrote this). We created a small router that detects these questions and answers them using an API call + LLM instead of the full-blown RAG set-ups.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Our stack&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vector database: Azure -&amp;gt; Pinecone -&amp;gt; Turbopuffer (cheap, supports keyword search natively)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Document Extraction: Custom&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chunking: Unstructured.io by default, custom for enterprises (heard that Chonkie is good)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Embedding: text-embedding-large-3, haven't tested others&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reranker: None -&amp;gt; Cohere 3.5 -&amp;gt; Zerank (less known but actually good)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;LLM: GPT 4.1 -&amp;gt; GPT 5 -&amp;gt; GPT 4.1, covered by Azure credits&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Going Open-source&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We put all our learning into an open-source project: agentset-ai/agentset under an MIT license. Feel free to reach out if you have any questions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.abdellatif.io/production-rag-processing-5m-documents"/><published>2025-10-20T15:55:36+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45646958</id><title>x86-64 Playground – An online assembly editor and GDB-like debugger</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:23.067939+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="aefedf1ae8255dda"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;x86-64 Playground is a web app for experimenting and learning x86-64 assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Playground web app provides an online code editor where you can write, compile, and share assembly code for a wide range of popular assemblers such as GNU As, Fasm and Nasm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike traditional onlide editors, this playground allows you to follow the execution of your program step by step, inspecting memory and registers of the running process from a GDB-like interface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can bring your own programs! Drag and drop into the app any x86-64-Linux static executable to run and debug it in the same sandboxed environment, without having to install anything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The app is for anyone that wants to run amd64 assembly snippets or inspect the inner workings of simple Linux ELF files.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has been designed with the academic world of binary exploitation in mind; The debugger interface offers visualizations similar to the GDB+PwnGDB debugger plugin, and all the controls are labelled with the respective GDB commands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Combined with Compiler Explorer, this app provides a noise-free environment to learn the basics behind the inner workings of a Linux process. When you are ready, it includes the guides and resources necessary to keep experimenting on your own linux environment, with the actual GDB debugger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have you ever seen a responsive debugger? The app places the mobile experience at the center of its design, and can be embedded in any web page to add interactivity to technical tutorials or documentations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow the guide to embed in your website both the asm editor and debugger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The app is open-source, and available on Github. It's powered by the Blink Emulator, which emulates an x86-64-Linux environment entirely client side in your browser. This means that all the code you write, or the excutables you debug are never sent to the server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;everything runs in your browser, and once the Web App loads it will work without an internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://x64.halb.it/"/><published>2025-10-20T17:55:18+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45647166</id><title>Claude Code on the web</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:22.892754+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7f0c0efeffb1c2ef"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Claude Code on the web&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we're introducing Claude Code on the web, a new way to delegate coding tasks directly from your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now in beta as a research preview, you can assign multiple coding tasks to Claude that run on Anthropic-managed cloud infrastructure, perfect for tackling bug backlogs, routine fixes, or parallel development work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Run coding tasks in parallel&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Code on the web lets you kick off coding sessions without opening your terminal. Connect your GitHub repositories, describe what you need, and Claude handles the implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each session runs in its own isolated environment with real-time progress tracking, and you can actively steer Claude to adjust course as it’s working through tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Claude Code running in the cloud, you can now run multiple tasks in parallel across different repositories from a single interface and ship faster with automatic PR creation and clear change summaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Flexible for every workflow&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The web interface complements your existing Claude Code workflow. Running tasks in the cloud is especially effective for:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Answering questions about how projects work and how repositories are mapped&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bugfixes and routine, well-defined tasks&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Backend changes, where Claude Code can use test-driven development to verify changes&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also use Claude Code on mobile. As part of this research preview, we’re making Claude Code available on our iOS app so developers can explore coding with Claude on the go. It’s an early preview, and we hope to quickly refine the mobile experience based on your feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Security-first cloud execution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every Claude Code task runs in an isolated sandbox environment with network and filesystem restrictions. Git interactions are handled through a secure proxy service that ensures Claude can only access authorized repositories—helping keep your code and credentials protected throughout the entire workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also add custom network configuration to choose what domains Claude Code can connect to from its sandbox. For example, you can allow Claude to download npm packages over the internet so that it can run tests and validate changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read our engineering blog and documentation for a deep dive on Claude Code’s sandboxing approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Getting started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Code on the web is available now in research preview for Pro and Max users. Visit claude.com/code to connect your first repository and start delegating tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloud-based sessions share rate limits with all other Claude Code usage. Explore our documentation to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-code-on-the-web"/><published>2025-10-20T18:12:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45649178</id><title>Today is when the Amazon brain drain sent AWS down the spout</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:22.678880+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d28b35914248ecf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Today is when the Amazon brain drain finally sent AWS down the spout&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;When your best engineers log off for good, don’t be surprised when the cloud forgets how DNS works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;column "It's always DNS" is a long-standing sysadmin saw, and with good reason: a disproportionate number of outages are at their heart DNS issues. And so today, as AWS is still repairing its downed cloud as this article goes to press, it becomes clear that the culprit is once again DNS. But if you or I know this, AWS certainly does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so, a quiet suspicion starts to circulate: where have the senior AWS engineers who've been to this dance before gone? And the answer increasingly is that they've left the building — taking decades of hard-won institutional knowledge about how AWS's systems work at scale right along with them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What happened?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS reports that on October 20, at 12:11 AM PDT, it began investigating “increased error rates and latencies for multiple AWS services in the US-EAST-1 Region.” About an hour later, at 1:26 AM, the company confirmed “significant error rates for requests made to the DynamoDB endpoint” in that region. By 2:01 AM, engineers had identified DNS resolution of the DynamoDB API endpoint for US-EAST-1 as the likely root cause, which led to cascading failures for most other things in that region. DynamoDB is a "foundational service" upon which a whole mess of other AWS services rely, so the blast radius for an outage touching this thing can be huge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a result, much of the internet stopped working: banking, gaming, social media, government services, buying things I don't need on Amazon.com itself, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS has given increasing levels of detail, as is their tradition, when outages strike, and as new information comes to light. Reading through it, one really gets the sense that it took them 75 minutes to go from "things are breaking" to "we've narrowed it down to a single service endpoint, but are still researching," which is something of a bitter pill to swallow. To be clear: I've seen zero signs that this stems from a lack of transparency, and every indication that they legitimately did not know what was breaking for a patently absurd length of time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that for those 75 minutes, visitors to the AWS status page (reasonably wondering why their websites and other workloads had just burned down and crashed into the sea) were met with an "all is well!" default response. Ah well, it's not as if AWS had previously called out slow outage notification times as an area for improvement. Multiple times even. We can keep doing this if you'd like.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The prophecy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS is very, very good at infrastructure. You can tell this is a true statement by the fact that a single one of their 38 regions going down (albeit a very important region!) causes this kind of attention, as opposed to it being "just another Monday outage." At AWS's scale, all of their issues are complex; this isn't going to be a simple issue that someone should have caught, just because they've already hit similar issues years ago and ironed out the kinks in their resilience story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you reach a certain point of scale, there are no simple problems left. What's more concerning to me is the way it seems AWS has been flailing all day trying to run this one to ground. Suddenly, I'm reminded of something I had tried very hard to forget.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of 2023, Justin Garrison left AWS and roasted them on his way out the door. He stated that AWS had seen an increase in Large Scale Events (or LSEs), and predicted significant outages in 2024. It would seem that he discounted the power of inertia, but the pace of senior AWS departures certainly hasn't slowed — and now, with an outage like this, one is forced to wonder whether those departures are themselves a contributing factor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can hire a bunch of very smart people who will explain how DNS works at a deep technical level (or you can hire me, who will incorrect you by explaining that it's a database), but the one thing you can't hire for is the person who remembers that when DNS starts getting wonky, check that seemingly unrelated system in the corner, because it has historically played a contributing role to some outages of yesteryear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When that tribal knowledge departs, you're left having to reinvent an awful lot of in-house expertise that didn't want to participate in your RTO games, or play Layoff Roulette yet again this cycle. This doesn't impact your service reliability — until one day it very much does, in spectacular fashion. I suspect that day is today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AWS outage exposes Achilles heel: central control plane&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Major AWS outage across US-East region breaks half the internet&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Amazon spills plan to nuke Washington...with X-Energy mini-reactors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Amazon turns James Bond into the Man Without the Golden Gun&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The talent drain evidence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is The Register, a respected journalistic outlet. As a result, I know that if I publish this piece as it stands now, an AWS PR flak will appear as if by magic, waving their hands, insisting that "there is no talent exodus at AWS," a la Baghdad Bob. Therefore, let me forestall that time-wasting enterprise with some data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It is a fact that there have been 27,000+ Amazonians impacted by layoffs between 2022 and 2024, continuing into 2025. It's hard to know how many of these were AWS versus other parts of its Amazon parent, because the company is notoriously tight-lipped about staffing issues.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Internal documents reportedly say that Amazon suffers from 69 percent to 81 percent regretted attrition across all employment levels. In other words, "people quitting who we wish didn't."&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The internet is full of anecdata of senior Amazonians lamenting the hamfisted approach of their Return to Office initiative; experts have weighed in citing similar concerns.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you were one of the early employees who built these systems, the world is your oyster. There's little reason to remain at a company that increasingly demonstrates apparent disdain for your expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;My take&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a tipping point moment. Increasingly, it seems that the talent who understood the deep failure modes is gone. The new, leaner, presumably less expensive teams lack the institutional knowledge needed to, if not prevent these outages in the first place, significantly reduce the time to detection and recovery. Remember, there was a time when Amazon's "Frugality" leadership principle meant doing more with less, not doing everything with basically nothing. AWS's operational strength was built on redundant, experienced people, and when you cut to the bone, basic things start breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to be very clear on one last point. This isn't about the technology being old. It's about the people maintaining it being new. If I had to guess what happens next, the market will forgive AWS this time, but the pattern will continue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS will almost certainly say this was an "isolated incident," but when you've hollowed out your engineering ranks, every incident becomes more likely. The next outage is already brewing. It's just a matter of which understaffed team trips over which edge case first, because the chickens are coming home to roost. ®&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/20/aws_outage_amazon_brain_drain_corey_quinn/"/><published>2025-10-20T20:50:03+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45650792</id><title>Old Computer Challenge – Modern Web for the ZX Spectrum</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:22.506713+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a76899312b36a4a4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025/10/19&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Table of contents&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last year I participated in the OCC challenge and between work and personal life I totally forgot about it, luckily I saw a post online of someone doing the challenge and remembered about it. I didn’t want to miss this year challenge as it was fun learning something new last year, so hopefully its not too late.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This years challenge it was a DIY, you could create your own OCC challenge. So I thought it’d be fun to try to recreate a website and navigation for the ZX Spectrum using BASIC and the limited graphics capabilities of the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, in this case the hardware is the ZX Spectrum, though I must say that I used an emulator (Fuse) to test and run my code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ZX Spectrum image resolution is 256x192 pixels, so the space is very limited. The colour palette is made up of 8 colors, with a “brighter” variation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this in mind I had to design a website for the ZX Spectrum and how you’d navigate with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So given the hardware and limitations I thought that I’d first do Google, since they have a simple design and is I’d say well known by everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The image below, is what Googles homepage would look like.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’d access their services listed by pressing the first letter of that service, in case there is more than 1 with the same letter you’d use another letter or simply add a second page of services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case you can access Search by pressing “S”. It will simply prompt for your search and in this case I searched for “How to run LLM on a microprocessor” and you’d navigate through the different results by going pressing “w” (up) or “s” (down).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hacker news is text heavy content, so it makes it “easy” to design it for the ZX Spectrum as its graphics capabilities are kinda limited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you can see, you’ll be able to see your username and the amount of points you have in the top bar and in this case I decided that navigation would be done “less” interactively and you’ll access posts by simply selecting the number (1 to 6). If you want to go to the second page of posts you can press “M” and if you want to submit you press “S”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So if we select the first post by pressing 1, we’ll load more details about the post and the comment section.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll see the title, user that posted it, time and the comment section with the amount of comments, in this case 42. The problem with the comment section is that some comment threads can go deep and have different branches as multiple users will reply. So in this case what I thought was to simply navigate the top level comments with “M” for the next comment and “B” to go back to the previous top level comment. I guess you could add a “[R]eply” option, to reply to the comment you are seeing on screen and navigating through the comment replies, you’d press something like “C” and you’ll enter a page of the child comments of the parent comment. The only problem with this is that because the screen is so tiny and limited, that most of the time you’ll only be able to see 1 comment at a time and when posts have 300 comments, navigating them is going to be hard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And this is what submitting a new link would look like, you’d simply “edit” the different fields and then “S"ubmit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Personally I had fun doing this, I didn’t have to spend a lot of time researching before doing that as I had already done a lot of that work in last year challenge, so I could focus on what I wanted to do. You can check the source code and try it yourself in my repository https://codeberg.org/0x00cl/Web-ZX&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are videos of the interactions in the ZX Spectrum&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://0x00.cl/blog/2025/occ-2025/"/><published>2025-10-20T23:40:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45652859</id><title>Practical Scheme</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:22.142754+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="c343dacf9eb15a95"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This page is a collection of libraries and extensions to use Scheme as a production tool. By "production tools" I mean the tools to process daily chores for systems engineers and programmers---parsing files, generate reports, watching processes, providing small GUI wrappers, and all sorts of those things. Currently I'm using Perl for those purpose, but I'm always longing to use Scheme for them. So I started this page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most stuffs in this site are done as my private project at home, except the ones explicitly stated otherwise. I upload libraries even in its alpha/beta stage, since I'd like to test and use them at work, too. In a way, my primary interest is to make my life happier. No warranty comes with them, as usual, but it'll be nice if somebody else finds they are useful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you can read Japanese, visit the Japanese page which contains some translations of Lisp/Scheme related articles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wrote a Wiki Clone in Scheme (Gauche). Come and try it: WiLiKi.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Applications and tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scheme-related stand alone programs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Gauche - Current version 0.9.15 (2024/04/24)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;An R7RS Scheme implementation aimed at a handy script engine. Quick startup, built-in system interface, and native multilingual support are some of the goals.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;WiLiKi - Current version 0.6.2 (2014/11/28)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A wiki engine written in Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Chaton - Current version&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A Comet-based Webchat system.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;escm - Current version 1.1 (2014/11/28)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A filter program which copies the input text to output, with processing embedded Scheme expressions. This program itself is independent from any Scheme implementation; you can use your favorite one. Useful to process text files with a bit of dynamic parts. This page itself is processed by escm to embed information such as the update time of libraries, and synchronize with Japanese version. A complete new version of escm, named aescm, is being developed by TAGA Yoshitaka ( http://sourceforge.net/projects/escm/)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Libraries and Extensions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following libraries and extensions are written for Gauche. See here for libraries written for STk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Gauche-gl - Download Document Current version 0.6 (2014/08/09)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;OpenGL binding for Gauche. Supports most of OpenGL 1.0 to 4.1 APIs (including OpenGL Shading Language API), and some of GLU and GLUT API. Requires Gauche 0.9.4 or later.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Gauche-gtk2 - Download Document Current version 0.6.1 (2022/3/20)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;GTK2 binding for Gauche.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Documents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Scheme Cross Reference&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A cross reference of library procedures of various Scheme implementations. Updated constantly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Shooting A Moving Target--- An Experience In Developing A Production Tracking Database&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;An application of CommonLisp in practice. (yeah, it's not Scheme... anyway, I put it here).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Tracking Assets in the Production of 'Final Fantasy : The Spirits Within'&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A follow-up of the article above, a kind of post-mortem of the production.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;Gluing Things Together - Scheme in the Real-time CG Content Production&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A paper presented at International Lisp Conference 2002 at San Francisco, October 2002. (there's also a pdf version).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-5"&gt;Efficient floating-point number handling for dynamically typed scripting languages (pdf)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-5"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A paper presented at Dynamic Language Symposium 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-6"&gt;Schemer's Way&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-6"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Trying to explain Scheme's merits to non-Scheme programmers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Other Resources&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This list no way covers everything, but you can follow links in those links.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Schemers.org&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;A good anchor point to collect information of Scheme. You can get R*RS, the language standard. The site is also a center of SRFI's--- Scheme Request For Implementation---which provides common interface of libraries across various implementations.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;SCM&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;A compact, fast and portable implementation of Scheme interpreter.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;SLIB&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;A large collection of portable Scheme libraries. The contents spans from small utilities complements the standard conformance, to the full-featured relational database.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;Programming Languages by Dai Inukai&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;Scheme-related documents by Dai Inukai, the author of "Nyuumon Scheme (Scheme Primer)" in Japan. Check this out if you're interested in processing Japanese in Scheme.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-5"&gt;Bigloo&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-5"&gt;A scheme system with compiler and integrated development environment. If you're planning to write an enterprise software rather than just a bunch of scripts, look at it.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-6"&gt;Guile&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-6"&gt;GNU adopted Scheme for the base of extension language several years ago. The effort became Guile. If you have one of popular Linux distributions, you may already have it.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-7"&gt;scsh&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-7"&gt;I haven't used this one much, but looks good if you're looking for a tool to do syste programming.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-8"&gt;The Internet Scheme Repository&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-8"&gt;As the name suggests.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-9"&gt;Kawa - the Java-based Scheme System&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-9"&gt;A Scheme environment written in Java by Per Bothner. Scheme code is compiled to Java bytecode, hence has the property "write once run everywhere".&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://practical-scheme.net/index.html#docs"/><published>2025-10-21T05:47:39+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45653143</id><title>Language Support for Marginalia Search</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:21.465463+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f210038521b88b84"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the big ambitions for the search engine this year has been to enable searching in more languages than English, and a pilot project for this has just been completed, allowing experimental support for German, French and Swedish.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These changes are now live for testing, but with an extremely small corpus of documents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the search engine has been up to this point built with English in mind, some anglo-centric assumptions made it into its code. A lot of the research on search engines generally seems to embed similar assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As this is a domain rife with unknown unknowns, the ambition for this pilot was to implement support for just a few additional languages in order to get a feel for how much work would be required to support more languages in general, as well as to assess how much the index grows when this is done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though it was fully understood upfront that supporting all languages in one go is unrealistic, as some languages are more different than others and require significant additional work. Human language is surprisingly disparate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A language like Japanese, for example, has not only multiple alphabets, but embeds character width in unicode; on top of that the language doesn’t put spaces between words. As such the language requires special normalization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Latin, on the other hand, has dozens of forms for each word, and the words can often be reordered without significantly changing the meaning of a sentence. On the one hand this makes the grammatical analysis of the language somewhat easier since the words announce their function in the sentence fairly unambiguously, but on the other you probably need to store the text in a lemmatized form, and then strongly de-prioritize word order when matching.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google’s bungled handling of Russian was supposedly why Yandex was able to eke out a foothold in that market.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What needs changing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The search engine’s language processing chain is fairly long, but the most salient parts go something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text is extracted from the HTML&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Language is identified using fasttext&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text is broken into sentences&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Words are lowercased and Unicode is normalized&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sentences are stemmed and POS-tagged&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sentences, with stemming and POS-tag data is fed into keyword extraction algorithms&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Keywords are mapped to positions and HTML tags&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Important keywords are identified using TF-IDF (using stemmed forms)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Important keywords are identified using grammar patterns (POS-tags)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Important keywords are identified using other heuristics&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Keywords are hashed&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stemming is an imperfect way of getting a base form of a word, though generally such algorithms have a great number of flaws, so that e.g. universe and university seem to be the same word. This is only used in tf-idf calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part-of-Speech (POS) tagging is a grammatical annotation process where the role of each word is as best possible identified. This helps identify named entities, subjects, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both of these processes needless to say require some awareness of the language being acted upon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These “important keywords” are used to assign documents to a special index that helps with recall by ensuring these documents are included in the set that is ranked before the execution timer runs out. This is not strictly necessary, and in some cases such as where POS-tagging is not possible, can be disabled, partially or as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The normalization step is subject to cultural differences that do not translate. In English you’d probably expect to find the metal band TrÃ¶jan, typing “trojan”. In Swedish these are different letters entirely that should not match, the former means “the shirt”, the latter “trojan” in the Homeric or IT-security sense. Though a Swedish person would likely also say that they should be able to find mÃ¼(e)sli with the keyword “musli”, but a German-speaker would disagree and say that u and Ã¼ are clearly not the same.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There also exists a bootstrapping problem, as the statistical model used to calculate TF-IDF is based on documents in the index. Since almost all of the documents in the index up until this point have been in English, term frequencies for the newly added languages are missing. This breaks TF-IDF, as used in identifying important keywords, until a new model can be constructed. Thankfully the BM-25 model used in ranking is robust to this, as it relies on live data from the index itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The basic approach to parametrize language handling selected was to inject a language definition object, from which language appropriate logic is accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is configurable via XML. Here XML was chosen because it arguably has the best built-in validation support, making it a fantastic use case for a self-contained configuration file like this one, where late validation would be very annoying to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Much of the configuration file consists of various grammatical patterns used to identify important keywords based on the role of a word in a sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;ngrams type="noun"&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;VBG&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;RB VBG&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NNP* JJ)&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NN* JJ) NN*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NN* JJ) (NN* JJ) NN*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NN* JJ) (NN* JJ) (NN* JJ) NN*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NNP* JJ) (NNP* IN TO CC) NNP*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NNP* JJ) (NNP* IN TO CC) DT NNP*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NNP* JJ) (NNP* IN TO CC) (NNP* IN TO CC) NNP*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ngrams&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An expression like &lt;code&gt;(NN* JJ) (NN* JJ) NN*&lt;/code&gt; is interpreted as&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Any tag starting with &lt;code&gt;NN&lt;/code&gt;, or the tag&lt;code&gt;JJ&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Any tag starting with &lt;code&gt;NN&lt;/code&gt;, or the tag&lt;code&gt;JJ&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Any tag starting with &lt;code&gt;NN&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Previously these patterns were hard coded, and finding a performant alternative implementation took some effort. A bit mask approach was selected, as it allows for some very basic bit-level concurrency that drastically reduces the number of branches needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as grammatical analysis goes, the approach used by the search engine is pretty medieval, but it does do a fairly good job at what it sets out to do, and as a result, one thing it is generally pretty good at is finding websites about some topic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In some ways the imperfections introduced by the old-fashioned way of approaching language processing is almost helpful in bringing in more relevant results, as they tend to capture more variations of the words related to the topic of the document.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are more places that need minor language dependent behavior changes that are glossed over here, both in the language processing pipeline discussed above, and in the query parser, though in the interest of keeping this update from becoming an overly verbose git diff, these will be glossed over.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Tooling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To help make sense of this, a test tool was built that runs the language processing pipeline in isolation, and outputs annotated intermediate results for human inspection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work in this domain poses special problems that all but demand human testing. Machine testing can be good for catching regressions or getting access to some code for easier debugging, but natural language has so many nuances that any test suite is woefully inadequate compared to a pair of human eyeballs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has already helped refine the algorithms used to identify important keywords in English, which wasn’t the intent of building the tool, but its immediate consequence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Integration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Integrating the new multi-language search data into the system poses some design considerations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One option would be to stick everything in one big index, and then filter results based on language during or after ranking. The strength of this is that it becomes possible to search in any language without specifying it upfront.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The drawbacks of the one-index approach is that it grows the index, which makes all queries slower; it also grows the number of keywords in the lexicon, which is something that we generally want to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The way the search engine handles mapping keywords to numeric ids is to use a hash algorithm. Not a hash table, but the output of the hash algorithm itself. This seems absolutely unhinged at first glance, but works remarkably well as long as the lexicon stays small enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hash collisions do happen on rare occasions, but they need to happen between words where the words actually appear in the same documents to be a problem, generally leading to the ranking algorithm having to trudge through irrelevant documents and performing worse as a result of wasting its time budget.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Massively expanding the lexicon like we would if we were to mingle the documents increases the likelihood there will be an actual problem arising from these rare false positives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we stick every keyword from every language in the same index, a different problem arises, namely that homophones exist across different languages, meaning that the index lookup needs to wade through irrelevant documents that are trivially unrelated to the query.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The words &lt;code&gt;salt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lag&lt;/code&gt;, if they appear in the same document in English likely selects documents relating to esports, whereas in Swedish they select for documents relating to food preservation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The alternative option is to separate the indexes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The drawback here is that you must specify the language upfront, and querying in all languages becomes very expensive, as it executing multiple queries, though the desired language of the search results are generally known beforehand so this is a relatively small concern that, at best, affects a small number of machine-access use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since it has far fewer problems, and promises to be faster and more accurate, this approach was selected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In practice this was implemented as language-specific keyword-document mappings, that point into a common file containing document lists.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially the indexes were constructed from a common journal file, which was consumed repeatedly, but this turned out to be slow, and a partitioned approach was selected instead, with one journal per language. This almost completely removes any overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Outcome&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The changes discussed above have been implemented, and upon evaluation seems to work reasonably well, though evaluation has somewhat run into a dead end, as the index itself is extremely small for the newly added languages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The experience of small index is devious as it may just mean poor recall, though looking at the documents database for one index partition, this is about 12% of the index, it really is quite small!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;iso&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;document count&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;en&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;112,846,397&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;de&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7,623,983&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;fr&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4,852,759&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sv&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1,020,962&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To verify this is not due some silent, catastrophic processing error, the proportions were compared against the number of documents found in the 50 GB document sample used in testing, using a simplified process that only does language identification.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;iso&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;document count&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;en&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11,497,571&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;de&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;614,311&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;fr&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;409,877&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;es&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;267,408&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ja&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;217,599&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;nl&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;196,130&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&amp;amp;mldr;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&amp;amp;mldr;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sv&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;67,670&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proportions aren’t identical, but in the same general ballpark. The small size of the sample, along with the uneven distribution and apparent rarity of these documents adequately explains the disparity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lack of documents in languages other than English is likely due to how the index has been grown, by following and adding links from English websites. These occasionally lead to bilingual websites, and on rare occasions to websites completely in a different language, though it seems reasonable most websites that are not at least partially in English sees few or no links from English-language websites.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adding to the problem, up until fairly recently the index wasn’t really growing very much at all, only through manual submissions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond a certain point, meaningfully growing the index by just following links became difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most known domains are dead, so merely adding more domains to the list of websites to crawl only serves to pollute the database with junk data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order to get around this, and reach the goal of indexing a billion documents, a new process was built to visit candidate websites to verify that they are in fact real and on-line, before assigning them to an index partition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The process has been running for almost a quarter, and has managed to identify about 800,000 viable new domains in that time window. (This has brought the document total up to 969M documents. So very nearly there now!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Web search is unusual in how often you run into these extremely long running processes that need to cook for months, sometimes up to a year before they really begin to pay off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll have to see whether building this new process was so prescient it ends up being sufficient to identify and add new domains in more languages, as links from the newly processed Swedish, French and German websites have been added to the domain database, or if some sort of manual seeding or targeted selection process is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems plausible it will at least begin to remedy the data starvation, as the rate of successful domain discovery has shot up significantly since processing links from the documents processed in the newly added languages, and many of the new domains are indeed from &lt;code&gt;.de&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.se&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.fr&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;.ch&lt;/code&gt; domains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For now we’ll have to wait and see how the data-set evolves. It is difficult to further refine the multi-language aspect of the search data with a data-set this small.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.marginalia.nu/log/a_126_multilingual/"/><published>2025-10-21T06:48:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45653330</id><title>Pasta/80 is a simple Pascal cross compiler targeting the Z80 microprocessor</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:20.979037+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a6f5f818a2971b8d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PASTA/80 is a simple Pascal cross compiler targeting the Z80 microprocessor. It generates code for these classic and modern machines:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The compiler follows the single-pass recursive-descent approach championed by Niklaus Wirth, inventor of Pascal, in his books and lectures. It doesn't have an explicit syntax tree, but instead generates code on the fly during parsing. As a result, the compiler might not always generate the most efficient code possible (it definitely cannot compete with LLVM and doesn't try to), but it's very fast.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The supported Pascal dialect is an almost exact clone of the original Turbo Pascal 3.0 for CP/M (see this manual for details). So you have at your disposal the following language elements:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All the basic data types (&lt;code&gt;Boolean&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Byte&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Char&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Integer&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Pointer&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Real&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;array of&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;record&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;set of&lt;/code&gt;, enumerations, subranges and pointers as a way of building new data types.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The decision-making elements &lt;code&gt;if..then..else&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;case..of&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The loop elements &lt;code&gt;for..do&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;while..do&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;repeat..until&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The &lt;code&gt;with..do&lt;/code&gt;notation for "opening" records.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;procedure&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;function&lt;/code&gt;including value and&lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt;parameters and nesting.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The standard procedures for screen input and output (i.e. &lt;code&gt;ReadLn&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;WriteLn&lt;/code&gt;etc.).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All conversion and utility procedures and functions that Turbo Pascal 3.0 had.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The three kinds of disk files, that is untyped (&lt;code&gt;file&lt;/code&gt;), typed (&lt;code&gt;file of&lt;/code&gt;) and&lt;code&gt;Text&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A dynamic heap of up to 32767 bytes with &lt;code&gt;GetMem&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;FreeMem&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;New&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;Dispose&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inline assembly (via opcodes, not via mnemonics, so this page might be handy).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Overlays (in memory, Spectrum 128K and Next only, see below).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Some compiler directives: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;$i &amp;lt;file&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;for including Pascal source files (including nesting and cycle detection)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;$l &amp;lt;file&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;for including an assembly file (aka "linking" a library)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;$a(+/-)&lt;/code&gt;for enabling or disabling absolute mode (default is on, disable for recursion)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;$i(+/-)&lt;/code&gt;for enabling or disabling IO checking (when off, check&lt;code&gt;IOResult&lt;/code&gt;after calls)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;$k(+/-)&lt;/code&gt;for enabling or disabling stack overflow checking&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;$u(+/-)&lt;/code&gt;for enabling or disabling Ctrl-C checking&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The compiler also has some features that were borrowed from or inspired by later versions of Turbo Pascal:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;C-style &lt;code&gt;//&lt;/code&gt;one-line comments in addition to&lt;code&gt;{..}&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;(*..*)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Binary literals (using a &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt;prefix).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Break&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;Continue&lt;/code&gt;for loop control.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Querying the keyboard via &lt;code&gt;KeyPressed&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;ReadKey&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Color support via &lt;code&gt;TextColor&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;TextBackground&lt;/code&gt;with constants for the 8 Spectrum Next colors.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Inc&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;Dec&lt;/code&gt;for more efficient increasing and decreasing of variables.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Include&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;Exclude&lt;/code&gt;for more efficient handling of sets.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A simple &lt;code&gt;Assert&lt;/code&gt;facility that counts passes/fails and shows the failed line number.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since that covers most of the functionality of Turbo Pascal 3 you might ask what is missing. These are the current limitations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All the remaining compiler directives are not yet supported.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mark&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;Release&lt;/code&gt;are not currently supported.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The standard files &lt;code&gt;Input&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Output&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Kbd&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Con&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;Lst&lt;/code&gt;are not supported.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Chain&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;Execute&lt;/code&gt;are not supported.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add-on libraries from the PC version of Turbo Pascal 3.0 are not yet supported (although there are a few graphics primitives for the ZX targets).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The new instructions of the Z80N CPU inside the ZX Spectrum Next are not yet being leveraged.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No separate compilation. Everything is compiled from source, always.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Binary size is quite large compared to the original.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The runtime library, being partially written in Pascal itself, gets quite large when compiled. I hope to bring this down again by reimplementing more of it in Z80 assembly (or improve the code generator, which, although it has a peephole optimizer, is not generating super-efficient Z80 code).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The compiler is itself written in Pascal. You can compile it with Free Pascal (I use version 3.2.2). Just run&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ fpc pasta&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Pascal compiler generates Z80 assembler code and relies on sjasmplus as a backend for the final translation step to binary. It can also, in &lt;code&gt;--ide&lt;/code&gt; mode (see below), make use of various other external tools. The compiler tries to detect these external tools automatically (from your system's &lt;code&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt;), but sometimes it's best to create a file &lt;code&gt;.pasta80.cfg&lt;/code&gt; in your home directory specifying necessary paths (there is a sample in &lt;code&gt;misc&lt;/code&gt; that you can adapt).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# PASTA/80 config

HOME      = ~/Spectrum/pasta80
ASSEMBLER = ~/Spectrum/sjasmplus/sjasmplus
...
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can check your whole setup by calling the compiler with &lt;code&gt;--config&lt;/code&gt;. It will show the full paths of all internal and external requirements and whether they are fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To run the compiler just invoke the executable with the name of a Pascal source file to translate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default target is CP/M. There is an optional parameter that enables some simple peephole optimizations and another one that uses dependency analysis to eliminate unused Pascal procedures and functions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ pasta hello.pas             # Compiles hello.pas to hello.com
$ pasta hello                 # Source file .pas suffix is optional
$ pasta --opt hello.pas       # Enables peephole optimizations
$ pasta --opt --dep hello.pas # The same plus dependency analysis&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can run the resulting &lt;code&gt;.com&lt;/code&gt; files on a real CP/M machine or in a CP/M emulator. I recommend the excellent tnylpo. For programs that use VT52 control codes you have to start tnylpo in full-screen mode:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ tnylpo hello                # Run in line-mode
$ tnylpo -s -t @ hello        # Monochrome full-screen, wait when finished
$ tnylpo -soy,4,0 -t @ hello  # Color full-screen, wait when finished&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;"Hello, World" in line mode&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;"Hello, World" in full-screen&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To generate binaries for the ZX Spectrum 48K, 128K and Next targets, use the &lt;code&gt;--zx48&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;--zx128&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;--zxnext&lt;/code&gt; parameters, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ pasta --zx48 hello.pas      # Compiles for ZX Spectrum 48K
$ pasta --zx128 hello.pas     # Compiles for ZX Spectrum 48K
$ pasta --zxnext hello.pas    # Compiles for ZX Spectrum Next&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The main difference between the three (currently) is that the ZX Spectrum Next target supports file IO (on the SD card), while the other two do not. The remaining routines are mostly the same. Screen output is handled via &lt;code&gt;rst $10&lt;/code&gt; in the ROM. In both cases the binaries are expected to be run from address 0x8000.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default output format for the ZX Spectrum targets is a simple binary file that contains exactly the bytes of the compiled program (plus a +3DOS header when compiling for the Spectrum Next). In addition to that (and for more complex cases involving overlays), the compiler can also generate snapshot files or tape files, the latter including a suitable BASIC loader:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ pasta --zx48 --sna examples/hello.pas   # .sna file
$ pasta --zx48 --tap examples/jacques.pas # .tap file with BASIC loader&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being self-contained, snapshots and tapes are a convenient way to distribute your programs and to launch them an emulator, such as Fuse:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ open -a Fuse examples/hello.sna         # Launch .sna file in FUSE (on Mac)
$ open -a Fuse examples/jacques.tap       # Launch .tap file in FUSE (on Mac)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Hello world in FUSE&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Frere Jacques in FUSE (yes, with sound!)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When compiling for the Next, another useful format is a runnable directory. It contains exactly the same files that would also be in the .tap file, including a BASIC loader named &lt;code&gt;run.bas&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ pasta --zxnext --run examples/pq.pas    # Results in directory named pq.run&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The directory has the suffix &lt;code&gt;.run&lt;/code&gt;. When attempting to enter such a directory in the Next's file browser, the loader is started automatically (press Symbol Shift + Enter to really see the contents). If you are a Mac user: Yes, it's a bit like an &lt;code&gt;.app&lt;/code&gt; bundle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Spectrum 128K and Next targets support overlays. This means you can have larger programs than would normally fit into the 64K address space of a Z80 machine. The rules are the same as for Turbo Pascal 3.0:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Overlays can be applied to global procedures and functions only, not to nested ones (though nested ones will be overlayed if the containing ones are, too).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Overlays cannot be applied to global variables, that is, you cannot use them for data (at least not without tricks).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All consecutive procedures and functions that are marked as &lt;code&gt;overlay&lt;/code&gt;go into the same overlay. Use any declaration inbetween to separate overlays.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the following example, there are three overlays: Overlay 0 contains A and B, overlay 1 contains D, and overlay 2 contains E.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;overlay procedure A; (* Overlay 0 *)
begin
end;

overlay procedure B; (* Overlay 0 *)
begin
end;

procedure C; (* Not in an overlay *)
begin
end;

overlay procedure D; (* Overlay 1 *)
begin
end;

type
  Dummy = Integer;   (* Separator *)

overlay procedure E; (* Overlay 2 *)
begin
end;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In contrast to Turbo Pascal 3.0, overlays are not implemented via disk files. Instead, they use the additional RAM of the Spectrum 128K and Next machines. The uppermost 16K bank (Spectrum 128K) or 8K page (Spectrum Next) will be reserved for overlays. Each overlay can have a maximum size of 8K. The compiler manages everything and generates special "far calls" whenever necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enable overlays, use the &lt;code&gt;--ovr&lt;/code&gt; command line parameter, ideally in conjuncton with the &lt;code&gt;--tap&lt;/code&gt; parameter, as the tape loaders for 128K and Next are fully overlay-aware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ pasta --zx128 --tap --opt --dep --ovr tests/all.pas # Test suite as 128K tape&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The compiler prints a report of which overlays go into which RAM banks or pages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;----------------------------------------
PASTA/80 Pascal System      Version 0.96
                            ZX 128K, Z80

Copyright (C) 2020-25 by  Joerg Pleumann
----------------------------------------

Compiling...
  tests/all.pas -&amp;gt; tests/all.z80
Assembling...
  tests/all.z80 -&amp;gt; tests/all.tap

Program   : 10781 bytes ($8000-$AA1C)
Heap      :  1507 bytes ($AA1D-$AFFF)
Stack     :  4096 bytes ($B000-$BFFF)

Overlay  0:  7399 bytes ($C000-$DCE6) in bank  0
Overlay  1:  7185 bytes ($E000-$FC10) in bank  0
Overlay  2:  2725 bytes ($C000-$CAA4) in bank  1
Overlay  3:  6293 bytes ($E000-$F894) in bank  1
Overlay  4:  6392 bytes ($C000-$D8F7) in bank  3
Overlay  5:  6527 bytes ($E000-$F97E) in bank  3
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without the &lt;code&gt;--ovr&lt;/code&gt; parameter, overlay markers are simply ignored. This means you can use the same source code for platforms that do support overlays and for those that don't.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Caution: Overlays somewhat break the safety of the Pascal language. Be careful when using pointers or &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; parameters for passing data between overlays. The memory you refer to may have just been paged out! It might make sense to compile your overlays with &lt;code&gt;{$a-}&lt;/code&gt;, so that all local variables are stored on the stack (which is always visible).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a folder containing &lt;code&gt;examples&lt;/code&gt; and a folder containing &lt;code&gt;tests&lt;/code&gt; for the compiler. The main test suite &lt;code&gt;all.pas&lt;/code&gt; needs to be compiled with &lt;code&gt;--opt --dep&lt;/code&gt; because of its size. Otherwise it won't fit into 64K. The Spectrum 128K and Next targets can (only) handle it using overlays, the Spectrum 48K target can't. Both the examples and the tests should give you a pretty good overview of what the compiler can do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also solved all puzzles of Advent of Code 2022 with an earlier version of the compiler and made YouTube videos of the solutions running on the ZX Spectrum Next, in CP/M mode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a fun little gimmick the compiler can be started like this&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ pasta --ide&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;to run it in an interactive mode that has an interface reminiscient of Turbo Pascal 3.0.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Main menu&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Editor&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When started in an ordinary terminal, this mode relies on the editor &lt;code&gt;nano&lt;/code&gt; being present on your system (on MacOS you might want to install the real &lt;code&gt;nano&lt;/code&gt; via a package manager because Apple sells you the much more limited &lt;code&gt;pico&lt;/code&gt; editor as &lt;code&gt;nano&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also run it in a shell within Visual Studio Code, in which case it would automatically use VSC's editor (via the &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; command, which, on a Mac, you might have to make available from VCS's settings) and act a bit like a plugin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following external tools are supported for running compiled programs on the host machine:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;tnylpo for CP/M programs (press &amp;lt;R&amp;gt; for line mode, &amp;lt;Shift-R&amp;gt; for full-screen mode).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fuse for programs targeting the ZX Spectrum 48K and 128K machines.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CSpect for ZX Spectrum Next programs. &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Please have hdfmonkey ready for manipulating the SD card image.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;If you're on MacOS or Linux, you also need &lt;code&gt;mono&lt;/code&gt;because CSpect is a .NET application.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, everything that is in your &lt;code&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt; should be detected automatically. There are some exceptions, though, so it makes sense to copy &lt;code&gt;misc/.pasta80.cfg&lt;/code&gt; to your home directory and adapt it. Use the &lt;code&gt;--config&lt;/code&gt; parameter to let PASTA/80 check your setup and get feedback on what is in place and what is missing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following screenshots show some applications compiled for the CP/M target and running in the &lt;code&gt;tnylpo&lt;/code&gt; emulator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;2048&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Game of Life&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Micro Calc&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Galactic Empire&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These screenshots show some applications compiled for the ZX Spectrum 48K target and running in the FUSE emulator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;2048&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Game of Life&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Graphics Demo&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Equation Solver&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PASTA/80 Pascal Compiler&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Copyright (c) 2020-2025 by Jörg Pleumann&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The PASTA/80 compiler is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License (GPL) as published by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The runtime library (folder&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rtl&lt;/code&gt;) comes with a linking exception that makes sure the GPL does not transfer to binaries created using PASTA/80.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The examples (folder&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;examples&lt;/code&gt;) are considered public domain or whatever comes closest to that in your jurisdiction.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Individual files or folders may use different licenses, so you might want to double check.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everything is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What does this mean for you?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;You can use the compiler, free of charge, to build any application, open-source or prioprietary, free or paid, and distribute the generated binary without restriction. You can distribute binaries created with PASTA/80 under a license of your choosing.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;You can modify the compiler according to your needs. If you distribute the compiler or parts of it, binary or source, modified or not, you have to comply with the rules laid out in the GPL (copyright info, source code, ...) unless the linking exception applies.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The math48 library is coypright (c) 1980 by Anders Hejlsberg, used by permission.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some assembly routines adapted from Leventhal/Saville, "Z80 Assembly Subroutines", Osborne/McGraw-Hill 1983.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turbo Pascal is a registered trademark of Code Gear LLC / Embarcadero.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Z80 is a registered trademark of Zilog, Inc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/pleumann/pasta80"/><published>2025-10-21T07:23:09+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45653350</id><title>Show HN: I'm rewriting a web server written in Rust for speed and ease of use</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:20.285934+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="fdb285ba2972be9c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would you like to use stable version of Ferron? Visit Ferron 1.x website&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ferron is a fast web server with automatic TLS certificate management, easy configuration, and rock-solid security — so you can go live in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Command unavailable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch, as Ferron serves a website with automatic TLS setup in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite powering much of the internet, popular web servers (such as Apache and NGINX) weren't designed for ease of use, security, or modern developer experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you spent hours configuring a web server just to set up a website? NGINX configs can become verbose, even for something as common as a high-performance reverse proxy. Apache's directives can be hard to navigate too, with many options that can make simple tasks needlessly hard.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many popular web servers (including Apache and NGINX) are written in programming languages and use libraries that aren't designed for memory safety. This caused many issues, such as Heartbleed in OpenSSL, putting servers at unnecessary risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apache's architecture can struggle under modern workloads, often underperforming compared to newer, leaner servers. This means wasted resources and slower response times for your website visitors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Designed with modern web hosting needs in mind, Ferron combines speed, security, and ease of use in one powerful package.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thoroughly optimized for speed with support for high concurrency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Built with memory safety as a priority, eliminating common security vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Automatic SSL/TLS certificate acquisition and renewal with Let's Encrypt integration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simple, intuitive configuration with sensible, secure defaults and comprehensive documentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advanced reverse proxy capabilities with support for load balancing and health checks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Built-in support for modern API patterns including WebSockets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discover how Ferron simplifies the process of securing your website with HTTPS through automatic TLS management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ferrondemo&lt;/code&gt; of your domain name (for example, &lt;code&gt;ferrondemo.example.com&lt;/code&gt;) to either:&lt;p&gt;You will notice how Ferron manages the TLS certificate for your subdomain automatically.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not working? Check your DNS settings and ensure that the subdomain is correctly pointing to the IP address or CNAME provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ferron can outperform other popular web servers in performance benchmark tests across different workloads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Higher is better | Benchmarks run on AMD Ryzen 5 8600G, 32GB RAM, with the &lt;code&gt;ferrbench -c 1000 -d 60s -t 12 -h https://localhost --http2&lt;/code&gt; command | Benchmarks performed on September 19, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Higher is better | Benchmarks run on AMD Ryzen 5 8600G, 32GB RAM, with the &lt;code&gt;ferrbench -c $CONCURRENCY -d 5s -t 12 -h https://localhost --http2&lt;/code&gt; command | Benchmarks performed on September 25, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lower is better | Benchmarks run on AMD Ryzen 5 8600G, 32GB RAM, with the &lt;code&gt;ferrbench -c $CONCURRENCY -d 5s -t 12 -h https://localhost --http2&lt;/code&gt; command | Benchmarks performed on September 25, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Higher is better | Benchmarks run on AMD Ryzen 5 8600G, 32GB RAM, with the &lt;code&gt;ferrbench -c 100 -d 60s -t 12 -h https://localhost --http2&lt;/code&gt; command | Benchmarks performed on June 13, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get started with Ferron in minutes. Choose your preferred platform and installation method.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Command unavailable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ferron has simple, intuitive configuration, compared to more complex configurations of some popular web servers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;server {
    listen 80;
    listen 443 ssl http2;

    server_name example.com;
    server_tokens off;

    # Assuming you use Certbot for automatic certificate management
    ssl_certificate /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/fullchain.pem;
    ssl_certificate_key /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/privkey.pem;

    root /var/www/html;
    gzip on;

    location / {
        try_files $uri $uri/ =404;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;// TLS certificate is obtained automatically by Ferron
example.com {
    root "/var/www/html"
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;upstream backend {
    server localhost:3000;
    keepalive 32;
}

server {
    listen 80;
    listen 443 ssl http2;

    server_name example.com;
    server_tokens off;

    # Assuming you use Certbot for automatic certificate management
    ssl_certificate /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/fullchain.pem;
    ssl_certificate_key /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/privkey.pem;

    location / {
        proxy_pass http://backend/;
        proxy_http_version 1.1;
        proxy_set_header Upgrade $http_upgrade;
        proxy_set_header Connection 'upgrade';
        proxy_set_header Host $host;
        proxy_cache_bypass $http_upgrade;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;// TLS certificate is obtained automatically by Ferron
example.com {
    proxy "http://localhost:3000"
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;server {
    listen 80;
    listen 443 ssl http2;

    server_name example.com;
    server_tokens off;

    # Assuming you use Certbot for automatic certificate management
    ssl_certificate /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/fullchain.pem;
    ssl_certificate_key /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/privkey.pem;

    root /var/www/html;
    index index.php index.html index.htm;

    location / {
        gzip on;
        try_files $uri $uri/ =404;
    }

    location ~ \.php$ {
        fastcgi_split_path_info ^(.+\.php)(/.+)$;
        fastcgi_pass unix:/var/run/php/php-fpm.sock;
        set $path_info $fastcgi_path_info;
        fastcgi_param PATH_INFO $path_info;
        fastcgi_index index.php;
        # The "fastcgi.conf" is located in the NGINX configuration directory (at least on Debian-based systems)
        include fastcgi.conf;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;// TLS certificate is obtained automatically by Ferron
example.com {
    root "/var/www/html"
    // Check if the PHP-FPM socket file is accessible by the web server user, often "ferron"
    fcgi_php "unix:///var/run/php/php-fpm.sock"
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don't take our word for it — hear from the system administrators and developers who use Ferron every day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I suspect that people don't like changing web servers, and perhaps that's why it took the industry so long to move away from Apache. Ferron actually looks great â great performance, automatic TLS, easy reverse proxy configuration and more. Congrats on shipping this!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may want to check out what Ferron is doing. I've been using it for a few months. Highly recommend. (...) Significantly easier to set up than nginx, and by far the most effortless auto TLS integration. (...) Highly recommend using the v2 docker images though. It now uses KDL for configuration, which is much cleaner than YAML. The syntax is versatile enough that you can create a custom DSL of sorts. Ferron uses it to replicate if statements, and uses them to filter access by IP or headers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Join many sysadmins and developers using Ferron to serve websites faster, more securely, and with less overhead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://ferron.sh/"/><published>2025-10-21T07:26:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45653981</id><title>Human Error Cripples the Internet (1997)</title><updated>2025-10-21T10:11:20.165031+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b629d39125b2a197"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;head&gt;July 17, 1997&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Human Error Cripples the Internet&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;By PETER WAYNER&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;ompanies, computers and people started disappearing from the Internet at 2:30 a.m. Eastern Time on Thursday after a human error at Network Solutions Inc., the company with the primary responsibility for maintaining the master list of domain names, corrupted Internet addresses around the world.&lt;td&gt;“Tens of millions of people are using the Internet, and very few of them know how truly complex it is.”&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adam Clayton Powell 3d,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;The Freedom Forum&lt;lb/&gt;The error caused e-mail to be returned to senders with messages akin to "address unknown" and also prevented many people from finding Web sites.&lt;p&gt;Alex Gadea, the President of Vscape International, a Web site hosting company, was among the hundreds of systems people rousted out of bed Thursday morning when server alarms started going off around the world. Gadea's company pays a private service to check his 10 main Web servers every 10 minutes and beep him if they fail to respond. The beeps started at 5:30 in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem occurred when the database of the top level domain name server (DNS) became corrupted. This database acts as the telephone book for the Internet, matching names like e-mail addresses and Web URLs to four-byte numbers known as IP (for Internet Protocol) addresses, which steer data through the Internet to the appropriate computer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For instance, the name "www.nytimes.com" corresponds to nine different computers that answer requests for The New York Times on the Web, one of which is 199.181.172.242. This four-byte address is used by the Internet in a manner roughly analogous to a nine-digit zip code to direct packets of information directly to the correct computer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each day at 2:30 a.m., Network Solutions updates its directory, known as a "lookup table," to reflect the changes made during the day. These include adding new addresses for anyone who has registered a new domain name and deleting addresses for sites than have surrendered their names. Network Solutions also shuts down the names of entities that haven't paid the $100 fee required to register the name.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this case, the database became corrupted when it was regenerated, effectively wiping out all of the more than one million companies in the .com and .net domains. The .edu, .gov and .org domains, which are also administered by Network Solutions were not affected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a result, when a computer queried Network Solutions for the IP address of a service like www.nytimes.com, it was told that the site didn't exist, because no record was found.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dave Grave, the Internet Business Manager of Network Solutions, said that the program responsible for converting the Ingres database information into the tables used by the DNS software failed. Internal error-checking software detected the problem, but the employee responsible for watching over the process ignored the warning and released the corrupted database to the network.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem was complicated by the fact that there are nine major top level servers responsible for answering calls to look up domain names and return the corresponding IP address. These are run by institutions both public and private throughout the network as a service. One of the top level servers is run by Network Solutions and is the authoritative record, but the other eight make copies of the Network Solutions database each night soon after the day's changes are made.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grave says that Network Solutions detected the problem and corrected it by 6:30 a.m. Eastern Time. The system administrators of the other eight machines, however, had to be notified individually to update their versions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;td&gt;In the four hours it took to repair one simple mistake, a problem had spread netwide.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Adding to the resulting chaos was the fact that the impact of the problem on individual users was literally random. Each computer tries to keep a cache of the latest IP addresses it requested. People who sent e-mail to -- or requested Web documents from -- common locations they frequently used may have never realized there was a problem with the Internet, because their own machines had stored the IP addresses they were using.&lt;p&gt;But if the local machine does not have the IP address cached, or if it decides that its current copy is too old to be trustworthy, it will send a request to a higher level DNS server, usually at the level of the Internet service provider. If this server does not have the IP address in question, it will kick it up another level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the request will reach the highest level, which is one of the nine top level machines named with the letters A through I. Older software will simply choose one of the nine machines at random for its request and then search through the nine machines in a round-robin fashion. Newer versions of the software will attempt to balance the load by looking for the machine that responds the fastest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The responses each user received this morning depended upon which of the top level machines processed their requests for IP addresses. If the request happened to reach a machine loaded with the corrupted database, their request came back address unknown. If it reached a machine with the corrected version, the request was handled successfully. This explains why the problem was often sporadic and affected people randomly throughout the morning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Asim Mughal is responsible for the E root server as the technical manager for network systems at NASA's Ames Research center at Moffet Field outside San Jose Calif. He said that NASA's server takes more than an hour to download the latest copies of the tables published by the A server at Network Solutions. His server checks the A server every three hours to determine if a new edition of the tables has been released. If one is available, it downloads a new copy. Each root server waits a different amount of time between checks, which is why some took longer than others to be updated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nine top level machines run versions of the Berkeley Internet Name Daemon (BIND), and the structure of this software was partially responsible for the magnitude of the problem. When each of the eight subordinate top level servers (servers B through I) ask the primary machine (server A) for a copy, BIND sends a complete copy of the database instead of just a list of the changed records. The .com database is about 142 megabytes and the .net database is about 10 megabytes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fact that a simple error could wreak so much havoc with the global computer network caused many people to reflect on how crucial the Internet has become in the daily life of businesses and individuals around the world and how vulnerable the system is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Tens of millions of people are using the Internet, and very few of them know how truly complex it is, almost like how people who fly on jet planes don't realize how complex that technology is," said Adam Clayton Powell 3d, head of the Freedom Forum, a New-York based foundation that studies new-media journalism. "The Web is deceptively simple. It's so easy to use it makes you think it's simpler than it really is. Even e-mail takes more work than it seems. Although it's easy and transparent to the user, there's a lot of technology."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business Problems&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;he glitch at Network Solutions is sure to compound the problems of the company, which has been a lightning rod for complaints since it began charging $100 for registering a domain name last year. Previously, registration had been free under the company's contract with the National Science Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fees can be quite lucrative. In the three months ending March 31, Network Solutions reported gross revenues of $8.6, 76.5 percent of which came from fees for registering domain names. This number does not include the 30 percent of the fees that are set aside in a fund for research into improving the Internet's infrastructure. The rest came from fees for setting up and running intranets for companies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The company is wholely owned by SAIC, the technical powerhouse that receives much of its revenues from government contracts. After SAIC assumed control of Network Solutions, SAIC absorbed some of Network Solutions' government contracts and began to spin off Network Solutions to handle the commercial side of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This information comes from the company's S-1 form filed on July 3 with the Securities and Exchange Commission, announcing an initial public offering led by Hambrecht and Quist. If the offering is successful, SAIC will still maintain effective control of Network Solutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many people on the Internet assert that competition would substantially reduce the cost of the registering domain names. The structure of the Internet makes this difficult, because most machines turn to the nine root servers for the ultimate answer to requests for address queries, and these machines mirror the list of people who have paid Network Solutions $100.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;td&gt;“We're going to see this type of problem replicated ad nauseum.”&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peter Neumann,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Scientist at SRI,&lt;lb/&gt;Some rebels are fighting back with stunts and by providing competitive services. Eugene Kashpureff, who runs the AlterNIC service for some of his network customers out of lower Manhattan, boasts that the 2 percent of the network that use his machines as their root server did not have problems on Thursday, because his database was not corrupted.&lt;p&gt;In the past, Kashpureff has been a vocal critic of Network Solutions and has pushed hard for the establishment of alternative domains with three-letter endings like ".nic", ".ltd" or ".xxx". He charges only $24 per year to maintain registration in these domains, about half of the $50 per year charged by Network Solutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The major problem with paying Kashpureff for registration in his databases is that most DNS servers don't know that these top-level domains exist. Earlier this week, Kashpureff pulled a stunt by fooling many servers around the nation into updating themselves to include his top-level domains. Network Solutions said that the problems this evening were not related in any way to Kashpureff's stunt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Karl Denninger, the president of the Chicago-based ISP MCSNET, is pushing for a different approach, which he calls "enhanced DNS," or eDNS. His company maintains a list of top-level domains like '.nic' or '.xxx' that are backed by real companies and real efforts. He makes an effort to screen out fakers who are simply hoping to reserve a top-level name, and he does not charge anything for a listing in the table. He feels that this quiet, efficient approach will draw the affections of more Internet users with time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In its S-1 filing, Network Solutions acknowledges that the competition from companies like the alter.nic is a potential problem. Each ISP chooses its own root domain server, and some may choose use the AlterNIC's machine because it provides more access to a greater number of top-level domains. Companies that point to Network Solution's server don't get access to URLs that end with the three letters .xxx, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This problem has proven to be a bit of a legal morass for Network Solutions. On March 20, the company announced that PG Media, a New York-based company, had sued, "alleging that the company had restricted access to the Internet by not adding [top level domains] in violation of the Sherman Act." But the National Science Foundation requested that Network Solutions not recognize these domains until a coherent policy emerged.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Worries About Terrorism&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;n many ways, this shows how the automated world of computers reflects the epigram about how the "want of a nail" resulted in losing a war. A small human error at Network Solutions led to the failure of many Web sites and the loss of a great deal of e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The vulnerability of the nation to accidents like these has attracted the attention of the Pentagon, which is actively investigating the 21st century notion of information warfare. Knocking out a nation's DNS service would be one way to cripple it in time of attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Network Solutions and many others companies are actively investigating how to defend against such problems in the future. One solution would be to bind a public key to each name, which would allow companies to control how their domain names were used. In the past, some people have masqueraded as others and directed Network Solutions to redirect mail and requests to their machine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peter Neumann, a scientist at SRI, a nonprofit research foundation in Menlo Park, Calif., and the editor of the highly influential comp.risks newsgroup, calls Thursday's wipeout an example of "inadvertigo" -- when a small, inadvertant problem spirals out of control. "We're going to see this type of problem replicated ad nauseum," Neumann predicted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Peter Wayner at pwayner@nytimes.com welcomes your comments and suggestions.&lt;lb/&gt;Related Sites&lt;lb/&gt;Following are links to the external Web sites mentioned in this article. These sites are not part of The New York Times on the Web, and The Times has no control over their content or availability. When you have finished visiting any of these sites, you will be able to return to this page by clicking on your Web browser's "Back" button or icon until this page reappears.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt; Home | &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://archive.nytimes.com/www.nytimes.com/library/cyber/week/071797dns.html"/><published>2025-10-21T09:28:29+00:00</published></entry></feed>