<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:55.911202+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46648714</id><title>Zep AI (Agent Context Engineering, YC W24) Is Hiring Forward Deployed Engineers</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:39:01.957296+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="af57259bffd2ec7b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Agent Context Is Hard. We Fixed It.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zep assembles the right context from chat history, business data, and user behavior so agents are personalized, accurate, and fast. Our open source project Graphiti hit 20k GitHub stars in under 12 months. Sub-200ms retrieval, SOC 2 Type 2/HIPAA certified, used by teams from startups to Fortune 500s.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/zep-ai/jobs/"/><published>2026-01-16T17:00:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46657122</id><title>ASCII characters are not pixels: a deep dive into ASCII rendering</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:39:01.555326+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="74d7db3c781d01ad"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;ASCII characters are not pixels: a deep dive into ASCII rendering&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently, I’ve been spending my time building an image-to-ASCII renderer. Below is the result — try dragging it around, the demo is interactive!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One thing I spent a lot of effort on is getting edges looking sharp. Take a look at this rotating cube example:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try opening the “split” view. Notice how well the characters follow the contour of the square.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This renderer works well for animated scenes, like the ones above, but we can also use it to render static images:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The image of Saturn was generated with ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, to get better separation between different colored regions, I also implemented a cel shading-like effect to enhance contrast between edges. Try dragging the contrast slider below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The contrast enhancement makes the separation between different colored regions far clearer. That was key to making the 3D scene above look as good as it does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I put so much focus on sharp edges because they’re an aspect of ASCII rendering that is often overlooked when programmatically rendering images as ASCII. Consider this animated 3D scene from Cognition’s landing page that is rendered via ASCII characters:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source: cognition.ai&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a cool effect, especially while in motion, but take a look at those blurry edges! The characters follow the cube contours very poorly, and as a result, the edges look blurry and jagged in places:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This blurriness happens because the ASCII characters are being treated like pixels — their shape is ignored. It’s disappointing to see because ASCII art looks so much better when shape is utilized. I don’t believe I’ve ever seen shape utilized in generated ASCII art, and I think that’s because it’s not really obvious how to consider shape when building an ASCII renderer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started building my ASCII renderer to prove to myself that it’s possible to utilize shape in ASCII rendering. In this post, I’ll cover the techniques and ideas I used to capture shape and build this ASCII renderer in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll start with the basics of image-to-ASCII conversion and see where the common issue of blurry edges comes from. After that, I’ll show you the approach I used to fix that and achieve sharp, high-quality ASCII rendering. At the end, we’ll improve on that by implementing the contrast enhancement effect I showed above.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s get to it!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Image to ASCII conversion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ASCII contains 95 printable characters that we can use. Let’s start off by rendering the following image containing a white circle using those ASCII characters:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ASCII art is (almost) always rendered using a monospace font. Since every character in a monospace font is equally wide and tall, we can split the image into a grid. Each grid cell will contain a single ASCII character.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The image with the circle is &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Monospace characters are typically taller than they are wide, so I made each grid cell a bit taller than it is wide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our task is now to pick which character to place in each cell. The simplest approach is to calculate a lightness value for each cell and pick a character based on that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can get a lightness value for each cell by sampling the lightness of the pixel at the cell’s center:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We want each pixel’s lightness as a numeric value between &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can use the following formula to convert an RGB color (with component values between &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See relative luminance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Mapping lightness values to ASCII characters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we have a lightness value for each cell, we want to use those values to pick ASCII characters. As mentioned before, ASCII has 95 printable characters, but let’s start simple with just these characters:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;: - # = + @ * % .&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can sort them in approximate density order like so, with lower-density characters to the left, and high-density characters to the right:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;. : - = + * # % @&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll put these characters in a &lt;code&gt;CHARS&lt;/code&gt; array:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const CHARS = [" ", ".", ":", "-", "=", "+", "*", "#", "%", "@"]&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I added space as the first (least dense) character.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can then map lightness values between &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;function getCharacterFromLightness(lightness: number) {const index = Math.floor(lightness * (CHARS.length - 1));return CHARS[index];}&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This maps low lightness values to low-density characters and high lightness values to high-density characters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rendering the circle from above with this method gives us:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That works... but the result is pretty ugly. We seem to always get &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt; for cells that fall within the circle and a space for cells that fall outside.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is happening because we’ve pretty much just implemented nearest-neighbor downsampling. Let’s see what that means.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Nearest neighbor downsampling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Downsampling, in the context of image processing, is taking a larger image (in our case, the &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The simplest and fastest method of sampling is nearest-neighbor interpolation, where, for each cell (pixel), we only take a single sample from the higher resolution image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider the circle example again. Using nearest-neighbor interpolation, every sample either falls inside or outside of the shape, resulting in either &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If, instead of picking an ASCII character for each grid cell, we color each grid cell (pixel) according to the sampled value, we get the following pixelated rendering:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pixelated rendering is pretty much equivalent to the ASCII rendering from before. The only difference is that instead of &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt;s we have white pixels, and instead of spaces we have black pixels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These square, jagged looking edges are aliasing artifacts, commonly called jaggies. They’re a common result of using nearest-neighbor interpolation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Supersampling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get rid of jaggies, we can collect more samples for each cell. Consider this line:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The line’s slope on the &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s try to get rid of the jagginess by taking multiple samples within each cell and using the average sampled lightness value as the cell’s lightness. The example below lets you vary the number of samples using the slider:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With multiple samples, cells that lie on the edge of a shape will have some of their samples fall within the shape, and some outside of it. Averaging those, we get gray in-between colors that smooth the downsampled image. Below is the same example, but with an overlay showing where the samples are taken:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This method of collecting multiple samples from the larger image is called supersampling. It’s a common method of spatial anti-aliasing (avoiding jaggies at edges). Here’s what the rotating square looks like with supersampling (using &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s look at what supersampling does for the circle example from earlier. Try dragging the sample quality slider:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The circle becomes less jagged, but the edges feel blurry. Why’s that?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, they feel blurry because we’re pretty much just rendering a low-resolution, pixelated image of a circle. Take a look at the pixelated view:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ASCII and pixelated views are mirror images of each other. Both are just low-resolution versions of the original high-resolution image, scaled up to the original’s size — it’s no wonder they both look blurry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increasing the number of samples is insufficient. No matter how many samples we take per cell, the samples will be averaged into a single lightness value, used to render a single pixel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that’s the core problem: treating each grid cell as a pixel in an image. It’s an obvious and simple method, but it disregards that ASCII characters have shape.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can make our ASCII renderings far more crisp by picking characters based on their shape. Here’s the circle rendered that way:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The characters follow the contour of the circle very well. By picking characters based on shape, we get a far higher effective resolution. The result is also more visually interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see how we can implement this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Shape&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what do I mean by shape? Well, consider the characters &lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;O&lt;/code&gt; placed within grid cells:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The character &lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt; is top-heavy. Its visual density in the upper half of the grid cell is higher than in the lower half. The opposite can be said for &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt; — it’s bottom-heavy. &lt;code&gt;O&lt;/code&gt; is pretty much equally dense in the upper and lower halves of the cell.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We might also compare characters like &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;J&lt;/code&gt;. The character &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt; is heavier within the left half of the cell, while &lt;code&gt;J&lt;/code&gt; is heavier in the right half:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also have more “extreme” characters, such as &lt;code&gt;_&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt;, that only occupy the lower or upper portion of the cell, respectively:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is, roughly, what I mean by “shape” in the context of ASCII rendering. Shape refers to which regions of a cell a given character visually occupies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Quantifying shape&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To pick characters based on their shape, we’ll somehow need to quantify (put numbers to) the shape of each character.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s start by only considering how much characters occupy the upper and lower regions of our cell. To do that, we’ll define two “sampling circles” for each grid cell — one placed in the upper half and one in the lower half:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It may seem odd or arbitrary to use circles instead of just splitting the cell into two rectangles, but using circles will give us more flexibility later on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A character placed within a cell will overlap each of the cell’s sampling circles to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One can compute that overlap by taking a bunch of samples within the circle (for example, at every pixel). The fraction of samples that land inside the character gives us the overlap as a numeric value between &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For T, we get an overlap of approximately &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can generate such a &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below are some ASCII characters and their shape vectors. I’m coloring the sampling circles using the component values of the shape vectors:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can use the shape vectors as 2D coordinates — here’s every ASCII character on a 2D plot:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Shape-based lookup&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s say that we have our ASCII characters and their associated shape vectors in a &lt;code&gt;CHARACTERS&lt;/code&gt; array:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const CHARACTERS: Array&amp;lt;{character: string,shapeVector: number[],}&amp;gt; = [...];&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can then perform a nearest neighbor search like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;function findBestCharacter(inputVector: number[]) {let bestCharacter = "";let bestDistance = Infinity;for (const { character, shapeVector } of CHARACTERS) {const dist = getDistance(shapeVector, inputVector);if (dist &amp;lt; bestDistance) {bestDistance = dist;bestCharacter = character;}}return bestCharacter;}&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;findBestCharacter&lt;/code&gt; function gives us the ASCII character whose shape best matches the input lookup vector.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: this brute force search is not very performant. This becomes a bottleneck when we start rendering thousands of ASCII characters at &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make use of this in our ASCII renderer, we’ll calculate a lookup vector for each cell in the ASCII grid and pass it to &lt;code&gt;findBestCharacter&lt;/code&gt; to determine the character to display.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s try it out. Consider the following zoomed-in circle as an example. It is split into three grid cells:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overlaying our sampling circles, we see varying degrees of overlap:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When calculating the shape vector of each ASCII character, we took a huge number of samples. We could afford to do that because we only need to calculate those shape vectors once up front. After they’re calculated, we can use them again and again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, if we’re converting an animated image (e.g. canvas or video) to ASCII, we need to be mindful of performance when calculating the lookup vectors. An ASCII rendering might have hundreds or thousands of cells. Multiplying that by tens or hundreds of samples would be incredibly costly in terms of performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With that being said, let’s pick a sampling quality of &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the top sampling circle of the leftmost cell, we get one white sample and two black, giving us an average lightness of &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From now on, instead of using the term “lookup vectors”, I’ll call these vectors, sampled from the image that we’re rendering as ASCII, sampling vectors. One sampling vector is calculated for each cell in the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway, we can use these sampling vectors to find the best-matching ASCII character. Let’s see what that looks like on our 2D plot — I’ll label the sampling vectors (from left to right) C0, C1, and C2:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hmm... this is not what we want. Since none of the ASCII shape vector components exceed &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can fix this by normalizing the shape vectors. We’ll do that by taking the maximum value of each component across all shape vectors, and dividing the components of each shape vector by the maximum. Expressed in code, that looks like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const max = [0, 0]for (const vector of characterVectors) {for (const [i, value] of Object.entries(vector)) {if (value &amp;gt; max[i]) {max[i] = value;}}}const normalizedCharacterVectors = characterVectors.map(vector =&amp;gt; vector.map((value, i) =&amp;gt; value / max[i]))&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what the plot looks like with the shape vectors normalized:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we now map the sampling vectors to their nearest neighbors, we get a much more sensible result:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We get &lt;code&gt;'&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;M&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt;.  Let’s see how well those characters match the circle:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nice! They match very well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s try rendering the full circle from before with the same method:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Much better than before! The picked characters follow the contour of the circle very well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Limits of a 2D shape vector&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using two sampling circles — one upper and one lower — produces a much better result than the &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, two circles don’t capture the shape of characters that fall in the middle of the cell. Consider &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;, we get a shape vector of &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two upper-lower sampling circles also don’t capture left-right differences, such as the difference between &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;q&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We could use such differences to get better character picks, but our two sampling circles don’t capture them. Let’s add more dimensions to our shape to fix that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Increasing to 6 dimensions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since cells are taller than they are wide (at least with the monospace font I’m using), we can use &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;q&lt;/code&gt;, while also capturing differences across the top, bottom, and middle regions of the cell, differentiating &lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;_&lt;/code&gt;. They also capture the shape of “diagonal” characters like &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; to a reasonable degree.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One problem with this grid-like configuration for the sampling circles is that there are gaps. For example, &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; falls between the sampling circles:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To compensate for this, we can stagger the sampling circles vertically (e.g. lowering the left sampling circles and raising the right ones) and make them a bit larger. This causes the cell to be almost fully covered while not causing excessive overlap across the sampling circles:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can use the same procedure as before to generate character vectors using these sampling circles, this time yielding a &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt;, we get the vector:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m presenting &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lightness values certainly look L-shaped! The 6D shape vector captures &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt;’s shape very well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Nearest neighbor lookups in a 6D space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we have a 6D shape vector for every ASCII character. Does that affect character lookups (how we find the best matching character)?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earlier, in the &lt;code&gt;findBestCharacter&lt;/code&gt; function, I referenced a &lt;code&gt;getDistance&lt;/code&gt; function. That function returns the Euclidean distance between the input points. Given two 2D points &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This generalizes to higher dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Put into code, this looks like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;function getDistance(a: number[], b: number[]): number {let sum = 0;for (let i = 0; i &amp;lt; a.length; i++) {sum += (a[i] - b[i]) ** 2;}return Math.sqrt(sum);}&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: since we’re just using this for the purposes of finding the closest point, we can skip the expensive &lt;code&gt;Math.sqrt()&lt;/code&gt; call and just return the squared distance. It does not affect the result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, no, the dimensionality of our shape vector does not change lookups at all. We can use the same &lt;code&gt;getDistance&lt;/code&gt; function for both 2D and 6D.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, let’s see what the 6D approach yields!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Trying out the 6D approach&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our new 6D approach works really well for flat shapes, like the circle example we’ve been using:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now let’s see how this approach works when we render a 3D scene with more shades of gray:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, the outer contours look nice and sharp. I also like how well the gradients across the sphere and cone look.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, internally, the objects all kind of blend together. The edges between surfaces with different lightnesses aren’t sharp enough. For example, the lighter faces of the cubes all kind of blend into one solid color. When there is a change in color — like when two faces of a cube meet — I’d like to see more sharpness in the ASCII rendering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To demonstrate what I mean, consider the following split:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s currently rendered like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The different shades result in &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt;s on the left and &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt;s on the right, but the boundary is not very sharp.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By applying some effects to the sampling vector, we can enhance the contrast at the boundary so that it appears sharper:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The added contrast makes a big difference in readability for the 3D scene. Let’s look at how we can implement this contrast enhancement effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Contrast enhancement&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider cells overlapping a color boundary like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the cells on the boundary, we get a 6D sampling vector that looks like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make future examples easier to visualize, I’ll start drawing the sampling vector using &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently, this sampling vector resolves to the character &lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s a sensible choice. The character &lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt; is visually dense in the top half and less so in the bottom half, so it matches the image fairly well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, I want the picked character to emphasize the shape of the boundary better. We can achieve that by enhancing the contrast of the sampling vector.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To increase the contrast of our sampling vector, we might raise each component of the vector to the power of some exponent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider how an exponent affects values between &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The level of pull depends on the exponent. Here’s a chart of &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This effect becomes more pronounced with higher exponents:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A higher exponent translates to a stronger pull towards zero.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applying an exponent should make dark values darker more quickly than light ones. The example below allows you to vary the exponent applied to the sampling vector:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the exponent is increased to &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t want that. I want to increase the contrast between the lighter and darker components of the sampling vector, not the vector in its entirety.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To achieve that, we can normalize the sampling vector to the range &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The normalization to &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const maxValue = Math.max(...samplingVector)samplingVector = samplingVector.map((value) =&amp;gt; {value = value / maxValue; // Normalizevalue = Math.pow(value, exponent);value = value * maxValue; // Denormalizereturn value;})&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the same example, but with this normalization applied:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Very nice! The lightest component values are retained, and the contrast between the lighter and darker components is increased by “crunching” the lower values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This affects which character is picked. The following example shows how the selected character changes as the contrast is increased:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Awesome! The pick of &lt;code&gt;"&lt;/code&gt; over &lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt; emphasizes the separation between the lighter region above and the darker region below!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By enhancing the contrast of the sampling vector, we exaggerate its shape. This gives us a character that less faithfully represents the underlying image, but improves readability as a whole by enhancing the separation between different colored regions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s look at another example. Observe how the L-shape of the sampling vector below becomes more pronounced as the exponent increases, and how that affects the picked character:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Works really nicely! I love the transition from &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp; -&amp;gt; b -&amp;gt; L&lt;/code&gt; as the L-shape of the vector becomes clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s nice about applying exponents to normalized sampling vectors is that it barely affects vectors that are uniform in value. If all component values are similar, applying an exponent has a minimal effect:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because the vector is fairly uniform, the exponent only has a slight effect and doesn’t change the picked character.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a good thing! If we have a smooth gradient in our image, we want to retain it. We very much do not want to introduce unnecessary choppiness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compare the 3D scene ASCII rendering with and without this contrast enhancement:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We do see more contrast at boundaries, but this is not quite there yet. Some edges are still not sharp enough, and we also observe a “staircasing” effect happening at some boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s look at the staircasing effect first. We can reproduce it with a boundary like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below is the ASCII rendering of that boundary. Notice how the lower edge (the &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt;s) becomes “staircase-y” as you increase the exponent:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We see a staircase pattern like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To understand why that’s happening, let’s consider the row in the middle of the canvas, progressing from left to right. As we start off, every sample is equally light, giving us &lt;code&gt;U&lt;/code&gt;s:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;UUUUUUUU -&amp;gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we reach the boundary, the lower right samples become a bit darker. Those darker components are crunched by contrast enhancement, giving us some &lt;code&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt;s:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So we get:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;UUUUUUUUYY -&amp;gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we progress further right, the middle and lower samples get darker, so we get some &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt;s:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This trend continues towards &lt;code&gt;"&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;'&lt;/code&gt;, and finally, &lt;code&gt;`&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Giving us a sequence like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;UUUUUUUUYYf""''` -&amp;gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That looks good, but at some point we get no light samples. Once we get no light samples, our contrast enhancement has no effect because every component is equally light. This causes us to always get &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt;s:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Making our sequence look like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;UUUUUUUUYYf""''`!!!!!!!!!! -&amp;gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This sudden stop in contrast enhancement having an effect is what causes the staircasing effect:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see how we can counteract this staircasing effect with another layer of contrast enhancement, this time looking outside of the boundary of each cell.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Directional contrast enhancement&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We currently have sampling circles arranged like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For each of those sampling circles, we’ll specify an “external sampling circle”, placed outside of the cell’s boundary, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each of those external sampling circles is “reaching” into the region of a neighboring cell. Together, the samples that are collected by the external sampling circles constitute an “external sampling vector”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s simplify the visualization and consider a single example. Imagine that we collected a sampling vector and an external sampling vector that look like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The circles colored red are the external sampling vector components. Currently, they have no effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The “internal” sampling vector itself is fairly uniform, with values ranging from &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enhance this apparent boundary, we’ll darken the top-left and middle-left components of the sampling vector. We can do that by applying component-wise contrast enhancement using the values from the external vector.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the previous contrast enhancement, we calculated the maximum component value across the sampling vector and normalized the vector using that value:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const maxValue = Math.max(...samplingVector)samplingVector = samplingVector.map((value) =&amp;gt; {value = value / maxValue; // Normalizevalue = Math.pow(value, exponent);value = value * maxValue; // Denormalizereturn value;})&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the new component-wise contrast enhancement will take the maximum value between each component of the sampling vector and the corresponding component in the external sampling vector:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;samplingVector = samplingVector.map((value, i) =&amp;gt; {const maxValue = Math.max(value, externalSamplingVector[i])// ...});&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aside from that, the contrast enhancement is performed in the same way:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;samplingVector = samplingVector.map((value, i) =&amp;gt; {const maxValue = Math.max(value, externalSamplingVector[i]);value = value / maxValue;value = Math.pow(value, exponent);value = value * maxValue;return value;});&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The example below shows how light values in the external sampling vector push values in the sampling vector down:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I call this “directional contrast enhancement”, since each of the external sampling circles reaches outside of the cell in the direction of the sampling vector component that it is enhancing the contrast of. I describe the other effect as “global contrast enhancement” since it acts on all of the sampling vector’s components together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see what this directional contrast enhancement does to get rid of the staircasing effect:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hmm, that’s not doing what I wanted. I wanted to see a sequence like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;..::!!..::!!!!!!!!..::!!!!!!!!!!!!!!&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But we just see &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt; changing to &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This happens because the directional contrast enhancement doesn’t reach far enough into our sampling vector. The light upper values in the external vector do push the upper values of the sampling vector down, but because the lightness of the four bottom components is retained, we don’t get to &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;, just &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Widening the directional contrast enhancement&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’d like to “widen” the directional contrast enhancement so that, for example, light external values at the top spread to the middle components of the sampling vector.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To do that, I’ll introduce a few more external sampling circles, arranged like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are a total of &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For each component of the internal sampling vector, we’ll calculate the maximum value across the external sampling vector components that affect it, and use that maximum to perform the contrast enhancement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s implement that. I’ll order the internal and external sampling circles like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can then define a mapping from the internal circles to the external sampling circles that affect them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const AFFECTING_EXTERNAL_INDICES = [[0, 1, 2, 4],[0, 1, 3, 5],[2, 4, 6],[3, 5, 7],[4, 6, 8, 9],[5, 7, 8, 9],];&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this, we can change the calculation of &lt;code&gt;maxValue&lt;/code&gt; to take the maximum affecting external value:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;// Beforeconst maxValue = Math.max(value, externalSamplingVector[i]);// Afterlet maxValue = value;for (const externalIndex of AFFECTING_EXTERNAL_INDICES[i]) {maxValue = Math.max(value, externalSamplingVector[externalIndex]);}&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now look what happens if the top four external sampling circles are light: it causes the contrast enhancement to reach into the middle of the sampling vector, giving us the desired effect:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We now smoothly transition from &lt;code&gt;! -&amp;gt; : -&amp;gt; .&lt;/code&gt; — beautiful stuff!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see if this change resolves the staircasing effect:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oh yeah, looks awesome! We get the desired effect. The boundary is nice and sharp while not being too jagged.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the 3D scene again. The contrast slider now applies both types of contrast enhancement at the same time — try it out:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This really enhances the contrast at boundaries, making the image far more readable!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Together, the 6D shape vector approach and contrast enhancement techniques have given us a really nice final ASCII rendering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Final words&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post was really fun to build and write! I hope you enjoyed reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ASCII rendering is perhaps not the most useful topic to write about, but I think the idea of using a high-dimensional vector to capture shape is interesting and could easily be applied to many other problems. There are parallels to be drawn to word embeddings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started writing this ASCII renderer to see if the idea of using a vector to capture the shape of characters would work at all. That approach turned out to work very well, but the initial prototype was terribly slow — I only got single-digit FPS on my iPhone. To get the ASCII renderer running at a smooth &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My colleagues, after reading a draft of this post, suggested many alternatives to the approaches I described in this post. For example, why not make the sampling vector &lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt; far better — just look how &lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt;’s stem falls between the two sampling circles in each row:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yeah, he’s right! A &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s really fun how large the solution space to the problem of ASCII rendering is. There are so, so many approaches and trade-offs to explore. I imagine you probably thought of a few yourself while reading this post!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One dimension I intentionally did not explore was using different colors or lightnesses for the ASCII characters themselves. This is for many reasons, but the two primary ones are that 1) it would have expanded the scope of this post too much, and 2) it’s just a different effect, and I personally don’t like the look.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the time of writing these final words, around &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! And huge thanks to Gunnlaugur Þór Briem and Eiríkur Fannar Torfason for reading and providing feedback on a draft of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— Alex Harri&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be notified of new posts, subscribe to my mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Appendix I: Character lookup performance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earlier in this post, I showed how to find the best character by finding the character with the shortest Euclidean distance to our sampling vector.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;function findBestCharacter(inputVector: number[]) {let bestCharacter = "";let bestDistance = Infinity;for (const { character, shapeVector } of CHARACTERS) {const dist = getDistance(shapeVector, inputVector);if (dist &amp;lt; bestDistance) {bestDistance = dist;bestCharacter = character;}}return bestCharacter;}&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried benchmarking this for &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we allow ourselves &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;k-d trees&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Internally, &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I won’t go into much detail on &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One could also look at the hierarchical navigable small worlds (HNSW) algorithm, which Eiríkur pointed me to. It is used for approximate nearest neighbor lookups in vector databases, so definitely relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see how it performs! We’ll construct a &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const kdTree = new KdTree(CHARACTERS.map(({ character, shapeVector }) =&amp;gt; ({point: shapeVector,data: character,})));&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can now perform nearest-neighbor lookups on the &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const result = kdTree.findNearest(samplingVector);&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s a lot of lookups per frame, but again, we’re benchmarking on a powerful machine. This is still not good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see how we can eke out even more performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Caching&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An obvious avenue for speeding up lookups is to cache the result:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;function searchCached(samplingVector: number[]) {const key = generateCacheKey(samplingVector)if (cache.has(key)) {return cache.get(key)!;}const result = search(samplingVector);cache.set(key, result);return result;}&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But how does one generate a cache key for a &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, one way is to quantize each vector component so that it fits into a set number of bits and packing those bits into a single number. JavaScript numbers give us &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can quantize a numeric value between &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const BITS = 5;const RANGE = 2 ** BITS;function quantizeTo5Bits(value: number) {return Math.min(RANGE - 1, Math.floor(value * RANGE));}&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applying a max of &lt;code&gt;RANGE - 1&lt;/code&gt; is done so that a &lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; of exactly &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can quantize each of the sampling vector components in this manner and use bit shifting to pack all of the quantized values into a single number like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;const BITS = 5;const RANGE = 2 ** BITS;function generateCacheKey(vector: number[]): number {let key = 0;for (let i = 0; i &amp;lt; vector.length; i++) {const quantized = Math.min(RANGE - 1, Math.floor(vector[i] * RANGE));key = (key &amp;lt;&amp;lt; BITS) | quantized;}return key;}&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;RANGE&lt;/code&gt; is current set to &lt;code&gt;2 ** 5&lt;/code&gt;, but consider how large that makes our key space. Each vector component is one of &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alright, &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Range&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Number of keys&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Memory needed to store keys&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;46,656&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;364 KB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;117,649&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;919 KB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;262,144&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2.00 MB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;531,441&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4.05 MB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1,000,000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7.63 MB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1,771,561&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13.52 MB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2,985,984&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22.78 MB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are trade-offs to consider here. As the range gets smaller, the quality of the results drops. If we pick a range of &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, if we increase the possible number of keys, we need more memory to store them. Additionally, the cache hit rate might be very low, especially when the cache is relatively empty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I ended up picking a range of &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cached lookups are incredibly fast — fast enough that lookup performance just isn’t a concern anymore (&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Appendix II: GPU acceleration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lookups were not the only performance concern. Just collecting the sampling vectors (internal and external) turned out to be terribly expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just consider the sheer amount of samples that need to be collected. The 3D scene I’ve been using as an example uses a &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that’s if we use a sampling quality of &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Collecting these samples absolutely crushed performance on my iPhone, so I needed to either collect fewer samples or speed up the collection of samples. Collecting fewer samples would have meant rendering fewer ASCII characters or removing the directional contrast enhancement, neither of which was an appealing solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My initial implementation ran on the CPU, which could only collect one sample at a time. To speed this up, I moved the work of sampling collection and applying the contrast enhancement to the GPU. The pipeline for that looks like so (each of the steps listed is a single shader pass):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Collect the raw internal sampling vectors into a &lt;mjx-container/&gt;texture, using the canvas (image) as the input texture.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Do the same for the external sampling vectors.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Calculate the maximum external value affecting each internal vector component into a &lt;mjx-container/&gt;texture.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apply directional contrast enhancement to each sampling vector component, using the maximum external values texture.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Calculate the maximum value for each internal sampling vector into a &lt;mjx-container/&gt;texture.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apply global contrast enhancement to each sampling vector component, using the maximum internal values texture.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m glossing over the details because I could spend a whole other post covering them, but moving work to the GPU made the renderer many times more performant than it was when everything ran on the CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be notified of new posts, subscribe to my mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://alexharri.com/blog/ascii-rendering"/><published>2026-01-17T11:15:26+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46658345</id><title>The recurring dream of replacing developers</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:39:01.336991+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d5de5d392af7abd9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;07.12.2025, By Stephan Schwab&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every decade brings new promises: this time, we'll finally make software development simple enough that we won't need so many developers. From COBOL to AI, the pattern repeats. Business leaders grow frustrated with slow delivery and high costs. Developers feel misunderstood and undervalued. Understanding why this cycle persists for fifty years reveals what both sides need to know about the nature of software work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Neil Armstrong stepped onto the lunar surface in 1969, the world witnessed what organized human ingenuity could accomplish. Behind that achievement stood Margaret Hamilton and her team, writing Apollo’s guidance software by hand, catching critical errors through careful review, and proving that software could be mission-critical.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Apollo program demonstrated that software development was essential to achieving the impossible. Yet it also revealed something that would frustrate business leaders for decades to come: writing software required specialized knowledge, intense focus, and significant time investment. The dream of making it easier—of needing fewer of these expensive specialists—began almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The late 1960s and 1970s saw COBOL emerge with an explicit goal stated in its name: Common Business-Oriented Language. The vision was clear: make the language read like English sentences, and business analysts would write their own programs. No need for specialized programmers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This vision had genuine appeal. Software was becoming essential to business operations, yet programmers remained a scarce, expensive resource. COBOL promised to democratize software creation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What happened instead? COBOL became another programming language requiring specialized training. Business analysts who tried to write COBOL quickly discovered that readable syntax didn’t eliminate the complexity of logic, data structures, or system design. A new class of COBOL programmers emerged, and the dream of eliminating specialized developers remained unfulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet the dream didn’t die. It simply waited for the next technological wave.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computer-Aided Software Engineering tools arrived in the 1980s with tremendous promise. Draw flowcharts and entity-relationship diagrams, and the tool would generate working code. The marketing message resonated: visual design was more intuitive than typing cryptic commands. Business experts could model their processes, and software would materialize.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organizations invested heavily. Vendors promised productivity increases of 10x or more. Yet most CASE tool initiatives struggled or failed outright.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The generated code often required substantial manual intervention. Performance problems emerged. Maintenance became a nightmare when generated code diverged from the visual models. Most critically, drawing accurate diagrams required understanding the same logical complexity that programming demanded. The tool changed the interface but not the fundamental challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once again, the problem proved more stubborn than the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 1990s brought a different approach. Microsoft’s Visual Basic and Borland’s Delphi made building user interfaces dramatically easier. Drag components onto a form, set properties, write event handlers. Suddenly, creating a Windows application felt achievable for developers with modest experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This wave succeeded differently than COBOL or CASE tools. These environments acknowledged that programming knowledge was still necessary, but they reduced the barrier to entry. A broader range of people could create useful applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet the dream of eliminating developers persisted. “Power users” and “citizen developers” would build departmental applications. IT departments could focus on infrastructure while business units solved their own software needs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reality proved more nuanced. Simple applications were indeed accessible to more people. But as requirements grew in complexity—integration with existing systems, security considerations, performance under load, long-term maintenance—the need for experienced developers became evident. The tools expanded who could write software, but they didn’t eliminate the expertise required for substantial systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so the cycle continued into the new millennium.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each subsequent decade introduced new variations. Ruby on Rails promised convention over configuration. Low-code platforms offered visual development with minimal coding. No-code platforms claimed to eliminate programming entirely for common business applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each wave delivered real value. Development genuinely became faster in specific contexts. More people could participate in creating software solutions. Yet professional software developers remained essential, and demand for their skills continued growing rather than shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which brings us to the question: why does this pattern repeat?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The recurring pattern reveals something important about how we think about complexity. Software development looks like it should be simple because we can describe what we want in plain language. “When a customer places an order, check inventory, calculate shipping, process payment, and send a confirmation email.” That description sounds straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The complexity emerges in the details. What happens when inventory is temporarily reserved by another order? How do you handle partial payments? What if the email service is temporarily unavailable? Should you retry? How many times? What if the customer’s session expires during checkout? How do you prevent duplicate orders?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each answer leads to more questions. The accumulated decisions, edge cases, and interactions create genuine complexity that no tool or language can eliminate. Someone must think through these scenarios. That thinking is software development, regardless of whether it’s expressed in COBOL, a CASE tool diagram, Visual Basic, or an AI prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which brings us to today’s excitement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today’s AI coding assistants represent the most capable attempt yet to assist with software creation. They can generate substantial amounts of working code from natural language descriptions. They can explain existing code, suggest improvements, and help debug problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This represents genuine progress. The assistance is real and valuable. Experienced developers use these tools to work more efficiently. People learning to code find the interactive guidance helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet we’re already seeing the familiar pattern emerge. Initial excitement about AI replacing developers is giving way to a more nuanced understanding: AI changes how developers work rather than eliminating the need for their judgment. The complexity remains. Someone must understand the business problem, evaluate whether the generated code solves it correctly, consider security implications, ensure it integrates properly with existing systems, and maintain it as requirements evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI amplifies developer capability. It doesn’t replace the need for people who understand both the problem domain and the technical landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the paradox that makes this pattern particularly poignant. We’ve made extraordinary progress in software capabilities. The Apollo guidance computer had 4KB of RAM. Your smartphone has millions of times more computing power. We’ve built tools and frameworks that genuinely make many aspects of development easier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet demand for software far exceeds our ability to create it. Every organization needs more software than it can build. The backlog of desired features and new initiatives grows faster than development teams can address it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This tension—powerful tools yet insufficient capacity—keeps the dream alive. Business leaders look at the backlog and think, “There must be a way to go faster, to enable more people to contribute.” That’s a reasonable thought. It leads naturally to enthusiasm for any tool or approach that promises to democratize software creation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The challenge is that software development isn’t primarily constrained by typing speed or syntax knowledge. It’s constrained by the thinking required to handle complexity well. Faster typing doesn’t help when you’re thinking through how to handle concurrent database updates. Simpler syntax doesn’t help when you’re reasoning about security implications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what should leaders do with this understanding?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understanding this pattern changes how you evaluate new tools and approaches. When someone promises that their platform will let business users build applications without developers, you can appreciate the aspiration while maintaining realistic expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right question isn’t “Will this eliminate our need for developers?” The right questions are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These questions acknowledge that development involves irreducible complexity while remaining open to tools that provide genuine leverage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And they point to something deeper about the nature of software work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This fifty-year pattern teaches us something fundamental about software development itself. If the problem were primarily mechanical—too much typing, too complex syntax, too many steps—we would have solved it by now. COBOL made syntax readable. CASE tools eliminated typing. Visual tools eliminated syntax. AI can now generate entire functions from descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each advancement addressed a real friction point. Yet the fundamental challenge persists because it’s not mechanical. It’s intellectual. Software development is thinking made tangible. The artifacts we create—whether COBOL programs, Delphi forms, or Python scripts—are the visible outcome of invisible reasoning about complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can’t shortcut that reasoning any more than you can shortcut the reasoning required to design a building or diagnose a medical condition. Better tools help. Experience helps. But someone must still think it through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So how should we move forward, knowing all this?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next wave of development tools will arrive. Some will provide genuine value. Some will repeat familiar promises with new technology. Having perspective on this recurring pattern helps you engage with new tools productively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use AI assistants. Evaluate low-code platforms. Experiment with new frameworks. But invest primarily in your people’s ability to think clearly about complexity. That capability remains the constraining factor, just as it was during the Apollo program.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The moon landing happened because brilliant people thought carefully about every detail of an extraordinarily complex challenge. They wrote software by hand because that was the available tool. If they’d had better tools, they would have used them gladly. But the tools wouldn’t have eliminated their need to think through the complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re still in that same fundamental situation. We have better tools—vastly better tools—but the thinking remains essential.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps the recurring dream of replacing developers isn’t a mistake. Perhaps it’s a necessary optimism that drives tool creation. Each attempt to make development more accessible produces tools that genuinely help. The dream doesn’t come true as imagined, but pursuing it creates value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;COBOL didn’t let business analysts write programs, but it did enable a generation of developers to build business systems effectively. CASE tools didn’t generate complete applications, but they advanced our thinking about visual modeling. Visual Basic didn’t eliminate professional developers, but it brought application development to more people. AI won’t replace developers, but it will change how we work in meaningful ways.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pattern continues because the dream reflects a legitimate need. We genuinely require faster, more efficient ways to create software. We just keep discovering that the constraint isn’t the tool—it’s the complexity of the problems we’re trying to solve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understanding this doesn’t mean rejecting new tools. It means using them with clear expectations about what they can provide and what will always require human judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's talk about your real situation. Want to accelerate delivery, remove technical blockers, or validate whether an idea deserves more investment? Book a short conversation (20 min): I listen to your context and give 1–2 practical recommendations—no pitch, no obligation. If it fits, we continue; if not, you leave with clarity. Confidential and direct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prefer email? Write me: sns@caimito.net&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.caimito.net/en/blog/2025/12/07/the-recurring-dream-of-replacing-developers.html"/><published>2026-01-17T14:31:33+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46659550</id><title>An Elizabethan mansion's secrets for staying warm</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:39:01.083816+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b42e10265ba205d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;'The past is an underused tool': An Elizabethan mansion's secrets for staying warm&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a bleak, deadly period of cold weather known as the Little Ice Age, clever Elizabethan designs helped keep a magnificent stately home unusually warm. The house has lessons for how we can heat our homes more efficiently today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;England's longest river was usually flowing freely. But on New Year's Eve in 1564, the River Thames was frozen solid, from bank to bank. Bonfires crackled on the stuck-fast surface, oxen roasted on spits, and people danced on the ice. Some accounts say that Queen Elizabeth I even practised archery on the glacial river. This sort of thing wasn't a one off. It had happened before: King Henry VIII and his queen had dashed downriver in a sleigh nearly three decades previously in 1537.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These frosty conditions were the result of a climatic plot twist roughly between the 14th and 19th centuries, known today as the Little Ice Age. As well as festivals on the ice, this prolonged cold period brought periods of famine, and frightening unseasonable frosts. Soldiers froze to death in the middle of the European summer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cold forced Europeans to develop new ways of coping with extreme weather. One of the best-studied examples of architectural adaptation is Hardwick Hall in Derbyshire, England – a building whose design is a carefully choreographed effort to keep as warm as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The same tricks for more efficient heating can be used in modern designs, helping reduce our reliance on fossil fuels today. And they can even inspire small changes in our existing homes to keep temperatures cosier through the winter without turning up the thermostat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;An 'exceptional' house&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I drive the long, meandering driveway uphill to the house, confronted by the occasional long-horn cattle grazing between leafless oak trees. At the crest of the hill, I'm met with a striking sight: not one hall, but two.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hardwick "old" Hall is massive, despite its ruinous state. I can tell it's been repeatedly extended over the years, as the bricks are misaligned at the joins of each extension and the windows are mismatched in style and size across the facade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What caused the Little Ice Age?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It appears there's no single cause of the Little Ice Age, but a deadly and complex combination. Scientists have found evidence for reduced solar activity, increased volcanic eruptions, changes in ocean circulation and the natural fluctuations within the global climate system. In addition, the arrival of the Europeans in North America in the late 15th Century led to an estimated 56 million deaths of indigenous peoples, resulting in widespread abandonment of farming and regrowth of forests. More trees mean less planet-warming gases were circulating in the atmosphere, reducing the global average temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hardwick "new" Hall is a few dozen metres away. This pale yellow manor was built in the 1590s and is eye-pleasingly symmetrical, complete with three-story turrets and huge expanses of glass. Whoever quipped at the time of its construction that it was "more window than wall" was right. It is a magnificent display of wealth, built in a time when glass was extremely expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elizabeth (Bess), Countess of Shrewsbury, was the woman who had deep enough pockets to build it. She was mid-way through extending the massive, rambling Hardwick "old" Hall, but for some reason or another, stopped midway through and began afresh. The experts I spoke to say we don't know why she did that, but theories range from coming into money when her husband died and feeling the need to have a house in keeping with her elevated status, to using what she'd learnt in previous builds to design a house warm and cosy for a lady approaching her seventies and living through the Little Ice Age.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The late 16th Century is really one of the coldest stretches of the Little Ice Age, and it's bitterly cold in England," says Dagomar Degroot, professor of environmental history at Georgetown University in Washington, DC, and author of The Frigid Golden Age.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Global average temperatures during the Little Ice Age dipped "at most" by 0.5C (less than 0.9F), with impacts mostly documented in the northern hemisphere. That figure is an average over about five centuries, so temperatures would have swung more dramatically year to year and region to region.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Turning to the Sun&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A key difference between the old hall and the new hall is their orientation in relation to the Sun. The old hall is just off east-west. The new hall has been rotated by about 90 degrees, which means it can soak up much more sunshine and, therefore, heat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The incredible thing about Hardwick [new Hall] is… when you set it on the compass, it's almost exactly north-south," says Ranald Lawrence, a lecturer in architecture at the University of Liverpool in the UK. He's also published papers on Hardwick's design and thermal comfort. "And," he adds, "the whole internal planning of the [new] house is then based around that geometry."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bess moved around the rooms, following the Sun's path. Her mornings were spent walking the 63m (200ft) east-facing Long Gallery, where the bright morning light hits. The afternoon and evening Sun illuminates the south-western flank of the building, where Bess' bed chambers were. And the darkest, coldest corner of the house in the north-west was where the kitchens were placed, which would have been handy in keeping food cool and fresh.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I experience this first hand as I walk around – the kitchens are much colder. Elena Williams, the senior house and collections manager at The National Trust, a UK charity which preserves historic sites, notices too. "It's a well-designed building that is also designed around comfort and that uses the natural environment to do that," she says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Windows, walls and fireplaces&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's not just the orientation that helps keep the house warm. As Williams shows me around, she points out that some of the windows on the north of the building are actually "blind" or fake. She explains that on the outside, there is a window, but on the inside, it's lined with lead and blocked up. Unlike south-facing windows, north-facing windows bring little thermal benefit, even in summer, Lawrence says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pretty much all the fireplaces I see are also built on the central spine of the building, meaning not much heat would be lost to the windows or exterior wall. It's not until we take a door through this spine that I realise that the girth of it is staggering – 1.37m (4.5ft) thick. This is yet another trick to keep its inhabitants warm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"You have thermal mass, effectively," Lawrence says. "So something heavy like brick or stone, like you have at Hardwick, stores the heat from the fire and gives it out 12 hours later."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All these construction techniques appear to have made a difference. Lawrence has measured the temperature difference between inside and outside in modern times and depending on the season and weather, he told me it can feel around 10C (18F) warmer inside on a cold winter's day. Other, typical Elizabethan houses, he estimates, would have only feel 2-3C (3.6-5.4F) warmer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Tudors had other coping mechanisms, Williams says – like lining the walls with thick tapestries – adding further thermal mass and keeping out the drafts. Curtains were hung around the beds and over some of the windows too. And Elizabethan fashion of giant neck ruffs and layers and layers of linens, thick velvet and fur all helped people like Bess keep warm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other large and flashy manors at the time were using some of the same solar strategies. But Lawrence believes Hardwick is "exceptional" in the way these elements are carefully integrated and brought together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though Lawrence says there is no written evidence to suggest that the architectural designs were purposeful, he thinks that "it can't be coincidence". Williams agrees. "I think they definitely thought about using the Sun in the design of Hardwick," she says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All this despite the fact that the Elizabethans may have been unaware that they were living through what is now known as the Little Ice Age, says Degroot. "Why would I expect somebody living 400 years ago would realise that their climate was 0.5C colder than the climate had been in their mother's or father's lifetime?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Lessons for modern times&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are still lessons we can learn today when we build new homes and in the way we use the ones we've already got – especially with the need to heat and cool our homes more efficiently in order to save money and tackle climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The past is an underused tool," Degroot says. "I think by trying to identify the complex and diverse ways in which people responded to history's climate changes, we can come up with new tools for understanding how we might respond in the future and for identifying responses that are constructive versus destructive."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brutalist architects Peter and Alison Smithson knew of and even admired Hardwick Hall. Some academics claim that it likely inspired their own designs, like the Solar Pavillion, in south-west England, which is only has glass on its east, west and south-facing walls. Sun-soaking designs aren't just the preserve of the rich, though. One of London's most striking council estates is on Alexandria Road in Camden, in the north of the city, and Lawrence says it too features south facing terraces with lots of concrete to store the Sun's heat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But on the whole, he tells me, we generally don't use these Elizabethan building secrets. Instead, we use air conditioning and heating in an attempt to override building designs that are poorly suited to their climate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Our assumption that the solution to all of our problems is technological," Lawrence says. Glass box skyscrapers, now common in both cold and hot climates, are a good example of this. In winter, heat escapes through the glass, and require a lot of heating. Conversely in summer, the glass traps the heat – like a greenhouse – and require massive amounts of energy for cooling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But without taking apart our existing housing and building it again from scratch, there are also micro-adjustments we can make.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hacks to keep your home warmer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The homes heated without fossil fuels&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How living in a cold home affects your health&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I get a compass out at my house – for the first time – and begin to think about how I could follow the Sun's path throughout the day. Since it's winter, and cold, I move my desk to a south-eastern window. It brightens the mornings and if I wear another layer, I find I can lower the thermostat by 2C (3.6F). Longer term, I've been thinking about planting a tree just outside. In a couple of decades, it would shade my house from scorching heatwaves that are predicted to be much more common because of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are modest changes, imperceptible to most, and they won't enable us to forgo active heating and cooling entirely. But they do echo a way of thinking which, today, is oft ignored. Hardwick Hall was designed with Sun, season and temperature in mind. It paid attention to the world outside its walls. As the climate becomes more volatile, architecture that works with its environment feels more urgent than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For essential climate news and hopeful developments to your inbox, sign up to the Future Earth newsletter, while The Essential List delivers a handpicked selection of features and insights twice a week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more science, technology, environment and health stories from the BBC, follow us on Facebook and Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20260116-an-elizabethan-mansions-secrets-for-staying-warm"/><published>2026-01-17T16:53:24+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46660543</id><title>Raising money fucked me up</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:39:00.713827+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7d4e111769e460bd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About four months ago I quit my job at Doublepoint and decided to start my own thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'd been working on a little project with Pedrique (who would become my co-founder) for a bit over half-a-year and decided I had enough signal to determine he was someone I wanted to start a business with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was excited about the idea we were working on at the time, but being truly honest about my motivations, I mostly wanted to run my own thing. In a dream world I'd have had the "idea of my life" while working at PostHog or Doublepoint and have gone on to build that with maximum conviction but this wasn't the case, so I got tired of waiting for a spark and decided to go out and make it happen, with the idea we were working on being our best bet at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since I'd just quit my job, I had my finances well in order. Thus, my ideal scenario would have been to work on the idea we had the MVP for, try to get it off the ground, and if that didn't work, try something else, then something else, until something did indeed get off the ground, and only at that point we would consider whether or not to raise VC funding, depending on whether it made sense or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My ideal scenario wasn't going to work for Pedrique, though. He had told me for a while that the money he had saved up for trying to build his own thing was running out and that soon he'd need to start freelancing or something to make some income in order to sustain the search for a little longer. Prior to us working together, he had a bit of success with his MicroSaaS products but only just enough to increase his personal runway, which was now reasonably short.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We had spoken about this before, but with me now being 110% in, we had to do something about it. I had just come in full-time so we weren't about to go back to a dynamic where one person was full-time and the other part-time because they needed to make ends meet. The decision then became clear: we're gonna raise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At that point, it was an easy decision to make. Again, we have two co-founders who have a lot of confidence in each other, and we don't want to let the opportunity pass us by. So while this wasn't my ideal choice, we were a business now and this was the best decision for the company. "Just don't die" goes the advice I think, and Skald had just then been born.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so raise we did. We brought in four phenomenal angels, including, and this is relevant, my last few bosses (PostHog co-founders James and Tim and Doublepoint co-founder Ohto), and then decided to look for an early-stage fund. We eventually landed with Broom Ventures and passed up on a few other opportunities to limit dilution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Great, right? I didn't need a salary yet, but for equality purposes, I now had one. Our investors are amazing. James and Ohto have been particularly helpful as angels (thank you!), and our investors are all founders of successful companies, including Jeff and Dan, the Broom GPs. We're super early, but Broom has been massively helpful and all-around just a great hands-off VC to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most importantly, none of them put any pressure on us. All understand the nature of pre-seed investing well, and that can't be said about all the potential investors we took meetings with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So some time passes and we decide to pivot. We're really excited about the new idea. We launch and get a bit of early traction. The open source project is doing well, but we're struggling to monetize. We fail to close a few customers and the traction wanes a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then I find myself fucked in the head.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here's where we get to the point that I'm not sure I should be talking publicly about. Does this hurt my image a bit? Maybe. Do I look like I'm not cut for this? Potentially. But I've always appreciated when people share about the process rather than just talking about things in hindsight, and reflecting while things are happening + being super transparent publicly is how I am. You're witnessing my growth, live, as I type these words.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway, so what happened is I found myself spending days with my head spinning, searching for ideas. I'm angry, I'm annoyed, and I'm not being super productive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I dug deeper into these feelings, I realized I was feeling pressured. We weren't making that much money, we weren't growing super fast. Then you look around and see "startup X gets to $1M ARR a month after launch" and shit like that and I'm feeling terrible about how we're barely growing. I'm thinking people that I really respect and admire have placed a bet on me and I'm letting them down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Except they're not saying this, I am.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's an interesting reflection that came up in a discussion between me and my girlfriend a few months prior that I realized applied to me, but in reverse. It's much more comfortable to be the person that "could be X" than to be the person that tries to actually do it. We were speaking about this regarding people who have a clear innate talent for something like music or sports but don't practice at all. Everyone says things like "you'd be the best at this if you just practiced more" but then they never do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thing is: it's a lot easier to live your life thinking you could have done X if you wanted to, than to "disappoint" these people that believed in you by trying and failing. You can always lean on this idea in your head of what you could have been, and how everyone believed in you so it must be true, but you just chose not to follow that path.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my case, I found myself on the other side of that coin. Throughout my career, I've always had really high ownership roles, and have been actively involved in a couple 0 to 1 journeys. This led me throughout my career to get many comments about how great of a founder I'd be or how I have the "founder profile". I led teams, I wore a bunch of different hats, I worked hard as fuck, and I always thought about the big picture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those traits led my former bosses to then invest in me, and now suddenly I have to, in my head, live up to all of this. I can no longer take solace in some excuse like "I could have been a founder but working full-time was the best financial decision (it almost always is) so I never started my own thing". I set foot down a path from which there's no return. I've begun my attempt. I can of course stop and try again later. But from now on, I'm either gonna be a successful founder, or I'm not. And if I'm not, I'll have to deal with having broken with the expectations that people had of me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's a lot to unpack here, including what "success" means, and how most of what I say are other people's expectations are actually my own projected onto them (I've learned this about my relationship with my father too), but this post is already a bit too long so I'll save those for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the whole point here is not just that having raised this money from friends my head got a bit messy, but that I started to actually operate in a way that is counterproductive for my startup, while thinking I was actually doing what was best.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ideas we considered when pivoting were looked more through a lens of "how big does this feel" rather than "what problem does this solve and for who". The slow growth was eating me, and while slow growth is terrible and can be a sign that you're on the wrong path it needs to be looked at from an objectively strategic lens. Didn't we say we were going to build an open source community and only later focus on monetization? Is that a viable strategy? Do we actually have a sound plan? Those were the things I should have been thinking about, rather than looping on "we need something that grows faster".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The people who invested in us, invested in us, not whatever idea we pitched them. And the best thing we can do is to follow our own process for building a great business based on what we believe and know, rather than focusing on making numbers look good so I can feel more relieved the next time I send over an investor update.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have a ton to learn, particularly about sales (since we're both engineers), so we can't just be building shit for the sake of building shit because that's our comfort zone. But if our process is slower than company X on TechCrunch, that's fine. It's a marathon after all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So after probably breaking many rules about what a founder should talk about publicly, what was my whole goal here? I mean, the main thing for me with posts like this is to get things off my chest. I've always said that the reason I publish writing that includes poems about my breakup, stories about falling in love, posts about my insecurities, and reflections about my dreams is that by there being the possibility of someone reading them (because technically it could be the case that nobody does) I can truly be who I really am in my day-to-day life. If I'm ok with there being the possibility of a friend I'll meet later today having read about how I felt during my last breakup, I can be myself with them without reservations, because I've made myself available to be seen. That's always been really freeing to me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a side effect, I'd hope that if this does get read by some people, particularly those starting or looking to start a business, that they can reflect about themselves, their lives, and their companies through listening to my story. I thought about writing a short bullet list about lessons I learned from raising money and dealing with its aftermath here, but honestly, that's best left to the reader to figure out. We're all different, and how one person reacts to a set of circumstances will differ from someone else. Some people don't feel pressure at all, or at least not from friends or investors. Or they only respond positively to pressure (because it certainly has benefits too). Maybe they're better off than me. Maybe they're not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is my story, after all. I wish you the best of luck with yours.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;P.S. I'm doing good now. I'm motivated and sharp. If someone finds themselves in a similar situation, feel free to shoot me an email if you're keen to talk. Happy to go over what was useful for me, which fell outside of the scope of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.yakkomajuri.com/blog/raising-money-fucked-me-up"/><published>2026-01-17T18:29:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46661897</id><title>Kip: A programming language based on grammatical cases of Turkish</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:39:00.339918+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="4a813f1d0f75a8ca"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kip (meaning "grammatical mood" in Turkish) is an experimental programming language that uses Turkish grammatical cases as part of its type system. It demonstrates how natural language morphology—specifically Turkish noun cases and vowel harmony—can be integrated into programming language design.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a research/educational project exploring the intersection of linguistics and type theory, not a production programming language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is also a tutorial in Turkish and a tutorial in English that explains how to write Kip programs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kip is experimental. Expect changes in syntax and behavior over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For you to get a taste of what Kip looks like, here is an example program that prompts the user to enter a number and then prints that many of the Fibonacci numbers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* İlk n Fibonacci sayısını yazdırır. *)
(bu tam-sayıyı) (şu tam-sayıyı) (o tam-sayıyı) işlemek,
  (onla 0'ın eşitliği) doğruysa,
    durmaktır,
  yanlışsa,
    bunu yazıp,
    şunu (bunla şunun toplamını) (onla 1'in farkını) işlemektir.

çalıştırmak,
  "Bir sayı girin:" yazıp,
  isim olarak okuyup,
  ((ismin tam-sayı-hali)
    yokluksa,
      "Geçersiz sayı." yazmaktır,
    n'nin varlığıysa,
      0'ı 1'i n'yi işlemektir).

çalıştır.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Language Features&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Installation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Example Program&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WASM Playground&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bytecode Cache&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Project Structure&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Testing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Morphological Analysis&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;License&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kip uses Turkish noun cases (ismin halleri) to determine argument relationships in function calls:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Case&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Turkish Name&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Suffix&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Example&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Nominative&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Yalın hal&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;(none)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;sıfır&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Accusative&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-i hali&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-i, -ı, -u, -ü&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;sayıyı&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Dative&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-e hali&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-e, -a&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;sayıya&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Locative&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-de hali&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-de, -da, -te, -ta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;listede&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ablative&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-den hali&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-den, -dan, -ten, -tan&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;listeden&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Genitive&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tamlayan eki&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-in, -ın, -un, -ün&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;sayının&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Instrumental&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-le eki&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-le, -la, ile&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;sayıyla&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Possessive (3s)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tamlanan eki&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-i, -ı, -u, -ü, -si, -sı&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;ardılı&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because Turkish cases mark grammatical relationships explicitly, Kip allows flexible argument ordering. These two calls are equivalent:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(5'le 3'ün farkını) yaz.
(3'ün 5'le farkını) yaz.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As long as arguments have different case suffixes or different types, Kip can determine which argument is which.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Define algebraic data types with Turkish syntax:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bir doğruluk ya doğru ya da yanlış olabilir.

Bir doğal-sayı
ya sıfır
ya da bir doğal-sayının ardılı
olabilir.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Type variables are supported for generic data structures:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bir (öğe listesi)
ya boş
ya da bir öğenin bir öğe listesine eki
olabilir.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pattern match using the conditional suffix &lt;code&gt;-sa/-se&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(bu doğruluğun) tersi,
  bu doğruysa, yanlış,
  yanlışsa, doğrudur.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supports nested pattern matching, binders, and wildcard patterns (&lt;code&gt;değilse&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(bu doğal-sayının) kopyası,
  bu sıfırsa, sıfır,
  öncülün ardılıysa, öncülün ardılıdır.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Define named constants with &lt;code&gt;diyelim&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sıfırın ardılına bir diyelim.
birin ardılına iki diyelim.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sequencing with &lt;code&gt;-ip/-ıp/-up/-üp&lt;/code&gt; suffixes and binding with &lt;code&gt;olarak&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;selamlamak,
  isim olarak okuyup,
  ("Merhaba "yla ismin birleşimini) yazmaktır.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Integers (&lt;code&gt;tam-sayı&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Arithmetic: &lt;code&gt;toplamı&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;farkı&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;çarpımı&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Comparison: &lt;code&gt;eşitliği&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;küçüklüğü&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;büyüklüğü&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Other: &lt;code&gt;öncülü&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;sıfırlığı&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;faktöriyeli&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strings (&lt;code&gt;dizge&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;uzunluğu&lt;/code&gt;- length&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;birleşimi&lt;/code&gt;- concatenation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;tam-sayı-hali&lt;/code&gt;- parse as integer&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I/O:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;yazmak&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;yaz&lt;/code&gt;- print to stdout&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;okumak&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;oku&lt;/code&gt;- read from stdin&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* This is a comment *)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;5'i yaz.              (* Integer literal with case suffix *)
"merhaba"'yı yaz.     (* String literal with case suffix *)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Foma - finite-state morphology toolkit&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;macOS: &lt;code&gt;brew install foma&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Debian/Ubuntu: &lt;code&gt;apt install foma libfoma-dev&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Fedora: &lt;code&gt;dnf install foma foma-devel&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;macOS: &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Stack - Haskell build tool&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;See haskellstack.org&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you only want to explore the language, you can start with &lt;code&gt;stack exec kip&lt;/code&gt; after a successful build.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clone this repository, then:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Quick install (macOS/Linux)
chmod +x install.sh
./install.sh

# Or manual build
stack build&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The TRmorph transducer is bundled at &lt;code&gt;vendor/trmorph.fst&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Start REPL
stack exec kip

# Execute a file
stack exec kip -- --exec path/to/file.kip

# Install to PATH
stack install&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A browser playground build is available under &lt;code&gt;playground/&lt;/code&gt;. It compiles the
non-interactive runner (&lt;code&gt;kip-playground&lt;/code&gt;) to &lt;code&gt;wasm32-wasi&lt;/code&gt; and ships a small
HTML/JS harness that runs Kip in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See &lt;code&gt;playground/README.md&lt;/code&gt; for prerequisites, toolchain setup, and build steps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kip stores a cached, type-checked version of each &lt;code&gt;.kip&lt;/code&gt; file in a sibling &lt;code&gt;.iz&lt;/code&gt; file. When you run a file again, Kip will reuse the &lt;code&gt;.iz&lt;/code&gt; cache if both the source and its loaded dependencies are unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to force a fresh parse and type-check, delete the &lt;code&gt;.iz&lt;/code&gt; file next to the source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Important&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;.iz&lt;/code&gt; files include a compiler hash. If the compiler changes, the cache is invalidated automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* Natural numbers *)
Bir doğal-sayı
ya sıfır
ya da bir doğal-sayının ardılı
olabilir.

(* Define some constants *)
sıfırın ardılına bir diyelim.
birin ardılına iki diyelim.
ikinin ardılına üç diyelim.

(* Addition function *)
(bu doğal-sayıyla) (şu doğal-sayının) toplamı,
  bu sıfırsa,
    şu,
  öncülün ardılıysa,
    (öncülle) (şunun ardılının) toplamıdır.

(* Print result *)
(ikiyle üçün toplamını) yaz.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;app/
└── Main.hs            - CLI entry point

src/
├── Kip/
│   ├── AST.hs         - Abstract syntax tree
│   ├── Cache.hs       - .iz cache handling
│   ├── Eval.hs        - Interpreter
│   ├── Parser.hs      - Parser
│   ├── Render.hs      - Pretty-printing with morphological inflection
│   └── TypeCheck.hs   - Type checker validating grammatical case usage
└── Language/
    └── Foma.hs        - Haskell bindings to Foma via FFI

lib/
├── giriş.kip          - Prelude module loaded by default
├── temel.kip           - Core types
├── temel-doğruluk.kip  - Boolean functions
├── temel-dizge.kip     - String functions
├── temel-etki.kip      - I/O primitives
├── temel-liste.kip     - List functions
└── temel-tam-sayı.kip  - Integer functions

tests/
├── succeed/            - Passing golden tests (.kip + .out + optional .in)
└── fail/               - Failing golden tests (.kip + .err)

vendor/
└── trmorph.fst        - TRmorph transducer
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;stack test&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tests are in &lt;code&gt;tests/succeed/&lt;/code&gt; (expected to pass) and &lt;code&gt;tests/fail/&lt;/code&gt; (expected to fail).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kip uses TRmorph for Turkish morphological analysis. When a word has multiple possible parses (e.g., "takası" could be "taka + possessive" or "takas + accusative"), Kip carries all candidates through parsing and resolves ambiguity during type checking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For intentionally ambiguous words, use an apostrophe to force a specific parse: &lt;code&gt;taka'sı&lt;/code&gt; vs &lt;code&gt;takas'ı&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See LICENSE file.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/kip-dili/kip"/><published>2026-01-17T20:44:52+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46662399</id><title>Show HN: Speed Miners – A tiny RTS resource mini-game</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:39:00.126327+00:00</updated><link href="https://speedminers.fun/"/><published>2026-01-17T21:40:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46663268</id><title>No knives, only cook knives</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:39:00.054693+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://kellykozakandjoshdonald.substack.com/p/no-knives-only-cook-knives"/><published>2026-01-17T23:38:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46663338</id><title>If you put Apple icons in reverse it looks like someone getting good at design</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:59.585609+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f8eb8f2f2d953eed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To use the Mastodon web application, please enable JavaScript. Alternatively, try one of the native apps for Mastodon for your platform.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://mastodon.social/@heliographe_studio/115890819509545391"/><published>2026-01-17T23:47:16+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46663507</id><title>Computer Systems Security 6.566 / Spring 2024</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:59.444876+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="27522c412109a2bc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lectures cover a broad overview of systems security together with a deeper focus on several topics: isolation techniques, privilege separation, dealing with buggy code, networked and distributed systems, and human-focused security and privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Links to notes etc. on future days are copies of materials from last year, to give you an idea of what the future will bring. We will update the notes as the course progresses. The year of publication for class readings are shown in parentheses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Monday&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tuesday&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Wednesday&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Thursday&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Friday&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 5&lt;p&gt;First day of classes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 6&lt;p&gt;LEC 1: Introduction, threat models (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Optionally read Modern Android exploit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assigned: Lab 1: Buffer overflows&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 7&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 8&lt;p&gt;LEC 2: OS and VM isolation (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read about OS and VM isolation (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 9&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 12&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 13&lt;p&gt;LEC 3: Software fault isolation (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read about WebAssembly (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 14&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 15&lt;p&gt;LEC 4: Trusted hardware (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read BitLocker (2006), sections 1-2 (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 16&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 1 part 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 1 part 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 19&lt;p&gt;Presidents day&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 20&lt;p&gt;Monday schedule&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 21&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 22&lt;p&gt;LEC 5: CPU side-channels (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read Transient Execution Attacks and Defenses (2019) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assigned: Lab 2: Privilege separation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 23&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 1 all parts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 26&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 27&lt;p&gt;LEC 6: Privilege separation (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read OpenSSH (2003) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 28&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;feb 29&lt;p&gt;LEC 7: Data center infrastructure (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read Google Infrastructure Security (2023) and BeyondProd (2023) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 1&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 2 part 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 4&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 5&lt;p&gt;LEC 8: Mobile phone security (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read about iOS Security (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 6&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 7&lt;p&gt;LEC 9: Web security model (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read about web security (2022) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 8&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 2 parts 2+3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ADD DATE&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 11&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 12&lt;p&gt;LEC 10: Buffer overflow defenses (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read Baggy bounds checking (2009) + errata (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assigned: Lab 3: Symbolic execution&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 13&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 14&lt;p&gt;LEC 11: Symbolic execution (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read EXE: Automatically generating inputs of death (2006) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 15&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 2 all parts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 18&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 19&lt;p&gt;LEC 12: Verification (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read HACL* (2017) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 20&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 21&lt;p&gt;Quiz 1: Covers lectures 1-12 and labs 1-2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reference: Past quizzes, solutions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Materials: Open laptop&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time and Location: 2:30-4p in 45-230&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 22&lt;p&gt;Assigned: Lab 4: Browser security&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 25&lt;p&gt;Spring vacation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 26&lt;p&gt;Spring vacation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 27&lt;p&gt;Spring vacation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 28&lt;p&gt;Spring vacation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mar 29&lt;p&gt;Spring vacation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 1&lt;p&gt;REC 1 (anna): Getting started with lab 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time and Location: 4-5pm in 24-115&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 2&lt;p&gt;LEC 13 (guest): Supply chain security (Russ Cox) (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read Trusting Trust (1984) and Russ's blog post (2023), and optionally xz attack (2024)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 3&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 4&lt;p&gt;LEC 14: Network security (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read about network security (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 5&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 3 part 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 8&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 9&lt;p&gt;LEC 15: Secure channels (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read TLS 1.3 blog post (2018) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 10&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 11&lt;p&gt;LEC 16: Certificates (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read Let's Encrypt (2019) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 12&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 3 all parts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assigned: Lab 5: ACME + WebAuthn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 15&lt;p&gt;Patriots day&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 16&lt;p&gt;REC 2 (bill): Getting started with lab 4 (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time and Location: 2:30-4pm in 45-230&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 17&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 18&lt;p&gt;LEC 17: User authentication (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read U2F (2016) and optionally from U2F to passkeys (2023) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 19&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 4 part 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 22&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 23&lt;p&gt;LEC 18: Messaging security (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read Analysis of Signal (2019), sections 1-3 (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DROP DATE&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 24&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 25&lt;p&gt;LEC 19: Key transparency (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read CONIKS (2015) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 26&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 4 all parts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 29&lt;p&gt;REC 3 (sanjit): Getting started with lab 5, notes (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time and Location: 10-11am in 24-121&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;apr 30&lt;p&gt;LEC 20: Anonymous communication (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read Tor (2004) and blog posts 1, 2, and 3 (2012) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 1&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 2&lt;p&gt;LEC 21 (guest): Cybersecurity policy (Daniel Weitzner) (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read Keys under doormats (2015) and Cyber risk (2024)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 3&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 5 part 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 6&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 7&lt;p&gt;LEC 22: Security economics (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read Click trajectories (2011) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 8&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 9&lt;p&gt;LEC 23: Differential privacy (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preparation: Read PINQ (2009) (Question)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 10&lt;p&gt;DUE: Lab 5 all parts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 13&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 14&lt;p&gt;LEC 24 (guest): Information security in real life (Max Burkhardt) (video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last day of classes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 15&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 16&lt;p&gt;REC 4: Final exam review&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time and Location: 2:30-4pm in 32-123&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 17&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 20&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 21&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 22&lt;p&gt;Final exam: Emphasis on lectures 13-24 and labs 3-5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reference: Past quizzes, solutions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Materials: Open laptop&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time and Location: Johnson Ice Rink, 1:30-4:30pm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 23&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;may 24&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://css.csail.mit.edu/6.858/2024/"/><published>2026-01-18T00:09:43+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46663731</id><title>Data Activation Thoughts</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:59.366781+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3637c2303c80859b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;data activation thoughts&lt;/head&gt;17 Jan 2026&lt;p&gt;The landscape is shifting in recent years — it’s a cliche to start texts like this these days, but the fact that it’s a cliche doesn’t make it any less true.1 In 2019, the folks at Andreessen Horowitz wrote this about data (in a piece titled The Empty Promise of Data Moats): “Instead of getting stronger, the defensible moat erodes as the data corpus grows and the competition races to catch up.” (Trying to prove some data has value — I’ve experienced it firsthand.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LLMs have shifted where value comes from. It’s no longer enough to simply have proprietary data; what matters now is how effectively you can make that data useful to these systems (and therefore, to anything else that lives off that). So, if traditional data moats are eroding, the new competitive edge lies in data activation. The pressing question becomes: how quickly can you connect your proprietary data to LLMs in ways that demonstrably improve their performance (before someone else figures out how to replicate your insights without your data)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before we continue I want to think about a simple metaphor here — LLMs can ingest the data. They’ll happily consume every row and column you throw at them. But (and this is important) without the right transformation, they can’t metabolize it. The nutritional value passes through unabsorbed. They’re missing the “enzymes” I guess you can call it. Data activation is about providing those enzymes: converting raw information into a form the model can actually digest and turn into a capability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why this matters now (healthcare as case study)&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking specifically at healthcare data, the opportunity is immense — and let’s face it, time limited. Looking at OpenAI’s report from January 2026: more than 5% of all ChatGPT messages globally are healthcare-related. 25% of weekly active users ask health-related questions. More than 40 million people turn to ChatGPT daily for healthcare guidance (!!!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The big labs are clearly taking notice: within the span of a single week (January 2026), OpenAI launched “ChatGPT for Healthcare” (already rolling out to institutions like Cedars-Sinai, Memorial Sloan Kettering, and Stanford Medicine) and Anthropic announced “Claude for Healthcare” with HIPAA-ready infrastructure and native integrations to medical databases/ontologies (CMS Coverage Database, ICD-10, PubMed). To me, it looks like healthcare is now a primary battleground for frontier AI companies.2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yet, if you look at the numbers from OpenRouter, they claim that health remains “the most fragmented of the top categories”. What does this mean? According to OpenRouter, it signals both the domain’s complexity and the inadequacy of current general-purpose models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;One (potential) method for data activation&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;It seems that recent research already demonstrates that the bridge between structured medical data and improvements in LLM reasoning is working.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tables2Traces established a framework for converting raw, tabular patient-level data into contrastive reasoning traces that can be used for LLM fine-tuning. They tried to “mirror how a clinician would think” — what they did is pretty simple. For every patient record, they identified similar patients with different outcomes (someone similar who died and someone similar who survived). Once they had those triplets of patients they prompted a strong LLM to generate explanations for the divergence. These reasoning traces become fine-tuning data for smaller models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For their specific use-case they showed significant improvement (&amp;gt;17% in domain-specific MedQA and even generalization capabilities — they trained only on cardiovascular cases but noted improvement in other areas of medicine as well). The paper’s “simple vs. full” comparison also provides empirical evidence: naively converting tables to patient narratives doesn’t work (and can hurt performance). So the models actually need the structured reasoning scaffold — the contrastive comparison, together with the reasoning and quasi-counterfactual thinking, is what makes the difference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saying it a bit differently — they kind of show that the value in structured medical data is like potential energy trapped behind a dam. The power is real, but it just sits there. Naive table-to-text conversion doesn’t work; you’re essentially drilling a small hole in the dam and expecting electricity. The reasoning scaffold (in their case — contrastive comparison, counterfactual thinking) is the turbine. It converts stored potential into usable power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another work worth mentioning is EHR-R1. They synthesized 300k “high-quality” traces using a different method — something they call a “thinking-graph pipeline”: [1] extract medical entities from each patient’s longitudinal EHR (including free-text), [2] quantify associations between medical entities, then [3] map entities to medical ontology (UMLS concepts) and use graph search to recover medical relations that connect context entities to the target labels. They then prompted an LLM with the patient record plus these retrieved relations to produce a structured reasoning chain, which became the supervision data. The results? Their model outperforms strong commercial/open models, averaging &amp;gt;30 points over GPT-4o on EHR-Bench (which they also created).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another paper shows this scales pretty well: fine-tuned 8B parameter models have achieved 89.3% accuracy while being 85x cheaper than their 70B teacher models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I think the existence proof is established: structured EHR/biobank data can be transformed into reasoning supervision that measurably improves LLM clinical performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s still unclear&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think Tables2Traces proved feasibility in some sense, but synthetic traces are still in the “unverified” realm. This gap showed mostly in the way physicians treated those traces (mostly, they didn’t think the traces were very good). And there’s a deeper issue — recent work shows that traces can sometimes be “unfaithful,” meaning they don’t accurately reflect the actual basis for a decision. Plainly: the trace says one thing, the model’s decision is different.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth noting that these papers tend to show improvements on less capable models. That’s not an accident — showing improvements on stronger models is harder (or the improvements aren’t there). We should be honest about that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So the question that keeps bothering me: what’s the right transformation? The papers above offer some approaches — contrastive reasoning, knowledge graphs, ontology grounding. There are others being explored (RL-based methods, temporal modeling for longitudinal records). But I don’t have a clean answer. The dam metaphor still holds — the potential energy is real — but we’re still figuring out how to build the right turbine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking of cliches — I’m aware this piece is full of em-dashes, which have become a telltale sign of AI-assisted writing. But as Nabeel Qureshi pointed out, David Foster Wallace was doing this decades ago. The italics for emphasis, the informality, the casual speech tone. I’ll keep my em-dashes. ↩&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;In some sense, what once seemed like a disadvantage — healthcare’s lagging technological infrastructure — may now be an asset: a greenfield opportunity with less legacy baggage to work around. But that might be substance for a different post. ↩&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://galsapir.github.io/sparse-thoughts/2026/01/17/data_activation/"/><published>2026-01-18T00:49:40+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46664195</id><title>Profession by Isaac Asimov</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:58.809012+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a6c49133f1e056eb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Profession&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;by&lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"/&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Isaac Asimov’s Profession is an allegorical description of the manner in which education currently functions in our primitive western societies — abelard [1]&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Profession, copyright ©1957 by Street and Smith Publications, Inc., from ISAAC ASIMOV: THE COMPLETE STORIES OF VOL. 1 by Isaac Asimov. &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Another sci-fi short story at abelard.org: &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;pdf version to download &lt;p&gt;[657 kB, opens in new tab/window.]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;If you wish to customise your browser, to change the text size or see this page in black on white, &lt;p&gt;click here for instructions on what to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George Platen could not conceal the longing in his voice. It was too much to suppress. He said, “Tomorrow’s 1 May. Olympics!”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He rolled over on his stomach and peered over the foot of his bed at his roommate. Didn’t he feel it, too? Didn’t this make some impression on him?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George’s face was thin and had grown a trifle thinner in the nearly year and a half that he had been at the House. His figure was slight but the look in his blue eyes was as intense as it had ever been, and right now there was a trapped look in the way his fingers curled against the bedspread.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George’s roommate looked up briefly from his book and took the opportunity to adjust the light-level of the stretch of wall near his chair. His name was Hali Omani and he was a Nigerian by birth. His dark brown skin and massive features seemed made for calmness, and mention of the Olympics did not move him.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I know, George.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George owed much to Hali’s patience and kindness when it was needed, but even patience and kindness could be overdone.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Was this a time to sit there like a statue built of some dark, warm wood?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George wondered if he himself would grow like that after ten years here and rejected the thought violently. No!&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said defiantly, “I think you’ve forgotten what May means.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The other said,“I remember very well what it means. It means nothing! You’re the one who’s forgotten that. May means nothing to you, George Platen, and,' he added softly, “It means nothing to me, Hali Omani.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “The ships are coming in for recruits. By June, thousands and thousands will leave with millions of men and women heading for any world you can name, and all that means nothing?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Less than nothing. What do you want me to do about it, anyway?” Omani ran his finger along a difficult passage in the book he was reading and his lips moved soundlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George watched him. Damn it, he thought, yell scream; you can do that much. Kick at me, do anything.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was only that he wanted not to be so alone in his anger. He wanted not to be the only one so filled with resentment, not to be the only one dying a slow death.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was better those first weeks when the Universe was a small shell of vague light and sound pressing down upon him. It was better before Omani had wavered into view and dragged him back to a life that wasn’t worth living.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani! He was old! He was at least thirty. George thought: Will I be like that at thirty? Will I be like that in twelve years?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And because he was afraid he might be, he yelled at Omani, “Will you stop reading that fool book?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani turned a page and read on a few words, then lifted his head with its skullcap of crisply curled hair and said, “What?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What good does it do you to read the book?” He stepped forward, snorted “More electronics,” and slapped it out of Omani’s hands.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani got up slowly and picked up the book. He smoothed a crumpled page without visible rancor. “Call it the satisfaction of curiosity,” he said. “I understand a little of it today, perhaps a little more tomorrow. That’s a victory in a way.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“A victory. What kind of a victory? Is that what satisfies you in life? To get to know enough to be a quarter of a Registered Electronician by the time you’re sixty-five?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Perhaps by the time I’m thirty-five.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And then who’ll want you? Who’ll use you? Where will you go?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No one. No one. Nowhere. I’ll stay here and read other books.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And that satisfies you? Tell me! You’ve dragged me to class. You’ve got me to reading and memorizing, too. For what? There’s nothing in it that satisfies me.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What good will it do you to deny yourself satisfaction?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It means I’ll quit the whole farce. I’ll do as I planned to do in the beginning before you dovey-lovied me out of it. I’m going to force them to — to —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani put down his book. He let the other run down and then said, “To what, George?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“To correct a miscarriage of justice. A frame-up. I’ll get that Antonelli and force him to admit he — he —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani shook his head. “Everyone who comes here insists it’s a mistake. I thought you’d passed that stage.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Don’t call it a stage,” said George violently. “In my case, it’s a fact. I’ve told you —�”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You’ve told me, but in your heart you know no one made any mistake as far as you were concerned.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Because no one will admit it? You think any of them would admit a mistake unless they were forced to? — Well: I’ll force them.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was May that was doing this to George; it was Olympics month. He felt it bring the old wildness back and he couldn’t stop it. He didn’t want to stop it. He had been in danger of forgetting.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “I was going to be a Computer Programmer and I can be one. I could be one today, regardless of what they say analysis shows.” He pounded his mattress. “They’re wrong. They must be.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“The analysts are never wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“They must be. Do you doubt my intelligence?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Intelligence hasn’t one thing to do with it. Haven’t you been told that often enough? Can’t you understand that?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George rolled away, lay on his back, and stared somberly at the ceiling.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What did you want to be, Hali?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I had no fixed plans. Hydroponicist would have suited me, I suppose.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Did you think you could make it?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I wasn’t sure.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George had never asked personal questions of Omani before. It struck him as queer, almost unnatural, that other people had had ambitions and ended here. Hydroponicist!&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “Did you think you’d make this?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No, but here I am just the same.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And you’re satisfied. Really, really satisfied. You’re happy. You love it. You wouldn’t be anywhere else.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Slowly, Omani got to his feet. Carefully, he began to unmake his bed. He said, “George, you’re a hard case. You’re knocking yourself out because you won’t accept the facts about yourself. George, you’re here in what you call the House, but I’ve never heard you give it its full title. Say it, George, say it. Then go to bed and sleep this off.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George gritted his teeth and showed them. He choked out, “No!”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Then I will,” said Omani, and he did. He shaped each syllable carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George was bitterly ashamed at the sound of it. He turned his head away.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;For most of the first eighteen years of his life, George Platen had headed firmly in one direction, that of Registered Computer Programmer. There were those in his crowd who spoke wisely of Spationautics, Refrigeration Technology, Transportation Control, and even Administration. But George held firm.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He argued relative merits as vigorously as any of them, and why not? Education Day loomed ahead of them and was the great fact of their existence. It approached steadily, as fixed and certain as the calendar — the first day of November of the year following one’s eighteenth birthday. After that day, there were other topics of conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;One could discuss with others some detail of the profession, or the virtues of one’s wife and children, or the fate of one’s space-polo team, or one’s experiences in the Olympics. Before Education Day, however, there was only one topic that unfailingly and unwearyingly held everyone’s interest, and that was Education Day.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What are you going for? Think you’ll make it? Heck, that’s no good. Look at the records; quota’s been cut. Logistics now—”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Or Hypermechanics now — Or Communications now — Or Gravitics now —&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Especially Gravitics at the moment. Everyone had been talking about Gravitics in the few years just before George’s Education Day because of the development of the Gravitic power engine.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Any world within ten light-years of a dwarf star, everyone said, would give its eyeteeth for any kind of Registered Gravitics Engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The thought of that never bothered George. Sure it would; all the eyeteeth it could scare up. But George had also heard what had happened before in a newly developed technique. Rationalization and simplification followed in a flood. New models each year; new types of gravitic engines; new principles. Then all those eyeteeth gentlemen would find themselves out of date and superseded by later models with later educations. The first group would then have to settle down to unskilled labor or ship out to some backwoods world that wasn’t quite caught up yet.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Now Computer Programmers were in steady demand year after year, century after century. The demand never reached wild peaks; there was never a howling bull market for Programmers; but the demand climbed steadily as new worlds opened up and as older worlds grew more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He had argued with Stubby Trevelyan about that constantly. As best friends, their arguments had to be constant and vitriolic and, of course, neither ever persuaded or was persuaded.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But then Trevelyan had had a father who was a Registered Metallurgist and had actually served on one of the Outworlds, and a grandfather who had also been a Registered Metallurgist. He himself was intent on becoming a Registered Metallurgist almost as a matter of family right and was firmly convinced that any other profession was a shade less than respectable.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“There’ll always be metal, he said, “and there’s an accomplishment in molding alloys to specification and watching structures grow. Now what’s a Programmer going to be doing? Sitting at a coder all day long, feeding some fool mile-long machine.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Even at sixteen, George had learned to be practical. He said simply, “There’ll be a million Metallurgists put out along with you.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Because it’s good. A good profession. The best.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But you get crowded out, Stubby. You can be way back in line. Any world can tape out its own Metallurgists, and the market for advanced Earth models isn’t so big. And it’s mostly the small worlds that want them. You know what per cent of the turn-out of Registered Metallurgists get tabbed for worlds with a Grade A rating. I looked it up. It’s just 13.3 per cent. That means you’ll have seven chances in eight of being stuck in some world that just about has running water. You may even be stuck on Earth; 2.3 per cent are.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan said belligerently, “There’s no disgrace in staying on Earth. Earth needs technicians, too. Good ones.” His grandfather had been an Earth-bound Metallurgist, and Trevelyan lifted his finger to his upper lip and dabbed at an as yet nonexistent mustache.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George knew about Trevelyan’s grandfather and, considering the Earth-bound position of his own ancestry, was in no mood to sneer. He said diplomatically, “No intellectual disgrace. Of course not. But it’s nice to get into a Grade A world, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan frowned. “If only one in a million makes it, what makes you think you’ll make it?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said guardedly, “I’ll make it.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He never dared tell anyone; not Trevelyan; not his parents; of exactly what he was doing that made him so confident. But he wasn’t worried. He was simply confident (that was the worst of the memories he had in the hopeless days afterward). He was as blandly confident as the average eight-year-old kid approaching Reading Day — that childhood preview of Education Day.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Of course, Reading Day had been different. Partly, there was the simple fact of childhood. A boy of eight takes many extraordinary things in stride. One day you can’t read and the next day you can. That’s just the way things are. Like the sun shining.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And then not so much depended upon it. There were no recruiters just ahead, waiting and jostling for the lists and scores on the coming Olympics. A boy or girl who goes through the Reading Day is just someone who has ten more years of undifferentiated living upon Earth’s crawling surface; just someone who returns to his family with one new ability.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;By the time Education Day came, ten years later, George wasn’t even sure of most of the details of his own Reading Day.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Most clearly of all, he remembered it to be a dismal September day with a mild rain falling. (September for Reading Day; November for. Education Day; May for Olympics. They made nursery rhymes out of it.) George had dressed by the wall lights, with his parents far more excited than he himself was. His father was a Registered Pipe Fitter and had found his occupation on Earth. This fact had always been a humiliation to him, although, of course, as anyone could see plainly, most of each generation must stay on Earth in the nature of things.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There had to be farmers and miners and even technicians on Earth. It was only the late-model, high-specialty professions that were in demand on the Outworlds, and only a few millions a year out of Earth’s eight billion population could be exported. Every man and woman on Earth couldn’t be among that group.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But every man and woman could hope that at least one of his children could be one, and Platen, Senior, was certainly no exception. It was obvious to him (and, to be sure, to others as well) that George was notably intelligent and quick-minded. He would be bound to do well and he would have to, as he was an only child. If George didn’t end on an Outworld, they would have to wait for grandchildren before a next chance would come along, and that was too far in the future to be much consolation.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Reading Day would not prove much, of course, but it would be the only indication they would have before the big day itself. Every parent on Earth would be listening to the quality of reading when his child came home with it; listening for any particularly easy flow of words and building that into certain omens of the future. There were few families that didn’t have at least one hopeful who, from Reading Day on, was the great hope because of the way he handled his trisyllabics.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dimly, George was aware of the cause of his parents’ tension, and if there was any anxiety in his young heart that drizzly morning, it was only the fear that his father’s hopeful expression might fade out when he returned home with his reading.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The children met in the large assembly room of the town’s Education Hall. All over Earth, in millions of local halls, throughout that month, similar groups of children would he meeting. George felt depressed by the grayness of the room and by the other children, strained and stiff in unaccustomed finery.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Automatically, George did as all the rest of the children did. He found the small clique that represented the children on his floor of the apartment house and joined them.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan, who lived immediately next door, still wore his hair childishly long and was years removed from the sideburns and thin, reddish mustache that he was to grow as soon as he was physiologically capable of it.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan (to whom George was then known as Jawjee) said, “Bet you’re scared.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I am not,’ said George. Then, confidentially, “My folks got a hunk of printing up on the dresser in my room, and when I come home, I’m going to read it for them.” (George’s main suffering at the moment lay in the fact that he didn’t quite know where to put his hands. He had been warned not to scratch his head or rub his ears or pick his nose or put his hands into his pockets. This eliminated almost every possibility.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan put his hands in his pockets and said, “My father isn’t worried.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan, Senior, had been a Metallurgist on Diporia for nearly seven years, which gave him a superior social status in his neighborhood even though he had retired and returned to Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Earth discouraged these re-immigrants because of population problems, but a small trickle did return. For one thing the cost of living was lower on Earth, and what was a trifling annuity on Diporia, say, was a comfortable income on Earth. Besides, there were always men who found more satisfaction in displaying their success before the friends and scenes of their childhood than before all the rest of the Universe besides.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan, Senior further explained that if he stayed on Diporia, so would his children, and Diporia was a one-spaceship world. Back on Earth, his kids could end up anywhere, even Novia.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Stubby Trevelyan had picked up that item early. Even before Reading Day, his conversation was based on the carelessly assumed fact that his ultimate home would be in Novia.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George, oppressed by thoughts of the other’s future greatness and his own small-time contrast, was driven to belligerent defense at once.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“My father isn’t worried either. He just wants to hear me read because he knows I’ll be good. I suppose your father would just as soon not hear you because he knows you’ll be all wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I will not be all wrong. Reading is nothing. On Novia, I’ll hire people to read to me.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Because you won’t be able to read yourself, on account of you’re dumb!”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Then how come I’ll be on Novia?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And George, driven, made the great denial, “Who says you’ll be on Novia? Bet you don’t go anywhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Stubby Trevelyan reddened. “I won’t be a Pipe Fitter like your old man.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Take that back, you dumbhead.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You take that back.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;They stood nose to nose, not wanting to fight but relieved at having something familiar to do in this strange place. Furthermore, now that George had curled his hands into fists and lifted them before his face, the problem of what to do with his hands was, at least temporarily, solved. Other children gathered round excitedly.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But then it all ended when a woman’s voice sounded loudly over the public address system. There was instant silence everywhere. George dropped his fists and forgot Trevelyan.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Children,” said the voice, “we are going to call out your names. As each child is called, he or she is to go to one of the men waiting along the side walls. Do you see them? They are wearing red uniforms so they will be easy to find. The girls will go to the right. The boys will go to the left. Now look about and see which man in red is nearest to you —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George found his man at a glance and waited for his name to be called off. He had not been introduced before this to the sophistications of the alphabet and the length of time it took to reach his own name grew disturbing.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The crowd of children thinned; little rivulets made their way to each of the red-clad guides.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When the name ‘George Platen’ was finally called, his sense of relief was exceeded only by the feeling of pure gladness at the fact that Stubby Trevelyan still stood in his place, uncalled.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George shouted back over his shoulder as he left, “Yay, Stubby, maybe they don’t want you.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;That moment of gaiety quickly left. He was herded into a line and directed down corridors in the company of strange children. They all looked at one another, large-eyed and concerned, but beyond a snuffling, “Quitcher pushing” and “Hey, watch out” there was no conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;They were handed little slips of paper which they were told must remain with them. George stared at his curiously. Little black marks of different shapes. He knew it to be printing but how could anyone make words out of it? He couldn’t imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was told to strip; he and four other boys who were all that now remained together. All the new clothes came shucking off and four eight-year-olds stood naked and small, shivering more out of embarrassment than cold. Medical technicians came past, probing them, testing them with odd instruments, pricking them for blood. Each took the little cards and made additional marks on them with little black rods that produced the marks, all neatly lined up, with great speed. George stared at the new marks, but they were no more comprehensible than the old. The children were ordered back into their clothes.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;They sat on separate little chairs then and waited again. Names were called again and ‘George Platen’ came third.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He moved into a large room, filled with frightening instruments with knobs and glassy panels in front. There was a desk in the very center, and behind it a man sat, his eyes on the papers piled before him.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “George Platen?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir,” said George, in a shaky whisper. All this waiting and all this going here and there was making him nervous. He wished it were over.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The man behind the desk said, “I am Dr Lloyd, George. How are you?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The doctor didn’t look up as he spoke. It was as though he had said those words over and over again and didn’t have to look up any more.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I’m all right.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Are you afraid, George?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“N — no, sir,” said George, sounding afraid even in his own ears.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That’s good,” said the doctor, “because there’s nothing to be afraid of you know. Let’s see, George. It says here on your card that your father is named Peter and that he’s a Registered Pipe Fitter and your mother is named Amy and is a Registered Home Technician. Is that right?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Y — yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And your birthday is 13 February,and you had an ear infection about a year ago. Right?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Do you know how I know all these things?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It’s on the card, I think, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That’s right.” The doctor looked up at George for the first time and smiled. He showed even teeth and looked much younger than George’s father. Some of George’s nervousness vanished.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The doctor passed the card to George. “Do you know what all those things there mean, George?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Although George knew he did not he was startled by the sudden request into looking at the card as though he might understand now through some sudden stroke of fate. But they were just marks as before and he passed the card back. “No, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Why not?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George felt a sudden pang of suspicion concerning the sanity of this doctor. Didn’t he know why not?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “I can’t read, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Would you like to read?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Why, George?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George stared, appalled. No one had ever asked him that. He had no answer. He said falteringly, “I don’t know, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Printed information will direct you all through your life. There is so much you’ll have to know even after Education Day. Cards like this one will tell you. Books will tell you. Television screens will tell you. Printing will tell you such useful things and such interesting things that not being able to read would be as bad as not being able to see. Do you understand?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Are you afraid, George?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Good. Now I’ll tell you exactly what we’ll do first. I’m going to put these wires on your forehead just over the corners of your eyes. They’ll stick there but they won’t hurt at all. Then, I’ll turn on something that will make a buzz. It will sound funny and it may tickle you, but it won’t hurt. Now if it does hurt, you tell me, and I’ll turn it off right away, but it won’t hurt. All right?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George nodded and swallowed.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Are you ready?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George nodded. He closed his eyes while the doctor busied himself. His parents had explained this to him. They, too, had said it wouldn’t hurt, but then there were always the older children. There were the ten- and twelve-year-olds who howled after the eight-year-olds waiting for Reading Day, “Watch out for the needle.” There were the others who took you off in confidence and said, “They got to cut your head open. They use a sharp knife that big with a hook on it,” and so on into horrifying details.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George had never believed them but he had had nightmares, and now he closed his eyes and felt pure terror.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He didn’t feel the wires at his temple. The buzz was a distant thing, and there was the sound of his own blood in his ears, ringing hollowly as though it and he were in a large cave. Slowly he chanced opening his eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The doctor had his back to him. From one of the instruments a strip of paper unwound and was covered with a thin, wavy purple line. The doctor tore off pieces and put them into a slot in another machine. He did it over and over again. Each time a little piece of film came out which the doctor looked at. Finally, he turned toward George with a queer frown between his eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The buzzing stopped.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said breathlessly, “Is it over?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The doctor said, “Yes,” but he was still frowning.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Can I read now?’ asked George. He felt no different.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The doctor said, “What?” then smiled very suddenly and briefly. He said, “It works fine, George. You’ll be reading in fifteen minutes. Now we’re going to use another machine this time and it will take longer. I’m going to cover your whole head, and when I turn it on you won’t be able to see or hear anything for a while, but it won’t hurt. Just to make sure I’m going to give you a little switch to hold in your hand. If anything hurts, you press the little button and everything shuts off. All right?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;In later years, George was told that the little switch was strictly a dummy; that it was introduced solely for confidence. He never did know for sure, however, since he never pushed the button.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A large smoothly curved helmet with a rubbery inner lining was placed over his head and left there. Three or four little knobs seemed to grab at him and bite into his skull, but there was only a little pressure that faded. No pain.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The doctor’s voice sounded dimly. “Everything all right, George?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And then, with no real warning, a layer of thick felt closed down all about him. He was disembodied, there was no sensation, no universe, only himself and a distant murmur at the very ends of nothingness telling him something — telling him — telling him —&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He strained to hear and understand but there was all that thick felt between.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Then the helmet was taken off his head, and the light was so bright that it hurt his eyes while the doctor’s voice drummed at his ears.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The doctor said, “Here’s your card, George. What does it say?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George looked at his card again and gave out a strangled shout. The marks weren’t just marks at all. They made up words. They were words just as clearly as though something were whispering them in his ears. He could hear them being whispered as he looked at them.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What does it say, George?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It says — it says — ‘Platen, George. Born 13 February 6492 of Peter and Amy Platen in...’” He broke off.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You can read, George,” said the doctor. “It’s all over.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“For good? I won’t forget how?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Of course not” The doctor leaned over to shake hands gravely. “You will be taken home now.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was days before George got over this new and great talent of his. He read for his father with such facility that Platen, Senior, wept and called relatives to tell the good news.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George walked about town, reading every scrap of printing he could find and wondering how it was that none of it had ever made sense to him before.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He tried to remember how it was not to be able to read and he couldn’t. As far as his feeling about it was concerned, he had always been able to read. Always.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;At eighteen, George was rather dark, of medium height, but thin enough to look taller. Trevelyan, who was scarcely an inch shorter, had a stockiness of build that made ‘Stubby’ more than ever appropriate, but in this last year he had grown self-conscious. The nickname could no longer be used without reprisal. And since Trevelyan disapproved of his proper first name even more strongly, he was called Trevelyan or any decent variant of that. As though to prove his manhood further, he had most persistently grown a pair of sideburns and a bristly mustache.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was sweating and nervous now, and George, who had himself grown out of ‘Jaw-jee’ and into the curt monosyllabic gutturability of ‘George,’ was rather amused by that.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;They were in the same large hall they had been in ten years before (and not since). It was as if a vague dream of the past had come to sudden reality. In the first few minutes George had been distinctly surprised at finding everything seem smaller and more cramped than his memory told him; then he made allowance for his own growth.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The crowd was smaller than it had been in childhood. It was exclusively male this time. The girls had another day assigned them.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan leaned over to say, “Beats me the way they make you wait.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Red tape,” said George. “You can’t avoid it.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan said, “What makes you so damned tolerant about it?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I’ve got nothing to worry about.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Oh, brother, you make me sick. I hope you end up Registered Manure Spreader just so I can see your face when you do.” His somber eyes swept the crowd anxiously.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George looked about, too. It wasn’t quite the system they used on the children. Matters went slower, and instructions had been given out at the start in print (an advantage over the pre-Readers). The names Platen and Trevelyan were well down the alphabet still, but this time the two knew it.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Young men came out of the education rooms, frowning and uncomfortable, picked up their clothes and belongings, then went off to analysis to learn the results.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Each, as he come out, would be surrounded by a clot of the thinning crowd. “How was it?” “How ’d it feel?” “Whacha think ya made?” “Ya feel any different?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Answers were vague and noncommittal.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George forced himself to remain out of those clots. You only raised your own blood pressure. Everyone said you stood the best chance if you remained calm. Even so, you could feel the palms of your hands grow cold. Funny that new tensions came with the years.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;For instance, high-specialty professionals heading out for an Outworld were accompanied by a wife (or husband). It was important to keep the sex ratio in good balance on all worlds. And if you were going out to a Grade A world, what girl would refuse you? George had no specific girl in mind yet; he wanted none. Not now! Once he made Programmer; once he could add to his name, Registered Computer Programmer, he could take his pick, like a sultan in a harem. The thought excited him and he tried to put it away. Must stay calm.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan muttered “What’s it all about anyway? First they say it works best if you’re relaxed and at ease. Then they put you through this and make it impossible for you to be relaxed and at ease.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Maybe that’s the idea. They’re separating the boys from the men to begin with. Take it easy, Trev.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Shut up.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George’s turn came. His name was not called. It appeared in glowing letters on the notice board.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He waved at Trevelyan. “Take it easy. Don’t let it get you.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was happy as he entered the testing chamber. Actually happy.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The man behind the desk said, “George Platen?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;For a fleeting instant there was a razor-sharp picture in George’s mind of another man, ten years earlier, who had asked the same question, and it was almost as though this were the same man and he, George, had turned eight again as he had stepped across the threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But the man looked up and, of course, the face matched that of the sudden memory not at all. The nose was bulbous, the hair thin and stringy, and the chin wattled as though its owner had once been grossly overweight and had reduced.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The man behind the desk looked annoyed. “Well?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George came to Earth. “I’m George Platen, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Say so, then. I’m Dr Zachary Antonelli, and we’re going to be intimately acquainted in a moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He stared at small strips of film, holding them up to the light owlishly.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George winced inwardly. Very hazily, he remembered that other doctor (he had forgotten the name) staring at such film. Could these be the same? The other doctor had frowned and this one was looking at him now as though he were angry.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;His happiness was already just about gone.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dr Antonelli spread the pages of a thickish file out before him now and put the films’s carefully to one side. “It says here you want to be a Computer Programmer.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, doctor.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Still do?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It’s a responsible and exacting position. Do you feel up to it?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Most pre-Educates don’t put down any specific profession. I believe they are afraid of queering it.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I think that’s right sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Aren’t you afraid of that?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I might as well be honest, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dr Antonelli nodded, but without any noticeable lightening of his expression. “Why do you want to be a Programmer?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It’s a responsible and exacting position as you said, sir. It’s an important job and an exciting one. I like it and I think I can do it.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dr Antonelli put the papers away, and looked at George sourly. He said, “How do you know you like it? Because you think you’ll be snapped up by some Grade A planet?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George thought uneasily: He’s trying to rattle you. Stay calm and stay frank.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “I think a Programmer has a good chance, sir, but even if I were left on Earth, I know I’d like it.” (That was true enough. I’m not lying, thought George.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“All right how do you know?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He asked it as though he knew there was no decent answer and George almost smiled. He had one.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “I’ve been reading about Programming, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You’ve been what?” Now the doctor looked genuinely astonished and George took pleasure in that.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Reading about it, sir. I bought a book on the subject and I’ve been studying it.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“A book for Registered Programmers?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But you couldn’t understand it.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Not at first. I got other books on mathematics and electronics. I made out all I could. I still don’t know much, but I know enough to know I like it and to know I can make it.” (Even his parents never found that secret cache of books or knew why he spent so much time in his own room or exactly what happened to the sleep he missed.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The doctor pulled at the loose skin under his chin. “What was your idea in doing that, son?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I wanted to make sure I would be interested, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Surely you know that being interested means nothing. You could be devoured by a subject and if the physical make-up of your brain makes it more efficient for you to be something else, something else you will be. You know that, don’t you?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I’ve been told that,” said George cautiously.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Well, believe it. It’s true.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dr Antonelli said, “Or do you believe that studying some subject will bend the brain cells in that direction, like that other theory that a pregnant woman need only listen to great music persistently to make a composer of her child. Do you believe that?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George flushed. That had certainly been in his mind. By forcing his intellect constantly in the desired direction, he had felt sure that he would be getting a head start. Most of his confidence had rested on exactly that point.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I never-” he began, and found no way of finishing.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Well it isn’t true. Good Lord, youngster, your brain pattern is fixed at birth. It can be altered by a blow hard enough to damage the cells or by a burst blood vessel or by a tumor or by a major infection — each time, of course, for the worse. But it certainly can’t be affected by your thinking special thoughts.” He stared at George thoughtfully, then said, “Who told you to do this?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George, now thoroughly disturbed, swallowed and said, “No one, doctor. My own idea.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Who knew you were doing it after you started?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No one. Doctor, I meant to do no wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Who said anything about wrong? Useless is what I would say. Why did you keep it to yourself?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I — I thought they’d laugh at me.” (He thought abruptly of a recent exchange with Trevelyan. George had very cautiously broached the thought, as of something merely circulating distantly in the very outermost reaches of his mind, concerning the possibility of learning something by ladling it into the mind by hand, so to speak, in bits and pieces. Trevelyan had hooted, “George, you’ll be tanning your own shoes next and weaving your own shirts.” He had been thankful then for his policy of secrecy.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dr Antonelli shoved the bits of film he had first looked at from position to position in morose thought. Then he said, “Let’s get you analyzed. This is getting me nowhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The wires went to George’s temples. There was the buzzing. Again there came a sharp memory of ten years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George’s hands were clammy; his heart pounded. He should never have told the doctor about his secret reading. It was his damned vanity, he told himself. He had wanted to show how enterprising he was, how full of initiative. Instead, he had showed himself superstitious and ignorant and aroused the hostility of the doctor. (He could tell the doctor hated him for a wise guy on the make.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And now he had brought himself to such a state of nervousness, he was sure the analyzer would show nothing that made sense.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He wasn’t aware of the moment when the wires were removed from his temples. The sight of the doctor, staring at him thoughtfully, blinked into his consciousness and that was that; the wires were gone. George dragged himself together with a tearing effort. He had quite given up his ambition to be a Programmer. In the space of ten minutes, it had all gone.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said dismally, “I suppose no?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No what?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No Programmer?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The doctor rubbed his nose and said, “You get your clothes and whatever belongs to you and go to room 15-C. Your files will be waiting for you there. So will my report.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said in complete surprise, “Have I been Educated already? I thought this was just to —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dr Antonelli stared down at his desk. “It will all be explained to you. You do as I say.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George felt something like panic. What was it they couldn’t tell him? He wasn’t fit for anything but Registered Laborer. They were going to prepare him for that; adjust him to it.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was suddenly certain of it and he had to keep from screaming by main force.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He stumbled back to his place of waiting. Trevelyan was not there, a fact for which he would have been thankful if he had had enough self-possession to be meaningfully aware of his surroundings. Hardly anyone was left, in fact, and the few who were looked as though they might ask him questions were it not that they were too worn out by their tail-of-the-alphabet waiting to buck the fierce, hot look of anger and hate he cast at them.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;What right had they to be technicians and he, himself, a Laborer? Laborer! He was certain!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was led by a red-uniformed guide along the busy corridors lined with separate rooms each containing its groups, here two, there five: the Motor Mechanics, the Construction Engineers, the Agronomists — There were hundreds of specialized Professions and most of them would be represented in this small town by one or two anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He hated them all just then: the Statisticians, the Accountants, the lesser breeds and the higher. He hated them because they owned their smug knowledge now, knew their fate, while he himself, empty still, had to face some kind of further red tape.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He reached 15-C, was ushered in and left in an empty room. For one moment, his spirits bounded. Surely, if this were the labor classification room, there would be dozens of youngsters present.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A door sucked into its recess on the other side of a waist-high partition and an elderly, white-haired man stepped out. He smiled and showed even teeth that were obviously false, but his face was still ruddy and unlined and his voice had vigor.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “Good evening, George. Our own sector has only one of you this time, I see.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Only one?” said George blankly.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Thousands over the Earth, of course. Thousands. You’re not alone.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George felt exasperated. He said, “I don’t understand, sir. What’s my classification? What’s happening?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Easy, son. You’re all right. It could happen to anyone. He held out his hand and George took it mechanically. It was warm and it pressed George’s hand firmly. “Sit down, son. I’m Sam Ellenford.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George nodded impatiently. “I want to know what’s going on, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Of course. To begin with, you can’t be a Computer Programmer, George. You’ve guessed that I think.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, I have,’ said George bitterly. “What will I be, then?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That’s the hard part to explain, George.” He paused, then said with careful distinctness, “Nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What!”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Nothing!”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But what does that mean? Why can’t you assign me a profession?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“We have no choice in the matter, George. It’s the structure of your mind that decides that.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George went a sallow yellow. His eyes bulged. “There’s something wrong with my mind?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“There’s something about it. As far as professional classification is concerned, I suppose you can call it wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But why?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ellenford shrugged. “I’m sure you know how Earth runs its Educational program, George. Practically any human being can absorb practically any body of knowledge, but each individual brain pattern is better suited to receiving some types of knowledge than others. We try to match mind to knowledge as well as we can within the limits of the quota requirements for each profession.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George nodded. “Yes, I know.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Every once in a while, George, we come up against a young man whose mind is not suited to receiving a superimposed knowledge of any sort.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You mean I can’t be Educated?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That is what I mean.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But that’s crazy. I’m intelligent. I can understand —” He looked helplessly about as though trying to find some way of proving that he had a functioning brain.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Don’t misunderstand me, please”, said Ellenford gravely. “ You’re intelligent. There’s no question about that. You’re even above average in intelligence. Unfortunately that has nothing to do with whether the mind ought to be allowed to accept superimposed knowledge or not. In fact, it is almost always the intelligent person who comes here.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You mean I can’t even be a Registered Laborer?” babbled George. Suddenly even that was better than the blank that faced him. “What’s there to know to be a Laborer?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Don’t underestimate the Laborer, young man. There are dozens of subclassifications and each variety has its own corpus of fairly detailed knowledge. Do you think there’s no skill in knowing the proper manner of lifting a weight? Besides, for the Laborer, we must select not only minds suited to it but bodies as well. You’re not the type, George, to last long as a Laborer.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George was conscious of his slight build. He said, “But I’ve never heard of anyone without a profession.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“There aren’t many,” conceded Ellenford. “And we protect them.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Protect them?” George felt confusion and fright grow higher inside him.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You’re a ward of the planet, George. From the time you walked through that door, we’ve been in charge of you.” And he smiled.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was a fond smile. To George it seemed the smile of ownership; the smile of a grown man for a helpless child.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “You mean, I’m going to be in prison?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Of course not. You will simply be with others of your kind.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Your kind. The words made a kind of thunder in George’s ear.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ellenford said, “You need special treatment. We’ll take care of you.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;To George’s own horror, he burst into tears. Ellenford walked to the other end of the room and faced away as though in thought.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George fought to reduce the agonized weeping to sobs and then to strangle those. He thought of his father and mother, of his friends, of Trevelyan, of his own shame — He said rebelliously, “I learned to read.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Everyone with a whole mind can do that. We’ve never found exceptions. It is at this stage that we discover — exceptions. And when you learned to read, George, we were concerned about your mind pattern. Certain peculiarities were reported even then by the doctor in charge.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Can’t you try Educating me? You haven’t even tried. I’m willing to take the risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“The law forbids us to do that, George. But look, it will not be bad. We will explain matters to your family so they will not be hurt. At the place to which you’ll be taken, you’ll be allowed privileges. We’ll get you books and you can learn what you will.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Dab knowledge in by hand,” said George bitterly. “Shred by shred. Then, when I die I’ll know enough to be a Registered Junior Office Boy, Paper-Clip Division.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yet I understand you’ve already been studying books.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George froze. He was struck devastatingly by sudden understanding. “That’s it”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What is?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That fellow Antonelli. He’s knifing me.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No, George. You’re quite wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Don’t tell me that.” George was in an ecstasy of fury. “That lousy bastard is selling me out because he thought I was a little too wise for him. I read books and tried to get a head start toward programming. Well, what do you want to square things? Money? You won’t get it. I’m getting out of here and when I finish broadcasting this —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was screaming.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ellenford shook his head and touched a contact.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Two men entered on catfeet and got on either side of George. They pinned his arms to his sides. One of them used an air-spray hypodermic in the hollow of his right elbow and the hypnotic entered his vein and had an almost immediate effect.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;His screams cut off and his head fell forward. His knees buckled and only the men on either side kept him erect as he slept.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;They took care of George as they said they would; they were good to him and unfailingly kind — about the way, George thought, he himself would be to a sick kitten he had taken pity on.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;They told him that he should sit up and take some interest in life; and then told him that most people who came there had the same attitude of despair at the beginning and that he would snap out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He didn’t even hear them.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dr Ellenford himself visited him to tell him that his parents had been informed that he was away on special assignment.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George muttered, “Do they know —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ellenford assured him at once,“We gave no details.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;At first George had refused to eat. They fed him intravenously. They hid sharp objects and kept him under guard. Hali Omani came to be his roommate and his stolidity had a calming effect.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;One day, out of sheer desperate boredom, George asked for a book. Omani, who himself read books constantly, looked up, smiling broadly. George almost withdrew the request then, rather than give any of them satisfaction, then thought: What do I care?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He didn’t specify the book and Omani brought one on chemistry. It was in big print, with small words and many illustrations. It was for teenagers. He threw the book violently against the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;That’s what he would be always. A teenager all his life. A pre-Educate forever and special books would have to be written for him. He lay smoldering in bed, staring at the ceiling, and after an hour had passed, he got up sulkily, picked up the book, and began reading.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It took him a week to finish it and then he asked for another.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Do you want me to take the first one back?” asked Omani.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George frowned. There were things in the book he had not understood, yet he was not so lost to shame as to say so.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But Omani said, “Come to think of it, you’d better keep it. Books are meant to be read and reread.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was that same day that he finally yielded to Omani’s invitation that he tour the place. He dogged at the Nigerian’s feet and took in his surroundings with quick hostile glances.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The place was no prison certainly. There were no walls, no locked doors, no guards. But it was a prison in that the inmates had no place to go outside.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was somehow good to see others like himself by the dozen. It was so easy to believe himself to be the only one in the world so — maimed.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He mumbled, “How many people here anyway?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Two hundred and five, George, and this isn’t the only place of the sort in the world. There are thousands.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Men looked up as he passed, wherever he went; in the gymnasium, along the tennis courts; through the library (he had never in his life imagined books could exist in such numbers; they were stacked, actually stacked, along long shelves). They stared at him curiously and he returned the looks savagely. At least they were no better than he; no call for them to look at him as though he were some son of curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Most of them were in their twenties. George said suddenly, “What happens to the older ones?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani said, “This place specializes in the younger ones.” Then, as though he suddenly recognized an implication in George’s question that he had missed earlier, he shook his head gravely and said, “They’re not put out of the way, if that’s what you mean. There are other Houses for older ones.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Who cares?” mumbled George, who felt he was sounding too interested and in danger of slipping into surrender.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You might. As you grow older, you will find yourself in a House with occupants of both sexes.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;That surprised George somehow. “Women, too?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Of course. Do you suppose women are immune to this sort of thing?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George thought of that with more interest and excitement than he had felt for anything since before that day when — He forced his thought away from that.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani stopped at the doorway of a room that contained a small closed-circuit television set and a desk computer.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Five or six men sat about the television. Omani said, “This is a classroom.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “What’s that?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“The young men in there are being educated. Not,” he added, quickly, “in the usual way.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You mean they’re cramming it in bit by bit.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That’s right. This is the way everyone did it in ancient times.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;This was what they kept telling him since he had come to the House but what of it? Suppose there had been a day when mankind had not known the diatherm-oven. Did that mean he should be satisfied to eat meat raw in a world where others ate it cooked?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “Why do they want to go through that bit-by-bit stuff?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“To pass the time, George, and because they’re curious.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What good does it do them?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It makes them happier.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George carried that thought to bed with him.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The next day he said to Omani ungraciously, “Can you get me into a classroom where I can find out something about programming?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani replied heartily, “Sure.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;advertisement&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was slow and he resented it. Why should someone have to explain something and explain it again? Why should he have to read and reread a passage, then stare at a mathematical relationship and not understand it at once? That wasn’t how other people had to be.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Over and over again, he gave up. Once he refused to attend classes for a week.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But always he returned. The official in charge, who assigned reading, conducted the television demonstrations, and even explained difficult passages and concepts, never commented on the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George was finally given a regular task in the gardens and took his turn in the various kitchen and cleaning details. This was represented to him as being an advance, but he wasn’t fooled. The place might have been far more mechanized than it was, but they deliberately made work for the young men in order to give them the illusion of worth-while occupation, of usefulness. George wasn’t fooled.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;They were even paid small sums of money out of which they could buy certain specified luxuries or which they could put aside for a problematical use in a problematical old age. George kept his money in an open jar, which he kept on a closet shelf. He had no idea how much he had accumulated. Nor did he care.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He made no real friends though he reached the stage where a civil good day was in order. He even stopped brooding (or almost stopped) on the miscarriage of justice that had placed him there. He would go weeks without dreaming of Antonelli, of his gross nose and wattled neck, of the leer with which he would push George into a boiling quicksand and hold him under, till he woke screaming with Omani bending over him in concern.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani said to him on a snowy day in February, “It’s amazing how you’re adjusting.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But that was February, the thirteenth to be exact, his nineteenth birthday. March came, then April, and with the approach of May he realized he hadn’t adjusted at all.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The previous May had passed unregarded while George was still in his bed, drooping and ambitionless. This May was different.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;All over Earth, George knew, Olympics would be taking place and young men would be competing, matching their skills against one another in the fight for a place on a new world. There would be the holiday atmosphere, the excitement, the news reports, the self-contained recruiting agents from the worlds beyond space, the glory of victory or the consolations of defeat.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;How much of fiction dealt with these motifs, how much of his own boyhood excitement lay in following the events of Olympics from year to year; how many of his own plans —&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George Platen could not conceal the longing in his voice.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was too much to suppress. He said, “Tomorrow’s the first of May. Olympics!”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And that led to his first quarrel with Omani and to Omani’s bitter enunciation of the exact name of the institution in which George found himself.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani gazed fixedly at George and said distinctly, “A House for the Feeble-minded.”&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George Platen flushed. Feeble-minded!&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He rejected it desperately. He said in a monotone, “I’m leaving.” He said it on impulse. His conscious mind learned it first from the statement as he uttered it.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani, who had returned to his book, looked up. “What?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George knew what he was saying now. He said it fiercely, “I’m leaving.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That’s ridiculous. Sit down, George, calm yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Oh, no. I’m here on a frame-up, I tell you. This doctor, Antonelli, took a dislike to me. It’s the sense of power these petty bureaucrats have. Cross them and they wipe out your life with a stylus mark on some card file.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Are you back to that?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And staying there till it’s all straightened out. I’m going to get to Antonelli somehow, break him, force the truth out of him.” George was breathing heavily and he felt feverish. Olympics month was here and he couldn’t let it pass. If he did, it would be the final surrender and he would be lost for all time.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani threw his legs over the side of his bed and stood up. He was nearly six feet tall and the expression on his face gave him the look of a concerned Saint Bernard. He put his arm about George’s shoulder, “If I hurt your feelings —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George shrugged him off. “You just said what you thought was the truth, and I’m going to prove it isn’t the truth, that’s all. Why not? The door’s open. There aren’t any locks. No one ever said I couldn’t leave. I’ll just walk out.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“All right, but where will you go?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“To the nearest air terminal, then to the nearest Olympics center. I’ve got money.” He seized the open jar that held the wages he had put away. Some of the coins jangled to the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That will last you a week maybe. Then what?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“By then I’ll have things settled.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“By then you’ll come crawling back here,” said Omani earnestly, “with all the progress you’ve made to do over again. You’re mad, George.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Feeble-minded is the word you used before.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Well, I’m sorry I did. Stay here, will you?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Are you going to try to stop me?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani compressed his full lips. “No, I guess I won’t. This is your business. If the only way you can learn is to buck the world and come back with blood on your face, go ahead. — Well, go ahead.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George was in the doorway now, looking back over his shoulder. “I’m going” — he came back to pick up his pocket grooming set slowly — “I hope you don’t object to my taking a few personal belongings.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani shrugged. He was in bed again reading, indifferent.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George lingered at the door again, but Omani didn’t look up. George gritted his teeth, turned and walked rapidly down the empty corridor and out into the night-shrouded grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He had expected to be stopped before leaving the grounds. He wasn’t. He had stopped at an all-night diner to ask directions to an air terminal and expected the proprietor to call the police. That didn’t happen. He summoned a skimmer to take him to the airport and the driver asked no questions.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Yet he felt no lift at that. He arrived at the airport sick at heart. He had not realized how the outer world would be. He was surrounded by professionals. The diner’s proprietor had had his name inscribed on the plastic shell over the cash register. So and so, Registered Cook. The man in the skimmer had his license up, Registered Chauffeur. George felt the bareness of his name and experienced a kind of nakedness because of it worse, he felt skinned. But no one challenged him. No one studied him suspiciously and demanded proof of professional rating.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George thought bitterly: Who would imagine any human being without one?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He bought a ticket to San Francisco on the 3 a.m. plane. No other plane for a sizable Olympics center was leaving before morning and he wanted to wait as little as possible. As it was, he sat huddled in the waiting room, watching for the police. They did not come.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was in San Francisco before noon and the noise of the city struck him like a blow. This was the largest city he had ever seen and he had been used to silence and calm for a year and a half now.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Worse, it was Olympics month. He almost forgot his own predicament in his sudden awareness that some of the noise, excitement, confusion was due to that.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Olympics boards were up at the airport for the benefit of the incoming travelers, and crowds jostled around each one. Each major profession had its own board. Each listed directions to the Olympics Hall where the contest for that day for that profession would be given; the individuals competing and their city of birth; the Outworld (if any) sponsoring it.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was a completely stylized thing. George had read descriptions often enough in the newsprints and films, watched matches on television, and even witnessed a small Olympics in the Registered Butcher classification at the county seat. Even that, which had no conceivable Galactic implication (there was no Outworlder in attendance, of course) aroused excitement enough.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Partly, the excitement was caused simply by the fact of competition, partly by the spur of local pride (oh, when there was a home-town boy to cheer for, though he might be a complete stranger), and, of course, partly by betting. There was no way of stopping the last.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George found it difficult to approach the board. He found himself looking at the scurrying, avid onlookers in a new way.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There must have been a time when they themselves were Olympic material. What had they done? Nothing!&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;If they had been winners, they would be far out in the Galaxy somewhere, not stuck here on Earth. Whatever they were, their professions must have made them Earth-bait from the beginning; or else they had made themselves Earth-bait by inefficiency at whatever high-specialized professions they had had.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Now these failures stood about and speculated on the chances of newer and younger men. Vultures!&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;How he wished they were speculating on him.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He moved down the line of boards blankly, clinging to the outskirts of the groups about them. He had eaten breakfast on the strato and he wasn’t hungry. He was afraid, though. He was in a big city during the confusion of the beginning of Olympics competition. That was protection, sure. The city was full of strangers. No one would question George. No one would care about George.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;No one would care. Not even the House, thought George bitterly. They cared for him like a sick kitten, but if a sick kitten up and wanders off, well too bad, what can you do?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And now that he was in San Francisco, what did he do? His thoughts struck blankly against a wall. See someone? Whom? How? Where would he even stay? The money he had left seemed pitiful.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The first shamefaced thought of going back came to him. He could go to the police — He shook his head violently as though arguing with a material adversary.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A word caught his eye on one of the boards, gleaming there: Metallurgist. In smaller letters, nonferrous. At the bottom of a long list of names, in flowing script, sponsored by Novia.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It induced painful memories: himself arguing with Trevelyan, so certain that he himself would be a Programmer, so certain that a Programmer was superior to a Metallurgist, so certain that he was following the right course, so certain that he was clever —&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;So clever that he had to boast to that small-minded, vindictive Antonelli. He had been so sure of himself that moment when he had been called and had left the nervous Trevelyan standing there, so cocksure.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George cried out in a short, incoherent high-pitched gasp. Someone turned to look at him, then hurried on. People brushed past impatiently pushing him this way and that. He remained staring at the board, openmouthed.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was as though the board had answered his thought. He was thinking ‘Trevelyan’ so hard that it had seemed for a moment that of course the board would say ‘Trevelyan’ back at him.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But that was Trevelyan, up there. And Armand Trevelyan (Stubby’s hated first name: up in lights for everyone to see) and the right home town. What’s more, Trev had wanted Novia, aimed for Novia, insisted on Novia; and this competition was sponsored by Novia.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;This had to be Trev; good old Trev. Almost without thinking he noted the directions for getting to the place of competition and took his place in line for a skimmer.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Then he thought somberly: Trev made it! He wanted to be a Metallurgist, and he made it!&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George felt colder, more alone than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;advertisement&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There was a line waiting to enter the hall. Apparently, Metallurgy Olympics was to be an exciting and closely fought one. At least, the illuminated sky sign above the ball said so, and the jostling crowd seemed to think so.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It would have been a rainy day, George thought, from the color of the sky, but San Francisco had drawn the shield across its breadth from bay to ocean. It was an expense to do so, of course, but all expenses were warranted where the comfort of Outworlders was concerned. They would be in town for the Olympics. They were heavy spenders. And for each recruit taken, there would be a fee both to Earth, and to the local government from the planet sponsoring the Olympics. It paid to keep Outworlders in mind of a particular city as a pleasant place in which to spend Olympics time. San Francisco knew what it was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George, lost in thought, was suddenly aware of a gentle pressure on his shoulder blade and a voice saving, “Are you in line here, young man?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The line had moved up without George’s having noticed the widening gap. He stepped forward hastily and muttered, “Sorry, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There was the touch of two fingers on the elbow of his jacket and he looked about furtively.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The man behind him nodded cheerfully. He had iron-gray hair, and under his jacket he wore an old-fashioned sweater that buttoned down the front. He said, “I didn’t mean to sound sarcastic.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No offense.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“All right, then.” He sounded cozily talkative. “I wasn’t sure you might not simply be standing there, entangled with the line, so to speak. only by accident. I thought you might be a —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“A what?” said George sharply. “Why, a contestant, of course. You look young.” George turned away. He felt neither cozy nor talkative, and bitterly impatient with busybodies.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A thought struck him. Had an alarm been sent out for him? Was his description known, or his picture? Was Gray-hair behind him trying to get a good look at his face?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He hadn’t seen any news reports. He craned his neck to see the moving strip of news headlines parading across one section of the city shield, somewhat lackluster against the gray of the cloudy afternoon sky. It was no use. He gave up at once. The headlines would never concern themselves with him. This was Olympics time and the only news worth headlining was the comparative scores of the winners and the trophies won by continents, nations, and cities.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It would go on like that for weeks, with scores calculated on a per capita basis and every city finding some way of calculating itself into a position of honor. His own town had once placed third in an Olympics covering Wiring Technician; third in the whole state. There was still a plaque saying so in Town Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George hunched his head between his shoulders and shoved his hands in his pocket and decided that made him more noticeable. He relaxed and tried to look unconcerned, and felt no safer. He was in the lobby now, and no authoritative hand had yet been laid on his shoulder. He filed into the hall itself and moved as far forward as he could.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It was with an unpleasant shock that he noticed Gray-hair next to him. He looked away quickly and tried reasoning with himself. The man had been right behind him in line after all.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Gray-hair, beyond a brief and tentative smile, paid no attention to him and, besides, the Olympics was about to start. George rose in his seat to see if he could make out the position assigned to Trevelyan and at the moment that was all his concern.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The hall was moderate in size and shaped in the classical long oval with the spectators in the two balconies running completely about the rim and the contestants in the linear trough down the center. The machines were set up, the progress boards above each bench were dark, except for the name and contest number of each man. The contestants themselves were on the scene, reading, talking together; one was checking his fingernails minutely.(It was, of course, considered bad form for any contestant to pay any attention to the problem before him until the instant of the starting signal.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George studied the program sheet he found in the appropriate slot in the arm of his chair and found Trevelyan’s name. His number was twelve and, to George’s chagrin, that was at the wrong end of the hall. He could make out the figure of Contestant Twelve, standing with his hands in his pockets, back to his machine, and staring at the audience as though he were counting the house. George couldn’t make out the face.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Still that was Trev.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George sank back in his seat. He wondered if Trev would do well. He hoped, as a matter of conscious duty, that he would, and yet there was something within him that felt rebelliously resentful. George, professionless, here, watching. Trevelyan, Registered Metallurgist, Nonferrous, there, competing.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George wondered if Trevelyan had competed in his first year. Sometimes men did, if they felt particularly confident — or hurried. It involved a certain risk. However efficient the Educative process, a preliminary year on Earth ('oiling the stiff knowledge’, as the expression went) insured a higher score.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;If Trevelyan was repeating, maybe he wasn’t doing so well. George felt ashamed that the thought pleased him just a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He looked about. The stands were almost full. This would be a well-attended Olympics, which meant greater strain on the contestants — or greater drive, perhaps, depending on the individual.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Why Olympics, he thought suddenly? He had never known. Why was bread called bread?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Once he had asked his father: “Why do they call it Olympics, Dad?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And his father had said: “Olympics means competition.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George had said: “Is when Stubby and I fight an Olympics, Dad?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Platen, Senior, had said: “No. Olympics is a special kind of competition and don’t ask silly questions. You’ll know all you have to know when you get Educated.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George, back in the present, sighed and crowded down into his seat.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;All you have to know!&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Funny that the memory should be so clear now. “When you get Educated.” No one ever said, “If you get Educated.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He always had asked silly questions, it seemed to him now. It was as though his mind had some instinctive foreknowledge of its inability to be Educated and had gone about asking questions in order to pick up scraps here and there as best it could.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And at the House they encouraged him to do so because They agreed with his mind’s instinct. It was the only way.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He sat up suddenly. What the devil was he doing? Falling for that lie? Was it because Trev was there before him, an Educee, competing in the Olympics that he himself was surrendering?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He wasn’t feeble-minded! No!&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And the shout of denial in his mind was echoed by the sudden clamor in the audience as everyone got to his feet. The box seat in the very center of one long side of the oval was filling with an entourage wearing the colors of Novia, and the word ‘Novia’ went up above them on the main board.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Novia was a Grade A world with a large population and a thoroughly developed civilization, perhaps the best in the Galaxy. It was the kind of world that every Earthman wanted to live in someday; or, failing that to see his children live in. (George remembered Trevelyan’s insistence on Novia as a goal — and there he was competing for it.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The lights went out in that section of the ceiling above the audience and so did the wall lights. The central trough, in which the contestants waited, became floodlit.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Again George tried to make out Trevelyan. Too far.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The clear, polished voice of the announcer sounded. “Distinguished Novian sponsors. Ladies. Gentlemen. The Olympics competition for Metallurgist, Nonferrous, is about to begin. The contestants are —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Carefully and conscientiously, he read off the list in the program. Names. Home towns. Educative years. Each name received its cheers, the San Franciscans among them receiving the loudest. When Trevelyan’s name was reached, George surprised himself by shouting and waving madly. The gray-haired man next to him surprised him even more by cheering likewise.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George could not help but stare in astonishment and his neighbor leaned over to say (speaking loudly in order to be heard over the hubbub), “No one here from my home town; I’ll root for yours. Someone you know?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George shrank back. “No.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I noticed you looking in that direction. Would you like to borrow my glasses?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No. Thank you.” (Why didn’t the old fool mind his own business?)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The announcer went on with other formal details concerning the serial number of the competition, the method of timing and scoring and so on. Finally, he approached the meat of the matter and the audience grew silent as it listened.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Each contestant will be supplied with a bar of nonferrous alloy of unspecified composition. He will be required to sample and assay the bar, reporting all results correctly to four decimals in per cent. All will utilize for this purpose a Beeman Microspectrograph Model FX-2, each of which is, at the moment, not in working order.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There was an appreciative shout from the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Each contestant will be required to analyze the fault of his machine and correct it. Tools and spare parts are supplied. The spare part necessary may not be present, in which case it must be asked for, and time of delivery thereof will be deducted from final time. Are all contestants ready?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The board above Contestant Five flashed a frantic red signal. Contestant Five ran off the floor and returned a moment later. The audience laughed good-naturedly.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Are all contestants ready?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The boards remained blank.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Any questions”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Still blank.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You may begin.”&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There was, of course, no way anyone in the audience could tell how any contestant was progressing except for whatever notations went up on the notice board. But then, that didn’t matter. Except for what professional Metallurgists there might be in the audience, none would understand anything about the contest professionally in any case. What was important was who won, who was second, who was third. For those who had bets on the standings (illegal but unpreventable) that was all-important. Everything else might go hang.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George watched as eagerly as the rest, glancing from one contestant to the next, observing how this one had removed the cover from his microspectrograph with deft strokes of a small instrument; how that one was peering into the face of the thing; how still a third was setting his alloy bar into its holder; and how a fourth adjusted a vernier with such small touches that he seemed momentarily frozen.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan was as absorbed as the rest. George had no way of telling how he was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The notice board over Contestant Seventeen flashed:&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Focus plate out of adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The audience cheered wildly.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Contestant Seventeen might be right and he might, of course, be wrong. If the latter, he would have to correct his diagnosis later and lose time. Or he might never correct his diagnosis and be unable to complete his analysis or, worse still, end with a completely wrong analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Never mind. For the moment, the audience cheered.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Other boards lit up. George watched for Board Twelve. That came on finally: ‘Sample holder off-center. New clamp depresser needed.’&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;An attendant went running to him with a new pan. If Trevelyan was wrong, it would mean useless delay. Nor would the time elapsed in waiting for the pan be deducted. George found himself holding his breath.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Results were beginning to go up on Board Seventeen, in gleaming letters: aluminum, 41.2649; magnesium, 22.1914; copper, 10.1001.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Here and there, other boards began sprouting figures.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The audience was in bedlam.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George wondered how the contestants could work in such pandemonium, then wondered if that were not even a good thing. A first-class technician should work best under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Seventeen rose from his place as his board went red-rimmed to signify completion. Four was only two seconds behind him. Another, then another.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan was still working, the minor constituents of his alloy bar still unreported. With nearly all contestants standing, Trevelyan finally rose, also. Then, tailing off, Five rose, and received an ironic cheer.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It wasn’t over. Official announcements were naturally delayed. Time elapsed was something, but accuracy was just as important. And not all diagnoses were of equal difficulty. A dozen factors had to be weighed.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Finally, the announcer’s voice sounded, “Winner in the time of four minutes and twelve seconds, diagnosis correct, analysis correct within an average of zero point seven parts per hundred thousand, Contestant Number — Seventeen, Henry Anton Schrnidt of —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;What followed was drowned in the screaming. Number Eight was next and then Four, whose good time was spoiled by a five part in ten thousand error in the niobium figure. Twelve was never mentioned. He was an also-ran. George made his way through the crowd to the Contestant’s Door and found a large clot of humanity ahead of him. There would be weeping relatives (joy or sorrow, depending) to greet them, newsmen to interview the top-scorers, or the home-town boys, autograph hounds, publicity seekers and the just plain curious. Girls, too, who might hope to catch the eye of a top-scorer, almost certainly headed for Novia (or perhaps a low-scorer who needed consolation and had the cash to afford it).&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George hung back. He saw no one he knew. With San Francisco so far from home, it seemed pretty safe to assume that there would be no relatives to condole with Trev on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Contestants emerged, smiling weakly, nodding at shouts of approval. Policemen kept the crowds far enough away to allow a lane for walking. Each high-scorer drew a portion of the crowd off with him, like a magnet pushing through a mound of iron filings.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When Trevelyan walked out, scarcely anyone was left. (George felt somehow that he had delayed coming out until just that had come to pass.) There was a cigarette in his dour mouth and he turned, eyes downcast, to walk off. It was the first hint of home George had had in what was almost a year and a half and seemed almost a decade and a half. He was almost amazed that Trevelyan hadn’t aged, that he was the same Trev he had last seen.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George sprang forward. “Trev!”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan spun about, astonished. He stared at George and then his hand shot out. “George Platen, what the devil — ”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And almost as soon as the look of pleasure had crossed his face, It left. His hand dropped before George had quite the chance of seizing it.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Were you in there?’ A curt jerk of Trev’s head indicated the hall.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I was.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“To see me?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Didn’t do so well did I?” He dropped his cigarette and stepped on it, staring off to the street, where the emerging crowd was slowly eddying and finding its way into skimmers, while new lines were forming for the next scheduled Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan said heavily, “So what? It’s only the second time I missed. Novia can go shove after the deal I got today. There are planets that would jump at me fast enough — But, listen, I haven’t seen you since Education Day. Where did you go? Your folks said you were on special assignment but gave no details and you never wrote. You might have written.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I should have,” said George uneasily. “Anyway, I came to say I was sorry the way things went just now.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Don’t be,” said Trevelyan. “I told you. Novia can go shove — At that I should have known. They've been saying for weeks that the Beeman machine would be used. All the wise money was on Beeman machines. The damned Education tapes they ran through me were for Henslers and who uses Henslers? The worlds in the Goman Cluster if you want to call them worlds. Wasn’t that a nice deal they gave me?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Can’t you complain to —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Don’t be a fool. They’ll tell me my brain was built for Henslers. Go argue. Everything went wrong. I was the only one who had to send out for a piece of equipment. Notice that?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“They deducted the time for that, though.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Sure, but I lost time wondering if I could be right in my diagnosis when I noticed there wasn’t any clamp depresser in the parts they had supplied. They don’t deduct for that. If it had been a Hensler, I would have known I was right. How could I match up then? The top winner was a San Franciscan. So were three of the next four. And the fifth guy was from Los Angeles. They get big-city Educational tapes. The best available. Beeman spectrographs and all. How do I compete with them? I came all the way out here just to get a chance at a Novian-sponsored Olympics in my classification and I might just as well have stayed home. I knew it, I tell you, and that settles it. Novia isn’t the only chunk of rock in space. Of all the damned —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He wasn’t speaking to George. He wasn’t speaking to anyone. He was just uncorked and frothing. George realized that.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “If you knew in advance that the Beemans were going to be used, couldn’t you have studied up on them?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“They weren’t in my tapes, I tell you.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You could have read — books.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The last word had tailed off under Trevelyan’s suddenly sharp look.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan said, “Are you trying to make a big laugh out of this? You think this is funny? How do you expect me to read some book and try to memorize enough to match someone else who knows.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I thought —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You try it. You try —” Then, suddenly, “What’s your profession, by the way?” He sounded thoroughly hostile.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Well —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Come on, now. If you’re going to be a wise guy with me, let’s see what you’ve done. You’re still on Earth, I notice, so you’re not a Computer Programmer and your special assignment can’t be much.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “Listen, Trev, I’m late for an appointment.” He backed away, trying to smile.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No, you don’t.” Trevelyan reached out fiercely, catching hold of George’s jacket. “You answer my question. Why are you afraid to tell me? What is it with you? Don’t come here rubbing a bad showing in my face, George, unless you can take it, too. Do you hear me?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was shaking George in frenzy and they were struggling and swaying across the floor, when the Voice of Doom struck George’s ear in the form of a policeman’s outraged call.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“All right now. All right. Break it up.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George’s heart turned to lead and lurched sickeningly. The policeman would be taking names, asking to see identity cards, and George lacked one. He would be questioned and his lack of profession would show at once; and before Trevelyan, too, who ached with the pain of the drubbing he had taken and would spread the news back home as a salve for his own hurt feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George couldn’t stand that. He broke away from Trevelyan and made to run, but the policeman’s heavy hand was on his shoulder. “Hold on there. Let’s see your identity card.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Trevelyan was fumbling for his, saying harshly, “I’m Amand Trevelyan, Metallurgist, Nonferrous. I was just competing in the Olympics. You better find out about him, though, officer.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George faced the two, lips dry and throat thickened past speech.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Another voice sounded, quiet, well-mannered. “Officer. One moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The policeman stepped back. “Yes, sir?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“This young man is my guest. What is the trouble?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George looked about in wild surprise. It was the gray-haired man who had been sitting next to him. Gray-hair nodded benignly at George.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Guest? Was he mad?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The policeman was saying, “These two were creating a disturbance, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Any criminal charges? Any damages?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Well, then, I’ll be responsible.” He presented a small card to the policeman’s view and the latter stepped back at once.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Trevelyan began indignantly, “Hold on, now —” but the policeman turned on him.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“All right, now. Got any charges?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I just —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“On your way. The rest of you — move on.” A sizable crowd had gathered, which now, reluctantly, unknotted itself and raveled away.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George let himself be led to a skimmer but balked at entering.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “Thank you, but I’m not your guest.” (Could it be a ridiculous case of mistaken identity?)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But Gray-hair smiled and said, “You weren’t but you are now. Let me introduce myself, I’m Ladislas Ingenescu, Registered Historian.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Come, you will come to no harm, I assure you. After all, I only wanted to spare you some trouble with a policeman.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But why?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Do you want a reason? Well, then, say that we’re honorary towns-mates, you and I. We both shouted for the same man, remember, and we towns-people must stick together, even if the tie is only honorary. Eh?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And George, completely unsure of this man, Ingenescu, and of himself as well, found himself inside the skimmer. Before he could make up his mind that he ought to get off again, they were off the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He thought confusedly: The man has some status. The policeman deferred to him.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was almost forgetting that his real purpose here in San Francisco was not to find Trevelyan but to find some person with enough influence to force a reappraisal of his own capacity of Education.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It could be that Ingenescu was such a man. And right in George’s lap.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Everything could be working out fine — fine. Yet it sounded hollow in his thought. He was uneasy.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;During the short skimmer-hop, Ingenescu kept up an even flow of small talk, pointing out the landmarks of the city, reminiscing about past Olympics he had seen. George, who paid just enough attention to make vague sounds during the pauses, watched the route of flight anxiously.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Would they head for one of the shield-openings and leave the city altogether?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The skimmer landed at the roof-entry of a hotel and, as he alighted, Ingenescu said, “I hope you’ll eat dinner with me in my room?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “Yes,” and grinned unaffectedly. He was just beginning to realize the gap left within him by a missing lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu let George eat in silence. Night closed in and the wall lights went on automatically. (George thought: I’ve been on my own almost twenty-four hours.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And then over the coffee, Ingenescu finally spoke again. He said, “You’ve been acting as though you think I intend you harm.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George reddened, put down his cup and tried to deny it, but the older man laughed and shook his head.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It’s so. I’ve been watching you closely since I first saw you and I think I know a great deal about you now.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George half rose in horror.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said, “But sit down. I only want to help you.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George sat down but his thoughts were in a whirl. If the old man knew who he was, why had he not left him to the policeman? On the other hand, why should he volunteer help?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said, “You want to know why I should want to help you? Oh, don’t look alarmed. I can’t read minds. It’s just that my training enables me to judge the little reactions that give minds away, you see. Do you understand that?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George shook his head.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said, “Consider my first sight of you. You were waiting in line to watch an Olympics, and your micro-reactions didn’t match what you were doing. The expression of your face was wrong, the action of your hands was wrong. It meant that something, in general was wrong, and the interesting thing was that, whatever it was, it was nothing common, nothing obvious. Perhaps, I thought, it was something of which your own conscious mind was unaware.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George was in an agony of indecision. If this was a trap, why should it be such an indirect, roundabout one? And he had to turn to someone. He had come to the city to find help and here was help being offered. Perhaps what was wrong was that it was being offered. It came too easy.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said, “Of course, what you tell me as a Social Scientist is a privileged communication. Do you know what that means?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It means, it would be dishonorable for me to repeat what you say to anyone for any purpose. Moreover no one has the legal right to compel me to repeat it.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, with sudden suspicion, “I thought you were a Historian.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“So I am.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Just now you said you were a Social Scientist.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;lngenescu broke into loud laughter and apologized for it when he could talk. “I’m sorry, young man, I shouldn’t laugh, and I wasn’t really laughing at you. I was laughing at Earth and its emphasis on physical science, and the practical segments of it at that. I’ll bet you can rattle off every subdivision of construction technology or mechanical engineering and yet you’re a blank on social science.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Well, then what is social science?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Social science studies groups of human beings and there are many high-specialized branches to it, just as there are to zoology, for instance. For instance, there are Culturists, who study the mechanics of cultures, their growth, development, and decay. Cultures,’ he added, forestalling a question, “are all the aspects of a way of life. For instance it includes the way we make our living, the things we enjoy and believe, what we consider good and bad and so on. Do you understand?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I think I do.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“An Economist — not an Economic Statistician, now, but an Economist — specializes in the study of the way a culture supplies the bodily needs of its individual members. A psychologist specializes in the individual member of a society and how he is affected by the society. A Futurist specializes in planning the future course of a society, and a Historian — That’s where I come in, now.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“A Historian specializes in the past development of our own society and of societies with other cultures.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George found himself interested. “Was it different in the past?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I should say it was. Until a thousand years ago, there was no Education; not what we call Education, at least.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “I know. People learned in bits and pieces out of books.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Why, how do you know this?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I’ve heard it said,’ said George cautiously. Then, “Is there any use in worrying about what’s happened long ago? I mean, it’s all done with, isn’t it?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It’s never done with, my boy. The past explains the present. For instance, why is our Educational system what it is?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George stirred restlessly. The man kept bringing the subject back to that. He said snappishly, “Because it’s best.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Ah, but why is it best? Now you listen to me for one moment and I’ll explain. Then you can tell me if there is any use in history. Even before interstellar travel was developed —” He broke off at the look of complete astonishment on George’s face. “Well, did you think we always had it?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I never gave it any thought, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I’m sure you didn’t. But there was a time, four or five thousand years ago, when mankind was confined to the surface of Earth. Even then, his culture had grown quite technological and his numbers had increased to the point where any failure in technology would have meant mass starvation and disease. To maintain the technological level and advance it in the face of an increasing population, more and more technicians and scientists had to be trained, and yet, as science advanced, it took longer and longer to train them.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Does it help you to understand knowing that without it, interstellar colonization was impossible for fifteen hundred years?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Then you see the uses of history.” The Historian smiled. “ And now I wonder if you see why I’m interested in you?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George snapped out of time and space back to reality. Ingenescu, apparently, didn’t talk aimlessly. All this lecture had been a device to attack him from a new angle.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, once again withdrawn, hesitating, “Why?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Social Scientists work with societies and societies are made up of people.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“All right.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But people aren’t machines. The professionals in physical science work with machines. There is only a limited amount to know about a machine and the professionals know it all. Furthermore, all machines of given sort are just about alike so that there is nothing to interest them in any given individual machine. But people, ah — They are so complex and so different one from another that a Social Scientist never knows all there is to know or even a good part of what there is to know. To understand his own specialty, he must always be ready to study people; particularly unusual specimens.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Like me,’ said George tonelessly.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I shouldn’t call you a specimen, I suppose, but you are unusual. You’re worth studying, and If you will allow me that privilege then, in return, I will help you if you are in trouble and if I can.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There were pin wheels whirring in George’s mind. — All this talk about people and colonization made possible by Education. It was as though caked thought within him were being broken up and strewn about mercilessly.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “Let me think,” and clamped his hands over his ears.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He took them away and said to the Historian, “Will you do something for me, sir?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“If I can,” said the Historian amiably.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And everything I say in this room is a privileged communication. You said so.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And I meant it.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Then get me an interview with an Outworld official with — with a Novian.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu looked startled. “Well, now —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You can do it,’ said George earnestly. “You’re an important official. I saw the policeman’s look when you put that card in front of his eyes. If you refuse, I — I won’t let you study me.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It sounded a silly threat in George’s own ears, one without force. On Ingenescu, however, it seemed to have a strong effect.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “That’s an impossible condition. A Novian in Olympics month —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“All right, then, get me a Novian on the phone and I’ll my own arrangements for an interview.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Do you think you can?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I know I can. Wait and see.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu stared at George thoughtfully and then reached for the visiphone.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George waited, half drunk with this new outlook on the whole problem and the sense of power it brought. It couldn’t miss. It couldn’t miss. He would be a Novian yet. He would leave Earth in triumph despite Antonelli and the whole crew of fools at the House for the (he almost laughed aloud) Feeble-minded.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;advertisement&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George watched eagerly as the visiplate lit up. It would open up a window into a room of Novians, a window into a small patch of Novia transplanted to Earth. In twenty-four hours, he had accomplished that much.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There was a burst of laughter as the plate unmisted and sharpened, but for the moment no single head could be seen but rather the fast passing of the shadows of men and women, this way and that. A voice was heard, clearworded over a background of babble. “Ingenescu? He wants me?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Then there he was, staring out of the plate. A Novian. A genuine Novian. (George had not an atom of doubt. There was something completely Outworldly about him. Nothing that could be completely defined, or even momentarily mistaken.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was swarthy in complexion with a dark wave of hair combed rigidly back from his forehead. He wore a thin black mustache and a pointed beard, just as dark, that scarcely reached below the lower limit of his narrow chin, but the rest of his face was so smooth that it looked a though it had been depilated permanently.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He was smiling. “Ladislas, this goes too far. We fully expect to be spied on, within reason, during our stay on Earth, but mind reading is out of bounds.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Mind reading, Honorable?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Confess! You knew I was going to call you this evening. You knew I was only waiting to finish this drink.” His moved up into view and his eye peered through a glass of a faintly violet liqueur. “I can’t offer you one, afraid.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George, out of range of Ingenescu’s transmitter, could not be seen by the Novian. He was relieved at that. He wanted time to compose himself and he needed it badly. It was as though he were made up exclusively of restless fingers, drumming, drumming —&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;But he was right. He hadn’t miscalculated. Ingenescu was important. The Novian called him by his first name.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Good! Things worked well. What George had lost on Antonelli, he would make up, with advantage, on Ingenescu. And someday, when he was on his own at last, and could come back to Earth as powerful a Novian as this one who could negligently joke with Ingenescu’s first name and be addressed as ‘Honorable’ in turn — when he came back, he would settle with Antonelli. He had a year and a half to pay back and he —&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He all but lost his balance on the brink of the enticing daydream and snapped back in sudden anxious realization that he was losing the thread of what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian was saying, “— doesn’t hold water. Novia has a civilization as complicated and advanced as Earth’s. We’re not Zeston, after all. It’s ridiculous that we have to come here for individual technicians.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said soothingly, “Only for new models. There is never any certainty that new models will be needed. To buy the Educational tapes would cost you the same price as a thousand technicians and how do you know you would need that many?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian tossed off what remained of his drink and laughed. (It displeased George, somehow, that a Novian should be this frivolous. He wondered uneasily if perhaps the Novian ought not to have skipped that drink and even the one or two before that.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian said, 'That’s typical pious fraud, Ladislas. You know we can make use of all the late models we can. I collected five Metallurgists this afternoon —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I know,’ said Ingenescu. “I was there.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Watching me! Spying!” cried the Novian. “I’ll tell you What it is. The new-model Metallurgists I got differed from the previous model only in knowing the use of Beeman Spectrographs. The tapes couldn’t be modified that much, not that much” (he held up two fingers close together) “from last year’s model. You introduce the new models only to make us buy and spend and come here hat in hand.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“We don’t make you buy.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No, but you sell late-model technicians to Landonum and so we have to keep pace. It’s a merry-go-round you have us on, you pious Earthmen, but watch out, there may be an exit somewhere.” There was a sharp edge to his laugh, and it ended sooner than it should have.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said, “In all honesty, I hope there is. Meanwhile, as to the purpose of my call-”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That’s right, you called. Oh, well, I’ve said my say and I suppose next year there’ll be a new model of Metallurgist anyway for us to spend goods on, probably with a new gimmick for niobium assays and nothing else altered and the next year — But go on, what is it you want?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I have a young man here to whom I wish you to speak.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Oh?” The Novian looked not completely pleased with that. “ Concerning what?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I can’t say. He hasn’t told me. For that matter he hasn’t even told me his name and profession.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian frowned. “Then why take up my time?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“He seems quite confident that you will be interested in what he has to say.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I dare say.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And,” said Ingenescu, “as a favor to me.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian shrugged. “Put him on and tell him to make it short.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu stepped aside and whispered to George,“Address him as ‘Honorable’.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George swallowed with difficulty. This was it.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George felt himself going moist with perspiration. The thought had come so recently, yet it was in him now so certainly. The beginnings of it had come when he had spoken to Trevelyan, then everything had fermented and billowed into shape while Ingenescu had prattled, and then the Novian’s own remarks had seemed to nail it all into place.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “Honorable, I’ve come to show you the exit from the merry-go-round.” Deliberately, he adopted the Novian’s own metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian stared at him gravely. “What merry-go-round?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You yourself mentioned it, Honorable. The merry-go-round that Novia is on when you come to Earth to — to get technicians.” (He couldn’t keep his teeth from chattering; from excitement not fear.)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian said, “You’re trying to say that you know a way by which we can avoid patronizing Earth’s mental super-market. Is that it?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, sir. You can control your own Educational system.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Umm. Without tapes?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Y — yes, Honorable.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian, without taking his eyes from George, called out, “Ingenescu, get into view.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Historian moved to where he could be seen over George’s shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian said, “What is this? I don’t seem to penetrate.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I assure you solemnly,” said Ingenescu, “that whatever this is it is being done on the young man’s own initiative, Honorable. I have not inspired this. I have nothing to do with it.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Well, then, what is the young man to you? Why do you call me on his behalf?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said, “He is an object of study, Honorable. He has value to me and I humor him.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What kind of value?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It’s difficult to explain; a matter of my profession.” The Novian laughed shortly. “Well, to each his profession.” He nodded to an invisible person or persons outside plate range. “There’s a young man here, a protégé of Ingenescu or some such thing, who will explain to us how to Educate without tapes.” He snapped his fingers, and another glass of pale liqueur appeared in his hand. “Well, young man?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The faces on the plate were multiple now. Men and women, both, crammed in for a view of George, their faces molded into various shades of amusement and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George tried to look disdainful. They were all, in their own ways, Novians as well as the Earthman, ‘studying’ him as though he were a bug on a pin. Ingenescu was sitting in a corner, now, watching him owl-eyed.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Fools, he thought tensely, one and all. But they would have to understand. He would make them understand.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He said, “I was at the Metallurgist Olympics this afternoon.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You, too?’ said the Novian blandly. “It seems all Earth was there.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No, Honorable, but I was. I had a friend who competed and who made out very badly because you were using the Beeman machines. His education had included only the Henslers, apparently an older model. You said the modification involved was slight.” George held up two fingers close together in conscious mimicry of the other’s previous gesture. “And my friend had known some time in advance that knowledge of the Beeman machines would be required.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And what does that signify?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It was my friend’s lifelong ambition to qualify for Novia. He already knew the Henslers. He had to know the Beemans to qualify and he knew that. To learn about the Beemans would have taken just a few more facts, a bit more data, a small amount of practice perhaps. With a life’s ambition riding the scale, he might have managed this —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And where would he have obtained a tape for the additional facts and data? Or has Education become a private matter for home study here on Earth?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There was dutiful laughter from the faces in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “That’s why he didn’t learn, Honorable. He thought he needed a tape. He wouldn’t even try without one, no matter what the prize. He refused to try without a tape.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Refused, eh? Probably the type of fellow who would refuse to fly without a skimmer.” More laughter and the Novian thawed into a smile and said, “The fellow is amusing. Go on. I’ll give you another few moments.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said tensely, “Don’t think this is a joke. Tapes are actually bad. They teach too much; they’re too painless. A man who learns that way doesn’t know how to learn any other way. He’s frozen into whatever position he’s been taped. Now if a person weren't given tapes but were forced to learn by hand, so to speak, from the start; why, then he’d get the habit of learning, and continue to learn. Isn’t that reasonable? Once he has the habit well developed he can be given just a small amount of tape-knowledge, perhaps, to fill in gaps or fix details. Then he can make further progress on his own. You can make Beeman Metallurgists out of your own Hensler Metallurgists in that way and not have to come to Earth for new models.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian nodded and sipped at his drink. “And where does everyone get knowledge without tapes? From interstellar vacuum?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“From books. By studying the instruments themselves. By thinking.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Books? How does one understand books without Education?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Books are in words. Words can be understood for the most part. Specialized words can be explained by the technicians you already have.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What about reading? Will you allow reading tapes?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Reading tapes are all right, I suppose but there’s no reason you can’t learn to read the old way, too. At least in part.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian said, “So that you can develop good habits from the start?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, yes,” George said gleefully. The man was beginning to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And what about mathematics?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“That’s the easiest of all, sir — Honorable. Mathematics is different from other technical subjects. It starts with certain simple principles and proceeds by steps. You Can start with nothing and learn. It’s practically designed for that. Then, once you know the proper types of mathematics, other technical books become quite understandable. Especially if you start with easy ones.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Are there easy books?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Definitely. Even if there weren’t, the technicians you now have can try to write easy books. Some of them might be able to put some of their knowledge into words and symbols.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Good Lord,” said the Novian to the men clustered about him. “ The young devil has an answer for everything.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I have. I have,’ shouted George. “Ask me.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Have you tried learning from books yourself? Or is this just theory with you?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George turned to look quickly at Ingenescu, but the Historian was passive. There was no sign of anything but gentle interest in his face.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said,“I have.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And do you find it works?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, Honorable,” said George eagerly. “Take me with you to Novia. I can set up a program and direct —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Wait I have a few more questions. How long would it take, do you suppose, for you to become a Metallurgist capable of handling a Beeman machine, supposing you started from nothing and did not use Educational tapes?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George hesitated. “Well — years, perhaps.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Two years? Five? Ten?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I can’t say, Honorable.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Well, there’s a vital question to which you have no answer, have you? Shall we say five years? Does that sound reasonable to you?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“I suppose so.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“All right. We have a technician studying metallurgy according to this method of yours for five years. He’s no good to us during that time, you’ll admit but he must be fed and housed and paid all that time.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Let me finish. Then when he’s done and can use the Beeman, five years have passed. Don’t you suppose we’ll have modified Beemans then which he won’t be able to use?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But by then he’ll be expert on learning. He could learn the new details necessary in a matter of days.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“So you say. And suppose this friend of yours, for instance, had studied up on Beemans on his own and managed to learn it; would he be as expert in its use as a competitor who had learned it off the tapes?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Maybe not —” began George.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Ah,” said the Novian.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Wait, let me finish. Even if he doesn’t know something as well, it’s the ability to learn further that’s important. He may be able to think up things, new things that no tape-Educated man would. You’ll have a reservoir of original thinkers — ”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“In your studying,” said the Novian, “have you thought up any new things?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“No, but I’m just one man and I haven’t studied long —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes. — Well, ladies, gentlemen, have we been sufficiently amused?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Wait,” cried George, in sudden panic.“I want to arrange a personal interview. There are things I can’t explain over the visiphone. There are details —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The Novian looked past George. “Ingenescu! I think I have done you your favor. Now, really, I have a heavy schedule tomorrow. Be well!”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The screen went blank.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George’s hands shot out toward the screen, as though in a wild impulse to shake life back into it. He cried out, “He didn’t believe me. He didn’t believe me.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said, “No, George. Did you really think he would?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George scarcely heard him. “But why not? It’s all true. It’s all so much to his advantage. No risk. I and a few men to work with — A dozen men training for years would cost less than one technician. — He was drunk! Drunk! He didn’t understand.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George looked about breathlessly. “How do I get to him? I’ve got to. This was wrong. Shouldn’t have used the visiphone. I need time. Face to face. How do I-”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said, “He won’t see you, George. And if he did, he wouldn’t believe you.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“He will, I tell you. When he isn’t drinking. He-” George turned squarely toward the Historian and his eyes widened. “Why do you call me George?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Isn’t that your name? George Platen?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You know me?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“All about you.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George was motionless except for the breath pumping his chest wall up and down.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Ingenescu said, “I want to help you, George. I told you that. I’ve been studying you and I want to help you.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George screamed, “I don’t need help. I’m not feeble-minded. The whole world is, but I’m not.” He whirled and dashed madly for the door.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He flung it open and two policemen roused themselves suddenly from their guard duty and seized him.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;For all George’s straining, he could feel the hypo-spray at the fleshy point just under the corner of his jaw, and that was it. The last thing he remembered was the face of Ingenescu, watching with gentle concern.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George opened his eyes to the whiteness of a ceiling. He remembered what had happened. He remembered it distantly as though it had happened to somebody else. He stared at the ceiling till the whiteness filled his eyes and washed his brain clean, leaving room, it seemed, for new thought and new ways of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;He didn’t know how long he lay there so, listening to the drift of his own thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There was a voice in his ear. “Are you awake?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And George heard his own moaning for the first time. Had he been moaning? He tried to turn his head.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The voice said, “Are you in pain, George?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George whispered, “Funny. I was so anxious to leave Earth. I didn’t understand.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Do you know where you are?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Back in the — the House.” George managed to turn. The voice belonged to Omani.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “It’s funny I didn’t understand.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani smiled gently, “Sleep again —”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George slept.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And woke again. His mind was clear.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani sat at the bedside reading, but he put down the book as George’s eyes opened.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George struggled to a sitting position. He said, “Hello.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Are you hungry?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You bet.” He stared at Omani curiously. “I was followed when I left, wasn’t I?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani nodded. “You were under observation at all times. We were going to maneuver you to Antonelli and let you discharge your aggressions. We felt that to be the way you could make progress. Your emotions were clogging your advance.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, with a trace of embarrassment, “I was all wrong about him.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“It doesn’t matter now. When you stopped to stare at the Metallurgy notice board at the airport, one of our agents reported back the list of names. You and I had talked about your past sufficiently so that I caught the significance of Trevelyan’s name there. You asked for directions to the Olympics; there was the possibility that this might result in the kind of crisis we were hoping for; we sent Ladislas Ingenescu to the hall to meet you and take over.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“He’s an important man in the government, isn’t he?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, he is.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And you had him take over. It makes me sound important.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You are important, George.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A thick stew had arrived, steaming, fragrant. George grinned wolfishly and pushed his sheets back to free his arms. Omani helped arrange the bed-table. For a while, George ate silently.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Then George said, “I woke up here once before just for a short time.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani said, “I know. I was here.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, I remember. You know, everything was changed. It was as though I was too tired to feel emotion. I wasn’t angry any more. I could just think. It was as though I had been drugged to wipe out emotion.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You weren’t,” said Omani. “Just sedation. You had rested.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Well, anyway, it was all clear to me, as though I had known it all the time but wouldn’t listen to myself. I thought: What was it I had wanted Novia to let me do? I had wanted to go to Novia and take a batch of un-Educated youngsters and teach them out of books. I had wanted to establish a House for the Feeble-rninded — like here — and Earth already has them — many of them.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omani’s white teeth gleamed as he smiled. “The Institute of Higher Studies is the correct name for places like this.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Now I see it,” said George, “so easily I am amazed at my blindness before. After all, who invents the new instrument models that require new-model technicians? Who invented the Beeman spectrographs, for instance? A man called Beeman, I suppose, but he couldn’t have been tape-Educated or how could he have made the advance?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Exactly.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Or who makes Educational tapes? Special tape-making technicians? Then who makes the tapes to train them? More advanced technicians? Then who makes the tapes — You see what I mean. Somewhere there has to be an end. Somewhere there must be men and women with capacity for original thought.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Yes, George.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George leaned back, stared over Omani’s head, and for a moment there was the return of something like restlessness to his eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Why wasn’t I told all this at the beginning?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Oh, if we could,” said Omani, “the trouble it would save us. We can analyze a mind, George, and say this one will make an adequate architect and that one a good woodworker. We know of no way of detecting the capacity for original, creative thought? It is too subtle a thing. We have some rule-of-thumb methods that mark out individuals who may possibly or potentially have such a talent.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“On Reading Day, such individuals are reported. You were, for instance. Roughly speaking, the number so reported comes to one in ten thousand. By the time Education Day arrives, these individuals are checked again, and nine out of ten of them turn out to have been false alarms. Those who remain are sent to places like this.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George said, “Well, what’s wrong with telling people that one out of — of a hundred thousand will end at places like these? Then it won’t be such a shock to those who do.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“And those who don’t? The ninety-nine thousand nine hundred and ninety-nine that don’t? We can’t have all those people considering themselves failures. They aim at the professions and one way or another they all make it. Everyone can place after his or her name: Registered something-or-other. In one fashion or another every individual has his or her place in society and this is necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“But we?” said George. “The one in one hundred thousand exception?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“You can’t be told. That’s exactly it. It’s the final test. Even after we’ve thinned out the possibilities on Education Day, nine out of ten of those who come here are not quite the material of creative genius, and there’s no way we can distinguish those nine from the tenth that we want by any form of machinery. The tenth one must tell us himself.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“How?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“We bring you here to a House for the Feeble-minded and the man who won’t accept that is the man we want. It’s a method that can be cruel but it works. It won’t do to say to a man, ‘You can create. Do so.’ It is much safer to wait for a man to say, ‘I can create, and I will do so whether you wish it or not.’ There are ten thousand men like you, George, who support the advancing technology of fifteen hundred worlds. We can’t allow ourselves to miss one recruit to that number or waste our efforts on one member who doesn’t measure up.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George pushed his empty plate out of the way and lifted a cup of coffee to his lips.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What about the people here who don’t — measure up?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“They are taped eventually and become our Social Scientists. Ingenescu is one. I am a Registered Psychologist. We are second echelon, so to speak.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George finished his coffee. He said, “I still wonder about one thing?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“What is that?”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;George threw aside the sheet and stood up. “Why do they call them Olympics?”&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Other sci-fi short stories at abelard.org:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;End Notes&lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;email email_abelard [at] abelard.org&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;© abelard, 4 december, 2000 &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;the address for this document is https://www.abelard.org/asimov.php&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;20,420 words&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.abelard.org/asimov.php"/><published>2026-01-18T02:17:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46664631</id><title>Erdos 281 solved with ChatGPT 5.2 Pro</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:58.408576+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d635e49f34142863"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve detected that JavaScript is disabled in this browser. Please enable JavaScript or switch to a supported browser to continue using x.com. You can see a list of supported browsers in our Help Center.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Help Center&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Terms of Service Privacy Policy Cookie Policy Imprint Ads info © 2026 X Corp.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://twitter.com/neelsomani/status/2012695714187325745"/><published>2026-01-18T03:48:03+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46664638</id><title>The longest Greek word</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:58.292335+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7f0ed6816b391b61"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Lopadotemachoselachogaleokranioleipsanodrimhypotrimmatosilphiokarabomelitokatakechymenokichlepikossyphophattoperisteralektryonoptekephalliokigklopeleiolagoiosiraiobaphetraganopterygon&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lopadotemachoselachogaleokranioleipsanodrimhypotrimmatosilphiokarabomelitokatakechymenokichlepikossyphophattoperisteralektryonoptokephalliokigklopeleiolagoiosiraiobaphetraganopterygon is a fictional dish originating from Aristophanes' 391 BC comedy Assemblywomen,[1] deriving from a transliteration of the Ancient Greek word λοπαδοτεμαχοσελαχογαλεοκρανιολειψανοδριμυποτριμματοσιλφιοκαραβομελιτοκατακεχυμενοκιχλεπικοσσυφοφαττοπεριστεραλεκτρυονοπτοκεφαλλιοκιγκλοπελειολαγῳοσιραιοβαφητραγανοπτερύγων. In A Greek–English Lexicon, it is defined as the "name of a dish compounded of all kinds of dainties, fish, flesh, fowl, and sauces".[2]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is the longest Greek word, containing 171 letters and 78 syllables. The transliteration has 183 Latin characters and is the longest word ever to appear in literature, according to the Guinness World Records (1990).[3]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Variant forms&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;The form of the word quoted here is the version listed in the Liddell &amp;amp; Scott Greek lexicon (1940) and quoted therein as being amended by August Meineke,[2] contrasting F.W. Hall and W.M. Geldart's 1907 edition of Aristophanis Comoediae (used in the Assemblywomen play) variant of (differences underlined):&lt;lb/&gt; λοπαδοτεμαχοσελαχογαλεοκρανιολειψανοδριμυποτριμματοσιλφιοτυρομελιτοκατακεχυμενοκιχλεπικοσσυφοφαττοπεριστεραλεκτρυονοπτεκεφαλλιοκιγκλοπελειολαγῳοσιραιοβαφητραγανοπτερυγώ.[4] &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Description&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;The dish was a fricassée, with at least 16 sweet and sour ingredients, including the following:[3]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Fish slices&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Fish of the Elasmobranchii subclass (a shark or ray fish)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Rotted dogfish or small shark's head&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;A generally sharp-tasting dish of several ingredients grated and pounded together&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Silphion, possibly a kind of giant fennel, now believed extinct&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;A kind of crab, shrimp, or crayfish&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Honey poured down&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Wrasse (or thrush)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;A kind of sea fish or blackbird as topping&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Wood pigeon&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Domestic pigeon&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Rooster&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The roasted head of dabchick&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Hare, which could be a kind of bird or a kind of sea hare&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;New wine boiled down&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Wing and/or fin&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Context&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;The term is used in the ultimate chorus of the play, when Blepyrus (and the audience) are summoned to the first feast laid on by the new system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1167] And you others, let your light steps too keep time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;[1168] Very soon we'll be eating&lt;lb/&gt;[1170] lopadotemachoselachogaleokranioleipsanodrimypotrimmatosilphiokarabomelitokatakechymenokichlepikossyphophattoperisteralektryonoptekephaliokigklopeleiolagoiosiraiobaphetraganopterygon [sic].&lt;lb/&gt;[1175] Come, quickly, seize hold of a plate, snatch up a cup, and let's run to secure a place at table. The rest will have their jaws at work by this time.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;— translation ed. Eugene O'Neill, 1938[1]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;English translations&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;In English prose translation by Leo Strauss (1966), this Greek word is rendered as "oysters-saltfish-skate-sharks'-heads-left-over-vinegar-dressing-laserpitium-leek-with-honey-sauce-thrush-blackbird-pigeon-dove-roast-cock's-brains-wagtail-cushat-hare-stewed-in-new-wine-gristle-of-veal-pullet's-wings".[5]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;English verse translation by Benjamin Bickley Rogers (1902) follows the original meter and the original form of composition:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plattero-filleto-mulleto-turboto-&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;-Cranio-morselo-pickleo-acido-&lt;lb/&gt;-Silphio-honeyo-pouredonthe-topothe-&lt;lb/&gt;-Ouzelo-throstleo-cushato-culvero-&lt;lb/&gt;-Cutleto-roastingo-marowo-dippero-&lt;lb/&gt;-Leveret-syrupu-gibleto-wings.[6]&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;An older English verse translation by Rev. Rowland Smith (1833) breaks the original word into several verses:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Limpets, oysters, salt fish,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;And a skate too a dish,&lt;lb/&gt;Lampreys, with the remains&lt;lb/&gt;Of sharp sauce and birds' brains,&lt;lb/&gt;With honey so luscious,&lt;lb/&gt;Plump blackbirds and thrushes,&lt;lb/&gt;Cocks' combs and ring doves,&lt;lb/&gt;Which each epicure loves,&lt;lb/&gt;Also wood-pigeons blue,&lt;lb/&gt;With juicy snipes too,&lt;lb/&gt;And to close all, O rare!&lt;lb/&gt;The wings of jugged hare![7]&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;See also&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Longest word in English&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Hubert Blaine Wolfeschlegelsteinhausenbergerdorff Sr.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Cneoridium dumosum (Nuttall) Hooker F. Collected March 26, 1960, at an Elevation of about 1450 Meters on Cerro Quemazón, 15 Miles South of Bahía de Los Angeles, Baja California, México, Apparently for a Southeastward Range Extension of Some 140 Miles&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;References&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b "Aristophanes, Ecclesiazusae (ed. Eugene O'Neill, Jr.), line 1163". Perseus.tufts.edu. Retrieved 2011-01-27.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b λοπαδοτεμαχοσελαχογαλεοκρανιολειψανοδριμυποτριμματοσιλφιοκαραβόμελιτοκατακεχυμενοκιχλεπικοσσυφοφαττοπεριστεραλεκτρυονοπτοκεφαλλιοκιγκλοπελειολαγῳοσιραιοβαφητραγανοπτερύγων. Liddell, Henry George; Scott, Robert; A Greek–English Lexicon at the Perseus Project.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b "Guinness Book of World Records, 1990 ed, pg. 129". Archived from the original on 2020-10-07. (ISBN 0-8069-5790-5)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Aristophanes (1907). "1169–1175". Aristophanis Comoediae. Vol. 2 (F.W. Hall and W.M. Geldart ed.). Oxford: Clarendon Press. Archived from the original on 2021-02-26. Retrieved 2021-02-20.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ "Leo Strauss: On Aristophanes' Ecclesiazusae, &amp;amp; translation [1966]". Retrieved 2013-03-20.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ "The Ecclesiazusae of Aristophanes". Retrieved 2013-03-20.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Rev. Rowland Smith (1833). The Ecclesiazusae, or Female Parliament. Oxford.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lopado%C2%ADtemacho%C2%ADselacho%C2%ADgaleo%C2%ADkranio%C2%ADleipsano%C2%ADdrim%C2%ADhypo%C2%ADtrimmato%C2%ADsilphio%C2%ADkarabo%C2%ADmelito%C2%ADkatakechy%C2%ADmeno%C2%ADkichl%C2%ADepi%C2%ADkossypho%C2%ADphatto%C2%ADperister%C2%ADalektryon%C2%ADopte%C2%ADkephallio%C2%ADkigklo%C2%ADpeleio%C2%ADlagoio%C2%ADsiraio%C2%ADbaphe%C2%ADtragano%C2%ADpterygon"/><published>2026-01-18T03:49:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46664646</id><title>U.S. Court Order Against Anna's Archive Spells More Trouble for the Site</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:58.112799+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a20022354561115b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive has had its fair share of domain troubles over the past two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, the site lost control over its original annas-archive.org domain after the U.S.-based Public Interest Registry (PIR) placed it on serverHold.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PIR typically only takes these kinds of measures based on a court order. However, when we asked for more details, the registry informed us that it was “unable to comment on the situation at this time,” only adding to the mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few days ago, the domain trouble continued when Anna’s Archive’s .SE domain suddenly became unresponsive after being operational for years. For this domain, the registrar took action, as the site was put on clientHold. While we tried to get additional information from the registrar, our requests remained unanswered.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While it is clear that ‘something’ is going on, it’s not clear what. The troubles started not long after Anna’s Archive announced that it had backed up Spotify, but there is no concrete link to a music industry push against the site.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;OCLC Seeks Permanent Injunction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What we do know for certain is that Anna’s Archive’s troubles are not over yet. Yesterday, a federal court in Ohio issued a default judgment and permanent injunction against the site’s unidentified operator(s).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This order was requested by OCLC, which owns the proprietary WorldCat database that was scraped and published by Anna’s Archive more than two years ago. OCLC initially demanded millions of dollars in damages but eventually dropped this request, focusing on taking the site down through an injunction that would also apply to intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Anna’s Archive’s flagrantly illegal actions have damaged and continue to irreparably damage OCLC. As such, issuance of a permanent injunction is necessary to stop any further harm to OCLC,” the request read.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pivot makes sense since Anna’s Archive did not respond to the lawsuit and would likely ignore all payment demands too. However, with the right type of court order, third-party services such as hosting companies and domain registrars might come along.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Court Grants Default Judgment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The permanent injunction, issued by U.S. District Court Judge Michael Watson yesterday, does not mention any third-party services by name. However, it is directed at all parties that are “in active concert and participation with” Anna’s Archive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Specifically, the site’s operator and these third parties are prohibited from scraping WorldCat data, storing or distributing the data on Anna’s Archive websites, and encouraging others to store, use or share this data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additionally, the site has to delete all WorldCat data, which also includes all torrents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Judge Watson denied the default judgment for ‘unjust enrichment’ and ‘tortious interference.’ However, he granted the order based on the ‘trespass to chattels’ and ‘breach of contract’ claims.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The latter is particularly noteworthy, as the judge ruled that because Anna’s Archive is a ‘sophisticated party’ that scraped the site daily, it had constructive notice of the terms and entered into a ‘browsewrap‘ agreement simply by using the service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While these nuances are important for legal experts, the result for Anna’s Archive is that it lost. And while there are no monetary damages, the permanent injunction can certainly have an impact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More Trouble Ahead?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is expected that OCLC will use the injunction to motivate third-party intermediaries to take action against Anna’s Archive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether intermediaries are considered in “active concert” with Anna’s Archive will differ based on who you ask. However, OCLC previously said that it intends to “take the&lt;lb/&gt; judgment to website hosting services to remove WorldCat data from Anna’s Archive’s websites”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The injunction that was issued yesterday obviously cannot explain the earlier domain name troubles. That said, it’s not unthinkable that OCLC will also send the injunction to domain registrars and registries, to add further pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;—&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A copy of the opinion and order issued by U.S. District Court Judge Michael Watson is available here (pdf).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://torrentfreak.com/u-s-court-order-against-annas-archive-spells-more-trouble-for-the-site/"/><published>2026-01-18T03:52:10+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46664755</id><title>jQuery 4</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:58.038676+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://blog.jquery.com/2026/01/17/jquery-4-0-0/"/><published>2026-01-18T04:23:28+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46665310</id><title>ThinkNext Design</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:57.629316+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="95b8fa1149122166"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design is far more than form or function. Itâs the tangible expression of a brandâs identity, values, and promise. While a brand defines what a company stands for, design gives those aspirations form and substance. Design uniquely delivers value: visually, physically, and experientially.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At ThinkNext Design, every creation begins with empathy and seeks purpose. We look to understand not just what people need, but what they desire. Whether crafting something entirely new or reimagining the familiar, our work blends aesthetic restraint with purposeful clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result is innovative design that resonates emotionally, performs beautifully, and endures as a reflection of the brand behind it. More than 200,000,000 ThinkPads have been sold since 1992, and still counting. That didn't happen by accident.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the early 1990's, the original IBM AS/400 product line was rapidly losing market share due to a growing perception that the product family employed outdated technology, and was highly overpriced. David led a strategic design initiative to recast that image via a sweeping change that would forever reposition the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The resulting award winning design featured stark black enclosures, dramatic air inlets, and simple yet powerful forms. This was a striking contrast to the putty colored neutral appearance that had come to dominate not only the IBM server products, but the entire industry. Following the series introduction, AS/400 Division revenues jumped by a double-digit percentage. Comments of yesterday's technology were quickly replaced by associations with objects such as the innovative F117a stealth fighter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AS/400 systems had a control panel that included special functions that were designed to only be accessed by authorized operators. Restricted access was achieved using a traditional stainless steel keylock mated to a rotating electric switch. Without the key only basic functions could be operated. Unfortunately the assembly was very costly and the metal key/lock was a source of potential electrostatic discharge. The security keystick eliminated the dated and flawed assembly entirely. Inserting the asymmetrical key enabled access to the restricted functions, cost a fraction of the previous solution and eliminated the ESD issue altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The soft rim and soft dome caps were added in 1997 creating a suite of Trackpoint cap options. The introduction followed an exhaustive design-led initiative to improve the existing cat tongue cap's comfort and utility. The effort revealed that three caps were better than one, giving the user choice. All three were shipped with every ThinkPad for many years. Only the soft dome cap remains in production.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prior to the introduction of the Netfinity 7000, IBM's PC servers were tower based offerings that often found themselves awkwardly placed on shelves in generic computer racks. The Netfinity design eliminated this makeshift approach with a "rack and stack" solution. The system could truly rack mount using industry standard rails, or stand alone as a tower. The design also included a stacking NetBay with provision for mounting rack mounted OEM devices without purchasing a full blown rack. Many of the system components, including hardfiles, were removable from the front without tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ThinkPad ThinkLight was first introduced on the ThinkPad i Series 1400. Observing a fellow airline passenger reading using a small light clipped to the top edge of their book, David immediately thought this idea could be adapted for use on a laptop. The final design used a white LED to illuminate the keyboard from the top bezel. It was the industry's first, and arguably most effective method, of illuminating a laptop keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The introduction of the IBM Personal Computer in 1981 was a technology milestone that forever changed the world. Subsequent innovation, however, was primarily limited to technology advancements and improved affordability. In nearly 20 years, little had been done to dramatically change the design paradigm of metal box, chunky monitor, and keyboard. David initiated and led a design project to reinvent the standard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Working in close collaboration with noted designer Richard Sapper, David and his team created an industry-leading all-in-one computer that capitalized on emerging flat-panel display technology. The final, award-winning design integrated the monitor, CPU, and optical drive into a remarkably slim profile. The optical drive was discreetly concealed within the base structure, dropping down smoothly at the touch of a button.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bucking the trend for bloated, frivolous designs, the Aptiva S Series speakers were conceived to match the unique angular design language of the flat panel based computer design. The sophisticated desktop speakers could be customized with brightly colored fabric grills adding to the premium image. The design was selected by Dieter Rams for a Best of Category award at the annual IF Design Exhibition in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ThinkPad X300 stands as a landmark in industrial design, proving how disciplined engineering and purposeful aesthetics can redefine an entire product category. Its carbon-fiber and magnesium construction, meticulously refined form, and forward-looking adoption of SSD storage and LED backlighting positioned it as a breakthrough ultraportable long before such features became commonplace. Its development earned widespread attention, most notably in BusinessWeekâs cover story âThe Making of the ThinkPad X300,â which showcased the intense, design-driven effort behind the machine. The project was explored even more deeply in Steve Hammâs book The Race for Perfect, which chronicled the X300âs creation as an example of ambitious, high-stakes innovation. Together, these accounts cement the X300âs legacy as one of the most influential and thoughtfully crafted ThinkPads ever made.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Skylight was an early âsmartbookâ product designed as a lightweight, always-connected device that blended elements of a smartphone and laptop. The imaginative overall product design was created by Richard Sapper, but the keyboard was the work of David and his team. Although the product was short-lived, the sculpted island style keyboard was eventually adopted for use on future ThinkPad and consumer laptops. The sculpted key surface and unique D-shape aid substantially in enhancing comfort and improving typing accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shortly following the Lenovo acquisition of IBM's PC business, the IBM logo was removed from ThinkPad. David was a strong proponent of establishing ThinkPad as the primary badge on the product due to the brand's high recognition and subsequent value. He proposed using the sub-brand font, normally appearing below the IBM logo, as ThinkPad's new wordmark. He enhanced it with a bright red dot over the letter i which was derived from the TrackPoint cap. His now iconic concept was universally adopted as the new ThinkPad product badge worldwide in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2010 the dot was enhanced with a glowing red LED that is still in use today. The dot glows solid if the ThinkPad is powered on and slowly pulses like a heartbeat when in a suspended sleep state. The design draws attention and adds life to the brand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first-generation ThinkPad X1 Carbon introduced a bold new interpretation of classic ThinkPad design. It's carbon-fiber reinforced chassis delivered exceptional strength with a remarkably low weight. The sculpted island-style keyboard, subtle red accents, and gently tapered edges gave it a modern precision appearance without sacrificing the brand's renowned usability &amp;amp; iconic visual impression.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scaled-down travel mouse shares it's essential geometry with a mouse originally created for IBM's Aptiva lineup in the late 1990's. The characteristically low front, generously sculpted tail and inwardly inclined side surfaces enhance ergonomics and daily use. These design concepts have been nearly universally adopted by other computer/accessory manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When using a tablet as a camera the screen cover typically flops around since folding it all the way around would block the camera. The quickshot cover eliminates this inconvenience thanks to a patented folding corner. When folded back, it automatically launched the camera app to let you take a picture instantly. The flopping cover annoyance was eliminated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The revolutionary design replaced the bezel/box paradigm with a form that resembles a rectangular tube through which large volumes of air pass. The unique appearance telegraphs raw power. The design, however, is much more than skin deep. The machine's innovative interior is highly modular and eliminates the need for tools to replace or upgrade key components. Flush handles are thoughtfully incorporated in the shell for moving the workstation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pioneering ThinkPad X1 Tablet design featured a uniquely hinged kickstand that enabled customizing the user experience with a system of snap-on modules. Modules offered were the Productivity Module, which added extra battery life and additional ports; the Presenter Module, featuring a built-in pico projector for critical presentations; and the 3D Imaging Module, equipped with an Intel RealSense camera for depth sensing and 3D scanning. Together, these modules provided flexible, on-demand functionality while preserving the tabletâs portability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ThinkPad 25 was created and launched to celebrate the 25th anniversary of the iconic brand. It artfully blended retro design elements with modern engineering. Inspired heavily by years of passionate customer feedback and social-media campaigns calling for a âclassic ThinkPadâ revival, the project brought back beloved features such as the 7-row keyboard with blue accents, a tradition-inspired ThinkPad logo, and TrackPoint cap options. Wrapped in a soft-touch black chassis and powered by contemporary hardware, the ThinkPad 25 stood as a collaborative tributeâshaped not only by Lenovoâs designers but also by a global community of fans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originally written and designed for the 20th anniversary celebration held at the MoMA. The highly collectable work was updated in 2025 for the 25th anniversary limited edition ThinkPad T25. Both booklets document and illuminate David Hill's beliefs and philosophies that have shaped the design of ThinkPad for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ThinkPad ThinkShutter is a simple, built-in mechanical privacy cover designed to give users instant control over their webcam. Sliding smoothly across the lens, it provides a clear visual indication when the camera is physically blocked, eliminating reliance on questionable software controls or LED indicators. It integrates cleanly into the display bezel adding negligible thickness. Achieving peace of mind with makeshift solutions such as masking tape, Post-it notes, and even clothespins are a thing of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://thinknextdesign.com/home.html"/><published>2026-01-18T06:27:24+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46665393</id><title>Show HN: GibRAM an in-memory ephemeral GraphRAG runtime for retrieval</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:57.177009+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d280b119988a81d3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Graph in-Buffer Retrieval &amp;amp; Associative Memory&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Graph in-Buffer: Graph structure (entities + relationships) stored in RAM&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Retrieval: Query mechanism for retrieving relevant context in RAG workflows&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Associative Memory: Traverse between associated nodes via relationships, all accessed from memory&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GibRAM is an in-memory knowledge graph server designed for retrieval augmented generation (RAG) workflows. It combines a lightweight graph store with vector search so that related pieces of information remain connected in memory. This makes it easier to retrieve related regulations, articles or other text when a query mentions specific subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;In memory and Ephemeral: Data lives in RAM with a configurable time to live. It is meant for short lived analysis and exploration rather than persistent storage.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Graph and Vectors Together: Stores named entities, relationships and document chunks alongside their embeddings in the same structure.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Graph aware Retrieval: Supports traversal over entities and relations as well as semantic search, helping you pull in context that would be missed by vector similarity alone.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Python SDK: Provides a GraphRAG style workflow for indexing documents and running queries with minimal code. Components such as chunker, extractor and embedder can be swapped out.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Install via script
curl -fsSL https://gibram.io/install.sh | sh

# Run server
gibram-server --insecure&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Server runs on port 6161 by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Run server
docker run -p 6161:6161 gibramio/gibram:latest

# With custom config
docker-compose up -d&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pip install gibram&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Basic Usage:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from gibram import GibRAMIndexer

# Initialize indexer
indexer = GibRAMIndexer(
    session_id="my-project",
    host="localhost",
    port=6161,
    llm_api_key="sk-..."  # or set OPENAI_API_KEY env
)

# Index documents
stats = indexer.index_documents([
    "Python is a programming language created by Guido van Rossum.",
    "JavaScript was created by Brendan Eich at Netscape in 1995."
])

print(f"Entities: {stats.entities_extracted}")
print(f"Relationships: {stats.relationships_extracted}")

# Query
results = indexer.query("Who created JavaScript?", top_k=3)
for entity in results.entities:
    print(f"{entity.title}: {entity.score}")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom Components:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from gibram import GibRAMIndexer
from gibram.chunkers import TokenChunker
from gibram.extractors import OpenAIExtractor
from gibram.embedders import OpenAIEmbedder

indexer = GibRAMIndexer(
    session_id="custom-project",
    chunker=TokenChunker(chunk_size=512, chunk_overlap=50),
    extractor=OpenAIExtractor(model="gpt-4o", api_key="..."),
    embedder=OpenAIEmbedder(model="text-embedding-3-small", api_key="...")
)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/gibram-io/gibram"/><published>2026-01-18T06:47:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46665411</id><title>Iconify: Library of Open Source Icons</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:56.567827+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="c0e6ff1a983ae48e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iconify .design Filter icon sets... Category Tag Grid Palette and license Material UI 24px UI 16px / 32px UI Other / Mixed Grid UI Multicolor Programming Logos Emoji Flags / Maps Thematic Archive / Unmaintained Material (6 icon sets) Material Symbols Apache 2.0 15107 icons Material Symbols Light Apache 2.0 15180 icons Google Material Icons Apache 2.0 10955 icons Material Design Icons Apache 2.0 7447 icons Material Design Light Open Font License 284 icons Material Line Icons MIT 1218 icons UI 24px (54 icon sets) Solar CC BY 4.0 7401 icons Tabler Icons MIT 5986 icons MingCute Icon Apache 2.0 3320 icons Remix Icon Apache 2.0 3188 icons Myna UI Icons MIT 2580 icons IconaMoon CC BY 4.0 1781 icons Iconoir MIT 1671 icons Lucide ISC 1667 icons Lucide Lab ISC 373 icons Unicons Apache 2.0 1215 icons TDesign Icons MIT 2130 icons Sargam Icons MIT 1299 icons BoxIcons CC BY 4.0 814 icons BoxIcons Solid CC BY 4.0 665 icons Majesticons MIT 760 icons css.gg MIT 704 icons Flowbite Icons MIT 751 icons Basil CC BY 4.0 493 icons Pixelarticons MIT 486 icons Pixel Icon CC BY 4.0 450 icons Akar Icons MIT 454 icons coolicons CC BY 4.0 442 icons ProIcons MIT 539 icons Typicons CC BY-SA 4.0 336 icons Meteor Icons MIT 321 icons Prime Icons MIT 313 icons Circum Icons Mozilla Public License 2.0 288 icons Feather Icon MIT 255 icons EOS Icons MIT 253 icons Bitcoin Icons MIT 250 icons Humbleicons MIT 286 icons Unicons Monochrome Apache 2.0 298 icons Unicons Thin Line Apache 2.0 216 icons Unicons Solid Apache 2.0 190 icons Gridicons GPL 2.0 207 icons Mono Icons MIT 180 icons Cuida Icons Apache 2.0 182 icons WeUI Icon MIT 162 icons Duoicons MIT 91 icons SVG Spinners MIT 46 icons Huge Icons MIT 4653 icons Lets Icons CC BY 4.0 1528 icons Ultimate free icons CC BY 4.0 1999 icons Plump free icons CC BY 4.0 1499 icons Sharp free icons CC BY 4.0 1500 icons Mage Icons Apache 2.0 1042 icons Stash Icons MIT 982 icons Lineicons MIT 606 icons IconPark Outline Apache 2.0 2658 icons IconPark Solid Apache 2.0 1947 icons IconPark TwoTone Apache 2.0 1944 icons Jam Icons MIT 940 icons Cyber free icons CC BY 4.0 500 icons Guidance CC BY 4.0 360 icons UI 16px / 32px (18 icon sets) Carbon Apache 2.0 2439 icons IonIcons MIT 1357 icons Famicons MIT 1342 icons Ant Design Icons MIT 830 icons Lsicon MIT 716 icons Gravity UI Icons MIT 744 icons CoreUI Free CC BY 4.0 554 icons Röntgen CC BY 4.0 514 icons Element Plus MIT 293 icons Charm Icons MIT 261 icons Quill Icons MIT 140 icons Bytesize Icons MIT 101 icons Bootstrap Icons MIT 2078 icons Pixel free icons CC BY 4.0 662 icons Streamline Block CC BY 4.0 300 icons Rivet Icons BSD 3-Clause 210 icons Nimbus MIT 140 icons FormKit Icons MIT 144 icons UI Other / Mixed Grid (34 icon sets) Fluent UI System Icons MIT 18959 icons Phosphor MIT 9072 icons Teenyicons MIT 1200 icons Clarity MIT 1103 icons Freehand free icons CC BY 4.0 1000 icons Siemens Industrial Experience Icons MIT 1415 icons Octicons MIT 720 icons Memory Icons Apache 2.0 651 icons System UIcons Unlicense 430 icons Radix Icons MIT 332 icons Zondicons MIT 297 icons uiw icons MIT 214 icons CodeX Icons MIT 78 icons Evil Icons MIT 70 icons HeroIcons MIT 1288 icons SidekickIcons MIT 232 icons Pepicons Pop! CC BY 4.0 1275 icons Pepicons Print CC BY 4.0 1275 icons Pepicons Pencil CC BY 4.0 1275 icons Framework7 Icons MIT 1253 icons Gitlab SVGs MIT 410 icons Garden SVG Icons Apache 2.0 912 icons Streamline CC BY 4.0 3000 icons Flex free icons CC BY 4.0 1500 icons Font Awesome Solid CC BY 4.0 1983 icons Font Awesome Regular CC BY 4.0 272 icons Pico-icon Open Font License 824 icons OOUI MIT 370 icons Maki CC0 215 icons Temaki CC0 543 icons OpenSearch UI Apache 2.0 437 icons NRK Core Icons CC BY 4.0 236 icons Dinkie Icons MIT 1198 icons Qlementine Icons MIT 863 icons UI Multicolor (12 icon sets) Ultimate color icons CC BY 4.0 998 icons Plump color icons CC BY 4.0 1000 icons Freehand color icons CC BY 4.0 1000 icons Kameleon color icons CC BY 4.0 400 icons Stickies color icons CC BY 4.0 200 icons Fluent UI System Color Icons MIT 890 icons Streamline color CC BY 4.0 2000 icons Flex color icons CC BY 4.0 1000 icons Sharp color icons CC BY 4.0 1000 icons Cyber color icons CC BY 4.0 500 icons IconPark Apache 2.0 2658 icons Marketeq MIT 590 icons Programming (9 icon sets) VSCode Icons MIT 1467 icons Codicons CC BY 4.0 534 icons Material Icon Theme MIT 1136 icons File Icons ISC 930 icons Devicon MIT 1022 icons Devicon Plain MIT 745 icons Catppuccin Icons MIT 656 icons Skill Icons MIT 397 icons UnJS Logos Apache 2.0 63 icons Logos (15 icon sets) Simple Icons CC0 1.0 3379 icons SVG Logos CC0 1837 icons Logos free icons CC BY 4.0 1362 icons CoreUI Brands CC0 1.0 830 icons Font Awesome Brands CC BY 4.0 548 icons BoxIcons Logo CC BY 4.0 155 icons Nonicons MIT 69 icons Arcticons CC BY-SA 4.0 14006 icons Custom Brand Icons CC BY-NC-SA 4.0 1491 icons Brandico CC BY SA 45 icons Entypo+ Social CC BY-SA 4.0 76 icons Web3 Icons MIT 1769 icons Web3 Icons Branded MIT 2024 icons Cryptocurrency Icons CC0 1.0 483 icons Cryptocurrency Color Icons CC0 1.0 483 icons Emoji (11 icon sets) OpenMoji CC BY-SA 4.0 4449 icons Twitter Emoji CC BY 4.0 3988 icons Noto Emoji Apache 2.0 3710 icons Fluent Emoji Flat MIT 3145 icons Fluent Emoji High Contrast MIT 1595 icons Noto Emoji (v1) Apache 2.0 2162 icons Emoji One (Colored) CC BY 4.0 1834 icons Emoji One (Monotone) CC BY 4.0 1403 icons Emoji One (v1) CC BY-SA 4.0 1262 icons Firefox OS Emoji Apache 2.0 1034 icons Streamline Emojis CC BY 4.0 787 icons Flags / Maps (7 icon sets) Circle Flags MIT 634 icons Flag Icons MIT 542 icons Flagpack MIT 254 icons CoreUI Flags CC0 1.0 199 icons Font-GIS CC BY 4.0 367 icons Map Icons Open Font License 167 icons GeoGlyphs MIT 30 icons Thematic (8 icon sets) Game Icons CC BY 3.0 4123 icons FontAudio CC BY 4.0 155 icons Academicons Open Font License 158 icons Weather Icons Open Font License 219 icons Meteocons MIT 447 icons Health Icons MIT 2024 icons Medical Icons MIT 144 icons Covid Icons CC BY 4.0 142 icons Archive / Unmaintained (30 icon sets) Line Awesome Apache 2.0 1544 icons Eva Icons MIT 490 icons Dashicons GPL 342 icons Flat Color Icons MIT 329 icons Entypo+ CC BY-SA 4.0 321 icons Foundation MIT 283 icons Raphael MIT 266 icons Icons8 Windows 10 Icons MIT 234 icons Innowatio Font Apache 2.0 105 icons Gala Icons GPL 51 icons HeroIcons v1 Outline MIT 230 icons HeroIcons v1 Solid MIT 230 icons Font Awesome 6 Solid CC BY 4.0 1402 icons Font Awesome 6 Regular CC BY 4.0 163 icons Font Awesome 6 Brands CC BY 4.0 495 icons Font Awesome 5 Solid CC BY 4.0 1001 icons Font Awesome 5 Regular CC BY 4.0 151 icons Font Awesome 5 Brands CC BY 4.0 457 icons Font Awesome 4 Open Font License 678 icons Fluent UI MDL2 MIT 1735 icons Fontisto MIT 615 icons IcoMoon Free GPL 491 icons Subway Icon Set CC BY 4.0 306 icons Open Iconic MIT 223 icons Icons8 Windows 8 Icons MIT 200 icons Simple line icons MIT 189 icons Elegant GPL 3.0 100 icons Elusive Icons Open Font License 304 icons Vaadin Icons Apache 2.0 636 icons Grommet Icons Apache 2.0 636 icons&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://icon-sets.iconify.design/"/><published>2026-01-18T06:53:36+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46665453</id><title>Launching the Handmade Software Foundation</title><updated>2026-01-18T09:38:56.343106+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7c385e58f82723b4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hello Handmade Network, and happy new year! 2025 was a relatively quiet year for us where we focused on just running our jams and building relationships across the Handmade community. But we’ve got lots of plans for 2026 and we’ve already been at work kicking them off!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We are finally launching the Handmade Software Foundation and using it to support the development of more Handmade software&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We’re planning an in-person gathering for this spring, more details forthcoming&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We’ll be doing two jams as usual, dates TBD based on other events&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Launching the Handmade Software Foundation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few years ago we announced that we were creating a nonprofit to support the development of Handmade software. Well, it took some time, but I am pleased to announce that the Handmade Software Foundation is now officially a 501(c)(6) nonprofit corporation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What does this mean? It means we are a nonprofit under the category carved out for business leagues, chambers of commerce, etc. In other words, we have a nonprofit category that allows us to work towards improving business conditions in the software industry. This is perfect for us, because the software industry desperately needs fixing, and by supporting Handmade software we can make more programmers aware of how powerful computers are, while also providing direct benefit to Foundation members. And the nonprofit status exempts us from income tax, meaning that 100% of donations will go directly to the nonprofit, not the government.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 501(c)(6) differs from the more familiar 501(c)(3) designation in that we are not a charity. The 501(c)(3) is explicitly designed for charitable organizations, and confers the additional benefit of donations being tax-deductible. Over time, though, the definition of a 501(c)(3) has become extremely distorted, especially in the software space, since companies were able to convince the IRS that making open-source software is a charitable/scientific activity. The result is that large companies were able to fund their own development by creating a “charity”, open-sourcing some of their core technology, and then building their extremely lucrative closed-source software on top. That way they get to deduct the core tech expenses from their taxes! What a deal!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is stupid and the IRS is not allowing this anymore. This set us back by at least a year on our nonprofit journey, but it was a blessing in disguise: the 501(c)(6) is a vastly better category that gives us much more freedom in our activities and fewer restrictions on how we spend our money. And we can support for-profit projects (like File Pilot, for example) without worry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What will the Foundation do?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The number one goal of the Handmade Software Foundation is to support, promote, and sustain the development of Handmade software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2025 we saw the breakout success of File Pilot. If you somehow haven’t seen it, it’s a brilliant little file explorer for Windows, made by a single developer, that is a mere 2 MB and is shockingly fast. It has a completely custom UI and has so much love and attention poured into every pixel. And it came out at the perfect time, as Microsoft has continued to ship baffling bugs and horrible performance regressions month after month. They even messed up Windows Explorer’s performance, and then “fixed” it by preloading it in the background so the horrible performance wouldn’t be so obvious. Who would win: a trillion-dollar company, or one guy from Croatia who watched Handmade Hero? Obviously the Croatian.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;File Pilot is an excellent template for what Handmade software should be, and how to launch it. We want to take the lessons learned from File Pilot and use them to launch more industry-redefining software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Basically, the thinking goes that Handmade programmers have the technical chops to make amazing software, but don’t always have the aptitude or desire for the many, many other tasks that go into shipping. Payments, licensing, emails, support, design, marketing, testing, the list goes on. At the same time, we want to foster self-sustaining businesses. We feel we can bring people together to provide support and guide developers through that process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our core value is that we will never compromise on self-sufficiency. We will not lock you into a Handmade E-Commerce Platform; instead, we will give you the code and the resources you need to run it yourself. I’m excited to spend more time building these resources over the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How will the Foundation make money?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Memberships! You will be able to join the Handmade Software Foundation as a member for a monthly subscription fee, the exact pricing of which is yet to be determined.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Membership will grant you access to a private Discord channel with other members, access to the aforementioned business resources, and possibly more benefits down the line. We have other ideas for Foundation activities, but we don’t want to distract ourselves from our primary goal as we get the Foundation off the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Can I join?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not quite yet! We are actively building the payment processing infrastructure now and look forward to launching memberships as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;In-person gathering this spring!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s been a while now since we got people together. We figure we should change that!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later this spring, we will be hosting an in-person gathering in Vancouver, BC. Community member Matthew (AbjMakesAPizza on Discord) is a Vancouver native who kindly volunteered to organize an event. We’ve been looking at a variety of venues and have a few good leads, and we hope to have a final location and date soon. We’re looking to host up to 100 people or so, which we feel is a healthy number to get started with in our first year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The plan is to host a “super-meetup”, of sorts: not a conference, but not just a meetup either. We want to create a space for demos, informal presentations, social gathering, jamming, and generally inspiring each other. Think a big room with lots of demo tables, a projector, a few chairs, and a mic. What’s on the agenda? Demos! Perhaps some lightning talks? That all remains to be seen as we find what the space will be capable of.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re targeting April or May, so although it’s somewhat short notice, we hope to give you all enough time to make travel plans. Stay tuned for more info!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Jams as usual&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, we’re planning to run two jams again this year. The topic for the first jam has yet to be determined; the second will be Wheel Reinvention as usual.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately at this time we don’t yet know when these jams will be held. The timing will depend on our in-person gathering in Vancouver, plus any other events of interest to Handmade folks (such as another BSC). But, just to confirm, we are doing them :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As for jam topics, I’ve been pondering how to keep the jams from getting stale. And I’m open to ideas! Should we give out prizes for different categories? Make people draw project ideas at random? Shorten the jams? Make people work in teams? In the end, I want the jams to spark new ideas and kickstart interesting projects, and that means we need to get creative juices flowing and get lots of talented programmers to participate. I’d love to hear your thoughts on Discord or in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;So long!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Look forward to more news next month! I’m committed to publishing one news post per month this year, for actual real this time. You may all heckle me if I fall behind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;May the Handmade community make a dent in the software industry in 2026!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://handmade.network/blog/p/9106-welcome_to_2026%2521#30623"/><published>2026-01-18T07:01:12+00:00</published></entry></feed>