<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:56.999542+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46139761</id><title>Show HN: I built a dashboard to compare mortgage rates across 120 credit unions</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:04.580897+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3c94a31214402b4c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Buying a home or refinancing a mortgage is tough enough without confusing ads from banks and big lenders. Credit unions can offer competitive rates compared to big banks because theyâre member-owned, non-profit institutions. They focus on serving their members, not maximizing profits for shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But without big budgets and marketing departments, credit union rates arenât always easy to find or compare. Thatâs why we built a daily-updated comparison of mortgage rates from over 120 credit unions across the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Credit Union Mortgage Rates&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last updated: December 3, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;30-Year Fixed&lt;/head&gt;Updating...&lt;p&gt;Loading rate comparison table...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: These rates are informational and not a commitment to lend. FinFam has no institutional affiliation and does not receive any referral fees.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why build this dashboard?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we bought our home, the big bank Iâd been using for years tried to sell me on a mortgage with 7% APR. Turns out a local credit union was offering 5.5% for the exact same mortgage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What surprised me most wasnât that there were cheaper options, but that two mortgages can be exactly the same product, just with different packaging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the USA, the government buys almost all mortgages, requiring them to be standardized. So why the price difference? As explored in this Bloomberg Odd Lots episode about credit card rates, higher rates are mostly to pay for advertising and marketing. Big banks have marketing departments that non-profit credit unions donât have.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That âexclusiveâ inbox offer from Chase or Wells Fargo isnât generosity. Itâs a bet that you wonât shop around. My goal with this tool is simple: help people realize they have options and potentially save thousands of dollars a year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How the dashboard works&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Itâs a little involved! ð&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Rates are collected throughout the day from the websites of approximately 120 credit unions.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;National benchmarks come from the St. Louis Federal Reserve Bank, aka FRED: 30-Year Fixed benchmark (15Y). These update weekly.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Credit union eligibility data is manually curated from individual institution websites.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some rates (around a dozen) are hidden by default because theyâre statistical outliers: likely errors or ultra-specialized products. Toggle âShow outliersâ in the filters if you want to see them anyway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Found an error? Email blog@finfam.app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Next Steps: Make Decisions, Get Quotes&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our dashboard can only take you so far. Your actual rate depends on: credit score, down payment (20%+ is ideal), property type (primary residence gets best rates), and whether you pay points for a lower rate (always compare APR).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next step: Get quotes from multiple lenders by using the rate table above to contact institutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protip: Before submitting to any credit checks, protect your privacy with optoutprescreen.com, another free and regulated service I wish Iâd known about sooner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still not sure about buying or refinancing? Check out these interactive guides:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FinFam is built around collaborative financial planning, including community-authored, spreadsheet-powered guides, like those above. Read more in our docs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Questions or Feedback?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have questions about these rates or suggestions for improving this tool? Reach out to us at blog@finfam.app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Donât see your favorite CU here? As long as it has a website with a public rates page and clear eligibility requirements, weâd be happy to add it!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Disclaimers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;These rates are informational only and donât represent rate locks. Your actual rate will vary. Contact lenders with the links in the rate table to get your personalized quotes. FinFam has no institutional affiliation and receives no referral fees, nor provides any guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shoutout /r/dataisbeautiful for the encouragement. And big thanks to Asheesh Laroia for his guidance on the matter of mortgages. See his spreadsheet-friendly take on the data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://finfam.app/blog/credit-union-mortgages"/><published>2025-12-03T20:35:27+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46140244</id><title>8086 Microcode Browser</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:04.504853+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f1bc214a171d033"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;8086 Microcode Browser&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since releasing 486Tang, I’ve been working on recreating the 8086 with a design that stays as faithful as possible to the original chip. That exploration naturally led me deep into the original 8086 microcode — extracted and disassembled by Andrew Jenner in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like all microcoded CPUs, the 8086 hides a lot of subtle behavior below the assembly layer. While studying it I kept extensive notes, and those eventually evolved into something more useful: an interactive browser for the entire 8086 microcode ROM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So here it is: the online 8086 microcode browser. Every 21-bit micro-instruction is decoded into readable fields. Hover over any field and you’ll get a tooltip explaining what it does. All jump targets are clickable — the 8086 μcode uses a surprising number of indirect jumps, calls, and short branches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One handy feature is Browse by Instruction. Click the button and you’ll get a list of ~300 documented 8086 instructions. Select any one, and the viewer jumps directly to its μcode entry point. Internally there are only about 60 unique μcode entry routines, and this feature makes navigating them effortless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;A few fun tidbits about 8086 μcode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Register IDs change meaning depending on context. For example,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;10100&lt;/code&gt;refers to SIGMA (the ALU result) when used as a source, but to tmpaL (the low 8 bits of a temporary ALU register) when used as a destination.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;N and R are the same physical register. Meanwhile, SI is called IJ internally — naming inside the chip is extremely inconsistent and reflects its evolutionary design process.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;IP (PC) does not point to the next instruction. It actually points to the next prefetch address. The μcode uses a dedicated micro-operation called CORR to rewind IP back to the true next-instruction boundary when handling branches and interrupts.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost all arithmetic instructions share the same 4 μinstructions (&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;008–00B&lt;/code&gt;). The heavy lifting is done by a single micro-operation named XI, which performs different arithmetic behaviors depending on opcode or ModRM bits. The amount of reuse here is elegant — and very 1978 Intel.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nand2mario.github.io/posts/2025/8086_microcode_browser/"/><published>2025-12-03T21:16:11+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46141745</id><title>Acme, a brief history of one of the protocols which has changed the Internet</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:03.754091+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6d19b1920b220c9d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ACME, a brief history of one of the protocols which has changed the Internet Security&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Preamble&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would like to share with you this article I wrote about the ACME protocol, which I “fell in love with” about ten years ago. It is for me a way to give back to this fantastic Free Software and Open Protocols developers community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This article is about the roots, the conception, the standardization, the relation with its ecosystem and the evolution challenges faced by the ACME protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To write this article, I had the privilege of interviewing several people who have been involved in the creation and the evolution of ACME: Aaron Gable, Sarah Gran, Jacob Hoffman-Andrews and J.C. Jones (more below).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you so much to all of you for your time and support! ð&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Internet and Network Protocols&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Open and Standardized Protocols at the Heart of the Internetâs Success&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During the 1990s, computing underwent a true revolution driven by the rise and global spread of the Internet. The Internet fulfilled the promise embodied in Sun Microsystemsâ slogan “The Network is the Computer”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By interconnecting individual computers, the Internet enabled its users to communicate without limits and without worrying about borders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This unrestricted interconnection emerged at a pivotal moment in modern history: the opposition between the West and the Eastern Bloc led by the USSR hadâalbeit temporarily, as we now knowâfaded away, China was becoming the worldâs factory, and the movement and collaboration between people were much freer and open than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Internet supported a kind of utopia of instant communication and sharing, previously unknown. This utopia was made possible by a set of open and standardized protocols. This was the key to enabling all kinds of different systems to cooperate and communicate seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were, of course, isolationist or monopolistic temptations from certain manufacturers or software editors. But open and standardized protocols ultimately prevailed, enabling unprecedented expansion. Built on top of IP, TCP, UDP, and DNS, among others, the HTTP and HTML duo would propel the Web as the Internetâs preferred communication platform for the next 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Limited Use of Encryption&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The success of this communication utopia was achieved without much concern for ensuring authentication, integrity, and confidentiality of exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2015, only ~40% of websites used encryption. The consequences of this negligence in addressing security risks were confirmed by Edward Snowdenâs revelations in 2013: our data was exposed to anyone who wanted and could intercept and collect it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Let’s Encrypt is coming&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Birth of an Automated and Free Certificate Authority&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When asked about the main obstacles to the widespread adoption of encryption, J.C. Jones, one of the architects of Letâs Encrypt and now one of its site reliability engineers after leading Firefoxâs cryptographic team, responds:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“More and more information was flowing across the Web, and most data being transferred did not have integrity or confidential protections from TLS. The biggest stumbling block to using TLS everywhere was obtaining and managing server-side certificates, and so: Letâs Encrypt” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Obtaining a certificate was the main obstacle, and this was the priority to address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This view was shared by a group of partners who, starting in 2013, pooled resources to establish Letâs Encrypt, an automated and free certificate authority. Sarah Gran, VP of Advancement at Letâs Encrypt, shares:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Early collaborators included people from Mozilla, Electronic Frontier Foundation, Akamai, Cisco, and the University of Michigan” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that’s how Let’s Encrypt was born.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the Web ecosystem, certificate authorities are organizations from which you can obtain a certificate for a domain after proving you control it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so, Let’s Encrypt is since 2015 a certificate authority that delivers for free (as in free beer) TLS Server certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the legal/administrative side, Let’s Encrypt certificate authority operates for the publicâs benefit and is a service provided by the Internet Security Research Group (ISRG), a California public benefit corporation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regarding Let’s Encrypt results ten years after its birth, they are really impressive (over 700M active certificates, over 60% of all the public TLS server certificates) and as Sarah Gran points out, so is the global HTTPS usage:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“When we started issuance, only about 39% of website visits were HTTPS. Today, itâs nearly 95% in the United States, and over 83% globally. We still have work to do, but we are proud of the progress weâve made over the last ten years” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s Encrypt delivers certificates in a automated manner using the ACME protocol which implies no manual action from the site owner nor the certificate authority. So, let’s speak now a little about the automation aspect!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Automation: The Core of the Operation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the mid-2020s perspective, the automation at the heart of Letâs Encrypt might seem obvious, but in the first half of the 2010s, it was far from the norm. The ecosystem of public certificate authorities issuing server certificates was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At first glance, automation appears to be there to help website managers reliably deploy the TLS protocol on their sites, but it was first and foremost an absolute prerequisite for the very viability of the Let’s Encrypt project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Aaron Gable, tech lead of Boulderâthe software at the core of Letâs Encryptâ, confirms:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Automation was always going to be critical to Letâs Encryptâs success. From the very beginning, we knew that there was no way we could scale manual validation on a non-profitâs budget” – Aaron Gable&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, it is worth noting that Letâs Encrypt has operated on an Internet scale from the start with a small team of about fifteen engineers, or even fewer at launch. For this team, automation was the only viable way to fulfill the immense mission they had set for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ACME&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Open and automated Protocol That Powers Letâs Encrypt&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we talk about automation in relation to Letâs Encrypt, we are talking about ACME (Automated Certificate Management Environment).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This protocol allows client software to prove to an ACME-compatible certificate authority that it controls the domain for which it is requesting a certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sarah Gran clarifies an important point:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“An important aspect of how Letâs Encrypt works is that we verify control over a domain, not ownership” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Control vs. ownership of a domainâa nuance everyone should keep in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This proof of control involves the client responding to a challenge issued by the ACME-compatible certificate authority. The challenge can be an HTTP, DNS, or TLS challenge, depending on the clientâs choice and certificate authority support. Completing the challenge requires the ACME client to place a value provided by the ACME serverâin a standardized HTTP path, a DNS zone, or a TLS response, respectively. All of these operations involve cryptography, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key point with ACME is that this entire dialogue between the client and the ACME server is executed without any human intervention, enabling the automatic issuance of certificates. Their deployment and integration into the web service can also generally be automated using scripts triggered after issuance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the Let’s Encrypt website, you can discover more information about how ACME works and get more detailled information about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Birth of ACME&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One might wonder whether ACME was part of Letâs Encryptâs design from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;J.C. Jones confirms:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“By late 2014, the idea of an HTTP REST API with “/challenge” and “/certificate” existed, but we hadnât defined much beyond that. We had a series of in-person meetings, in the Mozilla San Francisco office on Embarcadero and the EFF office in the Tenderloin through the spring of 2015 where we worked out the details” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ACME was indeed at the core of Letâs Encrypt from the start and underwent a refinement process to cover all use cases as thoroughly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To learn more about the roots of ACME and Let’s Encrypt, there is a very informative document to read: the Let’s Encrypt paper for ACM CCS 2019 in London. It mentions the previous work of two teams:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“A group led by Alex Halderman at the University of Michigan and Peter Eckersley at EFF was developing a protocol for automatically issuing and renewing certificates. Simultaneously, a team at Mozilla led by Josh Aas and Eric Rescorla was working on creating a free and automated certificate authority”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When these two teams discovered each other’s work, they joined forces. ACME and its implementation in Let’s Encrypt were the result of this joint effort supported by the initial partners mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Securing the Web or the Internet?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of use cases, one might wonder whether the Web was Letâs Encryptâs primary target, or if securing the Internet with its multiple protocols was also part of the objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sarah Gran provides an unambiguous first-level answer:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“From Day One, we have sought to get the web to 100% encryption” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But when asked about the various types of challenges in the protocol, J.C. Jones offers a nuance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“DNS, TLS-SNI, and HTTP were all in planning in spring 2015, but many of us were less confident in the procedure around the DNS validation. Which is ironic, as it turned out TLS-SNI had a vulnerability so we had to stop using it and our DNS validation was ultimately fine. In general, the collection of us were simply respectful of the great complexity within the DNS” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a perspective not often publicly expressed by engineers primarily from the Web: their lack of confidence in implementing a DNS challenge stemmed from their humility regarding the complexity of the DNS ecosystem and the level of expertise required to master it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The challenge was ultimately met, and this DNS challengeâthough not its primary purposeâenabled multiple protocols outside HTTP like SMTP to be secured by ACME.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Standardization and Open Source&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Developed in the Open&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ACME was documented openly from the start, and Certbot, the first open-source ACME client co-developed with the EFF, served as the client side reference implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, a standardization process through the IETF resulted in RFC 8555 in March, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the consequences developing an open and standardized protocol was the creation of a multitude of ACME clients covering a very wide range of use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;J.C. Jones confirms that this was the goal:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“This is what we foresaw, or at least hoped for. The initial client development often had conversations like, âoh, if someone wants that, then theyâll write their own client.â It was a key part of why the REST API needed to be an IETF standard, and was part of the argument at the IETF BoF that resulted in the formation of the ACME Working Group in Q3 2015” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Letâs Encrypt has also always provided constant support to developers by responding in its forum or on its GitHub issue tracker, and all this work has truly paid off. An interesting post has been recently written about support on the Let’s Encrypt blog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Standardization for what benefits?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other question that can be asked is whether or not the standardization process within the IETF has led to an improvement in the ACME protocol thanks to the cooperation that guides this process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jacob Hoffman-Andrews, one of the RFC 8555 authors working for EFF &amp;amp; Let’s Encrypt, confirms an initial benefit that the ACME protocol has been able to derive from its standardization process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“One of the big changes was from a validation-first flow to a certificate-request-first flow. In other words, earlier drafts had subscribers requesting validation for domain names and then requesting a certificate once those validations were successful. The final RFC has subscribers request a certificate, and then the CA tells the subscriber what validations are needed. This change originated from within the IETF discussion process, and was intended to make handling of wildcard certificates more natural.” – Jacob Hoffman-Andrews&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aside this first design improvement, Jacob details a second major improvement of the security of the protocol, improvement that also landed during the IETF standardization process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Another big change, also originated from within the IETF, was to make all requests authenticated, including GET requests. Since ACME is authenticated with signed POSTs, this necessitated the POST-as-GET concept thatâs in ACME today” – Jacob Hoffman-Andrews&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can see there how IETF iterations can challenge the security of a protocol and leads its development to innovative solutions to tackle the challenges it faces!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last, Jacob adds another information that illustrates the benefits of developing a protocol into the open: it allows the community to evaluate (and sometimes, fix) its security level due to the availability of all materials and often, of the reference implementation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Another very important evolution was the deprecation of the tls-sni-01 challenge method. This was found to be flawed by Frans Rosen, a security researcher. It was replaced with TLS-ALPN-01, developed at IETF with significant input from Google” – Jacob Hoffman-Andrews&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Letâs Encrypt, ACME, and the Public Certificate Authorities Ecosystem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2015, the arrival of Letâs Encrypt in the public certificate authorities ecosystem raised a number of questions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What level of cooperation or hostility? What impact on the viability of existing certificate authorities?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here again, the fact that Letâs Encrypt was based on an open protocol, immediately subject to an IETF standardization initiative, enabled collaboration and adoption by the most innovative certificate authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I spoke about the External Account Binding (EAB) option of the protocol with J.C. Jones. EAB is a way for an ACME client to authenticate to an ACME server using an identifier and a key value which are verifiable by the server in a repository it maintains. With EAB, an ACME server can filter who can uses its service which is useful for commercial certificate authorities for example; it is an alternative model to Let’s Encrypt one where anybody can ask for a certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the example of EAB, J.C. Jones confirms the collaboration with certificate authorities that happens during the IETF standardization process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“EAB was an early addition at the IETF ACME Working Group. Many in the room were worried that without a means to bind to a payment method, ACME would not get adoption. In fact, some of the counterarguments to forming ACME were blunted by EAB, as such a mechanism wasnât in the theoretically-competing, already-existent standard: SCEP. SCEP, it was argued, already handled ‘free’ certificate issuance, for private certificate authorities. Anything else needed a feasible path for usage payment.” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond billing, the addition of EAB enabled also some commercial certificate authorities to integrate their existing domain control validation systems with ACME, allowing some of them to skip the challenge step of the ACME protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The IETF standardization process, based on an open process, created the necessary discussion space for cooperation among entities that did not necessarily share the same objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result, ten years after the introduction of ACME and the completion of its standardization process in 2019, is that ACME has become the primary means by which all public certificate authoritiesâboth free and commercialârely on for their transition to an automated future of issuing short-lived certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Effectively, until early this year, the maximum lifespan of a public TLS server certificate was set to 398 days by the CA/B Forum, the organization that set the rules for public certificate authorities. With the vote of the ballot SC081 at the CA/B Forum in April 2025, it has been decided that the certificate lifespan will decrease gradually starting March 2026 to reach 47 days in March 2029. The automation provided by ACME seems to be one of the main identified levers to help organizations to adapt to this drastic reduction in the lifespan of public TLS server certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Created at Let’s Encrypt, adopted everywhere&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is important to note that although ACME was developed by the team managing Let’s Encrypt, this protocol is now one of the main protocols for automated certificate acquisition adopted by all public certificate authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And outside the public certificate authorities ecosystem, I think it’s fair to say that this protocol is also becoming increasingly popular with technical architects in companies with private certificate authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This has been the case in my company for several years now, where we have deployed an ACME endpoint in front of our internal certificate authority. Among the benefits we have seen, we have been able to rely on the vast ACME clients ecosystem in order to provide an ACME client to each OS or middleware that powers our infrastructure. We can see there how certificate obtention agility powered by ACME helps organizations in their journey to global IT agility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Innovation and the adoption challenge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The ARI episode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We may fear that the development of a protocol supported primarily by a team as small as Let’s Encrypt’s will be fairly limited in terms of evolution and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the history of ACME shows that its evolution continues after its initial standardization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2025, we saw with the ARI (ACME Renewal Information – RFC 9773) extension that the ACME protocol continues to evolve. ARI is a way for a certificate authority to suggest a renewal period to its clients, often earlier than they would have determined themselves. This use case is particularly relevant when the certificate authority needs to mass-revoke certificates that, for example, did not comply with the rules the certificate authority must follow when issuing certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More specifically, J.C. Jones and Aaron Gable point two incidents that had to be handled by the Let’s Encrypt team and that were the start for the ARI initiative:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Explicitly, as remediation of https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1619179 and https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1715672 " J.C. Jones and Aaron Gabble&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Support to encourage adoption&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aaron Gable leads the effort of designing and implementing ARI. But even if a new extension to the protocol has been produced, it can only reach its potential users after ACME clients have implemented it into their code base. As previously said, the team and some community members invest a lot on providing support to the community. In the case of ARI, this support is oriented to the ACME clients developers in order to make these clients ARI aware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Providing an efficient support and effective resources to the client side ACME actors is a huge part of the challenge in order to keep ACME ecosystem healthy and agile.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As illustrates by Sarah Gran, another way to give momentum to a new feature is to lift certain restrictions on access to the certificate authority:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In order to encourage ARI adoption, weâve configured Letâs Encrypt to allow subscribers who renew via ARI to bypass our rate limits.” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Client Side Update Challenge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But despite a good support work and incentive measures, Aaron Gable confirms ARI adoption is just at its start:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“There is still much progress to be made. Part of the appeal of the Automated Certificate Management Environment is that many users can set-and-forget their client and configuration. This means that most clients never receive software updates, and even client projects that have implemented ARI in their latest version still have massive install bases that arenât running that version. Weâve worked closely with many clients developers to implement ARI, and contributed implementations ourselves in several cases, but for widespread adoption the whole ecosystem will need to slowly turn over” – Aaron Gable&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This situation is really shared with a lot of client side softwares that “just work”(c) and it raises some concerns about how to make an ecosystem keeping track with innovation on its client side.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This challenge arises not only in terms of updating the client, but also in terms of updating the configuration. Many ACME clients rely on cron tasks. To have an efficient ARI setup, your task has to run ideally on a daily basis be able to ask the certification authority every day whether the certificate needs to be reissued. This is not the classic cron task setup. So, users have to modify this cron task frequency to reach the ARI goal of certificate reissuance led by certificate authority. Client side ACME setup evolution is a really challenging task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Evolution on server side ACME implementation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CA/B Forum has recently asked public certificate authorities to adopt Multi-Perspective Issuance Corroboration (MPIC) to guard against BGP attacks. We have asked Aaron Gable about the impacts that kind of measure have had on ACME server side implementation in the Let’s Encrypt infrastructure:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Weâve had to make few if any changes to our infrastructure to accommodate recent requirements changes such as MPIC and DNSSEC validation. We innovated MPIC (then called Remote Validation) along with a research team at Princeton, and implemented it in 2020. Our experience already running such a service helped inform the requirements as they were incorporated by the CA/B Forum.” – Aaron Gable&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lesson learnt here is that being at the edge of the innovation let you shape part of the future of your ecosystem and significantly lower the impact on your infrastructure of many regulatory measures that come into effect over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Future&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is really encouraging to see a lot of innovation in the ACME ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what evolutions can we expect to see in the future?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have asked the question to Aaron Gable who gave us two upcoming developments:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“Weâre currently working on standardizing profile selection for ACME, and our deployment of the early draft of this standard has already brought some much-needed flexibility to the WebPKI, enabling us to make changes to our certificate contents with minimal disruption.”&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“Iâm also excited about a potential future change which would introduce a ‘pubkey’ identifier type, along with a set of challenges that allow the client to demonstrate control over the corresponding keypair. This would fix the gap today that presenting a CSR does not actually prove possession of the key in that CSR.” – Araron Gable&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fastly has also recently contributed to ACME in order to improve the &lt;code&gt;dns-01&lt;/code&gt; challenge in a multi-cloud and multi-PKI environment. An IETF draft describing this &lt;code&gt;dns-account-01&lt;/code&gt; challenge is online. This is further proof that the public TLS ecosystem has truly embraced the ACME protocol as its primary automation tool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another recent development based on ACME has also shed new light on the potential of this protocol: since 2022, a draft is under progress at the IETF in order to write an ACME extension. The goal of this extension is to use ACME to obtain a certificate for a device in order to prove its identity. The challenge is based on device attestation and what’s new in this case is the arrival of a third party, the attestation server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is remarkable here is that we are no longer dealing with ACME’s initial use case, namely obtaining TLS server certificates: we can see in this IETF draft the potential of ACME as a challenge-based framework to obtain certificate in very different contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, we can venture to say that ACME’s future looks bright ð&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is heartening to see that, 30 years after the widespread adoption of the Internet, open and standardized protocols continue to revolutionize its use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ACME and its Let’s Encrypt implementation at scale have enabled the widespread adoption of HTTPS, thereby raising the level of security for billions of Internet users and also of private networks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having been able to do it inside a non profit organization, providing the Internet with an open and standardized protocol is a great success for all people believing in FreeSoftware and an Open Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a community, I really think we can thank these organizations, teams, and engineers who continue to uphold the promise of efficiency and Freedom brought about by cooperation around open protocols. They inspire new generations (and older ones I guess ð) demonstrating big things can still be achevied today in the open for the common good at the Internet scale!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would like to extend a special thank you to the members of the Let’s Encrypt team, J.C. Jones, Aaron Gable, Sarah Gran and Jacob Hoffman-Andrews, for the time and effort they dedicated to answering my questions. Without them, this article would not have been possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A big shout out also to Eric Leblond and Philippe Teuwen who carefully proofread some early drafts of the article and Philippe Bonnef and Thibault Meunier for proofreading some of the last drafts. They all gave me so valuable and insightful advices ð&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.brocas.org/2025/12/01/ACME-a-brief-history-of-one-of-the-protocols-which-has-changed-the-Internet-Security/"/><published>2025-12-03T23:28:34+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46142000</id><title>Kea DHCP: Modern, open source DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 server</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:03.432764+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ea1b597bc497298e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Kea 3.0, our first LTS version&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISC is excited to announce the release of Kea 3.0.0! This is a major release, and is the first Long-Term Support (LTS) version of Kea.&lt;/p&gt;Read&lt;p&gt;Modern, open source DHCPv4 &amp;amp; DHCPv6 server&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISC distributes TWO full-featured, open source, standards-based DHCP server distributions: Kea DHCP and ISC DHCP. Kea includes all the most-requested features, is far newer, and is designed for a more modern network environment. ISC announced the End of Life for the older ISC DHCP system in 2022. Users of ISC DHCP may find these resources helpful in migrating their DHCP server deployments to the Kea server.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modular Component Design, Extensible with Hooks Modules. The Kea distribution includes separate daemons for a DHCPv4 server, a DHCPv6 server, and a dynamic DNS (DDNS) module. Many optional features are enabled with dynamically-loaded “Hooks Modules,” which you need run only if you are using them. You can write your own hooks modules (in C++) or try some of the hooks we offer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On-line Re-configuration with REST API. Kea uses a JSON configuration file that can be modified remotely via &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; commands and reloaded without stopping and restarting the server, an operation that could take quite a while with ISC DHCP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Designed to Integrate with Your Existing Systems. Kea allows you to separate the data from the execution environment, enabling new deployment options. Your network data - leases, host reservation definitions, and most configuration data - can be located separately from the DHCP server itself, using a Kea “backend.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kea supports two database backends; MySQL and PostgreSQL. Besides the obvious benefits (you avoid JSON formatting errors, you can quickly and easily mine the data for other purposes) using a database backend enables multiple Kea servers to share the data. Potential benefits:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Web-based graphical dashboard. Kea now has a graphical dashboard for monitoring multiple Kea servers. This system, called Stork, uses agents deployed on the Kea servers to relay information to a centralized management platform, providing the administrator with an easy-to-use quick view of system status and activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modern, higher performance implementation. Kea is multi-threaded, and when configured for efficient operation, it can be performant enough for a large-scale, short-lease duration environment, which is the most demanding scenario.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The core Kea daemons are open source, shared under MPL2.0 licensing. Kea is developed in the open on ISC’s GitLab; we welcome you to open issues and submit patches there. Kea runs on most Linux and Unix platforms, as well as MacOS. If you don’t want to build from our source distribution, we also provide a repository of pre-built packages for most popular operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contact ISC for Support&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your major design decisions are whether to deploy in pairs for High Availability and use the default csv file for host and lease data, or to install a separate database for a Kea data “backend.” Some of these decisions can limit your performance. See our Knowledgebase for advice on designing for optimal performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instructions are available for building and installing Kea from the source packages downloadable below. ISC provides pre-built packages for RHEL, Fedora, Ubuntu, and Debian. If you are using any Kea hook libraries, you will also need to install and configure those.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Kea Administrator Reference Manual (ARM) is the primary reference for Kea configuration. The extensive set of example configuration files in the project repo and our knowledgebase may help you get started. If you are migrating from an existing ISC DHCP deployment, try the Kea Migration Assistant (a special feature of the ISC DHCP distribution). This will enable you to save your current ISC DHCP server configuration as a Kea configuration file. It will still need some manual adjustment, but this tool should translate the bulk of your configuration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most users will benefit from joining the kea-users mailing list. Consider joining our Kea project GitLab to log issues, see what we’re working on, submit patches, and participate in development. Consider deploying Stork for a graphical management dashboard. If your DHCP is critical to your business, we recommend you subscribe for technical support from ISC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stork aggregates data about the health of the system hosting Kea, as well as the status and activity level of Kea itself. Parameters reported include memory, CPU utilization, software versions, and uptime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stork displays configured pools, with # of addresses provisioned and assigned and even tracks pool utilization across shared networks. Graphical elements highlight areas of high utilization to alert the operator to take actionHigh Availability pairs are monitored and their configured role and status are shown, making it easy to see which servers don’t have a backup established, and when a failover event has occurred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add, update and view DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 host reservations, using a graphical interface to select a host identifier, assign a hostname, reserve an IP address, associate a client class, and configure boot file information and DHCP options.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Service Options&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Gold support&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Silver support&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Bronze support&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Basic (no support)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Premium (no longer offered)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Critical issue response&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;30 minutes, 24x7&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1 hour, 24x7&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2 hours, business hours only*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;not included&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;not included&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Standard issue response&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4 business hours*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;8 business hours*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Next business day&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;community support via public mailing list&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;community support via public mailing list&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Early vulnerability notifications&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5 days&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5 days&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5 days&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3 days&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;not included&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Kea 3.0 hook libraries (RBAC and Configuration Backend are the only commercially-licensed ones)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Subscriber&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Subscriber&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Subscriber&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Subscriber&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;N/A&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Kea 2.6 and earlier hook libraries included&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Enterprise, Premium and Subscription&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Enterprise, Premium and Subscription&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Premium and Subscription&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Premium and Subscription&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Premium&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Stork support&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Available&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Available&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Available&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Community support via user mailing list&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Community support via user mailing list&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Purchasing&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Quotation/Purchase order&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Quotation/Purchase order&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Quotation/Purchase order&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Quotation/Purchase order&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;no longer offered&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pricing based on deployment size and service level.&lt;/p&gt;Contact ISC for a quote&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;VERSION&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;STATUS&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;DOCUMENTATION&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;RELEASE DATE&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;EOL DATE&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;DOWNLOAD&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3.0.2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Current Stable - LTS&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Kea ARM ( HTML PDF )&lt;p&gt;Kea Messages ( HTML PDF )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Release Notes ( TXT )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;October 2025&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;June 2028&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2.6.4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Current Stable&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Kea ARM ( HTML PDF )&lt;p&gt;Kea Messages ( HTML PDF )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Release Notes ( TXT )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;July 2025&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;July 2026&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3.1.4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Development&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Kea ARM ( HTML PDF )&lt;p&gt;Kea Messages ( HTML PDF )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Release Notes ( TXT )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;November 2025&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;June 2026&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.isc.org/kea/"/><published>2025-12-03T23:58:04+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46142100</id><title>Average DRAM price in USD over last 18 months</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:03.302462+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://pcpartpicker.com/trends/price/memory/"/><published>2025-12-04T00:08:26+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46142866</id><title>Why WinQuake exists and how it works</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:02.997904+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e73b81353f2276d7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I took a look at the history of Quake binaries, they all made sense to me. &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; was the original release, able to run on DOS and Windows 95. Then came &lt;code&gt;vquake.exe&lt;/code&gt; to support the hardware accelerated chip Vérité 1000. Later, &lt;code&gt;glquake.exe&lt;/code&gt; generalized hardware acceleration to any vendor providing OpenGL drivers. And to revolutionize Internet deathmatch, id Software released QuakeWorld server and client (&lt;code&gt;qwsv.exe&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;qwcl.exe&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, I could not figure out the point of &lt;code&gt;winquake.exe&lt;/code&gt;. Until now. Here is what I understood and a little bit of a dive into how it works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; runs on both DOS and Windows 95 but how well does it perform? A quick benchmark on my Pentium MMX 233MHz, Matrox Mystique PC (320x200 with 101 screen size) and sound on, showed the following numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Configuration&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Framerate&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; started from DOS&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;48 fps&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; started from Windows 95&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;38 fps&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So "framerate" is the beginning of an answer to justify the existence of WinQuake. &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; running from Windows 95 is roughly 25% slower than the same binary started from DOS. And that is to be expected. Windows 95 runs DOS applications in a virtual machine ("DOS BOX"), where memory access, interrupts, and signals are virtualized, which incurs overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another element of the answer comes from Quake Chunnel. &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; can access Windows 95 TCP/IP stack, but only via a convoluted tech from Mpath to bridge a "DOS BOX" to win32 dlls. By having a win32-only application, id Software had guaranteed direct access to &lt;code&gt;winsock.dll&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last but not least, id Software really wanted Quake to work on Windows NT. Despite their best efforts, the people at DJGPP could not make their DPMI client in &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; compatible with the NT Virtual DOS Machine (NTVDM).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Near pointers don't work under NT - which was a huge disappointment to iD and generated some conference calls to Microsoft.&lt;lb/&gt;- Charles Sandmann[1]&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A fun way to start exploring is to first read WQREADME.TXT and then take a look at all the modes available in &lt;code&gt;winquake.exe&lt;/code&gt;. They are configured with the script wq.bat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Options for running WinQuake: wq max: all features on, but doesn't work on all systems wq fast: maximum speed, but doesn't work on all systems wq fastvid: maximum video speed, but safer, probably slower sound wq fastsnd: maximum sound speed, but safer, probably slower video wq safe: very likely to run, but may be slower wq verysafe: almost sure to run, but probably slower, and no sound&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are the numbers I got for each mode, still with the same Pentium MMX 233MHz machine and same configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Configuration&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Framerate&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;wq max&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;42.4 fps&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;wq fast&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;41.8 fps&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;wq fastvid&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;45.0 fps&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;wq fastsnd&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;41.8 fps&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;wq safe&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;45.0 fps&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;wq verysafe&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;40.0 fps*&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Impressive. &lt;code&gt;winquake.exe&lt;/code&gt; managed to bring up the framerate within 6% of &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; running on DOS. Mission accomplished. But how does it works?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each "mode" is configured via command-line flags. This part reveals there are three types of backend for input controls, audio, and video.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;max winquake -dinput fast winquake fastvid winquake -wavonly fastsnd winquake -nodirectdraw -nowindirect safe winquake -wavonly -nodirectdraw -nowindirect verysafe winquake -dibonly -nosound -nojoy&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amusingly, the mode that provides the highest framerate, &lt;code&gt;fastvid&lt;/code&gt; keeps everything default but disables an audio backend!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"fastvid" was also the name of a tool to fix the Pentium Pro abysmal video write speed on chipset that shipped with buggy "Write Posting". The option in &lt;code&gt;qw.bat&lt;/code&gt; has nothing to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WinQuake can send its sound effects (the music comes from CD tracks) using two audio backends (with &lt;code&gt;-nosound&lt;/code&gt; disables sound effects altogether).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two backends are DirectSound (&lt;code&gt;dsound.h&lt;/code&gt; from DirectX) and what id calls wave sound which is in fact &lt;code&gt;winmm.h&lt;/code&gt;, the Windows MultiMedia audio API, dating back to Windows 3.1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If DirectSound is available, WinQuake uses it to provide the lowest latency. However this backend has a higher impact on the CPU and results in 10% lower framerate. With &lt;code&gt;-wavonly&lt;/code&gt;, users can force usage of &lt;code&gt;WinMM&lt;/code&gt; which results in higher latency but higher framerate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To read user inputs, WinQuake uses either DirectInput (&lt;code&gt;dinput.h&lt;/code&gt; from DirectX) or the legacy Windows API &lt;code&gt;winuser.h&lt;/code&gt;.

&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default WinQuake uses &lt;code&gt;winuser.h&lt;/code&gt; but usage of DirectInput can be requested via &lt;code&gt;-dinput&lt;/code&gt; for slightly smoother motion and responsiveness to fast spinning motions. I suspect it was not enabled by default for cases where DirectX was not installed or perhaps fear of driver problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joystick inputs are handled with &lt;code&gt;joystickapi.h&lt;/code&gt;. Likewise, it seems drivers may not have been stable since id provided a way to disable it with &lt;code&gt;-nojoy&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The part that was the most interesting to me was the video backends. WinQuake can operate in five modes using GDI, VGA, VESA, Accelerated VESA, or DirectDraw.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Graphics Device Interface (GDI) (&lt;code&gt;wingdi.h&lt;/code&gt;) is the foundation to render anything on the desktop in Windows 95. Applications usually did not use it directly but instead called &lt;code&gt;winuser.h&lt;/code&gt; (which in turns used low-level &lt;code&gt;wingdi.h&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WinQuake can render to a Device-Independent Bitmaps (DIB) which is a surface to be blitted towards a window though GDI. The surface can be of any dimension so there are no "display mode" to detect here, WinQuake hardcodes its DIB modes to square-pixel resolutions 320x240, 640x480, and 800x600.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because it is using Windows "by the book", DIB mode is the safest mode that should always work. It is also the slowest way to render to the screen because WinQuake first renders to a DIB that is then sent to the GDI and then sent to the video card.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While slower, it is not devoid of hardware acceleration. Many graphic cards wanting to perform well under Windows 95 had hardware acceleration implementation of crucial functions such as &lt;code&gt;bitBlt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, DIB mode is the only one able to render in "windowed" mode. Every other mode takes over and renders in "fullscreen" mode. Note that DIB can also render in pseudo-full screen if WinQuake is started with &lt;code&gt;dibonly&lt;/code&gt; but this is "faked" with a borderless window covering the whole screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For everything not DIB, WinQuake uses SciTech's MegaGraph Graphics Library. It was a rather expensive lib ($499 in 1997, $1,000 in 2025)[2] but well worth its price because it brought order into the chaos that was the world of video systems in 1997 if a game operated outside GDI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WinQuake could find itself having to deal with the following types of video systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;1. VBEAF : VESA Accelerator Function 2. VBE2 : VESA Linear Frame Buffer for direct to VRAM write/read. 3. DirectDraw : Only available if DirectX is installed. 4. StandardVGA : That good ol' VGA video mode.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When it starts, WinQuake registers the drivers it wants MGL to load (see &lt;code&gt;registerAllDispDrivers&lt;/code&gt;). MGL then lists all supported resolutions and pick the highest performance drivers to access each of them (in the order list above).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;void registerAllDispDrivers(void) { /* Even though these driver require WinDirect, we register * them so that they will still be available even if DirectDraw * is present and the user has disabled the high performance * WinDirect modes. */ MGL_registerDriver(MGL_VGA8NAME,VGA8_driver); if (useWinDirect){ MGL_registerDriver(MGL_LINEAR8NAME,LINEAR8_driver); if (!COM_CheckParm ("-novbeaf")) MGL_registerDriver(MGL_ACCEL8NAME,ACCEL8_driver); } if (useDirectDraw) { MGL_registerDriver(MGL_DDRAW8NAME,DDRAW8_driver); } }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The list of modes and which driver was selected by MGL is available via the command &lt;code&gt;vid_describemodes&lt;/code&gt; in Quake console. In the screenshot below, we can see almost the full house of drivers &lt;code&gt;VGA8.DRV&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;DDRAW.DRV&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;LINEAR8.DRV&lt;/code&gt;, and the windowed DIB modes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had never heard of VBE/AF before reading MGL source code. As far as I understand, it never gained much traction and few vendors wrote drivers to support it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many games used MGL: WinQuake, Hexen II, Grand Theft Auto, Maui Mallard in Cold Shadow, Total Mayhem, Balls of Steel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft was very much aware that GDI was fine for applications but not enough for video games. Already in Windows 3.1 they had released a game developer SDK called WinG to give a more direct fullscreen access to the screen. The second version of WinG was renamed DirectX and contained the 2D fullscreen API which they called DirectDraw.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Although safer and more reliable, Microsoft Windows imposed many restrictions on applications. One result of this situation was that games, and other high-performance graphics applications, could no longer access the hardware resources directly in order to maximize performance and expand functionalities. For several years game programmers continued to exercise the craft in DOS, and Windows users had to switch to the DOS mode to run games, simulations, and other graphics programs. The resulting situation implied a major contradiction: a graphical operating system in which graphics applications would execute with marginal performance&lt;lb/&gt;The first effort in this direction was a product named WinG, in reference to Windows for Games. WinG was first made available in 1994 and it required Win32 in Windows 3.1. Its main feature is that WinG enabled the game programmer to rapidly transfer bitmaps from system memory into video memory. This made possible the creation of Windows games that executed with much better performance.&lt;lb/&gt;Microsoft renamed the new version of the Game SDK, calling it DirectX 2. Other versions later released were named DirectX 3, DirectX 5, DirectX 6, and currently, DirectX 7.&lt;lb/&gt;- Feng Yuan, "Windows Graphics Programming Win32 GDI and DirectDraw"&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In terms of performance, DirectDraw was a step up from GDI but it was also not guaranteed to work due to driver bugs or if the user had not installed DirectX. It can be disabled with &lt;code&gt;nodirectdraw&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Readers may have picked up on something written earlier that was blatantly wrong. Direct access to the hardware is forbidden to Win32 applications. So how is MGL able to bypass GDI/DirectDraw and directly hit VBEAF, VBE, and VGA?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is possible thanks to the secret tech from SciTech called WinDirect. How it works is explained in SciTech MGL Reference Guide v4.pdf.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;What is WinDirect?&lt;lb/&gt;A key component of the SciTech MGL, WinDirect is a runtime package for DOS and Windows 95 that provides direct access to the display hardware for both 16 and 32-bit applications. Traditionally Windows applications have had to perform all graphics output using the standard Graphics Device Interface (GDI). Although the GDI is very extensive and powerful, it is also not particularly fast for the sort of graphics that real time applications like interactive video games require.&lt;lb/&gt;WinDirect breaks this barrier by allowing high performance applications to shut down the normal GDI interface, and to take over the entire graphics display hardware just like you would normally do under DOS. Once GDI has been shut down, interactive graphics applications can re-program the display controller and write directly to video memory. A WinDirect application can program any standard VGA graphics mode such as 320x200x256, it can re-program the controller and run standard VGA ModeX style graphics, or it can call the standard VESA BIOS services to run high resolution SuperVGA graphics.&lt;lb/&gt;- MGL v4 Programmer Guide[3]&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MGL v4 programmer guide, is a treasure strove of information. If, like me, you wondered what were these &lt;code&gt;WDIR32.DLL&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;WDIR16.DLL&lt;/code&gt; libraries that came with WinQuake, the doc mentions them (WinDIRect). Likewise, the doc describes &lt;code&gt;PMPRO16.DLL&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;PMPRO32.DLL&lt;/code&gt; as DOS extender independent API for protected mode services. Michael Abrash's Zen Timer is also mentioned in there :)!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WinQuake source code does not include MGL. Only the headers and a pre-compiled 32-bit &lt;code&gt;MGLLT.LIB&lt;/code&gt; (MGL Lite) are provided to allow compilation. SciTech did eventually publish the source in 2000[4] but it is no longer available. What was uploaded on GitHub[5] is v5 which by then had dramatically changed (e.g: WinDirect was gone).&lt;lb/&gt; Luckily a kind soul has mirrored MGL v4. If you want to do your own digging, install mglb405.exe and mgls405.exe. Or just download my installation, src.rar.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overall, &lt;code&gt;winquake.exe&lt;/code&gt; was often able to find a fast rendering path, either through DirectDraw or WinDirect. The fallback to DIB mode was not ideal but still a win compared to &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt;. Add to that the ability to select a sound backend to optimize for framerate or audio latency and the result was a damn good experience that completely justified the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More than 30 years later, you can still run &lt;code&gt;winquake.exe&lt;/code&gt; on Windows 11. Fullscreen does not support widescreen but the windowed mode still works flawlessly. As much as Microsoft has been questionable lately, their commitment to backward compatibility is impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;^&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;[1]&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Why did ID choose DJGPP for Quake?&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;^&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;[2]&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SciTech's MGL price&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;^&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;[3]&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;MGL v4 Programmer Guide&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;^&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;[4]&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SciTech Releases MGL 4.0 OpenGL Source Code&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;^&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;[5]&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SciTech Mult-platform Graphics Library&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://fabiensanglard.net/winquake/index.html"/><published>2025-12-04T01:58:15+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46144113</id><title>Show HN: A Minimal Monthly Task Planner (printable, offline, no signup)</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:02.621704+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f61c1ba9314363"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;PrintCalendar.top&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Minimal Monthly Task Planner&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A calm, printer-friendly canvas to map your month, capture notes, and keep a lightweight log of what matters.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Stay on month&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Jump to today, share month links, pick Mon/Sun as week start.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Notes that travel&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Monthly notes with inline editing, saved locally in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Ready to print&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Clean A4 layout, dark/light themes, and PDF in one click.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://printcalendar.top/"/><published>2025-12-04T05:29:51+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46144275</id><title>Uncloud - Tool for deploying containerised apps across servers without k8s</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:01.645116+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6f4f5cfad58e4b63"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Mix and Match Infrastructure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mix and match cloud and on-premise across regions and providers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Deploy customer-facing apps on reliable cloud VMs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Run resource-hungry background jobs on budget-friendly bare metal servers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Transform that dusty Mac mini into a powerful staging environment&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://uncloud.run/"/><published>2025-12-04T06:02:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46144613</id><title>Saturn (YC S24) Is Hiring Senior AI Engineer</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:01.206383+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9b8e9e540cf160ea"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why Saturn?&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Saturn is revolutionizing financial services with AI, building the operating system for financial advisors. Our mission is to democratize financial advice for one billion people by providing the world's most trusted, intelligent platform for financial planning and compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is a rare chance to build a category-defining company in a high-stakes, regulated environment. We operate with a Dual Mandate: relentless Speed of Execution to deliver reliable, robust products today, and dedicated Speed of Learning to explore the frontier of AI and unlock the next generation of features.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you are driven by the pursuit of greatness, thrive on end-to-end ownership, and want to build the gold standard for AI trust and reliability, we invite you to build with us.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Role Overview&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As a Senior AI Engineer at Saturn, you are the single-threaded owner of critical, customer-facing AI features that form the backbone of the advisory operating system. This is a highly autonomous role requiring robust software engineering fundamentals, deep LLM intuition, and an obsessive focus on product quality in a regulated domain.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You will own the entire feature lifecycle: from defining the Gold Standard with our domain experts (Guardians), architecting the agentic workflow, designing and building the comprehensive evaluation suites, to deploying and operating the solution reliably in production. You are expected to move quickly, making pragmatic, data-backed decisions that drive measurable value.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What You'll Do&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;1. End-to-End Feature Ownership and Architecture:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Ownership: Take complete ownership of a product domain or complex feature, making architectural decisions independently and delivering high-quality results from concept through to long-term maintenance.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Defensive Design: Architect and implement fault-tolerant AI systems, incorporating robust fallbacks (via a model-agnostic gateway), retries, and comprehensive monitoring and tracing, driven by the Will to Care about system reliability.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Explicit Orchestration: Design and deploy complex, multi-step AI agents using explicit orchestration frameworks, ensuring state transitions are visible, testable, and auditable.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;2. Drive Evaluation and Quality Discipline:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Design Evaluation Strategy: Design, implement, and maintain the comprehensive, systematic evaluation framework (Evals Flywheel) specifically for your features to rigorously measure performance, manage regressions, and ensure quality compounds over time.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Domain Partnership: Work directly with our domain experts to translate complex financial and compliance requirements into executable evaluation rubrics and Gold Standard datasets.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Quality Feedback Loop: Instrument features end-to-end to rapidly diagnose probabilistic failures, converting production issues into high-priority regression tests.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;3. Elevate Engineering Standards:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Technical Excellence: Write clean, modular, Python code that raises the bar for the team. Actively participate in code review, using the process to mentor peers and reinforce architectural standards.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What You Have&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;5+ years of professional experience in a highly demanding engineering environment.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Proven track record (3+ years) of building, shipping, and operating scaled, impactful products where Generative AI or LLMs are a core component.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Deep Experience with Agentic Systems: Expertise in RAG pipelines, systematic prompt engineering, agentic workflow orchestration, and defining reliability trade-offs for production systems.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Evaluation Focus: Direct, demonstrable experience designing, writing, and maintaining automated evaluation frameworks (&lt;code&gt;evals&lt;/code&gt;) used to rigorously test and improve probabilistic systems.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;End-to-End Ownership: A history of thriving in ambiguity, taking complete ownership of large features, and driving initiatives forward independently with a strong bias for action.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Engineering Excellence: Mastery of Python and modern backend development practices, including system design, testing, CI/CD, and robust production observability.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Product &amp;amp; User Focus: Strong product sense and the drive to quickly build domain expertise, translating user needs and compliance context into high-value technical solutions (the expression of Will to Care for the customer).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Saturn Values in Practice:&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Earn Trust: Building verifiably correct, explainable systems (Citation-First, Adviser-in-the-Loop).&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Pursue Greatness: Driving our Evaluation-Driven Development flywheel to compound quality daily.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Seek Truth: Relying on data, traces, and customer feedback (Guardians) to inform every decision.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Be Audacious: Taking decisive ownership and building intelligent agents that solve previously unsolvable problems in finance.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Will to Care: Obsessively anticipating customer needs and building systems with extreme attention to detail, ensuring long-term quality, reliability, and the success of our users and peers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/saturn/jobs/R9s9o5f-senior-ai-engineer"/><published>2025-12-04T07:00:51+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46145180</id><title>Elites could shape mass preferences as AI reduces persuasion costs</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:01.031702+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="849e200a55f594ac"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Economics &amp;gt; General Economics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 3 Dec 2025]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:Polarization by Design: How Elites Could Shape Mass Preferences as AI Reduces Persuasion Costs&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:In democracies, major policy decisions typically require some form of majority or consensus, so elites must secure mass support to govern. Historically, elites could shape support only through limited instruments like schooling and mass media; advances in AI-driven persuasion sharply reduce the cost and increase the precision of shaping public opinion, making the distribution of preferences itself an object of deliberate design. We develop a dynamic model in which elites choose how much to reshape the distribution of policy preferences, subject to persuasion costs and a majority rule constraint. With a single elite, any optimal intervention tends to push society toward more polarized opinion profiles - a ``polarization pull'' - and improvements in persuasion technology accelerate this drift. When two opposed elites alternate in power, the same technology also creates incentives to park society in ``semi-lock'' regions where opinions are more cohesive and harder for a rival to overturn, so advances in persuasion can either heighten or dampen polarization depending on the environment. Taken together, cheaper persuasion technologies recast polarization as a strategic instrument of governance rather than a purely emergent social byproduct, with important implications for democratic stability as AI capabilities advance.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt; Current browse context: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;econ.GN&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04047"/><published>2025-12-04T08:38:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46145365</id><title>It’s time to free JavaScript</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:52:00.337539+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="4737c13992a7be78"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dear Oracle,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have long ago abandoned the JavaScript trademark, and it is causing widespread, unwarranted confusion and disruption.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JavaScript is the world’s most popular programming language, powering websites everywhere. Yet, few of the millions who program in it realize that JavaScript is a trademark you, Oracle, control. The disconnect is glaring: JavaScript has become a general-purpose term used by countless individuals and companies, independent of any Oracle product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oracle’s hold on the JavaScript trademark clearly fits the legal definition of trademark abandonment. A previous blog post addressed this issue, requesting that you, Oracle, release the trademark. Unsurprisingly, the request was met with silence. It is therefore time to take active steps in order to bring the JavaScript trademark into the public domain, where it belongs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Trademark abandonment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Title 15 of the United States Code, section 1127, states:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A mark shall be deemed to be “abandoned” if either of the following occurs:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When its use has been discontinued with intent not to resume such use. Intent not to resume may be inferred from circumstances. Nonuse for 3 consecutive years shall be prima facie evidence of abandonment. “Use” of a mark means the bona fide use of such mark made in the ordinary course of trade, and not made merely to reserve a right in a mark.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When any course of conduct of the owner, including acts of omission as well as commission, causes the mark to become the generic name for the goods or services on or in connection with which it is used or otherwise to lose its significance as a mark. Purchaser motivation shall not be a test for determining abandonment under this paragraph.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the case of JavaScript, both criteria apply.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Netscape, Sun, Oracle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The JavaScript trademark is currently held by Oracle America, Inc. (US Serial Number: 75026640, US Registration Number: 2416017). How did this come to be?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1995, Netscape partnered with Sun Microsystems to create interactive websites. Brendan Eich famously spent only 10 days creating the first version of JavaScript, a dynamic programming language with a rough syntactic lineage from Sun’s Java language. As a result of this partnership, Sun held the JavaScript trademark. In 2009, Oracle acquired Sun Microsystems and the JavaScript trademark as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trademark is simply a relic of this acquisition. Neither Sun nor Oracle has ever built a product using the mark. Legal staff, year after year, have renewed the trademark without question. It’s likely that only a few within Oracle even know they possess the JavaScript trademark, and even if they do, they likely don’t understand the frustration it causes within the developer community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Use it or lose it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oracle has abandoned the JavaScript trademark through nonuse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oracle has never seriously offered a product called JavaScript. In the 1990s and early 2000s, Netscape Navigator, which supported JavaScript as a browser feature, was a key player. However, Netscape’s usage and influence faded by 2003, and the browser saw its final release in 2008. JavaScript, meanwhile, evolved into a widely used, independent programming language, embedded in multiple browsers, entirely separate from Oracle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most recent specimen, filed with the USPTO in 2019, references nodejs.org (a project created by Ryan Dahl, the author of this letter) and Oracle’s JavaScript Extension Toolkit (JET). But Node.js is not an Oracle product, and JET is merely a set of JavaScript libraries for Oracle services, particularly Oracle Cloud. There are millions of JavaScript libraries; JET is not special.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Oracle is not even a member of the OpenJS Foundation - the body that the Node.js project lives under now. Nor does Oracle have any involvement whatsoever in the development of Node.js.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oracle also offers GraalVM, a JVM that can execute JavaScript, among other languages. But GraalVM is far from a canonical JavaScript implementation; engines like V8, JavaScriptCore, and SpiderMonkey hold that role. GraalVM’s product page doesn’t even mention “JavaScript”; you must dig into the documentation to find its support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oracle’s use of JavaScript in GraalVM and JET does not reflect genuine use of the trademark. These weak connections do not satisfy the requirement for consistent, real-world use in trade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A generic term&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A mark can also be considered abandoned if it becomes a generic term.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1996, Netscape announced a meeting of the ECMA International standards organization to standardize the JavaScript programming language. Sun (now Oracle), refused to give up the “JavaScript” mark for this use though, so it was decided that the language would be called “ECMAScript” instead. (Microsoft happily offered up “JScript”, but no-one else wanted that.) Brendan Eich, the creator of JavaScript and a co-signatory of this letter, wrote in 2006 that “ECMAScript was always an unwanted trade name that sounds like a skin disease.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ecma International formed TC39, a technical steering committee, which publishes ECMA-262, the specification for JavaScript. This committee includes participants from all major browsers, like Google’s Chrome, Apple’s Safari, and Mozilla’s Firefox, as well as representatives from server-side JavaScript runtimes like Node.js and Deno.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oracle’s ownership of the JavaScript trademark only causes confusion. The term “JavaScript” is used freely by millions of developers, companies, and organizations around the world, with no interference from Oracle. Oracle has done nothing to assert its rights over the JavaScript name, likely because they do not believe their claim to the mark would hold up in court. Unlike typical trademark holders who protect their trademarks by extracting licensing fees or enforcing usage restrictions, Oracle has allowed the JavaScript name to be used by anyone. This inaction further supports the argument that the trademark has lost its significance and has become generic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programmers working with JavaScript have formed innumerable community organizations. These organizations, like the standards bodies, have been forced to painstakingly avoid naming the programming language they are built around—for example, JSConf. Sadly, without risking a legal trademark challenge against Oracle, there can be no “JavaScript Conference” nor a “JavaScript Specification.” The world’s most popular programming language cannot even have a conference in its name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a vast misalignment between the trademark’s ownership and its widespread, generic use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Free the mark&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By law, a trademark is abandoned if it is either not used or becomes a generic term. Both apply to JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s time for the USPTO to end the JavaScript trademark and recognize it as a generic name for the world’s most popular programming language, which has multiple implementations across the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oracle, you likely have no real business interest in the mark. It’s renewed simply because legal staff are obligated to renew all trademarks, regardless of their relevance or use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We urge you to release the mark into the public domain. However, asking nicely has been tried before, and it was met with silence. If you do not act, we will challenge your ownership by filing a petition for cancellation with the USPTO.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;To you, the readers of this letter:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you agree with us, you are encouraged to sign this open letter below. Your support will help raise awareness and add weight to this cause. If you want to sign as an organization (minimum 25 employees), please email companies@javascript.tm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition, we’re seeking pro bono assistance from lawyers with experience in trademark law to help file a Petition for Trademark Cancellation with the USPTO. It’s likely that simply asking nicely will not get a response from Oracle; a legal challenge must be made. Reach out to lawyers@javascript.tm if you can help.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://javascript.tm/letter"/><published>2025-12-04T09:01:55+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46145797</id><title>Programming peaked</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:59.770277+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2f221b5d0fb53ef1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Programming peaked&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by Samir Talwar&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tuesday, 25 November 2025 at 09:00 CET&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I remember my first job vividly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It helps, of course, that I still consider many of the people I worked with friends, and I know some of them even still read this blog. (Hi!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also think it might have been the beginning of the end. At least, as programming is concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Programming in 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s 2025. We write JavaScript with types now. It runs not just in a browser, but on Linux. It has a dependency manager, and in true JavaScript style, there’s a central repository which anyone can push anything to. Nowadays it’s mostly used to inject Bitcoin miners or ransomware onto unsuspecting servers, but you might find a useful utility to pad a string if you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We don’t write the JavaScript, of course. We ask an autocorrect machine to make it up, and complain at it until it generates something plausible enough. Often, it does, and it only installs a malicious package 20% of the time. 30%, tops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortunately, when we do need to make manual changes, our editor has our back. The most popular is “VS Code”, which needs only a few gigabytes of RAM to render the text. It ships a web browser, because everything ships a web browser. It can also perform fancy refactoring techniques such as renaming a variable (in a single file).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order to test our application, we build it regularly. On a modern computer, with approximately 16 cores, each running at 3 GHz, TypeScript only takes a few seconds to compile and run.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once our work is done, we create a “pull request”. This is a way of emulating open-source development inside a single company, which as we know, is the only way to work. Typically, this means that the code is downloaded and built on another computer, and then several hours later, a colleague will come along and ask to change a few words. Once we change these words, the computer builds everything again, and then the next day, the same colleague will allow the code to be merged into the mainline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once it’s merged, we take that JavaScript and package it into a “container”, which is a fancy word for “kitchen sink”. The packaging process takes 20 minutes, because for reasons no one understands, we download the entirety of the Debian package repository every time we do it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also download all the JavaScript dependencies again, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, we take that container, and attempt to push it to a “registry”. Sometimes it works, sometimes a security scanner complains because we have an insecure version of Perl in the container. We don’t need Perl in the container, but it’s there, and no one knows how to get rid of it. So we turn off the scanner.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, we write a lot of YAML to tell something called “k8s” how to run the container. (“K8s” used to stand for something but ever since the wars of 2019, we don’t have enough letters to spell it out, and the true meaning has been lost to time.) Unlike the JavaScript, the YAML is not type-checked, and in fact cannot be, because we use a string templating language to stick bits of YAML inside other YAML. We all agree that this is the best kind of programming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We run our k8s cluster in the “Cloud”. It’s a bunch of services that run on Linux, but we don’t run Linux ourselves, we run it on VMs that we rent by the hour for approximately the same cost as buying a computer outright every month. We do this because no one knows how to plug a computer in any more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We send the YAML to the cluster, which eats it up, digests it, and then does something random. Hopefully, it will run a program. It might also reject it, run a different program, or shut down something else. As there’s no way of testing this except doing it, there’s no way of telling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We therefore have an entirely separate cluster that we use to verify that our sacrifice to the YAML gods is holy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There was some programming in here somewhere, but I don’t really remember where.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fifteen years ago&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turns out, I’m old now. But not so old that I’ve forgotten how things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started my first real, full-time job in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We wrote Java, which is a general-purpose, highly-verbose programming language. It’s mostly type-safe (except &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;, which we did our best to avoid), and achieves this by making you type out everything so many times and verifying that you didn’t make any mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like JavaScript, it’s fast to compile, taking only a few seconds as well. Of course, this was on my single-core, 2 GHz computer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The editor was cool too. We used Eclipse, which was a bit like VS Code. It could also perform refactoring techniques, though it was a bit smarter: it could extract and inline functions, classes, interfaces, etc. It also compiled the code as you typed, so often, you could compile the application and run the tests on every keystroke.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We wrote tests, of course. Usually first, and ran them constantly. We did this using a strange method called “talking to each other”, in which we’d discuss the functionality at hand, and write it down in code so it could be verified. We’d run these tests constantly; it’d usually take around a minute to run all 10,000 unit tests, but you could be a bit more selective if you were in a hurry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Funnily enough, everything ran at about the same speed as it does now. Strange, that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, we pushed code directly to trunk. We were pairing, after all. We’d then start work on the next thing, perhaps after a coffee break. Typically, we’d let a tester know so they could check out the changes and take a look.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, we didn’t have containers, so we made these things called “JARs”, which is a big zip file of the application and all its dependencies, pulled from Maven Central. (Maven Central is a bit like NPM but for Java, and also actually vetted submitters and their domain names before allowing them to publish.) This produces a different kind of dependency hell to containers, and I would not wish it upon anybody, but it did, at least, kind of work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’d run that inside a Java server, such as Apache Tomcat, on a Linux VM, on a computer. Deployment was done through “Puppet”; nowadays you’d use Ansible, but whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The computer was inside a datacentre.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The datacentre was down the road. If the computer broke, we could go and turn it off and on again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here’s the funny thing: it never broke, because the person who built it did it well, because it wasn’t taxed within an inch of its life, and because we were keeping an eye on it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;I miss those days&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think back to those days, and remember writing Java, pairing with my old colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We were good at it, but the tools also had our backs. Eclipse was dependable; it did so much amazing stuff that I haven’t seen since. Maven is a thoughtful approach to dependency management that solved several problems (such as namespacing, and trust) in elegant ways, and no one has even tried to copy them. And I really, really miss deploying to a real computer, which I own, and can touch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It astonishes me every time I realise that builds and deployment have become slower in the last 15 years, not faster. I was able to go from code to shipping in less than a minute back then, and now, it takes hours, or sometimes days to get it merged and deployed. Even pushing an application to k8s is an ordeal. Especially if everything has to go through a staging environment first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t really understand why we’ve stopped hiring testers, but I wish we could get back to it. I like having people around who are good at breaking things. It makes me feel safe when they’re on my side.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, some things are better. I’d much rather use Git than Subversion. I actually quite like containers, when they’re built well (i.e. not with a Dockerfile), and deployed sensibly. And I think the Cloud is useful, up to a point, especially when starting out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this world… I do not like it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Where did it all go wrong?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have been trying to figure out what happened, and I think I can point to the catalyst.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NPM happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, this doesn’t mean it’s NPM’s fault, it just means that it made it possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You see, with NPM, node.js (and therefore JavaScript) became a serious programming language, which is both a blessing and a curse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also saw the rise of React, which is possibly the greatest tragedy to ever befall front-end programming (and I say this as a recovering React fan).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then, because we could create applications in the browser, we got Electron. Now everything’s a browser!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love writing JavaScript, and I’m glad I can run it on the server. But this doesn’t mean I think it’s a good idea to use it for everything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would really like to reset, and go back to using a sensible tool for the job at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just a little.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed this post, you can subscribe to this blog using Atom.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe you have something to say. You can email me or toot at me. I love feedback. I also love gigantic compliments, so please send those too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please feel free to share this on any and all good social networks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This article is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License (CC-BY-4.0).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://functional.computer/blog/programming-peaked"/><published>2025-12-04T10:01:27+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46145834</id><title>Unreal Tournament 2004 is back</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:59.732259+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://old.reddit.com/r/unrealtournament/comments/1pdbe69/breaking_unreal_tournament_2004_is_back/"/><published>2025-12-04T10:06:35+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46146133</id><title>PGlite – Embeddable Postgres</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:59.484347+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e74292d12d3170e0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Lightweight&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A complete WASM build of Postgres that's under 3MB Gzipped.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Embeddable Postgres&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run a full Postgres database locally in WASM with reactivity and live sync.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create and publish a Postgres database using AI Supabase:&lt;/p&gt;built on PGlite by&lt;p&gt;This is a full PGlite Postgres running in your browser. pgvector!&lt;/p&gt;It even includes&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://pglite.dev/"/><published>2025-12-04T10:52:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46146204</id><title>Building optimistic UI in Rails (and learn custom elements)</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:59.249849+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2c37e83ac8e004ec"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom elements are one of those web platform features that sound complicated but turn out to be surprisingly simple. If you have used Hotwire in Rails, you have already used them. Both &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;turbo-frame&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;turbo-stream&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; are custom elements. They are just HTML tags with JavaScript behavior attached.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This article walks through what custom elements are, how they compare to Stimulus controllers and how to build them yourself! Starting with a simple counter and ending with an optimistic form that updates instantly without waiting for the server. 🤯&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code is available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What are custom elements?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom elements let you define your own HTML tags with custom behavior. They fall under the Web Components umbrella, alongside Shadow DOM (encapsulated styling and markup) and templates (reusable HTML fragments), though each can be used independently. To use custom elements, just define a class, register it with the browser, and use your new tag anywhere (Shadow DOM or templates not required).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the simplest possible custom element:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;class HelloWorld extends HTMLElement {
  connectedCallback() {
    this.textContent = "Hello from a custom element 👋"
  }
}

customElements.define("hello-world", HelloWorld)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now you can use &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;hello-world&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/hello-world&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in your HTML and it will display the message. The &lt;code&gt;connectedCallback&lt;/code&gt; runs when the element is added to the page. This is similar to Stimulus’s &lt;code&gt;connect()&lt;/code&gt; method. There is also, just like with Stimulus, a &lt;code&gt;disconnectedCallback&lt;/code&gt;. This can be used similar to Stimulus’: removing event listeners and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom element names must contain a hyphen. This prevents conflicts with future HTML elements. So &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;hello-world&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; works, but &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;helloworld&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; does not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Attributes and properties&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom elements can read attributes just like regular HTML elements:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;class GreetUser extends HTMLElement {
  connectedCallback() {
    const name = this.getAttribute("name") || "stranger"

    this.textContent = `Hello, ${name}!`
  }
}

customElements.define("greet-user", GreetUser)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use it like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;greet-user name="Cam"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/greet-user&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To react to attribute changes, use &lt;code&gt;attributeChangedCallback&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;class GreetUser extends HTMLElement {
  static observedAttributes = ["name"]

  connectedCallback() {
    this.#render()
  }

  attributeChangedCallback(name, oldValue, newValue) {
    this.#render()
  }

  // private

  #render() {
    const name = this.getAttribute("name") || "stranger"

    this.textContent = `Hello, ${name}!`
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;observedAttributes&lt;/code&gt; array tells the browser which attributes to watch. Without it, &lt;code&gt;attributeChangedCallback&lt;/code&gt; never fires.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The &lt;code&gt;is&lt;/code&gt; attribute&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can extend built-in HTML elements using the &lt;code&gt;is&lt;/code&gt; attribute. For example, extending a button:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;class FancyButton extends HTMLButtonElement {
  connectedCallback() {
    this.classList.add("fancy")
  }
}

customElements.define("fancy-button", FancyButton, { extends: "button" })
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then use it like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button is="fancy-button"&amp;gt;Click me&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This keeps all the built-in button behavior while adding your custom features (simply adding the &lt;code&gt;fancy&lt;/code&gt; class in above example). However, Safari does not support this feature. So I stick to autonomous custom elements (the hyphenated tags) for better compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Custom elements vs Stimulus&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have used Stimulus, custom elements will feel familiar. Here is how they compare:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Feature&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Stimulus&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Custom Element&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Lifecycle&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;connect()&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;disconnect()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;connectedCallback()&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;disconnectedCallback()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Finding elements&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;targets&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;querySelector()&lt;/code&gt; / direct children&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;State&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;values&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;attributes + properties&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Events&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;action&lt;/code&gt; attributes&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;addEventListener()&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Framework&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Requires Stimulus&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Browser-native&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stimulus is great for connecting behavior to existing HTML. Custom elements are better when you want a reusable component that works anywhere. They are also simpler when you do not need Stimulus’s conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The main difference is how you find elements. Stimulus uses targets:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div data-controller="counter"&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;span data-counter-target="count"&amp;gt;0&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;

  &amp;lt;button data-action="click-&amp;gt;counter#increment"&amp;gt;+&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom elements use standard DOM/query methods (see example below):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;click-counter&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;span class="count"&amp;gt;0&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;

  &amp;lt;button&amp;gt;+&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/click-counter&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom elements feel more like writing vanilla JavaScript. Stimulus is more convention-based (which is often confusing to many).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the end it is all a regular JavaScript class. I’ve explored these extensively in the book JavaScript for Rails Developers. 💡&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building a simple counter&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time to build something. Start with a counter that increments when clicked:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// app/javascript/components/click_counter.js
class ClickCounter extends HTMLElement {
  connectedCallback() {
    this.count = 0

    this.addEventListener("click", () =&amp;gt; this.#increment())
  }

  #increment() {
    this.count++

    this.querySelector("span").textContent = this.count
  }
}

customElements.define("click-counter", ClickCounter)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Import it in your application JavaScript:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// app/javascript/application.js
import "@hotwired/turbo-rails"
import "controllers"

import "components/click_counter"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Configure importmap to find the new directory:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# config/importmap.rb
pin_all_from "app/javascript/controllers", under: "controllers"

pin_all_from "app/javascript/components", under: "components"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now use it in your views:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;click-counter&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;button&amp;gt;Clicked &amp;lt;span&amp;gt;0&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt; times&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/click-counter&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click the button and watch the counter increment. Simple! 😊&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building an optimistic form&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now for something a bit more useful. Build a form that updates instantly without waiting for the server. If the save fails, show an error. If it succeeds, keep the optimistic UI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See how the message gets appended immediately and then (notice the blue Turbo progress bar) gets replaced with the server rendered version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The HTML looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;optimistic-form&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;form action="&amp;lt;%= messages_path %&amp;gt;" method="post"&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;%= hidden_field_tag :authenticity_token, form_authenticity_token %&amp;gt;

    &amp;lt;%= text_area_tag "message[content]", "", placeholder: "Write a message…", required: true %&amp;gt;

    &amp;lt;%= submit_tag "Send" %&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/form&amp;gt;

  &amp;lt;template response&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;%= render Message.new(content: "", created_at: Time.current) %&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/template&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/optimistic-form&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;template response&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag (indeed also part of the Web Components standard) holds the display HTML for new messages. When the form submits, the custom element renders this template with the form values and appends it to the list. The form still submits normally to Rails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start with the basic structure:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// app/javascript/components/optimistic_form.js
class OptimisticForm extends HTMLElement {
  connectedCallback() {
    this.form = this.querySelector("form")
    this.template = this.querySelector("template[response]")
    this.target = document.querySelector("#messages")

    this.form.addEventListener("submit", () =&amp;gt; this.#submit())
  }

  #submit() {
    if (!this.form.checkValidity()) return

    const formData = new FormData(this.form)
    const optimisticElement = this.#render(formData)

    this.target.append(optimisticElement)
  }
}

customElements.define("optimistic-form", OptimisticForm)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;submit&lt;/code&gt; method checks form validity first using the browser’s built-in validation. If the form is invalid, let the browser show its validation messages. Otherwise render the optimistic UI and let the form submit normally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Getting optimistic&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Extract the form data and populate the template:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#render(formData) {
  const element = this.template.content.cloneNode(true).firstElementChild

  element.id = "optimistic-message"

  for (const [name, value] of formData.entries()) {
    const field = element.querySelector(`[data-field="${name}"]`)

    if (field) field.textContent = value
  }

  return element
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;cloneNode(true)&lt;/code&gt; creates a copy of the template content. Loop through the form data and update any element with a matching &lt;code&gt;data-field&lt;/code&gt; attribute. This is why the partial has a &lt;code&gt;data-field="message[content]"&lt;/code&gt; on the message display.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The optimistic element appears in the list immediately, then the form submits to Rails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Turbo Stream does not append the message, but replaces the “optimistic message” with the real one from the database:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;%# app/views/messages/create.turbo_stream.erb %&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;%= turbo_stream.replace "optimistic-message", @message %&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since both the optimistic template and the message partial render the same HTML, the replacement is seamless. The user sees the message appear instantly, then it gets replaced with the real version (with the correct ID, timestamp, etc.) a moment later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the full implementation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// app/javascript/components/optimistic_form.js
class OptimisticForm extends HTMLElement {
  connectedCallback() {
    this.form = this.querySelector("form")
    this.template = this.querySelector("template[response]")
    this.target = document.querySelector("#messages")

    this.form.addEventListener("submit", () =&amp;gt; this.#submit())
    this.form.addEventListener("turbo:submit-end", () =&amp;gt; this.#reset())
  }

  // private

  #submit() {
    if (!this.form.checkValidity()) return

    const formData = new FormData(this.form)
    const optimisticElement = this.#render(formData)

    this.target.append(optimisticElement)
  }

  #render(formData) {
    const element = this.template.content.cloneNode(true).firstElementChild

    element.id = "optimistic-message"

    for (const [name, value] of formData.entries()) {
      const field = element.querySelector(`[data-field="${name}"]`)

      if (field) field.textContent = value
    }

    return element
  }

  #reset() {
    this.form.reset()
  }
}

customElements.define("optimistic-form", OptimisticForm)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do not forget to import it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// app/javascript/application.js
import "components/optimistic_form"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now when you submit the form, the message appears instantly in the list. The form submits to Rails, which responds with a Turbo Stream (I added &lt;code&gt;sleep&lt;/code&gt; to mimic a slow response) that replaces the optimistic message with the real one. If the save fails, Rails can show an error message normally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cool, right? I’ve used this technique before with a client successfully. Many months later and it holds up nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pattern can work great for any form where you want instant feedback. Like chat messages, comments or todos. The new item appears immediately. No loading spinners, no waiting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key is that the partial lives right within the &lt;code&gt;template&lt;/code&gt; element. You are not duplicating it in JavaScript. Change the partial and the optimistic UI updates automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom elements make this pattern reusable. Drop &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;optimistic-form&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; anywhere in your app. It works with any form and any partial (with client’s project mentioned above I stubbed the partial with more advanved “stand-in” model instance).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet another tool in your Rails toolkit. Did this inspire you to use custom elements more too? Let me know below! ❤️&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://railsdesigner.com/custom-elements/"/><published>2025-12-04T11:03:16+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46146406</id><title>30 years ago today "Netscape and Sun announce JavaScript"</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:58.924274+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a919d91b0aa1aa76"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MOUNTAIN VIEW, Calif. (December 4, 1995) -- Netscape Communications Corporation (NASDAQ: NSCP) and Sun Microsystems, Inc. (NASDAQ:SUNW), today announced JavaScript, an open, cross-platform object scripting language for the creation and customization of applications on enterprise networks and the Internet. The JavaScript language complements Java, Sun's industry-leading object-oriented, cross-platform programming language. The initial version of JavaScript is available now as part of the beta version of Netscape Navigator 2.0, which is currently available for downloading from Netscape's web site.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition, 28 industry-leading companies, including America Online, Inc., Apple Computer, Inc., Architext Software, Attachmate Corporation, AT&amp;amp;T;, Borland International, Brio Technology, Inc., Computer Associates, Inc., Digital Equipment Corporation, Hewlett-Packard Company, Iconovex Corporation, Illustra Information Technologies, Inc., Informix Software, Inc., Intuit, Inc., Macromedia, Metrowerks, Inc., Novell, Inc., Oracle Corporation, Paper Software, Inc., Precept Software, Inc., RAD Technologies, Inc., The Santa Cruz Operation, Inc., Silicon Graphics, Inc., Spider Technologies, Sybase, Inc., Toshiba Corporation, Verity, Inc., and Vermeer Technologies, Inc., have endorsed JavaScript as an open standard object scripting language and intend to provide it in future products. The draft specification of JavaScript, as well as the final draft specification of Java, is planned for publishing and submission to appropriate standards bodies for industry review and comment this month.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JavaScript is an easy-to-use object scripting language designed for creating live online applications that link together objects and resources on both clients and servers. While Java is used by programmers to create new objects and applets, JavaScript is designed for use by HTML page authors and enterprise application developers to dynamically script the behavior of objects running on either the client or the server. JavaScript is analogous to Visual Basic in that it can be used by people with little or no programming experience to quickly construct complex applications. JavaScript's design represents the next generation of software designed specifically for the Internet and is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With JavaScript, an HTML page might contain an intelligent form that performs loan payment or currency exchange calculations right on the client in response to user input. A multimedia weather forecast applet written in Java can be scripted by JavaScript to display appropriate images and sounds based on the current weather readings in a region. A server-side JavaScript script might pull data out of a relational database and format it in HTML on the fly. A page might contain JavaScript scripts that run on both the client and the server. On the server, the scripts might dynamically compose and format HTML content based on user preferences stored in a relational database, and on the client, the scripts would glue together an assortment of Java applets and HTML form elements into a live interactive user interface for specifying a net-wide search for information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Java programs and JavaScript scripts are designed to run on both clients and servers, with JavaScript scripts used to modify the properties and behavior of Java objects, so the range of live online applications that dynamically present information to and interact with users over enterprise networks or the Internet is virtually unlimited. Netscape will support Java and JavaScript in client and server products as well as programming tools and applications to make this vision a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Programmers have been overwhelmingly enthusiastic about Java because it was designed from the ground up for the Internet. JavaScript is a natural fit, since it's also designed for the Internet and Unicode-based worldwide use," said Bill Joy, co-founder and vice president of research at Sun. "JavaScript will be the most effective method to connect HTML-based content to Java applets."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Netscape's authoring and application development tools -- Netscape Navigator Gold 2.0, Netscape LiveWire and Netscape LiveWire Pro -- are designed for rapid development and deployment of JavaScript applications. Netscape Navigator Gold 2.0 enables developers to create and edit JavaScript scripts, while Netscape LiveWire enables JavaScript programs to be installed, run and managed on Netscape servers, both within the enterprise and across the Internet. Netscape LiveWire Pro adds support for JavaScript connectivity to high-performance relational databases from Illustra, Informix, Microsoft, Oracle and Sybase. Java and JavaScript support are being built into all Netscape products to provide a unified, front-to-back, client/server/tool environment for building and deploying live online applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Java is available to developers free of charge. The Java Compiler and Java Developer's Kit as well as the HotJava browser and related documentation are available from Sun's web site at http://java.sun.com. In addition, the Java source code can be licensed for a fee. Details on licensing are also available via the java.sun.com web page. To date, Sun has licensed Java to a number of leading technology companies, including Borland, Macromedia, Mitsubishi, Netscape, Oracle, Silicon Graphics, Spyglass, and Toshiba. Sun's Workshop for Java toolkit is scheduled for release in Spring 1996. Sun's NEO product family, the first complete development, operating and management environment for object-oriented networked applications, will also use Java-enabled browsers as front-ends to the NEO environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Netscape and Sun plan to propose JavaScript to the W3 Consortium (W3C) and the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) as an open Internet scripting language standard. JavaScript will be an open, freely licensed proposed standard available to the entire Internet community. Existing Sun Java licensees will receive a license to JavaScript. In addition, Sun and Netscape intend to make a source code reference implementation of JavaScript available for royalty-free licensing, further encouraging its adoption as a standard in a wide variety of products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Netscape Communications Corporation is a premier provider of open software for linking people and information over enterprise networks and the Internet. The company offers a full line of Netscape Navigator clients, Netscape servers, development tools and Netscape Internet Applications to create a complete platform for next-generation, live online applications. Traded on Nasdaq under the symbol "NSCP", Netscape Communications Corporation is based in Mountain View, California.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With annual revenues of $6 billion, Sun Microsystems, Inc. provides solutions that enable customers to build and maintain open network computing environments. Widely recognized as a proponent of open standards, the company is involved in the design, manufacture and sale of products, technologies and services for commercial and technical computing. Sun's SPARC(TM) workstations, multiprocessing servers, SPARC microprocessors, Solaris operating software and ISO-certified service organization each rank No. 1 in the UNIX(R) industry. Founded in 1982, Sun is headquartered in Mountain View, Calif., and employs more than 14,000 people worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional information on Netscape Communications Corporation is available on the Internet at , by sending email to info@netscape.com or by calling 415-528-2555. Additional information on Sun Microsystems is available on the Internet at http://www.sun.com or, for Java information, http://java.sun.com Netscape Communications, the Netscape Communications logo, Netscape, and Netscape Navigator are trademarks of Netscape Communications Corporation. JavaScript and Java are trademarks of Sun Microsystems, Inc. All other product names are trademarks of their respective companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WHAT COMPANIES SAY ABOUT JAVASCRIPT&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Company Contacts:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; America Online, Inc. Pam Mcgraw: (703) 556-3746&lt;lb/&gt; Apple Computer, Inc. Nancy Morrison: (408) 862-6200&lt;lb/&gt; Architext Software Mike Brogan/Roederer-Johnson: (415) 802-1850&lt;lb/&gt; AT&amp;amp;T; Mary Whelan: (908) 658-6000&lt;lb/&gt; Borland International Bill Jordan: (408) 431-4721&lt;lb/&gt; Brio Technology, Inc. Yorgen Edholm: yhe@brio.com&lt;lb/&gt; Computer Associates, Inc. Yogesh Gupta: (516) 342-4045&lt;lb/&gt; Digital Equipment Corporation Ethel Kaiden: (508) 486-2814&lt;lb/&gt; Hewlett-Packard Company Bill Hodges: (408) 447-7041&lt;lb/&gt; Iconovex Corporation Robert Griggs: (800) 943-0292&lt;lb/&gt; Illustra Information Technologies, Inc. Sandra Bateman: (510) 873-62 09&lt;lb/&gt; Informix Software, Inc. Cecilia Denny: (415) 926-6420&lt;lb/&gt; Intuit, Inc. Sheryl Ross: (415) 329-3569&lt;lb/&gt; Macromedia Miles Walsh: (415) 252-2000&lt;lb/&gt; Metrowerks, Inc. Greg Galanos: gpg@austin.metrowerks.com&lt;lb/&gt; Novell, Inc. Christine Hughes: (408) 577-7453&lt;lb/&gt; Oracle Corporation Mark Benioff: (415) 506-7000&lt;lb/&gt; Paper Software, Inc. Mike Mccue: (914) 679-2440&lt;lb/&gt; Precept Software, Inc. Judy Estrin: (408) 446-7600&lt;lb/&gt; RAD Technologies, Inc. Jeff Morgan: jmorgan@rad.com&lt;lb/&gt; The Santa Cruz Operation, Inc. Marty Picco: (408) 425-7222&lt;lb/&gt; Silicon Graphics, Inc. Virginia Henderson: (415) 933-1306&lt;lb/&gt; Spider Technologies Diana Jovin: (415) 969-6128&lt;lb/&gt; Sybase, Inc. Robert Manetta: (510) 922-5742&lt;lb/&gt; Verity, Inc. Marguerite Padovani: (415) 960-7724&lt;lb/&gt; Vermeer Technologies, Inc. Ed Cuoco: (617) 576-1700x130&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Netscape Communications Corporation is a premier provider of open software for linking people and information over enterprise networks and the Internet. The company offers a full line of Netscape Navigator clients, Netscape servers, development tools and Netscape Internet Applications to create a complete platform for next-generation, live online applications. Traded on Nasdaq under the symbol "NSCP", Netscape Communications Corporation is based in Mountain View, California. &lt;lb/&gt; Netscape Communications, the Netscape Communications logo, Netscape, Netscape Commerce Server, Netscape Communications Server, Netscape Proxy Server and Netscape News Server are trademarks of Netscape Communications Corporation. NCSA Mosaic is a trademark of the University of Illinois. All other product names are trademarks of their respective companies. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Help | Site Map | How to Get Netscape Products | Advertise With Us | Add Site | Custom Browser Program&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Autos | Business | Computing &amp;amp; Internet | Entertainment | Family | Games | Health | Lifestyles | Local | Netscape | Netscape Open Directory | News | Personal Finance | Real Estate | Research &amp;amp; Learn | Shopping | Small Business | Sports | Travel&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt; © 1999 Netscape, All Rights Reserved. Legal &amp;amp; Privacy Notices&lt;p&gt;This site powered by Netscape SuiteSpot servers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://web.archive.org/web/20070916144913/http://wp.netscape.com/newsref/pr/newsrelease67.html"/><published>2025-12-04T11:32:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46146451</id><title>I ignore the spotlight as a staff engineer</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:58.738120+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f7d094139d346c2f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why I Ignore The Spotlight as a Staff Engineer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been reading Sean Goedecke’s essays on being a Staff+ engineer. His work (particularly Software engineering under the spotlight and It’s Not Your Codebase) is razor-sharp and feels painfully familiar to anyone in Big Tech.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On paper, I fit the mold he describes: I’m a Senior Staff engineer at Google. Yet, reading his work left me with a lingering sense of unease. At first, I dismissed this as cynicism. After reflecting, however, I realized the problem wasn’t Sean’s writing but my reading.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sean isn’t being bleak; he is accurately describing how to deal with a world where engineers are fungible assets and priorities shift quarterly. But my job looks nothing like that and I know deep down that if I tried to operate in that environment or in the way he described I’d burn out within months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead I’ve followed an alternate path, one that optimizes for systems over spotlights, and stewardship over fungibility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;We Live in Different Worlds&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The foundational reason for our diverging paths is that Sean and I operate in entirely different worlds with different laws governing them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From Sean’s resume, my understanding is that he has primarily worked in product teams 1 building for external customers. Business goals pivot quarterly, and success is measured by revenue or MAU. Optimizing for the “Spotlight” makes complete sense in this environment. Product development at big tech scale is a crowded room: VPs, PMs and UX designers all have strong opinions. To succeed, you have to be agile and ensure you are working specifically on what executives are currently looking at.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I’ve spent my entire career much more behind the scenes: in developer tools and infra teams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My team’s customers are thousands of engineers in Android, Chrome, and throughout Google 2. End users of Google products don’t even know we exist; our focus is on making sure developers have the tools to collect product and performance metrics and debug issues using detailed traces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this environment, our relationship with leadership is very different. We’re never the “hot project everyone wants,” so execs are not fighting to work with us. In fact, my team has historically struggled to hire PMs. The PM career ladder at Google incentivizes splashy external launches so we cannot provide good “promotion material” for them. Also, our feedback comes directly from engineers. Adding a PM in the middle causes a loss in translation, slowing down a tight, high-bandwidth feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of this together means our team operates “bottom-up”: instead of execs telling us “you should do X”, we figure out what we think will have the most impact to our customers and work on building those features and tools. Execs ensure that we’re actually solving these problems by considering our impact on more product facing teams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Compounding Returns of Stewardship&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the product environments Sean describes, where goals pivot quarterly and features are often experimental, speed is the ultimate currency. You need to ship, iterate, and often move on before the market shifts. But in Infrastructure and Developer Experience, context is the currency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Treating engineers as fungible assets destroys context. You might gain fresh eyes, but you lose the implicit knowledge of how systems actually break. Stewardship, staying with a system long-term, unlocks compounding returns that are impossible to achieve on a short rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first is efficiency via pattern matching. When you stay in one domain for years, new requests are rarely truly “new.” I am not just debugging code; I am debugging the intersection of my tools and hundreds of diverse engineering teams. When a new team comes to me with a “unique” problem, I can often reach back in time: “We tried this approach in 2021 with the Camera team; here is exactly why it failed, and here is the architecture that actually works”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the more powerful return is systemic innovation. If you rotate teams every year, you are limited to solving acute bugs that are visible right now. Some problems, however, only reveal their shape over long horizons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take Bigtrace, a project I recently led; it was a solution that emerged solely because I stuck around long enough to see the shape of the problem:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Start of 2023 (Observation): I began noticing a pattern. Teams across Google were collecting terabytes or even petabytes of performance traces, but they were struggling to process them. Engineers were writing brittle, custom pipelines to parse data, often complaining about how slow and painful it was to iterate on their analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Most of 2023 (Research): I didn’t jump to build a production system. Instead, I spent the best part of a year prototyping quietly in the background while working on other projects. I gathered feedback from these same engineers who had complained and because I had established long-term relationships, they gave me honest and introspective feedback. I learned what sort of UX, latency and throughput requirements they had and figured out how I could meet them.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;End of 2023 to Start of 2024 (Execution): We built and launched Bigtrace, a distributed big data query engine for traces. Today, it processes over 2 billion traces a month and is a critical part of the daily workflow for 100+ engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I had followed the advice to “optimize for fungibility” (i.e. if I had switched teams in 2023 to chase a new project) Bigtrace would not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, I would have left during the research phase and my successor would have seen the same “noise” of engineers complaining. But without the historical context to recognize a missing puzzle piece, I think they would have struggled to build something like Bigtrace.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Power of “No”&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the most seductive arguments for chasing the “Spotlight” is that it guarantees resources and executive attention. But that attention is a double-edged sword.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;High-visibility projects are often volatile. They come with shifting executive whims, political maneuvering, and often end up in situations where long-term quality is sacrificed for short-term survival. For some engineers, navigating this chaos is a thrill. For those of us who care about system stability, it feels like a trap.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The advantage of stewardship is that it generates a different kind of capital: trust. When you have spent years delivering reliable tools, you earn the political capital to say “No” to the spotlight when it threatens the product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently, the spotlight has been on AI. Every team is under pressure to incorporate it. We have been asked repeatedly: “Why don’t you integrate LLMs into Perfetto?” If I were optimizing for visibility, the answer would be obvious: build an LLM wrapper, demo it to leadership, and claim we are “AI-first.” It would be an easy win for my career.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But as a steward of the system, I know that one of Perfetto’s core values is precision. When a kernel developer is debugging a race condition, they need exact timestamps, not a hallucination. Users trust that when we tell them “X is the problem” that it actually is the problem and they’re not going to go chasing their tail for the next week, debugging an issue which doesn’t exist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it’s important not to take this too far: skepticism shouldn’t become obstructionism. With AI, it’s not “no forever” but “not until it can be done right” 3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A spotlight-seeking engineer might view this approach as a missed opportunity; I view it as protecting what makes our product great: user trust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Alternate Currency of Impact&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most common fear engineers have about leaving the “Spotlight” is career stagnation. The logic goes: If I’m not launching flashy features at Google I/O, and my work isn’t on my VP’s top 5 list, how will I ever get promoted to Staff+?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is true that you lose the currency of “Executive Visibility.” But in infrastructure, you gain two alternate currencies that are just as valuable, and potentially more stable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadow Hierarchy&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a product organization, you often need to impress your manager’s manager. In an infrastructure organization, you need to impress your customers’ managers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I call this the Shadow Hierarchy. You don’t need your VP to understand the intricacies of your code. You need the Staff+ Engineers in other critical organizations to need your tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a Senior Staff Engineer in Pixel tells their VP, “We literally cannot debug the next Pixel phone without Perfetto”, that statement carries immense weight. It travels up their reporting chain, crosses over at the Director/VP level, and comes back down to your manager.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This kind of advocacy is powerful because it is technical, not political. It is hard to fake. When you are a steward of a critical system, your promotion packet is filled with testimonials from the most respected engineers in the company saying, “This person’s work enabled our success”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Utility Ledger&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While product teams might be poring over daily active users or revenue, we rely on metrics tracking engineering health:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Utility: Every bug fixed using our tools is an engineer finding us useful. It is the purest measure of utility.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Criticality: If the Pixel team uses Perfetto to debug a launch-blocking stutter, or Chrome uses it to fix a memory leak, our impact is implicitly tied to their success.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ubiquity: Capturing a significant percentage of the engineering population proves you’ve created a technical “lingua franca”. This becomes especially obvious when you see disconnected parts of the company collaborating with each other, using shared Perfetto traces as a “reference everyone understands”.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Scale: Ingesting petabytes of data or processing billions of traces proves architectural resilience better than any design doc.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you combine Criticality (VIP teams need this) with Utility (bugs are being fixed), you create a promotion case that is immune to executive reorganizations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Archetypes and Agency&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Staff Archetypes&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am far from the first to notice the idea of “there are multiple ways to be a staff software engineer”. In his book Staff Engineer, Will Larson categorizes Staff-plus engineers into four distinct archetypes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sean describes the Solver or the Right Hand: engineers who act as agents of executive will, dropping into fires and moving on once the problem is stabilized. I am describing the Architect or the Tech Lead: roles defined by long-term ownership of a specific domain and deep technical context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The “Luck” Rebuttal&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can hear the criticism already: “You just got lucky finding your team. Most of us don’t have that luxury.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two caveats to all my advice in this post. First, the strategy I have employed so far requires a company profitable enough to sustain long-term infrastructure. This path generally does not exist in startups or early growth companies; it is optimized for Big Tech.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, luck does play a role in landing on a good team. It is very hard to accurately evaluate team and company culture from the outside. But while finding the team might have involved luck, staying there for almost a decade was a choice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And, at least in my experience, my team is not particularly special: I can name five other teams in Android alone 4. Sure, they might have a director change here or a VP change there, but the core mission and the engineering team remained stable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reason these teams seem rare is not that they don’t exist, but that they are often ignored. Because they don’t offer the rapid, visible “wins” of a product launch nor are they working on the “shiny cool features”, they attract less competition. If you are motivated by “shipping to billions of users” or seeing your friends and family use something you built, you won’t find that satisfaction here. That is the price of admission.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if you want to build long-term systems and are willing to trade external validation for deep technical ownership, you just need to look behind the curtain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The tech industry loves to tell you to move fast. But there is another path. It is a path where leverage comes from depth, patience, and the quiet satisfaction of building the foundation that others stand on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t have to chase the spotlight to have a meaningful, high-impact career at a big company. Sometimes, the most ambitious thing you can do is stay put, dig in, and build something that lasts. To sit with a problem space for years until you understand it well enough to build a Bigtrace.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;By product team I don’t mean “frontend team”: even as a backend engineer, you are still working on some part of what is being served directly to end users. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This is not exhaustive, Perfetto is open source and we do also care about external developers but that’s not why we get paid. From the company perspective, time we spent on open source bugs is “wasted” time but we do it because we believe in the mission of open source. I talked about this more in a recent post, On Perfetto, Open Source, and Company Priorities. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;For what it’s worth, LLMs might not even be the best solution to “let’s put AI into Perfetto”: in my opinion there is lots of value with “old school” machine learning techniques like neural networks. A lot of trace analysis is just pattern matching. This is something I’m hoping to explore more in the coming year! ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Android Kernel, Android System Health, Android Runtime, Android Camera HAL, Android Bionic ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lalitm.com/software-engineering-outside-the-spotlight/"/><published>2025-12-04T11:36:36+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46147341</id><title>Functional Quadtrees</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:57.802983+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="4cfaac21040e533b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1.12.2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Functional Quadtrees&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Quadtree is a tree data structure, which is useful for giving more focus/detail to certain regions of your data, while saving resources elsewhere. I could only find a couple tutorials/guides and both were imperative, so I figured it'd be fun to do a functional version in Clojure which runs in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A demo&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this blogpost I'll show you how to build both a functional Quadtree and the visualization you see below. Imagine the canvas to be a top-view of map and your mouse-position to be the spot you're occupying on the map. Near you, you want crisp details, small cells of high resolution. The further away we get from you/the camera (your mouse-position), the less we care about details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be aware that on mobile, you have to click at the spot you want to simulate the cameras position. I recommend you view this on a desktop system with a mouse, where the simulation reacts to the mouse position in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The recursive approach&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's hard to find any tutorials on how to build a general purpose Quadtree, but the 2 I did find both took the imperative approach, ie. editing directly on each node. Nothing wrong with that approach, it can be blazingly fast but it does leave you with the housekeeping, ie. downscaling nodes that are no longer close to the camera. I'd much prefer a declarative definition that rebuilds the entire tree in sub-milliseconds, so let's make that happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this implementation, I want to show a very general functional approach and goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Read a camera (player,mouse,focus-point,whatever) position&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Test if the current node is optimally sized&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If not, split into 4 children, goto 2&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Optimally sized in this case is just "Am I too far away from the edge of the node" ? If the distance is greater than some threshold, let's say the width of the node, then we split.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Our data model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Depending on your use-case, you can fit as much information as you want into this model. If you're doing some kind of 3D rendering, you might want to keep tabs on neighbor-relations, &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(defn qtree
  " Instantiates a tree node "
  [[x1 y1 x2 y2]]
  {:root?   false
   :bounds  [x1 y1 x2 y2]
   :center  (mapv #(js/Math.floor %)
                  [(half x2 x1)
                   (half y2 y1)])
   :width   (- x2 x1)})&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact we strictly speaking, don't need the center/width stored, but it does make life a bit easier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given a root node and a camera-position we can determine if we want to split or not, simply by testing the distance from the camera to the center:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(defn distance
  [[x1 y1] [x2 y2]]
  (js/Math.sqrt
   (+ (js/Math.pow (- x2 x1) 2)
      (js/Math.pow (- y2 y1) 2))))

(defn too-close?
  " Determines if the camera is closer than halfway to
    the edge of a node "
  [ node camera ]
  (&amp;lt; (distance camera (:center node))
     (:width node)))

(defn split?
  [ node camera ]
  (and (too-close? node camera)
       (&amp;gt; (:width node) _Q_MINIMUM_SIZE)))
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That final check on the width of the node, essentially allow us to recurse until we can't split anymore. In Clojure we have 2 very powerful idioms for walking a tree structure: Postwalk and Prewalk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Postwalk is a depth-first, post-order walk of the tree which applies some arbitrary function to each element.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(w/postwalk (fn [e]
                (prn "Looking at: " e)
                e)
            {:rootval 1
            :node1 {:data "foo"
            :vec  [1 2 3]}})
"Looking at: " :rootval
"Looking at: " 1
"Looking at: " [:rootval 1]
"Looking at: " :node1
"Looking at: " :data
"Looking at: " "foo"
"Looking at: " [:data "foo"]
"Looking at: " :vec
"Looking at: " 1
"Looking at: " 2
"Looking at: " 3
"Looking at: " [1 2 3]
"Looking at: " [:vec [1 2 3]]
"Looking at: " {:data "foo", :vec [1 2 3]}
"Looking at: " [:node1 {:data "foo", :vec [1 2 3]}]
"Looking at: " {:rootval 1, :node1 {:data "foo", :vec [1 2 3]}}
{:rootval 1, :node1 {:data "foo", :vec [1 2 3]}}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hope this is an intuitive way to see the path postwalk takes. The function only prints what it sees and then returns it as is, thus the end result is exactly the map we started out with. Notice how we first see the root key, then its value, then both together as a MapEntry, then it goes deeper into the tree.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now compare that with prewalk:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(w/prewalk (fn [e]
               (prn "Looking at: " e)
               e)
           {:rootval 1
           :node1 {:data "foo"
           :vec  [1 2 3]}})
"Looking at: " {:rootval 1, :node1 {:data "foo", :vec [1 2 3]}}
"Looking at: " [:rootval 1]
"Looking at: " :rootval
"Looking at: " 1
"Looking at: " [:node1 {:data "foo", :vec [1 2 3]}]
"Looking at: " :node1
"Looking at: " {:data "foo", :vec [1 2 3]}
"Looking at: " [:data "foo"]
"Looking at: " :data
"Looking at: " "foo"
"Looking at: " [:vec [1 2 3]]
"Looking at: " :vec
"Looking at: " [1 2 3]
"Looking at: " 1
"Looking at: " 2
"Looking at: " 3
{:rootval 1, :node1 {:data "foo", :vec [1 2 3]}}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prewalk examines the same elements and in the same way, but the path is what we call a pre-order traversal, which means you see contents of nodes before the elements - And by implication, you can swap those nodes and then visit the elements. All in all, prewalk makes for a very simple recursive pattern:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(w/prewalk
 (fn [n]
     (if (and (map? n) (split? n [x y]))
         (subdivide n)
       n))
 qtree)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, it's really that simple. Given a root-node and a camera-position (x,y), this will recursively resolve all children to the maximum resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Visualization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to read ahead, I've shared a repo here: Github&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code should run straight out of the box and open a webinterface on port 8020. Shadow-cljs makes light work of compiling anything from a single file to a huge frontend application, into a single JS file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running in a browser we get a nice 2D API from the standard canvas element. Basically, to draw our Quadtree we need only 3 things:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A Quadtree&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A function which draws a node&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A function which draws all children&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you've probably guessed, the Quadtree itself is just a simple map with some keys. But because this is a realtime visualization, I want to create a connection between whichever tree I generated and what's drawn on screen. Fortunately both Clojure and Clojurescript support both atoms and watches:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(def quadInst (atom nil))

(add-watch quadInst :updateQuads
           (fn [_ _ old-tree new-tree]
             (draw-all new-tree)))&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By convention in Clojure, we name arguments underscore (_) if we do not care about them. In this case, I only need the new-tree for the visualization. If you're not a native Clojurian you might find this pattern appealing as it gives you access to both the pre-updated version and the updated tree, meaning you can run diffs, add new children to a scene while removing others.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I mention it here for demonstration purposes only, in the latest commit you'll see I actually remove all atoms and demonstrate a 100% pure functional solution without atoms. However for the purpose of explaining Quadtree this is a simple subscription-pattern which most developers will recognize. It ensures that whenever the atom Quadtree is updated, so is the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(defn draw-all
  [ tree ]
  (draw (:root? tree)
        tree
        (get-tree-color tree))
  (when-let [children (:children tree)]
    (doseq [c children]
      (draw-all c))))&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However there's a fun detail here. To make it seem fairly consistent I couldn't just use random colors, that would make the entire screen flicker whenever you moved the mouse. Basically, if I have a rectangle centered at 50,50 - I always want it to have the same color. A really neat and simple trick is the 32bit hash, which is succinctly implemented in javascript like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;function fastHash(str) {
    let hash = 0;
    for (let i = 0; i &amp;lt; str.length; i++) {
        hash = (hash &amp;lt;&amp;lt; 5) - hash + str.charCodeAt(i); // Hash computation
        hash |= 0; // Convert to 32bit integer
    }
    return hash &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; 0; // Ensure the result is unsigned
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Basically my idea is to hash the center, ie "[50,50]" and convert that to a hex color. In Clojurescript, you could do it like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(defn hash-str
  " Standard 32bit hash: [..].map((% &amp;lt;&amp;lt; 5) - h + ch(idx) "
  [ s ]
  (reduce #(-&amp;gt; (bit-shift-left %1 5)
               (- %1)
               (+ (.charCodeAt %2 0))
               (bit-or 0))
          0 s))

(defn get-tree-color
  [ {c :center} ]
  (let [hash (bit-and (hash-str (str c)) 0xffffff)
        hex  (.toString hash 16)]
    (str "#" (apply str (repeat (- 6 (count hex)) "0")) hex)))&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's basically all you need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quadtrees are great when you have more work to do, than resources available. Imagine using a VR headset. Whichever point you're focused at, needs to be crisp in detail, you want the highest resolution possible on your hardware. Everything outside of your focus area should be dialed down in resolution because your eyes won't be able to pick it up anyway, so that compute power can be used elsewhere. There are many other applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clojurescript is great, because it allows us to express ourselves succinctly and functionally. The core of this implementation is only about 25 lines long. That's much easier to reason about and debug, than some other implementations I've seen, which span several hundred lines.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadow-cljs is great for more reasons than I can cover in this post, but I will highlight the ability to quickly ship highly optimized bit of JS using only 10 lines of configuration - And they even throw in a free webserver for easy testing and repl driven development, what's not to like?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full source code: Github&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lau B. Jensen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lau is a seasoned Danish software developer and consultant with over 15 years of experience in backend systems, web development, and functional programming using Lisp and Clojure. Since 2007, he has co-founded and scaled multiple successful startups while navigating the venture capital landscape. Lau combines deep technical expertise with entrepreneurial insight, delivering robust, scalable solutions tailored to business needs. Creative, driven, and results-/quality oriented, he thrives turning bold ideas into reality.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lbjgruppen.com/en/posts/functional-quadtree-clojure"/><published>2025-12-04T13:18:38+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46147353</id><title>RAM is so expensive, Samsung won't even sell it to Samsung</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:57.682006+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bb7aac81a5b6d3e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The price of eggs has nothing on the price of computer memory right now. Thanks to a supply crunch from the “AI” bubble, RAM chips are the new gold, with prices on consumer PC memory kits ballooning out of control. In an object lesson in the ridiculousness of an economic bubble, Samsung won’t even sell its memory to… Samsung.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the situation. Samsung makes everything from refrigerators to supermassive oil tankers. Getting all that stuff made requires an organization that’s literally dozens of affiliated companies and subsidiaries, which don’t necessarily work as closely or harmoniously as you might assume. For this story, we’re talking about Samsung Electronics, which makes Galaxy phones, tablets, laptops, watches, etc., and Samsung Semiconductor Global, which manufactures memory and other chips and supplies the global market. That global market includes both Samsung subsidiaries and their competitors—laptops from Samsung, Dell, and Lenovo sitting on a Best Buy store shelf might all have Samsung-manufactured memory sitting in their RAM slots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Samsung subsidiaries are, naturally, going to look to Samsung Semiconductor first when they need parts. Such was reportedly the case for Samsung Electronics, in search of memory supplies for its newest smartphones as the company ramps up production for 2026 flagship designs. But with so much RAM hardware going into new “AI” data centers—and those companies willing to pay top dollar for their hardware—memory manufacturers like Samsung, SK Hynix, and Micron are prioritizing data center suppliers to maximize profits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The end result, according to a report from SE Daily spotted by SamMobile, is that Samsung Semiconductor rejected the original order for smartphone DRAM chips from Samsung Electronics’ Mobile Experience division. The smartphone manufacturing arm of the company had hoped to nail down pricing and supply for another year. But reports say that due to “chipflation,” the phone-making division must renegotiate quarterly, with a long-term supply deal rejected by its corporate sibling. A short-term deal, with higher prices, was reportedly hammered out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Assuming that this information is accurate—and to be clear, we can’t independently confirm it—consumers will see prices rise for Samsung phones and other mobile hardware. But that’s hardly a surprise. Finished electronics probably won’t see the same meteoric rise in prices as consumer-grade RAM modules, but this rising tide is flooding all the boats. Raspberry Pi, which strives to keep its mod-friendly electronics as cheap as possible, has recently had to bring prices up and called out memory costs as the culprit. Lenovo, the world’s largest PC manufacturer, is stockpiling memory supplies as a bulwark against the market.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if you’re hoping to see prices lower in 2026, don’t hold your breath. According to a forecast from memory supplier TeamGroup, component prices have tripled recently, causing finished modules to jump in prices as quickly as 100 percent in a month. Absent some kind of disastrous market collapse, prices are expected to continue rising into next year, and supply could remain constrained well into 2027 or later.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.pcworld.com/article/2998935/ram-is-so-expensive-samsung-wont-even-sell-it-to-samsung.html"/><published>2025-12-04T13:20:07+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46147371</id><title>Human hair grows through 'pulling' not pushing, study shows</title><updated>2025-12-04T13:51:57.403690+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://phys.org/news/2025-12-human-hair.html"/><published>2025-12-04T13:22:35+00:00</published></entry></feed>