<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:36.797115+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46752151</id><title>A flawed paper in management science has been cited more than 6k times</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:44.131881+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2026/01/22/aking/"/><published>2026-01-25T09:04:30+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46752261</id><title>Jurassic Park - Tablet device on Nedry's desk? (2012)</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:43.941680+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.therpf.com/forums/threads/jurassic-park-tablet-device-on-nedrys-desk.169883/"/><published>2026-01-25T09:22:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46752907</id><title>150k lines of vibe coded Elixir: The good, the bad and the ugly</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:43.676582+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f72c54daabbd7c64"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;150,000 Lines of Vibe Coded Elixir: The Good, The Bad, and The Ugly&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Good: AI is great at Elixir. It gets better as your codebase grows.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bad: It defaults to defensive, imperative code. You need to be strict about what good Elixir looks like.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ugly: It can’t debug concurrent test failures. It doesn’t understand that each test runs in an isolated transaction, or that processes have independent lifecycles. It spirals until you step in.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bottom Line: Even with the drawbacks, the productivity gains are off the charts. I expect it will only get better.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BoothIQ is a universal badge scanner for trade shows. AI writes 100% of our code. We have 150,000 lines of vibe coded Elixir running in production. Here’s what worked and what didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Good&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Elixir is Small: It Gets It Right the First Time&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elixir is a small language. Few operators. Small standard library. Only so many ways to control flow. It hasn’t been around for decades. It hasn’t piled up paradigms like .NET or Java, where functional and OOP fight for space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This matters. AI is bad at decisions. If you want your agent to succeed, have it make fewer decisions. With Elixir, Claude doesn’t need to pick between OOP and functional. It doesn’t need to navigate old syntax next to new patterns. There’s one way to skin the cat. Claude finds it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This matters more if you’re adding AI to an existing codebase. In languages where paradigms came and went—often with whatever developer pushed them—Claude tries to match the existing code. The existing code is inconsistent. So Claude is inconsistent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Elixir is Terse: Longer Sessions, Fewer Compactions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Small and terse are related but different. Small means few concepts. Terse means fewer tokens to express the same thing. Go is small but not terse—few concepts, but verbose syntax and explicit error handling everywhere. Elixir is both. We got lucky.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Context windows are a real constraint. Elixir uses fewer tokens than most languages. No braces. No semicolons. No verbose boilerplate. I can stay in a working session longer. More iterations. Fewer compactions—those moments when the AI summarizes and forgets earlier context. More context in memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I built the React Native version of our app, I hit compactions constantly. JavaScript is small-ish, but it’s not terse. It burns tokens to do what Elixir does with fewer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also see more compactions when working on heavy HTML and Tailwind in LiveView. Adding, updating, or editing large sections of markup at once. HTML and HEEx templates are token-heavy. But even then, it’s less painful than JavaScript-heavy work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Tidewave: Longer Unassisted Runs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tidewave supercharges Elixir-specific context. It lets the agent read logs from the running app—debug, info, error, warning—so you don’t copy/paste logs around. It can query the dev database, see Ecto schemas, and view package documentation. Fewer hallucinations. Longer unassisted runs. The agent can check and validate its own assumptions without human intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Immutability: Fewer Decisions, Less Code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If a variable gets mutated by a function call, AI now has three problems instead of one. The actual feature you want implemented. Whether to work around the mutation or update other call sites to stop mutating. And the mutated data itself—what is it, what was it, what will it be, what can it be?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI ponders all of this and contorts itself into an overly defensive mess. It writes nonsense validation checks and if-statements on mutated data. Defensive code that wouldn’t exist in an immutable language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Elixir, the data is what it is. It’s not going to change. Fewer decisions. Less code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Frontend: Higher Quality, Less Time&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I prompt high-level changes—“give the top section more padding”—and Claude does it faster than I could. It’s especially good at modifying or moving large chunks of page structure. Mobile-first views? Easy. Way faster than me, and it’s a better designer than me too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The quality floor has gone way up. You can’t hide behind “I’m not a designer” anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Git Worktrees: Build Multiple Features in Parallel&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I use three git worktrees, so I can work on up to three features at any given time. Typically a main feature, a slightly less important one, and the third reserved for quick fixes, low priority stuff, or quick experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three is about the limit. Any more and context switching between features becomes the bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Bad&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;AI Can’t Organize: Architecture Is Still On You&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI is exceptional at churning out lines of code. It’s significantly less exceptional at deciding where those lines should go. It defaults to creating new files everywhere. It repeats code it’s already written. It introduces inconsistencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the “mess” people describe in vibe code projects as they grow. You still need a human making structural decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Trained on Imperative: It Writes Defensive Code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; AI trained mostly on imperative code. Ruby, Python, JavaScript, C#. Elixir looks like Ruby. So Claude writes Ruby-style Elixir—&lt;code&gt;if/then/else&lt;/code&gt; chains, defensive nil-checking, early returns that don’t make sense in a functional context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elixir wants you to be assertive. Pattern match on what you expect. Let it crash if something’s wrong. The process restarts in a good state. This is foreign to most code Claude trained on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This gets better as the codebase grows. Claude sees more assertive patterns. It starts to infer the style. But it still defaults to defensive. I still correct it regularly. Be strict about what good Elixir looks like.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Git Operations: Keep It Out of Context&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every git operation takes context window space. Checking status. Writing commit messages. Describing PRs. That space could go to actual work. Git context goes stale fast—a commit message from 20 minutes ago is worthless after three more changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I’m babysitting a feature, I commit manually. Every point I’m happy with. It’s fast. It’s cheap version control. It doesn’t burn context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Code has “checkpoints” now. Internal version control that protects vibe coders without explicit commits. That’s better than AI managing git directly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Ugly&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;OTP and Async: It Chases Ghosts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude is useless for debugging OTP, Task, or async issues. It doesn’t understand how processes, the actor model, and GenServers work together. When it tries to introspect the running system, it feeds itself bad data. It gets very lost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It can course correct when you point out where it went wrong. But on its own, it chases ghosts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Ecto Sandbox: It Chases Red Herrings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Elixir tests, each test runs in a database transaction that rolls back at the end. Tests run async without hitting each other. No test data persists.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude doesn’t understand this. It uses Tidewave’s dev DB connection and thinks it’s looking at the test DB—which is always empty. A test fails. Claude queries the database. Finds nothing. Thinks there’s a data problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve watched Claude try to seed the test database so a test will pass. That’s clearly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other times, two tests insert or query the same schema. Claude doesn’t understand transaction isolation—tests can’t see each other’s data. It confuses itself and recommends disabling async tests altogether. Manageable once you watch for it. But ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Bottom Line&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI writing all the code has been a massive win. The friction exists, but it’s manageable and doesn’t interfere much with day-to-day work. By far the most important thing: have a consistent, coherent codebase architecture. Without it, you’ll quickly end up with spaghetti code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal for this year: automate myself out of a job. That means giving Claude more control over the entire software development lifecycle—from a simple problem statement to a fully tested, working PR that only needs a quick glance before it’s merged and deployed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://getboothiq.com/blog/150k-lines-vibe-coded-elixir-good-bad-ugly"/><published>2026-01-25T10:54:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46753078</id><title>Show HN: TUI for managing XDG default applications</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:43.312417+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="fe9cba7b7ba6b9a3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;xdgctl&lt;/code&gt; is a TUI for managing XDG default applications. View and set defaults for file categories without using &lt;code&gt;xdg-mime&lt;/code&gt; directly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Built with C using GLib/GIO and termbox2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head class="px-3 py-2"&gt;xdgctl.mp4&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Browse by category (Browsers, Text Editors, etc.)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Current default marked with &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Key&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Arrow Up/Down&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Navigate through categories or applications&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Arrow Right/Tab&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Switch from category list to application list&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Arrow Left&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Switch back to category list&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Enter&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Set selected application as default for current category&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Esc / q&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Quit the application&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To build &lt;code&gt;xdgctl&lt;/code&gt;, you need the following development libraries:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;glib-2.0&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;gio-2.0&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;gio-unix-2.0&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;clang&lt;/code&gt;or&lt;code&gt;gcc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# On Void Linux
sudo xbps-install glibc-devel pkg-config&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/mitjafelicijan/xdgctl.git
cd xdgctl

# Build
make
sudo make install

# Using prefix
sudo make PREFIX=/usr/local install
make PREFIX=~/.local install&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you manually add new applications to your &lt;code&gt;~/.local/share/applications&lt;/code&gt; directory, you might need to run &lt;code&gt;update-desktop-database&lt;/code&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ls /usr/share/applications
ls ~/.local/share/applications&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;xdg-mime query default text/plain
xdg-mime query default text/html
xdg-mime query default x-scheme-handler/http
xdg-mime query default x-scheme-handler/https
xdg-mime query default inode/directory&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;xdg-mime default brave.desktop x-scheme-handler/http
xdg-mime default brave.desktop x-scheme-handler/https&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# ~/.local/share/applications/brave.desktop
[Desktop Entry]
Exec=/home/m/Applications/brave
Type=Application
Categories=Applications
Name=Brave Browser
MimeType=text/html;text/xml;application/xhtml+xml;x-scheme-handler/http;x-scheme-handler/https;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;update-desktop-database ~/.local/share/applications
less ~/.config/mimeapps.list
less /usr/share/applications/mimeapps.list&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/mitjafelicijan/xdgctl"/><published>2026-01-25T11:19:04+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46753301</id><title>Show HN: Bonsplit – Tabs and splits for native macOS apps</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:42.801360+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="8d0973528a96f1e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bonsplit is a custom tab bar and layout split library for macOS apps. Enjoy out of the box 120fps animations, drag-and-drop reordering, SwiftUI support &amp;amp; keyboard navigation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;.package(url: "https://github.com/almonk/bonsplit.git", from: "1.0.0")&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;### Features&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create tabs with optional icons and dirty indicators. Target specific panes or use the focused pane.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;let tabId = controller.createTab(title: "Document.swift",icon: "swift",isDirty: false,inPane: paneId)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create tabs with optional icons and dirty indicators. Target specific panes or use the focused pane.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;let tabId = controller.createTab(title: "Document.swift",icon: "swift",isDirty: false,inPane: paneId)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Split any pane horizontally or vertically. New panes are empty by default, giving you full control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;// Split focused pane horizontallylet newPaneId = controller.splitPane(orientation: .horizontal)// Split with a tab already in the new panecontroller.splitPane(orientation: .vertical,withTab: Tab(title: "New", icon: "doc"))&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Split any pane horizontally or vertically. New panes are empty by default, giving you full control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;// Split focused pane horizontallylet newPaneId = controller.splitPane(orientation: .horizontal)// Split with a tab already in the new panecontroller.splitPane(orientation: .vertical,withTab: Tab(title: "New", icon: "doc"))&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update tab properties at any time. Changes animate smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;// Mark document as modifiedcontroller.updateTab(tabId, isDirty: true)// Rename tabcontroller.updateTab(tabId, title: "NewName.swift")// Change iconcontroller.updateTab(tabId, icon: "doc.text")&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update tab properties at any time. Changes animate smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;// Mark document as modifiedcontroller.updateTab(tabId, isDirty: true)// Rename tabcontroller.updateTab(tabId, title: "NewName.swift")// Change iconcontroller.updateTab(tabId, icon: "doc.text")&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programmatically navigate between panes using directional navigation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;// Move focus between panescontroller.navigateFocus(direction: .left)controller.navigateFocus(direction: .right)controller.navigateFocus(direction: .up)controller.navigateFocus(direction: .down)// Or focus a specific panecontroller.focusPane(paneId)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programmatically navigate between panes using directional navigation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;// Move focus between panescontroller.navigateFocus(direction: .left)controller.navigateFocus(direction: .right)controller.navigateFocus(direction: .up)controller.navigateFocus(direction: .down)// Or focus a specific panecontroller.focusPane(paneId)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;### Read this, agents...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Complete reference for all Bonsplit classes, methods, and configuration options.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The main controller for managing tabs and panes. Create an instance and pass it to BonsplitView.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Implement this protocol to receive callbacks about tab bar events. All methods have default implementations and are optional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Configure behavior and appearance. Pass to BonsplitController on initialization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;allowSplits&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enable split buttons and drag-to-split&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;allowCloseTabs&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Show close buttons on tabs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;allowCloseLastPane&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Allow closing the last remaining pane&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;allowTabReordering&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enable drag-to-reorder tabs within a pane&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;allowCrossPaneTabMove&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enable moving tabs between panes via drag&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;autoCloseEmptyPanes&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Automatically close panes when their last tab is closed&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;contentViewLifecycle&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ContentViewLifecycle&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How tab content views are managed when switching tabs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;.recreateOnSwitch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;newTabPosition&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;NewTabPosition&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where new tabs are inserted in the tab list&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;.current&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;let config = BonsplitConfiguration(allowSplits: true,allowCloseTabs: true,allowCloseLastPane: false,autoCloseEmptyPanes: true,contentViewLifecycle: .keepAllAlive,newTabPosition: .current)let controller = BonsplitController(configuration: config)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Controls how tab content views are managed when switching between tabs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Mode&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Memory&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;State&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Use Case&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;.recreateOnSwitch&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Low&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;None&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Simple content&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;.keepAllAlive&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Higher&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Full&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Complex views, forms&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Controls where new tabs are inserted in the tab list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Mode&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Behavior&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;.current&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Insert after currently focused tab, or at end if none&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;.end&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Always insert at the end of the tab list&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;tabBarHeight&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CGFloat&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Height of the tab bar&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;33&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;tabMinWidth&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CGFloat&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minimum width of a tab&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;140&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;tabMaxWidth&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CGFloat&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maximum width of a tab&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;220&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;tabSpacing&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CGFloat&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spacing between tabs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;minimumPaneWidth&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CGFloat&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minimum width of a pane&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;100&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;minimumPaneHeight&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CGFloat&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minimum height of a pane&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;100&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;showSplitButtons&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Show split buttons in the tab bar&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;animationDuration&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Double&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Duration of animations in seconds&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;0.15&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;enableAnimations&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enable or disable all animations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default: &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;.default&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BonsplitConfiguration&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default configuration with all features enabled&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;.singlePane&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BonsplitConfiguration&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Single pane mode with splits disabled&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;.readOnly&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BonsplitConfiguration&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read-only mode with all modifications disabled&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://bonsplit.alasdairmonk.com"/><published>2026-01-25T11:56:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46753336</id><title>Nango (YC W23, Dev Infrastructure) Is Hiring Remotely</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:42.666317+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e10fcdab2cdf53e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need to enable JavaScript to run this app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/Nango"/><published>2026-01-25T12:02:01+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46753484</id><title>Doom has been ported to an earbud</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:41.913552+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a6567235022113ff"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's almost your turn, get ready!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Player queue&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your position&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Players queued&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wait time&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You know the 1993 classic DOOM? I made it run on an earbud, then I connected it to the internet and made it possible for visitors like you to sit in a queue for hours play the game remotely!.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yeah but it won't just run on any old earbud, this only works with the Pinebuds Pro, the only earbuds with open source firmware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You sure can! There are two relevant repos:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was a necessary optimisation to avoid paying outgoing bandwidth fees, once you're 5th in the queue, the twitch player will switch to a low-latency MJPEG stream.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;shhhh don't look don't look it's ok just join the queue&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's switch to a more readable font first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; I'll put out an article / video diving deeper into this later, but here are a few bits of info:&lt;lb/&gt; This project is made up of four parts: &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The firmware pushes up against a few hardware limitations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Earbuds don't have displays, so the only way to transfer data to/from them is either via bluetooth, or the UART contact pads.&lt;lb/&gt; Bluetooth is pretty slow, you'd be lucky to get a consistent 1mbps connection, UART is easily the better option.&lt;lb/&gt; DOOM's framebuffer is (width * height) bytes, 320 * 200 = 96kB. (doom's internal framebuffer is 8-bit not 24-bit)&lt;lb/&gt; The UART connection provides us with 2.4mbps of usable bandwidth. 2,400,000 / 8 / 96,000 gives us... 3 frames per second.&lt;lb/&gt; Clearly we need to compress the video stream. Modern video codecs like h264 consume way too much CPU and RAM.&lt;lb/&gt; The only feasible approach is sending the video as an MJPEG stream. MJPEG is a stream of JPEG images shown one after the other.&lt;lb/&gt; I found an excellent JPEG encoder for embedded devices here, thanks Larry!&lt;lb/&gt; A conservative estimate for the average HIGH quality JPEG frame is around 13.5KB, but most scenes (without enemies) are around 11kb.&lt;lb/&gt; Theoretical maximum FPS:&lt;lb/&gt; - Optimistic: `2,400,000 / (11,000 * 8)` = 27.3 FPS&lt;lb/&gt; - Conservative: `2,400,000 / (13,500 * 8)` = 22.2 FPS &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; The stock open source firmware has the CPU set to 100mhz, so I cranked that up to 300mhz and disabled low power mode.&lt;lb/&gt; The Cortex-M4F running at 300mhz is actually more than enough for DOOM, however it struggles with JPEG encoding.&lt;lb/&gt; This is why it maxes out at ~18fps, I don't think there's much else I can do to speed it up. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; By default, we only have access to 768KB of RAM, after disabling the co-processor it gets bumped up to the advertised 992KB.&lt;lb/&gt; DOOM requires 4MB of RAM, though there are plenty of optimisations that can reduce this amount.&lt;lb/&gt; Pre-generating lookup tables, making variables const, reading const variables from flash, disabling DOOM's caching system, removing unneeded variables. It all adds up! &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; The shareware DOOM 1 wad (assets file) is 4.2MB and the earbuds can only store 4MB of data.&lt;lb/&gt; Thankfully, fragglet, a well-known doom modder, has already solved this issue for me.&lt;lb/&gt; Squashware is his trimmed-down DOOM 1 wad that is only 1.7MB in size.&lt;lb/&gt; With this wad file, everything comfortably fits in flash. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought you'd never ask! (please hire me)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://doombuds.com"/><published>2026-01-25T12:22:12+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46753708</id><title>Web-based image editor modeled after Deluxe Paint</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:41.791836+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="56223e185d452d87"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Webbased image editor modeled after the legendary Deluxe Paint with a focus on retro Amiga file formats. Next to modern image formats, DPaint.js can read and write Amiga icon files and IFF ILBM images.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Online version available at https://www.stef.be/dpaint/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fully Featured image editor with a.o. &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Layers&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Selections&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Masking&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Transformation tools&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Effects and filters&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Multiple undo/redo&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Copy/Paste from any other image program or image source&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Customizable dither tools&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Color Cycling&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Heavy focus on colour reduction with fine-grained dithering options&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Amiga focus &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Read/write/convert Amiga icon files (all formats)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Reads IFF ILBM images (all formats including HAM and 24-bit)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Writes IFF ILBM images (up to 256 colors)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Read and write directly from Amiga Disk Files (ADF)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Embedded Amiga Emulator to preview your work in the real Deluxe Paint.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Limit the palette to 12 bit for Amiga OCS/ECS mode, or 9 bit for Atari ST mode.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Deluxe Paint Legacy &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Supports PBM files as used by the PC version of Deluxe Paint (Thanks to Michael Smith)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Supports Deluxe Paint Atari ST compression modes (Thanks to Nicolas Ramz)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It runs in your browser, works on any system and works fine on touch-screen devices like iPads.&lt;lb/&gt; It is written in 100% plain JavaScript and has no dependencies.&lt;lb/&gt; It's 100% free, no ads, no tracking, no accounts, no nothing.&lt;lb/&gt; All processing is done in your browser, no data is sent to any server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only part that is not included in this repository is the Amiga Emulator Files. (The emulator is based on the Scripted Amiga Emulator)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DPaint.js doesn't need building.&lt;lb/&gt; It also has zero dependencies so there's no need to install anything.&lt;lb/&gt; DPaint.js is written using ES6 modules and runs out of the box in modern browsers.&lt;lb/&gt; Just serve "index.html" from a webserver and you're good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's an optional build step to create a compact version of DPaint.js if you like.&lt;lb/&gt; I'm using Parcel.js for this.&lt;lb/&gt; For convenience, I've included a "package.json" file.&lt;lb/&gt; open a terminal and run &lt;code&gt;npm install&lt;/code&gt; to install Parcel.js and its dependencies.
Then run &lt;code&gt;npm run build&lt;/code&gt; to create a compact version of DPaint.js in the "dist" folder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Documentation can be found at https://www.stef.be/dpaint/docs/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dpaint.js is a web application, not an app that you install on your computer. That being said: DPaint.js has no online dependencies and runs fine offline if you want. One caveat: you have to serve the index.html file from a webserver, not just open it in your browser.&lt;lb/&gt; A quick way to do this is - for example - using the Spark app.&lt;lb/&gt; Download the binary for your platform, drop the Spark executable in the folder where you downloaded the Dpaint.js source files and run it. If you then point your browser to http://localhost:8080/ it should work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are using Chrome, you can also "install" dpaint.js as app.&lt;lb/&gt; It will then show up your Chrome apps and work offline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Current version is still alpha.&lt;lb/&gt; I'm sure there are bugs and missing features.&lt;lb/&gt; Bug reports and pull requests are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Planned for the next release, already in the works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;del rend="overstrike"&gt;Color Cycling&lt;/del&gt;(done)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;del rend="overstrike"&gt;Animation support (GIf and Amiga ANIM files)&lt;/del&gt;(done)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;del rend="overstrike"&gt;Shading/transparency tools that stay within the palette.&lt;/del&gt;(done)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Planned for a future release if there's a need for it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Support for non-square pixel modes such as HiRes and Interlaced&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;PSD import and export&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;SpriteSheet support&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Write HAM,SHAM and Dynamic HiRes images&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Commodore 64 graphics modes&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please note that the Brave browser is using "farbling" that introduces random image noise in certain conditions. They claim this is to protect your privacy. Although I totally understand the sentiment, In my opinion a browser should not actively alter the content of a webpage or intentionally break functionality.&lt;lb/&gt; But hey, who am I to speak, it's a free world. Just be aware that if you are using Brave, you will run into issues, so please "lower your shields" for this app in Brave or use another browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dpaint.js supports Color-Cycling - a long lost art of "animating" a static image by only rotating some colors in the palette. See an example here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head class="px-3 py-2"&gt;The_Vision_cycle.mp4&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open the layered source file of the above image directly in Dpaint.js&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/steffest/DPaint-js"/><published>2026-01-25T12:54:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46754944</id><title>A macOS app that blurs your screen when you slouch</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:41.376560+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="709cd7c437d6538d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A macOS app that blurs your screen when you slouch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posturr uses your Mac's camera and Apple's Vision framework to monitor your posture in real-time. When it detects that you're slouching, it progressively blurs your screen to remind you to sit up straight. Maintain good posture, and the blur clears instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Real-time posture detection - Uses Apple's Vision framework for body pose and face tracking&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Progressive screen blur - Gentle visual reminder that intensifies with worse posture&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Menu bar controls - Easy access to settings, calibration, and status from the menu bar&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multi-display support - Works across all connected monitors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Privacy-focused - All processing happens locally on your Mac&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lightweight - Runs as a background app with minimal resource usage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No account required - No signup, no cloud, no tracking&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Download the latest &lt;code&gt;Posturr-vX.X.X.zip&lt;/code&gt;from the Releases page&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unzip the downloaded file&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Drag &lt;code&gt;Posturr.app&lt;/code&gt;to your Applications folder&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since Posturr is not signed with an Apple Developer certificate, macOS Gatekeeper will initially block it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Right-click (or Control-click) on &lt;code&gt;Posturr.app&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Select "Open" from the context menu&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Click "Open" in the dialog that appears&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Grant camera access when prompted&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You only need to do this once. After the first launch, you can open Posturr normally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posturr requires camera access to monitor your posture. When you first launch the app, macOS will ask for permission. Click "OK" to grant access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you accidentally denied permission, you can grant it later:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Open System Settings &amp;gt; Privacy &amp;amp; Security &amp;gt; Camera&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Find Posturr and enable the toggle&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once launched, Posturr appears in your menu bar with a person icon. The app continuously monitors your posture and applies screen blur when slouching is detected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click the menu bar icon to access:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Status - Shows current state (Monitoring, Slouching, Good Posture, etc.)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enabled - Toggle posture monitoring on/off&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Recalibrate - Reset your baseline posture (sit up straight, then click)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sensitivity - Adjust how sensitive the slouch detection is (Low, Medium, High, Very High)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dead Zone - Set the tolerance before blur kicks in (None, Small, Medium, Large)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compatibility Mode - Use public macOS APIs for blur (try this if blur doesn't appear)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Quit - Exit the application (or press Escape anywhere)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Position your camera at eye level when possible&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ensure adequate lighting on your face&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sit at a consistent distance from your screen&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The app works best when your shoulders are visible&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posturr uses Apple's Vision framework to detect body pose landmarks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Body Pose Detection: Tracks nose, shoulders, and their relative positions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Face Detection Fallback: When full body isn't visible, tracks face position&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Posture Analysis: Measures the vertical distance between nose and shoulders&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Blur Response: Applies screen blur proportional to posture deviation&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The screen blur uses macOS's private CoreGraphics API by default for efficient, system-level blur. If the blur doesn't appear on your system, enable Compatibility Mode from the menu to use &lt;code&gt;NSVisualEffectView&lt;/code&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;macOS 13.0 (Ventura) or later&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Xcode Command Line Tools (&lt;code&gt;xcode-select --install&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/yourusername/posturr.git
cd posturr
./build.sh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The built app will be in &lt;code&gt;build/Posturr.app&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Standard build
./build.sh

# Build with release archive (.zip)
./build.sh --release&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;swiftc -O \
    -framework AppKit \
    -framework AVFoundation \
    -framework Vision \
    -framework CoreImage \
    -o Posturr \
    main.swift&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No code signing: Requires manual Gatekeeper bypass on first launch&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Camera dependency: Requires a working camera with adequate lighting&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Detection accuracy: Works best with clear view of upper body/face&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posturr exposes a file-based command interface for external control:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Command&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;capture&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Take a photo and analyze pose&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;blur &amp;lt;0-64&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Set blur level manually&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;quit&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Exit the application&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write commands to &lt;code&gt;/tmp/posturr-command&lt;/code&gt;. Responses appear in &lt;code&gt;/tmp/posturr-response&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;macOS 13.0 (Ventura) or later&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Camera (built-in or external)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Approximately 10MB disk space&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posturr processes all video data locally on your Mac. No images or data are ever sent to external servers. The camera feed is used solely for posture detection and is never stored or transmitted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT License - see LICENSE for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contributions are welcome! Please feel free to submit issues and pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Built with Apple's Vision framework for body pose detection&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Uses private CoreGraphics API for blur, with NSVisualEffectView fallback&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inspired by the need for better posture during long coding sessions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Thanks to @wklm for the compatibility mode implementation&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/tldev/posturr"/><published>2026-01-25T15:34:51+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46755115</id><title>Using PostgreSQL as a Dead Letter Queue for Event-Driven Systems</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:41.205671+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f4c263785a28d80"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While I was working on a project with Wayfair, I got the opportunity to work on a system that generated daily business reports aggregated from multiple data sources flowing through event streams across Wayfair. At a high level, Kafka consumers listened to these events, hydrated them with additional data by calling downstream services, and finally persisted the enriched events into a durable datastoreâCloudSQL PostgreSQL on GCP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When everything was healthy, the pipeline worked exactly as expected. Events flowed in, got enriched, and were stored reliably. The real challenge started when things went wrong, which, in distributed systems, is not an exception but a certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were multiple failure scenarios we had to deal with. Sometimes the APIs we depended on for hydration were down or slow. Sometimes the consumer itself crashed midway through processing. In other cases, events arrived with missing or malformed fields that could not be processed safely. These were all situations outside our direct control, but they still needed to be handled gracefully.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where the concept of a Dead Letter Queue came into the picture. Whenever we knew an event could not be processed successfully, instead of dropping it or blocking the entire consumer, we redirected it to a DLQ so it could be inspected and potentially reprocessed later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our first instinct was to use Kafka itself as a DLQ. While this is a common pattern, it quickly became clear that it wasn't a great fit for our needs. Kafka is excellent for moving data, but once messages land in a DLQ topic, they are not particularly easy to inspect. Querying by failure reason, retrying a specific subset of events, or even answering simple questions like "what failed yesterday and why?" required extra tooling and custom consumers. For a system that powered business-critical daily reports, this lack of visibility was a serious drawback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's when we decided to treat PostgreSQL itself as the Dead Letter Queue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of publishing failed events to another Kafka topic, we persisted them directly into a DLQ table in PostgreSQL. We were already using CloudSQL as our durable store, so operationally this added very little complexity. Conceptually, it also made failures first-class citizens in the system rather than opaque messages lost in a stream.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Whenever an event failed processingâdue to an API failure, consumer crash, schema mismatch, or validation errorâwe stored the raw event payload along with contextual information about the failure. Each record carried a simple status field. When the event first landed in the DLQ, it was marked as &lt;code&gt;PENDING&lt;/code&gt;. Once it was successfully reprocessed, the status was updated to &lt;code&gt;SUCCEEDED&lt;/code&gt;. Keeping the state model intentionally minimal made it easy to reason about the lifecycle of a failed event.
                    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;DLQ Table Schema and Indexing Strategy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To support inspection, retries, and long-term operability, the DLQ table was designed to be simple, query-friendly, and retry-aware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Table Schema&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CREATE TABLE dlq_events (
    id BIGSERIAL PRIMARY KEY,
    event_type VARCHAR(255) NOT NULL,
    payload JSONB NOT NULL,
    error_reason TEXT NOT NULL,
    error_stacktrace TEXT,
    status VARCHAR(20) NOT NULL, -- PENDING / SUCCEEDED
    retry_count INT NOT NULL DEFAULT 0,
    retry_after TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE NOT NULL,
    created_at TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE NOT NULL DEFAULT NOW(),
    updated_at TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE NOT NULL DEFAULT NOW()
);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Key Design Considerations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;payload&lt;/code&gt;is stored as&lt;code&gt;JSONB&lt;/code&gt;to preserve the raw event without enforcing a rigid schema.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;status&lt;/code&gt;keeps the lifecycle simple and explicit.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;retry_after&lt;/code&gt;prevents aggressive retries when downstream systems are unstable.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;retry_count&lt;/code&gt;allows retry limits to be enforced without external state.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Timestamps make auditing and operational analysis straightforward.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Indexes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CREATE INDEX idx_dlq_status
ON dlq_events (status);

CREATE INDEX idx_dlq_status_retry_after
ON dlq_events (status, retry_after);

CREATE INDEX idx_dlq_event_type
ON dlq_events (event_type);

CREATE INDEX idx_dlq_created_at
ON dlq_events (created_at);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These indexes allow the retry scheduler to efficiently locate eligible events while still supporting fast debugging and time-based analysis without full table scans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;DLQ Retry Mechanism with ShedLock&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Persisting failed events solved the visibility problem, but we still needed a safe and reliable way to retry them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; For this, we introduced a DLQ retry scheduler backed by ShedLock. The scheduler periodically scans the DLQ table for &lt;code&gt;PENDING&lt;/code&gt; events that are eligible for retry and attempts to process them again. Since the service runs on multiple instances, ShedLock ensures that only one instance executes the retry job at any given time. This eliminates duplicate retries without requiring custom leader-election logic.
                    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Retry Configuration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;dlq:
  retry:
    enabled: true
    max-retries: 240
    batch-size: 50
    fixed-rate: 21600000 # 6 hours in milliseconds&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;How Retries Work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The scheduler runs every six hours.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Up to fifty eligible events are picked up per run.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Events exceeding the maximum retry count are skipped.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Successful retries immediately transition the event status to &lt;code&gt;SUCCEEDED&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Failures remain in &lt;code&gt;PENDING&lt;/code&gt;and are retried in subsequent runs.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Query Implementation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; The retry scheduler uses a SQL query with &lt;code&gt;FOR UPDATE SKIP LOCKED&lt;/code&gt; to safely select eligible events across multiple instances. This PostgreSQL feature ensures that even if multiple scheduler instances run simultaneously, each will pick up different rows without blocking each other:
                    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@QueryHints(@QueryHint(name = "jakarta.persistence.lock.timeout", value = "-2"))
@Query(
    value = "SELECT * FROM dlq_table "
        + "WHERE messagetype = :messageType "
        + "AND retries &amp;lt; :maxRetries "
        + "AND (replay_status IS NULL OR replay_status NOT IN ('COMPLETED')) "
        + "ORDER BY created_at ASC "
        + "FOR UPDATE SKIP LOCKED",
    nativeQuery = true
)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; The &lt;code&gt;FOR UPDATE SKIP LOCKED&lt;/code&gt; clause is crucial here. It allows each instance to lock and process different rows concurrently, preventing duplicate processing while maintaining high throughput. The query hint sets the lock timeout to &lt;code&gt;-2&lt;/code&gt;, which means "wait indefinitely" but combined with &lt;code&gt;SKIP LOCKED&lt;/code&gt;, it effectively means "skip any rows that are already locked by another transaction."
                    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This setup allowed the system to tolerate long downstream outages while avoiding retry storms and unnecessary load on dependent services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Operational Benefits&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this approach, failures became predictable and observable rather than disruptive. Engineers could inspect failures using plain SQL, identify patterns, and reprocess only the events that mattered. If a downstream dependency was unavailable for hours or even days, events safely accumulated in the DLQ and were retried later without human intervention. If an event was fundamentally bad, it stayed visible instead of being silently dropped.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most importantly, this design reduced operational stress. Failures were no longer something to fear; they were an expected part of the system with a clear, auditable recovery path.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;My Thoughts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal was never to replace Kafka with PostgreSQL. Kafka remained the backbone for high-throughput event ingestion, while PostgreSQL handled what it does bestâdurability, querying, and observability around failures. By letting each system play to its strengths, we ended up with a pipeline that was resilient, debuggable, and easy to operate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the end, using PostgreSQL as a Dead Letter Queue turned failure handling into something boring and predictable. And in production systems, boring is exactly what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.diljitpr.net/blog-post-postgresql-dlq"/><published>2026-01-25T15:51:03+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46755999</id><title>FAA institutes nationwide drone no-fly zones around ICE operations</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:41.053041+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="5c9064d05e9c8590"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Federal Aviation Administration has issued a nationwide security notice, effectively creating a moving drone no-fly zone around operations conducted by Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) and other components of the Department of Homeland Security.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The notice, NOTAM FDC 6/4375, prohibits unmanned aircraft systems from operating within 3,000 feet laterally and 1,000 feet vertically of DHS facilities and mobile assets, including ground vehicle convoys and their escorts. The restriction applies nationwide and continuously, rather than at fixed locations or during defined time windows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because ICE operates under DHS and routinely conducts enforcement actions using mobile vehicle convoys in public spaces, the restriction functions as a drone no-fly zone around ICE operations, including arrests, transport activities and other field actions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FAA classifies the restricted airspace as “national defense airspace,” and cites its authority under federal security statutes. Drone operators who violate the restriction may face criminal prosecution, civil penalties, administrative enforcement actions, or revocation of FAA operating privileges. The notice also states that drones deemed a credible security threat may be intercepted, seized, damaged, or destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike traditional Temporary Flight Restrictions, the NOTAM does not provide geographic coordinates, activation times, or public notification when the restriction is in effect near a specific location. Instead, the restricted airspace moves with DHS assets, meaning the no-fly zone can appear wherever ICE or other DHS units operate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new NOTAM replaces an earlier security notice, FDC 5/6378, which covered similar federal agencies but was less explicit about mobile operations. The updated version removes ambiguity by clearly stating that the restriction applies to moving DHS assets, including vehicles and convoys, and not just fixed facilities such as offices or bases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That clarification has drawn attention from drone operators and civil liberties groups because it creates dynamic, invisible exclusion zones that may be impossible to identify in real time. The FAA does not publish public tracking of DHS or ICE movements, and the NOTAM does not include a mechanism for drone pilots to determine when covered assets are nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In practical terms, a drone operator flying legally in a public area could unknowingly enter restricted airspace if an ICE convoy passes within the protected radius. The FAA instructs operators to “exercise caution” when flying near DHS facilities and mobile assets, but offers no specific guidance on how to do so in environments where enforcement activity is not publicly disclosed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The notice mentions limited exceptions. Drone operations conducted in direct support of national defense, homeland security, law enforcement, firefighting, search and rescue, or disaster response missions may be authorized with advance coordination. Operators seeking approval are instructed to coordinate with DHS or other covered agencies, or contact the FAA’s System Operations Support Center.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FAA cites multiple federal statutes as the legal basis for the restriction, including laws governing national defense airspace and counter-UAS mitigation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.aerotime.aero/articles/faa-drone-no-fly-zone-ice-dhs"/><published>2026-01-25T17:24:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46756117</id><title>ICE using Palantir tool that feeds on Medicaid data</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:40.711565+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ad964554d5aa1139"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EFF last summer asked a federal judge to block the federal government from using Medicaid data to identify and deport immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also warned about the danger of the Trump administration consolidating all of the government’s information into a single searchable, AI-driven interface with help from Palantir, a company that has a shaky-at-best record on privacy and human rights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we have the first evidence that our concerns have become reality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Palantir is working on a tool for Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) that populates a map with potential deportation targets, brings up a dossier on each person, and provides a “confidence score” on the person’s current address,” 404 Media reports today. “ICE is using it to find locations where lots of people it might detain could be based.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The tool – dubbed Enhanced Leads Identification &amp;amp; Targeting for Enforcement (ELITE) – receives peoples’ addresses from the Department of Health and Human Services (which includes Medicaid) and other sources, 404 Media reports based on court testimony in Oregon by law enforcement agents, among other sources.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This revelation comes as ICE – which has gone on a surveillance technology shopping spree – floods Minneapolis with agents, violently running roughshod over the civil rights of immigrants and U.S. citizens alike; President Trump has threatened to use the Insurrection Act of 1807 to deploy military troops against protestors there. Other localities are preparing for the possibility of similar surges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Different government agencies necessarily collect information to provide essential services or collect taxes, but the danger comes when the government begins pooling that data and using it for reasons unrelated to the purpose it was collected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This kind of consolidation of government records provides enormous government power that can be abused. Different government agencies necessarily collect information to provide essential services or collect taxes, but the danger comes when the government begins pooling that data and using it for reasons unrelated to the purpose it was collected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As EFF Executive Director Cindy Cohn wrote in a Mercury News op-ed last August, “While couched in the benign language of eliminating government ‘data silos,’ this plan runs roughshod over your privacy and security. It’s a throwback to the rightly mocked ‘Total Information Awareness’ plans of the early 2000s that were, at least publicly, stopped after massive outcry from the public and from key members of Congress. It’s time to cry out again.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to the amicus brief we co-authored challenging ICE’s grab for Medicaid data, EFF has successfully sued over DOGE agents grabbing personal data from the U.S. Office of Personnel Management, filed an amicus brief in a suit challenging ICE’s grab for taxpayer data, and sued the departments of State and Homeland Security to halt a mass surveillance program to monitor constitutionally protected speech by noncitizens lawfully present in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But litigation isn’t enough. People need to keep raising concerns via public discourse and Congress should act immediately to put brakes on this runaway train that threatens to crush the privacy and security of each and every person in America.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2026/01/report-ice-using-palantir-tool-feeds-medicaid-data"/><published>2026-01-25T17:36:19+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46757067</id><title>First, make me care</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:40.109819+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="77b044a15c934274"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, Make Me Care Writing advice: some nonfiction fails because it opens with background instead of a hook—readers leave before reaching the good material. Find the single anomaly or question that makes your topic interesting, lead with that, and let the background follow once you’ve earned attention. [Return to blog index]&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://gwern.net/blog/2026/make-me-care"/><published>2026-01-25T19:03:40+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46757162</id><title>Spanish track was fractured before high-speed train disaster, report finds</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:39.765467+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ae6089bcbd13d29b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Spanish track was fractured before high-speed train disaster, report finds&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A fracture in a straight section of track "occurred prior to the passage" of a high-speed train that derailed, causing last Sunday's rail disaster in which 45 people died, an initial report has found.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A train run by private company Iryo derailed last Sunday and its rear carriages crossed on to the opposite track into the path of an oncoming train run by state-owned Renfe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The CIAF rail investigation commission said not only did Iryo train's front carriages which stayed on the track have "notches" in their wheels, but three earlier trains that went over the track earlier did too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A gap of almost 40cm (15in) in the track has become the focus of the investigation into the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sunday's deadly collision occurred at around 19:45 local time (18:45 GMT), about an hour after the Iryo train left Málaga for Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The train's last three carriages - carriages six to eight - derailed and collided with the Huelva-bound Renfe train. "Carriage six derailed due to a complete lack of continuity in the track," the preliminary report finds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of those killed and injured were in the front carriages of the state-operated train.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, Spanish Transport Minister Óscar Puente confirmed reports that grooves were found on the wheels of the Iryo train's carriages, which had passed over the track safely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"These notches in the wheels and the deformation observed in the track are compatible with the fact that the track was cracked," the CIAF preliminary report said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It added that three trains that had gone over the tracks at 17:21 on Sunday, 19:01 and then 19:09 had similar notches "with a compatible geometric pattern".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similar grooves are found on carriages two, three and four of the Iryo train, the report says, but carriage five - the last that did not derail - had a groove on its outer edge, suggesting the rail was already tilting outwards before carriage six derailed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The CIAF called its report a "working hypothesis", adding that it "must be corroborated by later detailed calculations and analysis".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The transport minister appeared before reporters again on Friday to say that it was too early to have definitive answers, but that if the cause of the crash was the fracture, then it occurred in the minutes and hours before the derailment and could not have been detected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Adamuz disaster is is the country's worst rail crash in more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2013, Spain suffered its worst high-speed train derailment in Galicia, north-west Spain, which left 80 people dead and 140 others injured.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c1m77dmxlvlo"/><published>2026-01-25T19:12:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46757357</id><title>I was right about ATProto key management</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:39.153669+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="eebcc91d3d2314dc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, a while ago, I wrote a post called “Key Management, ATProto, and Decentralization” in which I complained about ATProto’s approach to decentralization. Since then, Blacksky has spun up an AppView, which makes it theoretically possible to have an actually decentralized experience on Bluesky. This was my line in the sand, stated many times; I would make an account when and only when it was possible to do so without using anything running on Bluesky-the-company’s hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, today, I tried that. Let’s walk through the process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set up the PDS software on a server I control. Because I use NixOS, this was basically trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a did:web. This means creating a public-private keypair; I initially tried following this tutorial from Mai Lapyst, but it’s very out of date, and doesn’t include a critical step, as we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With that did:web, upload the &lt;code&gt;did.json&lt;/code&gt; document to my webserver and set the appropriate DNS entries. Easy enough, except that I also had to set the CORS header for the &lt;code&gt;did.json&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create an account on my shiny new PDS. I was able to get an invite and create an account, but it was in the “deactivated” status, and I couldn’t activate it. It was very frustrating, because I was making requests manually with &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; and reading the error outcomes in the PDS’s logs on my server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oh, and by the way, none of this is documented. Sure, the individual endpoints are - kind of - but the only place the whole process is collected in one place is in the comments to this GitHub issue… which is closed as WONTFIX.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seek help in the ATProto Touchers Discord server, and at their advice delete the account (foreshadowing!).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start over and re-create everything from scratch, finally noticing the comment line in the comment on the closed GitHub issue telling me to replace the public key in my DID with the public key from &lt;code&gt;getRecommendedDidCredentials&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The documentation for that endpoint, by the way, reads in full:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Describe the credentials that should be included in the DID doc of an account that is migrating to this service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that I am not “migrating”; this account is new. Plus, the JSON keys it returns are almost, but not quite, the same as those in a DID document, and the key it returns actually has to be edited by hand in order to be usable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update the DID document with the correct key.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Log into Bluesky (bsky.app) and see the brave new world of… never mind, I get a “Profile does not exist error.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was at this point that I found this GitHub issue, which seems to imply that, since I deleted my (completely empty and unused) account, my did:web is blacklisted from the remaining mostly-centralized bit of the system, the AppView. The term for this, apparently, is being “burned”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Asking in the Discord again, I was told as much, and that my best bet is to reach out to support. Support from the company that I am supposedly free from using. Ugh!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I feel that this completely vindicates my view in my other post that asking users - even pretty technical ones - to handle their own PKI without any tooling or even really any documentation is completely untenable. As a long time Fedi admin friend of mine said, this is somehow harder and more error-prone than setting up a Mastodon instance in 2017 - and you expect each and every user to choose between this and centralization?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ATProto may be decentralized, but Bluesky - the social network and social protocol on top of it - is not, at least not in a way anyone can actually use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’ve been drinking the coolaid, ask yourself this: why is a centralized “burn” able to completely prevent me from interacting with people using Bluesky?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that I don’t like ATProto, but I do actually want to use Bluesky. I find Blacksky really interesting, and I have several friends who post exclusively there. I would love to use Bluesky, with my own domain name, from my own PDS, but I’m not allowed to - because of a centralized authority.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may be aware that Mastodon has a similar system. If you set up a Mastodon server and then delete the database, anyone you’ve already federated with won’t federate with you again, because you can’t prove you’re the same instance. It’s a genuine issue - but it wouldn’t have resulted in this, because I hadn’t even made a post on my now-burned did:web identity, nor followed anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if I had, though, that would have burned a connection, not all connections. My experience would be degraded, but not ruined, and I could work with the admins of the affected servers to remediate it. You could say the same here, of course; maybe (maybe) support will get back to me some day, but it’s just that - support. There is only, really, one connection that matters; maybe two, if you count Blacksky, but their AppView is not generally available yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s centralization. I don’t understand how you could call it anything else.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://notes.nora.codes/atproto-again/"/><published>2026-01-25T19:31:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46757465</id><title>Data Leak Exposes 149M Logins, Including Gmail, Facebook</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:39.012505+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.techrepublic.com/article/news-149-million-passwords-exposed-infostealer-database/"/><published>2026-01-25T19:45:10+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46757944</id><title>OnePlus update blocks downgrades and custom ROMs by blowing a fuse</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:38.733592+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://consumerrights.wiki/w/Oneplus_phone_update_introduces_hardware_anti-rollback"/><published>2026-01-25T20:39:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46758175</id><title>AI Tribalism</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:38.606495+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7f6d1d56aeb484db"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Heartbreaking: The Worst Person You Know Just Made a Great Point” – ClickHole&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“When the facts change, I change my mind. What do you do, sir?” – John Maynard Keynes, paraphrased&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025 was a weird year for me. If you had asked me exactly a year ago, I would have said I thought LLMs were amusing toys but inappropriate for real software development. I couldn’t fathom why people would want a hyperactive five-year-old to grab their keyboard every few seconds and barf some gobbledygook into their IDE that could barely compile.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, I would say that about 90% of my code is authored by Claude Code. The rest of the time, I’m mostly touching up its work or doing routine tasks that it’s slow at, like refactoring or renaming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By now the battle lines have been drawn, and these arguments are getting pretty tiresome. Every day there’s a new thinkpiece on Hacker News about how either LLMs are the greatest thing ever or they’re going to destroy the world. I don’t write blog posts unless I think I have something new to contribute though, so here goes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I’ve noticed about a lot of these debates, especially if you spend a lot of time on Mastodon, Bluesky, or Lobsters, is that it’s devolved into politics. And since politics long ago devolved into tribalism, that means it’s become tribalism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I remember when LLMs first exploded onto the scene a few years ago, and the same crypto bros who were previously hawking monkey JPEGs suddenly started singing the praises of AI. Meanwhile upper management got wind of it, and the message I got (even if they tried to use euphemisms, bless their hearts) was “you are expendable now, learn these tools so I can replace you.” In other words, the people whose opinions on programming I respected least were the ones eagerly jumping from the monkey JPEGs to these newfangled LLMs. So you can forgive me for being a touch cynical and skeptical at the start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Around the same time, the smartest engineers I knew were maybe dabbling with LLMs, but overall unimpressed with the hallucinations, the bugs, and just the overall lousiness of these tools. I remember looking at the slow, buggy output of an IDE autocomplete and thinking, “I can type faster than this. And make fewer mistakes.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Something changed in 2025, though. I’m not an expert on this stuff, so I have no idea if it was Opus 4.5 or reinforcement learning or just that Claude Code was so cleverly designed, but some threshold was reached. And I noticed that, more and more, it just didn’t make sense for me to type stuff out by hand (and I’m a very fast typist!) when I could just write a markdown spec, work with Claude in plan mode to refine it, and have it do the busywork.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course the bugs are still there. It still makes dumb mistakes. But then I open a PR, and Cursor Bugbot works its magic, and it finds bugs that I never would have thought of (even if I had written the code myself). Then I plug it back into Claude, it fixes it, and I start to wonder what the hell my job as a programmer even is anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So that’s why, when I read about Steve Yegge’s Gas Town or Geoffrey Huntley’s Ralph loops (or this great overview by Anil Dash), I no longer brush it off as pure speculation or fantasy. I’ve seen what these tools can do, I’ve seen what happens when you lash together some very stupid barnyard animals and they’ve suddenly built the Pyramids, so I’m not surprised when smart engineers say that the solution to bad AI is to just add more AI. This is already working for me today (in my own little baby systems I’ve built), and I don’t have to imagine some sci-fi future to see what’s coming next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The models don’t have to get better, the costs don’t have to come down (heck, they could even double and it’d still be worth it), and we don’t need another breakthrough. The breakthrough is already here; it just needs a bit more tinkering and it will become a giant lurching Frankenstein-meets-Akira-meets-the-Death-Star monster, cranking out working code from all 28 of its sub-agent tentacles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can already hear the cries of protest from other engineers who (like me) are clutching onto their hard-won knowledge. “What about security?” I’ve had agents find security vulnerabilities. “What about performance?” I’ve had agents write benchmarks, run them, and iterate on solutions. “What about accessibility?” Yeah they’re dumb at that – but if you say the magic word “accessibility,” and give them a browser to check their work, then suddenly they’re doing a better job than the median web dev (which isn’t saying much, but hey, it’s an improvement).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And honestly, even if all that doesn’t work, then you could probably just add more agents with different models to fact-check the other models. Inefficient? Certainly. Harming the planet? Maybe. But if it’s cheaper than a developer’s salary, and if it’s “good enough,” then the last half-century of software development suggests it’s bound to happen, regardless of which pearls you clutch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I frankly didn’t want to end up in this future, and I’m hardly dancing on the grave of the old world. But I see a lot of my fellow developers burying their heads in the sand, refusing to acknowledge the truth in front of their eyes, and it breaks my heart because a lot of us are scared, confused, or uncertain, and not enough of us are talking honestly about it. Maybe it’s because the initial tribal battle lines have clouded everybody’s judgment, or maybe it’s because we inhabit different worlds where the technology is either better or worse (I still don’t think LLMs are great at UI for example), but there’s just a lot of patently unhelpful discourse out there, and I’m tired of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To me, the truth is this: between the hucksters selling you a ready-built solution, the doomsayers crying the end of software development, and the holdouts insisting that the entire house of cards is on the verge of collapsing – nobody knows anything. That’s the hardest truth to acknowledge, and maybe it’s why so many of us are scared or lashing out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My advice (and I’ve already said I know nothing) would just be to experiment, tinker, and try to remain curious. It certainly feels to me like software development is unrecognizable from where it was 3 years ago, so I have no idea where it will be 3 years from now. It’s gonna be a bumpy ride for everyone, so just try have some empathy for your fellow passengers in the other tribe.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nolanlawson.com/2026/01/24/ai-tribalism/"/><published>2026-01-25T21:01:37+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46758242</id><title>Canada</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:38.308278+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ef02d1961f6494f9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;On Canada&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've been visiting the US a lot these days: for work, for conferences, and simply to see friends. Commensurately, I've been also thinking more about what Canadian culture is, and what being Canadian means to me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My gratitude towards my nation goes deep. Canada shaped me into person I am today, and I'd go far as to say that Canada raised me; not as much as my mother did, but perhaps more than any other entity. Growing up, our family was poor to the point where there were stretches of weeks where all we ate were frozen dumplings for lunch and cabbage and rice for dinner. But mom did her best to hide our lack from me, and Canada helped her greatly with the conspiracy. Canada gave us a rent-subsidized apartment and five hundred dollars a month to care for me until I turned eighteen. And that would be cause enough for gratitude, but Canada went further in its generosity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Canada taught me how to swim, and how to skate. Here, municipally-run community centres with ice rinks, pools, and programming rooms are standard civic infrastructure, and our neighbourhoods are dotted with them.1 The municipality runs regular classes and programming in the community centres, generally priced at a few hundred dollars for ten-week classes, but low-income families could register their children for a song. Mom ponied up for skates and bathing suits, and I swam in the summers and skated in the winters my entire childhood.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so when in my teens when my friends started to invite me over to their families' summer cottages, I could join them in jumping into lakes with glee. And so when an airbnb my university friends booked over the holidays one year turned out to be unexpectedly close to an outdoor rink, I was able to play in a terribly silly game of pick-up hockey. And so even though my body is clumsy and stupid by nature, there were kinds of physical activity that I had cultivated a decade of muscle memory in, and can make pleasing amounts of improvement on in adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Canada let me read to my heart's content. I'll never forget the wonder and gratitude I felt, the very first time my parents took me to a public Canadian library. Looking around at the shelves, knowing that somehow every book inside was free for me to read and to take home. We didn't have anything like that in China.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With my children's library card I could take out forty books at a time. Forty books! We would make the trip at least once a week, where I would return my previous pile and get a new one — as much as can fit in my backpack, and two of mom's grocery totes. And I spent entire summers among the stacks, because the library had air conditioning and our apartment did not. I gobbled up one book after another in my formative years, which I was only able to do with Canada's generosity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Canada made the holidays magical for me. Mom could not afford much in the way of frivolous things, but I would have a giant bounty of new toys every Christmas anyways courtesy of a local charity. They gave them out in jumbo translucent garbage bags, pink for girls and blue for boys, big enough for me to fit in. I would get sketchbooks and markers and colour pencils, stuffed toys, play-doh, puzzle books, and countless other things. I liked the art supplies best, but I wasn't picky. (From the same charities we would also get two turkeys a year, one for Thanksgiving and one for Christmas, though mom never quite managed to figure out how one was supposed to cook them.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of every school year, Canada would slip a bunch of goodies into the same envelope that my report card came in — free tickets to the CNE and to the science centre2, and a booklet of deeply discounted tickets to other attractions near and far. And so my childhood was also filled with botanical gardens, and the giraffes at the zoo, and even the occasional Blue Jays game. And Canada ensured that memberships to the science centre were not too expensive, so mom was able to splurge on an annual family pass when it became clear how much I adored it, and we would go every rainy weekend until I knew all the exhibits by heart.3&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Canada continues to provide for me in adulthood. I applied for EI when I graduated into the pandemic and appreciated the breathing room that gave me, I'm grateful for my Canadian passport every time I breeze into the US for a visit. I know my mother will be cared for in her golden years, and I won't ever have to worry about her medical bills. Being Canadian gives me slack, enough for me to do meaningful work without having to worry about being underpaid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are many things wrong with Canada. It has a go for bronze mentality, the smartest of us keep going to the US because there is not enough opportunity here, much of its public infrastructure is crumbling and the housing prices are frightful. The nation is very obviously sick.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But in the US, when I step outside the walled gardens of my community, I notice the brittleness underneath the shining streets, the way the wealth is not load-bearing. I notice the medical self-serve kiosks in grocery stores, the necessities behind locked shelves at CVS. Parents there are not given five hundred dollars a month to buy infant formula for their babies, even with a GDP per capita twice ours. To the extent that feeding our infants preclude Canada from investing more in The Next Big Technology, the regret I can muster up about it is half-hearted at best.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I think about the counterfactual me that grew up in a large American city, New York or L.A. instead of Toronto, I see someone who's more stunted than me, in important ways. No skating classes, libraries too far to walk to on a regular basis and more poorly stocked. Student debt. Without generous public incentives, that version of me would only have the life that her own parents can afford to provide for her.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I see someone who is a little more mercenary about money, and somehow even more disembodied than I am. (Would she ever feel at home in her body enough to dance, just for the fun of it?) I see someone less optimistic about the capacity for large institutions and government to do good.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm glad that I grew up in Canada. And I want to stay here, and do my part in helping it recover from its sickness. And yes, some of this is because I feel some amount of obligation towards it. I feel deep gratitude towards every single Canadian who paid their taxes gladly to ensure that not only did I have enough to eat and a warm place to sleep, I would also have opportunities to be delighted by giraffes and taught how to swim. It wouldn't feel right to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if I just say that, I don't think you'd get the right impression. The truth is, I love my country so much. I want to stay because it is my home, and it is a home with good bones and a solid foundation. I want to stay because I think it is good to live in a place that loves its children that much, the way I felt loved by it. I want my taxes to go to a place where the social safety net is generous and the people are easygoing and public skating rinks are treated like a human right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want Canada to have a future, this wonderful nation that makes light of its harsh climate. If you are fortunate, you might not realize how much Canada cares for those who are not. And it feels like a terrible waste, to give up on it and count it out of the game. In any case, I love it too much to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Growing up in various Toronto suburbs, I've never lived more than a thirty minute walk away from one.↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;RIP :(↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I'm minimizing the amount of labour that my mom did throughout the piece, btw. Not every impoverished child got as much out of living in Canada as I did, because some of the programs required additional effort to apply for, and poor parents often do not have the time, effort, or knowledge to take advantage.↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.jenn.site/on-canada/"/><published>2026-01-25T21:07:41+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46758644</id><title>LED lighting undermines visual performance unless supplemented by wider spectra</title><updated>2026-01-25T22:10:37.204481+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="541a12230e7947d4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Abstract&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Life evolved under broad spectrum sunlight, from ultraviolet to infrared (300–2500 nm). This spectrally balanced light sculpted life’s physiology and metabolism. But modern lighting has recently become dominated by restricted spectrum light emitting diodes (350–650 nm LEDs). Absence of longer wavelengths in LEDs and their short wavelength dominance impacts physiology, undermining normal mitochondrial respiration that regulates metabolism, disease and ageing. Mitochondria are light sensitive. The 420–450 nm dominant in LEDs suppresses respiration while deep red/infrared (670–900 nm) increases respiration in aging and some diseases including in blood sugar regulation. Here we supplement LED light with broad spectrum lighting (400–1500 nm+) for 2 weeks and test colour contrast sensitivity. We show significant improvement in this metric that last for 2 months after the supplemental lighting is removed. Mitochondria communicate across the body with systemic impacts following regional light exposure. This likely involves shifting patterns of serum cytokine expression, raising the possibility of wider negative impacts of LEDs on human health particularly, in the elderly or in the clinical environment where individuals are debilitated. Changing the lighting in these environments could be a highly economic route to improved public health.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ambient light impacts on human health. Sunlight, under which life evolved, extends over approximately 300–2500 nm. Older incandescent lighting common until recently has a similar spectral range. But because our visual sensitivity is limited to 400–700 nm we are unaware of infrared light (approximately 700–2500 nm). However, light in the built environment is now driven by light emitting diodes (LEDs), whose restricted spectrum (approximately 350–650 nm) is designed around our visual sensitivity and consequently is economic1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Typical LED lighting produces strong elements in the shorter blue wavelengths (420–450 nm) with a second yellow peak which drops swiftly above 650 nm, with little light above 700 nm1. Short wavelength exposure in animals in the range of 420–450 nm reduces mitochondrial function, which provides the energy for physiological performance in the form of adenosine triphosphate (ATP). This short wavelength light reduces mitochondrial complex activity and ATP production, in a highly conserved manner. Hoh Kam et al. showed a significant decrease in mitochondrial enzymatic activity in fruit flies for complexes I-IV under 420 nm light2. Kaynezhad et al. used broadband near infrared spectroscopy (bNIRS) imaging the mouse retina and reported significant instability of deoxygenated haemoglobin and oxidised cytochrome-c-oxidase after exposure to 420 nm light. This instability remained significant through a 1 h recovery period when the light was withdrawn3. Short wavelength light (420 and 450 nm) also results in increased body weight. Hussaini et al. demonstrated that mice exposed to these wavelengths gaining weight rapidly compared to controls over the course of eight weeks4. Shorter wavelengths in similar ranges are also associated with reduced lifespan. Nash et al. revealed a 50% drop in the median lifespan of fruit flies exposed to unfiltered white LED light relative to those kept in darkness, but only 4% drop if this LED light was passed through a yellow filter, blocking the shorter wavelength light5. This negative influence is likely due to mitochondrial absorption by porphyrin that may increase proinflammatory oxygen singlet production reducing mitochondrial function as proposed by Kaynezhad et al.3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Longer wavelengths (700 nm+) penetrate deeply and those in sunlight can be measured passing through the human body6. These are absent from standard LEDs but present in sunlight and incandescent lighting. Their presence increases mitochondrial performance and ATP production, particularly when challenged by age or disease. Gkotsi et al. demonstrated significantly increased ATP production in the retina, cortex, and thalamus of mice following exposure to 670 nm light7. Calaza et al. revealed a 50% increase in ATP in eight-month-old complement factor H knock out mice that have a mitochondrial deficit and are used as a murine model of macular degeneration8.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increased mitochondrial performance is associated with increased lifespan and enhanced mobility. Begum et al. demonstrated using fruit flies that exposure to 670 nm resulted in a positive divergence of ageing survival rates of 10% at 4 weeks of age and up to nearly 180% by 8 weeks of age. The older animals also displayed an almost doubling of mobility against controls9. Neonicotinoid insecticides specifically target mitochondrial respiration inducing Parkinson like symptoms of immobility resulting in death. Here 670 exposure reversed damaged ATP levels to normal and corrects mobility and lifespan issues10.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increased mitochondrial activity should result in reduced blood sugars and increased oxygen consumption as mitochondria use both in respiration. Powner and Jeffery found both in bumble bees exposed to 670 nm light11. The same authors translated this to humans showing again, reduced blood sugars and increased oxygen consumption in a standard glucose tolerance test following 15 min of 670 nm exposure. Here the spike in blood glucose was reduced significantly by around 27%12.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Changes in physiology produced by longer wavelengths translate to improved function. Shinhmar et al. revealed improved colour contrast sensitivity in humans after 3 min of morning exposure to 670 nm light13. Hence, exposure to different ends of the spectrum that impact differentially on mitochondria can translate into changes in key physiological metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similar changes are found at the population level. Those spending more time in sunlight generally have improved health including reduced incidents of cardiovascular disease and the incidence of cancer. They also have lower rates of type 2 diabetes14,15.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this study we confront the impact of LED lighting on human visual performance by measuring colour contrast detection in an LED illuminated working environment that is then supplemented with incandescent lighting. The hypothesis is that LED lighting suppresses mitochondrial function in the retina and that this can be corrected by introduction of wide spectrum incandescent lights. The results highlight the potential damaging influence of LED lighting on human performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Methods&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Subjects and their environment: The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and approved by University College London research ethics committee (16547/001). It was undertaken in University College London buildings in October to December. In October local daylight hours were approximately 10.37 with 75% cloud cover. In November local daylight hours were approximately 8.45 with 55% cloud cover. In December local daylight hours were approximately 7.5 with 90% cloud cover. Local sunset time in October is approximately 18.30. In November it is approximately 16.15 and in December it is approximately 16.00. Consequently, many subjects would be returning home after sunset in November and December. Subjects worked approximately 8 h a day 5 days a week and travel to and from work via public transport that was illuminated by LED devices. Most subjects did not leave the building in which they worked during the working day in these months. For those that did it was commonly for less than 15 min at lunch time. Within the work environment subjects were free to move around. Here the internal lighting they experienced was consistently LED based. Hence, natural daylight exposure during this latter part of the year was limited. We could not control for weekend exposure, however subjects homes were consistently illuminated with LEDs and because the weather in the UK at this time of year is inclement, their time outside buildings can be expected to be limited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each participant provided written informed consent prior to testing and data generated was anonymised. Subjects (N = 22) were of both sexes and between the ages of 23 and 65 years. Prior to the experiment all subjects were asked to confirm normal corrected visual function and general good systemic health. This was undertaken in a simple interview prior to their inclusion in the study. All were healthy without visual or other health problems. Experimental subjects (N = 11) worked exclusively under LED lighting in the back of the Here East building on the north side, &amp;gt; 50 m from what little light did manage to penetrate the entrance doors when open. The LED lighting delivered an illuminance of 1000 lx at working height, with a correlated colour temperature (CCT) of 4000 K, and a TM-30 average colour fidelity index, Rf, of 91. The infrared light that was introduced was provided by tungsten desk lamps placed around the working space was non-uniform. The visible component of the 60 W tungsten bulbs was small when compared with the 1000 lx of LED. The test subjects were not expected to use these as task lamps. The LED lighting delivered an irradiance of 3.7 W/m2 on the horizontal working plane.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Control subjects (N = 11) worked in similar environments under LED lighting without direct sunlight. The LED lighting delivered an illuminance of 900 lx at working height, with a CCT of 3000 K and a Rf of 85. The colour contrast tests were performed in a darkened room where the only light came from the test itself. There were no requirements restricting other light exposure patterns during the study.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The experimental location: Subjects worked at UCL Here East, a media and innovation complex located in East London (London E15 2GW), originally built as a press and broadcast centre for the London 2012 Olympics and subsequently repurposed as a campus. UCL Here East occupies part of the Broadcast Centre, taking up the ground and first floor of unit B. The footprint of the building is deep, with daylight only able to enter through the glazing at the front of the building. This glazing uses an infrared blocking film, which can be revealed using infrared photography.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Canon 500D digital camera was modified to replace the infrared blocking layer with clear glass that passes infrared wavelengths. This was used in conjunction with filters that block visible and infrared wavelengths to explore the presence and absence of infrared light. Spectral measurements were made with two spectrophotometers (Ocean Optics SR-6XR250-50 and FLAME-NIR) with optic fibre and cosine correctors used to collect the incandescent spectra in the shorter and longer wavelengths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incandescent desk lighting was introduced into the work environment using desk lamps with 60 W clear Edison bulbs (Polaris UK) placed on work benches. All subjects had worked in this LED-lit environment for more than 2 years. Desk lamps with incandescent bulbs were introduced onto the benches where experimental subjects spent the majority of their time. They were given the incandescent lighting for 2 weeks and, while they spend the majority of their time working near these lights, they were free to move around and leave their desks as they wished. The introduced light showed a high degree of reflectance from the work surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Colour contrast testing: All subjects were tested for colour contrast ability using ChromaTest prior to the introduction of incandescent lighting and then again 2 weeks later. This test must be carried out in a darkened room, so a nearby windowless room was set aside for this purpose. The incandescent lighting was then removed and subjects retested at 4 and 6 weeks. Hence, this element of the experiment was a before and after design which avoids between subject variability. However, there was also a separate control group (N = 11) composed of subjects that worked under LED lighting similar to those in the experimental group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChromaTests is a sensitive measure of colour contrast detection of letters presented in a random order against a noisy visual background in either tritan (blue) or protan (red) visual axes13. If subjects correctly identify a letter its contrast is reduced in the next presentation of a letter. Likewise, if they fail to correctly identify the letter, the contrast is increased. This is repeated until thresholds are determined in 5 identical repeated trials. This normally involved around 70–100 separate presentations in total. Subjects were given an initial trial before testing to avoid a learning effect. Initial presentations were at high colour contrast. No learning effects were noted in the study.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Results&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Light assessment in the experimental environment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 1 shows the front exterior of the Here East building using infrared imaging at ground level where experiments were undertaken. The windows are completely infrared reflective due to their blocking film and hence mirror-like. Figure 2 is an infrared image from inside the building looking out through the open doorway. Only infrared light coming through the open door and its reflectance can be seen, not light coming through adjacent windows. Hence, the building is relatively impervious to infrared light.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 3 shows the working environment in Here East in visible light in which the experiment took place. Images in infrared were completely black. The distance between the work environment and the front door was &amp;gt; 50 m with multiple doors between.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The internal lighting throughout Here East was provided by arrays of ceiling mounted standard LED units. Spectral profiles of the lighting within the building are shown in Fig. 4. against incandescent lighting in black and red.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The blue curve shows the spectral profile of the light delivered to the horizontal working plane. As the work environment was deep in the building and lit only with LED lighting, it received no daylight and was devoid of any infrared illumination. The LED units delivered 1000 lx on the horizontal working plane with a correlated colour temperature (CCT) of 4000 K and a TM-30 colour fidelity index of 91. The irradiance of this LED light was 3.6 W/m2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The specific spectra and energy levels were mapped over the workspace at fixed locations. This is shown in Fig. 5a and b. Here there is a plan of the space and measurements made at 9 locations of energy given in W/cm− 2 and lux, which is a metric corrected for the human eye. Also provided are the spectra at each location. Changes in brightness at different locations were largely not detectable by the human eye and were gradual. There were no differences in spectral profiles across the area only their relative intensity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Light assessment was also undertaken at bench level where individual subjects worked. This is shown in Fig. 6. This confirmed the absence of any part of the infrared spectrum in the work environment and how this changed with the addition of the incandescent lamps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this study, responses to lighting were measured in test subjects both before and also after the lighting had been changed. However, there was also an independent control group that comprised individuals under similar LED lighting condition without daylight. A comparison of the lighting conditions in the two groups is shown in Fig. 7. Critically, the LEDs in both groups had very similar profiles with no infrared components. The overall brightness in the control group was slightly less than in the test group, although this was not apparent to the human eye. As in the test group, subjects were free to move around.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Visual responses to shifts in spectral lighting&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exposure to 60 W incandescent luminaires, which have a wider spectrum than LEDs extending into the infra-red1, resulted in significant improvements in visual performance in all experimental subjects across both the protan and tritan visual ranges. Improvements in both tritan and protan were of the order of 25%. Hence, significant improvements were uniform across visual ranges (Fig. 8). This is unlike experiments where specific red/infrared ranges have been used in LED devices, for example via 670 nm, where visual improvements have been biased towards tritan function13.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 8 shows the results of both individual subjects on the left and also changes in the groups on the right. In spite of the universal improvement in visual function, in both tritan and protan range there was considerable variability between subjects. This variability validates the inclusion of a repeated measures design and the use of a sign test in the analysis. In all cases protan thresholds were lower than tritan consistent with previous studies13.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of the 2 week period the incandescent luminaires were removed and the subjects returned to an exclusively LED dominated light working environment. They were then retested at 4 and 6 weeks. In previous experiments where 670 nm alone has been used, rather than the wide spectrum infrared produced by incandescent lighting, visual improvements decline in approximately a week13. However, following incandescent light exposure improvements remain unchanged across both visual domains at both 4 and 6 weeks. Hence, the impact of broad-spectrum incandescent light not only resulted in balanced improvements in colour contrast but also these improvements lasted much longer than previous interventions with restricted red/infrared ranges13.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An independent control group was used in addition to a before and after experimental design. Again, data between individuals was varied on both visual metrics. However, over a 2 week period there were no significant changes in proton or tritan visual thresholds (Fig. 9).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Discussion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We demonstrate that the visual performance of those working under standard LED is significantly improved by exposure to incandescent lighting that has a spectrum similar to daylight with an extensive infrared component. These data are consistent with the hypothesis that LED lighting undermines human visual performance. This result is consistent with laboratory experiments where specific red/infrared wavelength ranges generated by LEDs have been used to improve visual function in animals and humans in a conserved manner13,16,17. But there are three critical differences from these earlier studies. First, we have simply changed environmental lighting in a free moving work environment. Second, we have obtained significant balanced improvements in both the protan and tritan range. Previously, exposure to restricted experimental 670 nm resulted in improvements biased strongly in favour of only tritan function13. Hence, exposure to full spectrum lighting results in a balanced pattern of improvement in visual performance. Third, we have shown that improvements in visual function following incandescent light exposure are sustained for up to 6 weeks, and possibly beyond, whereas benefits from single LED restricted range red light were confined to around 5 days13. These three features change the way in which long wavelength light may be applied to improve human physiology by delivery in normal environments with lasting balance effects. These results are novel and may have public health implications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our study used 22 subjects but was statistically significant using both a before and after metric and also against an independent control group. They are also similar to group sizes in aspects of Shinhmar et al.13 (Figs. 2, 3, 4 and 5). However, future studies would clearly benefit from inclusion of a larger number of subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The evolution of life on earth extends over 4 billion years, and that of humans over approximately 4–5 million years from the last common primate ancestor. This has all taken place under sunlight that has a spectral range of approximately 300–2500 nm+, within which there has been an invariant balance between short and longer wavelengths. Human adoption of fire 1–2 million years ago supplemented sunlight as they moved out of Africa as its spectrum is similar having a large infrared component. Likewise, development of the Edison filament luminaire, common until approximately the year 2000 had a spectrum similar to sunlight. However, around 2010 LED lighting with its highly restricted spectrum (350–650 nm) and energy saving characteristics became common, resulting in a loss of infrared light in the built environment1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The physiology of life forms are adapted to natural environmental light in a highly conserved pattern across species. Light impacts on mitochondrial function, which is a key regulator of metabolism and ageing in animals. When the balance of short and long wavelengths is shifted there are consequences for mitochondria. When shorter wavelength exposure is dominant, as in LED lighting, mitochondrial function declines. Mitochondrial complex proteins are reduced and there is reduced ATP production2,3. With reduced mitochondrial demand for glucose there is increased body weight and disruptions to serum cytokines4. Consequently, consistent with the mitochondrial theory of ageing there is an increased probability of cell/organism ageing and death18. It is suggested that this is partly due to 420–450 nm light, dominant in LEDs, being absorbed by porphyrin and the subsequent production of oxygen singlets driving inflammation3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conversely, exposure to longer wavelengths is associated with increased mitochondrial membrane potential and increased concentration of mitochondrial complex proteins that have declined with ageing and disease. This in turn is associated with elevated ATP, reduced inflammation and extended average lifespan7,9,10,19. The experimental use of longer wavelengths in such situations is commonly referred to as photobiomodulation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The retina has the greatest metabolic rate in the body and a high mitochondrial concentration20. Retinal metabolism declines with age, but this can be partly corrected with long wavelength light across species16,21. In humans a single 3 min 670 nm exposure improves colour vision within 3 h, which is sustained for almost a week13. But what the authors of this study did not appreciate was that this was within a population who worked and lived mainly under LED lighting that may have undermined their baseline measurements. Here, we made no attempt to control light exposures or subject movements as would occur in laboratory-based experiments. Rather, our aim was to introduce wide spectrum long wavelengths into a work environment to improving human performance via mitochondrial manipulation in a translational step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is considerable evidence that introduction of longer wavelengths impact systemically. Durieux et al.22 stated in relation to experiments in C.elegans that “ We find that mitochondrial perturbation in one tissue is perceived and acted upon by the mitochondrial stress response pathway in distal tissue”. In mice there are significant distinct changes serum cytokine expression to exposures of both short and long wavelength light4,23. Similarly, long wavelength exposures to the surface of the human body excluding the eyes significantly reduces blood glucose levels and increases oxygen consumption in humans. This is likely because mitochondrial upregulation will increase carbohydrate demand to support increased ATP production12. Other systemic impacts can be found and are clear in experimentally induced Parkinson’s in primates. Light targeted by implants focusing on the substantia nigra are effective in reducing symptoms24, but so also are those that are directed at distal locations25.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Single 3 min 670 nm exposures remain effective for about 5 days13. But we show that with a wider spectrum they remain effective for 6 weeks, although we did not find the end of the effect. Here it is worth considering potential mechanisms of action which remain subject of debate. Historically, improvements with red light were thought to be due to light absorption by cytochrome C in the respiratory chain26. However, positive effects are found in vitro in the absence of this. Consequently, it has been suggested that longer wavelengths reduce water viscosity around rotary ATP pumps allowing the rotor to increase speed27. This cannot explain the sustained impacts of light exposure as this effect should be relatively transitory as viscosity would increase rapidly following light withdrawal. However, a key feature of long wavelength light absorption is increased respiratory chain protein synthesis. These proteins are in flux throughout the day28 and complex IV is upregulated following red light exposure19. Hence, while red light may initially increase rotor pump speed there rapidly follows an increase in protein synthesis which may establish greater respiratory chain capacity. The life of these proteins could then determine the length of effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only thirteen polypeptides are made in mitochondrial protein synthesis. This probably slows with age and likely contributes to aged mitochondrial decline18. But critically, we do not know the speed of mitochondrial protein synthesis, the life of such proteins or the pace of their decline. We suggest that these may be key events in the length of the effects from light exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LED lighting clearly has the ability to undermine visual performance probably via reduced mitochondrial function. As light induced changes in mitochondrial ability have been shown to have systemic impacts4,15,22,23,25, the effects of LEDs revealed here may be wider than initially anticipated. Given the prevalence of LEDs, this may represent an important issue in public health and clinical environments where changing lighting patterns in appreciation of this point can have significant positive outcomes29.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given our results, it is important to ask what solutions may be found to improve health in terms of lighting in the built environment. Incandescent lights that we reveal here to have significant positive impact over standard LEDs are being phased out universally for reasons of energy efficiency, where focus is only on the visible light produced.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A solution may be found in creating lighting units with multiple longer wavelength LEDs to cover a wider span of the near infrared. However, our attempts here have had limited success. Multiple closely associated spectral peaks do not produce a smooth spectral output as found in incandescent lights and sunlight, which is problematic in improving function and has yet to deliver. This possibly may be overcome using a greater number of spectral peaks with tighter spacing. But this raises a different series of problems regarding cost and increased energy consumption making this solution no better than retention of incandescent sources in terms of environmental sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key to this issue is the question of how much infrared is needed to sustain improved function? Infrared has relatively few absorbers in the built environment and in current studies relatively little has to be added to the environment for effect. However, a viable option is to run an incandescent light at a lower temperature which results in both energy savings and increased life of the unit and also shifts the peak spectral output towards longer wavelengths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If this is done with a halogen bulb, which is a type of incandescent tungsten bulb, the filament lasts for a longer period as evaporated tungsten is redeposited on the filament rather than blackening the bulb glass. Hence, using a halogen bulb at lower voltage is a realistic alternative in terms of health and energy consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Data availability&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The data sets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;References&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ratto, G. E., Videla, F. A. &amp;amp; Martinez Valiviezd, J. H. Artificial light: traditional and new sources, their potential impact on health, and coping strategies: preliminary spectral analysis. Proc. SPIE Conf. 11814. San Diego California. (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Hoh Kam, J., Hogg, C., Fosbury, R., Shinhmar, H. &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Mitochondria are specifically vulnerable to 420nm light in drosophila which undermines their function and is associated with reduced fly mobility. Plos one. Sep 3;16(9):e0257149. (2021). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34478469. PMID: 34478469.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Kaynezhad, P. et al. Near infrared spectroscopy reveals instability in retinal mitochondrial metabolism and haemodynamics with blue light exposure at environmental levels. J.Biophotonics. ;15(4):e202100283. (2022). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35020273/. PMID: 35020273.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Al-Hussaini, H. et al. Impact of short wavelength light exposure on body weight, mobility, anxiety like behaviour and cytokine expression. Sci. Rep. ;15(1):5927. (2025). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39966413/. PMID: 39966413.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Nash, T. R. et al. Daily blue-light exposure shortens lifespan and causes brain neurodegeneration in Drosophila. Aging. Mech. Dis 2019 Oct 17:5:8. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31636947/. PMID: 31636947.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Jeffery, G. et al. Longer wavelengths in sunlight pass through the human body and have a systemic impact which improves vision. Sci. Rep. 2025 July;15(1);24435. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-025-09785-3&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Gkotsi, D. et al. Recharging mitochondrial batteries in old eyes. Near infra-red increases ATP. Exp.Eye Res. 2014 May:122:50 – 3. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24631333/ PMID: 24631333.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Calaza, K. C., Hoh Kam, J., Hogg, C. &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Mitochondrial decline precedes phenotype development in the complement factor H mouse model of retinal degeneration but can be corrected by near infrared light. Neurobiol. Aging. ;36(10):2869-76. (2015). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26149919/ PMID: 26149919.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Begum, R. et al. Near-infrared light increases ATP, extends lifespan and improves mobility in aged Drosophila melanogaster. Biol.Lett. ;11(3):20150073. (2015). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25788488/ PMID: 25788488.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Powner, P. MB, SaltTE, Hogg, C. &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Improving mitochondrial function protects bumblebees from neonicotinoid pesticides. Plos One. 11 (11), e0166531 (2016). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27846310/ PMID: 27846310.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Powner, P. MB &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Systemic glucose levels are modulated by specific wavelengths in the solar light spectrum that shift mitochondrial metabolism. Plos One. 17 (11), e0276937 (2022). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36327250/ PMID: 36327250.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Powner, M. B. &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Light stimulation of mitochondria reduces blood glucose levels. J.Biophotonics. ;17(5):e202300521. (2024). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38378043/. PMID: 38378043.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Shinhmar, H., Hoog, C., Neveu, M. &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Weeklong improved colour contrasts sensitivity after single 670 nm exposures associated with enhanced mitochondrial function. Sci. Rep. ;11(1):22872. (2021). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34819619/. PMID: 34819619.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Weller, R. B. &amp;amp; Sunlight Time for a Rethink? J.Invest. Dermatol. ;144(8):1724–1732. (2024). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38661623/ PMID: 38661623.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Shore-Lorenti, C. et al. Shining the light on Sunshine: a systematic review of the influence of sun exposure on type 2 diabetes mellitus-related outcomes. Clin. Endocrinol. ;81(6):799–811. (2014). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25066830/ PMID: 25066830.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Weinrich, T. W., Coyne, A., Salt, T. E., Hogg, C. &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Improving mitochondrial function significantly reduces metabolic, visual, motor and cognitive decline in aged Drosophila melanogaster. Neurobiol. Aging. 2017 Dec:60:34–43. doi: 10.1016. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28917665/ PMID: 28917665.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sivapathasuntharam, C., Sivaprasad, S., Hogg, C. &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Aging retinal function is improved by near infrared light (670 nm) that is associated with corrected mitochondrial decline. Neurbiol. Aging 2017 Apr:52:66–70. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28129566/ PMID: 28129566.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Lopez-Otin, C., Blasco, M. A., Partridge, L., Serrano, M. &amp;amp; Kroemer, G. The hallmarks of aging. Cell 153 (6), 1194–1217 (2013). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23746838/ PMID: 23746838.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Begum, R., Powner, P. MB, Hudson, N., Hogg, C. &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Treatment with 670 Nm light up regulates cytochrome C oxidase expression and reduces inflammation in an Age-Related macular degeneration model. Plos One. 8 (2), e57828 (2013). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23469078/ PMID: 23469078.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Kocherlakota, S., Hurley, J. B., Shu, D. Y. &amp;amp; Editorial Retinal metabolism in health and disease. Front Ophthalmol (Lausanne). 2024 Jul 17:4:1459318. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39086994/ PMID: 39086994.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Hoh Kam, J. et al. Mitochondrial decline in the ageing old world primate retina: Little evidence for difference between the centre and periphery. Plos One. ;18(5):e0273882. (2023). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37130143/ PMID: 37130143.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Durieux, J., Wolff, S. &amp;amp; Dillin, A. The cell-non-autonomous nature of electron transport chain-mediated longevity. Cell 144 (1), 79–91 (2011). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21215371/ PMID: 21215371.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Shinhmar, H., Hogg, C. &amp;amp; Jeffery, G. Exposure to long wavelength light that improves aged mitochondrial function shifts acute cytokine expression in serum and the retina. Plos One. 18 (7), e0284172 (2023). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37478072/ PMID: 37478072.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Darlot, F. et al. Near-infrared light is neuroprotective in a monkey model of Parkinson disease. Ann. Neurol. ;79(1):59–75. (2016). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26456231/ PMID: 26456231.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Gordon, L. C. et al. Remote photobiomodulation targeted at the abdomen or legs provides effective neuroprotection against parkinsonian MPTP insult. Eur. J. Neurosci. ;57(9):1611–1624. (2023). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36949610/. PMID: 36949610.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Salehpour, F., Mahmoudi, J., Kamari, F., Sadigh-Eteghad, Rasta, S. H. &amp;amp; Hamblin, M. R. Brain Photobiomodulation Therapy: a Narrative Review. Mol. Neurobiol. ;55(8):6601–6636. (2018). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29327206/ PMID: 29327206.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sommer, A. P. Mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase is not the primary acceptor for near infrared light-it is mitochondrial bound water: the principles of low-level light therapy. Ann. Transl. Med. ;7(Suppl 1):S13. (2019). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31032294/. PMID: 31032294.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Weinrich, T. et al. A day in the life of mitochondria reveals shifting workloads. Sci. Rep. ;9(1):13898. (2019). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31554906/ PMID: 31554906.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Neto, R. P. M. et al. Photobiomodulation therapy (red/NIR LEDs) reduced the length of stay in intensive care unit and improved muscle function: A randomized, triple-blind, and sham-controlled trial. J.Biophotonics. ;17(5):e202300501. (2024). https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/38262071/ PMID: 38262071.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We thank Chris Hogg for assistance with Chromatest, and Mandana Khanie for use of the Ocean Optics spectrophotometers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Funding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This research did not receive funding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Author information&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Authors and Affiliations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Contributions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GJ and EB designed the experiments undertook all the experimental work and wrote the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Corresponding author&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Ethics declarations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Competing interests&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The authors declare no competing interests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Additional information&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Publisher’s note&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Rights and permissions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;About this article&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Cite this article&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Barrett, E.M., Jeffery, G. LED lighting (350-650nm) undermines human visual performance unless supplemented by wider spectra (400-1500nm+) like daylight. Sci Rep 16, 3061 (2026). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-026-35389-6&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Received:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Accepted:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Published:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Version of record:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;DOI: https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-026-35389-6&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-026-35389-6"/><published>2026-01-25T21:44:10+00:00</published></entry></feed>