<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:36.339644+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46367224</id><title>Fabrice Bellard Releases MicroQuickJS</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:44.911973+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3b74d0de090e4684"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We read every piece of feedback, and take your input very seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To see all available qualifiers, see our documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There was an error while loading. Please reload this page.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/bellard/mquickjs/blob/main/README.md"/><published>2025-12-23T17:33:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46378554</id><title>Show HN: Minimalist editor that lives in browser, stores everything in the URL</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:44.414937+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2a34105e063698ad"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A minimalist text editor that lives entirely in your browser and stores everything in the URL hash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📝 It's a textarea! Actually not.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🗜️ Compression magic - Your text gets compressed with deflate because we're fancy like that&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🔗 URL storage - Share your notes by copying a 500-character URL. Your friends will love it!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🌓 Dark mode - Respects your poor eyes and your color scheme preference&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;💾 Auto-save - Debounced to 500ms because we're not savages&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📱 Mobile friendly - Type your manifesto on the go&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🎯 No backend - Zero servers were harmed in the making of this app&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Open textarea.my&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Type stuff&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Marvel at the URL getting longer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Try to share it&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;...&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Profit&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Start your document with &lt;code&gt;# Title&lt;/code&gt;to set a custom page title&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Your data lives in localStorage AND the URL. Double the fun!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Feeling fancy? Add a &lt;code&gt;style&lt;/code&gt;attribute to the&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;article&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;tag via DevTools. It'll be saved in the URL too!&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Made with ❤️ and JavaScript&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/antonmedv/textarea"/><published>2025-12-24T19:42:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46379145</id><title>Show HN: Lamp Carousel – DIY kinetic sculpture powered by lamp heat (2024)</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:44.120950+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="37d2569f58d80d5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Can Spinners&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I came up with these little spinning doodads a few years ago around Christmas, and I haven't seen anything like them online, so I'm writing about them here as they are quite fun to make. I've just been calling these things "can spinners" (ChatGPT suggested "twirluminum").&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They remind me a bit of candle carousels that I would see at my grandparents' house, but in this case they are cut from recycled aluminum soda cans and spin on sharpened tips of wire from the heat rising off the lamp.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I got my family to create their own this year and it was interesting to see the variety of designs they came up with (see the gallery below).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Construction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the spinners shown above are made from sides and bottoms of recycled soda cans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My process usually goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sharpen pivot wire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;The spinners need a fine pivot point to sit on with low friction. I used some steel craft wire that was laying around and sharpened it on a bench grinder. Paper clips and sandpaper would probably work too.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cut out blank&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;I've made these from the sides and bottoms of cans. Can sidewalls are much easier to cut and bend, so I'd recommend starting with that. Also be careful with the sharp scraps. I've been jabbed a few times making these.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create the central dimple&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;I usually just use a hard, blunt object like a ballpoint pen or pliers to push a dimple into the aluminum without crushing it. Can bottoms are made from thicker aluminum, so I had to gently tap on the back of the pen with a hammer to make the dimple. It's very easy to accidentally pierce the aluminum so be careful!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cut out blades and bend into shape.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Small precision scissors work best to avoid distorting the aluminum and for making fine cuts.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trim and balance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Balance the spinner on the pivot wire in your hand. Usually they're lopsided or fall off of their pivot initially, so trim small amounts of material from the outside until they spin well.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attach pivot wire to lamp&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Usually I'll just wrap the wire around the lampshade support (apparently this is called a "harp") or sandwich it under the lampshade nut for easy removal.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incandescent bulbs work the best, but even LED bulbs are enough to get the spinners moving after warming up for a few minutes. After a few weeks of spinning, I've noticed the spinners made of thinner sidewall aluminum have very small pinholes from the pivot wire wearing through, but they haven't stopped spinning! The spinners made from can bottoms haven't had this problem yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Gallery&lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://evan.widloski.com/posts/spinners/"/><published>2025-12-24T20:56:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46379173</id><title>Keystone (YC S25) is hiring engineer #1 to automate coding</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:43.709963+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="233a92f07e6fe468"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your team's on-call AI engineer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Keystone&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're building AI-native error monitoring that automatically investigates production issues and generates code fixes. Think Sentry, but built from the ground up for a world where AI can actually understand your codebase, trace through logs, and tell you exactly what broke and how to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're starting here and expanding until we're the default tool for building product, period. Our mission is to free engineers from the drudgery of digging through logs, setting up systems, and debugging- so they can focus on understanding users and designing great products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're in-person in SoMa, San Francisco. We raised a $5.2M seed from True Ventures, Twenty Two Ventures, Pear VC, and Ritual Capital- plus the founders of YC, Dropbox, Supabase, Eight Sleep, Graphite, Resend, RocketMoney, and more. Early design partners include teams at Perplexity and Lovable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About the Role&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You'd be the first engineering hire, working directly with me (the founder) to build the core product. You'll have more ownership and influence over the product, culture, and technical direction than you'd get almost anywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example projects:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might be a great fit if you:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stack: TypeScript, React (Next.js), Python, Postgres, Redis, AWS&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comp &amp;amp; benefits: Top-of-market salary + significant equity, full health/dental/vision, all meals covered, equipment budget&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To apply: submit an application here on workatastartup.com or email founders [at] withkeystone [dot] com with “Keystone Founding Engineer” in the subject line. I will reply to all such emails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there appears to be a fit, we'll reach to schedule 2-3 short technicals. After, we'll schedule an onsite in our office, where you'll work on a small project, discuss ideas, and get a sense for our in-person culture.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/keystone/jobs/J3t9XeM-founding-engineer"/><published>2025-12-24T21:01:05+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46380075</id><title>Phoenix: A modern X server written from scratch in Zig</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:43.191940+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d47bdcdd7826ad85"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Phoenix&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Phoenix is a new X server, written from scratch in Zig (not a fork of Xorg server). This X server is designed to be a modern alternative to the Xorg server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Current state&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Phoenix is not ready to be used yet. At the moment it can render simple applications that do GLX, EGL or Vulkan graphics (fully hardware accelerated) nested in an existing X server. Running Phoenix nested will be the only supported mode until Phoenix has progressed more and can run real-world applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Goals&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Simplicity&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be a simpler X server than the Xorg server by only supporting a subset of the X11 protocol, the features that are needed by relatively modern applications (applications written/updated in the last ~20 years).&lt;lb/&gt; This includes all software that you use, even old gtk2 applications.&lt;lb/&gt; Only relatively modern hardware (made/updated in the last ~15-20 years) which support linux drm and mesa gbm will be supported, and no server driver interface like the Xorg server. Just like how Wayland compositors work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Security&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be safer than the Xorg server by parsing protocol messages automatically. As it's written in Zig, it also automatically catches illegal behaviors (such as index out of array bounds) when building with the &lt;code&gt;ReleaseSafe&lt;/code&gt; option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applications will be isolated from each other by default and can only interact with other applications either through a GUI prompt asking for permission,&lt;lb/&gt; such as with screen recorders, where it will only be allowed to record the window specified or by explicitly giving the application permission before launched (such as a window manager or external compositor).&lt;lb/&gt; This will not break existing clients as clients wont receive errors when they try to access more than they need, they will instead receive dummy data.&lt;lb/&gt; Applications that rely on global hotkeys should work, as long as a modifier key is pressed (keys such as ctrl, shift, alt and super).&lt;lb/&gt; If an application needs global hotkeys without pressing a modifier key then it needs to be given permissions to do so (perhaps by adding a command to run a program with more X11 permissions).&lt;lb/&gt; There will be an option to disable this to make the X server behave like the Xorg server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Improvements for modern technology&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support modern hardware better than the Xorg server, such as proper support for multiple monitors (different refresh rates, VRR - not a single framebuffer for the whole collection of displays) and technology like HDR.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Improved graphics handling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No tearing by default and a built-in compositor. The compositor will get disabled if the user runs an external compositor (client application), such as picom or if the client runs a fullscreen application.&lt;lb/&gt; The goal is to also have lower vsync/compositor latency than the Xorg server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;New standards&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New standards will be developed and documented, such as per-monitor DPI as randr properties. Applications can use this property to scale their content to the specified DPI for the monitor they are on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Extending the X11 protocol&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there is a need for new features (such as HDR) then the X11 protocol will be extended.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Wayland compatibility&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some applications might only run on Wayland in the future. Such applications should be supported by either Phoenix supporting Wayland natively or by running an external application that works as a bridge between Wayland and X11 (such as 12to11).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Nested display server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being able to run Phoenix nested under X11 or Wayland with hardware acceleration. This is not only useful for debugging Phoenix but also for developers who want to test their window manager or compositor without restarting the display server they are running.&lt;lb/&gt; Being able to run Phoenix under Wayland as an alternative Xwayland server would be a good option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Non-goals&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Replacing the Xorg server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Xorg server will always support more features of the X11 protocol and wider range of hardware (especially older ones).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Multiple screens&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiple displays (monitors) are going to be supported but not X11 screens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Exclusive access&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GrabServer has no effect in Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Endian-swapped client/server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This can be reconsidered if there is a reason.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Indirect (remote) GLX.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is very complex as there are a lot of functions that would need to be implemented. These days remote streaming options are more efficient. Alternatively a proxy for glx could be implemented that does remote rendering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Differences between the X11 protocol and Phoenix&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Core protocol&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Several parts of the X11 protocol (core) are mandatory to be implemented by an X server, such as many font related operations.&lt;lb/&gt; However these are not going to be implemented in Phoenix, except for the simple ones that applications actually use (such as font operations used for cursors).&lt;lb/&gt; This will not affect applications that users actually use, even if they use old gtk2 applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Strings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strings are in ISO Latin-1 encoding in the X11 protocol unless specified otherwise, however in Phoenix all strings are UTF-8 unless the protocol states that it's not an ISO Latin-1 string.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Installing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;zig build -Doptimize=ReleaseSafe
sudo zig build install -p /usr/local -Doptimize=ReleaseSafe
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Uninstalling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zig does currently not support the uninstall command so you have to remove files manually:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo rm /usr/local/bin/phoenix
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building (for development)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;zig build&lt;/code&gt;, which builds Phoenix in debug mode. The compiled binary will be available at &lt;code&gt;./zig-out/bin/phoenix&lt;/code&gt;. You can alternatively build and run with one command: &lt;code&gt;zig build run&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Generate x11 protocol documentation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;zig build -Dgenerate-docs=true&lt;/code&gt;. This will generate &lt;code&gt;.txt&lt;/code&gt; files in &lt;code&gt;./zig-out/protocol/&lt;/code&gt;. This generates x11 protocol documentation in the style of the official protocol documentation. The documentation is automatically generated from the protocol struct code.
Note that the generated documentation feature is a work-in-progress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Dependencies&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Zig 0.14.1&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;x11 (&lt;code&gt;xcb&lt;/code&gt;) - for nested mode under X11, when building Phoenix with&lt;code&gt;-Dbackends=x11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;wayland (&lt;code&gt;wayland-client&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;wayland-egl&lt;/code&gt;) - for nested mode under Wayland, when building Phoenix with&lt;code&gt;-Dbackends=wayland&lt;/code&gt;(not currently supported)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;drm (&lt;code&gt;libdrm&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;gbm&lt;/code&gt;) - for running Phoenix as a standalone X11 server, when building Phoenix with&lt;code&gt;-Dbackends=drm&lt;/code&gt;(not currently supported)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OpenGL (&lt;code&gt;libglvnd&lt;/code&gt;which provides both&lt;code&gt;gl&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;egl&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;FAQ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Isn't it easier to write a Wayland compositor?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite popular belief, writing a simple X server that works in practice for a wide range of applications is easier to do than it is to write a Wayland compositor (+ related software).&lt;lb/&gt; Not many people have attempted to write an X server from scratch or have proper understanding of the protocol, but if you do you can see that it's quite simple.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://git.dec05eba.com/phoenix/about/"/><published>2025-12-24T22:43:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46380168</id><title>Tell HN: Merry Christmas</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:42.216134+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d2d13d459cf20bd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Different cultures celebrate Christmas at different days and time zones are a thing. But it's Christmas here, so:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Merry Christmas to everyone. I hope you get some rest and can spend time with people who are dear to you and get to focus on what's important rather than getting lost in stressing about everything having to be perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Also much love to everyone who cannot spend their Christmas with dear people.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To make sure this post meets the relevancy criteria, here is a Wikipedia article about some Christmas (more precisely advent) tradition which I personally really like: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christmas_market&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46380168"/><published>2025-12-24T22:56:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46380758</id><title>Who Watches the Waymos? I do [video]</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:41.355024+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7055905545553646"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Press Copyright Contact us Creators Advertise Developers Terms Privacy Policy &amp;amp; Safety How YouTube works Test new features NFL Sunday Ticket © 2025 Google LLC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oYU2hAbx_Fc"/><published>2025-12-25T00:10:12+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46383552</id><title>We invited a man into our home at Christmas and he stayed with us for 45 years</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:41.226866+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="76a191dce9279cf8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We invited a man into our home at Christmas and he stayed with us for 45 years&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Published&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Christmas is often regarded as a time for goodwill, but one young UK couple's act of kindness 50 years ago changed their lives forever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On 23 December 1975, Rob Parsons and his wife Dianne were preparing for Christmas at their Cardiff home when they heard a knock at the door.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On their doorstep stood a man with a bin bag containing his possessions in his right hand and a frozen chicken in his left.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rob studied the man's face and vaguely remembered him as Ronnie Lockwood, someone he would occasionally see at Sunday School as a boy and who he was told to be kind to as he was a "bit different".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I said 'Ronnie, what's with the chicken?' He said 'somebody gave it to me for Christmas'. And then I said two words that changed all of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"And I'm not exactly sure why I said them. I said come in."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aged just 27 and 26 years old at the time, the couple felt compelled to take Ronnie, who was autistic, under their wing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They cooked his chicken, let him bathe and agreed to let him stay for Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What began as an act of compassion turned into an unique companionship of love and compromise that lasted 45 years, until the day Ronnie died.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rob, now 77, and Dianne, now 76, had only been married for four years when they welcomed Ronnie into their home.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ronnie was then almost 30 and had been without a home from the age of 15, living in and around Cardiff and moving from job to job - Rob would sometimes see him at a youth club he ran.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make him feel as welcome as possible, they asked their family to bring him a gift for Christmas, anything from a pair of socks to some "smellies".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I can remember him now. He was sat at the Christmas table and he had these presents and he cried because he'd never known that sort of feeling of love, you know," said Dianne.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It was incredible, really, to watch."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pair planned to let him stay until the day after Christmas, but when the day came, they couldn't bring themselves to cast Ronnie out and sought advice from the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The homeless centre told them Ronnie needed an address to get a job, Rob said, but "to get an address, you need a job".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"That's the Catch 22 that loads of homeless people are in."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Put in a care home when he was just eight years old, Ronnie disappeared from Cardiff aged 11, said Rob, and it was only when he was researching for his book, A Knock on the Door, did he discover what happened to him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He had been sent 200 miles away to a school which was referred to in a report as a "school for subnormal boys" and he lived there for five years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"He didn't have any friends there. He had no social worker that knew him. He had no teachers that knew him."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rob said Ronnie would often ask "have I done a bad thing?" something which they believe he picked up from his time at the school.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"He was always worried he had offended you, or done something wrong."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aged 15, Ronnie was sent back to Cardiff "to nothing" they said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The couple said Ronnie was a bit awkward to begin with as he would struggle to make any eye contact and conversation was kept to a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"But then we got to know him and, in truth, we got to love him," they said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They helped Ronnie get a job as a waste collector and took him to buy new clothes after finding out he wore the same clothes he was given as a teenager at the school.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We didn't have kids of our own, it was like dressing your kids for school, we were proud parents," said Rob.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"As we came out of the shop, she [Dianne] said to me: 'He's got a job as a dustman, we've dressed him up as though he's the front man of the Dorchester Hotel'," Rob laughed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rob, who was a lawyer, would get up an extra hour early to drop Ronnie to work before going to work himself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When he would get home, Rob said Ronnie would often be sitting there, just smiling, and one night he asked: "Ronnie, what's amusing you so much?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ronnie replied: "Rob, when you take me to work in the mornings, the other men say 'who is that who brings you to work in that car?' And I say 'oh that's my solicitor'.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We don't think he was proud of being taken to work by a lawyer, but we think maybe he never had somebody take him on his first day of school," said Rob.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"And now he's almost 30... at last somebody is at the gate."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ronnie had many rituals they became accustomed to, including emptying the dishwasher each morning, to which Rob would act surprised to avoid Ronnie's disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's hard to look surprised when you get the same question on Tuesday that you had on Monday, but that was Ronnie.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We did that for 45 years," he laughed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"He obviously struggled to read and write, but he would buy the South Wales Echo every day," Dianne added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ronnie would buy them the same Marks and Spencer gift cards every Christmas but each year he held the same excitement for their reaction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ronnie spent a lot of his spare time at their local church, gathering donations for the homeless and setting up for services, "meticulously" lining out the chairs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dianne recalled one day he came home with a different pair of shoes on, and she asked: "Ronnie, where are your shoes."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He told her a homeless man needed them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"That's the type of person he was. He was amazing," they said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of their lowest times was when Dianne was ill with ME, also known as chronic fatigue syndrome, external, as she recalled there being days where she couldn't get out of bed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I had a little three-year-old daughter, Rob was away working," said Dianne.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But she said Ronnie was "remarkable" and came into his own, making milk bottles for their son Lloyd, helping out around the home and playing with their daughter Katie.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While they admitted the dynamic had its difficulties, including battling Ronnie's gambling addiction for 20 years, they couldn't imagine their lives without him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's not something I would recommend as a strategy," said Rob, "but Ronnie enriched our lives in many ways".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"He had a great heart Ronnie. He was kind, he was frustrating," said Dianne.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Sometimes I was his mother, sometimes I was his social worker and sometimes I was his carer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Somebody said to them [their children] one day, 'how did you cope with Ronnie when your friends came to the house' and they said 'well, we don't think about it really, it's just Ronnie'."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rob added: "Our kids had never ever known life without Ronnie. He was there before they came and he was there when they were gone, with children of their own."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only once did the couple consider supporting Ronnie to live independently, a few years after he moved in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As their two children were growing older and space felt limited in their one-bathroom home, they approached Ronnie's room to suggest him getting a flat down the road from them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But as they entered, he repeated that familiar question: "Have I done a bad thing?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rob said Dianne hushed him out of the room, burst into tears and said "I can't do it."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few nights later, Ronnie entered their room and asked: "We three are firm friends, aren't we?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I said 'yes Ronnie, we three are firm friends'," said Rob.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"And we will be together forever won't we?" he asked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"And there was a moment's pause, probably too long, I looked across to Di and I said 'yes Ronnie, we will be together forever'.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"And we were."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ronnie died in 2020 at the age of 75 after suffering a stroke and the couple say they miss him terribly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only 50 people were allowed to go to his funeral due to Covid but "tickets were hotter than a Coldplay concert" Rob joked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They received at least 100 sympathy cards, from "Oxford University professors, to politicians and the unemployed".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After his death, a new Â£1.6m wellbeing centre attached to Glenwood Church in Cardiff was named Lockwood House, after Ronnie.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the old building and the new building didn't quite match, and they needed extra funding to finish the renovation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"But they needn't have worried," said Rob.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Almost to the penny, it was the exact amount Ronnie had left in his will.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"In the end the homeless man put the roof over all of our heads."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Isn't that amazing, I just think it's all meant to be," said Dianne.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"People say to us, how did it happen - 45 years - but the honest truth is, in some ways, it happened a day at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Ronnie brought a richness into our lives."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional reporting by Greg Davies&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More top stories&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Published2 days ago&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Published2 days ago&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Published1 day ago&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/cdxwllqz1l0o"/><published>2025-12-25T10:35:34+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46384167</id><title>Python 3.15’s interpreter for Windows x86-64 should hopefully be 15% faster</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:41.076759+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ae609111fe37a5d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;24 December 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some time ago I posted an apology piece for Python’s tail calling results. I apologized for communicating performance results without noticing a compiler bug had occured.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can proudly say today that I am partially retracting that apology, but only for two platforms—macOS AArch64 (XCode Clang) and Windows x86-64 (MSVC).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In our own experiments, the tail calling interpreter for CPython was found to beat the computed goto interpreter by 5% on pyperformance on AArch64 macOS using XCode Clang, and roughly 15% on pyperformance on Windows on an experimental internal version of MSVC. The Windows build is against a switch-case interpreter, but this in theory shouldn’t matter too much, more on that in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is of course, a hopefully accurate result. I tried to be more diligent here, but I am of course not infallible. However, I have found that sharing early and making a fool of myself often works well, as it has led to people catching bugs in my code, so I shall continue doing so :).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also this assumes the change doesn’t get reverted later in Python 3.15’s development cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just a recap. There are two popular current ways of writing C-based interpreters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Switch-cases:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;switch (opcode) {
    case INST_1: ...
    case INST_2: ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where we just switch-case to the correct instruction handler.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the other popular way is a GCC/Clang extension called labels-as-values/computed gotos.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;goto *dispatch_table[opcode];
INST_1: ...
INST_2: ...
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which is basically the same idea, but to instead jump to the address of the next label. Traditionally, the key optimization here is that it needs only one jump to go to the next instruction, while in the switch-case interpreter, a naiive compiler would need two jumps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With modern compilers however, the benefits of the computed gotos is a lot less, mainly because modern compilers have gotten better and modern hardware has also gotten better. In Nelson Elhage’s excellent investigation on the next kind of interpreter, the speedup of computed gotos over switch case on modern Clang was only in the low single digits on pyperformance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A 3rd way that was suggested decades ago, but not really entirely feasible is call/tail-call threaded interpreters. In this scheme, each bytecode handler is its own function, and we tail-call from one handler to the next in the instruction stream:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;return dispatch_table[opcode];

PyObject *INST_1(...) {

}

PyObject *INST_2(...) {
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This wasn’t too feasible in C for one main reason—tail call optimization was merely an optimization. It’s something the C compiler might do, or might not do. This means if you’re unlucky and the C compiler chooses not to perform the tail call, your interpreter might stack overflow!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some time ago, Clang introduced &lt;code&gt;__attribute__((musttail))&lt;/code&gt;, which allowed
for mandating that a call must be tail-called. Otherwise, the compilation
will fail. To my knowledge, the first time this was popularized for use
in a mainstream interpreter was in
Josh Haberman’s Protobuf blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later on, Haoran Xu noticed that the GHC calling convention combined with tail calls produced efficient code. They used this for their baseline JIT in a paper and termed the technique Copy-and-Patch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After using a fixed XCode Clang, our performance numbers on CPython 3.14/3.15 suggest that the tail calling interpreter does provide a modest speedup over computed gotos. Around the 5% geomean range on pyperformance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To my understanding, &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt; already ships Python 3.14 on macOS with tail calling,
which might be responsible for some of the speedups you see on there.
We’re planning to ship the official 3.15 macOS binaries on &lt;code&gt;python.org&lt;/code&gt; with
tail calling as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, you’re not here for that. The title of this blog post is clearly about MSVC Windows x86-64. So what about that?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[!CAUTION] The features for MSVC discussed below are to my knowledge, experimental. They are not guaranteed to always be around unless the MSVC team decide to keep them. Use at your own risk!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are the preliminary pyperformance results for CPython on MSVC with tail-calling vs switch-case. Any number above 1.00x is a speedup (e.g. &lt;code&gt;1.01x == 1% speedup&lt;/code&gt;), anything below 1.00x is a slowdown.
The speedup is a geomtric mean of around 15-16%, with a
range of ~60% slowdown (one or two outliers) to 78% speedup.
However, the key thing is that the vast majority of benchmaarks sped up!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chart credits to Michael Droettboom&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[!WARNING] These results are on an experimental internal MSVC compiler, public results below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To verify this and make sure I wasn’t wrong yet again, I checked the results on my machine with Visual Studio 2026. These are the results from this issue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Mean +- std dev: [spectralnorm_tc_no] 146 ms +- 1 ms -&amp;gt; [spectralnorm_tc] 98.3 ms +- 1.1 ms: 1.48x faster
Mean +- std dev: [nbody_tc_no] 145 ms +- 2 ms -&amp;gt; [nbody_tc] 107 ms +- 2 ms: 1.35x faster
Mean +- std dev: [bm_django_template_tc_no] 26.9 ms +- 0.5 ms -&amp;gt; [bm_django_template_tc] 22.8 ms +- 0.4 ms: 1.18x faster
Mean +- std dev: [xdsl_tc_no] 64.2 ms +- 1.6 ms -&amp;gt; [xdsl_tc] 56.1 ms +- 1.5 ms: 1.14x faster
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So yeah, the speedups are real! For a large-ish library like xDSL, we see a 14% speedup, while for smaller microbenchmarks like nbody and spectralnorm, the speedups are greater.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Chris Eibl and Brandt Bucher, we managed to get the PR for this on MSVC over the finish line. I also want to sincerely thank the MSVC team. I can’t say this enough: they have been a joy to work with and I’m very impressed by what they’ve done, and I want to congratulate them on releasing Visual Studio 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is now listed in the What’s New for 3.15 notes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Builds using Visual Studio 2026 (MSVC 18) may now use the new tail-calling interpreter. Results on an early experimental MSVC compiler reported roughly 15% speedup on the geometric mean of pyperformance on Windows x86-64 over the switch-case interpreter. We have observed speedups ranging from 15% for large pure-Python libraries to 40% for long-running small pure-Python scripts on Windows. (Contributed by Chris Eibl, Ken Jin, and Brandt Bucher in gh-143068. Special thanks to the MSVC team including Hulon Jenkins.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the documentation for [[msvc::musttail]].&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I used to believe the the tail calling interpreters get their speedup from better register use. While I still believe that now, I suspect that is not the main reason for speedups in CPython.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My main guess now is that tail calling resets compiler heuristics to sane levels, so that compilers can do their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let me show an example, at the time of writing, CPython 3.15’s interpreter loop is around 12k lines of C code. That’s 12k lines in a single function for the switch-case and computed goto interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This has caused many issues for compilers in the past, too many to list in fact. I have a EuroPython 2025 talk about this. In short, this overly large function breaks a lot of compiler heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the most beneficial optimisations is inlining. In the past, we’ve found that compilers sometimes straight up refuse to inline even the simplest of functions in that 12k loc eval loop. I want to stress that this is not the fault of the compiler. It’s actually doing the correct thing—you usually don’t want to increase the code size of something already super large. Unfortunately, this does’t bode well for our interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might say just write the interpreter in assembly! However, the whole point of this exercise is to not do that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ok enough talk, let’s take a look at the code now. Taking a real example, we examine &lt;code&gt;BINARY_OP_ADD_INT&lt;/code&gt; which adds two Python integers.
Cleaning up the code so it’s readable, things look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;TARGET(BINARY_OP_ADD_INT) {
    // Increment the instruction pointer.
    _Py_CODEUNIT* const this_instr = next_instr;
    frame-&amp;gt;instr_ptr = next_instr;
    next_instr += 6;
    _PyStackRef right = stack_pointer[-1];

    // Check that LHS is an int.
    PyObject *value_o = PyStackRef_AsPyObjectBorrow(left);
    if (!_PyLong_CheckExactAndCompact(value_o)) {
        JUMP_TO_PREDICTED(BINARY_OP);
    }

    // Check that RHS is an int.
    // ... (same code as above for LHS)

    // Add them together.
    PyObject *left_o = PyStackRef_AsPyObjectBorrow(left);
    PyObject *right_o = PyStackRef_AsPyObjectBorrow(right);
    res = _PyCompactLong_Add((PyLongObject *)left_o, (PyLongObject *)right_o);

    // If the addition fails, fall back to the generic instruction.
    if (PyStackRef_IsNull(res)) {
        JUMP_TO_PREDICTED(BINARY_OP);
    }

    // Close the references.
    PyStackRef_CLOSE_SPECIALIZED(left, _PyLong_ExactDealloc);
    PyStackRef_CLOSE_SPECIALIZED(right, _PyLong_ExactDealloc);

    // Write to the stack, and dispatch.
    stack_pointer[-2] = res;
    stack_pointer += -1;
    DISPATCH();
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seems simple enough, let’s take a look at the assembly for switch-case on VS 2026. Note again, this is a non-PGO build for easy source information, PGO generally makes some of these problems go away, but not all of them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;                if (!_PyLong_CheckExactAndCompact(value_o)) {
00007FFC4DE24DCE  mov         rcx,rbx  
00007FFC4DE24DD1  mov         qword ptr [rsp+58h],rax  
00007FFC4DE24DD6  call        _PyLong_CheckExactAndCompact (07FFC4DE227F0h)  
00007FFC4DE24DDB  test        eax,eax  
00007FFC4DE24DDD  je          _PyEval_EvalFrameDefault+10EFh (07FFC4DE258FFh)
...
                res = _PyCompactLong_Add((PyLongObject *)left_o, (PyLongObject *)right_o);
00007FFC4DE24DFF  mov         rdx,rbx  
00007FFC4DE24E02  mov         rcx,r15  
00007FFC4DE24E05  call        _PyCompactLong_Add (07FFC4DD34150h)  
00007FFC4DE24E0A  mov         rbx,rax  
...
                PyStackRef_CLOSE_SPECIALIZED(value, _PyLong_ExactDealloc);
00007FFC4DE24E17  lea         rdx,[_PyLong_ExactDealloc (07FFC4DD33BD0h)]  
00007FFC4DE24E1E  mov         rcx,rsi  
00007FFC4DE24E21  call        PyStackRef_CLOSE_SPECIALIZED (07FFC4DE222A0h) 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Huh… all our functions were not inlined. Surely that must’ve mean they were too big or something right? Let’s look at &lt;code&gt;PyStackReF_CLOSE_SPECIALIZED&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;static inline void
PyStackRef_CLOSE_SPECIALIZED(_PyStackRef ref, destructor destruct)
{
    assert(!PyStackRef_IsNull(ref));
    if (PyStackRef_RefcountOnObject(ref)) {
        Py_DECREF_MORTAL_SPECIALIZED(BITS_TO_PTR(ref), destruct);
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That looks … inlineable?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s how &lt;code&gt;BINARY_OP_ADD_INT&lt;/code&gt; looks with tail calling on VS 2026 (again,
no PGO):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;                if (!_PyLong_CheckExactAndCompact(left_o)) {
00007FFC67164785  cmp         qword ptr [rax+8],rdx  
00007FFC67164789  jne         _TAIL_CALL_BINARY_OP_ADD_INT@@_A+149h (07FFC67164879h)  
00007FFC6716478F  mov         r9,qword ptr [rax+10h]  
00007FFC67164793  cmp         r9,10h  
00007FFC67164797  jae         _TAIL_CALL_BINARY_OP_ADD_INT@@_A+149h (07FFC67164879h) 
...
                res = _PyCompactLong_Add((PyLongObject *)left_o, (PyLongObject *)right_o);
00007FFC6716479D  mov         eax,dword ptr [rax+18h]  
00007FFC671647A0  and         r9d,3  
00007FFC671647A4  and         r8d,3  
00007FFC671647A8  mov         edx,1  
00007FFC671647AD  sub         rdx,r9  
00007FFC671647B0  mov         ecx,1  
00007FFC671647B5  imul        rdx,rax  
00007FFC671647B9  mov         eax,dword ptr [rbx+18h]  
00007FFC671647BC  sub         rcx,r8  
00007FFC671647BF  imul        rcx,rax  
00007FFC671647C3  add         rcx,rdx  
00007FFC671647C6  call        medium_from_stwodigits (07FFC6706E9E0h)  
00007FFC671647CB  mov         rbx,rax  
...
                PyStackRef_CLOSE_SPECIALIZED(value, _PyLong_ExactDealloc);
00007FFC671647EB  test        bpl,1  
00007FFC671647EF  jne         _TAIL_CALL_BINARY_OP_ADD_INT@@_A+0ECh (07FFC6716481Ch)  
00007FFC671647F1  add         dword ptr [rbp],0FFFFFFFFh  
00007FFC671647F5  jne         _TAIL_CALL_BINARY_OP_ADD_INT@@_A+0ECh (07FFC6716481Ch)  
00007FFC671647F7  mov         rax,qword ptr [_PyRuntime+25F8h (07FFC675C45F8h)]  
00007FFC671647FE  test        rax,rax  
00007FFC67164801  je          _TAIL_CALL_BINARY_OP_ADD_INT@@_A+0E4h (07FFC67164814h)  
00007FFC67164803  mov         r8,qword ptr [_PyRuntime+2600h (07FFC675C4600h)]  
00007FFC6716480A  mov         edx,1  
00007FFC6716480F  mov         rcx,rbp  
00007FFC67164812  call        rax  
00007FFC67164814  mov         rcx,rbp  
00007FFC67164817  call        _PyLong_ExactDealloc (07FFC67073DA0h) 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Would you look at that, suddenly our trivial functions get inlined :).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might also say, surely this does not happen on PGO builds? Well the issue I linked above actually says it does! So yeah happy days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once again I want to stress, this is not the compiler’s fault! It’s just that the CPython interpreter loop is not the best thing to optimize.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, for now, you will have to build from source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With VS 2026, after cloning CPython, for a release build with PGO:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$env:PlatformToolset = "v145"
./PCbuild/build.bat --tail-call-interp -c Release -p x64 --pgo
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hopefully, we can distribute this in an easier binary form in the future once Python 3.15’s development matures!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://fidget-spinner.github.io/posts/no-longer-sorry.html"/><published>2025-12-25T13:02:46+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46384565</id><title>Asahi Linux with Sway on the MacBook Air M2 (2024)</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:40.907628+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a66d905b53c3bbc7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Asahi Linux with Sway on the MacBook Air M2&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2024-12-01&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I bought a MacBook Air M2. As of writing, it’s very affordable with the 16 GB RAM, 256 GB SSD, 13.6” model available for $750. As of writing, also Asahi Linux doesn’t support anything newer than M2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had previously used:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2011-2015: MacBook Air 13.3” with Intel Core i5 1.8 GHz, 8 GB of RAM, and 256 GB SSD (aftermarket upgrade from OWC). I installed Arch Linux on it with the i3 window manager.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2014-2018: Dell XPS 13 Developer Edition. I used the Ubuntu 14.04 that came with it with the i3 window manager.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2018-2024: Lenovo Thinkpad X1 Carbon Gen 6 with Intel Core i7 8640U, 16 GB of RAM, and 1 TB SSD. I installed Arch Linux on it with Sway.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;1 Installing Asahi Linux&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the Asahi Linux there’s a one liner which you can paste into the Terminal. It worked very well. The only complaint is that it seemed to take hours to copy root.img and boot.img over at 150 KB/s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since I intended to run it with the Sway Window Manager, and storage space is precious, I installed Fedora minimal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;2 Getting set up&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I connected to wifi with&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;nmcli device wifi list nmcli device wifi connect 'my_ssid' password 'mypassword'&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and then I installed a bunch of packages I use, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;sudo dnf install @sway-desktop-environment fish alacritty rofi ruff rclone pavucontrol-qt i3status mako pass syncthing maim xdg-user-dirs firefox rustup openssl-devel ncdu fd-find neovim&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, I cloned my personal dotfile git repo and ran &lt;code&gt;setup.sh&lt;/code&gt;.
Of course, my configs weren’t meant for the MacBook, so I had to make some changes (which I’ve pushed to the dotfiles).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;3 Customizing for MacBook&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, the whole row containing the notch is disabled, leading to a large-bezels look which I personally don’t like. There has got to be a way to use that screen real estate nicely!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I re-enabled that part of the screen with&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;grubby --args=apple_dcp.show_notch=1 --update-kernel=ALL&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, I put the Sway bar on the top to make a seamless appearance where the left and right side are used for useful information but the middle part is all black. By experimentation I found that the notch is 56px tall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;bar { position top status_command i3status modifier $mod tray_output primary # the height of the m2 macbook air's notch??? height 56 colors { background #000000 statusline #cfcfd9 separator #000000 # border background text focused_workspace #0c0c0c #413459 #cfcfd9 active_workspace #0c0c0c #413459 #cfcfd9 inactive_workspace #0c0c0c #0c0c0c #cfcfd9 urgent_workspace #2f343a #ff3300 #ffffff } }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full &lt;code&gt;i3status&lt;/code&gt; shows a lot of information which might get occluded by the notch, and it doesn’t work with the MacBook battery levels by default, so I had to update the config:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;general { colors = true interval = 5 } order += "wireless _first_" order += "ethernet _first_" order += "battery 0" order += "tztime local" wireless _first_ { format_up = "W: (%quality at %essid) %ip" format_down = "W: down" } ethernet _first_ { format_up = "E: %ip (%speed)" format_down = "E: down" } battery 0 { format = "%status %percentage" hide_seconds = true path = /sys/class/power_supply/macsmc-battery/uevent } tztime local { format = "%Y-%m-%d %H:%M:%S" }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I usually don’t like having the bar on the top (as with macOS), since you won’t be able to move your mouse cursor to the top edge to, say, click on tabs. Despite being mostly keyboard-driven, clicking on browser tabs with the mouse is something I still do often.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To fix that, I prevented the mouse cursor from entering the bar on the top, with&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;# use swaymsg -t get_inputs for the touchpad's identifier input 1452:849:Apple_MTP_multi-touch map_to_region 0 56 2560 1608&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3.1 Using Waybar instead&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In around September 2025, I switched from the native Swaybar to Waybar. Somehow, I was running into some issues with &lt;code&gt;swaymsg&lt;/code&gt;‘s handling of battery levels, and my computer ricing was due for a slight visual update anyway.
It’s nice to save a tiny bit of screen real estate with icons instead of pure text, but of course, it is somewhat slower than Swaybar as it needs to render graphical stuff.
The Waybar is still situated behind the notch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new waybar config and css are at waybarconfig and waybarstyle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;4 Using it as a daily driver&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am very impressed with how smooth and problem-free Asahi Linux is. It is incredibly responsive and feels even smoother than my Arch Linux desktop with a 16 core AMD Ryzen 7945HX and 64GB of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The touchpad in particular is stunningly good and just as good as native macOS. The mouse cursor movement and two finger scroll with inertia just feel incredibly natural, much better than my old Thinkpad X1 Carbon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons for getting the laptop was to use it for line scan photography. I was able to install the Alkeria SDK for ARM64 without any issues, even though it came as a deb file instead of an rpm. I didn’t manage to get &lt;code&gt;alien&lt;/code&gt; to work properly (something about the architecture arm64 not matching Fedora’s convention of calling it aarch64?) so I just used bsdtar to extract the contents into the filesystem root, yolo!!!
The M2 compiles my code super fast!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With high screen brightness and compiling lots of code, my battery went down from 100% to 60% after about 4.5 hours of use — not as good as the 15 hours of battery life on macOS but still pretty respectable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, it isn’t perfect. Common issues are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;higher battery drainage during sleep, so I usually just shut it down entirely when not using it&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;no hardware acceleration for video decoding&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;some USB port quirks and external display quirks&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, fairly decent overall.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://daniel.lawrence.lu/blog/2024-12-01-asahi-linux-with-sway-on-the-macbook-air-m2/"/><published>2025-12-25T14:20:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46384919</id><title>Alzheimer’s disease can be reversed in animal models? Study</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:40.778429+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6f22933169f9f5e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;New study shows Alzheimer’s disease can be reversed to achieve full neurological recovery—not just prevented or slowed—in animal models&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers from Case Western Reserve University, University Hospitals and the Cleveland VA showed restoring brain’s energy balance led to both pathological and functional recovery&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more than a century, people have considered Alzheimer's disease (AD) an irreversible illness. Consequently, research has focused on preventing or slowing it, rather than recovery. Despite billions of dollars spent on decades of research, there has never been a clinical trial of any drug to reverse and recover from AD.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A research team from Case Western Reserve University, University Hospitals (UH) and the Louis Stokes Cleveland VA Medical Center has now challenged this long-held dogma in the field, testing whether brains already badly afflicted with advanced AD could recover.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study, led by Kalyani Chaubey, from the Pieper Laboratory, was published online Dec. 22 in Cell Reports Medicine. Using diverse preclinical mouse models and analysis of human AD brains, the team showed that the brain’s failure to maintain normal levels of a central cellular energy molecule, NAD+, is a major driver of AD, and that maintaining proper NAD+ balance can prevent and even reverse the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NAD+ levels decline naturally across the body, including the brain, as people age. Without proper NAD+ balance, cells eventually become unable to execute many of the critical processes required for proper functioning and survival. In this study, the team showed that the decline in NAD+ is even more severe in the brains of people with AD, and that this same phenomenon also occurs in mouse models of the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While AD is a uniquely human condition, it can be studied in the laboratory with mice that have been genetically engineered to express genetic mutations known to cause AD in people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The researchers used two of these mouse models: One carried multiple human mutations in amyloid processing; the other carried a human mutation in the tau protein.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amyloid and tau pathology are two of the major early events in AD. Both lines of mice develop brain pathology resembling AD, including blood-brain barrier deterioration, axonal degeneration, neuroinflammation, impaired hippocampal neurogenesis, reduced synaptic transmission and widespread accumulation of oxidative damage. These mice also develop the characteristics of severe cognitive impairments seen in people with AD.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After finding that NAD+ levels in the brain declined precipitously in both human and mouse AD, the research team tested whether preventing loss of brain NAD+ balance before disease onset or restoring brain NAD+ balance after significant disease progression could prevent or reverse AD, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study was based on their previous work, published in Proceeding of the National Academy of Sciences USA, showing that restoring the brain's NAD+ balance achieved pathological and functional recovery after severe, long-lasting traumatic brain injury. They restored NAD+ balance by administering a now well-characterized pharmacologic agent known as P7C3-A20, developed in the Pieper lab.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remarkably, not only did preserving NAD+ balance protect mice from developing AD, but delayed treatment in mice with advanced disease also enabled the brain to fix the major pathological events driven by the disease-causing genetic mutations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moreover, both lines of mice fully recovered cognitive function. This was accompanied by normalized blood levels of phosphorylated tau 217, a recently approved clinical biomarker of AD in people, providing confirmation of disease reversal and highlighting an objective biomarker that could be used in future clinical trials for AD recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We were very excited and encouraged by our results,” said Andrew A. Pieper, the study’s senior author, a professor at the Case Western Reserve School of Medicine and director of the Brain Health Medicines Center, Harrington Discovery Institute at UH. “Restoring the brain's energy balance achieved pathological and functional recovery in both lines of mice with advanced Alzheimer's. Seeing this effect in two very different animal models, each driven by different genetic causes, strengthens the new idea that recovery from advanced disease might be possible in people with AD when the brain's NAD+ balance is restored.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pieper also holds the Morley-Mather Chair in Neuropsychiatry at UH and the CWRU Rebecca E. Barchas, MD, DLFAPA, University Professorship in Translational Psychiatry. He serves as psychiatrist and investigator in the Louis Stokes VA Geriatric Research Education and Clinical Center.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The results prompt a paradigm shift in how researchers, clinicians and patients can think about treating AD in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The key takeaway is a message of hope—the effects of Alzheimer's disease may not be inevitably permanent,” Pieper said. “The damaged brain can, under some conditions, repair itself and regain function.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Through our study, we demonstrated one drug-based way to accomplish this in animal models, and also identified candidate proteins in the human AD brain that may relate to the ability to reverse AD,” Chaubey said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pieper emphasized that current over-the-counter NAD+-precursors have been shown in animal models to raise cellular NAD+ to dangerously high levels that promote cancer. The pharmacological approach in this study, however, uses a pharmacologic agent (P7C3-A20) that enables cells to maintain their proper balance of NAD+ under conditions of otherwise overwhelming stress, without elevating NAD+ to supraphysiologic levels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This is an important factor when considering patient care, and clinicians should consider the possibility that therapeutic strategies aimed at restoring brain energy balance might offer a path to disease recovery,” Pieper said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work also encourages new research into complementary approaches and eventual testing in patients, and the technology is being commercialized by Cleveland-based company Glengary Brain Health, which Pieper co-founded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This new therapeutic approach to recovery needs to be moved into carefully designed human clinical trials to determine whether the efficacy seen in animal models translates to human patients,” Pieper said. “Additional next steps for the laboratory research include pinpointing which aspects of brain energy balance are most important for recovery, identifying and evaluating complementary approaches to Alzheimer's reversal, and investigating whether this recovery approach is also effective in other forms of chronic, age-related neurodegenerative disease.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://case.edu/news/new-study-shows-alzheimers-disease-can-be-reversed-achieve-full-neurological-recovery-not-just-prevented-or-slowed-animal-models"/><published>2025-12-25T15:22:36+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46385308</id><title>I sell onions on the Internet (2019)</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:40.510530+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d51a9711ab1a3d5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;They’re classified as a sweet onion, and because of their mild flavor (they don’t make your eyes tear up), some folks can eat them like an apple. Most of my customers do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a phone order one season – 2018 I believe – a customer shared this story where he smuggled some Vidalias onto his vacation cruise ship, and during each meal, would instruct the server to ‘take this onion to the back, chop it up, and add it onto my salad ‘. That story made me smile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Folks who love Vidalias, love Vidalias.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me stop, though. I don’t want to get ahead of myself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How did all this start? I’m a web guy. I’m not a farmer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;I’M ADDICTED TO DOMAIN NAMES&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oddly enough, it didn’t start with an idea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in 2014, the domain name VidaliaOnions.com expired, and went up for auction. For some reason the original owner abandoned it, and being a Georgia native, I recognized it ’cause I was familiar with the industry. I’ve been buying expired or abandoned domain names for a while, and enjoy developing them into niche businesses. This one was different though – I backordered the domain as a spectator, but for kicks &amp;amp; giggles, I dropped in a bid around $2,200 ’cause I was confident I’d be outbid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;5 minutes later, I was the proud owner of VidaliaOnions.com. I had no idea what to do with it. Ready, fire, aim.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the domain landed in my account, I attempted to re-focus my attention on other projects, but the name kept clawing me. Like it was saying:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;… yoo-hoo… over here… 😘&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;William Faulkner had an interesting perspective on writing his characters – on how they essentially wrote themselves, and how he (Faulkner) served as a sortof mechanical in-between. His quote:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would say to get the character in your mind. Once he is in your mind, and he is right, and he’s true, then he does the work himself. All you need to do then is to trot along behind him and put down what he does and what he says… You’ve got to know the character. You’ve got to believe in him. You’ve got to feel that he is alive… After that, the business of putting him down on paper is mechanical. [source]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The way Faulkner treats his characters, I treat domain name projects. I buy them with an intention to develop. And I let them take the lead. They’re the inspiration for the business itself. They guide me towards what they need to become. I’m just the dude behind the keyboard (sorta).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I buy them at auction, sometimes I buy them from original-owners. But universally, the domain name always comes first, the business idea comes second.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t usually rush into development. The path of some domains is apparent before I acquire. Others, the path reveals itself down the road. Vidalia was the latter. And after I acquired it, it kept nudging me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build me… build me… you know how. And you know what I should be…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a month, I began to understand what it was telling me. That I buy pears from Harry &amp;amp; David every year, and I should mimic that same service for Vidalia Onions. Instead of farm-to-door pears, farm-to-door Vidalia Onions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An interesting idea, but daunting to approach. I’m not a farmer, I don’t have employees, I don’t have a packing shed. And I have no logistics or distribution system setup.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the domain name kept staring at me. ಠ~ಠ ////whispering////&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;… just start …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;“take the path to Nothing, and go Nowhere until you reach it.”&lt;/head&gt;-the tao of pooh&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And so I did. I’m just dumb enough to try a project of this complexity. The market size justified an online venture. Google Trends showed strong search volume for the phrase. And chefs around the world had already belted their praise over the ‘caviar of sweet onions’.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I just started down a path, with no end goal or milestone set. I just started going. No angel investor. No VC backer. I just used some modest profit from my other domain name developments to fund the endeavor. This was Feb of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once I began, I discovered there was a Vidalia Onion committee which represents all the Vidalia farmers. So I reached out to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They were kind enough to listen to me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They introduced me to several farmers in the Vidalia region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got along quite well with the 3rd farmer I met (Aries Haygood), so we decided to partner &amp;amp; give this a shot. His farm had been around for 25 years; they hadn’t focused on direct-to-consumer; but they understood its value. They operated a packing shed as well. And most importantly, they grew an award winning Vidalia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And so we went.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We conservatively estimated fifty (50) orders for our 2015 season. We ended up with over six hundred (600).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the farm concentrated on the Vidalia, I concentrated on customer service, marketing, branding, web development, &amp;amp; logistics. I didn’t have other projects that were this front-facing, customer wise. And I discovered I immensely enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The more we both focused on these efforts, the more we grew. So much so, that other Vidalia operations began shutting down their mail order efforts and simply directed folks our way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We began testing alternate marketing avenues – a billboard on I-95 just south of Savannah, GA facing northbound traffic; sponsoring a bike rider headed cross country for charity; sponsoring a high school basketball team, as well as a grade school auction fundraiser.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We added a phone order hotline, which – from time to time – generates more sales than online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also made a few colossal mistakes, which were entirely of my doing, like blowing $10,000 on faulty shipping boxes from an ill-informed &amp;amp; misleading box manufacturer in Dalton, GA. (it happened early in our journey, and nearly forced me to shut down)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I refused to let something like that kill this. Honestly, my customers would be quite upset if we disappeared. Last season, while I called a gentleman back regarding a phone order, his wife answered. While I introduced myself, she interrupted me mid-sentence and hollered in exaltation to her husband: ” THE VIDALIA MAN! THE VIDALIA MAN! PICK UP THE PHONE! ”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At that moment, I realized we were doing something right. Something helpful. Something that was making a positive impact.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I sometimes say I prefer projects that focus on purpose over profit. And as we enter our 5th season, this one continues to do just that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And it’s immensely gratifying. I feel so fortunate to be associated with this industry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m Peter Askew, and I sell onions on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Them: We leverage automated machine learning to enhance your existing BI visualizations with more proactive insights&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Me: I sell onions on the internet&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;— Peter Askew (@searchbound) June 13, 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;** below – from the field during harvest – these have been dug &amp;amp; are ready for clipping&lt;lb/&gt; ( click &amp;amp; drag )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Follow me on Twitter as I continue to document my journey there. Or get an email when I post new stuff (below):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.deepsouthventures.com/i-sell-onions-on-the-internet/"/><published>2025-12-25T16:24:45+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46385600</id><title>Clearspace (YC W23) Is Hiring a Founding Network Engineer (VPN and Proxy)</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:39.939766+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b792f12e5d21eddd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eliminate compulsive phone usage&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Clearspace&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clearspace is building the intentionality layer of the internet. Our mission is to build technology as effective at protecting human attention as social media is at exploiting it (infinite scrolling, short-form feeds, manipulative notifications, etc). Our category defining mobile app has been featured on Huberman Lab, New York Times Wirecutter, NPR Marketplace, Forbes, TBPN.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People that want a better relationship with their devices have nowhere to turn except for willpower. We are building a system allows users to control what their devices see by processing and filtering network traffic against natural language rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About The Role&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re looking for a networking-obsessed engineer to own the VPN + first-hop policy proxy that powers our AI agent. You don’t need to be an IKEv2 expert, we care more about deep networking intuition, debugging skill, and the desire to go all the way down the stack until the truth reveals itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might be a great fit if you’ve built:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What You’ll Build&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualifications&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nice to Have&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compensation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Clearspace we help people reduce compulsive phone usage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We exist to protect people's attention from the exploits of modern technology platforms and make space for the things that matter to them most.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe the technology to protect someones attention should be just as sophisticated and effective as the tech that is exploiting it and are building a world-class engineering team to arm the world with a comprehensive attention protection stack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/clearspace/jobs/5LtM86I-founding-network-engineer-at-clearspace"/><published>2025-12-25T17:01:29+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46386009</id><title>All I Want for Christmas Is Your Secrets: LangGrinch hits LangChain Core</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:39.626386+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1d9bd6974da50682"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yesterday, LangChain published a critical advisory for a vulnerability I reported in langchain-core: CVE-2025-68664 / GHSA-c67j-w6g6-q2cm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, my research focused on breaking secret managers in our “Vault Fault” work – systems that are explicitly designed to be the security boundary around your most sensitive credentials. One takeaway kept repeating: when a platform accidentally treats attacker-shaped data as trusted structure, that boundary collapses fast. This time, the system that “breaks” isn’t your secret manager. It’s the agent framework that may use them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why this vulnerability deserves extra attention:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It’s in Core. This is not a specific tool bug, not an integration edge-case, and not a “some community package did something weird.” The vulnerable APIs (dumps() / dumpd()) live in langchain-core itself.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The blast radius is scale. By download volume, langchain is one of the most widely deployed AI framework components globally today. As of late December 2025, public package telemetry shows hundreds of millions of installs, with pepy.tech reporting ~847M total downloads and pypistats showing ~98M downloads in the last month.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;One prompt can trigger a lot of machinery. The most common real-world path here is not “attacker sends you a serialized blob and you call load().” It’s subtler: LLM outputs can influence fields like additional_kwargs or response_metadata, and those fields can be serialized and later deserialized through normal framework features like streaming logs/events. Plainly, this means an exploit can be triggered by a single text prompt that cascades into a surprisingly complex internal pipeline. &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before you read further, patches are now released in versions 1.2.5 and 0.3.81. If you’re running LangChain in production, this one is trickier than it may seem; please update ASAP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The short version of the bug&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LangChain uses a special internal serialization format where dictionaries containing an ‘lc’ marker represent LangChain objects. The vulnerability was that dumps() and dumpd() did not properly escape user-controlled dictionaries that happened to include the reserved ‘lc’ key.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So once an attacker is able to make a LangChain orchestration loop serialize and later deserialize content including an ‘lc’ key, they would instantiate an unsafe arbitrary object, potentially triggering many attacker-friendly paths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The advisory lists 12 distinct vulnerable flows, which are extremely common use cases, such as standard event streaming, logging, message history/memory or caches:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most damaging outcomes include:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Secret extraction from environment variables. The advisory notes this happens when deserialization is performed with secrets_from_env=True. Notably, this was the default until yesterday. 🙂&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Object instantiation within pre-approved namespaces (including langchain_core, langchain_openai, langchain_aws, langchain_anthropic…), potentially triggering side effects in constructors (network calls, file operations, etc.).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Under certain conditions LangChain object instantiation may lead to arbitrary code execution.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is categorized under CWE-502: Deserialization of Untrusted Data, with a CNA CVSS score of 9.3 (Critical).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My research story: how I stumbled into it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;’Twas the night before Christmas, and I was doing the least festive kind of work: staring at serialization code and asking “wait… why is that trusted?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security research often looks dramatic from the outside. In reality, it is usually careful reading, small hypotheses, and a slow accumulation of “that’s odd” moments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one started the way many do at Cyata: with a simple question we ask constantly as we assess AI stacks for real-world risk:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where are the trust boundaries in AI applications, and do developers actually know where those boundaries are?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LangChain is a powerful framework, and like most modern frameworks it has to move complex structured data around: messages, tool calls, streaming events, traces, caches, and “runnables.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reviewing previous research, there was already extensive research on LangChain tooling and integrations, but very few findings on the core library.&lt;lb/&gt;I started the research working backwards. Finding interesting locations (sinks), then figuring out how an attacker might reach them. Deserialization was an obvious target.&lt;lb/&gt;It took me quite a while to find something meaningful. But after a while, I found that assuming an attacker-controlled deserialization primitive, I could trigger blind SSRF that could be leveraged to exfiltrate environment variables (to be detailed soon). Because the outcome was limited to secret exfil, instead of my primary RCE goal, I kept auditing the deserialization, and took my time.&lt;lb/&gt;The bug wasn’t a piece of bad code, it was the absence of code. dumps() simply didn’t escape user-controlled dictionaries containing ‘lc’ keys. A missing escape in the serialization path, not the deserialization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;It’s much easier to spot something wrong than to notice something missing, especially when you’re auditing load(), not dumps(). In one of the most scrutinized AI frameworks. For two and a half years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From there, the investigation became a structured exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Identify where untrusted content (mostly arbitrary dictionaries) gets serialized (LLM outputs, prompt injection, user input, external tools, retrieved docs).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Identify when that serialized data gets deserialized.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Identify what an attacker can achieve from arbitrary object instantiation.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At that point, the core finding was clear and actionable enough to responsibly report: there was an escaping gap in dumps() / dumpd() around ‘lc’ key dictionaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The advisory later captured what we often see in practice: fields like additional_kwargs and response_metadata can be influenced by LLM output and prompt injection, and those fields can get serialized-deserialized in many flows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To the LangChain team’s credit: the response and follow-through were decisive, not just patching the bug but also hardening defaults that were too permissive for the world we’re in now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The LangChain project decided to award a $4,000 USD bounty for this finding. According to huntr, the platform where LangChain operated its bounty program, this would be the maximum amount ever awarded in the project, with bounties so far awarded up to $125.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Technical deep dive&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Background: the “lc” marker and why it exists&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LangChain serializes certain objects using a structured dict format. The ‘lc’ key is used internally to indicate “this is a LangChain-serialized structure,” not just arbitrary user data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a common pattern, but it creates a security invariant: Any user-controlled data that could contain ‘lc’ must be treated carefully. Otherwise, an attacker can craft a dict that “looks like” an internal object and trick the deserializer into giving it meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The patch makes the intent explicit in the updated documentation: during serialization, plain dicts that contain an ‘lc’ key are escaped by wrapping them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This prevents those dicts from being confused with actual LangChain serialized objects during deserialization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The allowlist: what can be instantiated&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LangChain’s load()/loads() functions don’t instantiate arbitrary classes – they check against an allowlist that controls which classes can be deserialized. By default, this allowlist includes classes from langchain_core, langchain_openai, langchain_aws, and other ecosystem packages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the catch: most classes on the allowlist have harmless constructors. Finding exploitable paths required digging through the ecosystem for classes that do something meaningful on instantiation. The ones I found are detailed below, but there may be others waiting to be discovered.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The exfiltration path&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LangChain’s loads() function supports a secret type that resolves values from environment variables during deserialization. Before the patch, this feature secrets_from_env was enabled by default:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;if (
    value.get("lc") == 1
    and value.get("type") == "secret"
    and value.get("id") is not None
):
    [key] = value["id"]
    if key in self.secrets_map:
        return self.secrets_map[key]
    if self.secrets_from_env and key in os.environ and os.environ[key]:
        return os.environ[key] # &amp;lt;-- Returning env variable
    return None&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If a deserialized object is returned to an attacker, for example message history inside the LLM context, that could leak environment variables.&lt;lb/&gt;But the more interesting path is an indirect prompt injection. Even an attacker who cannot see any LLM responses can exfiltrate secrets by instantiating the right class. ChatBedrockConverse from langchain_aws is both in the default allowlist of loads and makes a GET request on construction.&lt;lb/&gt;The GET endpoint is attacker-controlled, and a specific HTTP header can be populated with an environment variable via the secrets_from_env feature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This validator runs when ChatBedrockConverse is instantiated. The attacker controls endpoint_url, triggering an outbound request. Combined with secrets_from_env, the aws_access_key_id header can be populated with any environment variable – not just AWS keys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are intentionally not publishing a copy-paste exploit here, to give time for security teams. In a few months, the Huntr website will publish them automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Code Execution via jinja2 templates&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the classes in the default loads() allowlist is PromptTemplate. This class creates a prompt from a template, and one of the available template formats is Jinja2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a template is rendered with Jinja2, arbitrary Python code can run. We did not find a way to trigger this directly from the loads() function alone, but if a subsequent call to the deserialized object triggers rendering, code execution follows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We suspect there may be paths to direct code execution from loads(), but we have not confirmed one yet. If you have a solid idea or a lead worth testing, we’d love to hear from you – this is exactly where the security community helps turn hypotheses into proof. 🤝&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also worth noting: in past versions, the Chain class was also in the allowlist. That class has special features that might have enabled a flow to template rendering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Who is affected? The practical checklist&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your application is potentially exposed if it uses vulnerable langchain-core versions. Here are some of the most common vulnerable patterns (12 flows have been identified in total):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;astream_events(version=”v1″) (v1 uses the vulnerable serialization; v2 is not vulnerable)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Runnable.astream_log()&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;dumps() / dumpd() on untrusted data, followed by load() / loads()&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Deserializing untrusted data with load() / loads()&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Internal serialization flows like RunnableWithMessageHistory, InMemoryVectorStore.load(), certain caches, pulling manifests from LangChain Hub (hub.pull), and other listed components in the advisory&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, the system’s behavior is complex enough that it’s risky to assume a quick code-path review will catch every reachable variant. The safer course is to upgrade to a patched version and not assume you’re in the clear until you do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, the advisory calls out what I consider the most important real-world point:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most common attack vector is through LLM response fields like additional_kwargs or response_metadata, which can be controlled via prompt injection and then serialized/deserialized in streaming operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is exactly the kind of “AI meets classic security” intersection where organizations get caught off guard. LLM output is an untrusted input. If your framework treats portions of that output as structured objects later, you must assume attackers will try to shape it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Defensive guidance: how to respond in production&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;1) Patch first (this is the fastest risk reduction)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upgrade langchain-core to a patched version. If you are using langchain, langchain-community, or other ecosystem packages, validate what version of langchain-core is actually installed in production environments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2) Assume LLM outputs can be attacker-shaped&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Treat additional_kwargs, response_metadata, tool outputs, retrieved documents, and message history as untrusted unless proven otherwise. This is especially important if you stream logs/events and later rehydrate them with a loader.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;3) Review deserialization features like secret resolution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even after upgrading, keep the principle: do not enable secret resolution from environment variables unless you trust the serialized input. The project changed defaults for a reason.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The LangChainJS parallel&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on my report, there is a closely related advisory in LangChainJS (GHSA-r399-636x-v7f6 / CVE-2025-68665) with similar mechanics: ‘lc’ marker confusion during serialization, enabling secret extraction and unsafe instantiation in certain configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your organization runs both Python and JavaScript LangChain stacks, treat this as a reminder that the pattern travels across ecosystems: marker-based serialization, untrusted model output, and later deserialization is a recurring risk shape.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why this matters beyond LangChain&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are entering a phase where agentic AI frameworks are becoming critical infrastructure inside production systems. Serialization formats, orchestration pipelines, tool execution, caches, and tracing are no longer “plumbing” – they are part of your security boundary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This vulnerability is not “just a bug in a library.” It is a case study in a bigger pattern:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Your application might deserialize data it believes it produced safely.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;But that serialized output can contain fields influenced by untrusted sources (including LLM outputs shaped by prompt injection).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A single reserved key used as an internal marker can become a pivot point into secrets and execution-adjacent behaviors.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Cyata, our work is to help organizations build visibility, risk assessment, control, and governance around AI systems – because if you can’t quickly answer where agents are running, which versions are deployed, and what data flows through it, you’re effectively flying blind when advisories like this land.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What this teaches us about AI governance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are a security leader reading this, here is the uncomfortable truth:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most organizations cannot currently answer, quickly and confidently:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Where are we using agents?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Which versions are deployed in production?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Which services have access to sensitive secrets?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Where do LLM outputs cross those boundaries?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is not a “developer problem.” It is a visibility and governance problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that is where Cyata comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How Cyata helps: visibility, risk assessment, control, governance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Cyata, we focus on a practical outcome: reducing AI and agent risk without slowing down builders. Vulnerabilities like this one are rarely “just a patch.” They expose gaps in how teams discover where agents run, understand real trust boundaries, and enforce safer defaults across fast-moving frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Visibility&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Know what is running, where, and how it is wired.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Answer the first CVE question quickly: are we exposed, and in which flows?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Discover agent runtimes and integrations across environments (IDEs, CI, services, worker jobs, hosted agents).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Track frameworks, packages, and versions in use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Risk assessment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prioritize what matters based on real-world blast radius, not just “library present.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support faster triage: what is internet-facing, what touches secrets, what runs with elevated credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Identify the highest-risk paths: untrusted content flowing into privileged contexts (services with secrets, broad tool permissions, prod network access).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Highlight where “structured fields” can cross trust boundaries (metadata, tool outputs, streamed events, cached artifacts).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reduce exposure even before every dependency is patched everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Encourage safer operational defaults: least privilege, isolation boundaries, and policy checks that scale across teams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enforce guardrails around risky patterns (for example: deserializing untrusted data, permissive object revival, unsafe streaming-to-cache-to-rehydrate flows).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gate or restrict sensitive capabilities in untrusted contexts (for example: secret access via environment, high-privilege tool execution, or running risky code paths in privileged workers).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Governance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make “safe agent usage” repeatable, auditable, and hard to drift.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Define policies for approved frameworks, versions, and configurations.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Track and time-box exceptions with owners and rationale.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Monitor for drift and risky feature usage over time, with an audit trail that supports security reviews and compliance.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a Christmas-week advisory drops, the goal is not heroics – it’s calm, controlled response backed by real inventory and enforced guardrails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Disclosure Timeline&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Report submitted via Huntr – December 4th, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Acknowledged by LangChain maintainers – December 5th, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Advisory and CVE published – December 24th, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Control Plane for Agentic Identity&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://cyata.ai/blog/langgrinch-langchain-core-cve-2025-68664/"/><published>2025-12-25T18:06:44+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46386211</id><title>Fahrplan – 39C3</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:37.839854+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="adf28d1d22b2a7ef"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sat - Day 1 - December 27&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Opening Ceremony&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pajowu, Stella&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;All Sorted by Machines of Loving Grace? "AI", Cybernetics, and Fascism and how to Intervene&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Katika Kühnreich&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;The art of text (rendering)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nicolas Rougier&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;A Tale of Two Leaks: How Hackers Breached the Great Firewall of China&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jade Sheffey&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;OpenAutoLab: photographic film processing machine. Fully automatic and DIY-friendly.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kauz&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Zentrum für Politische Schönheit: Ein Jahr Adenauer SRP+ und der Walter Lübke Memorial Park&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stefan Pelzer, Philipp Ruch&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Demystifying Fuzzer Behaviour&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Addison&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;ISDN + POTS Telephony at Congress and Camp&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Harald Welte&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Brennende Wälder und Kommentarspalten - Klimaupdate mit dem FragDenStaat Climate Helpdesk&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joschi Wolf&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Building hardware - easier than ever - harder than it should be&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kliment&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Neuroexploitation by Design: Wie Algorithmen in Glücksspielprodukten sich Wirkweisen des Reinforcement Learning und dopaminergen Belohnungssystems zunutze machen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elke Smith&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;FeTAp 611 unplugged: Taking a rotary dial phone to the mobile age&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michael Weiner&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Who cares about the Baltic Jammer? – Terrestrial Navigation in the Baltic Sea Region&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lars, Niklas Hehenkamp, Markus&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Liberating Bluetooth on the ESP32&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Antonio Vázquez Blanco (Antón)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Chaos macht Küche&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ingwer Andersen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Developing New Medicines in the Age of AI and Personalized Medicine&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dennis Özcelik&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Endlich maschinenlesbare Urteile! Open access für Juristen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beata Hubrig, Nuri Khadem-Al-Charieh&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Opening pAMDora's box and unleashing a thousand paths on the journey to play Beatsaber custom songs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;tihmstar&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Not an Impasse: Child Safety, Privacy, and Healing Together&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kate Sim&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;KIM 1.5: Noch mehr Kaos In der Medizinischen Telematikinfrastruktur (TI)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Christoph Saatjohann&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;RedScout42 – Zur digitalen Wohnungsfrage&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sandra, Leonard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;All my Deutschlandtickets gone: Fraud at an industrial scale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Q Misell, 551724 / maya boeckh&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Of Boot Vectors and Double Glitches: Bypassing RP2350's Secure Boot&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;stacksmashing, nsr&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;„KI“, Digitalisierung und Longevity als Fix für ein kaputtes Gesundheitssystem?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Manuel Hofmann&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Chaos all year round&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deanna&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;To sign or not to sign: Practical vulnerabilities in GPG &amp;amp; friends&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;49016, Liam&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Handy weg bis zur Ausreise – Wie Cellebrite ins Ausländeramt kam&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chris Köver&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Pwn2Roll: Who Needs a 595€ Remote When You Have wheelchair.py?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;elfy&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Escaping Containment: A Security Analysis of FreeBSD Jails&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ilja, Michael Smith&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Die Känguru-Rebellion: Digital Independence Day&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marc-Uwe Kling, Linus Neumann&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;And so it begins - Wie unser Rechtsstaat auf dem Highway Richtung Trumpismus rast – und warum afghanische Kläger*innen für uns die Notbremse ziehen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eva, Elaha&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;1965 + 60 Years of Algorithmic Art with Computers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enna Gerhard, Frieder Nake&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Life on Hold: What Does True Solidarity Look Like Beyond Duldung, Camps, Deportation, and Payment Cards?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hafid Shaaib, Eric Noel Mbiakeu&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Chatkontrolle - Ctrl+Alt+Delete&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;khaleesi, Markus Reuter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Excuse me, what precise time is It?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oliver Ettlin&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;BitUnlocker: Leveraging Windows Recovery to Extract BitLocker Secrets&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alon Leviev&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Not To Be Trusted - A Fiasco in Android TEEs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;0ddc0de, gannimo, Philipp&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Hacking washing machines&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Severin von Wnuck-Lipinski, Hajo Noerenberg&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Radikalisierungspipeline Esoterik: Von "Eso-Nazis" der NS-Zeit zu „geheimen Wissen“ auf TikTok &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Katharina Nocun&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Throwing your rights under the Omnibus - how the EU's reform agenda threatens to erase a decade of digital rights&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thomas Lohninger, Ralf Bendrath&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;DNGerousLINK: A Deep Dive into WhatsApp 0-Click Exploits on iOS and Samsung Devices&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zhongrui Li, Yizhe Zhuang, Kira Chen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Bluetooth Headphone Jacking: A Key to Your Phone&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dennis Heinze, Frieder Steinmetz&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Breaking architecture barriers: Running x86 games and apps on ARM&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;neobrain&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;The Eyes of Photon Science: Imaging, Simulation and the Quest to Make the Invisible Visible&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MarKuster&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Coding Dissent: Art, Technology, and Tactical Media&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helena Nikonole&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;AI-generated content in Wikipedia - a tale of caution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mathias Schindler&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Building a NOC from scratch&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;lilly, Scientress&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;From Silicon to Darude Sand-storm: breaking famous synthesizer DSPs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;giulioz&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Unnecessarily Complicated Kitchen – Die Wissenschaft des guten Geschmacks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LukasQ&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sun - Day 2 - December 28&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Junghacker:innentag Einführung&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Protecting the network data of one billion people: Breaking network crypto in popular Chinese mobile apps&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mona&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Hatupangwingwi: The story how Kenyans fought back against intrusive digital identity systems&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mustafa Mahmoud Yousif&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Lightning Talks - Tag 2&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bonnie, keldo, Andi Bräu&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Digitale Inklusion: Wie wir digitale Barrierefreiheit für alle erreichen können&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jakob Sponholz, Kathrin Klapper, Lena Christina Müller&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Skynet Starter Kit: From Embodied AI Jailbreak to Remote Takeover of Humanoid Robots&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shipei Qu, Zikai Xu, Xuangan Xiao&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Suing spyware in Europe: news from the front!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lori Roussey, Celia/Irídia&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Neue Chaos Events - InselChaos und Håck ma’s Castle plaudern aus dem Nähkästchen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Erwin Ernst "eest9" Steinhammer, lasii, Daniel, Niklas&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;A post-American, enshittification-resistant internet&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cory Doctorow&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;A space odyssey #2: How to study moon rocks from the Soviet sample return mission Luna 24&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paul Koetter, Christopher Hamann&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Agentic ProbLLMs: Exploiting AI Computer-Use and Coding Agents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Johann Rehberger&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;selbstverständlich antifaschistisch! Aktuelle Informationen zu den Verfahren im Budapest-Komplex - von family &amp;amp; friends Hamburg&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andreas family &amp;amp; friends Hamburg, Birgit family &amp;amp; friends Hamburg&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Chaospager - How to construct an Open Pager System for c3&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Max, Julian&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Chaos Communication Chemistry: DNA security systems based on molecular randomness&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anne Lüscher&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Live, Die, Repeat: The fight against data retention and boundless access to data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Klaus Landefeld&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Power Cycle B7 oder Warum kauft man eine Zeche?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kohlenpod, kater, Stephan&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Cracking open what makes Apple's Low-Latency WiFi so fast&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Henri Jäger&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Awful interception: misadventures of the russian surveillance machinery&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Xeniax&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Amateurfunk im All – Kontakt mit Fram2&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;akira25, flx, Gato&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Über europäische Grenzen hinweg auf klinischen Daten rechnen - aber sicher!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hendrik Ballhausen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;CCC-Jahresrückblick&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Constanze Kurz, khaleesi, Matthias Marx, Linus Neumann, erdgeist&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Persist, resist, stitch&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Philo&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Lessons from Building an Open-Architecture Secure Element&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jan Pleskac&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Auf die Dauer hilft nur Power: Herausforderungen für dezentrale Netzwerke aus Sicht der Soziologie&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marco Wähner&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Current Drone Wars&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Leonard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Variable Fonts — It Was Never About File Size&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bernd&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;A Quick Stop at the HostileShop&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mike Perry&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;In-house electronics manufacturing from scratch: How hard can it be?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Augustin Bielefeld, Alexander Willer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;CPU Entwicklung in Factorio: Vom D-Flip-Flop bis zum eigenen Betriebssystem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PhD (Philipp)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Amtsgeheimnis raus, Datenhalde rein: was die Informationsfreiheit in Österreich bringt&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Markus (fin) Hametner, Erwin Ernst "eest9" Steinhammer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;How to render cloud FPGAs useless&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dirk&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;freiheit.exe - Utopien als Malware&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Christiane Mudra&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Recharge your batteries with us - an empowering journey through the energy transition&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Salacidre, JulianeB&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Prometheus: Reverse-Engineering Overwatch&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;breakingbread&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Trump government demands access to European police databases and biometrics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias Monroy&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Verlorene Domains, offene Türen - Was alte Behördendomains verraten&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tim Philipp Schäfers (TPS)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;CSS Clicker Training: Making games in a "styling" language&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lyra Rebane&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Wie wir alte Flipperautomaten am Leben erhalten&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Axel Böttcher&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Power Cycles statt Burnout – Wie Einflussnahme nicht verpufft&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rahel Becker, Anna Kassautzki&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Don’t look up: There are sensitive internal links in the clear on GEO satellites&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nadia Heninger, Annie Dai&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Textiles 101: Fast Fiber Transform&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;octoprog&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;How To Minimize Bugs in Cryptography Code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jade&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Machine Vision – Vom Algorithmus zum Baumpilz im digitalen Metabolismus&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thomas Knüsel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Xous: A Pure-Rust Rethink of the Embedded Operating System&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;bunnie, Sean "xobs" Cross&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;51 Ways to Spell the Image Giraffe: The Hidden Politics of Token Languages in Generative AI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ting-Chun Liu, Leon-Etienne Kühr&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;When Vibe Scammers Met Vibe Hackers: Pwning PhaaS with Their Own Weapons&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chiao-Lin Yu (Steven Meow)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;The Maybe Talent Show&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Norman Müller-Schmitz, lukas-schmukas, James Bonne d'age&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Code to Craft: Procedural Generation for the Physical World&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;bleeptrack&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Reverse engineering the Pixel TitanM2 firmware&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;willem&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;The Small Packet of Bits That Can Save (or Destabilize) a City&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Manuel Rábade&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;GPTDash – Der Reverse-Turing-Test&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Benny, Kilian, BratscherBen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Mon - Day 3 - December 29&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Azubi-Tag Einführung&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Greenhouse Gas Emission Data: Public, difficult to access, and not always correct&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hanno Böck&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Design for 3D-Printing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;rahix&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Lightning Talks - Tag 3&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bonnie, keldo, Andi Bräu&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;The Museum of Care: Open-Source Survival Kit Collection&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nika Dubrovsky&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Celestial navigation with very little math&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trammell Hudson&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;a media-almost-archaeology on data that is too dirty for "AI"&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;jiawen uffline&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Hacking Karlsruhe - 10 years later&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jürgen Bering&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;What Makes Bike-Sharing Work? Insights from 43 Million Kilometers of European Cycling Data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Martin Lellep, Georg Balke, FelixW&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Teckids – eine verstehbare (digitale) Welt&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keno, Darius Auding&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;BE Modded: Exploring and hacking the Vital Bracelet ecosystem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;cyanic&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Wer hat Angst vor dem Neutralitätsgebot?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hannah Vos, Vivian Kube&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Shit for Future: turning human shit into a climate solution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elena&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Watch Your Kids: Inside a Children's Smartwatch&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nils Rollshausen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;When 8 Bits is Overkill: Making Blinkenlights with a 1-bit CPU&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;girst (Tobi)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Supplements und Social Media – wenn der Online-Hype zur realen Gesundheitsgefahr wird&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Christoph Wiedmer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Programmierte Kriegsverbrechen? Über KI-Systeme im Kriegseinsatz in Gaza und warum IT-Fachleute sich dazu äußern müssen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rainer Rehak&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Making the Magic Leap past NVIDIA's secure bootchain and breaking some Tesla Autopilots along the way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EliseZeroTwo&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Learning from South Korean Telco Breaches&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shinjo "peremen" Park, Yonghyu "perillamint" Ban&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Gegenmacht - Best of Informationsfreiheit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arne Semsrott&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;There is NO WAY we ended up getting arrested for this (Malta edition)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;mixy1, Luke Bjorn Scerri, girogio&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;APT Down and the mystery of the burning data centers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Christopher Kunz, Sylvester&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Von wegen Eisblumen! Wie man mit Code, Satelliten und Schiffsexpeditionen die bunte Welt des arktischen Phytoplanktons sichtbar macht&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moritz Zeising (er/he)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Schlechte Karten - IT-Sicherheit im Jahr null der ePA für alle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bianca Kastl&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Set-top box Hacking: freeing the 'Freebox'&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Frédéric Hoguin&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Wer liegt hier wem auf der Tasche? Genug mit dem Bürgergeld-Fetisch. Stürmt die Paläste!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helena Steinhaus&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;The Last of Us - Fighting the EU Surveillance Law Apocalypse&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Svea Windwehr, Chloé Berthélémy&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;AI Agent, AI Spy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Udbhav Tiwari, Meredith Whittaker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Build a Fake Phone, Find Real Bugs: Qualcomm GPU Emulation and Fuzzing with LibAFL QEMU&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Romain Malmain, Scott Bauer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Transkultureller Hack auf die klassische Musikszene – Vortrag und Konzert&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Johanna-Leonore Dahlhoff, Neina Doroshenko, Peter Klohmann, Alireza Meghrazi Solouklou, Mirweis Neda, Maria Carolina Pardo Reyes, Eduardo Sabella, Sarah Luisa Wurmer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Netzpolitik in der Schweiz: Zwischen Bodensee und Matterhorn&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kire, Rahel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;The Angry Path to Zen: AMD Zen Microcode Tools and Insights&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Benjamin Kollenda&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Blackbox Palantir&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Constanze Kurz, Franziska Görlitz&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Aber hier Leben? Nein danke! …oder doch? Wie wir der autoritären Zuspitzung begegnen können.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jaša Hiergeblieben, Lisa Zugezogen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Race conditions, transactions and free parking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Benjamin W. Broersma&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Hegemony Eroding: Excavating Diversity in Latent Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Karim Hamdi&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;10 years of Dieselgate&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Felix Domke, Karsten Burger&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;The Heartbreak Machine: Nazis in the Echo Chamber&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Martha Root, Eva Hoffmann, Christian Fuchs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Light in the Dark(net)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tobias Höller&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;The Spectrum - Hackspace Beyond Hacking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;sjaelv, MultisampledNight&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Rowhammer in the Wild: Large-Scale Insights from FlippyR.AM&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Martin Heckel, Florian Adamsky, Daniel Gruss&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Peep-Show für die Polizei. Staatliche Überwachung von Queers in Hamburger Toiletten bis 1980&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simon Schultz&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Human microservices at the Dutch Railways: modern architecture, ancient hardware?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maarten W&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Von Fuzzern zu Agenten: Entwicklung eines Cyber Reasoning Systems für die AIxCC&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mischa Meier (mmisc), Annika Kuntze&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;PRÜF&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nico Semsrott&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Verschlüsselung brechen durch physischen Zugriff - Smartphone Beschlagnahme durch Polizei&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Davy Wang, Viktor Schlüter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Spectre in the real world: Leaking your private data from the cloud with CPU vulnerabilities&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thijs Raymakers&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Die große Datenschutz-, Datenpannen- und DS-GVO-Show&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alvar C.H. Freude&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tue - Day 4 - December 30&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Asahi Linux - Porting Linux to Apple Silicon&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;sven&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Atoms in Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;manuel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;I Hated All The Cross-Stitch Software So I Made My Own: My Deranged Outsider Software Suite For Making Deranged Outsider Art&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;yomimono&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;How to keep Open Source open without leaving our communities open to threats&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quintessence&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;CCC&amp;amp;T - Cosmic ray, the Climate Catastrophe and Trains.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FantasticMisterFux, louiT&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;CUII: Wie Konzerne heimlich Webseiten in Deutschland sperren&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lina Lastname, Elias Zeidler (Northernside)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;“End Of 10”: How the FOSS Community is Combatting Software-Driven Resource and Energy Consumption&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joseph P. De Veaugh-Geiss, Carolina Silva Rode, belobe&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;What You Hack Is What You Mean: 35 Years of Wiring Sense into Text&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Torsten Roeder&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Security of Cardiac Implantable Electronic Devices&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;dilucide&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Who runs the www? WSIS+20 and the future of Internet governance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sophia Longwe&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Fossile Industrie liebt KI!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stefan, Yannik &amp;amp; Rike, Moritz&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Laser Beams &amp;amp; Light Streams: Letting Hackers Go Pew Pew, Building Affordable Light-Based Hardware Security Tooling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Patch, Sam. Beaumont (PANTH13R)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Breaking BOTS: Cheating at Blue Team CTFs with AI Speed-Runs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Leo Meyerovich, Sindre Breda&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Von Groschen und SpurLos - GNU Taler auch auf eurem Event!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mikolai Gütschow, signum&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;We, the EU, and 1064 Danes decided to look into YouTube: A story about how the EU gave us a law, 1064 Danes gave us their YouTube histories, and reality gave us a headache&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;David, LK Seiling&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Battling Obsolescence – Keeping an 80s laser tag system alive&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trikkitt&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Security Nightmares&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Constanze Kurz, Ron&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Infrastructure Review&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;nicoduck&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Closing Ceremony&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stella, pajowu&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://fahrplan.events.ccc.de/congress/2025/fahrplan/"/><published>2025-12-25T18:40:14+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46386835</id><title>URL Pattern API</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:37.697044+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ca240d7f4bed0e91"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;URL Pattern API&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head&gt; Baseline 2025 Newly available &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since â¨September 2025â©, this feature works across the latest devices and browser versions. This feature might not work in older devices or browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: This feature is available in Web Workers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The URL Pattern API defines a syntax that is used to create URL pattern matchers. These patterns can be matched against URLs or individual URL components.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Concepts and usage&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Patterns are specified using the &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt; interface.
The pattern syntax is based on the syntax from the path-to-regexp library.
Patterns can contain:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Literal strings which will be matched exactly.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Wildcards (&lt;code&gt;/posts/*&lt;/code&gt;) that match any character.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Named groups (&lt;code&gt;/books/:id&lt;/code&gt;) which extract a part of the matched URL.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Non-capturing groups (&lt;code&gt;/books{/old}?&lt;/code&gt;) which make parts of a pattern optional or be matched multiple times.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;RegExp&lt;/code&gt;groups (&lt;code&gt;/books/(\\d+)&lt;/code&gt;) which make arbitrarily complex regex matches. Note that the parentheses are not part of the regex but instead define their contents as a regex. Some APIs prohibit the use of regular expression groups in&lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt;objects. The&lt;code&gt;hasRegExpGroups&lt;/code&gt;property indicates whether or not regular expression groups are used.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find details about the syntax in the pattern syntax section below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Interfaces&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Represents a pattern that can match URLs or parts of URLs. The pattern can contain capturing groups that extract parts of the matched URL.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pattern syntax&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The syntax for patterns is based on the path-to-regexp JavaScript library. This syntax is similar to the one used in Ruby on Rails, or JavaScript frameworks like Express or Next.js.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Fixed text and capture groups&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each pattern can contain a combination of fixed text and groups. The fixed text is a sequence of characters that is matched exactly. Groups match an arbitrary string based on matching rules. Each URL part has its own default rules that are explained below, but they can be overwritten.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A pattern matching some fixed text
const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/books" });
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books")); // true
console.log(pattern.exec("https://example.com/books").pathname.groups); // {}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A pattern matching with a named group
const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/books/:id" });
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.exec("https://example.com/books/123").pathname.groups); // { id: '123' }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Segment wildcard&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, a group matching the &lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt; part of the URL will match all characters but the forward slash (&lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;). In the &lt;code&gt;hostname&lt;/code&gt; part, the group will match all characters except the dot (&lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;).
In all other parts, the group will match all characters.
The segment wildcard is non-greedy, meaning that it will match the shortest possible string.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Regex matchers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of using the default match rules for a group, you can specify a regex for each group by specifying it in parentheses. This regex defines the matching rules for the group. Below is an example of a regex matcher on a named group that constrains the group to only match if it contains one or more digits:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern1 = new URLPattern("/books/:id(\\d+)", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern1.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern1.test("https://example.com/books/abc")); // false
console.log(pattern1.test("https://example.com/books/")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also use regex when constructing a &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt; with the object syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern2 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/books/:id(\\d+)" });
console.log(pattern2.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern2.test("https://example.com/books/abc")); // false
console.log(pattern2.test("https://example.com/books/")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Pathname matching&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt; URL-part always starts with &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;.
If you omit the &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; in your regular expression the match will fail.
The example below&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Doesn't match, because omits the `/`
const pattern1 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(b.*)" });
console.log(pattern1.test("https://example.com/b")); // false
console.log(pattern1.test("https://example.com/ba")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following examples include the &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Matches URL where path is exactly "/b"
const pattern2 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(/b)" });
console.log(pattern2.test("https://example.com/b")); // true
console.log(pattern2.test("https://example.com/ba")); // false

// Matches URL where path is /b followed by any number of characters
const pattern3 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(/b.*)" });
console.log(pattern3.test("https://example.com/b")); // true
console.log(pattern3.test("https://example.com/ba")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Start and end of line anchors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The start of line anchor (&lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt;) and end-of line anchor (&lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt;) are used to anchor patterns to the start and end of the test string, respectively.
While these can be specified for the start and end of a URL-part they are redundant.
This is because all URL-parts are implicitly preceded by the &lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt; anchor, and followed by the &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; anchor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following code demonstrates that it doesn't matter whether or not &lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt; is specified.
The example uses a pattern in the &lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt; URL-part, but the other parts of the URL behave the same.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// with `^` in protocol
const pattern1 = new URLPattern({ protocol: "(^https?)" });
console.log(pattern1.test("https://example.com/index.html")); // true

// without `^` in protocol
const pattern2 = new URLPattern({ protocol: "(https?)" });
console.log(pattern2.test("https://example.com/index.html")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code below demonstrates that it doesn't matter whether or not &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; is specified.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// with `$` in pathname
const pattern1 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(/path$)" });
console.log(pattern1.test("https://example.com/path")); // true

// without `$` in pathname
const pattern2 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(/path)" });
console.log(pattern2.test("https://example.com/path")); // true

// with `$` in hash
const pattern3 = new URLPattern({ hash: "(/hash$)" });
console.log(pattern3.test("https://example.com/#hash")); // true

// without `$` in hash
const pattern4 = new URLPattern({ hash: "(/hash)" });
console.log(pattern4.test("https://example.com/#hash")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Lookahead and lookbehind assertions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lookahead and lookbehind asserts allow you to specify that text ahead or behind the current parsing position matches a particular pattern, without that match being captured, or the characters being consumed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are four types of assertions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;(?=...)&lt;/code&gt;: A positive lookahead assertion specifies a pattern that the following characters must match.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;(?!...)&lt;/code&gt;: A negative lookahead assertion specifies a pattern that the following characters must not match.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;(?&amp;lt;=...)&lt;/code&gt;: A positive lookbehind assertion specifies a pattern that the preceding characters must match.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;(?&amp;lt;!...)&lt;/code&gt;: A negative lookbehind assertion specifies a pattern that the preceding characters must not match.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be careful when using lookahead and lookbehind assertions with &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt;, as there is some behavior you may find unintuitive.
For example, you would expect the following lookahead assertion to match a &lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt; of &lt;code&gt;/ab&lt;/code&gt;, but this is not what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(/a(?=b))" });
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/ab")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt; engine matches the test string against the &lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt; pattern, first finding the match for &lt;code&gt;/a&lt;/code&gt; and then asserts that the next character in the test URL is &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; â but not consuming it.
The engine continues matching the test URL at the unconsumed character &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;, but there is nothing left in the pattern to match it against, which causes the match to fail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the match to work the pattern has to consume all the characters in the test string. To consume the &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; character you could add &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; to the end of the expression, a &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; to match any character, or &lt;code&gt;.*&lt;/code&gt; to match all characters after the lookahead assertion:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// positive-lookahead
const pattern1 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(/a(?=b).*)" });
console.log(pattern1.test("https://example.com/ab")); // true
console.log(pattern1.test("https://example.com/ax")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next example shows a negative lookahead match for &lt;code&gt;/a&lt;/code&gt; which is not followed by &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;.
Note that the assertion is followed by &lt;code&gt;.*&lt;/code&gt; to consume the character matched by the assertion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// negative-lookahead - matches /a&amp;lt;not b&amp;gt;&amp;lt;anything&amp;gt;
const pattern2 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(/a(?!b).*)" });
console.log(pattern2.test("https://example.com/ab")); // false
console.log(pattern2.test("https://example.com/ax")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows a positive lookbehind match that matches on a pathname like &lt;code&gt;/ba&lt;/code&gt;.
The pattern matches &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;, then &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; to consume the next character, followed by the assertion that the previous character was a &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;, and then an &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// positive-lookbehind
const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(/.(?&amp;lt;=b)a)" });
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/ba")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/xa")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This example shows a negative lookbehind match that matches on a pathname like &lt;code&gt;/&amp;lt;not b&amp;gt;a&lt;/code&gt;.
The pattern matches &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;, then &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; to consume the next character (&lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt;), followed by the assertion that the previous character was not &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;, and then an &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// negative-lookbehind
const pattern4 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "(/.*(?&amp;lt;!b)a)" });
console.log(pattern4.test("https://example.com/ba")); // false
console.log(pattern4.test("https://example.com/xa")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Other regex matcher limitations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some other regex patterns may not work as you may expect:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parentheses need to be escaped in range expressions within URLPattern even though they don't in RegExp.&lt;/p&gt;js&lt;code&gt;new URLPattern({ pathname: "([()])" }); // throws new URLPattern({ pathname: "([\\(\\)])" }); // ok new RegExp("[()]"); // ok new RegExp("[\\(\\)]"); // ok&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Unnamed and named groups&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Groups can either be named or unnamed. Named groups are specified by prefixing the group name with a colon (&lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt;).
Regex groups that are not prefixed by a colon and a name are unnamed. Unnamed groups are numerically indexed in the match result based on their order in the pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A named group
const pattern = new URLPattern("/books/:id(\\d+)", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.exec("https://example.com/books/123").pathname.groups); // { id: '123' }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// An unnamed group
const pattern = new URLPattern("/books/(\\d+)", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.exec("https://example.com/books/123").pathname.groups); // { '0': '123' }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Group modifiers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Groups can also have modifiers. These are specified after the group name (or after the regex if there is one). There are three modifiers: &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; to make the group optional, &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; to make the group repeat one or more times, and &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; to make the group repeat zero or more times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// An optional group
const pattern = new URLPattern("/books/:id?", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/456")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/456/789")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A repeating group with a minimum of one
const pattern = new URLPattern("/books/:id+", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/456")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/456/789")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A repeating group with a minimum of zero
const pattern = new URLPattern("/books/:id*", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/456")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/456/789")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Group delimiters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Patterns can also contain group delimiters. These are pieces of a pattern that are surrounded by curly braces (&lt;code&gt;{}&lt;/code&gt;).
These group delimiters are not captured in the match result like capturing groups, but can still have modifiers applied to them, just like groups.
If group delimiters are not modified by a modifier, they are treated as if the items in them were just part of the parent pattern.
Group delimiters may not contain other group delimiters, but may contain any other pattern items (capturing groups, regex, wildcard, or fixed text).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A group delimiter with a ? (optional) modifier
const pattern = new URLPattern("/book{s}?", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/book")); // true
console.log(pattern.exec("https://example.com/books").pathname.groups); // {}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A group delimiter without a modifier
const pattern = new URLPattern("/book{s}", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.pathname); // /books
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/book")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A group delimiter containing a capturing group
const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/blog/:id(\\d+){-:title}?" });
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/blog/123-my-blog")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/blog/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/blog/my-blog")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Automatic group prefixing in pathnames&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In patterns that match against the &lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt; part of a URL, groups get an automatic slash (&lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;) prefix added if the group definition is preceded by a slash (&lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;).
This is useful for groups with modifiers, as it allows for repeating groups to work as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you do not want automatic prefixing, you can disable it by surrounding the group with group delimiters (&lt;code&gt;{}&lt;/code&gt;).
Group delimiters do not have automatic prefixing behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A pattern with an optional group, preceded by a slash
const pattern = new URLPattern("/books/:id?", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A pattern with a repeating group, preceded by a slash
const pattern = new URLPattern("/books/:id+", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/456")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/456/")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Segment prefixing does not occur outside of pathname patterns
const pattern = new URLPattern({ hash: "/books/:id?" });
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com#/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com#/books")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com#/books/")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Disabling segment prefixing for a group using a group delimiter
const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/books/{:id}?" });
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Wildcard tokens&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The wildcard token (&lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt;) is a shorthand for an unnamed capturing group that matches all characters zero or more times.
You can place this anywhere in the pattern.
The wildcard is greedy, meaning that it will match the longest possible string.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A wildcard at the end of a pattern
const pattern = new URLPattern("/books/*", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/books/123/456")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// A wildcard in the middle of a pattern
const pattern = new URLPattern("/*.png", "https://example.com");
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/image.png")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/image.png/123")); // false
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/folder/image.png")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/.png")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Trailing slashes in pathname are not matched by default&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trailing slashes in a pathname are not automatically matched. The example below demonstrates that a &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt; match for a pathname of &lt;code&gt;/books&lt;/code&gt; will match &lt;code&gt;https://example.com/books&lt;/code&gt; but not &lt;code&gt;https://example.com/books/&lt;/code&gt; (and vice versa):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const patternSlash = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/books/" });
console.log(patternSlash.test("https://example.com/books")); // false
console.log(patternSlash.test("https://example.com/books/")); // true

const patternNoSlash = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/books" });
console.log(patternNoSlash.test("https://example.com/books")); // true
console.log(patternNoSlash.test("https://example.com/books/")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to match both then you need to use a match pattern that allows either. The easiest approach is to use a group delimiter that contains a forward slash, followed by the optional modifier. This will match the pattern with or without a terminating forward slash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const patternOptionalSlash = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/books{/}?" });
console.log(patternOptionalSlash.test("https://example.com/books")); // true
console.log(patternOptionalSlash.test("https://example.com/books/")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Pattern normalization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a pattern is parsed it is automatically normalized to a canonical form. For example, Unicode characters are percent-encoded in the pathname property, punycode encoding is used in the hostname, default port numbers are elided, paths like &lt;code&gt;/foo/./bar/&lt;/code&gt; are collapsed to &lt;code&gt;/foo/bar&lt;/code&gt;, etc.
In addition, there are some pattern representations that parse to the same underlying meaning, like &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;{foo}&lt;/code&gt;.
Such cases are normalized to the simplest form.
In this case &lt;code&gt;{foo}&lt;/code&gt; is normalized to &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt;, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Inheritance from a base URL&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both the match patterns defined in &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt; and the test URLs used in &lt;code&gt;URLPattern.test()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;URLPattern.exec()&lt;/code&gt; allow the inputs to be specified with an optional base URL (this base URL is a separate parameter when specifying the URL as a string, and a separate property when specifying the URL as an object).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If a base URL is defined then URL-parts may be inherited from the base URL and used to set parts of the pattern or test URL. URL resolution is much the same as you would expect when resolving a &lt;code&gt;URL&lt;/code&gt; that is specified with a base URL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;username&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;password&lt;/code&gt; are never inherited from the base URL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only URL parts that are "more specific" than the most-specific part defined in the input will be inherited from the base URL. The following lists show the order of specificity:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt;(most specific),&lt;code&gt;hostname&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;port&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;search&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;hash&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;hostname&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;port&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;username&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;password&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What this means, for example, is that if the &lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt; is specified in the input URL, then nothing is more specific, so nothing will be inherited from the base URL.
However if the &lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt; part is specified in the input, the &lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;hostname&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;port&lt;/code&gt; may be inherited from the base URL, but the &lt;code&gt;search&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;hash&lt;/code&gt; will not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that URL components that are not specified in the string/input object or inherited from the base URL will default to the wildcard value (&lt;code&gt;"*"&lt;/code&gt;) for a &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt; and to the empty string (&lt;code&gt;""&lt;/code&gt;) for a test URL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Case sensitivity&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The URL Pattern API treats many parts of the URL as case-sensitive by default when matching. In contrast, many client-side JavaScript frameworks use case-insensitive URL matching. An &lt;code&gt;ignoreCase&lt;/code&gt; option is available on the &lt;code&gt;URLPattern()&lt;/code&gt; constructor to enable case-insensitive matching if desired.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Case-sensitive matching by default
const pattern = new URLPattern("https://example.com/2022/feb/*");
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/2022/feb/xc44rsz")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/2022/Feb/xc44rsz")); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setting the &lt;code&gt;ignoreCase&lt;/code&gt; option to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; in the constructor switches all matching operations to case-insensitive for the given pattern:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Case-insensitive matching
const pattern = new URLPattern("https://example.com/2022/feb/*", {
  ignoreCase: true,
});
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/2022/feb/xc44rsz")); // true
console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/2022/Feb/xc44rsz")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Examples&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Filter on a specific URL component&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how a &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt; filters a specific URL component.
When the &lt;code&gt;URLPattern()&lt;/code&gt; constructor is called with a structured object of component patterns any missing components default to the &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; wildcard value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Construct a URLPattern that matches a specific domain and its subdomains.
// All other URL components default to the wildcard `*` pattern.
const pattern = new URLPattern({
  hostname: "{*.}?example.com",
});

console.log(pattern.hostname); // '{*.}?example.com'

console.log(pattern.protocol); // '*'
console.log(pattern.port); // '*'
console.log(pattern.username); // '*'
console.log(pattern.password); // '*'
console.log(pattern.pathname); // '*'
console.log(pattern.search); // '*'
console.log(pattern.hash); // '*'

console.log(pattern.test("https://example.com/foo/bar")); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ hostname: "cdn.example.com" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test("custom-protocol://example.com/other/path?q=1")); // true

// Prints `false` because the hostname component does not match
console.log(pattern.test("https://cdn-example.com/foo/bar"));
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Construct a URLPattern from a full URL string&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how to construct a &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt; from a full URL string with embedded patterns.
For example, a &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; can be both the URL protocol suffix, like &lt;code&gt;https:&lt;/code&gt;, and the beginning of a named pattern group, like &lt;code&gt;:foo&lt;/code&gt;.
It "just works" if there is no ambiguity between whether a character is part of the URL syntax or part of the pattern syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Construct a URLPattern that matches URLs to CDN servers loading jpg images.
// URL components not explicitly specified result in the wild string ("*")
const pattern = new URLPattern("https://cdn-*.example.com/*.jpg");

console.log(pattern.protocol); // 'https'
console.log(pattern.hostname); // 'cdn-*.example.com'
console.log(pattern.pathname); // '/*.jpg'

console.log(pattern.username); // '*'
console.log(pattern.password); // '*'
console.log(pattern.search); // '*'
console.log(pattern.hash); // '*'

// `true`
console.log(
  pattern.test("https://cdn-1234.example.com/product/assets/hero.jpg"),
);

// `true` because the search pattern defaults to wildcard
console.log(
  pattern.test("https://cdn-1234.example.com/product/assets/hero.jpg?q=1"),
);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Constructing a URLPattern with an ambiguous URL string&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how a &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt; constructed from an ambiguous string will favor treating characters as part of the pattern syntax.
In this case the &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; character could be the protocol component suffix or it could be the prefix for a named group in the pattern.
The constructor chooses to treat this as part of the pattern and therefore determines this is a relative pathname pattern.
Since there is no base URL the relative pathname cannot be resolved and it throws an error.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Throws because this is interpreted as a single relative pathname pattern
// with a ":foo" named group and there is no base URL.
const pattern = new URLPattern("data:foo*");
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Escaping characters to disambiguate URLPattern constructor strings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how an ambiguous constructor string character can be escaped to be treated as a URL separator instead of a pattern character. Here &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; is escaped as &lt;code&gt;\\:&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Constructs a URLPattern treating the `:` as the protocol suffix.
const pattern = new URLPattern("data\\:foo*");

console.log(pattern.protocol); // 'data'
console.log(pattern.pathname); // 'foo*'
console.log(pattern.username); // '*'
console.log(pattern.password); // '*'
console.log(pattern.hostname); // ''
console.log(pattern.port); // ''
console.log(pattern.search); // '*'
console.log(pattern.hash); // '*'

console.log(pattern.test("data:foobar")); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Using base URLs for test() and exec()&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how &lt;code&gt;test()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;exec()&lt;/code&gt; can use base URLs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ hostname: "example.com", pathname: "/foo/*" });

console.log(pattern.protocol); // '*'
console.log(pattern.pathname); // '/foo/*'
console.log(pattern.username); // '*'
console.log(pattern.password); // '*'
console.log(pattern.hostname); // 'example.com'
console.log(pattern.port); // '*'
console.log(pattern.search); // '*'
console.log(pattern.hash); // '*'

// `true` as the hostname is inherited from `baseURL` property
// (so is the protocol, but that is matched by the pattern wildcard)
console.log(
  pattern.test({
    pathname: "/foo/bar",
    baseURL: "https://example.com/baz",
  }),
);

// Prints `true` as the hostname in the second argument base URL matches.
console.log(pattern.test("/foo/bar", "https://example.com/baz"));

// Throws because the second argument cannot be passed with the object input.
try {
  pattern.test({ pathname: "/foo/bar" }, "https://example.com/baz");
} catch (e) {}

// The `exec()` method takes the same arguments as `test()`.
const result = pattern.exec("/foo/bar", "https://example.com/baz");
console.log(result.pathname.input); // '/foo/bar'
console.log(result.pathname.groups[0]); // 'bar'
console.log(result.hostname.input); // 'example.com'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Using base URLs in the URLPattern constructor&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how base URLs can also be used to construct the &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt;.
The base URL is treated strictly as a URL and cannot contain any pattern syntax itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pattern only inherits URL parts from the base URL that are less specific than those in the other properties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case the &lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt; is specified so the protocol and host can be inherited, but not the search, hash, username, or password.
The properties that are not inherited default to the wildcard string (&lt;code&gt;"*"&lt;/code&gt;).
The exception is the port, which is set to the empty string because the hostname is inherited from the base URL (which has an implied "default port" value).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern1 = new URLPattern({
  pathname: "/foo/*",
  baseURL: "https://example.com",
});

console.log(pattern1.protocol); // 'https'
console.log(pattern1.hostname); // 'example.com'
console.log(pattern1.pathname); // '/foo/*'
console.log(pattern1.username); // '*'
console.log(pattern1.password); // '*'
console.log(pattern1.port); // ''
console.log(pattern1.search); // '*'
console.log(pattern1.hash); // '*'

// Equivalent to pattern1
const pattern2 = new URLPattern("/foo/*", "https://example.com");

// Throws because a relative constructor string must have a base URL to resolve
// against.
try {
  const pattern3 = new URLPattern("/foo/*");
} catch (e) {}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Accessing matched group values&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how input values that match pattern groups can later be accessed from the &lt;code&gt;exec()&lt;/code&gt; result object.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;input&lt;/code&gt; property is the string that is matched by the pattern: in this case it's &lt;code&gt;cdn.example.com&lt;/code&gt;.
The &lt;code&gt;groups&lt;/code&gt; property contains captured groups, indexed by number for unnamed groups, and name for named groups.
In this case, there is only one unnamed group for the wildcard property, with the value &lt;code&gt;cdn&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ hostname: "*.example.com" });
const result = pattern.exec({ hostname: "cdn.example.com" });

console.log(result.hostname); // {"groups": {"0": "cdn"}, "input": "cdn.example.com"}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Accessing matched named group values&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how groups can be given custom names which can be used to access the matched value in the result object.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The match patterns in the pattern are indicated by the &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; symbol followed by a name.
The same names then appear as keys in the &lt;code&gt;groups&lt;/code&gt; property, with the matching values being the matched part of the test URL.
The &lt;code&gt;input&lt;/code&gt; property contains the whole part of the URL that matched the &lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt; pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Construct a URLPattern using matching groups with custom names.

const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/:product/:user/:action" });
const result = pattern.exec({ pathname: "/store/wanderview/view" });

console.log(result.pathname);
/*
{
    "groups": {
        "product": "store",
        "user": "wanderview",
        "action": "view"
    },
    "input": "/store/wanderview/view"
}
*/

// These names can then be later used to access the matched values
// in the result object, such as "user" below.
console.log(result.pathname.groups.user); // 'wanderview'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Regular expression with unnamed group&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how a matching group can use a regular expression to match either &lt;code&gt;/foo&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;/bar&lt;/code&gt; in a test URL.
The group is unnamed, so will be referenced by an index number in the result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/(foo|bar)" });

console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/foo" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/bar" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/baz" })); // false

const result = pattern.exec({ pathname: "/foo" });
console.log(result.pathname.groups[0]); // 'foo'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Regular expression with a named group&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how to use a custom regular expression with a named group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The group is named &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt;, and matches a path which is either &lt;code&gt;/foo&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;/bar&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/:type(foo|bar)" });
const result = pattern.exec({ pathname: "/foo" });

console.log(result.pathname.groups.type); // 'foo'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Making matching groups optional&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how to make a matching group optional by placing a &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; modifier after it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the pathname component this also causes any preceding &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; character to be treated as an optional prefix to the group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/product/(index.html)?" });

console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product/index.html" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product" })); // true

const pattern2 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/product/:action?" });

console.log(pattern2.test({ pathname: "/product/view" })); // true
console.log(pattern2.test({ pathname: "/product" })); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wildcards can be made optional as well. This may not seem to make sense since they already match the empty string, but it also makes the prefix &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; optional in a pathname pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern3 = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/product/*?" });

console.log(pattern3.test({ pathname: "/product/wanderview/view" })); // true
console.log(pattern3.test({ pathname: "/product" })); // true
console.log(pattern3.test({ pathname: "/product/" })); // true
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Making matching groups repeated&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how a matching group can be made repeated by placing a &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; modifier after it.
In the &lt;code&gt;pathname&lt;/code&gt; component this also treats the &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; prefix as special, so that it is effectively the start of the repeating group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/product/:action+" });
const result = pattern.exec({ pathname: "/product/do/some/thing/cool" });

console.log(result.pathname);
// { "groups": { "action": "do/some/thing/cool" }, "input": "/product/do/some/thing/cool" }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;code&gt;/product&lt;/code&gt; does not match because it is not followed by &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; and at least one character.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product" })); // false
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product/" })); // false
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product/do" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product/do/" })); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Making matching groups optional and repeated&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how to make a matching group that is both optional and repeated. Do this by placing a &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; modifier after the group.
Again, the pathname component treats the &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; prefix as special.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It both becomes optional and is also repeated with the group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/product/:action*" });
const result = pattern.exec({ pathname: "/product/do/some/thing/cool" });

console.log(result.pathname);
// { "groups": { "action": "do/some/thing/cool" }, "input": "/product/do/some/thing/cool" }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that unlike the previous example, &lt;code&gt;/product&lt;/code&gt; matches because the repeating segments, including &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; are optional.
However there must be at least one character to capture after a forward slash to match the repeating group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product/" })); // false
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product/do" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product/do/" })); // false
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Using a custom prefix or suffix for an optional or repeated modifier&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how curly braces (a group delimiter) can be with a named group to denote a custom prefix and/or suffix to be operated on by a subsequent &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; modifier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;code&gt;{:subdomain.}*&lt;/code&gt; matches against any subdomain of &lt;code&gt;example.com&lt;/code&gt; and the domain itself.
The match is assigned to the named group "subdomain".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ hostname: "{:subdomain.}*example.com" });
const result = pattern.exec({ hostname: "foo.bar.example.com" });

console.log(pattern.test({ hostname: "example.com" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ hostname: "foo.bar.example.com" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ hostname: ".example.com" })); // false

console.log(result.hostname);
// { "groups": { "subdomain": "foo.bar" }, "input": "foo.bar.example.com" }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Making text optional or repeated without a matching group&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how curly braces can be used to denote fixed text values as optional or repeated without using a matching group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pattern below matches either &lt;code&gt;/product&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;/product/&lt;/code&gt; but because group delimiter are non-capturing by default, the result is not found in a corresponding match group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({ pathname: "/product{/}?" });

console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product" })); // true
console.log(pattern.test({ pathname: "/product/" })); // true

const result = pattern.exec({ pathname: "/product/" });
console.log(result.pathname.groups); // {}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Using multiple components and features at once&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following example shows how many features can be combined across multiple URL components.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const pattern = new URLPattern({
  protocol: "http{s}?",
  username: ":user?",
  password: ":pass?",
  hostname: "{:subdomain.}*example.com",
  pathname: "/product/:action*",
});

const result = pattern.exec(
  "http://foo:bar@sub.example.com/product/view?q=12345",
);

console.log(result.username.groups.user); // 'foo'
console.log(result.password.groups.pass); // 'bar'
console.log(result.hostname.groups.subdomain); // 'sub'
console.log(result.pathname.groups.action); // 'view'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Specifications&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Specification&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;URL Pattern&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Browser compatibility&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;See also&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A polyfill of &lt;code&gt;URLPattern&lt;/code&gt;is available on GitHub&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The pattern syntax used by URLPattern is similar to the syntax used by path-to-regexp&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/URL_Pattern_API"/><published>2025-12-25T20:27:45+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46387164</id><title>Memory Safety</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:37.369103+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="5adb59997e9791e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;TLS (Rustls)&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's get the Rustls TLS library ready to replace OpenSSL in as many projects as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's get the Rustls TLS library ready to replace OpenSSL in as many projects as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's create a memory safe, high performance, fully recursive DNS resolver.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's make the utilities that mediate privileges safer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's create a memory safe NTP implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's create a memory safe AV1 decoder that delivers great performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's create a memory safe zlib compression library with great performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's make it possible to write memory safe drivers for the Linux kernel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's make the network edge memory safe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's make it possible to use memory safe TLS networking in Apache httpd.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's make TLS and HTTP networking code in curl memory safe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's improve the tools we use to bring memory safe software to the world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating error messages that are clear and detailed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Rust Foundation just announced the launch of the Rust Innovation Lab, with the Rustls TLS library as the inaugural hosted project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hickory DNS is getting support for RFC 9539 opportunistic encryption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We're in the beginning phases of a journey towards memory safety for the Internet's critical software infrastructure, and as we get going it makes the most sense to break down big problems into smaller ones by focusing on replacing components within existing C and C++ software.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being part of ambitious work like Prossimo is easier than you might think: 100% of our funding comes from charitable donations from companies and people like you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you support Prossimo, you’re helping to create a future for the Web that is more memory safe and more secure - and that benefits everyone using it!&lt;/p&gt;Donate&lt;p&gt;Bring greater security to your organization by advocating for memory safe code in your organization!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many organizations match donations to nonprofits made by employees. Check if your organization has a matching program and double your impact!&lt;/p&gt;See if your organization has a matching program&lt;p&gt;Prossimo works to connect maintainers behind the Internet's most critical pieces of software with the people and organizations who want to see Internet security move forward by adopting memory safe languages. Here's the simple framework of how Prossimo works:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By funding, you can support this important work!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contact us to learn about upcoming Prossimo initiatives: donate@abetterinternet.org&lt;/p&gt;Support this Work&lt;p&gt;Appreciated securities or mutual fund shares that you’ve owned for more than one year can be excellent charitable gifts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Brokerage Firm:&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Vanguard&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Account Name:&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Internet Security Research Group&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;ISRG Account #:&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;44865458&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;DTC #:&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0062&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Tax ID #:&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;46-3344200&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please let us know if you are transferring securities at donate@abetterinternet.org. You may also want to email the letter of authorization from your broker.&lt;/p&gt;Gifts of Cryptocurrency&lt;p&gt;We accept BTC, BCH, ETH, DOGE, WBTC, and all other currencies supported by BitPay. We are able to accept donations equivalent to $1,000 USD or greater. Please email donate@abetterinternet.org for invoicing.&lt;/p&gt;Donor Advised Funds&lt;p&gt;Recommend a donation to Internet Security Research Group (our parent org) from your gift fund. 100% of your donation will go to support a secure and privacy-respecting Internet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.memorysafety.org/"/><published>2025-12-25T21:31:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46387192</id><title>Google is 'gradually rolling out' option to change your gmail.com address</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:37.220459+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6eadb953b176bf41"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a Google support page, the company says it is rolling out a new option to let users change their email address even if it is an “@gmail.com” address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For quite some time now, Google has allowed users to change their account email address if they are using a third-party email address, but users with an “@gmail.com” address are left unable to change it, as Google says:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If your account’s email address ends in @gmail.com, you usually can’t change it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It appears this is changing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the same support page that currently says that you usually can’t change your email, Google is detailing a new process that is “gradually rolling out.” The altered page weirdly only shows in Hindi at the moment, meaning you can’t see the changes in English. Everything quoted below is translated. The page was first spotted in the “Google Pixel Hub” group on Telegram.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google explains:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The email address associated with your Google Account is the address you use to sign in to Google services. This email address helps you and others identify your account. If you’d like, you can change your Google Account email address that ends in gmail.com to a new email address that ends in gmail.com.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is new functionality that Google hasn’t detailed elsewhere yet, but says is “gradually rolling out to all users.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this change, Google will allow users to change their “@gmail.com” email address to a new “@gmail.com” address with an altered username. After changing, Google details that your original email address will still receive emails at the same inbox as your new one and work for sign-in, and that none of your account access will change. Users will be unable to change or delete their email within 12 months of the change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When you change your Google Account email address from an email address ending in gmail.com to a new email address ending in gmail.com:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The old email address in your Google Account that ends with gmail.com will be set as an alias. Learn more about alias email addresses .&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You will receive emails at both your old and new email addresses.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Data saved in your account, including photos, messages, and emails sent to your old email address, will not be affected.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can reuse your old Google Account email address at any time. However, you can’t create a new Google Account email address that ends with gmail.com for the next 12 months. You can’t delete your new email address either.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can sign in to Google services like Gmail, Maps, YouTube, Google Play, or Drive with your old or new email address.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each account can only change its “@gmail.com” address up to 3 times for a total of 4 addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google further details that your old Gmail address will still appear in some cases, and “won’t be immediately reflected in older instances” such as events on Calendar created before the change. You’ll also still be able to send emails from the old address. The old address remains yours and cannot be used by another user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Top comment by TurboFool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Huge if true. Many of us have had Gmail since the beginning when we didn't know it would matter this much. And many others got their accounts as kids under the same lack of realization. And some people have changed their names.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The page is very detailed on the process, but the changes just aren’t live yet. Presumably, this support page detailing the process in Hindi went up a little earlier than intended, but it certainly seems that we’ll be hearing more about this change in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the functionality goes live, users will be able to change their Gmail address via “My Account.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll update this article if further information comes out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More on Gmail:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Google says Gemini isn’t trained on Gmail, pushing back on ‘misleading reports’&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gmail for Android notifications adding photo &amp;amp; attachment previews&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gmail adding unread dots as Google Tasks gets deadlines&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow Ben: Twitter/X, Threads, Bluesky, and Instagram&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links. More.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://9to5google.com/2025/12/24/google-change-gmail-addresses/"/><published>2025-12-25T21:36:48+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46387657</id><title>Maybe the default settings are too high</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:37.090131+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e65b52868faaab9c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading Lord of the Rings for two months and I’m just at the end of the first part. It’s not because I’m not enjoying it. It’s one of the most enjoyable reading experiences I can remember.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the beginning, I’ve read the whole thing aloud. I’ve found reading aloud helpful for staying engaged — limiting myself to mouth-speed rather than eye-speed means I won’t rush, miss important details, and then lose interest, which has always been a problem for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At first I was anxious to read a 1,500-page book this way, because it would take so long. But, as someone pointed out to me, if I’m enjoying it, why would I want to be done with it sooner?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I tried slowing down even more, and discovered something. I slowed to a pace that felt almost absurd, treating each sentence as though it might be a particularly important one. I gave each one maybe triple the usual time and attention, ignoring the fact that there are hundreds of pages to go.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This leisurely pace made Middle-Earth blossom before my eyes. When I paused after each comma, and let each sentence ring for a small moment after the period, the events of the story reached me with more weight and strength. That extra time gave space for Tolkien’s images and moods to propagate in my mind, which they did automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some part of me still wanted to rush and get on with it, to make good time, to gloss over the songs and lore to get to Moria and Mount Doom and the other marquee moments of the story. But the more I ignored that impulse, the better the experience got.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By offering the book about triple the usual amount of attentiveness, I was getting about triple the storyness (i.e. meaning, engagement, literary pleasure). Whatever the thing is that I’m seeking when I pick up a novel in the first place, there’s much more of it available at this pace.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Eating Comprehension&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This effect reminded me of a paradox around eating I recognized long ago. When you slow down your eating speed, say to half or a third your default speed, you get much more enjoyment out of a smaller amount of food. The extra attention given to each bite allows more of the “good stuff,” whatever that is exactly, to reach you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s paradoxical is that it’s precisely the seeking of that “good stuff” that normally drives me to eat so quickly, and miss most of what I’m seeking. When you try to barrel ahead to access the good stuff quicker, you get less of it in the end. Slow down and much more of it is released.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it’s released automatically, in both reading and eating. You don’t have to search it out. The good stuff (the meaning in the text, the pleasure in the eating) just rises up to meet you in that extra time you give it. Slowing down, and offering more time to the act of consumption, immediately increases reading comprehension (and eating comprehension).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both are analogous to slowing down while you vacuum a carpet. If you pass the vacuum head too quickly, you miss half the dirt. Slow down, and you can hear how much more grit is sent skittering up the tube. The suction and bristles are working, but they need more time to do their work fully, to draw up the deeper-lying stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Question the default settings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems that my default consumption speeds for reading and eating (and maybe everything else) reduce the rewards of those things significantly, undermining the point of doing either.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part of it is my own impatience. But I also suspect that modern living, with its infinite supply of consumables, tends to push our rate-of-intake dials too high. I’m not going to run out of books, or snacks, or opportunities to learn something. There’s always more, so not every crust of bread or printed page needs to be appreciated fully.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Internally though, the mind is juggling like Lucy and Ethel on the conveyor belt at the chocolate factory. Our receptors for meaning and appreciation, like the vacuum head, need more time to do their full work, to make all the connections they’re designed to make.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It might sound like I’m just offering clichés – less is more, stop and smell the roses, take your time – and I guess I am. But clichés suffer the same issue: they are often profound insights, consumed and passed on too rapidly for their real meaning to register anymore. You really should stop and smell roses, as you know if you’re in the habit of doing that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At least see what happens when you reduce your consumption speed – of anything, but especially books, information, and food – by a half, or two thirds. Notice that (1) something in you really wants to plow through at the highest viable setting, and (2) how much more of the reward is released when you slow down anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, almost everything becomes more satisfying when you give it more time and intention, even things like checking the mailbox or writing a shopping list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Speed alters taste&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Slowing down your rate of consumption will inevitably change what you want to consume. Reading throwaway news articles or AI slop with great care and attention is only going to show you how empty of value it is. Reading dense writing in inky old books, crafted for your mind by great masters, becomes easier without the rushed pace, and the meaning just blooms out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Same with food. Try to savor a cheap, waxy “chocolate” bar, or a bag of store-brand cheese puffs, and you discover a harsh taste that you don’t want to look at too closely. Enjoy a homemade pastry with great attention, and discover there’s even more in it than you realized.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mass production is good in so many ways, but the faster we tend to consume its fruits, the more we end up seeking things for their glossy, candied surfaces. The more we go for these surface-level rewards, the more the culture focuses on offering only that part – such as TikTok videos, processed food, CGI-forward movies, and public discourse in the form of unexamined talking points.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Who knows how far we’ve drifted from the best modes of consuming the things we value. Once something becomes a norm, it seems like an appropriate standard, no matter how much has been lost. Apparently, reading silently and alone was unusual until as late as the 18th century. Certainly sit-down meals and cooking at home were.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t mean to sound like a scold. Let’s say none of this is morally good or bad. It’s just that in so much of what we do, we could be getting much more of the part of it that we really seek — but it’s only available at slower speeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re curious, try consuming things more slowly, so slowly it seems silly to others — say a third your habitual speed — and see what rises up to meet you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;***&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Want to quit something in January?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently I opened a discussion forum for Raptitude readers who want to give something up for the month of December (alcohol, social media, snacks, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s been a real success, and many people want to do something similar in January. If you want to quit something, or just give it up for a month, you’re invited to join.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow this link at the end of this post to get an invite.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.raptitude.com/2025/12/maybe-the-default-settings-are-too-high/"/><published>2025-12-25T23:13:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46387838</id><title>No shares in company, but 550 employees received a $240M gift from their owner</title><updated>2025-12-26T00:53:36.685094+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6a4311fa0a7a1fec"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;As reported by The Wall Street Journal, Fibrebond, a family-owned firm based in Minden, Louisiana, was acquired by power management giant Eaton in a deal valued at about $1.7 billion. What made the transaction extraordinary was a clause insisted upon by Fibrebond chief executive Graham Walker: 15 percent of the sale proceeds would be distributed among full-time employees.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Loyalty rewarded, not ownership&lt;/head&gt;The decision meant that roughly 550 employees, many of whom had spent decades at the company, shared bonuses averaging around $443,000, paid over five years. Long-serving staff members received substantially higher amounts. None of them owned shares in the business.&lt;p&gt;Walker told The Wall Street Journal that the payout was meant to recognise commitment rather than ownership. Employees had endured factory fires, layoffs, salary freezes and years when orders were scarce. When the company struggled, they stayed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A company shaped by survival&lt;/head&gt;Founded in the early 1980s, Fibrebond’s journey has been far from smooth. It survived a devastating factory fire in the late 1990s, the collapse of the telecom boom and repeated downturns that forced painful cost-cutting. During those years, management focused on preserving jobs where possible and fostering a close-knit workplace culture.&lt;p&gt;Instead of individual performance bonuses, the company introduced group incentives tied to safety and operational targets. Employees described the environment as one where colleagues relied on one another to keep the business afloat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A risky pivot that paid off&lt;/head&gt;Fibrebond’s fortunes changed after a bold investment to expand into infrastructure for data centers. That bet paid off when demand surged during the Covid-19 pandemic and later accelerated with the growth of artificial intelligence and energy exports. Sales rose sharply, drawing interest from larger corporations.&lt;p&gt;When acquisition talks began, Walker made it clear that any buyer would need to honour his commitment to employees. Despite warnings from advisers and concerns about legal and tax complexities, he held firm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Shock, disbelief and relief&lt;/head&gt;The day employees learned the size of their bonuses was marked by disbelief. Some thought the announcement was a prank. Others broke down in tears as they realised the money could erase debts, fund retirements or finally provide financial stability.&lt;p&gt;While some workers noted the tax burden and the requirement to remain with the company to receive the full payout, most expressed gratitude. Few had expected more than a modest reward from the sale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eaton, announcing the completion of the acquisition, said the agreement respected Fibrebond’s commitments to its employees and community while strengthening Eaton’s position in fast-growing power infrastructure markets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Catch all the Business News, Breaking News, and Latest News Updates on The Economic Times.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subscribe to The Economic Times Prime and read the ET ePaper online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Catch all the Business News, Breaking News, and Latest News Updates on The Economic Times.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subscribe to The Economic Times Prime and read the ET ePaper online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/magazines/panache/no-shares-in-company-but-550-employees-received-a-240-million-gift-from-their-owner-for-staying-with-him-through-tough-times/articleshow/126175955.cms?from=mdr"/><published>2025-12-25T23:48:08+00:00</published></entry></feed>