<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:16.432671+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45953452</id><title>FreeMDU: Open-source Miele appliance diagnostic tools</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:25.440010+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="af8dedd4595f4be1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FreeMDU project provides open hardware and software tools for communicating with Miele appliances via their optical diagnostic interface. It serves as a free and open alternative to the proprietary Miele Diagnostic Utility (MDU) software, which is only available to registered service technicians.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most Miele devices manufactured after 1996 include an optical infrared-based diagnostic interface, hidden behind one of the indicator lights on the front panel. On older appliances, this interface is marked by a Program Correction (PC) label.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Until now, communication with this interface required an expensive infrared adapter sold exclusively by Miele, along with their closed-source software. The goal of FreeMDU is to make this interface accessible to everyone for diagnostic and home automation purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The project is split into three main components:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Protocol: core protocol library and device implementations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TUI: terminal-based device diagnostic and testing tool&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Home: communication adapter firmware with MQTT integration for Home Assistant&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More details about the proprietary diagnostic interface and the reverse-engineering process behind this project can be found in this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Caution&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is highly experimental and can cause permanent damage to your Miele devices if not used responsibly. Proceed at your own risk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a connection is established via the diagnostic interface, the appliance responds with its software ID, a 16-bit number that uniquely identifies the firmware version running on the device's microcontroller. However, this ID does not directly correspond to a specific model or board type, so it's impossible to provide a comprehensive list of supported models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following table lists the software IDs and device/board combinations that have been confirmed to work with FreeMDU:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Software ID&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Device&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Board&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Microcontroller&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Optical interface location&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Status&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;360&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bare board&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;EDPW 223-A&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mitsubishi M38078MC-065FP&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Check inlet (PC) indicator&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;🟢 Fully supported&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;419&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bare board&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;EDPW 206&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mitsubishi M37451MC-804FP&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Check inlet (PC) indicator&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;🟢 Fully supported&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;605&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;G 651 I PLUS-3&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;EGPL 542-C&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mitsubishi M38027M8&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Salt (PC) indicator&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;🟢 Fully supported&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;629&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;W 2446&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;EDPL 126-B&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mitsubishi M38079MF-308FP&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Check inlet (PC) indicator&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;🟢 Fully supported&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your appliance is not listed here but has a model number similar to one of the above, it might already be compatible. In all other cases, determining the software ID is the first step toward adding support for new devices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Details for adding support for new devices will be provided soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before using any FreeMDU components, make sure you have the Rust toolchain installed on your system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, you'll need to build a communication adapter to interface with your Miele device. Once the adapter is ready, choose the appropriate use case from the options below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to repair or test your appliance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Flash the home firmware in bridge mode onto your communication adapter and attach it to your device.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Run the TUI application on your desktop computer.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to integrate your appliance into Home Assistant or another home automation system:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Flash the home firmware in standalone mode onto your communication adapter and attach it to your device.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to develop your own software to communicate with Miele devices:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Flash the home firmware in bridge mode onto your communication adapter and attach it to your device.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Use the protocol crate to implement your custom software.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is an independent, open-source project and is not affiliated with, endorsed by, or sponsored by Miele &amp;amp; Cie. KG or its affiliates. All product names and trademarks are the property of their respective owners. References to Miele appliances are for descriptive purposes only and do not imply any association with Miele.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Licensed under either of&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apache License, Version 2.0 (LICENSE-APACHE or http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MIT license (LICENSE-MIT or http://opensource.org/licenses/MIT)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;at your option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unless you explicitly state otherwise, any contribution intentionally submitted for inclusion in the work by you, as defined in the Apache-2.0 license, shall be dual licensed as above, without any additional terms or conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/medusalix/FreeMDU"/><published>2025-11-17T13:40:40+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45954210</id><title>WeatherNext 2: Our most advanced weather forecasting model</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:25.121218+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3ff8f453711c2ba8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;WeatherNext 2: Our most advanced weather forecasting model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The weather affects important decisions we make everyday — from global supply chains and flight paths to your daily commute. In recent years, artificial intelligence (AI) has dramatically enhanced what’s possible in weather forecasting and the ways in which we can use it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, Google DeepMind and Google Research are introducing WeatherNext 2, our most advanced and efficient forecasting model. WeatherNext 2 can generate forecasts 8x faster and with resolution up to 1-hour. This breakthrough is enabled by a new model that can provide hundreds of possible scenarios. Using this technology, we’ve supported weather agencies in making decisions based on a range of scenarios through our experimental cyclone predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're now taking our research out of the lab and putting it into the hands of users. WeatherNext 2's forecast data is now available in Earth Engine and BigQuery. We’re also launching an early access program on Google Cloud’s Vertex AI platform for custom model inference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By incorporating WeatherNext technology, we’ve now upgraded weather forecasts in Search, Gemini, Pixel Weather and Google Maps Platform’s Weather API. In the coming weeks, it will also help power weather information in Google Maps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Predicting more possible scenarios&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From a single input, we use independently trained neural networks and inject noise in function space to create coherent variability in weather forecast predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weather predictions need to capture the full range of possibilities — including worst case scenarios, which are the most important to plan for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WeatherNext 2 can predict hundreds of possible weather outcomes from a single starting point. Each prediction takes less than a minute on a single TPU; it would take hours on a supercomputer using physics-based models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our model is also highly skillful and capable of higher-resolution predictions, down to the hour. Overall, WeatherNext 2 surpasses our previous state-of-the-art WeatherNext model on 99.9% of variables (e.g. temperature, wind, humidity) and lead times (0-15 days), enabling more useful and accurate forecasts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This improved performance is enabled by a new AI modelling approach called a Functional Generative Network (FGN), which injects ‘noise’ directly into the model architecture so the forecasts it generates remain physically realistic and interconnected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This approach is particularly useful for predicting what meteorologists refer to as “marginals” and “joints.” Marginals are individual, standalone weather elements: the precise temperature at a specific location, the wind speed at a certain altitude or the humidity. What's novel about our approach is that the model is only trained on these marginals. Yet, from that training, it learns to skillfully forecast 'joints' — large, complex, interconnected systems that depend on how all those individual pieces fit together. This 'joint' forecasting is required for our most useful predictions, such as identifying entire regions affected by high heat, or expected power output across a wind farm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Continuous Ranked Probability Score (CRPS) comparing WeatherNext 2 to WeatherNext Gen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;From research to reality&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With WeatherNext 2, we're translating cutting edge research into high-impact applications. We’re committed to advancing the state of the art of this technology and making our latest tools available to the global community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, we’re actively researching capabilities to improve our models, including integrating new data sources, and expanding access even further. By providing powerful tools and open data, we hope to accelerate scientific discovery and empower a global ecosystem of researchers, developers and businesses to make decisions on today’s most complex problems and build for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To learn more about geospatial platforms and AI work at Google, check out Google Earth, Earth Engine, AlphaEarth Foundations, and Earth AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Learn more about WeatherNext 2&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Read our paper&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WeatherNext developer documentation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Explore the Earth Engine Data Catalog&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Query forecast data in BigQuery&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sign up to the early access program for Cloud Vertex AI&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/weathernext-2/"/><published>2025-11-17T15:04:26+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45954640</id><title>Project Gemini</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:24.516416+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7b91a15fbb3f9295"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Project Gemini&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Gemini in 100 words&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini is a new internet technology supporting an electronic library of interconnected text documents. That's not a new idea, but it's not old fashioned either. It's timeless, and deserves tools which treat it as a first class concept, not a vestigial corner case. Gemini isn't about innovation or disruption, it's about providing some respite for those who feel the internet has been disrupted enough already. We're not out to change the world or destroy other technologies. We are out to build a lightweight online space where documents are just documents, in the interests of every reader's privacy, attention and bandwidth. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; If you'd like to know more, read our FAQ&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Or, if you'd prefer, here's a video overview &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Official resources&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Project Gemini news&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Project Gemini documentation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Project Gemini history&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Known Gemini software &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All content at geminiprotocol.net is CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 licensed unless stated otherwise:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; CC Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://geminiprotocol.net/"/><published>2025-11-17T15:50:04+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45955565</id><title>How when AWS was down, we were not</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:24.142337+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="765090565d2694dd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For help understanding this article or how you can implement auth and similar security architectures in your services, feel free to reach out to me via the community server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð¨ AWS us-east-1 is down!â&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the most massive AWS incidents transpired on October 20th. The long story short is that the DNS for DynamoDB was impacted for &lt;code&gt;us-east-1&lt;/code&gt;, which created a health event for the entire region. It's the worst incident we've seen in a decade. Disney+, Lyft, McDonald'ss, New York Times, Reddit, and the list goes on were lining up to claim their share too of the spotlight. And we've been watching because our product is part of our customers critical infrastructure. This one graph of the event says it all:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The AWS post-incident report indicates that at 7:48 PM UTC DynamoDB had "increased error rates". But this article isn't about AWS, and instead I want to share how exactly we were still up when when AWS was down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now you might be thinking: why are you running infra in us-east-1?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it's true, almost no one should be using us-east-1, unless, well, of course, you are us. And that's because we end up running our infrastructure where our customers are. In theory, practice and theory are the same, but in practice they differ. And if our (or your) customers chose &lt;code&gt;us-east-1&lt;/code&gt; in AWS, then realistically, that means you are also choosing us-east-1 ð.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During this time, us-east-1 was offline, and while we only run a limited amount of infrastructure in the region, we have to run it there because we have customers who want it there. And even without a direct dependency on &lt;code&gt;us-east-1&lt;/code&gt;, there are critical services in AWS â CloudFront, Certificate Manager, Lambda@Edge, and IAM â that all have their control planes in that region. Attempting to create distributions or roles at that time were also met with significant issues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since there are plenty of articles in the wild talking about what actually happened, why it happened, and why it will continue to happen, I don't need to go into it here. Instead, I'm going to share a dive about exactly what we've built to avoid these exact issues, and what you can do for your applications and platforms as well. In this article, I'll review how we maintain a high SLI to match our SLA reliability commitment even when the infrastructure and services we use don't.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð What is reliability?â&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before I get to the part where I share how we built one of the most reliable auth solutions available. I want to define reliability. And for us, that's an SLA of five nines. I think that's so extraordinary that the question I want you to keep in mind through this article is: is that actually possible? Is it really achievable to have a service with a five nines SLA? When I say five nines, I mean that 99.999% of the time, our service is up and running as expected by our customers. And to put this into perspective, the red, in the sea of blue, represents just how much time we can be down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And if you can't see it, it's hiding inside this black dot. It amounts to just five minutes and 15 seconds per year. This pretty much means we have to be up all the time, providing responses and functionality exactly as our customers expect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð¤ But why?â&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To put it into perspective, it's important to share for a moment, the specific challenges that we face, why we built what we built, and of course why that's relevant. To do that, I need to include some details about what we're building â what Authress actually does. Authress provides login and access control for the software applications that you write â It generates JWTs for your applications. This means:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;User authentication and authorization&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;User identities&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Granular role and resource-based authorization (ReBAC, ABAC, TBAC, RBAC, etc...)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;API keys for your technical customers to interact with your own APIs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Machine to machine authentication, or services â if you have a microservice architecture.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Audit trails to track the permission changes within your services or expose this to your customers.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And there are of course many more components, that help complete full auth-platform, but they aren't totally relevant to this article, so I'm going to skip over them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With that, you may already start to be able to see why uptime is so critical for us. We're on the critical path for our customers. It's not inherently true for every single platform, but it is for us. So if our solution is down, then our customer applications are down as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we put the reliability part in the back corner for one second and just think about the features, we can theorize about a potential initial architecture. That is, an architecture that just focuses on the features, how might you build this out as simple as possible? I want to do this, so I can help explain all the issues that we would face with the simple solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe you've got a single region, and in that region you have some sort of HTTP router that handles requests and they forward to some compute, serverless, container, or virtual machine, or, and I'm very sorry for the scenario â if you have to use bare metal. Lastly, you're interacting with some database, NoSQL, SQL, or something else, file storage, and maybe there's some async components.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you take a look at this, it's probably obvious to you (and everyone else) that there is no way it is going to meet our reliability needs. But we have to ask, just exactly how often will there actually be a problem with this architecture? Just building out complexity doesn't directly increase reliability, we need to focus on why this architecture would fail. For us, we use AWS, so I look to the Amazon CTO for guidance, and he's famously quoted as saying, Everything fails all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And AWS's own services are no exception to this. Over the last decade, we've seen numerous incidents:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2014 - Ireland (Partial) - Hardware - Transformer failed - EC2, EBS, and RDS&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2016 - Sydney (Partial) - Severe Weather - Power Loss - All Services&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2017 - All Regions - Human error - S3 critical servers deleted - S3&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2018 - Seoul Region - Human error - DNS resolvers impacted - EC2&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2021 - Virginia - Traffic Scaling - Network Control Plane outage - All Services&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2021 - California - Traffic Scaling - Network Control Plane outage - All Services&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2021 - Frankfurt (Partial) - Fire - Fire Suppression System issues - All Services&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2023 - Virginia - Kinesis issues - Scheduling Lambda Invocations impact - Lambda&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2023 - Virginia - Networking issues - Operational issue - Lambda, Fargate, API Gatewayâ¦&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2023 - Oregon (Partial) - Error rates - Dynamodb + 48 services&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2024 - Singapore (Partial) - EC2 Autoscaling - EC2&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2024 - Virginia (Partial) - Describe API Failures ECS - ECS + 4 services&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2024 - Brazil - ISP issues - CloudFront connectivity - CloudFront&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2024 - Global - Network connectivity - STS Service&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2024 - Virginia - Message size overflow - Kinesis down - Lambda, S3, ECS, CloudWatch, Redshift&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025 - Virginia - Dynamo DB DNS - DynamoDB down - All Services&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And any one of these would have caused major problems for us and therefore our customers. And the frequency of incident is actually increasing in time. This shouldn't be a surprise, right? Cloud adoption is increasing over time. The number of services AWS is offering is also increasing. But how impactful are these events? Would single one of them have been a problem for us to actually reach our SLA promise? What would happen if we just trusted AWS and used that to pass through our commitments? Would it be sufficient to achieve 99.999% SLA uptime? Well, let's take a look.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð°ï¸ AWS SLA Commitmentsâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The AWS Lambda SLA is below 5 ninesâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The API Gateway SLA is below 5 ninesâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The AWS SQS SLA is below 5 ninesâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, so when it comes to trusting AWS SLAs, it isn't sufficient. At. All.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can't just use the components that are offered by AWS, and go from there. We fundamentally need to do something more than that. So the question becomes, what exactly must a dependency's reliability be in order for us to utilize it? To answer that question, it's time for a math lesson. Or more specifically, everyone's favorite topic, probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's quickly get through this &lt;del&gt;torture&lt;/del&gt; exercise. Fundamentally, you have endpoints in your service, and you get in an HTTP request, and it interacts with some third-party component or API, and then you write the result to a database. For us, this could be an integration such as logging in with Google or with Okta for our customers' enterprise customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð» Calculating the allowed failure rateâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So if we want to meet a 5-nines reliability promise, how unreliable could this third-party component actually be? What happens if this component out of the box is only 90% reliable? We'll design a strategy for getting around that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Uptime is a product of all of the individual probabilities:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the sake of this example, we'll just assume that every other component in our architecture is 100% reliable â That's every line of code, no bugs ever written in our library dependencies, or transitive library dependencies, or the dependencies' dependencies' dependencies, and everything always works exactly as we expect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So we can actually rewrite our uptime promise as a result of the failure rate of that third-party component.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the only way that we can actually increase the success rate of the uptime based off of failures is to retry. And so we can multiply out the third-party failure rate and retry multiple times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Logically that makes a lot of sense. When a component fails, if you retry again, and again, the likelihood it will be down every single time approaches zero. And we can generate a really nasty equation from this to actually determine how many exact times do we need to retry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How many exactly can it? Rather than guessing whether or not we should retry four times or five times, or put it in a &lt;code&gt;while(true)&lt;/code&gt; loop, we can figure it out exactly. So we take this equation and extend it out a little bit. Plugging in our 90% reliable third-party component:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We find that our retry count actually must be greater than or equal to five. We can see that this adds up to our uptime expectation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is this the end of the story? Just retry a bunch of times and you're good? Well, not exactly. Remember this equation?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We do really need to consider every single component that we utilize. And specifically when it comes to the third-party component, we had to execute it by utilizing a retry handler. So we need to consider the addition of the retry handler into our equation. Going back to the initial architecture, instead of what we had before, when there's a failure in that third-party component, now we will automatically execute some sort of asynchronous retries or in-process retries. And every time that third-party component fails, we execute the retry handler and retry again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means we need to consider the reliability of that retry handler.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's assume we have a really reliable retry handler and that it's even more reliable than our service. I think that's reasonable, and actually required. A retry handler that is less reliable than our stated SLA by default is just as faulty as the third-party component.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's consider one with five and a half nines â that's half a nine more reliable than our own SLA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But how reliable does it really need to be? Well, we can pull in our original equation and realize that our total uptime is the unreliability or the reliability of the third-party component multiplied by the reliability of our retry handler.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From here, we add in the retries to figure out what the result should be:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have a reliable retry handler, but it's not perfect. And with a retry handler that has reliability of five and a half nines, we can retry a maximum two times. Because remember, it has to be reliable every single time we utilize it, as it is a component which can also fail. Which means left with this equation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't think comes as a surprise to anyone that in fact five is greater than two. What is the implication here?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The number of retries required for that unreliable third-party component to be utilized by us exceeds the number of retries actually allowed by our retry handler.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's a failure, the retry handler can only retry twice before itself violates our SLA, but we need to retry five times in order to raise the third-party component reliably up. We can actually figure out what the minimum reliability of a third-party component is allowed to be, when using our retry handler:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which in turn validates that it's actually impossible for us to utilize that component. &lt;code&gt;99.7%&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;99.7%&lt;/code&gt; is the minimum allowed reliability for any third-party component in order for us to meet our required 5-nines SLA. This third-party component is so unreliable (&lt;code&gt;~90%&lt;/code&gt;), that even using a highly reliable retry handler, we still can't make it reliable enough without the retry handler itself compromising our SLA. We fundamentally need to consider this constraint, when we're building out our architecture. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That means we drop this third-party component. Done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then, let's assume we get rid of every flaky component, everything that don't have a high enough reliability for us. At this point, it's good to think, is this sufficient to achieve our 5-nines SLA? Well, it isn't just third-party components we have to be concerned about. We also have to be worried about those AWs infrastructure failures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð©ï¸ Infrastructure Failuresâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So let's flashback to our initial architecture again:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can have issues at the database layer, right? There could be any number of problems here. Maybe it's returning 500s, there are some slow queries, maybe things are timing out. Or there could be a problem with our compute. Maybe it's not scaling up fast enough. We're not getting new infrastructure resources. Sometimes, even AWS is out of bare metal machines when you don't reserve them, request them get them on demand, and the list go on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additionally, there could also be some sort of network issue, where requests aren't making it through to us or even throw a DNS resolution error on a request from our users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In many of these cases, I think the answer is obvious. We just have to declare the whole region as down. And you are probably thinking, well, this is where we failover to somewhere else. No surprise, yeah, this is exactly what we do:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, this means we have to have all the data and all the infrastructure components duplicated to another region in order to do this. And since Authress has six primary regions around the world, that also means we need multiple backup regions to be able to support the strategy. But this comes with significant wasted resources and wasted compute that we're not even getting to use. Costly! But I'll get to that later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Knowing a redundant architecture is required is a great first step, but that leaves us having to solve for: how do we actually make the failover happen in practice?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð§ The Failover Routing Strategyâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simply put â our strategy is to utilize DNS dynamic routing. This means requests come into our DNS and it automatically selects between one of two target regions, the primary region that we're utilizing or the failover region in case there's an issue. The critical component of the infrastructure is to switch regions during an incident:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In our case, when using AWS, this means using the Route 53 health checks and the Route 53 failover routing policy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We know how we're gonna do it, but the long pole in the tent is actually knowing that there is even a problem in the first place. A partial answer is to say Have a health check, so of course there is health check here. But the full answer is: have a health check that validates both of the regions, checking if the region is up, or is there an incident? And if it is, reports the results to the DNS router.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We could be utilizing the default provided handler from AWS Route 53 or a third-party component which pings our website, but that's not accurate enough from a standpoint of correctly and knowing for certain that our services are in fact down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It would be devastating for us to fail over when a secondary region is having worse problems than our primary region. Or what if there's an issue with with network traffic. We wouldn't know if that's an issue of communication between AWS's infrastructure services, or an issue with the default Route 53 health check endpoint, or some entangled problem with how those specifically interact with our code that we're actually utilizing. So it became a requirement to built something ourselves, custom, to actually execute exactly what we need to check.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a representation of what we're doing. It's not exactly what we are doing, but it's close enough to be useful. Health check request come in from the Route 53 Health Check. They call into our APIGW or Load Balancer as a router. The requests are passed to our compute which can interact and validate logic, code, access, and data in the database:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The health check executes this code on request that allows us to validate if the region is in fact healthy:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import Authorizer from './authorizer.js';&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We start a profiler to know how long our requests are taking.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Then we interact with our databases, as well as validate some secondary components, such as SQS. While issues with secondary components may not always be a reason to failover, they can cause impacts to response time, and those indicators can be used to predict incoming incidents.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;From there, we check whether or not the most critical business logic is working correctly. In our case, that's interactions with DynamoDB as well as core authorizer logic. Compared to a simple unit test, this accounts for corruption in a deployment package, as well instances where some subtle differences between regions interact with our code base. We can catch those sorts of problems here, and know that the primary region that we're utilizing, one of the six, is having a problem and automatically update the DNS based on this.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When we're done, we return success or failure so the health check can track changes.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð¿ Improving the Failover Strategyâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And we don't stop here with our infrastructure failover however. With the current strategy, it's good, in some cases, even sufficient. But it isn't that great. For starters, we have to completely failover. If there's just one component that's problematic, we can't just swap that one out easily, it's all or nothing with the Route 53 health check. So when possible, we push for an edge-optimized architecture. In AWS, this means utilizing AWS CloudFront with AWS Lambda@Edge for compute. This not only helps reduce latency for our customers and their end users depending where they are around the world, as a secondary benefit, fundamentally, it is an improved failover strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using CloudFront gives us a highly reliable CDN, which routes requests to the locally available compute region. From there, we can interact with the local database. When our database in that region experiences a health incident, we automatically failover, and check the database in a second adjacent region. And when there's a problem there as well, we do it again to a third region. We can do that because when utilizing DynamoDB we have Global Tables configured for authorization configuration. In places where we don't need the data duplicated, we just interact with the table in a different region without replication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After a third region with an issue, we stop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And maybe you're asking why three and not four or five or six? Aren't you glad we did the probabilities exercise earlier? Now you can actually figure out why it's three here. But, I'll leave that math as an exercise for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a quick recap, this handles the problems with at the infrastructure level and with third-party components. And if we solve those, is that sufficient for us to achieve our goal the 5-nines SLA?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For us the answer is No, and you might have guessed, if you peaked at the scrollbar or table contents that there are still quite some additional components integrated into our solution. One of them is knowing that at some point, there's going to be a bug in our code, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð» Application level failuresâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that bug will get committed to production, which means we're going to end up with an application failure. It should be obvious that it isn't achievable to write completely bug-free code. Maybe there is someone out there that thinks that, and maybe even that's you, and I believe you that you believe that. However, I know it's not me, and realistically, I don't want to sit around and pray that it's also my fellow team members. The risk is too high, because in the case something does get into production, that means it can impact some of our customers. So instead, let's assume that will happen and design a strategy around it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So when it does happen, we of course have to trigger our incident response. For us, we send out an email, we post a message on our community and internal communication workspaces, and start an on-call alert. The technology here isn't so relevant, but tools like AWS SES, SQS, SNS, Discord, and emails are involved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incidents wake an engineer up, so someone can start to take look at the incident, and most likely the code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But by the time they even respond to the alert, let alone actually investigate and fix the cause of the incident, we would long violated our SLA. So an alert is not sufficient for us. We need to also implement automation to automatically remediate any of these problems. Now, I'm sure you're thinking, yeah, okay, test automation. You might even be thinking about an LLM agent that can automatically create PRs. (Side note: LLM code generation, doesn't actually work for us, and I'll get to that a little further down) Instead, we have to rely on having sufficient testing in place. And yes, of course we do. We test before deployment. There is no better time to test.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This seems simple and an obvious answer, and I hope that for anyone reading this article it is. Untested code never goes to production. Every line of code is completely tested before it is merged to production, even if it is enabled on some flag. Untested code is never released, it is far too dangerous. Untested code never makes it to production behind some magic flag. Abusing feature flags to make that happen could not be a worse decision for us. And that's because we can need to be as confident as possible before those changes actually get out in front of our customers. The result is â we don't focus on test coverage percentage, but rather test value. That is, which areas provide most value, that are most risky, that we care about being the most reliable for our customers. Those are the ones we focus on testing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Root Cause Analysis (RCA)â&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every incident could have been prevented if we just had one more test. The trick though is actually having that right test, before the incident.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And in reality, that's not actually possible. Having every right test for a service that is constantly changing, while new features are being added, is just unmaintainable. Every additional test we write increases the maintenance burden of our service. Attempting to achieve 100% complete test coverage would require an infinite amount of time. This is known as the Pareto Principle, more commonly the 80-20 rule. If it takes 20% of the time to deliver 80% of the tests, it takes an infinite amount of time to achieve all the tests, and that assumes that the source code isn't changing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result is we'll never be able to catch everything. So we can't just optimize for prevention. We also need to optimize for recovery. This conclusion for us means also implementing tests against our deployed production code. One example of this are validation tests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð Validation Testsâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A validation test is where you have some data in one format and data in another format and you use those two different formats to ensure referential consistency. (Side note: There are many different kinds of tests, and I do a deep dive in the different types of tests and how they're relevant in building secure and reliable systems). One concrete example could be you have a request that comes in, you end up logging the request data and the response, then you can compare that logged data to what's actually saved in your database.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In our scenario, which focuses on the authorization and permissions enforcement checks, we have multiple databases with similar data. In one case, there's the storage of permissions as well as the storage of the expected checks and the audit trail tracking the creation of those permissions. So we actually have multiple opportunities to compare the data between our databases asynchronously outside of customer critical path usage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Running the Validationâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a schedule, via an AWS CloudWatch Scheduled Rule, we load the data from our different databases and we compare them against each other to make sure it is consistent. If there is a problem, then if this fires off an incident before any of our customers notice, so that we can actually go in and check what's going on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This sounds bad on the surface that it could ever happen. But the reality of the situation is that a discrepancy can show up as a result of any number of mechanisms. For instance, the infrastructure from AWS could have corrupted one of the database shards and what is written to the databases is inconsistent. We know that this can happen as there is no 100% guarantee on database durability, even from AWS. AWS does not guarantee Database Durability, are you assuming they do, because we don't! So actually reading the data back and verifying its internal consistency is something that we must do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While it might not seem that this could reduce the probability of there being an incident. Consider that a requested user permission check whose result doesn't match our customer's expectation is an incident. It might not always be one that anyone identifies or even becomes aware of, but it nonetheless a problem, just like a publicly exposed S3 is technically an issue, even if no one has exfiltrated the data yet, it doesn't mean the bucket isn'is sufficiently secured.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð¯ Incident Impactâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two parts to the actual risk of an incident. The probability and the impact. Everything in this article I've discuss until now talks about reducing the probability of an incident, that is â the likelihood of it happening. But since we know that we can't avoid ever having an incident, we also have to reduce the impact when it happens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One way we do that is by utilizing an incremental rollout. Hopefully everyone knows what incremental rollout is, so I'll instead jump straight into how we accomplish it utilizing AWS. And for that we focus again on our solution integrating with CloudFront and our edge architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The solution for us is what I call Customer Deployment Buckets. We bucket individual customers into separate buckets and then deploy to each of the buckets sequentially. If the deployment rolls out without a problem, and it's all green, that is everything works correctly, then we go on to the second bucket and then deploy our code to there, and then the third bucket, and so on and so forth until every single customer has the new version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there is an issue, we stop the rollout and we go and investigate what's actually going on. While we can't prevent the issue from happening to the earlier buckets, we are able to stop that issue from propagating to more customers, having an impact on everyone, and thus reduce the impact of the incident.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before the biggest recurring issue isn't executing an operations process during an incident, it's identifying there is a real incident in the first place. So, How do we actually know that there's an issue?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If it was an easy problem to solve, you would have written a unit task or integration test or service level test and thus already discovered it, right? So adding tests can't, by design, help us. Maybe there's an issue with the deployment itself or during infrastructure creation, but likely that's not what's happening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, I know you're thinking, When is he going to get to AI?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether or not we'll ever truly have AI is a separate &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;rant /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; that I won't get into here, so this is the only section on it, I promise. What we actually do is better called anomaly detection. Historically anomaly detection, was what AI always meant, true AI, rather than an LLM or agent in any way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð AI: Anomaly Detectionâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a graph of our detection analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might notice that it's not tracking 400s or 500s, which are in reality relatively easy to detect. But in fact don't actually tell us meaningfully what's wrong with our service or whether or not there really is a problem. Impact is measured by business value, not technical protocol level analytics, so we need to have a business-focused metric.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And for us, at Authress, the business-focussed metric we use to identify meaningful incidents we call: The Authorization Ratio. That is the ratio of successful logins and authorizations to ones that are blocked, rejected, timeout or are never completed for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The above CloudWatch metric display contains this exact ratio, and here in this timeframe represents an instance not too long ago where we got really close to firing off our alert.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here, there was a slight elevation of errors soon after a deployment. The expected ratio was outside of our allowance span for a short period of time. However not long enough to trigger an incident. We still investigated, but it wasn't something that required immediate remediation. And it's a good reminder that identifying problems in any production software isn't so straightforward. To achieve high reliability, we've needed an AI or in this case anomaly detection to actually identify additional problems. And realistically, even with this level of sophistication in place, we still can never know with 100% certainty that there is actually an incident at any moment. And that's because "what is an incident", is actually a philosophical question...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð¹ Does it smell like an incident?â&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our anomaly detection said â almost an incident, and we determined the result â no incident. But does that mean there wasn't an incident? What makes an incident, how do I define an incident? And is that exact definition ubiquitous, for every system, every engineer, every customer?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Obviously not, and one look at the AWS Health Status Dashboard is all you need to determine that the identification of incidents is based on subjective perspective, rather than objective criteria. What's actually more important is the synthesis of our perspective on the situation and what our customers believe. To see what I mean, let's do a comparison:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm going to use Authress as an example. So I've got the product services perspective on one side and our customer's perspective on the other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Incident Alignmentâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the top left corner we have alignment. If we believe that our system is up and working and our customers do, too, then success, all good. Everything's working as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inversely in the opposite corner, maybe there is a problem. We believe that one of our services is having an issue, and successfully, we're able to identify it. Most importantly, our customers sayâyes, there is an issue for us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's not great that there's an incident, but as I've identified incidents will absolutely happen, and the fact we've correctly aligned with our customers on the problem's existence independently allows us to deploy automation to automatically remediate the issue. That's a success! If it's a new problem that we haven't seen before, we can even design new automation to fix this. Correctly identifying incidents is challenging, so doing that step correctly, leads itself very well to automation for remediation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Perspective Mismatchâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One interesting corner is when our customers believe that there's nothing wrong, there have been no incidents reported, but all our alerts are saying â RED ALERT â someone has to go look at this!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case, our alerts have identified a problem that no one cares about. This often happens in scenarios where our customers are in one region, Switzerland for example, with local region users, a health care, manufacturing, or e-commerce app, is a good example, rather than global, who are likely asleep at 2:00 AM. And that means an incident at the moment, could be an issue affecting some customers. But if they aren't around to experience it, is it actually happening?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are probably wincing at that idea. There's a bug, it must be fixed! And sure that's a problem, it's happening and we should take note of what's going on. But we don't need to respond in real time. That's a waste of our resources where we could be investing in other things. Why wake up our engineers based on functionality that no one is using?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think one of the most interesting categories is in the top right-hand corner where:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;our customers say, "hey, your service is down"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;But we say, "Wait, really, is it?"_&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is known as a gray failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Gray Failuresâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it can happen for any number of reasons. Maybe there is something in our knowledge base that tells our customers to do something one way and it's confusing and they've interpreted it in a different way. So there's a different expectation here. That expectation can get codified into customer processes and product services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or maybe our customer is running different tests from us, ones that are of course, valuable for their business, but not ones that we consider. Or more likely they are just using a less resilient cloud provider.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most fundamentally, there could really be an incident, something that we haven't detected yet, but they have. And if we don't respond to that, it could grow, and left unchecked, escalate, and eventually impact all our customers. This means we need to give our customers an easy way to report incidents to us, which we can immediately follow up with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For us, every single incident, every single customer support ticket that comes into our platform, we immediately and directly send it to our engineering team. Now, I often get pushback on this from other leaders. I'm sure, even you might be thinking something like â I don't want to be on call for customer support incidents. But if you throw additional tiers in your organization between your engineering teams and your customers, that means you're increasing the time to actually start investigating and resolving those problems. If you have two tiers before your engineering team and each tier has its own SLA of 10 minutes to triage the issue, that means you've already gone through 20 minutes before an engineer even knows about it and can go and look at it. That violates our SLA by fourfold before investigation and remediation can even begin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, in those scenarios, what I actually recommend thinking about is how might you reduce the number of support tickets you receive in aggregate? This is the much more appropriate way to look at the problem. If you are getting support tickets that don't make sense, then you've got to investigate, why did we get this ticket? Do the root cause analysis on the ticket, not just the issue mentioned in it â why the ticket was even created in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A ticket means: Something is broken. From there, we can figure out, OK, maybe we need to improve our documentation. Or we need to change what we're doing on one of our endpoints. Or we need to change the response error message we're sending. But you can always go deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The customer support advantageâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And going deeper, means customer support is critical for us. We consider customer support to be the lifeline of our service level agreement (SLA). If we didn't have that advantage, then we might not have been able to deliver our commitment at all. So much so that we report some of our own CloudWatch custom metrics to our customers so they can have an aggregate view of both what they know internally and what we believe. We do this through our own internal dashboard in our application management UIs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helping our users identify incidents benefits us; because we can't catch everything. It's just not possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð Negligence and Maliceâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To this point, we've done the math on reliability of third-party components. We've implemented an automatic region failover and added incremental rollout. And we have a core customer support focus. Is that sufficient to achieve 5-nines of reliability?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you think yes, then you'd expect the meme pictures now. And, I wish I could say it was enough, but it's not. That's because we also have to deal with negligence and malice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're in a privileged position to have numerous security researchers out there on the internet constantly trying to find vulnerabilities within our service. For transparency, I have some of those reports I want to share:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;âRealâ Vulnerability Reportsâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I am a web security researcher enthusiast. Do you give a monetary reward?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, this isn't starting out that great. What else have we received?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I found some vulnerabilities in your website. Do you offer rewards for ethical hackers?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, maybe, but I think you would actually need to answer for us, what the problem actually is. And you also might notice this went to our spam. It didn't even get to our inbox. So a lot of help they might be providing. Actually we ignore any âsecurityâ email sent from a non-custom domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one was really interesting. We had someone attempting to phish our engineering team by creating a support ticket and putting in some configuration trying to get us to provide them our own credentials to one of our third-party dependencies. Interestingly enough, our teams don't even have access to those credentials directly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And, we know this was malicious because the credentials that they are referencing in the support request are from our honey pot, stuck in our UI to explicitly catch these sorts of things. The only way to get these credentials is if they hacked around our UI application and pulled out of the HTML. They aren't readily available any other way. So it was very easy for us to detect that this âreportâ was actually a social engineering attack.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And this is one of my favorites, and I can't make this up:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I have found many security loophole. How much will you pay if you want to working with me like project?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's the exact quote, I don't even know what that means. Unfortunately, LLMs will actually start to make all of these future "vulnerability reports" sound more appealing to read in the future, for better or worse. However, at the end of the day, the truth is that these are harmless. And we actually do have a security disclosure program that anyone can go and submit problems for. I hope the message to white-hat hackers is please use that process, and the legitimate reports usually do go through it. Do not send us emails. Those are going to go into the abyss. Alternatively, you can follow our security.txt public page or go to the disclosure form, but with email, the wrong people are going to get that and we can't triage effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vulnerabilities in our services can result in production incidents for our customers. That means security is part of our SLA. Don't believe me, I'll show you how:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Multitenant considerationsâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's relevant for us, that Authress is a multitenant solution. So some of the resources within our service are in fact shared between customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additionally, customers could have multiple services in a microservice architecture or multiple components. And one of these services could theoretically consume all of the resources that we've allocated for that customer. In that scenario, that would cause an incident for that customer. So we need to protect against resource exhaustion Intra-Tenant. Likewise, we have multiple customers. One of those customers could be consuming more resources than we've allocated to the entire tenant. And that could cause an incident across Inter-Tenant and cause an incident across our platform and impact other customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lastly, we have to be worried about our customers, our customers' customers, and our customers' customers' customers, because any one of those could be malicious and consume their resources and so on and so forth, thus causing a cascading failure. A failure due to lack of resources is an incident. The only solution that makes sense for this is, surprise, rate limiting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Helpful Rate Limitingâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So we need to rate-limit these requests at different levels for different kinds of clients, different kinds of users, and we do that within our architecture, at different fundamental levels within our infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Primarily there are protections at our compute level, as well at the region level, and also place protections at a global level. In AWS, this of course means using a web application firewall or WAF. I think our WAF configuration is interesting and in some ways novel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, one of the things that we love to use is the AWS managed IP reputation list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reputation list is list of IP addresses that have been associated with malicious activity outside of our service throughout other customers at AWS and other providers out there in the world where a problem has been detected. That means before those attacks even get to our service or to our customers' instances of Authress, we can already know to block them, and the WAF does that. This is great, and most importantly, has a very low false positive rate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the false positive rate is an important metric for consideration of counter measures against malicious attacks or negligent accidental abuse of resources, and something that prevents us from using any other managed rules from AWS or external providers. There's two problems with managed rules, fundamentally:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Number one is the false positive rate. If that is even a little bit more than, it couldn't be sustainable, and would result in us blocking legitimate requests coming for a customer. This means it is a problem, and it's an incident for them if some of their users can't utilize their software because of something we did. False positives are customer incidents.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The second one is that managed rules are gratuitously expensive. Lots of companies are building these just to charge you lots of money, and the ROI just doesn't seem to be there. We don't see useful blocks from them.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the truth is, we need to do something more than just the reputation list rule.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Handling Requests at Scaleâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the thing that we've decided to do is â add blocking for sufficiently high requests. By default, any Authress account's service client that goes above 2,000 requests per second (RPS), we just immediately terminate. Now, this isn't every customer, as there are some out there for us that do require such a high load or even higher (as 2k isn't that high). But for the majority of them, if you get to this number and they haven't talked to us about their volume, then it is probably malicious in some way. You don't magically go from zero to 2,000 one day, unless it is an import job.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Likewise, we can actually learn about a problem long before it gets to that scale. We have milestones, and we start reporting loads from clients at 100, 200, 500, 1,000, et cetera. If we see clients hitting these load milestones, we can already start to respond and create an incident for us to investigate before they reach a point where they're consuming all of the resources in our services for that customer. And we do this by adding alerts on the COUNT of requests for WAF metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, we also get attacks at a smaller scale. Just because we aren't being DDoS-ed doesn't mean there isn't attack. And those requests will still get through because they don't meet our blocking limits. They could be malicious in nature, but only identifiable in aggregate. So while single request might seem fine, if you see the same request 10 times a second, 100 times a second, something is probably wrong. Or if you have request urls that end in &lt;code&gt;.php?admin&lt;/code&gt;, when no one has run WordPress in decades, you also know that there's a problem. We catch these by logging all of the blocked requests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have automation in place to query those results and update our rules, but a picture is worth a thousand words:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here you can see a query based off of the IP addresses from the client that are being utilized and sorted by frequency. When we get these requests that look non-malicious individually, we execute a query such as this one and we check to see if the results match a pattern. You can use ip address matching or more intelligently, something called the JA3 or JA4 fingerprints of those requests There are actually lots of options available, I'm not going to get into exactly what they are, there are some great articles on the topic. And there are more mechanisms to actually track these used throughout the security industry, and utilizing them let's you instantly identify: Hey, you know what? This request violates one of our patterns, maybe we should block all the requests from that client.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so, rather than waiting for them to get to the point where an attacker is consuming 2,000 requests per second worth of resources, you can stop there right away. In the cases where we can't make a conclusive decision, this technology gives us another tool that we can utilize to improve our patterns for the future. Maybe it goes without saying, but of course because we've running our technology to many regions around the world, we have to work on deploying this infrastructure in all these places and push it out to the edge where possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ð The Conclusionâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I said a lot of things, so I to quickly want to quickly summarize our architecture that we have in place:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Third-party component reliability reviews. I can't stress this enough. Don't just assume that you can utilize something. And sometimes in order to achieve 5-nines, you actually have to remove components from your infrastructure. Some things are just not able to be utilized no matter what. Now maybe you can put it in some sort of async background, but it can't be on the critical path for your endpoints.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;DNS failover and health checks. For places where you have an individual region or availability zone or cluster, having a full backup with a way to conclusively determine what's up and automatically failover is critical.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Edge compute where possible. There's a whole network out there of services that are running on top of the cloud providers, which help guarantee your capability to run as close to as possible to where your users are and reduce latency.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Incremental rollout for when you want to reduce the impact as much as possible.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Web Application Firewall for handling those malicious requests.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Having a Customer Support Focus to enable escalating issues that outside your area of detection.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And through seven years or so that we've been doing this and building up this architecture, there's a couple of things that we've learned:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Murphy's Lawâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everything fails all the time. There absolutely will be failures everywhere. Every line of code, every component you pull in, every library, there's guaranteed to be a problem in each and everyone of those. And you will for sure have to deal with it, at some point. So being prepared to handle that situation, is something you have to be thinking through in your design.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;DNSâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DNS, yeah, AWS will say it, everyone out there will say, and now we get to say it. The global DNS architecture is pretty good and reliable for a lot of scenarios, but I worry that it's still a single point of failure in a lot of ways.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Infrastructure as Code (IAC)â&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last thing is infrastructure as code challenges. We deploy primary regions, but then there's also the backup regions, which are slightly different from the primary regions, and then there are edge compute, which are, again, even more slightly different. And then sometimes, we do this ridiculous thing, where we deploy infrastructure dedicated to one customers. And in doing so, we're running some sort of IaC to deploy those resources.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is almost exactly the same architecture. Almost! Because it isn't exactly the same there are quite the opportunities for challenges to sneak it. That's problematic with even Open Tofu or CloudFormation, and often these tools make it more difficult, not less. And good luck to you, if you're still using some else that hasn't been modernized. With those, it's even easier to run into problems and not get it exactly correct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last thing I want to leave you with is, well, With all of these, is that actually sufficient to achieve five nines?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No. Our commitment is 5-nines, what we do is in defense of that, just because you do all these things doesn't automatically mean your promise of 5-nines in guaranteed. And you know what, you too can promise a 5-nines SLA without doing anything. You'll likely break your promise, but for us our promise is important, and so this is our defense.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For help understanding this article or how you can implement auth and similar security architectures in your services, feel free to reach out to me via the community server.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://authress.io/knowledge-base/articles/2025/11/01/how-we-prevent-aws-downtime-impacts"/><published>2025-11-17T17:07:17+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45955900</id><title>Azure hit by 15 Tbps DDoS attack using 500k IP addresses</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:23.945645+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/microsoft/microsoft-aisuru-botnet-used-500-000-ips-in-15-tbps-azure-ddos-attack/"/><published>2025-11-17T17:39:15+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45957629</id><title>Compiling Ruby to machine language</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:23.715423+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="c606289e40bbfb0a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Compiling Ruby To Machine Language&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've started working on a new edition of Ruby Under a Microscope that covers Ruby 3.x. I'm working on this in my spare time, so it will take a while. Leave a comment or drop me a line and I'll email you when it's finished.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s an excerpt from the completely new content for Chapter 4, about YJIT and ZJIT. I’m still finishing this up… so this content is fresh off the page! It’s been a lot of fun for me to learn about how JIT compilers work and to brush up on my Rust skills as well. And it’s very exciting to see all the impressive work the Ruby team at Shopify and other contributors have done to improve Ruby’s runtime performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Chapter 4: Compiling Ruby To Machine Language&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Interpreting vs. Compiling Ruby Code&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Yet Another JIT (YJIT)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Virtual Machines and Actual Machines&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Counting Method and Block Calls&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;YJIT Blocks&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;YJIT Branch Stubs&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Executing YJIT Blocks and Branches&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Deferred Compilation&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Regenerating a YJIT Branch&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;YJIT Guards&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Adding Two Integers Using Machine Language&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Experiment 4-1: Which Code Does YJIT Optimize?&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;How YJIT Recompiles Code&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Finding a Block Version&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Saving Multiple Block Versions&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ZJIT, Ruby’s Next Generation JIT&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Counting Method and Block Calls&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ZJIT Blocks&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Method Based JIT&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Rust Inside of Ruby&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;33&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Experiment 4-2: Reading ZJIT HIR and LIR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;35&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Summary&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;37&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Counting Method and Block Calls&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To find hot spots, YJIT counts how many times your program calls each function or block. When this count reaches a certain threshold, YJIT stops your program and converts that section of code into machine language. Later Ruby will execute the machine language version instead of the original YARV instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To keep track of these counts, YJIT saves an internal counter nearby the YARV instruction sequence for each function or block.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4-5: YJIT saves information adjacent to each set of YARV instructions&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4-5 shows the YARV instruction sequence the main Ruby compiler created for the sum += i block at (3) in Listing 4-1. At the top, above the YARV instructions, Figure 4-5 shows two YJIT related values: jit_entry and jit_entry_calls. As we’ll see in a moment, jit_entry starts as a null value but will later hold a pointer to the machine language instructions YJIT produces for this Ruby block. Below jit_entry, Figure 4-5 also shows jit_entry_calls, YJIT’s internal counter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each time the program in Listing 4-1 calls this block, YJIT increments the value of jit_entry_calls. Since the range at (1) in Listing 4-1 spans from 1 through 40, this counter will start at zero and increase by 1 each time Range#each calls the block at (3).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the jit_entry_calls reaches a particular threshold, YJIT will compile the YARV instructions into machine language. By default for small Ruby programs YJIT in Ruby 3.5 uses a threshold of 30. Larger programs, like Ruby on Rails web applications, will use a larger threshold value of 120. (You can also change the threshold by passing —yjit-call-threshold when you run your Ruby program.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;YJIT Blocks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While compiling your Ruby program, YJIT saves the machine language instructions it creates into YJIT blocks. YJIT blocks, which are distinct from Ruby blocks, each contain a sequence of machine language instructions for a range of corresponding YARV instructions. By grouping YARV instructions and compiling each group into a YJIT block, YJIT can produce more optimized code that is tailored to your program’s behavior and avoid compiling code that your program doesn’t need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we’ll see next, a single YJIT block doesn’t correspond to a Ruby function or block. YJIT blocks instead represent smaller sections of code: individual YARV instructions or a small range of YARV instructions. Each Ruby function or block typically consists of several YJIT blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see how this works for our example. After the program in Listing 4-1 executes the Ruby block at (3) 29 times, YJIT will increment the jit_entry_calls counter again, just before Ruby runs the block for the 30th time. Since jit_entry_calls reaches the threshold value of 30, YJIT triggers the compilation process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;YJIT compiles the first YARV instruction getlocal_WC_1 and saves machine language instructions that perform the same work as getlocal_WC_1 into a new YJIT block:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4-6: Creating a YJIT block&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the left side, Figure 4-6 shows the YARV instructions for the sum += i Ruby block. On the right, Figure 4-6 shows the new YJIT block corresponding to getlocal_WC_1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, the YJIT compiler continues and compiles the second YARV instruction from the left side of Figure 4-7: getlocal_WC_0 at index 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4-7: Appending to a YJIT block&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the left side, Figure 4-7 shows the same YARV instructions for the sum += i Ruby block that we saw above in Figure 4-6. But now the two dotted arrows indicate that the YJIT block on the right contains the machine language instructions equivalent to both getlocal_WC_1 and getlocal_WC_0.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look inside this new block. YJIT compiles or translates the Ruby YARV instructions into machine language instructions. In this example, running on my Mac laptop, YJIT writes the following machine language instructions into this new block:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4-8: The contents of one YJIT block&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4-8 shows a closer view of the new YJIT block that appeared on the right side of Figures 4-6 and 4-7. Inside the block, Figure 4-8 shows the assembly language acronyms corresponding to the ARM64 machine language instructions that YJIT generated for the two YARV instructions shown on the left. The YARV instructions on the left are: getlocal_WC_1, which loads a value from a local variable located in the previous stack frame and saves it on the YARV stack, and getlocal_WC_0, which loads a local variable from the current stack from and also saves it on the YARV stack. The machine language instructions on the right side of Figure 4-8 perform the same task, loading these values into registers on my M1 microprocessor: x1 and x9. If you’re curious and would like to learn more about what the machine language instructions mean and how they work, the section “Adding Two Integers Using Machine Language” discusses the instructions for this example in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;YJIT Branch Stubs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, YJIT continues down the sequence of YARV instructions and compiles the opt_plus YARV instruction at index 4 in Figures 4-6 and 4-7. But this time, YJIT runs into a problem: It doesn’t know the type of the addition arguments. That is, will opt_plus add two integers? Or two strings, floating point numbers, or some other types?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Machine language is very specific. To add two 64-bit integers on an M1 microprocessor, YJIT could use the adds assembly language instruction. But adding two floating pointer numbers would require different instructions. And, of course, adding or concatenating two strings is an entirely different operation altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order for YJIT to know which machine language instructions to save into the YJIT block for opt_plus, YJIT needs to know exactly what type of values the Ruby program might ever add at (3) in Listing 4-1. You and I can tell by reading Listing 4-1 that the Ruby code is adding integers. We know right away that the sum += 1 block at (3) is always adding one integer to another. But YJIT doesn’t know this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;YJIT uses a clever trick to solve this problem. Instead of analyzing the entire program ahead of time to determine all of the possible types of values the opt_plus YARV instruction might ever need to add, YJIT simply waits until the block runs and observes which types the program actually passes in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;YJIT uses branch stubs to achieve this wait-and-see compile behavior, as shown in Figure 4-9.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4-9: A YJIT block, branch and stub&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4-9 shows the YARV instructions on the left, and the YJIT block for indexes 0000-0002 on the right. But note the bottom right corner of Figure 4-7, which shows an arrow pointing down from the block to a box labeled stub. This arrow represents a YJIT branch. Since this new branch doesn’t point to a block yet, YJIT sets up the branch to point to a branch stub instead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://patshaughnessy.net/2025/11/17/compiling-ruby-to-machine-language"/><published>2025-11-17T20:04:49+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45958717</id><title>Run ancient UNIX on modern hardware</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:23.049866+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b085fe091cbba1c6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The contents of this repository allow older versions of UNIX (ancient UNIX) to run easily on modern Unix-like systems (Linux, FreeBSD, macOS, among others).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this time, you can run the following versions of UNIX:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;UNIX versions for PDP-11 (run on a PDP-11 simulator):&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;UNIX versions for x86:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Version 7 UNIX ported to x86 architecture by Robert Nordier (original port in 1999 and patches in 2006-2007).&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First of all, credits and acknowledgment for material available in this repository that is not my own (or has been modified by me based on previous work).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The UNIX versions available in this repository have been released as open source under the Caldera license available in this repository. Please read the document carefully for concrete information about your rights and obligations when using the software. &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Note that various components within the system images may have been made available under other license conditions. Pay attention to these components. A clear example is version 2.11BSD UNIX, which features code covered by the Caldera license made available, in addition to code released under the BSD license. Source files available in the images show the license and due copyright. Check this data before reuse.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The UNIX images available in this repository were obtained from the w11 project (which uses these images for other purposes). You can get them directly here, as well as more information about the project, images, licenses and other data.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The scripts used to simulate the systems using SIMH for v5 and v7 UNIX were obtained from a w11 project repository, which can be accessed here. The original scripts are available under license GLP v3 or later. Modifications in these files were made by me, to fit the purpose of this repository. These modifications are restricted to the same license as the original script. &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;In addition, the general script for configuring the execution environment of versions v5 and v7 was obtained from the project, authored by Walter F.J. Mueller. You can get the original script here. The original script are available under license GLP v3 or later. Modifications in these files were made by me, to fit the purpose of this repository. These modifications are restricted to the same license as the original script.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The port of Version 7 UNIX to the x86 architecture was performed by Robert Nordier. These modifications are released under the simplified BSD license. For more information on all aspects of the distribution, read this file.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All my contributions and modifications (except for material that requires redistribution under the same license, such as the running scripts) are available in this repository under the BSD-3-Clause license.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You will need the following tools and utilities to run the available UNIX versions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First of all, you must have the &lt;code&gt;PDP-11 Simulator&lt;/code&gt; (SIMH), &lt;code&gt;qemu&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;GNU bash&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Python&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;wget&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; installed on your device. If you already have them installed, skip to section 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To install on Debian, Ubuntu, Pop!_OS and derivatives, use:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo apt install simh qemu qemu-system-i386 git wget python3 python3-pip python3-tk
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To install on Fedora and derivatives, use:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo dnf install simh qemu qemu-system-i386 git wget python3 python3-pip python3-tkinter
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To install on FreeBSD, use (for FreeBSD, installing GNU bash is also required. This shell is not normally installed in a default installation. Installation of GNU bash is not required on Linux systems, where bash is already installed by default):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;su root # &amp;lt;= Enter your password to login as root user
pkg install -q -y simh bash qemu git wget python3 py39-pip
ln -s /usr/local/bin/pip-3.9 /usr/local/bin/pip
pip install --upgrade pip
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To install on NetBSD, use (for NetBSD, installing GNU bash is also required. This shell is not normally installed in a default installation. Installation of GNU bash is not required on Linux systems, where bash is already installed by default):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;su root # &amp;lt;= Enter your password to login as root user
pkgin install simh bash qemu git wget python3 py39-pip
ln -s /usr/local/bin/pip-3.9 /usr/local/bin/pip
pip install --upgrade pip
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To install on OpenBSD, use (for OpenBSD, installing GNU bash is also required. This shell is not normally installed in a default installation. Installation of GNU bash is not required on Linux systems, where bash is already installed by default):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;su root # &amp;lt;= Enter your password to login as root user
pkg_add simh bash qemu git wget python3 py39-pip
ln -s /usr/local/bin/pip-3.9 /usr/local/bin/pip
pip install --upgrade pip
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After installation, proceed to section 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must clone this repository to your computer. For that, use:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/felipenlunkes/run-ancient-unix
cd run-ancient-unix
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After cloning the repository with the configuration files, you must populate the directories of each UNIX version with their respective image files. For that, go to the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, you have to run the available &lt;code&gt;run.sh&lt;/code&gt; script. For that, use:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;chmod +x run.sh
./run.sh
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, you have to run the script and select the option to install system images. You can also use the Python frontend to run the script. This is the easiest and simplest way to run script functions. To run this frontend and not rely on the command line, go to section 5. To continue the steps using the terminal, go to section 4.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You will see the following screen:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case, you should select option &lt;code&gt;7&lt;/code&gt;, which will install the system images. After pressing 7, press ENTER to make your choice effective. Wait for the process of obtaining, extracting, configuring and installing the images.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the installation is complete, you must run &lt;code&gt;run.sh&lt;/code&gt; again to start a UNIX version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When running the script, you will be asked to choose one of the available UNIX versions. After typing only the number relative to the choice, press ENTER to make your decision effective. Then wait for the desired version to run.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, you need to know peculiarities in the execution of each version of the system. For this, go to section 6.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need to start running the Python frontend that will manage the configuration and running of UNIX on your computer. First, you must install the TKinter Python package on your computer. For that, use:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pip install tk
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After that, you can press the &lt;code&gt;RAU.py&lt;/code&gt; script with the right button of your mouse and select the option of &lt;code&gt;Run as program&lt;/code&gt; or start the script from the terminal, using:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;python3 RAU.py
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;WARNING! The frontend is currently only compatible with the GNOME graphical environment (Linux and BSD systems). You can manually replace the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gnome-terminal&lt;/code&gt;calls with&lt;code&gt;konsole&lt;/code&gt;or another desired terminal emulator. Feel free to submit a pull request with any improvements or changes to the frontend.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After running the program, you will see the following screen:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On first run, you must install the UNIX disk images locally on your computer. Prior to this operation, you will NOT be able to run UNIX. To do so, click on the &lt;code&gt;Install UNIX system images&lt;/code&gt; button.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After downloading and installing the disk images, you are able to run UNIX. To do so, select the desired UNIX version in the &lt;code&gt;Running options&lt;/code&gt; section of the frontend screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go to the next section for more information about the specifics of running each version of UNIX available. Remember that when using the Python frontend, the command line selection screen, as shown in the next section, will not be displayed. However, the manual options and settings presented in the next section (after the selection screen, which will not appear) are still required to run each version of UNIX.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Select the desired UNIX version option below for details on how to start and operate the system. Each version of UNIX has different boot procedures. Pay attention to each particularity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head align="left"&gt;Particularities for Version 1 UNIX&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the start of execution after selecting v1 version, you will see a screen like below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 1

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Disabling CR
Disabling XQ
RF: buffering file in memory
TC0: 16b format, buffering file in memory

:login: 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just type &lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;, in lower case, and press ENTER. You will immediately be taken to the UNIX v1 shell.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 1

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Disabling CR
Disabling XQ
RF: buffering file in memory
TC0: 16b format, buffering file in memory

:login: root
root
# ls
bin
dev
etc
tmp
usr
# 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To end the simulation, press CTRL-E followed by CTRL-C or by typing quit when the &lt;code&gt;simh&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; prompt appears on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head align="left"&gt;Particularities for Version 5 UNIX&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the start of execution after selecting v5 version, you will see a screen like below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 2

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Disabling XQ
Logging to file "simh_dl0.log"
Listening on port 5671 (socket 5)
Listening on port 5672 (socket 7)
Modem control activated
@
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To start UNIX, you must type &lt;code&gt;unix&lt;/code&gt; and press ENTER after the @ character, without spaces and in lower case. After pressing ENTER, UNIX will load and you will be taken to a login screen as below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 2

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Disabling XQ
Logging to file "simh_dl0.log"
Listening on port 5671 (socket 5)
Listening on port 5672 (socket 7)
Modem control activated
@unix

login:
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must then type &lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; and press ENTER. You will then be taken to the shell and be able to use the system. See below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 2

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Disabling XQ
Logging to file "simh_dl0.log"
Listening on port 5671 (socket 5)
Listening on port 5672 (socket 7)
Modem control activated
@unix

login: root
# 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To end the simulation, press CTRL-E followed by CTRL-C or by typing quit when the &lt;code&gt;simh&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; prompt appears on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head align="left"&gt;Particularities for Version 7 UNIX&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the start of execution after selecting v7 version, you will see a screen like below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 3

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Disabling XQ
Logging to file "simh_dl0.log"
Listening on port 5671 (socket 5)
Listening on port 5672 (socket 7)
Modem control activated
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After seeing the screen above, you must type &lt;code&gt;boot&lt;/code&gt; in lower case and press ENTER. You will see the screen below after that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 3

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Disabling XQ
Logging to file "simh_dl0.log"
Listening on port 5671 (socket 5)
Listening on port 5672 (socket 7)
Modem control activated
boot
Boot
:
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the appearance of &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt;, you must type, without spaces and in lower case, the command &lt;code&gt;hp(0,0)unix&lt;/code&gt; and press ENTER, as below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 3

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Disabling XQ
Logging to file "simh_dl0.log"
Listening on port 5671 (socket 5)
Listening on port 5672 (socket 7)
Modem control activated
boot
Boot
: hp(0,0)unix
mem = 2020544
# 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pressing ENTER will immediately take you to the UNIX v7 shell.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; To enter multiuser mode and access all system functions, press CTRL-D. Afterwards, provide &lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;as username and password. You will again be taken to the UNIX v7 shell, as below:&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 3

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Disabling XQ
Logging to file "simh_dl0.log"
Listening on port 5671 (socket 5)
Listening on port 5672 (socket 7)
Modem control activated
boot
Boot
: hp(0,0)unix
mem = 2020544
# RESTRICTED RIGHTS: USE, DUPLICATION, OR DISCLOSURE
IS SUBJECT TO RESTRICTIONS STATED IN YOUR CONTRACT WITH
WESTERN ELECTRIC COMPANY, INC.
WED DEC 31 19:05:14 EST 1969

login: root
Password:
You have mail.
# 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To end the simulation, press CTRL-E followed by CTRL-C or by typing quit when the &lt;code&gt;simh&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; prompt appears on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head align="left"&gt;Particularities for 2.11BSD UNIX&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the start of execution after selecting 2.11BSD UNIX version, you will see a screen like below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 4

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Listening on port 4000 (socket 4)
Modem control activated
Auto disconnect activated
211bsd.simh&amp;gt; attach xq eth0
File open error
Disabling CR

73Boot from ra(0,0,0) at 0172150
: 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can just press ENTER when you see the screen to start UNIX. Afterwards, you will see the following screen:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 4

PDP-11 simulator V3.8-1
Listening on port 4000 (socket 4)
Modem control activated
Auto disconnect activated
211bsd.simh&amp;gt; attach xq eth0
File open error
Disabling CR

73Boot from ra(0,0,0) at 0172150
: 
: ra(0,0,0)unix
Boot: bootdev=02400 bootcsr=0172150

2.11 BSD UNIX #1: Fri Jun 9 08:42:54 PDT 1995
    root@SSU-64EN137:/usr/src/sys/SYSTEM

ra0: Ver 3 mod 3
ra0: RD54  size=311200
attaching qe0 csr 174440
qe0: DEC DELQA addr 00:50:56:01:01:01
attaching lo0

phys mem  = 3145728
avail mem = 1737664
user mem  = 307200

June  9 12:21:04 init: configure system

dz 0 csr 160100 vector 300 attached
ra 0 csr 172150 vector 154 vectorset attached
ts 0 csr 172520 vector 224 attached
erase, kill ^U, intr ^C
# 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; symbol indicates that the shell is ready to receive commands. Try using &lt;code&gt;uname -a&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; To enter multiuser mode and access all system functions, press CTRL-D. Afterwards, provide &lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;as username and password. You will again be taken to the 2.11BSD shell.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To end the simulation, press CTRL-E followed by CTRL-C or by typing quit when the &lt;code&gt;simh&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; prompt appears on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head align="left"&gt;Particularities for Version 7 UNIX for x86&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the start of execution after selecting v7 UNIX for x86, you will see a screen like below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You must select, from the list below, which edition/version of
UNIX you want to start. The available options are:

1) v1 UNIX
2) v5 UNIX
3) v7 UNIX
4) 2.11BSD UNIX
5) v7 UNIX for x86
6) Clear temporary files
7) Install the disk images for UNIX

Select a number and press &amp;lt;ENTER&amp;gt;: 5
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upon selection, &lt;code&gt;qemu&lt;/code&gt; will automatically start with the Version 7 UNIX for x86 disk image. After the initial boot, you will see the following screen:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then press ENTER to load and start UNIX. After pressing ENTER, you will see the following screen, and you will be able to interact with the Version 7 UNIX shell:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; To enter multiuser mode and access all system functions, press CTRL-D. Afterwards, provide &lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;as username and&lt;code&gt;password&lt;/code&gt;as password. You will again be taken to the Version 7 UNIX shell.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you are finished running the system on the PDP-11 simulator, you can clean up temporary and log files that may have been created by SIMH. To do so, go to section 7.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The simulator can create temporary and log files to simulate peripheral devices that would be connected to a PDP-11 minicomputer. These files typically have &lt;code&gt;.log&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.dat&lt;/code&gt; extensions. You can remove these files using the &lt;code&gt;run.sh&lt;/code&gt; script and selecting the cleanup temporary files option, as well as manually going into each system directory and entering, in your system shell:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cd UNIX_VERSION_DIRECTORY
rm *.log *.dat
cd ..
&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/felipenlunkes/run-ancient-unix"/><published>2025-11-17T21:46:06+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45959780</id><title>Show HN: Parqeye – A CLI tool to visualize and inspect Parquet files</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:22.471944+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="35fc99af4d856b82"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;parqeye&lt;/code&gt; lets you peek inside your Parquet files. Instantly inspect their contents, schema, and metadata — right from your terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Features&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Interactive Data Visualization - Browse through your Parquet data in a table view with keyboard navigation.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Schema Explorer - Inspect column types, nested structures, and field definitions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File Metadata - View Parquet file-level metadata including version, created by, encoding stats and more.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Row Group Statistics - Examine row group-level metadata, statistics, and data distribution across groups.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tab-based Interface - Quickly switch between Visualize, Schema, Metadata, and Row Groups views.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Terminal-native - Works directly in your terminal.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;parqeye&lt;/code&gt; by providing the path to the &lt;code&gt;.parquet&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;parqeye &amp;lt;path-to-parquet-file&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can download the latest release from the Releases page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can build from source by downloading the repository and running the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cargo build --release
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you use Rust, build directly from crates.io&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cargo install parqeye
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This package is released under the MIT License.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;csvlens for the inspiration&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lazy/streaming loading of parquet files.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Filter columns by value in the visualize tab.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Read parquet files on the cloud (&lt;code&gt;s3://...&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/kaushiksrini/parqeye"/><published>2025-11-17T23:45:42+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45959795</id><title>Windows 11 adds AI agent that runs in background with access to personal folders</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:22.350350+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.windowslatest.com/2025/11/18/windows-11-to-add-an-ai-agent-that-runs-in-background-with-access-to-personal-folders-warns-of-security-risk/"/><published>2025-11-17T23:47:27+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45960368</id><title>Rebecca Heineman has died</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:22.062076+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b06153b0a9e4610"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Legendary game designer, programmer, Space Invaders champion, and LGBTQ trailblazer Rebecca Heineman has died&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heineman's cancer fundraiser is now collecting for her funeral.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Game developer Rebecca Heineman has died after being diagnosed with cancer last month. The news was shared to Bluesky by Heineman's friend, Heidi McDonald, while the most recent post on Heineman's GoFundMe is a goodbye message stating that her health was rapidly deteriorating, and she was entering palliative care. Heineman was 62, and the GoFundMe will remain live to help her family make final arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Born in 1963, Heineman initially made a mark on the industry by winning a national Space Invaders tournament in 1980 in New York, becoming the first formally recognized US champion of any videogame. She went on to have a far-reaching career, being credited on 67 games according to MobyGames.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heineman co-founded Interplay in 1983 alongside Brian Fargo, Jay Patel, and Troy Worrell. The developer and publisher was the source of many foundational PC games, including Wasteland, Fallout, and Baldur's Gate. Heineman designed and programmed a number of games at Interplay, with her most prominent design credit being The Bard's Tale 3: Thief of Fate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heineman's friend and colleague from Interplay, Brian Fargo, shared a remembrance of the developer on X. "Rebecca Heineman sadly passed away," Fargo wrote. "Known her since the 80s when I'd drive her to work, one of the most brilliant programmers around. A real gut punch earlier today when she messaged me: 'We have gone on so many adventures together! But, into the great unknown! I go first!!!'"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later, in the '90s and 2000s, Heineman made a name primarily as a programmer, particularly on ports like the Macintosh versions of Wolfenstein 3D, Baldur's Gate, and Icewind Dale. The saga of Heineman overcoming a deranged businessman to solo program the ill-fated 3DO port of Doom in mere weeks has become a bit of an internet legend: Here's Digital Foundry and Heineman herself recounting the tale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rebecca Heineman sadly passed away. Known her since the 80s when I'd drive her to work, one of the most brilliant programmers around. A real gut punch earlier today when she messaged me: "We have gone on so many adventures together! But, into the great unknown! I go first!!!" :( pic.twitter.com/lu3i0fyt5CNovember 17, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heineman publicly came out as transgender in the 2000s, and was married to fellow games industry legend Jennell Jaquays. Heineman was the recipient of Gayming's 2025 Gayming Icon award, with the site writing that "her advocacy for LGBTQ+ inclusion, accessibility, and diversity in tech has inspired countless developers and players."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jaquays died of complications from Guillain–Barré syndrome in January 2024, and Heineman was blindsided last month by an aggressive cancer diagnosis. She turned to GoFundMe to help with the costs of treatment, where fans, friends, and industry peers showed up to support the developer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep up to date with the most important stories and the best deals, as picked by the PC Gamer team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heineman shared the message last night that her health was rapidly declining.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's time. According to my doctors. All further treatments are pointless," Heineman wrote. "So, please donate so my kids can create a funeral worthy of my keyboard, Pixelbreaker! So I can make a worthy entrance for reuniting with my one true love, Jennell Jaquays."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Game developers have begun sharing their own condolences and remembrances in the wake of Heineman's death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rebecca was one of the founders of Interplay and programmed &amp;amp; designed for some of the most influential games of my youth, notably Bard's Tale I &amp;amp; III and Wasteland. She will be missed.&lt;/p&gt;— @jesawyer.bsky.social (@jesawyer.bsky.social.bsky.social) 2025-11-18T00:17:03.191Z&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A game industry legend died a few mins ago, Rebecca Heineman (@burgerbecky), taken away by aggressive lung cancer. She oversaw the porting of Wizordum to the Mac OS most recently for Apogee. My local friends would often have dinner with her and I loved her industry stories and…November 17, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;What a remarkable human, and what a remarkable thing to know that she passed bemused at reading her own eulogies. Rest in peace, Rebecca. Thank you for everything.&lt;/p&gt;— @ramiismail.com (@ramiismail.com.bsky.social) 2025-11-18T00:15:53.662Z&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rebecca was in my life because she reached out to me, a stranger, because she'd caught wind of a layoff I was impacted by. Her achievements were great, and so too was her kindness.&lt;/p&gt;— @jyoungman.bsky.social (@jyoungman.bsky.social.bsky.social) 2025-11-18T00:15:53.699Z&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rest well, you legend, you pioneer, you wonderful soul. I'm lucky to have known you, though briefly. Please share her legacy by reposting Heidi's message. 💖&lt;/p&gt;— @caseymongillo.bsky.social (@caseymongillo.bsky.social.bsky.social) 2025-11-18T00:15:53.712Z&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;in the early 2000s Rebecca took the time to chat over IRC with a teenaged and gender-confused Me on the practicalities of transition - in a time where being out as trans online was something that could get you socially ostracized. I owe her a lot for that and only hope I can pay it forward.&lt;/p&gt;— @moomanibe.bsky.social (@moomanibe.bsky.social.bsky.social) 2025-11-18T00:15:53.675Z&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025 games: This year's upcoming releases&lt;lb/&gt;Best PC games: Our all-time favorites&lt;lb/&gt;Free PC games: Freebie fest&lt;lb/&gt;Best FPS games: Finest gunplay&lt;lb/&gt;Best RPGs: Grand adventures&lt;lb/&gt;Best co-op games: Better together&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ted has been thinking about PC games and bothering anyone who would listen with his thoughts on them ever since he booted up his sister's copy of Neverwinter Nights on the family computer. He is obsessed with all things CRPG and CRPG-adjacent, but has also covered esports, modding, and rare game collecting. When he's not playing or writing about games, you can find Ted lifting weights on his back porch. You can follow Ted on Bluesky.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must confirm your public display name before commenting&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please logout and then login again, you will then be prompted to enter your display name.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/legendary-game-designer-programmer-space-invaders-champion-and-lgbtq-trailblazer-rebecca-heineman-has-died/"/><published>2025-11-18T01:25:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45960852</id><title>Unofficial "Tier 4" Rust Target for older Windows versions</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:21.466833+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ac60d61a319bb854"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the main source code repository for Rust. It contains the compiler, standard library, and documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Performance: Fast and memory-efficient, suitable for critical services, embedded devices, and easily integrated with other languages.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Reliability: Our rich type system and ownership model ensure memory and thread safety, reducing bugs at compile-time.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Productivity: Comprehensive documentation, a compiler committed to providing great diagnostics, and advanced tooling including package manager and build tool (Cargo), auto-formatter (rustfmt), linter (Clippy) and editor support (rust-analyzer).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read "Installation" from The Book.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you really want to install from source (though this is not recommended), see INSTALL.md.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See https://www.rust-lang.org/community for a list of chat platforms and forums.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See CONTRIBUTING.md.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rust is primarily distributed under the terms of both the MIT license and the Apache License (Version 2.0), with portions covered by various BSD-like licenses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See LICENSE-APACHE, LICENSE-MIT, and COPYRIGHT for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Rust Foundation owns and protects the Rust and Cargo trademarks and logos (the "Rust Trademarks").&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to use these names or brands, please read the media guide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Third-party logos may be subject to third-party copyrights and trademarks. See Licenses for details.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/rust9x/rust"/><published>2025-11-18T02:46:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45960922</id><title>LeJEPA: Provable and Scalable Self-Supervised Learning Without the Heuristics</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:21.175632+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="acdc242ad4ffc2ae"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Machine Learning&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 11 Nov 2025 (v1), last revised 14 Nov 2025 (this version, v3)]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:LeJEPA: Provable and Scalable Self-Supervised Learning Without the Heuristics&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:Learning manipulable representations of the world and its dynamics is central to AI. Joint-Embedding Predictive Architectures (JEPAs) offer a promising blueprint, but lack of practical guidance and theory has led to ad-hoc R&amp;amp;D. We present a comprehensive theory of JEPAs and instantiate it in {\bf LeJEPA}, a lean, scalable, and theoretically grounded training objective. First, we identify the isotropic Gaussian as the optimal distribution that JEPAs' embeddings should follow to minimize downstream prediction risk. Second, we introduce a novel objective--{\bf Sketched Isotropic Gaussian Regularization} (SIGReg)--to constrain embeddings to reach that ideal distribution. Combining the JEPA predictive loss with SIGReg yields LeJEPA with numerous theoretical and practical benefits: (i) single trade-off hyperparameter, (ii) linear time and memory complexity, (iii) stability across hyper-parameters, architectures (ResNets, ViTs, ConvNets) and domains, (iv) heuristics-free, e.g., no stop-gradient, no teacher-student, no hyper-parameter schedulers, and (v) distributed training-friendly implementation requiring only $\approx$50 lines of code. Our empirical validation covers 10+ datasets, 60+ architectures, all with varying scales and domains. As an example, using imagenet-1k for pretraining and linear evaluation with frozen backbone, LeJEPA reaches 79\% with a ViT-H/14. We hope that the simplicity and theory-friendly ecosystem offered by LeJEPA will reestablish self-supervised pre-training as a core pillar of AI research (\href{this https URL}{GitHub repo}).&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Submission history&lt;/head&gt;From: Randall Balestriero [view email]&lt;p&gt;[v1] Tue, 11 Nov 2025 18:21:55 UTC (12,072 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v2] Wed, 12 Nov 2025 14:26:39 UTC (12,072 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v3] Fri, 14 Nov 2025 08:38:32 UTC (12,072 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Current browse context: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;cs.LG&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; IArxiv Recommender (What is IArxiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08544"/><published>2025-11-18T02:58:31+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45961481</id><title>The surprising benefits of giving up</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:21.045870+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="37f482b945538782"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might’ve been told to “hang in there” throughout your childhood, as illustrated by a kitten dangling from a rope. But it turns out that quitting might often be your healthiest option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers have long sought to understand how persistence is linked to personal well-being and human evolution more broadly. One poorly supported theory posited that our ancestors were so determined to catch prey that they ran for long stretches in hot, dry environments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Newer evidence suggests that ditching tough-to-attain goals can actually be good for us. According to a review of more than 230 studies recently published in the journal Nature Human Behaviour, adjusting our goals in response to stress or challenges, rather than grinding on, is often “a more appropriate and beneficial response.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The authors of the sweeping meta-analysis examined 235 studies spanning various fields, including psychology, health, and social sciences, that detailed how people shift their goals after encountering obstacles to success. The researchers wanted to consolidate this “fragmented” information and observe how adjusting goals relates not only to psychological well-being but also physical health, social functioning, and future ambitions. This allowed them to chart a goal “roadmap.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read more: “We Can Be Heroes”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Sticking with impossible goals can take a real toll, with previous research suggesting it can lead to higher stress, poorer well-being, and even physical health costs such as illness,” said study author Hugh Riddell, a professor at the School of Population Health at Curtin University in Australia, in a statement. “But letting go and—crucially—reengaging with new goals, was found to restore purpose and well-being.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The team employed statistical analysis to illuminate what causes people to ditch, adjust, or re-engage with goals. Disengagement from goals, for example, was most strongly linked to negative feedback on these ideas and an “action crisis” stemming from one’s failure to overcome related obstacles. Our personalities might also play a major role in these types of decisions: Optimism tended to be strongly linked to one’s openness to revise a goal to better fit their skills and resources. “These findings indicate that goal-striving flexibility is more likely to emerge when individuals feel secure, exhibit stable regulation, and possess emotional resilience,” the paper notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scientists also analyzed the impacts of these decisions. Giving up on goals was significantly linked to reduced stress, anxiety, and depression, for instance. And adopting new ones was strongly associated with high social and physical functioning. Finding new goals also came with moderate to large benefits to psychological functioning, feeling a sense of purpose in life, satisfaction, and personal growth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This analysis comes with limitations, the authors acknowledge, due to observational data collected at specific points in time and risks of bias in individual papers. The next step, they write, is to pinpoint the specific moment that people should rethink their dreams or keep on chugging. “Finding out when exactly people should stick with their goals or change course, without giving up too early, is really the next piece of the puzzle,” Riddell said in the statement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So whether you’re the type to stick with it to the bitter end or change course when you sense trouble up ahead, there may be an optimal method to help you achieve—or alter—your goals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enjoying Nautilus? Subscribe to our free newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lead image: eamesBot / Shutterstock&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nautil.us/the-surprising-benefits-of-giving-up-1248362/"/><published>2025-11-18T04:44:21+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45962178</id><title>Langfuse (YC W23) Hiring OSS Support Engineers in Berlin and SF</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:20.749273+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e10fcdab2cdf53e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need to enable JavaScript to run this app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/langfuse/5ff18d4d-9066-4c67-8ecc-ffc0e295fee6"/><published>2025-11-18T07:00:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45962654</id><title>How Quake.exe got its TCP/IP stack</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:20.424554+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2eea993caa203e87"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Released in June 1996, Quake had to ride three technological shock-waves during its lifetime. Besides the emergence of 3D hardware accelerator cards and the growth of the Internet, an operating system shift put game developers in a tough position.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With its push for Windows 95 and Windows NT, Microsoft was replacing its legacy PC operating system, MS-DOS. From 1996 to 1997, the market share of DOS dropped by 50%. Some developers, like Blizzard North, took the leap of faith and wrote Windows 95–exclusive titles such as Diablo. id Software on the other hand went through the effort of producing a single binary, &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt;, able to run on both DOS and Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is even more impressive is that id managed to make Quake better when Windows 95 TCP/IP stack was available. Here is how they did it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; is a DOS executable. id Software had used &lt;code&gt;Watcom&lt;/code&gt; compiler for DOOM but they switched to a GCC port named &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt;[1] to cross-compile Quake on Alpha servers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ file quake.exe quake.exe: MS-DOS executable, COFF for MS-DOS, DJGPP go32 DOS extender&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alike &lt;code&gt;watcom&lt;/code&gt;'s &lt;code&gt;DOS/4GW&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt; offered to developers an extender allowing to write programs with flat 32-bit addressing instead of the dreaded 16-bit near/far hellish real-mode otherwise mandated by DOS. An extender works with a client and a server. In the case of Quake the extender client is embedded in &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; while the server is in &lt;code&gt;cwsdpmi.exe&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the beginning of the development, id had requested from &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt; engineers that their DPMI client would be able to run on &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt;'s DPMI server but also Windows 95 DPMI server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It may not be apparent how much of a tour-de-force it was for &lt;code&gt;djgpp&lt;/code&gt; to make their DPMI client work with another DPMI server but knowing a little about how it works, it blows me away. Raymond Chen, Microsoft kernel engineer at the time, had the best description of how to perceive this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;The client application was written with the assumption that it is using the MS-DOS extender that is included with the application, but in reality it is talking to the DPMI host that comes with Windows.&lt;lb/&gt;The fact that programs seem to run mostly okay in spite of running under a foreign extender is either completely astonishing or totally obvious, depending on your point of view.&lt;lb/&gt;It’s completely astonishing because, well, you’re taking a program written to be run in one environment, and running it in a different environment. Or it’s totally obvious because they are using the same DPMI interface, and as long as the interface has the same behavior, then naturally the program will continue to work, because that’s why we have interfaces!&lt;lb/&gt;- Raymond Chen[2]&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being able to run with Windows 95 DPMI server was how &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; pulled off the ability to run under both DOS and Windows 95.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DOOM only needed two files to run, &lt;code&gt;doom.exe&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;doom.wad&lt;/code&gt; but there are many files that came with Quake.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ find quake ./mgenvxd.vxd ./genvxd.dll ./qlaunch.exe ./id1/pak0.pak ./pdipx.com ./cwsdpmi.exe ./q95.bat ./id1/config.cfg ./quake.exe ./quakeudp.dll&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It looks like a mess at first sight but running Quake under DOS only requires four files. Namely, the game engine &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt;, the config file &lt;code&gt;config.cfg&lt;/code&gt;, the asset file &lt;code&gt;pak0.pak&lt;/code&gt;, and the DOS extender server &lt;code&gt;cwsdpmi.exe&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;./mgenvxd.vxd ./genvxd.dll ./qlaunch.exe ./id1/pak0.pak ./pdipx.com ./cwsdpmi.exe ./q95.bat ./id1/config.cfg ./quake.exe ./quakeudp.dll&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quake supported four types of multiplayer protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two modes allowed gamers to enter a duel (1v1). Both modes expected a device plugged into the COM port of the PC. A modem allowed to call an opponent's phone number (hello $$$) while a NullModem cable (called here "Direct Connect") required both computers to be a few feet apart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both IPX and TCP/IP allowed a much more interesting deathmatch featuring up to 16 players. IPX technology was intended for LAN where all machines were a few feet apart, while TCP/IP allowed to reach anybody worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice how, under DOS, by default, both IPX and TCP modes were disabled (greyed out).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quake came with PDIPX.EXE which loaded an IPX DOS TSR. That TSR communicated with a packet driver which in turn hit the network card. Quake was able to probe for that DOS TSR and upon detection allowed players to select IPX.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using TCP/IP was nearly impossible. DOS did not come with a TCP/IP stack and it was something complex enough that only a single vendor provided a TSR for it on DOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The TSR name was BWNFS. Made by Beame &amp;amp; Whiteside, its cost $395 in 1996 ($830 in 2025!)[3]. It is reasonable to say that few gamers ever used TCP/IP on DOS to play QUAKE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; from Windows 95 works like a charm. The executable is loaded into a Windows 95 "dos-box"[4] that virtualizes memory, interrupts, and signals[5]. The game ran exactly like under DOS with the same multiplayer choices available. It was convenient since users did not have to load any mouse driver or set up the &lt;code&gt;BLASTER&lt;/code&gt; environment variable to make the sound card work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Much less convenient however, this way to run Quake requires 16 MiB RAM. Quake only needs 8 MiB but Windows 95 adds quite a bit of overhead! The same files used when running from DOS are used here as well, except for &lt;code&gt;cwsdpmi.exe&lt;/code&gt;, since the DJGPP client detects and uses Windows’ built-in DPMI server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;./mgenvxd.vxd ./genvxd.dll ./qlaunch.exe ./id1/pak0.pak ./pdipx.com ./cwsdpmi.exe ./q95.bat ./id1/config.cfg ./quake.exe ./quakeudp.dll&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is impressive to see Quake run at full speed knowing that Windows 95 runs DOS executable in a virtual machine. My guess is that, in full screen, memory writes and reads to the VGA are given direct access to the hardware to preserve performances.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting &lt;code&gt;quake.exe&lt;/code&gt; from DOS or Windows are not the only two options to run Quake. There is a third one which is to launch &lt;code&gt;q95.bat&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case, a window "Launching Quake" briefly pops up on Windows 95 desktop.&lt;lb/&gt; The text gives a clue about what is happening. Quake is loaded with a tunnel to Winsock, Microsoft's TCP/IP stack. There is further indication of what is doing that, "Powered by Mpath". But not much more to explain how this all works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mpath Interactive was a company dedicated to online gaming. They provided subscription services to help gamers find each other but also operated as an ISP reseller.[6]. It was in their interest to help gaming companies to release titles allowing Internet play as Larry Hastings, an Mpath employee at the time, recalls.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Back then in the primordial ooze that was the mid-90s internet, online multiplayer was still in its infancy. If you wanted to play a multiplayer game on the internet, either you needed to have explicit host &amp;amp; port information, or you needed to use an online multiplayer gaming service. And in 1995 there were only two: us, and Total Entertainment Network. You might think game creators would come to us and say "please put my game on your service!", but... nope! Not only did we have a licensing team that went out and got contracts to license games for our service, but we had to pay the vendor for the right to license their game, which was often an exclusive. So, we had Quake and Unreal; TEN got Duke Nukem 3D and NASCAR.&lt;lb/&gt;The user experience for Mplayer was like this. First, you'd run the "Gizmo", which was a Windows program that acted as a sort of game browser. It knew which compatible games you had installed, and it'd let you browse the multiplayer games on offer for each game; the metaphor we used for this was a "room". Quake was drop-in, so you could simply find a game in progress and hop right in--not a feature of very many games back then. Alternatively, you could find a "room" where someone was proposing to launch a game soon. Or you could create your own. You'd set the name of the room, and the Mplayer Gizmo had some per-game UI that let you set the settings for the game (what map, what features, etc). The room featured text and audio chat, and even a shared "whiteboard", a simple paint program. Once the owner of the "room" "launched" the game, everyone's Gizmos would automatically start the game for them, and the game would automatically join that online game and start playing.&lt;lb/&gt;In order for a game to run on Mplayer, it had to integrate with the Mplayer software stack. Mostly this integration work was done by Mpath engineers; we'd get source code from the game developer and "porting engineers" would get it to run on Mplayer. This often included modifying both the client and the server, so that both could talk via Mplayer's servers.&lt;lb/&gt;The early version of Quake was DOS only, and used the Chunnel to talk to the Windows 95 TCP/IP stack. (Which in retrospect makes the "Chunnel" a type of "thunk", like Microsoft's "Win32s".) I think the deal was, we licensed the Chunnel to id, and in return for that we got to have Quake on Mplayer. So, DOS Quake supported running on Mplayer via the Chunnel, in addition to connecting to open game servers on the Internet via host and port.&lt;lb/&gt;- Larry Hastings (Email conversation)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Larry was kind enough to share some Quake anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;One afternoon shortly after we got our first build of the game, we played a round of deathmatch with the id team over the internet. We were in Cupertino, CA, in a building on Bandley Drive (now a "Fitness Center" for Apple employees). They of course were in Mesquite TX. Yup, it was deathmatch over the internet--very exciting!&lt;lb/&gt;The only id employee I remember for sure being in the game was Tim Willits. He owned us, both because he was way more used to Quake, but also because he knew where all the secrets were. At one point I spotted him coming out of a secret doorway with a rocket launcher. And either he didn't see me, or I died shortly thereafter.&lt;lb/&gt;- Larry Hastings (Email conversation)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As for explaining how the Chunnel worked, I was out of luck.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;I didn't work on the Chunnel. That was mainly a British guy named Henry but I don't remember his last name, it was thirty years ago. All I remember about him is what he looked like, and the fact that he drove a cool car, a white Merkur XR4Ti.&lt;lb/&gt;- Larry Hastings (Email conversation)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When everything else fails, we still have Ghidra and doomworld's amazing community (thanks xttl[7]). After much decompiling and talking, it turned out all files previously ignored were part of Mpath's "Chunnel".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;./mgenvxd.vxd ./genvxd.dll ./qlaunch.exe ./id1/pak0.pak ./pdipx.com ./cwsdpmi.exe ./q95.bat ./id1/config.cfg ./quake.exe ./quakeudp.dll&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;q95.bat&lt;/code&gt; is just a small script to launch mpath's main program. &lt;code&gt;qlauncher.exe&lt;/code&gt; contains all the MPlayer functions. However the role of this executable is limited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It merely loads &lt;code&gt;quakeudp.dll&lt;/code&gt;. Despite its confusing name, this DLL is the heart of Quake Chunnel. It is the bridge to Microsoft TCP/UDP/IP stack (&lt;code&gt;wsock32.dll&lt;/code&gt;). It also starts Quake with &lt;code&gt;-path&lt;/code&gt; parameter to make it load a BSD network socket API &lt;code&gt;sys/socket.h&lt;/code&gt;. Finally, it also loads the virtual device driver manager &lt;code&gt;genvxd.dll&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The virtual device is the trick that allows a DOS executable running inside a Windows 95 dos box to communicate with win32. The &lt;code&gt;genvxd.dll&lt;/code&gt; dynamic library loads a virtual device driver[8] named &lt;code&gt;GENVXD.VXD&lt;/code&gt; which installs itself to respond on interrupt &lt;code&gt;0x48&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last piece of the puzzle is on Quake side. The implementation of BSD &lt;code&gt;sys/socket.h&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mpplc.c&lt;/code&gt;, is code provided by Mpath. It takes care of marshaling every BSD socket function call, then use the DPMI client to trigger a software interrupt that is received in win32 land. Data is passed up the pipeline we previously described until it is unmarshalled by &lt;code&gt;genvxd.dll&lt;/code&gt; and routed towards &lt;code&gt;wsock32.dll&lt;/code&gt;. Notice the symmetry of functions found in &lt;code&gt;mplib.c&lt;/code&gt; marshalling and the symbols found in &lt;code&gt;genvxd.dll&lt;/code&gt; unmarshalling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems John Cash was involved in compiling Mpath's stuff. We can find his name in the symbols of &lt;code&gt;mgenvxd.vxd&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;F:\cashcode\GENVXD\bin\Mgenvxd.pdb&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The source code of mgenvxd.vxd, genvxd.dll, qlaunch.exe and quakeudp.dll was never released. It was a proprietary, patented technology from Mpath. It is likely id only got permission to release the client side of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as I understood it, that is how Quake was able to send TCP and UDP packets over IP. This convoluted construct became obsolete when id stopped shipping DOS executable (the last one being &lt;code&gt;vquake.exe&lt;/code&gt;). After Dec 1996, &lt;code&gt;winquake.exe&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;glquake.exe&lt;/code&gt;, and all QuakeWorld binaries were win32 exclusive with direct access to &lt;code&gt;wsock32.dll&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://fabiensanglard.net/quake_chunnel/index.html"/><published>2025-11-18T08:18:35+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45963583</id><title>The Miracle of Wörgl</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:18.732283+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2681901966d72d90"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Story of Wörgl and others&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Miracle of Wörgl&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wörgl was the first in town in Austria that effectively managed to eliminate the extreme unemployment caused by the Great Depression. Its local currency experiment was such a success that it gained worldwide attention. That effort became known as the “Miracle of Wörgl .” For the full details, go here. Here is the summary of that story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On July 5th 1932, in the middle of the Great Depression, the Austrian town of Wörgl made economic history by introducing a remarkable complimentary currency. Wörgl was in trouble, and was prepared to try anything. Of its population of 4,500, a total of 1,500 people were without a job, and 200 families were penniless. The mayor, Michael Unterguggenberger, had a long list of projects he wanted to accomplish, but there was hardly any money with which to carry them out. These included repaving the roads, streetlights, extending water distribution across the whole town, and planting trees along the streets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rather than spending the 40,000 Austrian schillings in the town’s coffers to start these projects off, he deposited them in a local savings bank as a guarantee to back the issue of a type of complimentary currency known as ‘stamp scrip’. The Mayor then proceeded to hire people to do infrastructure projects for the town and the community quickly went from an unemployment rate of over 30% to near zero, as that money began to circulate very rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of all the business in town, only the railway station and the post office refused to accept the local money. When people ran out of spending ideas, they would pay their taxes early using scrip, resulting in a huge increase in town revenues. Over the 13-month period the project ran, the council not only carried out all the intended works projects, but also built new houses, a reservoir, a ski jump, and a bridge. The people also used scrip to replant forests, in anticipation of the future cash flow they would receive from the trees.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Six neighbouring villages copied the system successfully. The French Prime Minister, Eduoard Dalladier, made a special visit to see the ‘miracle of Wörgl’. In January 1933, the project was replicated in the neighbouring city of Kirchbuhl, and in June 1933, Unterguggenburger addressed a meeting with representatives from 170 different towns and villages. Two hundred Austrian townships were interested in adopting the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, the central bank panicked, and decided to assert its monopoly rights by banning complimentary currencies. The people unsuccessfully sued the bank, and later lost in the Austrian Supreme Court. It then became a criminal offence to issue ’emergency currency’. The town went back to 30% unemployment. In 1934, social unrest exploded across Austria. In 1938, when Hitler annexed Austria, he was welcomed by many people as their economic and political saviour.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the success of Wörgl attracted the attention of one of the leading economists in the U.S. at the time, Professor Irving Fisher, who informed the FDR administration he thought that idea could be used to end the Great Depression. That story is next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Irving Fisher, the Great Depression and FDR&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Professor Irving Fisher learned of the success of Wörgl and other European experiments, he determined that “The correct application of stamp scrip would solve the Depression crisis in the U.S. in three weeks.” He presented his findings to Dean Acheson, then under-secretary of the Treasury under FDR. Acheson sought input from Harvard economics professor Russell Sprague, who told him that this approach could indeed succeed in bringing America out of the Depression, but cautioned him to check with the President.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He did so. Unfortunately, fearing decentralization, President Roosevelt denounced complementary currencies soon afterwards and they were prohibited. He did so in probably his most famous address, the one including the phrase “The only thing we need to fear is fear itself.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In that speech he also announced that by “executive decree” he would henceforth prohibit ‘emergency currencies’. This was the code name for all the complementary currencies already in existence, and all those in preparation around the country. That prohibition lasted for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Imagine if Fisher’s recommendation had held the day. The Great Depression would have ended well before World War II and a great deal of suffering would have been avoided. Fortunately, complementary currencies are now legal in just about every country, as evidenced by the popularity of cryptocurrencies, one form of a complementary currency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Central Middle Ages and Cathedrals&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We now come to one of the most prolonged and significant times where the use of complementary currencies had a profound and widespread positive impact on the communities that adopted them. Here we find a sustained period of 250 years (1040-1290) of financial success based on local currencies spread throughout Western Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chapter 6 from the book, New Money for a New World by Bernard Lietaer (co-architect of the Euro) and Stephen Belgin details that period of widespread abundance throughout Western Europe that can be directly attributed to the extensive use of local currencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The authors note that, “There was work for all, with favorable working conditions and abundant time for family, community, and personal pursuits. This epoch was also characterized by significant advancements in science, technology, education, literature, music, arts, craftsmanship, and more.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It all commenced when communities like Paris decided they wanted to build a local cathedral like Notre Dame, each a massive infrastructure project that lasted on average between 50 and 100 years. Those communities printed their own money and hired architects, stone masons, carpenters, lead workers, glass workers and more to build those magnificent edifices and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What most people don’t know is that those citizens were directly responsible for building more than 1,000 cathedrals in Western Europe, alongside 350,000 churches and several thousand large abbeys. That means over 1,000 European communities adopted their own complementary currency program, yielding a building phase rarely matched throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Month after month those communities paid those workers “new money” they printed up which in turn was injected into the local economy. That money was spent on food, clothing, shelter and all the necessities of life, which stimulated all manner of new local merchants and the jobs they produced.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This medieval building phenomenon is more remarkable still,” say the authors, “given that there was no central authority, church or otherwise, in charge of initiating or funding the construction of these cathedrals. Contrary to popular belief today, these structures were neither built by nor belonged to the church or nobility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Local nobility and royalty customarily did make contributions, but these monuments were typically owned and financed by the citizens of the municipalities where they were built.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those efforts initiated over 800 years ago are still providing financial returns today. Tourists flock to those cathedrals bringing with them money that they leave in the communities they visit. Almost nothing in history has provided a greater return on investment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More examples&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See this document, Complementary Currencies in Use for more examples of complementary currencies and the positive impact they had on the communities that adopted them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://scf.green/story-of-worgl-and-others/"/><published>2025-11-18T10:59:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45963780</id><title>Cloudflare Global Network experiencing issues</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:18.105722+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e73fa6963d75d83"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Ahmedabad, India - (AMD) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Almaty, Kazakhstan - (ALA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Bangalore, India - (BLR) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Bangkok, Thailand - (BKK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Bandar Seri Begawan, Brunei - (BWN) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Cebu, Philippines - (CEB) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chandigarh, India - (IXC) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Changde, China - (CGD) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chennai, India - (MAA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chittagong, Bangladesh - (CGP) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Colombo, Sri Lanka - (CMB) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Dhaka, Bangladesh - (DAC) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Foshan, China - (FUO) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Fukuoka, Japan - (FUK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Fuzhou, China - (FOC) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Guangzhou, China - (CAN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Haikou, China - (HAK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Hanoi, Vietnam - (HAN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Hengshui, China - (SJW) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam - (SGN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Hong Kong - (HKG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Hyderabad, India - (HYD) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Islamabad, Pakistan - (ISB) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Jakarta, Indonesia - (CGK) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Jinan, China - (TNA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Johor Bahru, Malaysia - (JHB) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kanpur, India - (KNU) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kaohsiung City, Taiwan - (KHH) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Karachi, Pakistan - (KHI) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kathmandu, Nepal - (KTM) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kolkata, India - (CCU) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Krasnoyarsk, Russia - (KJA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia - (KUL) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Langfang, China - (PKX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Macau - (MFM) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Malé, Maldives - (MLE) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Manila, Philippines - (MNL) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Mumbai, India - (BOM) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Nagpur, India - (NAG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Naha, Japan - (OKA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; New Delhi, India - (DEL) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Osaka, Japan - (KIX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Patna, India - (PAT) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Phnom Penh, Cambodia - (PNH) Under Maintenance &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Qingdao, China - (TAO) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Seoul, South Korea - (ICN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Shanghai, China - (SHA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Singapore, Singapore - (SIN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Surat Thani, Thailand - (URT) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Taipei - (TPE) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Tokyo, Japan - (NRT) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Ulaanbaatar, Mongolia - (ULN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Vientiane, Laos - (VTE) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Xinyu, China - (KHN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Yerevan, Armenia - (EVN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Yogyakarta, Indonesia - (JOG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Cagayan de Oro, Philippines - (CGY) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kochi, India - (COK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Denpasar, Indonesia - (DPS) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kannur, India - (CNN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Shenzhen, China - (SZX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Guiyang, China - (KWE) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Shaoxing, China - (HGH) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Changzhou, China - (CZX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kunming, China - (KMG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chiang Mai, Thailand - (CNX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Zhengzhou, China - (CGO) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Yangquan, China - (TYN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Changsha, China - (CSX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Dalian, China - (DLC) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Beihai, China - (BHY) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chongqing, China - (CKG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Xiangyang, China - (XFN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Da Nang, Vietnam - (DAD) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Jiaxing, China - (JXG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Tarlac City, Philippines - (CRK) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Thimphu, Bhutan - (PBH) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Baoji, China - (XIY) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Astana, Kazakhstan - (NQZ) Partial Outage &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Nanning, China - (NNG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Zibo, China - (TNA) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Kuching, Malaysia - (KCH) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Aktobe, Kazakhstan - (AKX) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Chengmai, China - (HAK) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Nanchang, China - (KHN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Male, Maldives - (MLE) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Tongren, China - (TEN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Taizhou, China - (HYN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Shijiazhuang, China - (SJW) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Xining, China - (XNN) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan - (FRU) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Malang, Indonesia - (MLG) Operational &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.cloudflarestatus.com/?t=1"/><published>2025-11-18T11:35:10+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45963836</id><title>Gemini 3 Pro Model Card</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:17.692638+00:00</updated><link href="https://pixeldrain.com/u/hwgaNKeH"/><published>2025-11-18T11:40:01+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45964835</id><title>GoSign Desktop RCE flaws affecting users in Italy</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:17.463517+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.ush.it/2025/11/14/multiple-vulnerabilities-gosign-desktop-remote-code-execution/"/><published>2025-11-18T12:36:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45964987</id><title>Multiple Digital Ocean services down</title><updated>2025-11-18T13:05:17.194265+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d4ec18d2935020af"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt; Subscribe to updates for &lt;strong&gt;Multiple Services Disruption&lt;/strong&gt; via email and/or text message. You'll receive email notifications when incidents are updated, and text message notifications whenever DigitalOcean &lt;strong&gt;creates&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;resolves&lt;/strong&gt; an incident. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;VIA SMS:&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;
              &lt;select&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Afghanistan (+93)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Albania (+355)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Algeria (+213)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;American Samoa (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Andorra (+376)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Angola (+244)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Anguilla (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Antigua and Barbuda (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Argentina (+54)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Armenia (+374)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Aruba (+297)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Australia/Cocos/Christmas Island (+61)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Austria (+43)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Azerbaijan (+994)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Bahamas (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Bahrain (+973)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Bangladesh (+880)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Barbados (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Belarus (+375)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Belgium (+32)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Belize (+501)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Benin (+229)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Bermuda (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Bolivia (+591)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Bosnia and Herzegovina (+387)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Botswana (+267)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Brazil (+55)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Brunei (+673)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Bulgaria (+359)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Burkina Faso (+226)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Burundi (+257)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Cambodia (+855)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Cameroon (+237)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Canada (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Cape Verde (+238)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Cayman Islands (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Central Africa (+236)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Chad (+235)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Chile (+56)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;China (+86)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Colombia (+57)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Comoros (+269)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Congo (+242)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Congo, Dem Rep (+243)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Costa Rica (+506)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Croatia (+385)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Cyprus (+357)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Czech Republic (+420)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Denmark (+45)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Djibouti (+253)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Dominica (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Dominican Republic (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Egypt (+20)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;El Salvador (+503)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Equatorial Guinea (+240)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Estonia (+372)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Ethiopia (+251)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Faroe Islands (+298)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Fiji (+679)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Finland/Aland Islands (+358)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;France (+33)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;French Guiana (+594)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;French Polynesia (+689)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Gabon (+241)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Gambia (+220)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Georgia (+995)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Germany (+49)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Ghana (+233)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Gibraltar (+350)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Greece (+30)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Greenland (+299)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Grenada (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Guadeloupe (+590)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Guam (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Guatemala (+502)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Guinea (+224)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Guyana (+592)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Haiti (+509)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Honduras (+504)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Hong Kong (+852)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Hungary (+36)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Iceland (+354)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;India (+91)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Indonesia (+62)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Iraq (+964)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Ireland (+353)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Israel (+972)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Italy (+39)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Jamaica (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Japan (+81)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Jordan (+962)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Kenya (+254)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Korea, Republic of (+82)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Kosovo (+383)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Kuwait (+965)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Kyrgyzstan (+996)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Laos (+856)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Latvia (+371)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Lebanon (+961)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Lesotho (+266)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Liberia (+231)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Libya (+218)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Liechtenstein (+423)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Lithuania (+370)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Luxembourg (+352)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Macao (+853)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Macedonia (+389)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Madagascar (+261)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Malawi (+265)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Malaysia (+60)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Maldives (+960)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Mali (+223)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Malta (+356)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Martinique (+596)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Mauritania (+222)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Mauritius (+230)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Mexico (+52)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Monaco (+377)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Mongolia (+976)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Montenegro (+382)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Montserrat (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Morocco/Western Sahara (+212)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Mozambique (+258)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Namibia (+264)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Nepal (+977)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Netherlands (+31)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;New Zealand (+64)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Nicaragua (+505)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Niger (+227)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Nigeria (+234)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Norway (+47)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Oman (+968)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Pakistan (+92)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Palestinian Territory (+970)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Panama (+507)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Paraguay (+595)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Peru (+51)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Philippines (+63)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Poland (+48)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Portugal (+351)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Puerto Rico (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Qatar (+974)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Reunion/Mayotte (+262)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Romania (+40)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Russia/Kazakhstan (+7)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Rwanda (+250)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Samoa (+685)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;San Marino (+378)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Saudi Arabia (+966)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Senegal (+221)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Serbia (+381)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Seychelles (+248)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Sierra Leone (+232)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Singapore (+65)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Slovakia (+421)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Slovenia (+386)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;South Africa (+27)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Spain (+34)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Sri Lanka (+94)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;St Kitts and Nevis (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;St Lucia (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;St Vincent Grenadines (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Sudan (+249)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Suriname (+597)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Swaziland (+268)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Sweden (+46)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Switzerland (+41)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Taiwan (+886)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Tajikistan (+992)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Tanzania (+255)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Thailand (+66)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Togo (+228)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Tonga (+676)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Trinidad and Tobago (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Tunisia (+216)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Turkey (+90)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Turks and Caicos Islands (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Uganda (+256)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Ukraine (+380)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;United Arab Emirates (+971)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;United Kingdom (+44)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;United States (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Uruguay (+598)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Uzbekistan (+998)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Venezuela (+58)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Vietnam (+84)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Virgin Islands, British (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Virgin Islands, U.S. (+1)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Yemen (+967)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Zambia (+260)&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option&gt;Zimbabwe (+263)&lt;/option&gt;
              &lt;/select&gt;
            &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Enter mobile number&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;label&gt;Enter the OTP sent&lt;/label&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;To receive SMS updates, please verify your number. To proceed with just email click ‘Subscribe’ &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://status.digitalocean.com/incidents/lgt5xs2843rx"/><published>2025-11-18T12:48:45+00:00</published></entry></feed>