<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:48.277424+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45857053</id><title>Ticker: Don't die of heart disease</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:55.444611+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3ee91a0749e397e6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by Jared Hecht (blog, linkedin, twitter)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ToC&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TLDR&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why am I doing this?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Background&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Perverse Incentives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What is heart disease?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Preventing Disease&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How to not die of heart disease&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Current State of Affairs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What To Do&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Biomarkers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Imaging Diagnostics&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Treatment&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Medication&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Behavioral&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t Die!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How to get this from your doctor&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What should you do with your test results?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;TLDR&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You should be scared of heart disease. Heart disease is the leading cause of death globally, and it’s not just an old people problem. 25% of heart attacks occur in people under the age of 55.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The first sign of heart disease for many people is they drop dead of a heart attack. It’s a quiet disease that develops silently over many decades and then suddenly appears when it kills you.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You don’t have to die of heart disease if you don’t want to.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The way really rich people avoid dying of heart disease is they go to very expensive high-end concierge doctors who focus on preventative medicine (i.e. practitioners who help you prevent getting sick in the first place).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;But the things they do to avoid heart disease are simple and accessible to everyone. Instead of paying tens of thousands of dollars a year to see these expensive concierge doctors, you can actually do all the most important tests yourself for less than $300, and most medications you’d need should be covered by insurance.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We have all the knowledge, testing, diagnostics, and treatments to prevent heart disease and you can follow this instruction manual to start taking your heart health into your own hands.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The best time to make the decision to not die of heart disease and start taking action is in your 30s and 40s.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You cannot rely on your doctor to help you prevent heart disease or a heart attack. They are there to help you when you’re sick with heart disease or if you survive your first heart attack. You are the only person who can prevent yourself from dying of heart disease. The good news is, it’s pretty darn easy.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you only read one thing here, make it the “How to not die of heart disease” section.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can read my first post about heart disease here to see where it got started, and more about why I published this here. You can also download the PDF version here.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you are building or want to build something in this space and help people not die of heart disease, please email me at jared@usv.com.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why am I doing this?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One thing I’ve learned through experience is that nobody has your back in the healthcare system. You need to be your own Advocate. I want to help people become their own Advocate and put their heart health in their own hands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In early 2023 during a routine skin check at my dermatologist, I uncovered a basal-cell carcinoma. It’s a benign form of skin cancer. I freaked out. For the first time in my life I began to seriously think about my own mortality. I have two young children and I want to be there for them as they get old and be an engaged grandfather and all that amazing stuff. I don’t want to die young and have them grow up fatherless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I did the cliche thing every tech-entrepreneur-dude does: I signed up for a very expensive high-end concierge medicine service. This is an extraordinary privilege. I wanted to cover my bases, make sure nothing else was wrong with me, and do my best to understand how to stay healthy and protect against anything that could conceivably kill me while being relatively young. I wanted to control the things I could control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first thing that this high-end concierge practice did was evaluate my heart health. I thought my heart was totally fine. Previously, I would visit my primary care physician (PCP) twice a year and get my bloodwork done annually. Here’s what my last standard lipid panel (a standard cardiometabolic test conducted by most physicians) from my PCP looked like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The results told me my LDL-C was fine, and my doctor said I didn’t need to take any additional preventative measures. I should simply maintain whatever it was I had been doing (e.g. exercising and eating somewhat healthy). This was from Forward Health - a tech-forward company that attempted to be a better version of One Medical. I shared these results with a leading lipidologist who proclaimed: “Not sure if the lab or the primary care doc said an LDL-C of 116 mg/dL was fine but that concentration is the 50th percentile population cut point in the MESA study and should never ever be considered as normal.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I signed up for concierge medicine, the first thing they did was an extended lipid panel - a more extensive test that measures more important biomarkers like ApoB and Lp(a). I was shocked when my results came back:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I learned that my ApoB (Apoliproprotein B) is not good. (It’s also important to note that, according to a lipidologist friend, an ApoB of 96 is at a totally unacceptable 50th percentile population cutpoint from Framingham Offspring Study.) I needed to get it lower. This test showed that if I continued on my trajectory, I would likely suffer from heart disease over time. This test also told me I don’t suffer from bad Lp(a) - that was a relief. As a result of my high ApoB and moderate LDL-C, my doctor immediately prescribed a statin and said I should get a CTA scan to detect any existing heart disease. My CTA scan confirmed that I had calcified plaque in my arteries (ie, heart disease). (By the way, I’ll get to what all of these fancy acronyms mean soon. Don’t worry if you don’t know what they are - I didn’t know either.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comparing and contrasting these two experiences was profoundly insightful for me. My PCP (primary care physician) was following standard guidelines and proclaimed that based on my results I was “totally okay.” He was not looking for more important biomarkers like ApoB or Lp(a) or Hs-CRP. I could go on my merry way and do my thing. But my expensive concierge doctor showed me I had early-stage heart disease, needed to be on a statin to lower my ApoB, and that if I kept doing whatever I was doing, I’d grow increasingly more at risk of dying of heart disease. Since then, I’ve course-corrected and taken my heart health seriously. It’s something I work on every day and it’s reflected in the medications I take, the tests I get, the food I eat, and the way I live my life. I’ve made the conscious decision to not die of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I quickly realized that I didn’t need to sign up for an expensive concierge service to get these tests done. If I had known more about heart health beforehand, I could have asked (well, really demanded) my PCP to order these tests for me. When it comes to heart health, the tests you need to understand the most important biomarkers and whether or not you have disease (via imaging) are affordable for most people. We are talking $80 or so of blood tests twice annually and a one-time $150 imaging test that needs to be done every one to five years depending on your results. You don’t have to be rich to protect your heart the exact same way many billionaires and millionaires do. As far as preventative health goes, it’s easy, and my goal with this is to provide the knowledge, tools, and playbook to help you take control of your heart health the same way an elite billionaire would. For almost everyone, you don’t have to die of heart disease if you don’t want to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other reason I am doing this is because it’s critical that people be their own Advocate when they navigate the health system, and I want this to be a tool for everyone to do exactly that. What does being your own Advocate mean? I learned the term Advocate from my father-in-law who is a retired gastroenterologist. After we had our first child, my wife suffered from complications from a c-section. We were tied up in the hospital for over a week, and it was unclear whether we’d all make it home together. We were at one of the best hospitals in the country, but the attention we received from attending doctors and nurses was pretty frightening. Hours would go by between visits. They’d prescribe medications only to have them filled the following day. I quickly grew frustrated and realized that we needed to fight to take care of ourselves and find the right balance of being aggressively pushy and likable to the doctors and nurses. Even in hospitals where you think you are supposed to be taken care of every step of the way, you still need to fight for yourself and your loved ones. When I told my father-in-law about what was happening and that I was worried I was being too demanding, he told me I was doing the right thing by being our family’s Advocate, and that every doctor who is admitted to a hospital knows to do this if they want to receive quality care.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I experienced this repeatedly. We were admitted to the hospital for over a week when my daughter contracted viral meningitis (the scariest experience of my life). Even while working with incredible infectious disease doctors, I still had to fight and constantly remind people what the next steps were during our admission. Nobody is watching over you - it’s your job to organize things and ensure they’re on track. I had to coordinate between the infectious disease departments and neurology departments and make sure the people doing the lumbar puncture on my 9-month-old daughter weren’t just residents practicing on my child but experts who had conducted the procedure countless times before. You must Advocate for yourself and the ones you love.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While doctors may have the best of intentions and have in many ways engaged in one of the noblest of professions, they cannot and do not take care of you as well as you can take care of yourself. We are participating in a healthcare system that is incentivized to prioritize making money as opposed to keeping us healthy and out of the system in the first place. You need to fight for yourself. This guide is intended to help you fight for your heart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am also doing this because, like any child, there’s something deep down inside of me that wants to make my parents proud. Both of my parents are doctors. My mother was an internist for many years and my father was a cardiologist. He spent almost the entirety of his career trying to convince people they didn’t have to die of heart disease, and that we could use new technologies, namely CT and CTA scans, to detect and treat heart disease. His quest was initially met with resistance, but over time people converted, and now every cardiologist who understands anything about heart disease believes in what my father fought for, and they know his name and the work that he has done. He is widely published and has taught a new generation of cardiologists best practices when it comes to using imaging to detect and understand heart disease. There’s a piece of me that wants to help progress his work and bring what he has shared with the medical world to the broader patient population.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m a technology investor and entrepreneur, and believe we need a consumer facing company that is specifically dedicated to helping people not die of heart disease. I think you can do a lot of good in the world and build something quite meaningful by focusing on this problem. I have an idea of what the product and service looks like, but the thing I am questioning is how many people actually care about this? And care enough about it to actually do something. Of course we don’t want to die of something that’s totally avoidable, but heart disease is not something we experience every day. When we do experience it it’s because we either drop dead of a heart attack, have a near-death scare from a heart attack, or know someone in our family or friend group who suffered from a heart attack. We don’t think about it daily, and taking care of ourselves requires preventative measures that most people either don’t have the time to do or they just don’t want to prioritize. I get that completely. These services can also be expensive (although I am convinced a heart focused one can be delivered in an affordable way to millions of people). So part of my motivation is to actually see how many people care about this. How many people will read this? How many people will take the simple steps to avoid heart disease? And how many people would be interested in a service that makes taking these steps seamless and easy and affordable? I don’t know the answers to those questions, and I want to help figure them out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I do know is that whenever I talk about this with friends, their eyes light up. Particularly friends in their 30s and 40s who have recently had children and now think about their own mortality. They’re all interested in this, but I’ve been disappointed that only a minority of them have actually taken the requisite steps that I’ve learned about and recommend in this guide. I hope that changes. I’m an optimist, so I think it will. Today when I was dropping my children off at school, a fellow parent and entrepreneur told me he read an article I wrote about heart disease and called his doctor and is getting tested. That gave me hope. Interactions like that make me believe this is a worthwhile endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the very least, I hope this guide is informative and helps you or someone you love avoid dying from heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heart disease is the leading cause of death globally. It is the thing that kills more people on Planet Earth every year than anything else for both men and women.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not just an old-people problem. 25% of heart attacks occur in people younger than 54 years of age. This is a staggering statistic unknown to most, including primary care physicians! That percentage continues to grow over time as the general population becomes increasingly less healthy (ie, sedentary, obese, poor diet, etc.). For all the damage heart disease inflicts on people’s lives and our health systems, it receives very little attention. Take a look at how frequently population killers are covered by the media:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not sexy, and as a result, an overwhelming majority of the population is unaware of how to avoid succumbing to it. I think that’s super messed up and needs to change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thing about heart disease is that we have all the tools to make it a nonentity and remove it from the Top 10 leading causes of death. Unfortunately, for a whole host of reasons, our primary care physicians are neither equipped or incentivized to lead the charge on fixing the problem. More often than not the first sign that someone has heart disease is they drop dead of a heart attack. And by the time fortunate patients who don’t drop dead approach their doctor about chest pain or other symptoms (eg shortness of breath with exertion, palpitations, vague dizziness, and fatigue) and are referred to a cardiologist, that cardiologist is going to wish you had visited them five years ago. Atherosclerosis is a disease that slowly builds over decades, so the best way to really avoid dying from it is to start getting educated and taking action in your late 20s, 30s, and 40s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past several months, I’ve spoken with several of the world’s leading cardiologists and lipidologists to better understand the key elements of heart disease prevention. One lipidologist I spoke with who works for a high-end concierge medicine service has had zero patients die of heart disease in the past ten years. What he does is not rocket science and anyone can do it if they know the right questions to ask. I’ve been compiling notes to get to the lowest common denominator of what is good enough and affordable so I can arm friends and family with the information and steps to put their heart health in their own hands. The best doctors unanimously agree that this is a preventable disease, but patients just don’t know what to do or how to navigate the health system to make sure they don’t succumb to it. This begs the question, if it’s so preventable, why don’t doctors take care of this for you?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Perverse Incentives&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This section is just me on a soapbox with an axe to grind about the way our healthcare system works. Feel free to skip it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People who enter the medical profession usually do so for noble reasons. They want to help other people. It is extremely rewarding to save lives, and also emotionally turbulent when you can’t. Growing up, I watched my parents go to the hospital at all hours of the night when they were on-call. Their pagers would buzz and they’d drive right in. It’s a physically exhausting vocation, too. Doctors do not get enough credit for what they go through, both in terms of the time they spend training and the money they spend on medical school.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, as noble as the profession is, the incentives of our healthcare system are royally messed up. I am a firm believer that incentives drive behaviors. You can pretty much learn everything you need to know about why an industry works a certain way based on the underlying economic incentives. As a result, our healthcare system in the US is actually sick-care. It’s designed to treat sickness. That’s how it makes money. The sicker we are and the longer we are sick, the better it is for healthcare systems: from hospitals to big pharma to primary care doctors and all of these different constituents’ employees. The system doesn’t make money unless we are sick. (I highly recommend reading the book An American Sickness if you are interested in learning more about this.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you understand that, it becomes obvious why we receive the type of medical care we do. Very few people in the medical profession are focused on ensuring we do not get sick. This work is largely relegated to preventative care doctors. Most of their services are out-of-pocket expenses since insurance really only covers things that treat sickness, not things that prevent it. That fact in and of itself is absolutely nuts. You’d think that insurance companies would want to pay to prevent you from getting sick because paying to treat you when you get sick is exponentially more expensive. But since your insurance is normally covered by your employer, and since the average American only stays with their employer for 3-4 years, there is no incentive to keep you from getting really sick since it likely will happen when you’re employed by someone else and under their insurance plan and dime. That is something uniquely American and a severe dysfunction of the system. Nobody wants to foot the bill for someone else’s problem down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyways, back to these high-end concierge doctors that focus on preventative care. Since you’re paying out of pocket for them, they’re usually pretty darn good. They know a lot and are willing to do things that are outside of the standard healthcare guidelines. That’s because our guidelines usually lag 10-20 years behind the current science, and these preventative doctors follow the current science or something closer to it. The best practices they engage in are not common knowledge amongst most primary care physicians who are focused on cramming in as many patients in a day (every minute they run over with you is a dollar lost spending time with someone else). A lot of what concierge doctors do is bespoke and somewhat sophisticated and specific to their practices. But surprisingly, what they do to prevent and treat heart disease is not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After speaking with many different practitioners who work in and run these practices, I’ve come to learn that everyone can get the same type of preventative heart healthcare that billionaires receive for roughly $300 or less a year. In fact, one person I spoke with who runs a very high-end concierge practice said to me that the heart health protocol of concierge medicine is something that really anyone can participate in so long as they know how to navigate it. That’s been the thing that’s shocked me the most - the fact that all of us can have access to the same heart healthcare that billionaires have access to for a couple hundred dollars out of pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;What is heart disease?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are several different conditions that are categorized as heart disease, but for the sake of simplicity, I am going to talk about the most common one: atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (which I will henceforth refer to as ASCVD). ASCVD is what happens when cholesterol-laden plaque accumulates in the arteries and begins to obstruct blood flow to the heart and other parts of the body. Heart attacks happen when this plaque breaks free of the artery walls and clogs your artery pathway (called the lumens), creating a blood clot that restricts blood flow. This often results in death. This is also what causes a stroke, but instead of blood not being able to circulate to the heart, it cannot circulate to the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ASCVD is bad because the accumulation of plaque in your arteries is the thing that leads to a heart attack, and that’s the thing that can lead to death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So how does plaque form? The short answer is that something called LDL penetrates your artery walls and begins to accumulate there and gradually turns into plaque.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The medium scientific answer (which I’ve mostly summarized from the work of Peter Attia and Thomas Dayspring) is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Plaque forms in your arteries when a lipoprotein (a particle made of protein and fats that carries cholesterol and triglycerides through your bloodstream to your cells) called ApoB (short for apolipoprotein B, a lipoprotein that coats LDL) crosses the endothelium and gets stuck in the subendothelial space after it becomes oxidized there. There are several things that enable ApoB to make this journey, like smoking and high blood pressure which damage the endothelium and make it vulnerable to penetration. When ApoB accumulates in the subendothelium the immune system tries to attack them and it sends monocytes that turn into macrophages to eat this oxidized LDL in order to remove it from the artery walls. If the macrophages eat too much of it they explode into foam cells and when enough foam cells gather they form a fatty streak in the coronary artery. That is plaque! What’s crazy is this process begins when you are a teenager and compounds over the duration of your life. For some it moves fast, for others it moves slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These foam cells continue to ooze together and form a mass of lipids. To control the damage smooth muscle cells in your artery migrate to this site and they secrete a kind of matrix in an attempt to build a barrier around it, just like a scar, that ends up as a fibrous cap atop arterial plaque. This plaque continues to grow, at first towards the outer arterial wall, but then into the lumen, the passage through which the blood flows. At a certain point in time this plaque hardens and becomes calcified. Once it’s calcified it mostly becomes a permanent fixture within your artery. Since it’s calcified it doesn’t go anywhere. While it may seem scary, calcified plaque is not the plaque that breaks free and causes a blood clot leading to a heart attack. It’s the non-calcified plaque - or soft plaque, the stuff that over time becomes calcified - that we need to worry about. Soft plaque can erode and rupture and create a heart attack via blood clot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also like Jeffrey Wessler’s simple explanation of heart disease: “Coronary artery disease occurs when circulating fats in the blood (e.g. LDL) are pushed by a driving force (i.e. blood pressure) into a vessel wall that is vulnerable.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are several things called risk factors that increase the likelihood of developing heart disease (ie these are conditions that make it more likely bad things happen). Examples include things like high blood pressure (which, as Jeff alluded to, is the driving force pushing that LDL into your artery walls), high blood cholesterol (if you have more LDL in your blood, then it increases the likelihood it can penetrate your artery walls), and smoking (which damages and inflames your artery walls, making it easier for that LDL to enter). Over 50% of people in the United States have at least one of these risk factors. There are other medical conditions and lifestyle choices that are risk factors, too, like diabetes, obesity, poor nutrition, being physically inactive, and drinking alcohol - pretty much the run-of-the-mill things that we’ve all heard about that are considered unhealthy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My father’s friend, James Min, an entrepreneur and guru of mine who started Cleerly, explains heart disease as something that is multi-parametric. It’s a fancy way to say there are multiple different components as driving factors. He classified them as the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Thrombotic - how well does your blood flow through your body?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inflammatory - what is the state of your arteries and general cardiovascular system? Are they functional and healthy? Do they suffer from inflammation?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Atherosclerotic - what’s going on with your cholesterol?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metabolic - how well does your body turn food into energy? Are you diabetic?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of these things meaningfully contribute to heart disease if they’re on the wrong side of the spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are also some genetic things that determine how susceptible you are to heart disease. Genes like APOE, CETP and APOC3 all influence your risk of heart disease, and a bad lipoprotein called Lp(a) is also passed down hereditarily. It can be good to screen for these things so you know how at-risk you are and how seriously you need to take the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ASCVD happens when plaque builds in your arteries, and it’s caused by arterial wall cholesterol build up which is influenced by a variety of other issues. But the good news is that those things are largely within our control. If we can focus on them, we can ultimately avoid dying of the world’s #1 killer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Preventing Disease&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a term in medicine called preventative care. It’s a fancy way of saying, “Don’t get sick or diseased.” Preventing heart disease is important for a variety of reasons, the primary one being so you don’t die. There are some other benefits as well. The heart sits at the epicenter of all things longevity and healthspan. The things you do to protect your heart also carry over and help to stave off other deadly diseases like cancer, Alzheimers, and metabolic conditions. If you’re interested in living a long and healthy life, the heart is the best place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doctors talk about heart disease prevention in different stages. First, there is primordial prevention, which is preventing heart disease before you have any sign of atherosclerosis (plaque accumulation). This is the best time to start! After that is primary (defined as having identifiable risk factors but no plaque), secondary (having plaque seen on an imaging test but not yet having experienced a major adverse cardiovascular event) and tertiary (you’ve survived a majorly bad event). The second best time to start is primary, then secondary, then tertiary. This is because you really just want to avoid getting plaque in your arteries - that’s the stuff that causes heart attacks and stroke (ie death). Here’s an image one of the leading lipidologists, Thomas Dayspring, shared with me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m at the secondary prevention stage. I have a little bit of plaque in my arteries as seen on my CTA scan, so I take this stuff seriously. I don’t want anymore to accumulate over time. If I can achieve that by managing my risk factors, taking some medications, and living a healthy lifestyle, I’ll be totally fine. These healthy habits will likely help me avoid succumbing to other bad diseases, too. That begs the question, how do we prevent this thing so we don’t die from it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How to not die of heart disease&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Current State of Affairs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you speak with any good cardiologist, lipidologist, or concierge doctor who knows about heart health, they will emphatically claim that what most primary care physicians will do with patients to help them avoid heart disease is not enough. The status quo simply does not work. If you go for your annual physical, they will likely draw some blood for a standard lipid panel where they look at your total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, and triglycerides, and maybe some other stuff. They will also use antiquated scoring methodologies like the Framingham Score to determine what your 10 year risk of having a heart attack is. They’ll also check your blood pressure. It’s definitely better than nothing, but it’s not good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Primary care physicians are following standard guidelines. The problem is the guidelines that most doctors follow lag progress in science and knowledge by 10 to 20 years! That’s nuts! But that’s how long it takes to update these guidelines. The standard of healthcare you get is decades behind what it should and could be. Remember, the system behaves in a way that does not prevent you from getting sick or diseased. Fortunately, there’s a better way for you as a patient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What To Do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since I started my heart health journey, I’ve spoken with several of the world’s leading cardiologists and lipidologists to better understand the key elements of heart disease prevention. I’ve been lucky to access these people who mainly talk to me because they like my father. I’ve been compiling notes to get to the lowest common denominator of what is good enough (definitely not perfect!) and affordable so I can arm friends and family with the information and steps to put their heart health in their own hands. Fortunately, I’ve found that the steps and protocols for avoiding death by heart disease are very simple.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two things that are most important that your physician most likely will not do that you need to ask for to understand your risk factors and whether you currently suffer from heart disease. The results of these tests then determine the appropriate course of action for you (which will generally look similar for most people unless you are really diseased, in which case I’m glad you caught it now before dropping dead). These two things are called biomarkers and imaging diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Biomarkers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Biomarkers are measurements of specific things in your body, mainly lipids and proteins, that are proxies for how susceptible you are to developing heart disease. Biomarkers that are abnormal (ie too high or too low) may mean that something is wrong. They are indications as to whether your risk factors are actually showing up in the chemistry and biology of your body.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I asked several leading lipidologists to stack rank what they believe are the most important biomarkers for people to measure and manage. There’s no consensus, but this is close to it. All of these can be accessed through bloodwork and urinalysis and can be done at a local Quest Labs (I’d venture to bet there’s one within a 10-mile radius of your home), prescribed by your doctor, and will likely cost anywhere between $80-$120 out of pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ApoB&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lipid profile to know triglycerides&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;One time Lp(a)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;hsCRP&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Microalbumin creatinine ratio (MACR)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Uric acid&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Homocysteine&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Insulin level, glucose and A1C&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Omega 3 test (Omega 3 index or Omegacheck)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only thing you’d normally get from a physician as part of an annual physical bloodwork would be the lipid profile. And within that, really what you want to understand is Triglycerides and LDL-C as the most important components. Most of the above can be found in an expanded lipid panel, ideally from the Cleveland Heartlab (owned by Quest), Labcorp, or Boston Heart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every lipidologist I’ve spoken with has stressed the importance of measuring and managing ApoB above all else – it’s a far better predictor of cardiovascular disease than LDL-C (which is what physicians are most familiar with). Every standard deviation increase of ApoB raises the risk of myocardial infarction by 38%. Yet because guidelines regularly lag science, the AHA still recommends LDL-C over ApoB. Test for it regularly (ideally twice a year) and work to get it as low as possible (longevity doctor Peter Attia recommends 30-40mg per deciliter). Many lipidologists will say to focus on this above all else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about each of these biomarkers and why they are important, you can dig in further:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Biomarker&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Indicator for&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;What is it?&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;What Test Covers it?&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Don’t Die Ranges&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;How to address it&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ApoB&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Measures the ApoB (carrier for LDL and other cholesterol) in your blood. Cholesterol carried in ApoB particles builds up in arterial walls, starting the narrowing and hardening process; most similar to ‘non-HDL’ measurement on standard lipid panel.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Expanded Lipid Panel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;60 mg/dL&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Diet, statins, PCSK9 inhibitors, bempedoic acid, ezetimibe&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Triglycerides&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Metabolic&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Measures fats circulating in your blood stream. &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Expanded Lipid Panel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;150 mg/dL&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Diet and Exercise Fibrates, Statin, Fish Oil&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Lp(a)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Member of the ApoB particle family. Occurs when an LDL merges with an ApoA, and tends to capture other lipid molecules&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Expanded Lipid Panel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;30 mg/dL&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;PCSK9 inhibitors, muvalaplin&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;hsCRP&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Inflammation&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;C-reactive protein tends to spike in reaction to tissue injury or inflammation&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Expanded Lipid Panel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;0.5 mg/L&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Diet and Exercise, appropriate lipid modulating drugs&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;MACR (Urine microalbumin to creatinine ratio)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Inflammation&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Test for Microalbuminuria, which causes kidney disease but is also a morbidity factor for cardiovascular risk. Studies have shown increases in risk for hypertensive people / diabetics, but also one which just shows an overall correlation with CVD deaths for people without these factors&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Urine&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;30 mg/g&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Diet and Exercise&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Uric acid&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Inflammation /ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Product from metabolizing purine, found in alcohol and food like meat/seafood. Too much can cause endothelial damage, increase blood pressure, and some studies show a correlation with Afib&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Blood (Add On)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;5 mg/dL&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dietary changes to lessen purine rich foods, medication&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Homocysteine&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Excess homecysteine may damage the lining of arteries or cause blood clots&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Blood test&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;10 umol/L&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dietary Changes, specific B vitamins&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Insulin/Glucose/A1C&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Metabolic&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Measures insulin efficiency and glucose control, indicating diabetes risk, which is a major cardiovascular risk factor. Can also screw up lipid metabolism, causing high TG, low HDL-C, and abnormal LDL-C&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Blood test&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A1C &amp;lt;5.7%, Fasting glucose &amp;lt;100 mg/dL, Insulin within reference range&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Healthy diet, regular exercise, possibly medications for glucose control. &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omega 3 test (Omega 3 index or Omegacheck)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omega-3 fatty acids help lower triglyceride levels, which are linked with arterial buildup. When used in high-dose, prescription strength form can reduce TG and reduce residual risk after LDL-C is controlled in high CV-risk patients.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Blood test&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;8%&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Increase intake of fish or omega-3 supplements, reduce intake of omega-6 fats&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Imaging Diagnostics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lipidologists focus on understanding biomarkers and managing them as much as possible. Cardiologists care about understanding the state of disease and treating it. The only real way to understand whether you have heart disease is to know whether you have plaque in your arteries, and the best way to do that is to take a look at it with imaging technology. The same way people do colonoscopies to visually see if they have cancer, people use tools like a CT or CTA scan to visually see if there is any plaque (both soft and calcified) that has accumulated in your arteries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every cardiologist I’ve spoken with recommends getting your calcium score either through a basic CT scan (which costs roughly $150 out of pocket unless your doctor is savvy enough to navigate insurance) or a CTA scan, ideally one with Cleerly (or HeartFlow) imaging (these cost more – anywhere between $1-1.5k). Your calcium score will tell you how much calcified plaque you have in your arteries (i.e. atherosclerosis). Remember, everyone accumulates plaque as they age. You don’t want any more of it. Calcium scores measure calcified or “hard” plaque, the stuff soft plaque turns into. It’s a proxy for how much plaque you’re accumulating. CT scans will tell you this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A CTA will measure both hard and soft plaque and the Cleerly scan will give you a 3D visualization of your arteries, tell you where the plaque exists, how much and what kind there is, and where your arteries are narrowing. If price is not an issue for you, absolutely get a CTA with Cleerly. At the bare minimum, get a CT scan. Depending on these diagnostic results, you’ll need to repeat this test once every 1-5 years, depending on the state of disease. The same way you get a colonoscopy at regular intervals to detect colon cancer and other disease, you should do this, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most physicians will not be able to understand or read the results of your CT or CTA scan. You’ll likely need to visit a specialist, ideally a cardiologist, to do this. If you’re curious about what these look like, I had a CTA done with Cleerly and here are my results. Your results will tell you your state of disease. Sometimes you may have none. That’s great! Other times you may detect a severe stenosis (narrowing of the artery), in which case cardiologists may recommend some form of intervention. That may sound scary, but it’s less scary than waking up one morning and dying of a heart attack.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key Takeaway: Get a CT or CTA scan, and if you can afford it go for the CTA with Cleerly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other Tests: There are some other things that are important to know as well. You must know your blood pressure. Fortunately, your primary care physician is more than capable of doing this. Genetic testing helps understand your predisposition to heart disease. GBinsights seems to be the one most concierge doctors are currently obsessed with. An electrocardiogram can also be a good test for detecting other major heart problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we know the tests we need to run to better understand our biomarkers and state of disease, we need to know how to treat any existing disease and disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Treatment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Medication&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Between medication and knowledge about how to prevent or mitigate heart disease, we have all the requisite tools at our disposal to beat the thing. We should focus on mitigating our risk factors, managing biomarkers, and treating any existing disease we may have. If we think about the multi-parametric approach to heart disease, we have effective medications to help us across the board. The holy trifecta for heart disease are statins, ACE inhibitors, and baby aspirin (In Europe there is a polypill that combines these three drugs and has had an extremely positive impact).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Atherosclerotic: To help drive down our ApoB, we have statins which do miracles for lipid management. Some people believe that everyone should be on a statin so long as they don’t have adverse side effects. One thing to note is that statins can oftentimes be prescribed in doses that are too high. With drugs like rosuvastatin, at 5mg most people get 85% of the maximum reduction in ApoB reduction, so there’s really no need to go higher than 10mg. For those that have adverse reactions to statins, we now have substitutes like Nexlitol (which can be expensive). We also have new drugs like PCSK9 inhibitors such as Repatha, Praluent or Leqvio (an expensive injection) which do wonders for lipid management. I take a statin and Ezetimibe which has absolutely crushed my ApoB levels (I am likely what is called a hyperabsorber). There are even new drugs that are having a remarkable impact on Lp(a), a biomarker that we struggled to move with therapeutics for ages.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Thrombotic: ACE inhibitors will help to manage blood pressure if you have high blood pressure (another thing your PCP will test for). Baby aspirin will help with blood thinning and help to reduce blood clots - it has antiplatelet properties and can reduce arterial thrombosis.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inflammatory: To help manage inflammation, there are new medications like colchicine that are normally only used in very high-risk patients.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metabolic: We are entering an age of “magic medication.” With the advent of semaglutides (eg Ozempic, Wegovy, etc.), we now have medications that help with metabolic syndrome and weight management, and we have seen remarkable reductions in adverse heart events amongst populations on these medications.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we go back to one of my favorite quotes, you’ll notice we have the right medications to treat the things that treat heart disease: “Coronary artery disease occurs when circulating fats in the blood (lipids) are pushed by a driving force (blood pressure) into a vessel wall that is vulnerable (endothelial dysfunction).” Ask your doctor or cardiologist about all of these and whether they’re right for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Behavioral&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can’t medicate heart disease out of existence quite yet. Behavioral changes, meaning modifying how you live your life, are usually also required. These changes are oriented around mitigating those risk factors we talked about: high blood pressure, high blood cholesterol, smoking, diabetes, obesity, poor nutrition, being physically inactive, and drinking alcohol. None of this should surprise you - it’s essentially being healthy. Fortunately, everything I’ve learned that is “most important” to do behaviorally has many positive externalities - not only will it help your heart health, but it will also help your overall healthspan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means regular exercise (both strength training, ideally 3x per week, and cardio training that helps to improve V02 max like Zone 2 training). It also means diet (nutrition, in addition to pharmacology, is the most important thing to reduce ApoB). Sticking to a Mediterranean diet that is light on carbohydrates and saturated fats is almost always the safest bet. Almost every health diet is some permutation of this. Also, if you smoke, stop immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You need to be mindful of what you put into your body. There are so many fad diets out there, but when it comes to heart health, it’s safe to say that a Mediterranean diet is best, ideally one that is focused on low carbohydrate and saturated fat intake. Don’t eat too much. Don’t eat too little. For me, as simple as this guidance is, I’ve found it to be the most difficult part. I love food. Particularly the stuff that’s not good for you: pasta and pizza and bread. I don’t beat myself up over being perfect when I diet. I just try to focus on eating well during the week, and on the weekends, I’ll usually indulge a couple times. What’s more important to me is the quality of the food I eat - I really try to avoid processed foods and stick to whole foods.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Regular exercise is critical, but being deliberate about the type of exercise is super important. We should target strength training ideally three times per week with a focus on resistance training. For cardio work, we should focus on improving our VO2 max by trying to get 2-3 hours of Zone 2 training in per week, and a set of HIIT at Zone 4. That’s a lot of stuff. Realistically, it’s nearly impossible to do that every week if you have a job, children, responsibilities, etc. I try to focus on the resistance training and Zone 2 training and get in 5-6 workouts per week. I don’t stress when I’m not perfect about this.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You need to sleep. Ideally, somewhere between 7-9 hours per night. Without it, we die faster. End of story. I used to invest in sleep trackers and neat technology to help me sleep better, but I found that being overly scientific about it made me sleep worse. I was putting pressure on myself to sleep better, and that pressure made me sleep worse. I usually know how much sleep I get, and I don’t really care about what “kind” of sleep I get so long as I feel good in the morning.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Stress sucks, and it kills you. And throwing your emotional health to the wayside can make life feel not fun. There’s enough literature out there with regard to how to manage stress and stay in touch with your emotions. I won’t get into it. I have been talking to a therapist weekly for years. It’s helped me to understand how to label my emotions, how those emotions drive my behaviors, and what causes me to feel those things. That’s been super helpful. I also love the mindfulness app Waking Up by Sam Harris. I think it’s like meditation, but it really works for me.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you smoke, don’t. It’s going to kill you. You know that. It is the easiest way to die of heart disease. I used to smoke cigarettes. I picked them up in high school, smoked throughout college, and intermittently did when I was building my first two companies. I know how hard it is to quit. I’ve successfully used nicotine mints and gum over the years to wean myself off cigarettes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Alcohol isn’t good for your health, and it’s really bad for your heart health. I think it’s unreasonable to tell people not to drink alcohol if they like it. I like an occasional glass of wine, and I love tequila. And I also like to drink in some social settings, but I don’t drink very often. As I’ve gotten older, my body just can’t handle it. It makes me sleep like crap, and I always feel bad the next morning. If you’re going to drink, at least make sure it’s really good alcohol that you enjoy and don’t drink too much of it.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are a lot of behavioral changes! It can seem daunting. It is daunting. It’s hard to stomach just how to do all this stuff at once. Over time I think I’ve worked on it enough and it now brings me joy to exercise, eat well, and get sleep. I feel unhealthy if I don’t do those things, so they are just part of my routine. I’m no expert at habit forming. I’ve read some books on it, but generally, what I’ve found works for me is just biting off a little bit at a time and not getting mad at myself for not doing this perfectly. Everyone has their own healthy balance of enjoying life and its indulgences and being healthy. Find yours. It’s a lifelong journey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(PS - for those who are interested in supplements, I recommend following SuppCo’s Heart Health Supplement Stack)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Don’t Die!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Between medication and knowledge about how to prevent or mitigate heart disease, we have all the requisite tools at our disposal to beat the thing. Every single lipidologist and cardiologist I’ve spoken with unanimously agrees that for almost everyone (unless you are an edge case or severely meaningfully diseased already) what I’ve highlighted above will do the trick. It’s not perfect by any means, but if people just did this stuff, heart disease would no longer be the leading cause of death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These tests and medications and knowledge about healthy behavior have existed for a long time. They’re tools that are readily available and at our disposal, but you have to ask for them. They are not prescribed unless you are sick. And unfortunately, when it comes to heart disease, being sick sometimes means being dead. It takes effort to prevent this. Like many things, the biggest hurdles are knowledge and willpower. My hope is that the knowledge becomes pervasive, that accessing these diagnostics and treatments becomes easy, cheap, and ubiquitous (they pretty much already are), and that people are motivated enough to be their own advocates and take their health into their own hands and make the conscious decision to not die of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can die of something else, just not heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How to get this from your doctor&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have probably noticed this in the past, but if there’s one thing most physicians hate, it’s when their patients show up with a list of questions and demands because they “read something on the internet.” The “WebMD Patient” is oftentimes a loathed one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve gotten pretty good at this over time. Every time I visit the doctor or take my children to the doctor or have ended up in the hospital, I’m asked what type of medicine I practice. Both of my parents were doctors, so I was sort of raised with all this stuff floating around the house, but it doesn’t take much to have a physician begin to take you seriously. Normally, the biggest source of annoyance is they don’t want to spend unnecessary time with you because their incentive is to just see as many patients as they possibly can within one day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So you’re going to show up to your doctor, either in person or via telemedicine, and begin to ask for a bunch of stuff that they don’t do for other patients and that will likely be new to them. They may not even know what much of the stuff you’re going to ask for is or means. It’s a recipe for chaos! But whatever. It’s your health. You’re your own Advocate. You have every right to ask for this stuff. I wrote a script for you to make your life easy. You can recite this aloud, print it out and bring it in, or just email it to them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hi Doc,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve made the decision to take my heart health into my own hands, and I don’t want to die of heart disease. I need you to please order me some tests that are necessary for me, and I’ve made the decision that I want them. Here’s what I need:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I need an expanded lipid panel so I can understand the following biomarkers. You can order this from Cleveland Heart Labs, which is part of Quest Labs. I’ll also need a urinalysis to test for some of these biomarkers. I realize there will be an out-of-pocket expense, but it should not be any more than $100. Here’s what I need to test for:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ApoB&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lipid profile to know triglycerides&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lp(a)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;hsCRP&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MACR&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Uric acid&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Homocysteine&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Insulin level and of course glucose and A1C&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Omega 3 test (Omega 3 index or Omegacheck)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I also need to do a CT Scan because I need to know my calcium score. I know this will be another out-of-pocket expense, but it shouldn’t cost me more than $150.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you are willing to spend more and get a better test result, replace CT Scan with CTA scan and $150 with $1,000. Ask to do a CTA with a Cleerly or HeartFlow reading.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;While I’m at Quest or even right now, let’s check my blood pressure to ensure everything is okay.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I get the results from these tests, I’d love to review them with you. If you don’t feel comfortable reviewing them with me, I’m happy to work with another doctor or cardiologist within my network that you’d recommend. I will also dump them into ChatGPT and see what it recommends and you can tell me whether you agree or disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you for helping me not die of heart disease! I really appreciate your supporting my decision to learn more about my heart health and to live a long and healthy life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s pretty straightforward. If your doctor pushes back on you, just repeat: “I’ve decided to not die of heart disease and these are the tests I need to feel comfortable and address my own body and health. If you can’t order me these tests, please let me know and I am happy to take my business elsewhere.” And if they try to push and prod you on why you want every one of these tests, you can point them here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What should you do with your test results?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Throw them into ChatGPT, of course! (And share them with your doctor.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some of my latest labs that I’ve done. And below is what ChatGPT says in response to these questions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I am a 37-year-old male. I am 5’10 and weigh 170 pounds. I currently take a statin and ezetimibe.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Does anything stand out to you? Is anything abnormal?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Are there any biomarkers I should focus on improving?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What should I do to improve or maintain these results?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the response:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Based on the lab results you've shared, several markers are notable and some recommendations can be made. Let's break it down:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key Findings&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;LDL Cholesterol (LDL-C): Your LDL-C is at 29 mg/dL, which is considerably below the optimal range. This is very low, likely due to your statin and ezetimibe therapy. While low LDL-C reduces cardiovascular risk, extremely low levels should be discussed with your doctor to ensure they are safe and intended.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;HDL Cholesterol (HDL-C): Your HDL-C is 44 mg/dL, which is acceptable but on the lower side of optimal (optimal is usually above 50 mg/dL). Higher HDL-C is generally protective against heart disease.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Triglycerides: Your triglyceride level is 74 mg/dL, which is well within the optimal range.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lipoprotein (a) [Lp(a)]: Less than 10 mg/dL, which is excellent as high levels are associated with increased cardiovascular risk.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inflammation (hs-CRP): Your high-sensitivity C-reactive protein is &amp;lt;0.2 mg/L, indicating very low levels of inflammation, which is good for cardiovascular health.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Omega-3 Index: Your omega-3 fatty acid levels are healthy at 6.8%, with a good balance between EPA and DHA, which are important for heart health.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recommendations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Discuss LDL-C Levels: Given your very low LDL-C, it would be worthwhile to discuss with your healthcare provider whether adjustments to your statin therapy might be appropriate, or if such low levels are part of a therapeutic strategy, especially if you have a history of cardiovascular disease.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Boost HDL-C: To potentially improve your HDL-C, consider increasing physical activity, possibly incorporating more aerobic exercises. Additionally, dietary adjustments such as including more healthy fats from nuts, olive oil, and fatty fish can help.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Maintain Healthy Lifestyle: Continue with a balanced diet rich in fruits, vegetables, whole grains, and lean proteins. Limit intake of saturated fats and sugars, which you seem to be managing well given your current lipid profile.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Monitor and Maintain: Regular monitoring of your cholesterol levels and other biomarkers, along with routine consultations with your healthcare provider, will be essential in maintaining your health status, especially considering your current medication regimen.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your current lab results suggest effective management of cholesterol and cardiovascular risk factors, likely aided by your medication and possibly your lifestyle choices. However, always consult with your healthcare provider for personalized advice and to ensure that your treatment plan is optimal for your specific health needs.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pretty incredible. Also free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can share this and the results directly with my doctor and make life easy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will try to update this over time. Ideally, I’d just like to open this up to a handful of people who care about it and we can all update it together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hope you find this useful. I hope you get a CTA or CT scan. I hope you learn about your biomarkers and risk factors. I hope you share this with your friends and loved ones. I hope you help yourself and others not die of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in staying updated about heart-related things, drop your email here and I’ll send out a note whenever I get around to updating this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good luck. You got this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to thank a lot of people who helped me along my heart health journey: Harvey Hecht, James Min, Thomas Dayspring, Arthur Agatstan, Andrea Klemes, Louis Malinow, Jeffrey Wessler, Neil Parikh, Steve Martocci, Alan Tisch, David Kopp and Carrie Weprin.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://myticker.com/"/><published>2025-11-08T14:59:05+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45857836</id><title>Cloudflare scrubs Aisuru botnet from top domains list</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:54.719518+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a380bbd25c1024c3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the past week, domains associated with the massive Aisuru botnet have repeatedly usurped Amazon, Apple, Google and Microsoft in Cloudflare’s public ranking of the most frequently requested websites. Cloudflare responded by redacting Aisuru domain names from their top websites list. The chief executive at Cloudflare says Aisuru’s overlords are using the botnet to boost their malicious domain rankings, while simultaneously attacking the company’s domain name system (DNS) service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aisuru is a rapidly growing botnet comprising hundreds of thousands of hacked Internet of Things (IoT) devices, such as poorly secured Internet routers and security cameras. The botnet has increased in size and firepower significantly since its debut in 2024, demonstrating the ability to launch record distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attacks nearing 30 terabits of data per second.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Until recently, Aisuru’s malicious code instructed all infected systems to use DNS servers from Google — specifically, the servers at 8.8.8.8. But in early October, Aisuru switched to invoking Cloudflare’s main DNS server — 1.1.1.1 — and over the past week domains used by Aisuru to control infected systems started populating Cloudflare’s top domain rankings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As screenshots of Aisuru domains claiming two of the Top 10 positions ping-ponged across social media, many feared this was yet another sign that an already untamable botnet was running completely amok. One Aisuru botnet domain that sat prominently for days at #1 on the list was someone’s street address in Massachusetts followed by “.com”. Other Aisuru domains mimicked those belonging to major cloud providers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare tried to address these security, brand confusion and privacy concerns by partially redacting the malicious domains, and adding a warning at the top of its rankings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Note that the top 100 domains and trending domains lists include domains with organic activity as well as domains with emerging malicious behavior.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare CEO Matthew Prince told KrebsOnSecurity the company’s domain ranking system is fairly simplistic, and that it merely measures the volume of DNS queries to 1.1.1.1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The attacker is just generating a ton of requests, maybe to influence the ranking but also to attack our DNS service,” Prince said, adding that Cloudflare has heard reports of other large public DNS services seeing similar uptick in attacks. “We’re fixing the ranking to make it smarter. And, in the meantime, redacting any sites we classify as malware.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Renee Burton, vice president of threat intel at the DNS security firm Infoblox, said many people erroneously assumed that the skewed Cloudflare domain rankings meant there were more bot-infected devices than there were regular devices querying sites like Google and Apple and Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Cloudflare’s documentation is clear — they know that when it comes to ranking domains you have to make choices on how to normalize things,” Burton wrote on LinkedIn. “There are many aspects that are simply out of your control. Why is it hard? Because reasons. TTL values, caching, prefetching, architecture, load balancing. Things that have shared control between the domain owner and everything in between.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alex Greenland is CEO of the anti-phishing and security firm Epi. Greenland said he understands the technical reason why Aisuru botnet domains are showing up in Cloudflare’s rankings (those rankings are based on DNS query volume, not actual web visits). But he said they’re still not meant to be there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s a failure on Cloudflare’s part, and reveals a compromise of the trust and integrity of their rankings,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Greenland said Cloudflare planned for its Domain Rankings to list the most popular domains as used by human users, and it was never meant to be a raw calculation of query frequency or traffic volume going through their 1.1.1.1 DNS resolver.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“They spelled out how their popularity algorithm is designed to reflect real human use and exclude automated traffic (they said they’re good at this),” Greenland wrote on LinkedIn. “So something has evidently gone wrong internally. We should have two rankings: one representing trust and real human use, and another derived from raw DNS volume.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why might it be a good idea to wholly separate malicious domains from the list? Greenland notes that Cloudflare Domain Rankings see widespread use for trust and safety determination, by browsers, DNS resolvers, safe browsing APIs and things like TRANCO.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“TRANCO is a respected open source list of the top million domains, and Cloudflare Radar is one of their five data providers,” he continued. “So there can be serious knock-on effects when a malicious domain features in Cloudflare’s top 10/100/1000/million. To many people and systems, the top 10 and 100 are naively considered safe and trusted, even though algorithmically-defined top-N lists will always be somewhat crude.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over this past week, Cloudflare started redacting portions of the malicious Aisuru domains from its Top Domains list, leaving only their domain suffix visible. Sometime in the past 24 hours, Cloudflare appears to have begun hiding the malicious Aisuru domains entirely from the web version of that list. However, downloading a spreadsheet of the current Top 200 domains from Cloudflare Radar shows an Aisuru domain still at the very top.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to Cloudflare’s website, the majority of DNS queries to the top Aisuru domains — nearly 52 percent — originated from the United States. This tracks with my reporting from early October, which found Aisuru was drawing most of its firepower from IoT devices hosted on U.S. Internet providers like AT&amp;amp;T, Comcast and Verizon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experts tracking Aisuru say the botnet relies on well more than a hundred control servers, and that for the moment at least most of those domains are registered in the .su top-level domain (TLD). Dot-su is the TLD assigned to the former Soviet Union (.su’s Wikipedia page says the TLD was created just 15 months before the fall of the Berlin wall).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Cloudflare blog post from October 27 found that .su had the highest “DNS magnitude” of any TLD, referring to a metric estimating the popularity of a TLD based on the number of unique networks querying Cloudflare’s 1.1.1.1 resolver. The report concluded that the top .su hostnames were associated with a popular online world-building game, and that more than half of the queries for that TLD came from the United States, Brazil and Germany [it’s worth noting that servers for the world-building game Minecraft were some of Aisuru’s most frequent targets].&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A simple and crude way to detect Aisuru bot activity on a network may be to set an alert on any systems attempting to contact domains ending in .su. This TLD is frequently abused for cybercrime and by cybercrime forums and services, and blocking access to it entirely is unlikely to raise any legitimate complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/11/cloudflare-scrubs-aisuru-botnet-from-top-domains-list/"/><published>2025-11-08T16:25:41+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45857988</id><title>Opencloud – An alternative to Nextcloud written in Go</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:54.103359+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ef05bc5f19e668bf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For general information about OpenCloud and how to install please visit OpenCloud on Github and OpenCloud GmbH.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the main repository of the OpenCloud server. It contains the golang codebase for the backend services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The OpenCloud server is released under Apache 2.0. The project is thrilled to receive contributions in all forms. Start hacking now, there are many ways to get involved such as:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reporting issues or bugs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Requesting features&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Writing documentation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Writing code or extend our tests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reviewing code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Helping others in the community&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every contribution is meaningful and appreciated! Please refer to our Contribution Guidelines if you want to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To build the backend, follow these instructions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generate the assets needed by e.g., the web UI and the builtin IDP&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;make generate&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then compile the &lt;code&gt;opencloud&lt;/code&gt; binary&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;make -C opencloud build&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That will produce the binary &lt;code&gt;opencloud/bin/opencloud&lt;/code&gt;. It can be started as a local test instance right away with a two step command:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;opencloud/bin/opencloud init &amp;amp;&amp;amp; opencloud/bin/opencloud server&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This creates a server configuration (by default in &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.opencloud&lt;/code&gt;) and starts the server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more setup- and installation options consult the Development Documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Important information for contributors about the technology in use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The OpenCloud backend authenticates users via OpenID Connect using either an external IdP like Keycloak or the embedded LibreGraph Connect identity provider.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The OpenCloud backend does not use a database. It stores all data in the filesystem. By default, the root directory of the backend is &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.opencloud/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you find a security-related issue, please contact security@opencloud.eu immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/opencloud-eu/opencloud"/><published>2025-11-08T16:40:12+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45858905</id><title>Marko – A declarative, HTML‑based language</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:53.653496+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a876cc8c70be3ce3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Trusted&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Powering high-traffic, production-grade websites like eBay.com&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Powering high-traffic, production-grade websites like eBay.com&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you know HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, you know Marko&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Streaming, resumable, optimizing compiler, and a tiny runtime&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From simple HTML templates to powerful components as needed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marko is HTML re‑imagined as a language for building dynamic and reactive user interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just about any valid HTML is valid Marko, but Marko extends the HTML language to allow building modern applications in a declarative way.&lt;/p&gt;Check it out!&lt;p&gt;Marko streams content to your users as soon as it's ready. No waiting for client side JavaScript bundles or data requests to start rendering.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;HTML, assets, and images are loaded as soon as possible with asynchronous content loading in as it completes.&lt;/p&gt;Learn How&lt;p&gt;Browsers and servers are built differently, shouldn't your code be too? Marko compiles your templates to perform their best with optimized, environment-specific output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faster loads. Smaller bundles. One seamless language.&lt;/p&gt;Learn How&lt;p&gt;Marko has built-in TypeScript support , with strong type inference that works across templates and components. Editors get full language features like autocompletion, jump-to-definition, syntax highlighting, and clean formatting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build confidently. Catch errors early. Write better code, faster.&lt;/p&gt;Explore&lt;p&gt;Need help? Want to Contribute?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get involved in the Marko Community!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://markojs.com/"/><published>2025-11-08T18:43:55+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45858945</id><title>WriterdeckOS</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:53.229894+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="5e878a1b412da7b6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Requirements:&lt;lb/&gt; - 64bit processor (Intel/AMD)&lt;lb/&gt; - Will not work on an ARM processorThe installation ISO is hosted at The Internet Archive:&lt;lb/&gt; https://archive.org/details/tinkerWD-1.0Donate to the Internet Archive here: Donate&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;writerdeckOS is an operating system used to convert laptops and many Chromebooks (with 64-bit Intel/AMD processors) into a "Writer Deck".A Writer Deck is a device that is used solely for writing text.It minimizes distractions. No internet browsing, no apps, no games, no social media, no notifications. Not even major formatting!Just Writing.writerdeckOS is very light weight and specifically seeks to lower the barrier of entry to creating writer decks. It converts older, reused, refurbished, or inexpensive laptops into a dedicated writing machine.writerdeckOS sits on top of a "headless" Debian Linux image and boots directly into a console based text editor. We're using the Tilde Text Editor because it is simple text editor, has an intuitive User Interface, and allows for customized color schemes for light and dark modes.More information:&lt;lb/&gt; - General Info about Writer Decks: writerDeck.org&lt;lb/&gt; - Reddit: writerdeckOS Subreddit&lt;lb/&gt; - writerdeckOS: Github Repo | Archive Org ISO Page&lt;lb/&gt; - Tilde Text Editor: Github Repo | Website&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DISCLAIMER: writerdeckOS comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY, to the extent permitted by applicable law.WARNING: You are engaging in a DIY endeavor. You may break your machine. The installation may not work. You may erase the old operating system and not be able to start your device up ever again. This OS has only been tested on a couple of machines and is not guaranteed to work on every laptop. Only try this if you're willing to accept the consequences.WARNING: This will erase everything on the laptop you install it on. Please make backups before beginning.1. With the downloaded ISO, Create a bootable USB: Tutorial&lt;lb/&gt; 2. Plug the USB into your designated laptop and boot from USB: (Depending on your laptop, either press F12, Escape, or F2 during the boot up sequence. Check your laptop manual for specific instructions. Note: You may have to turn "Secure Boot" off within your BIOS.)&lt;lb/&gt; 3. Installation will proceed automatically. The hard drive and all previous contents will be erased and the writer deck will be installed.&lt;lb/&gt; 4. Once finished, press Enter when prompted. Between when the device shuts off and just as it starts up, remove the Installation USB.&lt;lb/&gt; 5. For First Boot you will enter&lt;lb/&gt; - Username: author&lt;lb/&gt; - Password: password&lt;lb/&gt; 6. After start up, shut down by pressing your laptops power button (this will take a short while but will be quicker on subsequent poweroffs).&lt;lb/&gt; 7. Restart laptop and it will boot directly into Tilde word processor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Always remember to Save (Ctrl+S). There is NO autosaving!!!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn On: Press your laptop's power button.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn Off: Press your laptop's power button.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn Off (alternate): From Tilde, Press Ctrl+Q to quit. From the command line, type: shutdown (press enter)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To use Tilde: Press Alt+F to bring up the menu system and use arrow keys to navigate around. More info: Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To change color scheme: (Light Mode / Dark Mode) - Press Alt+O, arrow key down to "Interface" and press Enter, then select "Text Area Attributes", then "Text". Change Foreground and Background Color to desired colors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Enable Word Wrap: Press Alt+O, arrow key down and select "Buffer Defaults". Press spacebar on "Wrap text", choose OK, and then restart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;USBs: Access plugged in USBs in the "USBs" folder in the home directory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Access File System: Press Ctrl+Q to quit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Navigate File System, Move Files, &amp;amp; Delete Files: Use common Bash commands: Tutorial&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¦ Photo of a writerdeckOS in Light Mode&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developer Mode: Press Ctrl+Q to quit Tilde. Underlying file system and command prompt is running Bash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To restart Tilde from the Command Line: Type tilde and press enter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To change keyboard layout: From the initial command line, run: exit to drop to a lower command line, then run sudo dpkg-reconfigure keyboard-configuration then run: sudo service keyboard-setup restart&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To use a different text editor besides Tilde: Edit the /home/author/.profile file. The Tinker WriterDeck comes preinstalled with several text editors. Use apt to install more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To connect to the internet: (For syncing and app installation purposes) Use: nmcli (from the command prompt).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To sync folders to cloud services: Follow service specific instructions. Examples: Nextcloud | Dropbox | Google Drive&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Encrypt Harddrive &amp;amp; Require Password to Log in: Install a headless version of Debian 12.10 "Bookworm" and select Full Disk Encryption using LUKS upon installation. Then run configuration script found: Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¦ Photo of a writerdeckOS in Dark Mode&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For questions or assistance, you're welcome to reach out directly to the developer via the Fediverse: @[email protected]For group discussion and questions, you're welcome to join the Reddit /r/writerdeckOS subreddit here: Reddit Discussion ThreadFor technical issues and bug discussions, please open an Issue Ticket on Github here: Github Issue Tracker&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://writerdeckos.com"/><published>2025-11-08T18:49:47+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45859243</id><title>Avería: The Average Font (2011)</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:52.882201+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="367d013713a223d1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iam not a type designer. This is the story of the creation of a new font, Avería: the average of all the fonts on my computer. The field of typography has long fascinated me, and I love playing with creative programming ideas, so it was perhaps inevitable that the idea came to me one day of “generative typography”. A Google on the subject brought up little, and I put the idea to the back of my mind until it occurred to me that perhaps the process of averaging, or interpolating, existing fonts might bring up interesting results. Luckily at this point I didn't do any more web searching – instead I grabbed my laptop and came up with an initial idea for finding what the average of all my fonts might look like – by overlaying each letter at low opacity. The results can be seen in the below image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was done by printing each letter of each font, at the same point size, to lots of separate images, and then averaging them – using ImageMagick and PHP. The letters were aligned to the same centre point. I later realised that each font has a ‘baseline’ defined, and an origin on that baseline which each glyph is drawn relative to. The same process, repeated with equal origins, gives slightly different results (see below) – here you can see the baseline is very well-defined, with the glyphs becoming more blurred towards the top right of each.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was quite pleased with the results. It was only later that I discovered this had already been done – though it appeared that my end results (whilst not as beautifully animated) had a little more clarity, so I'm glad I tried for myself. But this didn't seem like the end of the journey. Whilst this was an interesting experiment, and showed an lot of correlation between a sample of common fonts (as well as a couple of oddities – notably the lower case ‘g’ which clearly exists in two distinct common forms), what I really wanted was an average which somehow preserved the well-defined edges of existing fonts. So I started considering ways to produce a smoother, sharper average of letter forms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One idea which seemed obvious was to simply take the blurry results of the first experiment, and use a threshold to create monochrome images. A few experiments in this direction (I first tried with a lower-case ‘f’, which I later found was never likely to give good results due to the variance in height of the middle cross-stroke) convinced me that I needed to look into cleverer ways to achieve this. Surely there must be a simple way to average shapes, while keeping the result as a shape?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It turns out not to be straightforward. There are many possible ways to ‘morph’ between two shapes – and what might seem the most natural generally depends on our perception of ‘features’ in the shapes. Consider the average of a capital I with serifs, and one without: the natural thing to do would be something like, make the serifs half as big, and use a horizontal stem width about half-way between the two glyphs. That's two feature concepts being applied to the abstract forms¹. To take a simpler example, what is the average of a square with the same square rotated 45˚? There are a few possibilities …&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, this stumped me for a while. I decided I needed to get to know fonts better, so I built a simple web app to view the lines, curves and control points present in the fonts I had. On this basis, I started to consider the ways the features (vertices, curves, stems, serifs etc) might be matched up between fonts. However, this was a rabbit hole I might never get to the bottom of - particularly when considering some of the more unusual varieties of font. Perhaps there was a simpler idea that was evading me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then it occurred to me: since my aim was to average a large number of fonts, perhaps it would be best to use a very simple process, and hope the results averaged out well over a large number of fonts. So, how about splitting each letter perimeter into lots of (say, 500) equally-spaced points, and just average between the corresponding positions of each, on each letter? It would be necessary to match up the points so they were about the same location in each letter, and then the process would be fairly simple².&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having found a simple process to use, I was ready to start. And after about a month of part-time slaving away (sheer fun! Better than any computer game) – in the process of which I learned lots about bezier curves and font metrics – I had a result. I call it Avería – which is a Spanish word related to the root of the word ‘average’. It actually means mechanical breakdown or damage. This seemed curiously fitting, and I was assured by a Spanish friend-of-a-friend that “Avería is an incredibly beautiful word regardless of its meaning”. So that's nice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along the way I naturally called on the counsel of the best designers I know – my brother Nick Sayers, Lloyd Thomas, Tom Muller and Chris McGrail, for advice. In the end, I decided to release the font using the SIL Open Font License – which means anyone can use it pretty much however they like – and to include within the family Regular, Bold and Light variants with Italics. Each is made from the corresponding subsets of the fonts on my machine. Also included is a “Gruesa” version made from all my fonts (725 in total).&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Family (ZIP, 369kB) [Updated 9 Nov 2011]&lt;lb/&gt; Avería at The Open Font Library&lt;lb/&gt; *NEW* by popular demand:&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Serif Family (ZIP, 323kB) OFLB&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Sans Family (ZIP, 320kB) OFLB&lt;lb/&gt; *NEW* Avería, Serif and Sans packaged as TTC TrueType collections (so you can install each family in one go, rather than one variant at a time). Thanks Ludwig:&lt;lb/&gt; Avería TTC Files (ZIP, 946kB)&lt;lb/&gt; *NEW* versions of Avería, based on OFL fonts from the Google Web Fonts directory - now available through GWF as Avería Libre:&lt;lb/&gt; Avería GWF Family (ZIP, 488kB)&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Serif GWF Family (ZIP, 432kB)&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Sans GWF Family (ZIP, 426kB)&lt;lb/&gt; Preview all&lt;lb/&gt; Feel free to email me if you have any questions – or use the comments box below.&lt;lb/&gt; N.B. I've had a number of emails from people asking if they can use Avería in various commercial / non-commercial projects. I'd love to hear if you do something with these fonts – but there's no need to ask permission. You are absolutely free to use them however you like. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="http://iotic.com/averia/"/><published>2025-11-08T19:29:44+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45859471</id><title>Largest cargo sailboat completes first Atlantic crossing</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:52.660666+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="df5cacd41833d6da"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;World’s Largest Cargo Sailboat Completes Historic First Atlantic Crossing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The world’s largest cargo sailboat, Neoliner Origin, completed its first transatlantic voyage on 30 October despite damage to one of its sails during the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 136-metre-long vessel had to rely partly on its auxiliary motor and its remaining sail after the aft sail was damaged in a storm shortly after departure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French-built roll-on/roll-off (RoRo) cargo ship, which has two semi-rigid sails, first stopped at Saint Pierre and Miquelon, a French overseas territory near Canada, before continuing its journey to Baltimore in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neoline, the company behind the project, said the damage reduced the vessel’s ability to perform fully on wind power. The company’s CEO, Jean Zanuttini, said the crossing was a valuable experience in handling large sail surfaces across the North Atlantic, especially during late-season storms. He added that despite the difficulties, the ship showed strong resilience by reaching its destination with only a short delay in Saint Pierre.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Neoliner Origin is designed to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 80 to 90 per cent compared to conventional diesel-powered cargo ships. According to the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD), global shipping produces about 3 per cent of worldwide greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zanuttini said the company aims to balance industrial needs with environmental responsibility. He added that wind propulsion offers an advantage because it is a free, widely available, and predictable energy source that does not harm ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK’s National Clean Maritime Research Hub has reported that wind propulsion systems like those on the Neoliner Origin can cut emissions by over 50 per cent on new vessels optimised for wind conditions. Retrofitted vessels can also achieve reductions of 5 to 20 per cent, and up to 30 per cent when adjusted for wind conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Neoliner Origin was designed by the French naval engineering firm Mauric. The company’s CEO, Vincent Seguin, said the goal was to develop a ship that relies primarily on wind propulsion while ensuring consistent delivery schedules and efficient operation with a smaller crew.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inspired by historic sailing vessels, the Neoliner Origin integrates modern systems such as advanced navigation, anti-drift mechanisms, and automated sail management to comply with current safety and operational standards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ship can carry up to 5,300 tonnes of cargo, including containers, vehicles, machinery, and specialised goods. It arrived in Baltimore carrying Renault vehicles, French liqueurs, machinery, and other products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Neoliner Origin is scheduled to make monthly voyages between Europe and North America, maintaining a commercial cruising speed of around 11 knots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reference: Reuters&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;⚓️ Enhance Your Knowledge. Prevent Accidents. Stay Safe at Sea.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. eBooks for Engine Department&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Master machinery operations, troubleshooting, and safety procedures with expertly written guides tailored for marine engineers. Prevent costly breakdowns and onboard accidents through practical knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👉 Explore Engine Department eBooks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2. eBooks for Deck Department&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sharpen your seamanship, navigation, and cargo-handling skills with real-world case studies and practical insights designed for deck officers and cadets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👉Discover Deck Department eBooks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3. eBooks on Electrical Fundamentals &amp;amp; Issues&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand marine electrical systems, identify potential faults, and prevent onboard electrical failures with step-by-step explanations from industry experts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4. Pocket Guides for Quick Reference&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compact, handy, and loaded with essential checklists—perfect for on-the-go reference during operations and emergencies at sea.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;5. Combo Packs to Save Big&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Access multiple expert eBooks at discounted prices. Ideal for professionals seeking complete safety and operational knowledge across various ship departments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;6. Digital Maritime Courses – Learn at Your Own Pace&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upgrade your competence with Marine Insight Academy’s online courses. Learn from industry professionals anytime, anywhere, and become a safer, smarter seafarer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disclaimer : &lt;lb/&gt;The information on this website is for general purposes only. While efforts are made to ensure accuracy, we make no warranties of any kind regarding completeness, reliability, or suitability. Any reliance you place on such information is at your own risk. We are not liable for any loss or damage arising from the use of this website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disclaimer : &lt;lb/&gt;The information on this website is for general purposes only. While efforts are made to ensure accuracy, we make no warranties of any kind regarding completeness, reliability, or suitability. Any reliance you place on such information is at your own risk. We are not liable for any loss or damage arising from the use of this website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Subscribe To Our Daily Newsletter&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By subscribing, you agree to our Privacy Policy and may receive occasional deal communications; you can unsubscribe anytime.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.marineinsight.com/shipping-news/worlds-largest-cargo-sailboat-completes-historic-first-atlantic-crossing/"/><published>2025-11-08T19:57:52+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45860638</id><title>Debugging BeagleBoard USB boot with a sniffer: fixing omap_loader on modern PCs</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:52.503368+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b43e4190da629599"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post is about the original OMAP3530 BeagleBoard from 2008. Yes, the one so old that it doesn’t even show up in the board list on BeagleBoard.org anymore. The BeagleBoard, not the BeagleBone. During my Chumby 8 kernel escapades, at one point I ran into a UART bug that affected multiple drivers, including the omap-serial driver. This led me to buy a BeagleBoard so I could verify the omap-serial bug on hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After I figured out the bug with the UART driver, I realized that the OMAP3530 has support for booting from USB, so I decided to go off on a random tangent to get USB boot working. There was no problem I was trying to solve or anything like that. I just thought it would be a fun experiment (am I a masochist?). Little did I know, I would be getting myself into some tricky USB packet analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I struggled to find info about this process because of how old the OMAP is today. The main utility I found was a program called omap_loader by Grant Hernandez, which is a newer rewrite of Martin Mueller’s original omap3_usbload circa 2008. Thanks to some lucky searching combined with the Internet Archive, I connected the dots between 2008 and the present. At some point before 2013, Rick Bronson provided an update to omap3_usbload (along with a patch to TI’s X-Loader bootloader) that enabled uploading additional files like a full U-Boot and Linux kernel into RAM after X-Loader, all through USB. This unlocked the ability to boot all the way to Linux from a completely blank BeagleBoard. Grant’s newer omap_loader utility also incorporates these same improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of this research was difficult. Many of the links I found pointed to sites like gitorious.org and arago-project.org, both of which no longer exist (although Arago’s Git repos are now hosted by TI). eLinux.org’s BeagleBoard wiki was totally rearranged at some point and lost its info about USB recovery, and Rick’s site no longer exists, but as usual, the Internet Archive saved the day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At some point later on, X-Loader was replaced by U-Boot SPL, so I think that is partially why so much of this info eventually disappeared from the web. But it’s a darn shame. This USB booting functionality is really cool, and it seems like most of the documentation for it has slowly gone by the wayside! The main breadcrumbs remaining on modern Google are the newer omap_loader utility, and also some references to Nest thermostats. For example, Nest’s X-Loader had the USB patch applied (with some tweaks added).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With all that research out of the way, I was ready to try it all out. I compiled omap_loader, grabbed the pre-built binary of x-load.bin that was included with Rick’s patchset, and also used a u-boot.bin that I had compiled myself using Buildroot while performing my UART tests with a modern kernel on the BeagleBoard. Then, I tried to load it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ sudo ./omap_loader -p 0xd009 -f x-load.bin -f u-boot.bin -a 0x80800000 -j 0x80800000 -v&lt;lb/&gt;OMAP Loader 1.0.0&lt;lb/&gt;File 'x-load.bin' at 0x40200000, size 26956&lt;lb/&gt;File 'u-boot.bin' at 0x80800000, size 777760&lt;lb/&gt;[+] scanning for USB device matching 0451:d009...&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The idea behind this command is it sends X-Loader (x-load.bin) as the main payload that the OMAP’s on-chip bootloader is listening for over USB. Then, X-Loader starts up. Next, omap_loader sends any additional files using X-Loader’s USB protocol. In this case, I’ve supplied one extra file: u-boot.bin, which I told it to load into RAM at 0x80800000. Finally, the &lt;code&gt;-j 0x80800000&lt;/code&gt; argument tells X-Loader to jump into U-Boot rather than hanging around doing nothing afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The output of the command looked normal so far. I plugged in my BeagleBoard, which didn’t have an SD card inserted and also had its NAND flash erased, so it had no bootloader installed and thus it would attempt a USB boot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;[+] successfully opened 0451:d009 (Texas Instruments OMAP3430)&lt;lb/&gt;[+] got ASIC ID - Num Subblocks [05], Device ID Info [01050134300757], Reserved [13020100], Ident Data [1215010000000000000000000000000000000000000000], Reserved [1415010000000000000000000000000000000000000000], CRC (4 bytes) [150901f7488f2800000000]&lt;lb/&gt;[-] fatal transfer error (BULK_OUT) for 26956 bytes (0 made it): LIBUSB_ERROR_PIPE&lt;lb/&gt;[-] failed to send file 'x-load.bin' (size 26956)&lt;lb/&gt;[-] failed to transfer the first stage file 'x-load.bin'&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Darn. The utility recognized the BeagleBoard being plugged in, but libusb errored out with a pipe error. Long story short, I messed around with a few other computers, and I found that a few of my older computers, old enough that they didn’t have USB 3.0 ports on their motherboards, actually worked perfectly fine with omap_loader. I couldn’t get it to work properly with most of my modern machines though, AMD or Intel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought this would be a great application for a USB sniffer, so I decided to record some traces of success versus failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s a link to my in-depth investigation comparing success versus failure on the GitHub issue about this problem. Yep, it turns out I wasn’t the only one running into this exact same issue. Grant himself was seeing similar problems, and had come to a similar conclusion that it seemed to be machine-dependent. Other people had mentioned that adding delays at certain points in the code seemed to help. I was intrigued, so I tried to get to the bottom of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what the USB boot process is supposed to look like, according to TI’s OMAP35x Technical Reference Manual:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The OMAP device enumerates as a USB device.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Within 300 ms, the host needs to read an “ASIC ID” structure from the OMAP or else it will disconnect from USB.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Then, the host sends a 4-byte command: 0xF0030002 means to continue booting through USB.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Next, the host sends the 4-byte length of bootloader data it wants to transfer.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Finally, the host sends the bootloader (X-Loader in this case), which will be loaded into internal SRAM starting at 0x40200000.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;After the OMAP device receives all of the data, it runs the received bootloader by jumping to 0x40200000.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, this process worked perfectly fine on my older computers that don’t support USB 3.0, but on my newer computers with USB 3.0, it was hanging up. I did notice that the newer computers were trying to fit a lot more data into a single USB frame. For example, the start of my older computer’s communication with the OMAP looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Frame 1 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends boot command&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP confirms it&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Frame 2 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends length&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP confirms it&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Frame 3 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends first packet of bootloader data&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP confirms it&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends second packet of bootloader data&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP says it’s not ready&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host pings&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP says it’s ready now&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends second packet of bootloader data again&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP confirms it&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then from that point on, it was just a process of sending the rest of the data like that. About 5 data packets would fit into each frame. My newer computer’s traffic looked like this instead:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Frame 1 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends boot command&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP confirms it&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends length&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP says it’s not ready&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host pings a few times until the OMAP is ready&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends length again&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP confirms it&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends first packet of bootloader data&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP confirms it&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host sends second packet of bootloader data&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP says it’s not ready&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host pings several times, OMAP never says it’s ready during the rest of this frame&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Frame 2 &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Host pings&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OMAP responds with a STALL packet&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The newer xHCI host controller was trying its best to efficiently squeeze a lot of packets into the first frame. Even though this is a pattern that should be perfectly valid to follow when communicating with a USB device, the OMAP bootloader was clearly not happy about something, and eventually sent a STALL packet before omap_loader made much progress. Various USB packet traces on different modern computers revealed similar issues. It would either STALL after the second packet, or just NAK forever and never accept additional incoming data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inspired by other comments about adding delays, I tried to work around this by inserting an artificial 1 ms delay before every &lt;code&gt;libusb_bulk_transfer()&lt;/code&gt; call. This would force modern machines to slow down a little bit. As soon as I added those delays, all of my new computers had no trouble uploading X-Loader to the OMAP. So yeah, I think the OMAP just doesn’t like receiving USB data too quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That wasn’t the end of this little project, though. The 1 ms delay fixed the issue with getting X-Loader to run, but the newer computers also ran into problems while trying to upload U-Boot through X-Loader!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;[-] device timed out while transfering in 512 bytes (got 0)&lt;lb/&gt;[-] device timed out while transfering in 512 bytes (got 0)&lt;lb/&gt;[-] device timed out while transfering in 512 bytes (got 0)&lt;lb/&gt;[-] failed to read command from X-Loader&lt;lb/&gt;[-] failed to transfer the additional files in to memory&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rats. I went back to the USB sniffer for more research.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This time, it was a different problem. I found the point where the host would try to read the initial request from X-Loader: &lt;code&gt;USBf&lt;/code&gt;. On my older computer, this worked fine; it received a 13-byte string from X-Loader: &lt;code&gt;USBffile req&lt;/code&gt; followed by a null terminator. It was happy with this, and omap_usbload kept going on with the rest of the file load process and everything succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the newer computer, some shenanigans were going on. Let’s look at the USB trace in depth:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 335-byte packet contains 332 actual bytes of data (the packet ID and CRC account for the other 3 bytes), and is the final chunk of X-Loader. It was successfully received and confirmed by the OMAP with an ACK. At that point, we can assume that the OMAP has begun jumping into X-Loader to start it up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A millisecond later (due to the delay I added), we start trying to read from X-Loader. It’s clearly too soon, though; I don’t think X-Loader has finished starting up yet. There’s nothing ready to read. So these IN/NAK packets continue on for about 5 more milliseconds, which is totally normal. But then, something finally happens: the OMAP stops responding to our IN packets. My computer’s USB host controller tries three times (see the three IN packets in a row below?) and then it gives up. I’m guessing this is around the same time that X-Loader is doing its own hardware initialization, so maybe the OMAP’s USB controller is temporarily disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This all makes sense so far. We tried to read too quickly before X-Loader finished starting up, so when it did finally load, there was a brief moment where it would not respond to IN packets. The host controller didn’t like this and stopped trying, so all we saw from that point on was SOF packets because we weren’t attempting any more USB reads. Some of my other computers gave up after 15 unanswered IN packets instead of 3. I’m not sure if that’s a difference in the host controller or what, but it’s the same root problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may be wondering: why didn’t the older computers run into this same issue? They were also trying to talk with X-Loader too early, so why wouldn’t they run into this same roadblock? The answer is that their older host controllers are more tolerant of the missing NAKs. I recorded a similar trace with one of my older computers that works fine without any patches to omap_loader. It also immediately began sending IN packets trying to read from X-Loader way too soon. Just like the problematic computers, it experienced a brief period where the OMAP stopped responding to INs with NAKs. The difference is that it didn’t abandon hope so quickly. There were 33 unanswered IN packets. After that, the OMAP continued responding with NAKs again and everything was fine from that point on. 17 ms after we had originally finished sending out X-Loader, the OMAP finally responded with an actual data packet. So that’s the total time it took for X-Loader to launch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back to the newer computers that weren’t playing nicely. I was still confused. Even though this is a problem with newer host controllers, omap_loader has a retry mechanism! If it fails to read X-Loader’s initial data, it will try again 2 seconds later. You’d think it would succeed at that point. Let’s see what happens:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ah, interesting. The retry is actually 3 seconds later. I’m guessing the first failed read attempt had a 1-second timeout, so then with a 2-second retry timer, that adds up to 3 seconds total.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway, something funky happens here. The USB host finally reads the 13-byte string from X-Loader as a DATA1 packet (again, it shows up as 16 bytes because of the packet ID and CRC). The host then acknowledges reception with an ACK, but for some bizarre reason, it immediately continues attempting to read more data! I won’t show the whole trace, but the host keeps polling with IN packets for a whole second. And of course, they’re all NAKed. X-Loader knows it successfully sent data to us, so it has shifted over to waiting for the host to send an OUT packet instead. It’s like the host controller gets confused and expects X-Loader to send more data. The kernel never reports those 13 bytes back to libusb, even after the 1-second transfer timeout expires.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t consider myself to be a USB expert, so maybe I’m misunderstanding something. This behavior just seems wrong, though. When my computer finally reads 13 bytes (proven by the sniffer trace shown above), why isn’t this data reported back to libusb? I would have expected the reception of a short DATA0/1 packet to cause the host controller to stop reading and return the data back immediately. Is this some kind of strange bug in the Linux kernel or the host controller hardware or something? I don’t know for sure. I find this behavior to be very odd, and I can’t explain it. My off-the-cuff guess is that the initial failure to respond to the three IN packets results in something getting out of sync in the host controller, but I really don’t know for sure. In my opinion, the retry should have worked, but clearly, something got confused. Not sure what. I don’t think it’s libusb’s fault, though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hate adding arbitrary delays in order to fix things, but a 20-millisecond delay between uploading X-Loader and attempting to read from it fixes this final issue. It ensures that the OMAP has been given ample time to launch X-Loader before we try reading from it, preventing the host controller from encountering the weird situation with unanswered IN packets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After all of this tinkering and patching that I did to get things to play nicely on newer machines, here is a successful run of omap_loader:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;[+] successfully opened 0451:d009 (Texas Instruments OMAP3430)&lt;lb/&gt;[+] got ASIC ID - Num Subblocks [05], Device ID Info [01050134300757], Reserved [13020100], Ident Data [1215010000000000000000000000000000000000000000], Reserved [1415010000000000000000000000000000000000000000], CRC (4 bytes) [150901f7488f2800000000]&lt;lb/&gt;[+] uploading 'u-boot.bin' (size 777760) to 0x80800000&lt;lb/&gt;[+] jumping to address 0x80800000&lt;lb/&gt;[+] successfully transfered 2 files&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the following output pops up on the BeagleBoard’s UART:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Texas Instruments X-Loader 1.5.1 (Nov 15 2011 - 09:36:31)&lt;lb/&gt;Beagle Rev C4&lt;lb/&gt;Trying load from USB&lt;lb/&gt;USBLOAD_CMD_FILE total = 12 addr = 0x73425355 val = 0xbde20 val = 0x80800000&lt;lb/&gt;got file addr = 0x808bde20&lt;lb/&gt;USBLOAD_CMD_JUMP total = 8 addr = 0x6a425355 val = 0x80800000&lt;lb/&gt;U-Boot 2023.10 (May 25 2024 - 22:05:27 -0700)&lt;lb/&gt;OMAP3530-GP ES3.1, CPU-OPP2, L3-165MHz, Max CPU Clock 720 MHz&lt;lb/&gt;Model: TI OMAP3 BeagleBoard&lt;lb/&gt;OMAP3 Beagle board + LPDDR/NAND&lt;lb/&gt;I2C: ready&lt;lb/&gt;DRAM: 256 MiB&lt;lb/&gt;Core: 44 devices, 18 uclasses, devicetree: separate&lt;lb/&gt;NAND: 256 MiB&lt;lb/&gt;MMC: OMAP SD/MMC: 0&lt;lb/&gt;Loading Environment from NAND... *** Warning - bad CRC, using default environment&lt;lb/&gt;Beagle Rev C4&lt;lb/&gt;Timed out in wait_for_event: status=0000&lt;lb/&gt;Check if pads/pull-ups of bus are properly configured&lt;lb/&gt;No EEPROM on expansion board&lt;lb/&gt;OMAP die ID: 79b8000400000000040398da1401c009&lt;lb/&gt;Net: No ethernet found.&lt;lb/&gt;Hit any key to stop autoboot: 2&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I believe the “Timed out in wait_for_event” error is harmless. Anyway, success! It loads U-Boot! You can imagine that I could have easily transmitted a Linux kernel and initramfs as well, and fully booted this thing over USB. Once U-Boot is running, I can do whatever I want.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With these simple delay tweaks, omap_loader works great on all modern computers I’ve thrown at it, including Raspberry Pis. The only “gotcha” I’ve encountered is that some slower computers (my i3-7100U laptop and a Raspberry Pi Zero) don’t forward the USB hotplug event through udev quickly enough before the BeagleBoard decides it’s not being asked to boot over USB. omap_loader never gets past scanning for a device, even though the &lt;code&gt;dmesg&lt;/code&gt; log clearly shows that it was detected:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;[4076310.258842] usb 11-5: new high-speed USB device number 65 using xhci_hcd&lt;lb/&gt;[4076310.407944] usb 11-5: unable to get BOS descriptor or descriptor too short&lt;lb/&gt;[4076310.410041] usb 11-5: New USB device found, idVendor=0451, idProduct=d009, bcdDevice= 0.00&lt;lb/&gt;[4076310.410046] usb 11-5: New USB device strings: Mfr=33, Product=37, SerialNumber=0&lt;lb/&gt;[4076310.410051] usb 11-5: Product: OMAP3430&lt;lb/&gt;[4076310.410054] usb 11-5: Manufacturer: Texas Instruments&lt;lb/&gt;[4076310.710703] usb 11-5: USB disconnect, device number 65&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you can see, it’s a very short timeframe; just like TI’s manual says, it only stays connected for about 300 ms if it doesn’t hear from the host. I guess that’s not enough time for udev on some computers. The only solution I found for this issue on my slower machines was to compile a custom version of libusb with udev disabled, which forces it to directly use netlink for hotplug detection instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My patch also limits libusb transfers to 512 bytes at a time. I don’t think this change is critical, though. It fixed an issue I ran into where my bus was really loaded and libusb reported a memory error. I don’t think it actually helps anything in most cases as long as people aren’t performing crazy big USB transfers at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In summary:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trying to write USB data to the OMAP’s on-chip bootloader too quickly seems to hit some edge cases that it doesn’t handle correctly. A 1 ms delay fixes this.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trying to read from X-Loader before it’s ready to go irritates newer USB host controllers when they send out several IN packets without receiving any response (not even a NAK). A 20 ms delay fixes this. &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Even retries afterward fail; the host controller gets out of sync due to the unanswered IN packets or something like that.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;On some slower computers, udev doesn’t give you enough time to respond to the OMAP’s 300 ms timeout, so libusb never detects the hotplug. This can be solved with a custom libusb that uses netlink instead of udev.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I opened up a PR to submit these fixes (except for the udev thing) upstream to omap_loader in 2024. Why am I writing about this now? Well, remember when I mentioned Nest earlier? Google ended support for older Nest thermostats last month, which renewed some interest in merging my reliability improvements so that people can flash custom firmware to their Nest thermostats. Those old Nest devices also use OMAP processors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What it boils down to is: all this tinkering I did last year with pointlessly booting old BeagleBoards over USB accidentally ended up being useful. It helped out some Nest thermostat revival projects that have been popping up in the last month. So I thought now might be a fun time to talk about my tiny involvement with that. Yay! It’s always fun when a random side project unexpectedly helps other people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2025/11/debugging-beagleboard-usb-boot-with-a-sniffer-fixing-omap_loader-on-modern-pcs/"/><published>2025-11-08T22:30:58+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45860654</id><title>IP blocking the UK is not enough to comply with the Online Safety Act</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:52.364231+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3618901307771530"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A follow up to The Ofcom Files.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Some notes on Ofcom’s strategy to date.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As many of you know, I represent the U.S. website 4chan, pro bono, in its U.S. federal lawsuit against the UK’s communications regulator, Ofcom, together with my co-counsel Ron Coleman. The suit seeks to defend 4chan from the UK’s attempts to censor that website using the UK’s new Internet censorship law, the Online Safety Act.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What some of you may not know is that I have personally committed to defend, pro bono, any U.S. website which operates lawfully in the United States – no matter how large or small – against the UK’s attempts to infringe on the First Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And indeed, I am currently representing every single U.S. social-media enforcement target of the UK Online Safety Act, again pro bono, without exception. I will continue to do so until the Online Safety Act’s capacity to harm American citizens is destroyed, by America enacting a shield law.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means, necessarily, taking on some of the most controversial sites on the web as one’s clients. One such client, a social media forum called “Sanctioned Suicide” or “SaSu,” has long been a target for Ofcom’s ire because of the subject matter that the site hosts – principally, it is a mental health webforum where suicidal people are allowed to discuss the most taboo subject of all taboo subjects, suicide itself, and how they plan to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To say that this site’s subject matter is controversial is an understatement; as a Catholic I freely admit I struggled at first with representing the site. SaSu, 4chan, Gab, and Kiwi Farms – the complete list of Ofcom’s U.S. enforcement targets to date – are some of the most unsympathetic websites in the world, from a political point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was, in my view, a deliberate strategy by Ofcom: pick the most radioactive free speech targets in the world, isolate them in confidential proceedings, punish them, and publicly shame them when you claim the fine notices or blocking orders as a win. The only way to counter that strategy is to ensure that no target goes without competent counsel, every target knows what Ofcom is trying to do, and every case will be fought like hell, in as public a fashion as possible. As Justice Brandeis said, “sunlight is the best disinfectant.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The victory condition of the U.S. pushback against Ofcom is the successful defense of the First Amendment – all of the First Amendment. If we concede even a scintilla of our constitutional rights, we fail. If we let any target fight alone, we fail. If any censorship demand gets through our border, we fail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That means we defend every site, however small or controversial it may be, from foreign attempts to infringe on their constitutional rights. It means not giving up so much as an inch of ground without a major fight, if those are the instructions. It means we must not ever lose.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We do this because the defense of any American is the defense of us all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The story of Ofcom v SaSu&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SaSu is a tiny forum which didn’t have much of an appetite for a fight. Accordingly, when Ofcom came calling at the end of February, SaSu more or less immediately IP blocked the entire UK in hopes of avoiding enforcement action. (Ofcom claims this occurred in July; it in fact occurred in May.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And, for a time, this worked. Today, however, I can reveal that Ofcom has reversed its decision and is going after the site anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ofcom alleges that SaSu’s geo-block went down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is demonstrably false. The block has been consistently functional for months, and when Ofcom’s e-mail landed in my inbox, I went to check it myself by using my own VPN to access the Internet through a London IP (unlike UK policymakers, I know how to use one). Sure enough, SaSu’s nationwide site block prevented me from viewing the site.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What appears to have happened is that SaSu had a site mirror and that someone figured out a way to hit the mirror – which was also subject to the geoblock, something which took me under a minute to personally confirm – without using a VPN.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is possible for a range of reasons. The primary one is that the notion of a “UK based IP” is nonsense. Geolocation databases work by figuring out where people log in from and only after doing a lot of pattern recognition do those addresses get associated with that location. So there will be UK-based IPs that geolocate to Poland, for example, even though the end-user is sitting in the UK, because the database thinks that that IP address belongs in Poland.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What might have happened is that a third party, understanding this, could have found SaSu’s mirror, hit SaSu’s mirror with one of these IPs, and then handed the file off to the regulator as some kind of “gotcha” demonstrating that the IP geoblock was ineffective, and using the fact of the access plus the fact that there was a mirror URL to claim that SaSu was somehow trying to dishonestly mislead the regulator about its compliance with the OSA through geoblocking. (The reasons why SaSu had a mirror are SaSu’s alone/none of Ofcom’s fucking business; what it suffices to note is that both SaSu’s main site and the mirror blocked the UK.) If this is in fact what happened, it would have been a profoundly dishonest tactic by UK activists to try to bring down regulatory hellfire on a disfavored American company, and it merits a full parliamentary investigation (though, I won’t hold my breath waiting for that).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ofcom, in reopening the investigation on the basis that the geoblock was down when the geoblock was in fact up, (1) reveals that it has no idea how the Internet works and (2) has made a pretty titanic mistake. Now it’ll either need to assert that the geoblock isn’t effective (when, for the most part, it is) or it’ll need to climb down (causing fury among the political constituencies which have so much power in Westminster that they forced the file to reopen in the first place).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What seems clear to me is that Ofcom needs a scalp to present to Ofcom’s political masters. It’s been decided that SaSu is it. SaSu is, arguably, the most important scapegoat that was used to justify the Online Safety Act. Web censorship advocates like the Molly Rose Foundation – one of the major NGO sponsors of the Online Safety Act – seemingly exist for the sole purpose of advocating for increasingly insane levels of censorship of the Internet for everyone in the UK, always pointing to a single target as the justification, and never calling for any solution other than mass censorship of the entire country.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That target is, and for years has been, SaSu. The NGOs in question refuse to name the site, ostensibly for harm reduction purposes, but this also prevents people from openly engaging with the issue and having an honest conversation about what the site is, what (American) legal protections it benefits from, and, therefore, what practical limitations there are on the UK trying to close it down, both now and when the UK was drafting and enacting the UK Online Safety Act.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK’s inability to have those honest conversations at the proper time is what is causing the Online Safety Act to, slowly but surely, fail as an international regulatory scheme. This habit also led the UK to enact the Online Safety Act instead of adopting other, less censorial, approaches to make the Internet a safer place, which were ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even today, aforementioned “Safety” NGO and others are using the simple fact of the SaSu’s existence to try to convince legislators that a nationwide VPN ban that applies to every one of the 69 million men, women, and children in the United Kingdom is necessary to end SaSu specifically – tantamount to using a thermonuclear bomb to swat a fly. Only three weeks ago, these groups called for the Prime Minister to open a parliamentary inquiry and wrote a 51-page report seeking to apply additional pressure for retaliatory action and additional global censorship powers. SaSu was even mentioned by Keir Starmer, albeit not by name, when he tried justifying the Online Safety Act to President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There was even direct political pressure put on Ofcom by Parliament itself on October 31st to do something about SaSu.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One could be forgiven for thinking that SaSu is the UK censorship-industrial complex’s favorite company, given how much they talk about it to practically anyone who will listen. In a way, it is the Online Safety Act’s necessary target: these organizations have spent years saying that the Online Safety Act was the required solution to a company like SaSu. If the Act fails to end it, the Act itself also fails. The credibility of the entire regime rests on beating this one website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For this reason, SaSu was the very first site Ofcom targeted for enforcement action in February 2025, months before Ofcom went after 4chan or anyone else. When that happened, the UK censorship NGO sector clearly expected SaSu to get wiped off the face of the Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But SaSu, rudely, didn’t die, a fact which makes the UK censorship-industrial apparatus incandescent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK has no power to shut the site down, because the site and its operators are in the United States, they are not violating U.S. law, and they are conducting themselves in a manner that is protected by the First Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, it appears, as with 4chan, Ofcom has elected to proceed with a mock execution. Based on the fact that the nationwide IP block is still live, the precedent they want to set – the message they want to send – seems pretty clear to me: Geo-IP blocking the entire UK is no longer enough to comply with the Online Safety Act.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ofcom is trying to set the precedent that no matter where you are in the world, and no matter how much you try to keep UK users off your site, Ofcom believes you have to follow its rules – even if you’re American and you’re engaged in constitutionally protected speech and conduct. To that end, Ofcom has renewed its previous threats of fines, arrest, and imprisonment, against SaSu and its operators – all Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is not what I expected. I had expected the UK, after encountering serious resistance to its extraterritorial expansion plans in the United States with 4chan’s refusal to comply, to start considering the merits of backing down. Instead, the UK is choosing to escalate, going after a target who the Online Safety Act’s political masters desperately want to, even need to, eradicate, even though that target made good-faith efforts to block the UK from its services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hate to spoil the party, but Ofcom will need to go try some other country’s websites to set that precedent. The UK is not going to be allowed to lay a finger on an American.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I reproduce relevant correspondence below. We have also sent this correspondence to the White House, both Houses of Congress, individuals spearheading legislative initiatives to erect censorship shield laws in four different states, and the nation’s leading free speech advocacy organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My message to Washington and state legislators&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Free speech test cases are rarely made in relation to popular speech. But we call them “test cases” for a reason: because they are the test of the boundaries, and their outcome determines the future trajectory of the law and human behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lesson from this correspondence is unmistakable: the UK thinks that anyone who refuses to adhere to its content rules, wherever they are based, is fair game for threats of fines and imprisonment, even if they try to wall themselves off from the UK with comprehensive blocks of UK IP addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This includes every single person in the United States. Companies like SaSu are the canaries in the coal mine. Companies most of us use every day like Meta or X are next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This problem is not going to go away. As we have seen with the escalating war of words between the UK and X, which culminated in a British King’s Counsel putting X’s Head of Global Government Affairs through a Maoist-style pro-Online Safety Act struggle session at an inquiry hearing only yesterday, it is clear the United Kingdom – or, at least, the bunch of yahoos who currently run it – will not be content to allow any American to enjoy the full measure of their constitutional rights online, no matter how obscure the U.S. site in question may be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They will attempt to crush anyone who resists, even if that resistance is in the form of Americans doing everything in our power to block the entire UK from our services to try to get British censors off our backs. The UK is willing to punish and threaten American companies – large and small – and American citizens in order to set the precedent that the UK is in charge of America’s Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our government should not allow this to be done to any American, on principle. No American client of mine will ever bend to that sort of pressure. We need to act now to prevent our most valuable companies, and their hundreds of millions of American users, from being subjected to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These attempts to disrespect and override American sovereignty must be answered before the same thing is done to websites used by millions of other American citizens, when the UK inevitably turns its attention to the larger and more well-moderated services we all know and love, including all of our world-beating AI companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the final analysis, American citizens shouldn’t have to put up with this bullshit from foreigners. We fought, and won, many wars to secure our freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I have been doing for nearly an entire year, I strongly urge the White House and Congress, and legislators in each of the fifty States, to intervene to protect the free speech of all American citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;UPDATE, 7 NOVEMBER 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ofcom replied to our initial e-mail responding to their reopening this investigation (see first PDF at the bottom of this post) and this blog post as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This e-mail is extraordinary: Ofcom didn’t like that I referred to its enforcement effort against SaSu as a coordinated, politically motivated hit, so it felt the need – in correspondence to a target’s lawyer – to specifically respond to the allegation and complain about the public defense of my client that I made in a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As to the blog post, we’ll deal with that in a second.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s pretty obviously a true statement that this investigation has a political dimension to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Putting aside, for a moment, the fact that a certain UK NGO – the country’s leading pro-censorship organization…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;kvetched to Parliament about this matter in September,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;called for the Prime Minister to open an investigation into my client in October, and then&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;triggered the House of Lords’ Digital Committee to give Ofcom a written dressing-down repeating that NGO’s point of view, verbatim, only last week,&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;…it remains true that Ofcom reopened the investigation to minor but noticeable press fanfare and – miraculously! – also had that very NGO extensively quoted in a press drop that landed a mere 57 minutes after I received Ofcom’s message, followed up by prime morning TV spots for that UK NGO 14 hours later (approximately 8AM local time in London) – during which time the UK NGO called for my client to be fined, arrested, and prosecuted!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All for conduct that is perfectly lawful in the United States. Exhibit A:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If my client’s site is truly that dangerous to UK internet users, why did Ofcom wait two days preparing a press campaign instead of, oh, I dunno, calling us up and reporting any suspected “bugs” in the geo-block so that they can be patched?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Particularly when the target was voluntarily doing so already?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The answer, in all probability, is that highly political pressure groups are working hand-in-glove with the UK’s public bodies, Parliament and others, to try to show that the OSA can be successfully wielded against all those pesky Americans who won’t just be sensible and surrender our rights simply because a bunch of censors in the UK ordered us to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interesting how Ofcom treats investigations as confidential every time they get a FOIA request or a request for comment from a journalist, but not, apparently, when Parliament wants a prominent American scalp and they need to coordinate with friendly media and pro-censorship groups.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approaching the matter from this perspective, I replied to Ofcom as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As to the blog post, it occurred to me I forgot to clear up the record on that so I added the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ofcom then issued its own response, in public:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Utterly extraordinary. Let me explain what probably happened here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK regulator has now publicly confirmed that the “mirror” site for my client’s site is not accessible in the UK. This, of course, has been the case all along, as I verified within ten minutes of receiving Ofcom’s email on Thursday afternoon. I’m not sure what, exactly, happened here, but I am advised that both mirror and the base site in this case were both covered by the IP block at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I had to guess, it’s that some NGO found some UK-based IP addresses which weren’t captured by the block because they weren’t properly geolocated. They probably then assembled a dossier and reported this to the UK regulator, and the UK regulator, under pressure from its political masters in Westminster, decided to do a rush job on enforcement and drive a truck through a hole that can be measured in micrometers, betting no one would be willing to publicly defend what is, arguably, the most controversial lawful website on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They bet wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the fact that Ofcom felt the need to put up a corrective press release 36 hours after the start of the reopened “investigation,” and a mere 72 hours (max) after getting a tip from the Samaritans? They’re not treating this like a law enforcement investigation, where they’d take their time and make sure they got it right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They’re definitely not treating it like a public safety matter, where they know how to reach us and know that I generally respond within the hour.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you’re doing advance leaks to the press and rushing out statements to rebut your critics in real time, you’re not running a public safety operation. Ofcom is running a media campaign to defend the credibility of the Online Safety Act project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, the IP block doesn’t really matter: my client has that block up to minimize hassle from aggressive foreign regulators and to keep their spam out of its inbox, not because it has any legal obligation to give a single solitary fuck about what an unelected British bureaucrat tells it to do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ofcom doesn’t have the legal power to order around my dog in the United States. It certainly doesn’t have the legal power to order around American citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hope Washington, D.C. sees this and understands that this bullshit is what awaits every American Internet company, including Meta and X, if the United States doesn’t put a stop to this now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, what Ofcom is doing here is the perfect modern-day lesson lesson for why the First Amendment exists in the first place. A British regulator is threatening Americans in order to censor them, on pain of jail time, using only the flimsiest of excuses and immense, overbroad, and highly discretionary enforcement powers, to please politicians.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;America and the UK fought a war over this. UK regulators doing this to Americans for doing nothing other than lawfully exercising their constitutional rights is not a situation the United States should ever accept.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I call upon the Trump Administration to use all available trade levers to put this misbehavior to an end, and upon the U.S. Congress to enact a foreign censorship shield law.&lt;lb/&gt;—&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/"/><published>2025-11-08T22:33:56+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45860843</id><title>Ironclad – formally verified, real-time capable, Unix-like OS kernel</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:52.068611+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6f56f93a45a93f90"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ironclad is a formally verified, real-time capable, UNIX-like operating system kernel for general-purpose and embedded uses. It is written in SPARK and Ada, and is comprised of 100% free software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ironclad features a familiar POSIX-compatible interface, true simultaneous preemptive multitasking, Mandatory Access Control (MAC), and support for hard real-time scheduling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ironclad is fully open source and distributed under the GPLv3, ensuring it remains free. No firmware blobs are needed or shipped with the kernel. Every piece of the stack is open source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SPARK's state of the art formal verification is employed for ensuring absence of errors and correctness of huge swathes of Ironclad, like cryptography, MAC, and user-facing facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ported to several platforms and boards, and designed to be easily portable to many more. Dependency on only the GNU toolchain allows for easy cross-compilation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ironclad will always be free for use, study, and modification, so, to support the project, we rely on the use of donations and grants. Every contribution makes a difference and allows us to do more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is funded through NGI Zero Core, a fund established by NLnet with financial support from the European Commission's Next Generation Internet program. Learn more at the NLnet project page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additionally, we would like to thank the following organizations:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://ironclad-os.org/"/><published>2025-11-08T23:03:10+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45861411</id><title>Humanity's Endgame</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:51.715241+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ffaa11db28a113ed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Henry Wismayer is a writer based in London.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LONDON — There are 8 million artifacts in the British Museum. But to commence his tale of existential jeopardy, risk expert Luke Kemp made a beeline for just two items housed in a single room. On a visit in early fall, beyond a series of first-floor galleries displaying sarcophagi from pharaonic Egypt, we stopped beside a scatter of human bones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The exhibit comprised two of the 64 skeletons unearthed from the sands of Jebel Sahaba, in northern Sudan, in 1964. Believed to be over 13,000 years old, the bodies in this prehistoric cemetery were significant for what they revealed about how their owners died. Of those 64 skeletons, at least 38 showed signs of violent deaths: caved-in skulls, forearm bones with parry fractures from victims staving off blows, or other injuries. Whether a result of organized warfare, intercommunal conflict or even outright massacre, Jebel Sahaba is widely considered to be some of the earliest evidence of mass violence in the archaeological record.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to Kemp, these shattered bones were a foreshadowing of another object in this room. Ten feet away, displayed at knee-height, was the Palette of Narmer. Hewn from a tapering tablet of grey-green siltstone, the item on display was an exact cast of the 5,000-year-old original — discovered by British archaeologists in 1898 — that now sits in Cairo’s Egyptian Museum.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the center of the stone stands the giant figure of Narmer, the first king of Egypt. His left hand clasps the head of an enemy, presumed to be a rival ruler of the Western Delta. In his raised right hand he holds a mace. The image is thought to depict Narmer bludgeoning his greatest opponent to death, an act that solidified his sovereignty over all Egypt. Beneath his feet lie the contorted bodies of two other victims, while overhead a falcon presents Narmer with a ribbon, believed to represent the god Horus bestowing a gift of the Western Nile. “Here we have perfect historical evidence of what the social contract is. It’s written in blood,” Kemp told me. “This is the first depiction of how states are made.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the British Museum’s repository of ancient treasures and colonial loot, the palette is by no means a star attraction. For the half hour we spent in the room, few visitors gave it more than a passing glance. But to Kemp, its imagery “is the most important artwork in the world” — a blueprint for every city-state, nation and empire that has ever been carved out by force of arms, reified in stone and subsequently turned to dust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Systematizing Collapse&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Kemp set out seven years ago to write his book about how societies rise and fall — and why he fears that our own is headed for disaster — one biblical event provided him with the perfect allegory: the story of the Battle of the Valley of Elah, recounted in 1 Samuel 17. Fought between the Israelites and the Philistines in the 11th century BCE, it’s a tale more commonly known by the names of its protagonists, David and Goliath.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Goliath, we are told, was a Philistine warrior standing “six cubits and a span,” or around 9 feet, 9 inches, clad in the alloy of copper and tin armor that would give his epoch its name: the Bronze Age. As the rival armies faced off across the valley, the giant stepped onto the battlefield and laid down a challenge that the conflict should be resolved in single combat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For 40 days, Goliath goaded his enemy to nominate a champion, until a shepherd named David came forward from the Israelite ranks, strung a stone into his slingshot and catapulted it into Goliath’s brow, killing him at a stroke, and taking his head with the giant’s own sword. For centuries thereafter, the story of David and Goliath has served as a parable challenging the superiority of physical might. Even the most impressive entity has hidden frailties. A colossus can be felled by a single blow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to Kemp’s new book, “Goliath’s Curse,” it’s a lesson we would do well to heed. Early on, he dispenses with the word “civilization,” because in his telling, there is little that might be considered civil about how states are born and sustained. Instead, he argues that “Goliath” is a more apposite metaphor for the kind of exploitative, hierarchical systems that have grown to organize human society.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like the Philistine warrior, the Goliath state is defined by its size; in time, centralized polities would evolve to dwarf the hunter-gatherer societies that prevailed for the first 300,000 years of Homo sapiens. Ostensibly, it is well-armored and intimidating, exerting power through the threat and exercise of violence. And, in kind with the biblical colossus, it is vulnerable: Those characteristics that most project strength, like autocracy and social complexity, conceal hidden weaknesses. (A more modern allegory, Kemp writes, can be found in the early Star Wars movies, in which a moon-sized space station with the capacity to blow up a planet can be destroyed by a well-placed photon torpedo.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kemp is, of course, by no means the first scholar to try to chart this violence and vulnerability through the ages. The question of what causes societies to fail is arguably the ultimate mission of big-picture history, and a perennial cultural fixation. In the modern era, the historian Jared Diamond has found fame with his theories that collapse is usually a product of geographical determinism. The “Fall of Civilizations” podcast, hosted by the historian Paul Cooper, has over 220 million listens. Perusing a bookshop recently, I spotted a recent release, entitled “A Brief History of the End of the F*cking World,” among the bestsellers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What distinguishes Kemp’s book from much of the canon is the consistencies he identifies in how different political entities evolved, and the circumstances that precipitated their fall. A panoramic synthesis of archaeology, psychology and evolutionary biology, “Goliath’s Curse” is, above all, an attempt to systematize collapse. Reviewers have hailed the book as a skeleton key to understanding societal precarity. Cooper has described it as “a masterpiece of data-driven collapsology.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moreover, it is a sobering insight into why our own globalized society feels like it is edging toward the precipice. That’s because, despite all the features that distinguish modern society from empires of the past, some rules hold true throughout the millennia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Becoming ‘Dr. Doom’&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In September, Kemp traveled down from Cambridge to meet me in London for the day. Given his subject, I half-expected a superannuated and eccentric individual, someone like Diamond with his trademark pilgrim-father beard and penchant for European chamber music. But Kemp, 35, would prove to be the antithesis of the anguished catastrophist. The man waiting for me on the concourse at King’s Cross was athletic, swarthily handsome and lantern-jawed. He’d signed off emails regarding our plans to meet with a puckish “Cheerio.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kemp’s background is also hardly stereotypical of the bookish scholar. He spent his early years in the dairy-farming town of Bega in New South Wales, Australia, where cattle outnumbered people three-to-one. It was “something of a broken home,” he told me. His father was an active member of the Hell’s Angels, involved in organized crime, a formative presence that would later germinate Kemp’s interest in power dynamics, the way violence is at once a lever for domination and for ruin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Escaping to Canberra, after high school, Kemp read “interdisciplinary studies” at the Australian National University (ANU), where he found a mentor in the statistical climatologist Jeanette Lindsay. In 2009, it was Lindsay who persuaded him to join a student delegation heading to COP15 in Copenhagen, where Kemp found himself with a front row seat to what he calls “the paralysis of geopolitics.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At one stage, during a symposium over measures to curb deforestation, he watched his own Australian delegation engage in endless circumlocutions to derail the debate. Representatives from wealthier countries, most notably America, had large teams that they could swap in and out of the floor, enabling them to filibuster vital, potentially existential questions to a deadlock. “If you’re from Tuvalu, you don’t have that privilege,” Kemp explained.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Afterward, Kemp became preoccupied by “a startling red thread” evident in so many spheres of international negotiation: the role of America as arbiter of, and all too often barrier to, multilateral cooperation. Kemp wrote his doctoral thesis on how pivotal issues — such as biodiversity loss, nuclear weapons and climate change — had grown captive to the whims of the world’s great superpower. Later, when he published a couple of academic articles on the same subject, “the ideas weren’t very popular,” he said. “Then Trump got elected, and suddenly the views skyrocketed.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2018, Kemp relocated to the United Kingdom, landing a job as a research affiliate at Cambridge University’s “Centre for the Study of Existential Risk” (CSER, often articulated, in an inadvertent nod to a historical avatar of unalloyed power, to “Caesar”). His brother’s congratulatory present, a 3-D printed, hand-engraved mask of the Marvel character “Dr. Doom,” would prove prophetic. Years later, as Kemp began to publish his theories of societal collapse, colleagues at CSER began referring to him by the very same moniker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was around this time that Kemp read “Against the Grain,” a revisionist history of nascent conurbations by James C. Scott. Kemp had always been an avid reader of history, but Scott’s thesis, which argued that the growth of centralized states “hadn’t been particularly emancipatory or even necessarily good for human wellbeing,” turned some of Kemp’s earlier assumptions about human nature on their head.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Such iconoclastic ideas — subsequently popularized in blockbuster works of non-fiction like Rutger Bregman’s “Humankind” (2019), and “The Dawn of Everything” (2021) by Graeber and Wengrove — would prompt years of research and rumination about the preconditions that enable states and empires to rise, and why they never last forever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;‘Hobbes’ Delusion’&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Goliath’s Curse” opens with a refutation of a 17th-century figure whose theories still cast a long shadow across all considerations of societal fragility. In “Leviathan” (1651), the English philosopher Thomas Hobbes proposed that the social contract was contingent on the stewardship of a central authority — a “Leviathan” designed to keep a lid on humanity’s basest instincts. Political scientists refer to this doctrine as “veneer theory.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Once civilization is peeled away, chaos spreads like brushfire,” Kemp surmises. “Whether it be in post-apocalyptic fiction, disaster movies or popular history books, collapse is often portrayed as a Hobbesian nightmare.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For decades now, the predominant version of history has been beholden to this misanthropic worldview. Many of the most influential recent theories of collapse have echoed Hobbes’ grand theory with specific exemplars. Diamond has famously argued that the society on Rapa Nui, or Easter Island, unraveled due to self-inflicted ecocide before devolving into civil war. That interpretation, in which the islanders deforested the land in the service of ancestor worship, has since been held up as a species-wide admonition — evidence, as researchers John Flenley and Paul Bahn have written, that “humankind’s covetousness is boundless. Its selfishness appears to be genetically inborn.” In “The Better Angels of Our Nature” (2011), Steven Pinker estimated that 15% of Paleolithic people died of violent causes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Kemp was struck by a persistent “lack of empirics” undermining these hypotheses, an academic tendency to focus on a handful of “cherry-picked” and emotive case studies — often on islands, in isolated communities or atypical environments that failed to provide useful analogs for the modern world. Diamond’s theories about the demise of Rapa Nui — so often presented as a salutary cautionary tale —have since been debunked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To further rebut such ideas, Kemp highlights a 2013 study by the anthropologists Jonathan Haas and Matthew Piscitelli of Chicago’s Field Museum. In what amounted to the most comprehensive survey of violence in prehistory, the authors analyzed almost 3,000 skeletons interred during the Paleolithic Era. Of the more than 400 sites in the survey, they identified just one instance of mass conflict: the bones of Jebel Sahaba. “The presumed universality of warfare in human history and ancestry may be satisfying to popular sentiment; however, such universality lacks empirical support,” Haas and Piscitelli wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there was any truth to the Hobbesian standpoint, the Paleolithic, with its absence of stratified social structures, should have been marked by mass panic and all-out war. Yet the hunter-gatherer period appears to have been a time of relative, if fragile, peace. Instead, conflict and mass violence seemed to be by-products of the very hierarchical organization that Hobbes and his antecedents essentialized. Cave art of armies wielding bows and swords dates only to around 10,000 years ago. “As soon as you start tugging on the threat of collapse, the entire tapestry of history unravels,” Kemp told me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if Hobbes was wrong about the human condition — if most people are averse to violence, if mass panic and mutual animosity are not the principal vectors of societal disintegration — what then explains the successive state failures in the historical record? Where or what, to mix metaphors, is Goliath’s Achilles’ heel?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Fuels Goliath?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In seeking to disentangle a template of collapse from this historiography, Kemp turned to historical data, searching for traits of state emergence and disintegration shared by different polities. “When I see a pattern which needs to be explained, it becomes a fascination bordering upon obsession,” he told me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A central pillar of his research was the Seshat Global History Databank, an open-source database incorporating more than 862 polities dating back to the early Neolithic. Named after the Egyptian goddess of wisdom, Seshat includes a range of metrics like the degree of centralization and the presence of different types of weaponry; it aggregates these to create nine “complexity characteristics” (CCs), including polity size, hierarchy, governmental framework and infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using this and other sources, Kemp set out to collate his own novel dataset, this time focusing on the common features not of complexity, but of collapse. In keeping with Seshat’s old-god nomenclature, he dubbed it the “Mortality of States” index, shortened to “Moros”, after the Greek god of doom. Covering 300 states spanning the last five millennia, the resulting catalogue is, Kemp claims, “the most exhaustive list of state lifespans available today.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To some extent, Kemp’s data told a story that has become received wisdom: As Earth thawed out from the last ice age, we entered the Holocene, a period of warmer temperatures and climatic stability. This shift laid the terrain for the first big inflection point: the advent of agriculture, which encouraged our previously itinerant species to settle in place, leading to greater population density and eventually proto-city-states. These early states rose and fell, often condemned by internal conflict, climatic shocks, disease or natural disasters. But gradually the organization of human societies trended toward higher levels of complexity, from the diffuse proto-city-states, through the birth of nations, then empires, to the globalized system of today. The violent paroxysms of the past were merely hiccups on a continuum toward increased sophistication and civility, and perhaps someday immortality. Such is the tale that is commonly framed as the arc of human progress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But trawling through the data in more detail also revealed unexpected and recurrent patterns, leading Kemp to an early realization: states observably age. “For the first 200 years, they seem to become more vulnerable to terminating. And after 200 years, they stay at a high risk thereafter,” Kemp told me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other glaring commonality concerned the structure of these societies. “The common thread across all of them is not necessarily that they had writing or long-distance trade,” Kemp said. “Instead, it’s that they were organized into dominance hierarchies in which one person or one group gains hegemony through its ability to inflict violence on others.”&lt;lb/&gt;Kemp argues that dominance hierarchies arise due to the presence of three “Goliath fuels.” The first of these is “lootable resources,” assets that can be easily seen, stolen and stored. In this respect, the advent of agriculture was indisputably foundational. Cereal grains like wheat and rice could be taxed and stockpiled, giving rise to centralized authorities and, later, bureaucracies of the state.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second Goliath fuel is “monopolizable weapons.” As weaponry evolved from flint to bronze, the expertise and relative scarcity of the source material required for early metallurgy meant that later weapons could be hoarded by powerful individuals or groups, giving those who controlled the supply chain a martial advantage over potential rivals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The third criterion for Goliath evolution is “caged land,” territories with few exit options. Centralized power is predicated on barriers that hinder people from fleeing oppressive hierarchies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Kemp’s telling, every single political entity has grown from one of these seeds, or more commonly, a combination of all three. Bronze Age fiefdoms expanded at the tip of their metal weaponry. “Rome,” Kemp writes, “was an autocratic machine for turning grain into swords,” its vast armies sustained by crop imports from the Nile Valley, its endless military campaigns funded by the silver mines it controlled in Spain. In China, the Han dynasty circumscribed its territory with its Great Wall to the north, intended both to keep Xiongnu horseback raiders out and the citizenry in. Europe’s colonial empires were built, in Diamond’s famous summation, by “Guns, Germs and Steel.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For millennia, the nature of forager societies kept these acquisitive impulses to some extent contained, Kemp argues. The evolutionary logic of hunting and gathering demanded cooperation and reciprocity, giving rise to “counter-dominance strategies”: teasing, shaming or exile. With the advent of Goliath polities, however, the “darker angels of our nature” were given free rein, yielding social arrangements “more like the dominance hierarchies of gorillas and chimpanzees.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Rather than a stepladder of progress,” Kemp writes, “this movement from civilization to Goliath is better described as evolutionary backsliding.” Moreover, Goliaths “contain the seeds of their own demise: they are cursed. This is why they have collapsed repeatedly throughout history.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Kemp’s narrative, our retrograde rush toward these vicious social structures has been less about consensus than the relentless ascent of the wrong sort of people. Goliath hierarchies select for assholes — or, to use Kemp’s preferred epithet, “dark triad” personalities: people with high levels of psychopathy, narcissism and Machiavellianism. Consequently, history has been shaped by pathological figures in the Narmer mold, dominance-seekers predisposed to aggression. Reinforced by exceptionalist and paranoid ideologies, these strongmen have used violence and patronage to secure their dominion, whether driven by a lust for power or to avenge a humiliation. Several of the rebellions that plagued dynastic China, Kemp points out, were spearheaded by aggrieved people who failed their civil service examinations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wherever Goliath took hold, “arms races” followed, as other status-seeking aspirants jostled for hegemony. And Goliaths were contagious. The growth of “one bellicose city-state” would often produce a domino effect, in which the threat of an ascendant Goliath would provoke other regional polities to turn to their own in-house authoritarian as a counterweight to the authoritarian next door.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this way, humankind gravitated “from hunting and gathering to being hunted and gathered,” Kemp writes. Early states had little to distinguish them from “criminal gangs running protection rackets.” Many of the great men of history, who are often said to have bent society to their will, Kemp told me, are better thought of as “a rollcall of serial killers.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The 1% View Of History&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back downstairs, on the British Museum’s ground floor, we walked into a long gallery off the central atrium containing dozens of megalithic totems from the great ages of antiquity. The giant granite bust of Rameses II sat beatific on a pediment, and visitors peered into a glass cabinet containing the Rosetta Stone. Kemp, slaloming through the crowds, murmured: “The 1% view of history made manifest.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along both walls of an adjacent corridor, we came upon a series of bas-reliefs from the neo-Assyrian city of Nimrud, in modern-day Iraq. Depicting scenes from the life of the Ashurnasirpal II, who ruled Nimrud in the 9th century BCE, the gypsum slabs were like an artistic expression of Kemp’s historical themes: Ashurnasirpal sitting on a throne before vassals bearing tribute; Ashurnasirpal surrounded by protective spirits; Ashurnasirpal’s army ramming the walls of an enemy city, rivals dragging themselves along the ground, backs perforated with arrows. The entire carving was overlaid with cuneiform script, transcribed onto signage below, with sporadic sentences translated into English: “great king, strong king, king of the universe. … Whose command disintegrates mountains and seas.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Across the atrium, in a low-lit room containing a bequest from the Rothschild family’s antique collection, Kemp lingered over an assortment of small wooden altarpieces, with biblical scenes and iconography carved in minuscule, intricate detail. Elite status could be projected in the imposing size of a granite statue, he said. But it could just as well be archived in the countless hours spent chiseling the Last Supper into a fragment of boxwood.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is, of course, inevitable that our sense of history is skewed by this elite bias, Kemp explained. While quotidian objects and utensils were typically made of perishable materials, the palaces and monuments of the governing class were designed to be beautiful, awe-inspiring and durable. In the hours that we spent on the upper floors, we spied just one relic of ordinary life: a 3,000-year-old wooden yoke from Cambridgeshire.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Likewise, early writing often evolved to reinforce the “1% view of history” and formalize modes of control. The predominance of this elite narrative has produced a cultural blind spot, obscuring the brutality and oppression that has forever been the lot of those living at the base of a pyramid, both figurative and actual.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From all this aristocratic residue, Kemp sought to extract a “people’s history of collapse” — some means of inferring what it was like to live through collapse for the average person, rather than the elites immortalized in scripture and stone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Curse Of Inequality&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If Kemp’s research revealed that historical state formation appears to follow a pattern, so, too, did the forces that inexorably led toward their demise. To illustrate how the process works, Kemp provides the example of Çatalhöyük, a proto-city that arose on the Konya Plain in south-central Turkey around 9,000 years ago, one of thousands of “tells,” mounded remnants of aborted settlements found throughout the Near East.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Excavations of the site’s oldest layers suggest that early Çatalhöyük was notable for its lack of social differentiation. Crammed together in a dense fractal of similarly sized mud-brick dwellings, the settlement in this period exhibits no remnants of fortification and no signs of warfare. Analysis of male and female skeletons has shown that both sexes ate the same diet and performed the same work, indicating a remarkable degree of gender equity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This social arrangement, which the Stanford archaeologist Ian Hodder has described as “aggressively egalitarian,” lasted for around 1,000 years. Then, in the middle of the 7th millennium BCE, the archaeological record starts to shift. House sizes begin to diverge; evidence of communal activity declines. Later skeletal remains show more evidence of osteoarthritis, possibly betraying higher levels of workload and bodily stress. Economists have estimated that the Gini coefficient, which measures disparities in household income, doubled in the space of three centuries — “a larger jump than moving from being as equal as the Netherlands to as lopsided as Brazil,” Kemp writes. Within a few centuries, the settlement was abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fate of Çatalhöyük established a template that almost every subsequent town, city-state and empire would mirror. Its trajectory resounds throughout the historical record and across continents. Similar patterns can be discerned from the remnants of the Jenne-Jeno in Mali, the Olmecs of Mesoamerica, the Tiwanaku in Titicaca, and the Cahokia in pre-Columbian North America.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Occasionally, the archaeological record suggests a fluctuation between equality and disparity and back again. In Teotihuacan, near today’s Mexico City, the erection of the Feathered Serpent Pyramid by an emergent priestly class in around 200 CE ushered in a period of ritual bloodletting. A more egalitarian chapter followed, during which the temple was razed, and the city’s wealth was rechanneled into urban renewal. Then the old oligarchy reasserted itself, and the entire settlement, beset by elite conflict or popular rebellion, was engulfed in flames.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether societies collapsed through gradual depopulation, like Çatalhöyük, or abruptly, as with Teotihuacan’s conflagration, Kemp argues that the triggers were the same. As Acemoğlu and Robinson explored in “Why Nations Fail” (2012), the correlation between inequality and state failure often rests on whether its institutions are inclusive, involving democratic decision-making and redistribution, or extractive: “designed to extract incomes and wealth from one subset of society to benefit a different subset.” Time and again, the historical record shows the same pattern repeating — of status competition and resource extraction spiraling until a tipping-point, often in the shape of a rebellion, or an external shock, like a major climate shift or natural disaster, which the elites, their decision-making fatally undermined by the imperative to maintain their grip on power, fail to navigate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In almost every case, decline or collapse was foreshadowed by increases in the appearance of proxies of inequality. A rise in the presence of large communal pots indicates an upsurge in feasting. Deviation in the size of dwellings, preserved in the excavated footprints of early conurbations, is a measure of social stratification, as wealth accumulates among the elite. Graves of that same nobility become stuffed with burial goods. Great monuments, honoring political and religious leaders or the gods who were supposed to have anointed them, proliferate. Many of the most lucrative lootable resources throughout history have been materials that connote elevated social standing, an obsession with conspicuous consumption or “wastefully using resources,” that marked a break from the hunter-gatherer principle of taking only what was needed. (Kemp wears a reminder of the human compulsion to covet beauty as much as utility, an obsidian arrowhead, on his wrist.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the while, these signs of burgeoning inequality have tended to be twinborn with an increasing concentration of power, and its corollary: violence. War, often instigated for no more reason than the pursuit of glory and prestige, was just “the continuation of status competition by other means,” Kemp writes. On occasion, this violence would be manifested in the ultimate waste of all: human sacrifice, a practice custom-made to demonstrate the leadership’s exceptionality — above ordinary morality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Better Off Stateless&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Kemp dug into the data in more detail, his research substantiated another startling paradox. Societal collapse, though invariably catastrophic for elites, has often proved to be a boon for the population at large.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here again, Kemp found that the historiography is subject to pervasive and fallacious simplifications. In his book, he repudiates the 14th-century Tuscan scholar Petrarch, who promulgated the notion that the fall of classical Rome and Greece ushered in a “dark age” of cultural atrophy and barbarism. His was a reiteration of sentiments found in many earlier examples of “lamentation literature,” left behind on engraved tablets and sheaves of papyrus, which have depicted collapse as a Gomorran hellscape. One of Kemp’s favorites is the “Admonitions of Ipuwer,” which portrays the decline of Egypt’s Old Kingdom as a time of social breakdown, civil war and cannibalism. “But it actually spends a lot more time fretting about poor people becoming richer,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In reality, Kemp contends, Petrarch’s “rise-and-fall vision of history is spectacularly wrong.” For if collapse often engulfed ancient polities “like a brushfire,” the scorched earth left behind was often surprisingly fertile. Again, osteoarcheology, the study of ancient bones, gives the lie to the idea that moments of societal disintegration always spelled misery for the population at large.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take human height, which archaeologists often turn to as a biophysical indicator of general health. “We can look at things like did they have cavities in their teeth, did they have bone lesions,” Kemp explained. “Skeletal remains are a good indicator of how much exercise people were getting, how good their diet was, whether there was lots of disease.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prior to the rise of Rome, for example, average heights in regions that would subsequently fall under its yoke were increasing. As the empire expanded, those gains stalled. By the end of the Western Empire, people were eight centimeters shorter than they would have been if the preceding trends had continued. “The old trope of the muscle-bound Germanic barbarian is somewhat true. To an Italian soldier, they would have seemed very large,” Kemp said. People in the Mediterranean only started to get taller again following Rome’s decline. (In a striking parenthesis, Kemp points out that the average male height today remains two centimeters shorter than that of our Paleolithic forebears.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, too, collapse was not necessarily synonymous with popular immiseration. The demise of the extravagant Mycenaean civilization in Greece was pursued by a cultural efflorescence, paving the way for the proto-democracy of Athens. Collapse could be emancipatory, freeing the populace from instruments of state control such as taxes and forced labor. Even the Black Death, which killed as much as half of Europe’s population in the mid-14th century, became in time an economic leveler, slashing inequality and accelerating the decline of feudalism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a pattern that can still be discerned in modern contexts. In Somalia, the decade following the fall of the Barre regime in 1991 would see almost every single indicator of quality of life improve. “Maternal mortality drops by 30%, mortality by 24%, extreme poverty by 20%,” Kemp recounted from memory. Of course, there are endless caveats. But often, “people are better off stateless.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Invariably, however, Goliaths re-emerged, stronger and more bureaucratically sophisticated than before. Colonial empires refined systems of extraction and dominance until their tentacles covered diffuse expanses of the globe. Kemp, never shy of metaphor, calls this the “rimless wheel,” a centripetal arrangement in which the core reaps benefits at the margins’ expense.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At times, such regimes were simply continuations of existing models of extraction. In 1521, when the Spanish conquistador Hernán Cortés unseated the Aztec ruler Moctezuma II, it was merely a case of “translatio imperi” — the handing over of empire. The European imperial projects in the Americas were an unforgivable stain, Kemp said. But, more often than not, they assumed the mantle from pre-existing hierarchies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Endgame&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, we walked north from the British Museum over to Coal Drops Yard, formerly a Victorian entrepôt for the import and distribution of coal, now a shiny vignette of urban regeneration. The morning rain had cleared, and Granary Square was full of tourists and office workers enjoying the late summer sun. Kids stripped to their underwear and played among low fountains; people chatted at public tables beneath a matrix of linden trees. Kemp and I found an empty table and sat down to talk about how it could all fall apart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As “Goliath’s Curse” approaches its conclusion, the book betrays a sense of impending doom about our current moment. The final section, in which Kemp applies his schema to the present day, is entitled “Endgame,” after the stage in chess where only a few moves remain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we live in what Kemp calls the “Global Goliath,” a single interconnected polity. Its lootable resources are data, fossil fuels and the synthetic fertilizers derived from petrochemicals. Centuries of arms races have yielded an arsenal of monopolizable weapons like autonomous drones and thermonuclear warheads that are “50 trillion times more powerful than a bow and arrow.” The land — sectored into national borders, monitored by a “stalker complex” of mass surveillance systems and “digital trawl-nets” — is more caged than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have reached the apotheosis of the colonial age, a time when extractive institutions and administrative reach have been so perfected that they now span the globe. However, the resulting interdependencies and fetishes for unending growth have created an ever-growing catalog of “latent risks,” or accumulated hazards yet to be realized, and “tail risks,” or outcomes with a low probability but disastrous consequences. Kemp characterizes this predicament, in which the zenith of human achievement is also our moment of peak vulnerability, as a “rungless ladder.” The higher we go, the greater the fall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under a series of apocalyptic subtitles — “Mors ex Machina,” “Evolutionary Suicide,” “A Hellish Earth” — Kemp enumerates the existential threats that have come to shape the widespread intuition, now playing out in our geopolitics, that globalized society is sprinting toward disaster. After the post-Cold War decades of non-proliferation, nuclear weapons stockpiles are now growing. The architects of artificial intelligence muse about its potential to wipe out humanity while simultaneously lobbying governments to obstruct regulation. Our densifying cities have become prospective breeding grounds for doomsday diseases. Anthropogenic climate change now threatens to shatter the stability of the Holocene, warming the planet at “an order of magnitude (tenfold) faster than the heating that triggered the world’s greatest mass extinction event, the Great Permian Dying, which wiped away 80–90% of life on earth 252 million years ago,” Kemp warns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The culprits in this unfolding tragedy are not to be found among the ranks of common people. The free market has always been predicated on the concept of Homo economicus, a notional figure governed by dispassionate self-interest. But while most people don’t embody this paradigm, we are in thrall to political structures and corporations created in that image, with Dark Triad personalities at the wheel. “The best place to find a psychopath is in prison,” Kemp told me. “The second is in the boardroom.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, deep into the Global Goliath’s senescence, several of the indicators that Kemp identifies as having historically presaged collapse — egalitarian backsliding, diminishing returns on extraction, the rise of oligarchy — are flashing red. Donning his risk analyst hat, Kemp arrives at the darkest possible prognosis: The most likely destination for our globalized society is “self-termination,” self-inflicted collapse on a hitherto unprecedented scale. Goliath is more powerful than ever, but it is on a collision course with David’s stone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Lootable Silicon&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of this seemed hard to reconcile with the atmosphere of contented civility in Granary Square on this sunny September afternoon. I proposed that an advocate for global capitalism would doubtless view our current circumstances as evidence of the Global Goliath’s collective, trickle-down bounty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We should be thankful for a whole bunch of things that started, by and large, in the Industrial Revolution,” Kemp said. “Vaccines, the eradication of smallpox, low infant mortality and the fact that over 80% of the population is literate. These are genuine achievements to be celebrated.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kemp argued that most redistribution has been a product of “stands against domination”; for example, the formation of unions, public health movements and other campaigns for social justice. Meanwhile, underlying prosperity still depends on the rimless wheel: the hub exploiting the periphery. “If we were here 150 years ago, we’d be seeing child laborers working in these courtyards,” he said, gesturing at the former coal warehouses that are now an upmarket shopping mall and that once served as a nerve center of the fossil fuel industry that built the modern age.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The same dynamics hold sway today, albeit at a further remove. Just south of us, across the Regent’s Canal, sat the London headquarters of Google, a billion-dollar glass edifice. At first glance, Kemp gave the building an enthusiastic middle finger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later, he explained: “The people sitting in that building are probably having a pretty good time. They have lots of ping pong tables and Huel. But the cobalt that they’re using in their microchips is still often dug up by artisanal miners in the Democratic Republic of Congo, getting paid less than a couple of dollars a day.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like much of the oligarchic class, the boy-gods of Silicon Valley still cleave to Hobbesian myths to justify their grip on wealth and power. Their techno-Utopian convictions, encapsulated in Bill Gates’ mantra that “innovation is the real driver of progress,” are merely a secular iteration of the divine mandates that Goliaths once used to legitimize their rule. Promises of rewards in the afterlife have been supplanted by dreams of a technological singularity and interplanetary civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another plausible eventuality, which Kemp dubs the “Silicon Goliath,” is a future in which democracy and freedom are crushed beneath the heel of advanced algorithmic systems. He is already at work on his next book about the evolution of mass surveillance, an inquiry that he told me “is in many ways even more depressing.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Slaying Goliath&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Toward the end of “Goliath’s Curse,” Kemp imagines a scenario in which the decision of whether to detonate the Trinity atomic bomb test in New Mexico in 1945 was made not by a Department of War but by a “Trinity jury,” an assembly of randomly selected members of the public.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In such a counterfactual, with the Nazis defeated, Japan already inches from surrender and Manhattan Project physicists warning of a non-zero possibility that the test could ignite the whole atmosphere and exterminate all life on Earth, Kemp contends that a more inclusive decision-making process would have changed the course of history. “If you had a random selection by lottery of 100 U.S. citizens and asked them, ‘Should we detonate the bomb?’ What decision do they come to? Almost certainly ‘No,’ he told me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Kemp sees it, the widespread adoption of such open democracy is the only viable route to escape the endgame. These citizen juries wouldn’t be free-for-alls, where the loudest or most outrageous voice wins, but deliberative procedures that necessitate juror exposure to expert, nonpartisan context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Such assemblies wouldn’t be enough to “slay Goliath” on their own, Kemp told me. “Corporations and states … [must] pay for the environmental and social damages they cause … to make the economy honest again.” Per capita wealth, Kemp added, should be limited to a maximum of $10 million.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I challenged Kemp that this wish-list was beginning to sound like a Rousseauvian fever-dream. But seven years immersed in the worst excesses of human folly had left him in no mood for half-measures. “I’m not an anarcho-primitivist,” he said. There was no point trying to revivify our hunter-gatherer past. “We’d need multiple planet Earths!” Kemp conceded. And yet the urgency of our current circumstances demanded a radical departure from the existing status quo, and no less a shift in mindset.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His final demotic prescription, “Don’t be a dick,” was an injunction to everyone that our collective future depends as much on moral ambition as political revolution. Otherwise, Goliath won’t be just a Bible story. It could also be our epitaph.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.noemamag.com/humanitys-endgame/"/><published>2025-11-08T23:58:08+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45861829</id><title>Judge denies request to exempt Flock footage from Public Records Act</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:51.361389+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ea81b2f892b756d1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cities of Sedro-Woolley and Stanwood were denied Thursday their request for a declaratory judgment that the data and images from Flock Safety cameras are not public records.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ruling was made by Skagit County Superior Court Judge Elizabeth Neidzwski.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flock Safety cameras are used by many law enforcement agencies, including the Sedro-Woolley and Stanwood police departments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cameras record images of passing cars, and using artificial intelligence the system is able to identify cars’ makes, models, colors and license plates. Flock said it deletes the data after 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cities of Sedro-Woolley and Stanwood filed a motion for a declaratory judgment after receiving public records requests for images recorded by Flock Safety cameras.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The requests were made by the same man — Jose Rodriguez. He requested images from Stanwood’s cameras from 5 to 6 p.m. on March 30, and from Sedro-Woolley’s cameras from 5 to 5:30 p.m. on May 5.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rodriguez claims that the Stanwood Police Department informed him that it is not the holder of the records, but rather it is Flock Safety, and directed him to Flock’s website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Rodriguez requested the images from the Sedro-Woolley Police Department, he was advised that the city would seek a declaratory judgment on the status of Flock data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Law enforcement has said the data recorded by the Flock Safety cameras is only accessed during active investigations, such as during a missing persons case.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both the cities of Sedro-Woolley and Stanwood have turned off their Flock Safety cameras during the legal dispute.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In October, both motioned for declaratory judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cities were seeking a declaration that the data and images requested were not public records under the state Public Records Act, and if a judge decided that they were public records they should be exempt from public disclosure as disclosure is contrary to public policy, and exempt as they constitute specific intelligence information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Emily Guildner, a lawyer representing the two cities, argued in court Thursday that if these are considered public records, it could have compounding effects on public privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She argued that the data and images on cameras aren’t readily available to police until they make a query during an investigation, and that if the data isn’t regularly available to police, it shouldn’t be available to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are concerns among law enforcement surrounding Flock Safety cameras and federal immigration enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An October University of Washington study titled “Leaving the Door Wide Open” found that U.S. Border Patrol searched 17 Washington agencies’ Flock data. Most of the searches were done without law enforcements’ awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These concerns with immigration enforcement complicate whether they should be public records.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neidzwski also said that the AI component of these cameras adds complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Timothy Hall, who represents Rodriguez, argued that the Flock data is not exempt from the Public Records Act.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He said the data held by Flock serves a purpose to government.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The government agencies do not need to possess documents in order for the Public Records Act to apply to them,” Hall said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He cited a 2015 case between Cedar Grove Composting and the city of Marysville in which the state Supreme Court ruled that documents prepared by a third party and shared with the city were subject to the Public Record Act.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.goskagit.com/news/local_news/court-denies-request-that-it-find-flock-safety-camera-data-is-exempt-from-public-records/article_f1edd028-d242-479c-ada8-f2dfca73a1b1.html"/><published>2025-11-09T00:53:07+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45861933</id><title>He Chunhui's Tiny386 Turns an ESP32-S3 into a Fully-Functional 386-Powered PC</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:51.275533+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="879ee81b481bf4cf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;He Chunhui's Tiny386 Turns the Humble ESP32-S3 Into a Fully-Functional 386-Powered Desktop PC&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fancy running Microsoft's Windows 95 on a low-cost microcontroller? Well, now you can!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developer He Chunhui has turned the humble Espressif ESP32 microcontroller into a fully-fledged '90s personal computer with Tiny386 — a resource-efficient emulator capable of running Microsoft Windows 95 and a range of 16- and 32-bit software packages on the low-cost chip.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Tiny386 is a x86 PC emulator written in C99," Chunhui explains of the project. "The highlight of the project is its portability. It now boots Windows 9x/NT on MCU [Microcontroller Units] such as [the Espressif] ESP32-S3. The core of the project is a built-from-scratch, simple and stupid [Intel] i386 CPU emulator. Some features are missing, e.g. debugging, hardware tasking, and some permission checks, but it should be able to run most 16/32-bit software."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 80386, more commonly known as the 386 and later rebadged as the i386, was released in 1985 as the successor to the best-selling 80286, expanding the nascent x86 architecture's capabilities with a six-stage instruction pipeline and support for 32-bit operation with an on-board memory management unit. It was, at the time, a powerful chip and found a home in desktops, laptops, and even servers of the era.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Espressif ESP32-S3, by contrast, is a low cost — but nevertheless highly capable — microcontroller, available for a fraction of the price of the 386 in its heyday and drawing considerably less power. Despite this, it's also a lot more powerful: the 386 was available in clock speeds of 12MHz up to 40MHz; the ESP32-S3 features a pair of Tensilica Xtensa LX7 cores running at 240MHz. That gap in power means, somewhat surprisingly, it's possible to emulate a mostly-functional 386 PC using just the ESP32-S3 plus some external pseudo-static RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Tiny386 runs on the microcontroller itself — though is designed for portability to other platforms, with Chunhui releasing a demo that runs in-browser — and, despite having some functionality stripped out, can run a wide range of software including, naturally, Id Software's 1993 classic first-person shooter Doom. The project borrows peripherals from other emulators to flesh out the system, adding VGA graphics capabilities, an emulated Ethernet network interface, and even a choice of three sound devices: PC speaker, Adlib OPL2 synthesis, and Creative Labs' SoundBlaster 16.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"To boot [a] modern Linux kernel and [Microsoft] Windows, some 486 and 586 instructions are added," Chunhui notes of the overall feature set. "The CPU emulator is kept in ~6k LOC [Lines Of Code]. There is also an optional x87 FPU [Floating-Point Unit] emulator. For firmware, the BIOS/VGABIOS comes from [the] SeaBIOS [project]. Tiny386 also supports booting [the] Linux kernel directly, without traditional BIOS."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full source code for the project is available on GitHub under the permissive BSD three-clause license, with Chunhui having demonstrated success booting it on the low-cost Guition JC3248W535 ESP32-S3-based LCD development board. Additional information is available on Hackaday.io, with an in-browser demo available via GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.hackster.io/news/he-chunhui-s-tiny386-turns-the-humble-esp32-s3-into-a-fully-functional-386-powered-desktop-pc-5454cf6e36a1"/><published>2025-11-09T01:08:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45861984</id><title>How Airbus Took Off</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:51.155310+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f5e48050ae83878f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Airbus is an example of successful industrial policy and the rare European company that is better than its American rival. Could its success be copied elsewhere?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Would you rather fly in an Airbus or a Boeing? It seems like an easy question.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Alaska Airlines Flight 1282 flight climbed to 16,000 feet on a January evening in 2024, passengers were stunned when a hole was blasted in the side of the plane. They were hit by howling winds as tray tables were ripped from the backs of seats. Were it not for their seatbelts, they would likely have been sucked out of the plane. It later transpired that the plug which sealed the exit door was missing four critical bolts that held it in place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Subscribe for $100 to receive six beautiful issues per year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Alaska Airlines incident fortunately didn’t result in any fatalities. Not everyone who has flown on a Boeing 737 MAX in the last few years has been so lucky.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2018 and 2019 saw two 737 crashes that killed 346 people after the plane’s Maneuvering Characteristics Augmentation System, a feature that pushes the plane’s nose down to prevent stalling, triggered repeatedly due to a faulty sensor. It later transpired that Boeing had not adequately disclosed how the system worked in training manuals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While Boeing wrestles with lawsuits and regulatory investigations, its rival Airbus has stayed out of the headlines – a happier place for the manufacturer of commercial airliners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Europe is a graveyard of failed national champions. They span from the glamorous Concorde to obscure ventures like pan-European computer consortium Unidata or notorious Franco-German search engine Quaero.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Airbus is the rare success story. European governments pooled resources and subsidized their champion aggressively to face down a titan of American capitalism in a strategically vital sector. Why did Airbus succeed when so many similar initiatives crashed and burned?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Airbus prevailed because it was the least European version of a European industrial strategy project ever. It put its customer first, was uninterested in being seen as European, had leadership willing to risk political blowback in the pursuit of a good product, and operated in a unique industry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;An industry on the brink&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the early days of commercial aviation, US aerospace companies dominated the market for passenger jets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Buy America Act of 1933 forced the US government to buy from American producers where possible. Military orders supercharged the industry and brought significant knowledge spillovers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Boeing B-47 bomber, introduced in the late 1940s, pioneered the use of 35-degree swept wings, which point backwards at an angle of 35 degrees and reduce drag at high speeds. This design went on to inspire nearly every commercial airliner around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile the Boeing 707, the company’s first ever airliner, shared a fuselage with the KC-135 Stratotanker, a military refueling aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the face of the US, European aerospace companies cut a sorry figure. The British Aircraft Corporation, Sud Aviation in France, and Messerschmitt-Bölkow-Blohm (MBB) in West Germany were all left to compete for orders in a fragmented continental market, with little research or marketing heft. Meanwhile, European airliners who bought American planes could apply for discounted loans from EXIM, the America’s credit export agency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Between 1960 and 1967, British and French manufacturers saw a 50 percent decline in aircraft deliveries. In 1966, the UK government had even contemplated forcibly merging and nationalizing much of the country’s industry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;European governments had poured money into their national champions in the belief that the maintenance of a civilian aerospace industry was critical for sovereignty, but it was unclear if these companies would survive the decade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amid this gloomy backdrop, European governments concluded that their industry’s future depended on cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UK and France agreed to pool the resources behind Concorde in 1962 to fight what Charles De Gaulle called ‘the American colonization of the skies’, but the Germans declined to participate due to their (well-founded) skepticism about the project’s economics. This didn’t stop the Germans teaming up with the Dutch on the long-forgotten VFW-Fokker 614. This short-haul jet struggled to find customers at a time when airlines preferred to use cheap prop aircraft for regional city-hopping, dooming the project to collapse once state aid was withdrawn in 1977.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1965, the French, British, and German governments launched a working group to evaluate the potential of a wide-body commercial aircraft, which would later become the A300. Two years later, the three governments agreed to bear the entire costs of the development of the ‘European Airbus’. In 1970, the coalition was formalized with the creation of Airbus Industrie. The consortium quickly expanded to include Spain and the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The making of a world leader&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So how did this unlikely band of brothers go on to build a global leader, rather than another Econ101 case study about the perils of industrial policy?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The single biggest factor was a focus on the customer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike many future industrial strategy projects, which would focus on creating European-owned capabilities for their own sake, the Airbus team were seized by the need to build a jet that airliners would want to buy. They didn’t have much choice: if they failed, there was a reasonable chance the consortium’s domestic aerospace suppliers would collapse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They were helped enormously in this by their setup. While Airbus didn’t become a unified corporate entity until 2001, the partnership had a strong central leadership from the beginning. Unlike other industrial consortia, which tended to be leaderless venues for intra-European turf wars, Airbus united marketing, procurement, and design.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Roger Béteille, who led the A300 program, probably bears more responsibility for Airbus’s early success than anyone else. Béteille wasn’t interested in building an inferior European Boeing copy. Instead, he invested significant time in getting to know his potential customers and what they needed. This led to Airbus quickly tossing the original design for a 300-seat A300, in favor of a 225-250 seater, when it became clear that Air France and Lufthansa wanted a smaller product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The revised A300B would prove much cheaper to develop, in part because it allowed the consortium to dispense with the expensive Rolls Royce engine in favour of a cheaper American alternative. In response, the UK exited the project, only to later return with a lower ownership stake.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This willingness to risk political blowback and avoid petty chauvinism in equipment choice was rare in industrial strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Béteille went one step further. He designated English the official language of the project, instead of the usual mixture of languages that characterised European projects, and forbade the use of metric measurements to make it easier to sell into the US market.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along with Felix Kracht, Airbus’s first production director, Béteille set a division of labour between the different countries that has persisted, with minor adjustments. French firms handled the cockpit, control systems, and lower-center fuselage; Hawker Siddeley (the inventor of the Harrier jump jet) in the UK designed and built the wings; German companies produced various fuselage sections; the Netherlands managed moving wing components; and Spain was responsible for the horizontal tailplane.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on Béteille’s market research, the A300B was optimised for fuel efficiency. The team stripped out unnecessary weight by using composite materials and raised the cabin floor to add cargo space. Hawker Siddeley’s wings, which would go on to influence industry standards, were designed with a curved shape on top to reduce air resistance, allowing greater lift and fuel efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At a time when almost every commercial jet had three or four engines, Airbus opted for a twin-engine design. The plane could theoretically fly on one and the company concluded that only a single extra engine was needed to provide redundancy for safety. The much cheaper twin-engine design is now the industry standard, even for ultra long-haul flights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite the technical ingenuity behind the A300B, early business was slow. By the time the aircraft entered service in 1974, it had struggled to attract commercial interest beyond state-owned flag carriers like Air France, which had placed the first A300B order in 1971 for six jets. Even these airlines continued to operate Boeing-dominated fleets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One problem was unfortunate timing: the oil shock of 1973 had caused operating costs to spiral for airliners, so there was little appetite for experimentation in the air.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There was also residual suspicion of European industry among US airliners. Sud Aviation’s Caravelle had been used by some American airliners, but the company was notorious for its sloppy after sales maintenance and service. There had also been an ugly dispute over landing rights for Concorde, with the US heavily restricting the aircraft’s operation out of noise concerns. The French suspected more sinister commercial motivations were at work. Jacques Chirac, then French Prime Minister, raised the temperature, declaring that: ‘The Airbus consortium will not be daunted by the Americans who killed off the Concorde. … We will fight any trade war blow-by-blow as the future of the aeronautical industry and their employees is at stake’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Against this backdrop, Airbus did everything it could to deemphasize its European heritage as it toured the US. It refused to involve the French or German embassies in its sales efforts, much to their irritation. Airbus representatives drove home how a third of the plane’s value derived from US-made components, more than any single European partner nation’s contribution. They also mastered the world of DC lobbying, successfully outmaneuvering Boeing and Lockheed’s attempts to use anti-trust regulations to shut the European entrant out of the US market.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sustained by early European market commitments and early sales in Asia, Airbus was eventually able to clinch its first US order in 1977. Eastern Airlines (EAL), which had been impressed by the A300B’s fuel economy and low noise levels, agreed to the trial lease of four aircraft and three spare engines for … one dollar. These terms would have been unconscionable for a normal private company, but they were transformative for state-backed Airbus’s fortunes. Frank Borman, conservative Republican, former NASA astronaut, and EAL’s CEO emerged as a public champion of the A300B as an ‘American aircraft’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The A320&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Béteille and Kracht weren’t content with building one aircraft. From the beginning, Airbus had targeted a 30 percent global market share. This meant building more than wide-body aircraft like the A300B.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The A320, which entered operation in 1988 was a narrow-bodied aircraft that could carry 150-180 passengers. It was optimized to fly short- and medium-haul routes economically, and a masterclass in engineering and timing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the 1980s, airliners were looking to replace their aging narrow-bodied fleets, with the Boeing 272 and McDonnell Douglas DC-9 having been in operation for more than two decades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The A320 was the first commercial aircraft to implement full digital fly-by-wire controls. Before the A320, the pilot’s controls pulled physical cables attached to the flaps, rudder, and other control surfaces on the plane. Fly-by-wire meant that controls sent electric signals to the plane’s computers, which then commanded motors to move the control surfaces. This made life easier for the pilots by reducing the need for constant manual adjustment and stripped out heavy components that needed maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The A320 was also the first commercial aircraft to introduce envelope protection, a system that automatically prevents dangerous actions, such as tilting too steeply, flying too slowly, or making maneuvers that could overstress the aircraft structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, the A320 wasn’t an overnight success, with new technology and existing relations with Boeing slowing uptake. Airbus again relied on British and French orders to gain market credibility. But by the early 1990s, its superior technology combined with Airbus’s willingness to flex the design, with the A319 (smaller) and A321 (larger) allowing airliners to operate mixed fleets with common cockpits, began to win fans. The A320 is now the most popular airliner family in history and remains in widespread use today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The success of the A320 led Airbus to profitability in the mid-1990s. By 2019, Airbus had displaced Boeing as the largest aerospace company by revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why Airbus’s success is so hard to repeat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If Airbus proves industrial strategy can work, why haven’t other European ventures fared better?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good industrial strategy requires favorable market conditions, consistent strategy in the face of political headwinds, and the courage to call it a day if failure seems likely. Getting one of these right is tough, and all three is exceptionally rare.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concorde was a marvel of engineering, but even without US obstructionism, it had little prospect of commercial viability. In today’s money, it cost £16 billion to develop, roughly ten times the cost of the Boeing 727, making it the most expensive plane of its age by some margin. Its limited passenger capacity, fuel inefficiency, and expensive maintenance meant that a ticket for a round trip cost in excess of £10,000 adjusted for inflation. The ultra-premium air travel market wasn’t big enough in the 1980s or 1990s to bear the costs of 1960s technology, leading to Concorde’s retirement in 2003.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other European projects have lacked the centralized control or clear rationale that characterized Airbus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We see this in Unidata, a 1973 consortium that brought together CII (France), Philips (the Netherlands), and Siemens (Germany) to produce a European mainframe line to rival IBM. With no clear leadership, rival members of the consortium pushed their own hardware and software approaches. Engineering efforts were duplicated. The project collapsed within two years amid recriminations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, it was unclear why the 2005 Franco-German search engine project Quaero ever needed to exist. Widely seen as a vanity project at the time, the attempt to build a search engine by committee similarly splintered along national lines. It was also a victim of mission creep, evolving from a direct Google competitor to a multimedia search platform that would be powered by image and voice analysis. The project limped on until its mercy killing in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s also easier to build a global leadership position when your main rival wages a prolonged campaign of self-sabotage. By the new millennium, the competition had been reduced to a simple showdown between Airbus and Boeing. Lockheed had decided to bail on commercial aviation in the 1970s after losing billions of dollars on the L-1011, while Boeing acquired McDonnell Douglas in a $13 billion deal in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While Airbus has retained a strong engineering culture at the helm, this disappeared from Boeing. Harry Stonecipher, Boeing’s CEO in the early 2000s, notoriously claimed that: ‘When people say I changed the culture of Boeing, that was the intent, so that it is run like a business rather than a great engineering firm’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stonecipher’s successor, James McNerney, took this even further: ‘Every 25 years a big moonshot… and then produce a 707 or a 787 – that’s the wrong way to pursue this business. The more-for-less world will not let you pursue moonshots’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The McDonnell Douglas acquisition is often marked as a turning point for Boeing. Despite being the acquiring firm, Boeing absorbed much of their target’s management philosophy. This disconnect was embodied in the company’s decision to move its headquarters from Seattle (where its main production facility was located) to Chicago, for the sake of just $63 million in tax credits. Fatal crashes in 2018 and 2019 have since caused regulatory investigations and multi-billion dollar compensation claims to pile up, as well as allegations that the company has put shareholders and dividends before safety.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A strange industry&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does the Airbus story make a good case for a disciplined, well-executed industrial strategy?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To answer this question, we need to take a step back from Airbus and Boeing and think about their customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Airlines have one of the worst business models of any industry. They have eye-watering capital expenditures (a large jet costs in excess of $200 million). The product offering (flights) is relatively undifferentiated, while many of their customers are price-conscious and disloyal. Safety regulations, along with route and landing slot regulations mean there’s little space to drive painless efficiencies. This leaves airlines with two main routes to success: worsening their service through cost-cutting and engaging in kamikaze price wars.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is why airlines frequently go bankrupt, with US Airways, United Airlines, Northwest Airlines, Delta Air Lines and American Airlines among the dozens to almost collapse in the 2000s. Only three airlines without state ties (Southwest, Ryanair, and Copa) have consistently maintained profitability while avoiding bankruptcy or major restructuring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In his 2007 letter to Berkshire Hathaway shareholders, Warren Buffett described the airline industry as ‘the worst sort of business’, and noted that, ‘if a farsighted capitalist had been present at Kitty Hawk, he would have done his successors a huge favor by shooting Orville down’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Airbus, as a supplier to these businesses, has not been immune to these pressures. In the early 2000s, airliners were enthused about the ‘hub and spoke’ model. Passengers would fly on large aircraft between major hubs, then transfer to smaller aircraft for their final destinations. With a maximum capacity of over 800, the double-decker Airbus A380 would help allow airliners to consolidate their flights between busy international hubs. By the time it entered commercial operation in 2007, fashions had reversed and consumers were willing to pay a premium to fly direct. Airbus never came close to recouping its $25 billion development costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Against this backdrop, companies like Airbus and Boeing face a constant downward price pressure, operating on single digit margins in good years. The merry-go-round of buyers as airliners fall in and out of bankruptcy makes them fickle customers. With this in mind, Boeing’s desire to slash costs seems like a much more rational response, even if its execution was flawed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It may be nearly impossible to operate the multi-billion dollar, multi-decade product development cycle this industry requires without some form of government backstop, whether it is a direct subsidy (Airbus) or reliable military orders (Boeing).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is a business that is well-suited to subsidy for other reasons too. Governments are generally better at supporting companies in established markets where innovation takes place slowly and incrementally. This is likely why state-backed efforts have found it easier to be competitive against aerospace companies than Silicon Valley giants working at breakneck pace to keep pace with changing consumer tastes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can learn from Airbus’s engineering ingenuity and relentless customer focus. But its success in such an idiosyncratic sector probably isn’t as template for successful industrial policy in many of the other sectors that some people would like it to be.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://worksinprogress.co/issue/how-airbus-took-off/"/><published>2025-11-09T01:19:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862071</id><title>IRIX Introduction</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:50.490611+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd3c131148cca9cc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;IRIX Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Brief History&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first operating system developed for SGI systems ran on the IRIS line of terminals and workstations based on Motorola CPUs (see GL2 history). When the MIPS based IRIS 4D systems were introduced the 4D1 operating system accompanied these computers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The earliest common version is 4D1-3.0 (1988). IRIX 3.x was based on UNIX System V Release 3 with 4.3BSD enhancements, and incorporated the 4Sight windowing system, based on NeWS and IRIS GL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next major version (4D1-4.0) was introduced in 1991. SGI replaced 4Sight with the X Window System (X11R4), using Xsgi and the 4Dwm window manager providing a similar look and feel to 4Sight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the next version was introduced, the name IRIX was more widely used. IRIX 5.0, released in 1993, incorporated certain features of UNIX System V Release 4, including ELF-format executables. Later on in the IRIX 5 lifecycle the XFS journaling file system was introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beginning with IRIX 6.0, released in 1994 during the IRIX 5 era, full 64-bit support was added. After a few platform specific releases with IRIX 6.5 the last "major" all platform release was introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last IRIX release is IRIX 6.5.30, introduced in August 2006. The IRIX product line was discontinued after this version, according to the press release dated September, 6th 2006 support for IRIX will continue at least until December 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Main Versions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To decide which IRIX version is suitable for a system it is important to know specific information about the computer itself:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Which system family is it (O2, Indy, Origin 2000, ...)?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Which processor is installed?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Which graphics hardware is in it (if any)?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Are there options that require specific drivers?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another thing to note is that there are platform specific releases, that were made when some new hardware was introduced. These usually don't support all hardware that was available at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This chapter will go on with an introduction to most important all platform IRIX releases. It will conclude with a paragraph containing some considerations and recommendations for the choice of ann appropriate IRIX version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Major Versions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of all IRIX releases the following are the most important:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;IRIX 5.3&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;IRIX 5.3 was the last IRIX version to include support for systems with R3000 CPU. So this is the most recent operating system that can be installed on 4D era systems (Personal Iris, PowerSeries and so on).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;IRIX 6.2&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;Of the 6.x releases IRIX 6.2 was the first release that did support all current hardware of it's time. Although all of this hardware (except the Crimson) is still supported in the current 6.5 releases IRIX 6.2 can still be a reasonable choice for lowend configurations of Indigo, Indigo 2 or Indy (pre 1996).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;IRIX 6.5.22&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;This version is the last to support many of the popular Silicon Graphics classics like the Indigo 2 or Indy which are equipped with R4x00 microprocessors..&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;IRIX 6.5.30&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;IRIX 6.5.30 is the final IRIX release and is suitable for any of the last Silicon Graphics systems that were equipped with MIPS microprocessors (O2, Octane, Fuel, etc.).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Operating System Considerations and Recommendations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following list starts with current systems and goes back to the early IRIS 4D days (for hardware information go to the systems page. In a similar fashion for all the listed systems the most recent operating system will be named, followed by exceptions that make it neccessary to choose an older version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;O2, O2+, Octane, Octane 2,Fuel&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;All of these systems can run a current IRIX 6.5 release.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Origin 200, Origin 2000, Onyx 2, Origin 300, Onyx 300,Origin 3000, Onyx 3000&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;All of these systems can run a current IRIX 6.5 release.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Indigo 2, Challenge M&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;All Indigo 2 / Challenge M can run IRIX 6.5 up to 6.5.22. &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;RAM &amp;lt; 64MB: IRIX 6.2&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;CPU R4000/100: IRIX 6.2&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;Indy, Challenge S&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;All Indy / Challenge S can run IRIX 6.5 up to 6.5.22. &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;RAM &amp;lt; 64MB: IRIX 6.2&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;CPU R4000PC, R4600PC: IRIX 6.2&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-5"&gt;Challenge, Onyx&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-5"&gt;All of these systems can run IRIX 6.5 up to 6.5.22.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-6"&gt;Indigo&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-6"&gt;Indigo with R4x00 CPUs can run IRIX 6.5 up to 6.5.22.&lt;lb/&gt;Indigo with R3x00 CPUs are limited to IRIX 5.3.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-7"&gt;Crimson&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-7"&gt;All Crimson systems can run up to IRIX 6.2, with the following exception: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;GTX graphics: IRIX 5.3 (last version to support GTX)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-8"&gt;PowerSeries&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-8"&gt;All of these systems can run up to IRIX 5.3.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-9"&gt;Personal Iris&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-9"&gt;All of these systems can run up to IRIX 5.3.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-10"&gt;Professional Iris&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-10"&gt;All of these systems can run up to IRIX 5.3, with the following exception: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;G graphics: IRIX 4.0.5 (last version to support G graphics)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pictures&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;IRIX Media / Media Kits&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Developer Toolbox&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Support Advantage&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Indyzone&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Other&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;IRIX 3.3 Screenshots&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;IRIX 4.0.1 Screenshots&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;IRIX 5.3 Screenshots&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;IRIX 6.5 Screenshots&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Cyclone Software&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Technical Reports and White Papers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;IRIX 6.1 Technical Report [local copy]&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;IRIX 6.2 Technical Report [local copy]&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cellular IRIX 6.4 Technical Report [local copy]&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;XFS White Paper [local copy]&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="http://www.sgistuff.net/software/irixintro/index.html"/><published>2025-11-09T01:33:43+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862470</id><title>Tabloid: The Clickbait Headline Programming Language</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:50.439118+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="5205455d1cce1ea4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oops, please turn on JavaScript to enjoy Tabloid :)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://tabloid.vercel.app/"/><published>2025-11-09T02:53:45+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862500</id><title>Show HN: Geofenced chat communities anyone can create</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:49.959326+00:00</updated><link href="https://vicinity.social/"/><published>2025-11-09T02:59:58+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862591</id><title>Syntax and Semantics of Programming Languages (1995)</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:49.432021+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f3a56b95473fa4a0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Syntax and Semantics of Programming Languages Chapter 1 Chapter 2 Chapter 3 Chapter 4 Chapter 5 Chapter 6 Chapter 7 Chapter 8 Chapter 9 Chapter 10 Chapter 11 Chapter 12 Chapter 13 Appendix A Appendix B Title Pages Preface Table of Contents Bibliography Index Acrobat (pdf) viewers To Ken Slonneger's Home Page&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://homepage.cs.uiowa.edu/~slonnegr/plf/Book/"/><published>2025-11-09T03:15:33+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862674</id><title>Boring Company fined nearly $500K after it dumped drilling fluids into manholes</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:49.050633+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="36c83412eabaf286"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Elon Musk’s Boring Company fined nearly $500K after it dumped drilling fluids into Las Vegas manholes—then ‘feigned compliance’ and was caught doing it again&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A county environmental regulator has fined Boring Company, Elon Musk’s tunneling venture, nearly $500,000 after the company dumped “drilling fluids” into manholes around Las Vegas, which led to “substantial damage” to the broader county’s infrastructure, according to a notice of violation sent to the company last week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clark County Water Reclamation District (CCWRD) claims that, this summer, Boring Company employees refused to stop dumping drilling fluids when inspectors arrived at its project site near the center of town and directed them to stop, according to the violation. The next day, Boring apparently “feigned compliance” only to continue dumping the wastewater after a company manager “assumed district inspectors had departed the property,” according to a cease-and-desist letter. CCWRD says that its crews ultimately had to clean 12 cubic yards of “drilling mud, drilling spoils, and miscellaneous solid waste” from one of its sewage treatment facilities due to Boring’s discharges across two of its project sites, according to the notice of violation, which was obtained by Fortune via a records request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The drilling fluids and spoils noted in the citation appear to refer to the toxic liquid that collects in the bottom of the tunnels as Boring’s machinery drills through earth and rock—liquid which can contain a variety of chemicals including MasterRoc AGA 41S. Many Boring workers have gotten burned by these chemicals when their skin was directly exposed to them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new fines and allegations are the latest controversy to flare up around Boring Company. The company has on several occasions been accused by employees and regulators of skirting safety protocols or regulations as it constructs a network of tunnels below Las Vegas that the company says will serve as an “underground highway” for Teslas to zip through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Clark County water agency said that Boring Company’s actions had violated federal laws and regulations, and told Boring it was issuing $493,297.08 in fines, including $131,297.08 for the district’s expenses to remedy the fluid dumping. CCWRD said the fine was due to “the egregious nature of the violations, the substantial damage to district infrastructure, the district emergency resources expended responding to the Violations, and [Boring Company’s] acknowledgement of responsibility for the Violations,” according to the notice of violation. CCWRD has only issued a fine greater than $100,000 to one other company for wastewater discharge in the last three years, according to other documents obtained by Fortune in a separate records request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The violation records show that several Boring Company executives attended a hearing with CCWRD at the end of September and that Boring Company acknowledged responsibility and agreed not to expand Boring’s operations to new drilling locations “until certain conditions were met.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Boring Company did not respond to multiple requests for comment. A spokeswoman for the Las Vegas Convention and Visitors Authority, which pays Boring to operate the tunnel system below the Convention Center, said the agency was still reviewing the documents and declined to comment further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CCWRD says the agency began to look into the dumpings after an anonymous complaint that was sent to the state’s environmental regulator on Aug. 12. Inspectors at CCWRD went out to the project site and confirmed that drilling fluids and spoils were “actively” being discharged into two on-site cleanouts (capped pipe fittings that connect to sewer lines), as well as into two manholes, and that there was “extensive damage to the District’s infrastructure” as a result, according to the documents. CCWRD says that “TBC staff refused” to stop dumping the fluids when inspectors told them to stop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next day, on Aug. 14, inspectors returned and again instructed Boring Company employees to stop discharging. CCWRD says that Boring’s superintendent, Filippo Fazzino, “feigned compliance” and removed connections to on-site cleanouts, but the regulators says that he immediately replaced them “after he assumed District inspectors had departed the Property,” according to a cease-and-desist letter that was sent to Boring later that day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Notably, Mr. Fazzino attempted to minimize the extent of the discharge by falsely claiming that the discharge was initiated only the night before—contrary to the District’s inspection records from the day prior. TBC’s brazen refusal to stop its illicit discharges after being caught in the act, coupled with TBC’s representative’s false statements to District inspectors, proves TBC’s activities to be knowing and intentional,” the cease-and-desist letter wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fazzino did not respond to multiple requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a letter Boring sent to CCWRD Aug. 15, the day after the second inspection, Boring’s director of legal affairs acknowledged that “water was improperly discharged to the sewer system,” that it was investigating the matter, and that the company had taken certain actions as a result, including physically disconnecting certain sewage connections and sealing leaks in its tunnels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One current Boring Company employee, who spoke with Fortune on the condition of anonymity for fear of reprisal, confirmed that, while the company is required under county rules to pretreat water and fluids before disposing of it, Boring Co. workers were pumping it directly into the sewage system without pretreating it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Founded in 2017, the Boring Company is a lower-profile venture in Musk’s empire of moonshots, though no less ambitious than his rocket startup SpaceX or brain chip operation Neuralink. The idea for Boring is to eliminate traffic by digging tunnels below cities that can shuttle passengers with autonomous Teslas. Boring has raised more than $900 million in funding from some of Silicon Valley’s top investment firms such as Sequoia Capital, according to PitchBook, though it has struggled with delays and employee safety incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Boring has made the most progress in Nevada, where a 4-mile stretch underneath the Las Vegas Convention Center is currently the lone working example of Musk’s vision. But the company has had several brushes with regulators in the state. In September, Nevada’s Bureau of Water Pollution Control fined the company nearly $250,000 for violating environmental regulations nearly 800 times in the last two years, including for spilling untreated groundwater onto public roads and not reporting it to authorities, ProPublica first reported. Boring had previously entered into a settlement agreement in 2022 with the regulator for similar violations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In June 2023, Boring Co. exposed the foundations of two pillars supporting Las Vegas’s elevated monorail while searching for an irrigation pipe, Fortune reported in April 2024. Regulators ordered the active monorail to temporarily halt operations for a day, with Boring workers exposing the base of another column a few months later. Clark County issued three violations related to the two incidents, accusing Boring Co. of doing work without a permit and creating a potential hazard. (Boring Company, at the time, didn’t respond to a request for comment. The LVCVA said that “TBC was fixing a broken irrigation line and inadvertently exposed a Monorail foundation, so we took the correct steps to repair that, including pausing operations for a day.”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Boring has also dealt with investigations from Nevada’s Occupational Safety and Health Administration, including eight citations in 2023 that Boring is still contesting. According to those citations, many employees have been burned by the chemicals in the liquid that pools up in Boring’s tunnels. (Boring is disputing these violations and will defend itself in an upcoming hearing)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are you a current or former Boring Company employee with thoughts on this topic? Have a tip to share? Contact Jessica Mathews at jessica.mathews@fortune.com or jessica.m101@proton.me, or through the secure messaging app Signal at jessica_mathews.36. You can also contact her on LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More coverage from Fortune on the Boring Co.:&lt;lb/&gt;—Tunneling halted at Boring Company job site in Las Vegas after ‘crushing injury’ of worker reported&lt;lb/&gt;—The CEO of the Las Vegas agency behind Boring Company’s first tunnel system says his team will be ‘more involved’ after safety incidents&lt;lb/&gt;—‘We have consistently flirted with death’: Elon Musk wanted the Boring Co. to build a tunnel system below Las Vegas. Former employees say they feared for their lives while working there&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This story was originally featured on Fortune.com&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/articles/elon-musk-boring-company-fined-150000426.html"/><published>2025-11-09T03:32:46+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862802</id><title>Reverse engineering Codex CLI to get GPT-5-Codex-Mini to draw me a pelican</title><updated>2025-11-09T06:44:48.892833+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bc2fcf3649af53d8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Reverse engineering Codex CLI to get GPT-5-Codex-Mini to draw me a pelican&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;9th November 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenAI partially released a new model yesterday called GPT-5-Codex-Mini, which they describe as "a more compact and cost-efficient version of GPT-5-Codex". It’s currently only available via their Codex CLI tool and VS Code extension, with proper API access "coming soon". I decided to use Codex to reverse engineer the Codex CLI tool and give me the ability to prompt the new model directly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I made a video talking through my progress and demonstrating the final results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;This is a little bit cheeky&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Codex CLI is written in Rust&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Iterating on the code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Let’s draw some pelicans&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bonus: the --debug option&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;This is a little bit cheeky&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenAI clearly don’t intend for people to access this model directly just yet. It’s available exclusively through Codex CLI which is a privileged application—it gets to access a special backend API endpoint that’s not publicly documented, and it uses a special authentication mechanism that bills usage directly to the user’s existing ChatGPT account.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I figured reverse-engineering that API directly would be somewhat impolite. But... Codex CLI is an open source project released under an Apache 2.0 license. How about upgrading that to let me run my own prompts through its existing API mechanisms instead?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This felt like a somewhat absurd loophole, and I couldn’t resist trying it out and seeing what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Codex CLI is written in Rust&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The openai/codex repository contains the source code for the Codex CLI tool, which OpenAI rewrote in Rust just a few months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t know much Rust at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I made my own clone on GitHub and checked it out locally:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone git@github.com:simonw/codex
cd codex&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then I fired up Codex itself (in dangerous mode, because I like living dangerously):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;codex --dangerously-bypass-approvals-and-sandbox&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And ran this prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Figure out how to build the rust version of this tool and then build it&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This worked. It churned away for a bit and figured out how to build itself. This is a useful starting point for a project like this—in figuring out the compile step the coding agent gets seeded with a little bit of relevant information about the project, and if it can compile that means it can later partially test the code it is writing while it works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the compile had succeeded I fed it the design for the new feature I wanted:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Add a new sub-command to the Rust tool called “codex prompt”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;codex prompt “prompt goes here”—this runs the given prompt directly against the OpenAI API that Codex uses, with the same code path and authentication credentials as the rest of Codex.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;codex prompt -m &amp;lt;model_name&amp;gt; “prompt goes here”—same again but lets you set the model&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;codex prompt “prompt goes here” -s/--system “system prompt goes here”—runs with a custom system/developer message&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;codex prompt --models—this lists all available models that can be used with the “codex prompt” command&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My design for this new sub-command is lifted directly from my own llm command.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Iterating on the code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Codex got to work. I’ve shared the full transcript here (using the tool I described here), but this TODO list it made itself is a useful summary of what it decided to do:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Updated Plan
└ ✔ Inspect CLI structure and relevant core utilities for sending prompts and listing models
  ✔ Implement new `codex prompt` subcommand (CLI plumbing + command handler)
  ✔ Format, lint, and test (`just fmt`, `just fix -p codex-cli`, `cargo test -p codex-cli`)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I like that it figured out the justfile in the repo and decided to use it to run formatting and linting commands without me needing to tell it to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried running the first version of the code it wrote like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;./target/debug/codex prompt 'Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle' -m gpt-5-codex-mini&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;... and it didn’t quite work. I got this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(reasoning summary) **Seeking
(reasoning summary)  instructions
(reasoning summary)  and
(reasoning summary)  sandbox
(reasoning summary)  info
(reasoning summary) **
(reasoning summary) **Dec
(reasoning summary) iding
(reasoning summary)  on
(reasoning summary)  SVG
(reasoning summary)  creation
(reasoning summary)  approach
(reasoning summary) **
(reasoning summary) **Checking
(reasoning summary)  current
(reasoning summary)  directory
(reasoning summary) **
(reasoning summary) **Preparing
(reasoning summary)  to
(reasoning summary)  check
(reasoning summary)  current
(reasoning summary)  directory
(reasoning summary) **
I�m ready to help�what would you like me to do next?I�m ready to help�what would you like me to do next?
Token usage: total=2459 input=2374 cached_input=0 output=85 reasoning_output=64
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that it DID think about SVG creation, but then decided it should look at the current directory. This isn’t what I want—it appeared to be running in Codex’s normal mode with a system prompt telling it to edit files on disk. I wanted it to respond to the prompt without acting as if it had a full workspace available to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I prompted it again, pasting in the broken output:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;this did not seem to work—here is what happened—note that the reasoning summary comes out on a lot of lines when I would rather it streams out to stderr on the same line (flushing constantly)—and then despite the reasoning summary thinking about pelican on SVG it did not actually act on that and display the result, which is very surprising. [pasted content]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It churned for a bit more, but from the output it looked like it was still trying to include Codex-specific tools and workspace information. So I said:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note that this new ’codex prompt’ command should NOT be able to execute any tools at all, and should not have to think about the workspace or sandbox—it should send a single prompt with no tools and then stream and display a response and then stop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This got me a new build, but when I ran it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Error: unexpected status 400 Bad Request: {"detail":"Instructions are not valid"}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My guess is that OpenAI’s custom backend API for Codex doesn’t like it if you attempt to call it without passing in the expected instructions. Fair enough!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rather than paste that error in I got Codex to try the command itself, so it could see the error:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You try running this and see what happens: ./target/debug/codex prompt ’Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Codex switched back to the default instructions. From its reply:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;code&gt;cli/src/prompt_cmd.rs#L1-L320&lt;/code&gt;now forces a tool-free request: we keep the workspace defaults, inject a lightweight system/developer message (“don’t run tools”), disable apply_patch/web search via config overrides, and build the outbound prompt as just that system span plus the user text.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I guess that will have to do. I asked for one more feature:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Add a --debug option to the codex prompt command which causes the full JSON request and response to be printed to stderr, plus the URL that is being accessed and the HTTP verb&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;... and we’re ready to try this thing out!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably I haven’t written a single line of Rust myself here and paid almost no attention to what it was actually doing. My main contribution was to run the binary every now and then to see if it was doing what I needed yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve pushed the working code to a prompt-subcommand branch in my repo if you want to take a look and see how it all works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Let’s draw some pelicans&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the final version of the code built, I drew some pelicans. Here’s the full terminal transcript, but here are some highlights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is with the default GPT-5-Codex model:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;./target/debug/codex prompt "Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I pasted it into my tools.simonwillison.net/svg-render tool and got the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I ran it again for GPT-5:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;./target/debug/codex prompt "Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle" -m gpt-5&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And now the moment of truth... GPT-5 Codex Mini!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;./target/debug/codex prompt "Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle" -m gpt-5-codex-mini&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t think I’ll be adding that one to my SVG drawing toolkit any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Bonus: the --debug option&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had Codex add a &lt;code&gt;--debug&lt;/code&gt; option to help me see exactly what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;./target/debug/codex prompt -m gpt-5-codex-mini "Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle" --debug&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The output starts like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;[codex prompt debug] POST https://chatgpt.com/backend-api/codex/responses
[codex prompt debug] Request JSON:
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "model": "gpt-5-codex-mini",
  "instructions": "You are Codex, based on GPT-5. You are running as a coding agent ...",
  "input": [
    {
      "type": "message",
      "role": "developer",
      "content": [
        {
          "type": "input_text",
          "text": "You are a helpful assistant. Respond directly to the user request without running tools or shell commands."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "type": "message",
      "role": "user",
      "content": [
        {
          "type": "input_text",
          "text": "Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "tools": [],
  "tool_choice": "auto",
  "parallel_tool_calls": false,
  "reasoning": {
    "summary": "auto"
  },
  "store": false,
  "stream": true,
  "include": [
    "reasoning.encrypted_content"
  ],
  "prompt_cache_key": "019a66bf-3e2c-7412-b05e-db9b90bbad6e"
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This reveals that OpenAI’s private API endpoint for Codex CLI is &lt;code&gt;https://chatgpt.com/backend-api/codex/responses&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also interesting is how the &lt;code&gt;"instructions"&lt;/code&gt; key (truncated above, full copy here) contains the default instructions, without which the API appears not to work—but it also shows that you can send a message with &lt;code&gt;role="developer"&lt;/code&gt; in advance of your user prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/"/><published>2025-11-09T04:02:47+00:00</published></entry></feed>