<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:19.182901+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46579864</id><title>The struggle of resizing windows on macOS Tahoe</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:33.415505+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="164e58dfa3c7bbf5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lot has already been said about the absurdly large corner radius of windows on macOS Tahoe. People are calling the way it looks comical, like a child’s toy, or downright insane.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setting all the aesthetic issues aside – which are to some extent a matter of taste – it also comes at a cost in terms of usability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since upgrading to macOS Tahoe, I’ve noticed that quite often my attempts to resize a window are failing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This never happened to me before in almost 40 years of using computers. So why all of a sudden?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It turns out that my initial click in the window corner instinctively happens in an area where the window doesn’t respond to it. The window expects this click to happen in an area of 19 × 19 pixels, located near the window corner.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the window had no rounded corners at all, 62% of that area would lie inside the window:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But due to the huge corner radius in Tahoe, most of it – about 75% – now lies outside the window:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Living on this planet for quite a few decades, I have learned that it rarely works to grab things if you don’t actually touch them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I instinctively try to grab the window corner inside the window, typically somewhere in that green area, near the blue dot:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And I assume that most people would also intuitively expect to be able to grab the corner there. But no, that’s already outside the accepted target area:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, for example, grabbing it here does not work:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But guess what – grabbing it here does:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So in the end, the most reliable way to resize a window in Tahoe is to grab it outside the corner – a gesture that feels unnatural and unintuitive, and is therefore inevitably error-prone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://noheger.at/blog/2026/01/11/the-struggle-of-resizing-windows-on-macos-tahoe/"/><published>2026-01-11T20:47:55+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46580136</id><title>FUSE is All You Need – Giving agents access to anything via filesystems</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:33.164002+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="678b289beab4cee0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Giving agents access to a sandboxed environment with a shell and a filesystem has been the latest hype when it comes to agentic harnesses. Recent examples of this include:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Turso’s AgentFS&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anthropic’s Agent SDK, which brings Claude Code’s harness to non-coding domains&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vercel rebuilding their text-to-SQL agent on top of a sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anthropic’s Agent Skills for filesystem-based progressive disclosure&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The argument for why this is good goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The big labs are doing heavy RL for coding tasks in these kinds of environments. Aligning more closely with such a harness brings free gains from the coding domain to other problem spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond that, replacing a bunch of search/write/move/list tools with a single Bash tool reduces the tool space significantly. Agents can chain operations together intuitively. Unix paradigms give you good tool design for free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On top of that there is more nice patterns that emerge from having a filesystem, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Plan/scratch files: Agents can create temporary files to organize their thoughts, track progress, or store intermediate results. This emerges naturally from having filesystem access, no need to design a separate “notepad” tool.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Long context handling: As conversations grow, you can compact old messages and tool results into files on the filesystem. The agent can re-read them when needed rather than keeping everything in context.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So the advantages are clear. But how do you actually apply this to your domain? This is where things get tricky. Consider two examples:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A domain with parallels to filesystems: For example an agent for organizing emails. There are folders, items (emails), and you can browse them and move things around.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;An existing platform that already looks like a filesystem: For example an agent inside Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you try to fit these into a sandboxed filesystem you might wonder:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When do I copy over the files?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Do I copy over everything?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How do I write back updates that the agent made?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When do I sync edits made by a human?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How do I show folders/files progressively as the agent progresses? (Particularly useful if you want to lean into the filesystem as a tool to manage long context.)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A reply to a recent post on X from Vercel about building filesystem-based agents puts it well:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This article doesn’t really answer that question though.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;They explain the shape of the filesystem really well, but the missing piece is still the main question for existing apps: how do you actually materialize Postgres + object storage + APIs into that sandbox FS in a practical and scalable way? “Preload files” is hand-wavy without a recommended ingestion/snapshot pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post will show a pattern to close that gap: turning anything into a filesystem with the help of FUSE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;An example: Email agent&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make this tangible, let’s build a fictional agent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Imagine we’re building an AI-powered email platform, think Gmail but with AI on top. We have our own database storing emails, folders, and contacts. We have a UI that users interact with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we want to add a powerful agent on top of that platform. We could build a simple agent loop with tools like &lt;code&gt;list-emails&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;move-email&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;read-email&lt;/code&gt;, but as we established there’s a more ergonomic approach: put our emails in a filesystem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After some thinking, we come up with the following file layout for the agent’s sandbox:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;workspace/
  Inbox/
    Customer Inquiry - Size Chart (emily.wolfe@gmail.com)
    PO Confirmation #2026-0038 (supplierC@fabricdirect.com)
    Shipping Delay Notice (supplierA@logisticsco.com)
    Partnership Proposal - TrendCircle (marketing@trendcircle.io)

  Starred/
    Wholesale Inquiry - SilverLeaf Boutique (boutique@silverleaf.co)
    Re: Restock ETA For Red Jackets (supplierA@logisticsco.com)

  Needs_Action/
    Missing Documents - Customs (carrier-support@airbridge.co)
    Last Call: VAT Filing Deadline (gov-tax@tradeportal.gov)

  Orders/
    2026/
      Feb/
        PO Confirmation #2026-0038 (supplierC@fabricdirect.com)
        Shipping Delay Notice (supplierA@logisticsco.com)

  Customers/
    Returns/
      Return Request #8743 (john.hartley@yahoo.com)

  Sent/
    Re: Customer Inquiry - Size Chart (emily.wolfe@gmail.com)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now comes the problem: we need to bridge the gap from our database to the sandboxed filesystem that the agent uses to consume our data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to turn anything into a FS, enter FUSE&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FUSE stands for Filesystem in Userspace. It’s a framework that lets you implement filesystems outside the kernel, while the kernel makes it look like a ‘real’ filesystem to the rest of Linux. You just write a userland process that implements the actual filesystem logic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A FUSE filesystem needs to implement a small, well-defined interface: &lt;code&gt;lookup&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;open&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;write&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;readdir&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;create&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;unlink&lt;/code&gt;, etc. Whenever the OS interacts with the mounted filesystem, operations get forwarded to your userspace implementation. This indirection makes it possible to expose arbitrary data structures as if they were files.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are wrappers and bindings for higher-level languages that let you write these filesystems in the language and tech stack of your choice. No need to dive into C :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Architecture&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coming back to our email agent, here’s how FUSE would fit into a very high-level architecture:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The top row shows the traditional path: users interact with your app through a UI that talks to a backend, which reads and writes to a database.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bottom row shows the agent path: the agent runs inside a sandbox and sees a mounted filesystem. When it does &lt;code&gt;ls /workspace/Inbox&lt;/code&gt;, that call hits the FUSE layer, which translates it into a query against the same backend. The agent and your users are looking at the same data through different interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can think of the filesystem as a UI layer for the agent. Just like your frontend decides how to present data to users, your FUSE implementation decides how to present data to the agent. Realistically you’ll have additional tools for actions that don’t map well to filesystem operations (like sending an email), but for browsing, reading, and organizing data, the filesystem abstraction works great.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For this blog post we’ll keep things simple: the agent loop and FUSE implementation both run inside a Docker container, talking directly to a database. We are going to implement this in Typescript using the fuse-native library. In production you’d want to structure things a bit differently, like running the agent loop outside the sandbox and have your FUSE bindings be only a thin client that calls out to your backend with proper authentication for example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Implementing the filesystem operations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make our data accessible via the filesystem, we need to implement the subset of FUSE operations relevant for our use case. Let’s start with listing directories (&lt;code&gt;readdir&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;export async function readdir(path: string, cb: (err: number, names?: string[]) =&amp;gt; void) {
  const [folder] = await db.select().from(foldersTable).where(eq(foldersTable.path, path));

  if (!folder) {
    return cb(Fuse.ENOENT);
  }

  const emailsInFolder = await db.select({
    email: emailsTable,
    sender: contactsTable,
  }).from(emailsTable)
  .leftJoin(contactsTable, eq(emailsTable.sender, contactsTable.id))
  .where(eq(emailsTable.folderId, folder.id));


  const entries = new Set&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;();

  for (const {email, sender} of emailsInFolder) {
    entries.add(`${email.subject} (${sender.email}).eml`);
  }

  const subfolders = await db.select().from(foldersTable).where(like(foldersTable.path, sql`${path}/%`));
  for (const subfolder of subfolders) {
    entries.add(subfolder.path.split("/").pop() || "");
  }

  cb(0, Array.from(entries));
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We match which email folder we’re in based on the filesystem path, list all emails inside that folder, and add any subfolders. Together with implementing &lt;code&gt;getattr&lt;/code&gt; (to get file attributes), this makes listing and navigating the folder tree via &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To choose how email content will be represented we implement &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;export async function read(path: string, fd: number, buf: Buffer, len: number, pos: number, cb: (err: number) =&amp;gt; void) {
  const email = await getEmailById(fd);
  if (!email) {
    return cb(Fuse.ENOENT);
  }
  const content = emailToContent(email);
  const slice = content.slice(pos, pos + len);
  const bytesRead = buf.write(slice);
  cb(bytesRead);
}

export function emailToContent(email: EmailWithSender): string {
  return `From: ${email.senderEmail}
Date: ${email.sentAt.toISOString()}
Subject: ${email.subject}
X-Folder: ${email.folderPath}
X-Starred: ${email.starred}
X-Needs-Action: ${email.needsAction}

${email.body}
`;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are a few more operations I implemented like &lt;code&gt;open&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mkdir&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;rename&lt;/code&gt; to allow moving email files around and reassigning folder IDs in the database.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On top of that, I introduced the concept of virtual folders—the &lt;code&gt;Starred&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Needs_Action&lt;/code&gt; folders in the layout above. They work like this: if an email has the starred or needsAction flag set, it appears in these folders. Because an email can be both starred and part of an actual folder, the Starred folder contains symlinks to the “actual” files. The agent can unlink these files or create new links to flip attributes on the email. This might be overkill and better covered via regular tools, but I wanted to see how far I could lean into the filesystem abstraction. For this to work, I implemented additional FUSE operations: &lt;code&gt;readlink&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;symlink&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;unlink&lt;/code&gt;, and adjusted the existing ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deciding how to map your domain to a filesystem is really a context engineering challenge in the end. The key is finding the right balance between leveraging familiar filesystem semantics and not over-abstracting to the point where the mapping becomes confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With all the filesystem operations defined, we’re ready to mount it and see it in action. While it’s possible to get this working on a Mac via macFUSE, I chose the easier path and spun up a Docker container and mounted the filesystem there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s a quick demo of navigating the filesystem. As you can see, it looks and works just like regular files.&lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mv&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; all behave as expected. The best part? There’s no risk of anything going out of sync because we read directly from the database. We also only load the things we needed when they are accessed instead of preloading our entire database into a sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Giving the agent access to it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we have the filesystem working, it’s time to hook up an agent and see how it performs. I used the Anthropic Agent SDK to whip up a quick filesystem agent with tools to run Bash, Read, Glob, etc. To give the agent some context about the filesystem, I added the following system prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You are an email assistant helping the user manage their inbox.

You have access to a filesystem at /workspace representing their email:

- Folders: Inbox, Sent, Orders, Customers, etc.
- Emails: .eml files named "Subject (sender@email.com).eml"
- Filenames contain spaces (from email subjects), so always quote paths in shell commands
- Starred/Needs_Action: contain symlinks to flagged emails

Commands you use internally:
- ls, cat, find → browse emails
- mv → move emails between folders
- ln -s &amp;lt;email&amp;gt; /Starred/ → star an email
- rm /Starred/&amp;lt;email&amp;gt; → unstar an email
- mkdir → create folders

When responding to the user:
- Describe emails by subject and sender, not filenames
- Say "starred" not "created symlink"
- Say "moved to Orders" not "mv to /Orders/"
- Summarize what you found/did in plain language
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see how it approaches some common user queries:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; which emails do i have in my Inbox?

I'll check your Inbox to see what emails you have.

[Bash] ls -la /workspace/Inbox/

You have 6 emails in your Inbox:

1. **"Missing Documents - Customs"** from carrier-support@airbridge.co (Jan 4)
2. **"PO Confirmation #2026-0038"** from supplierC@fabricdirect.com (Jan 9)
3. **"Partnership Proposal - TrendCircle"** from marketing@trendcircle.io (Jan 7)
4. **"Re: Restock ETA For Red Jackets"** from supplierA@logisticsco.com (Jan 5)
5. **"Shipping Delay Notice"** from supplierA@logisticsco.com (Jan 8)
6. **"Wholesale Inquiry - SilverLeaf Boutique"** from boutique@silverleaf.co (Jan 6)

Would you like me to read any of these emails or help you organize them?
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; find the email about that wholesale inquiry, i need to remember to follow up on it

I'll help you find the wholesale inquiry email. Let me search for it.

[Bash] find /workspace -type f -name "*.eml" -exec grep -l "wholesale" {} \;

Found it! There's a wholesale inquiry from SilverLeaf Boutique (boutique@silverleaf.co) in your Inbox.

Would you like me to:
1. Star it so you can easily find it later to follow up?
2. Move it to a specific folder?
3. Show you the email content?

&amp;gt; show me the email and star it

[Read] /workspace/Inbox/Wholesale Inquiry - SilverLeaf Boutique (boutique@silverleaf.co).eml

[Bash] ln -s "/workspace/Inbox/Wholesale Inquiry - SilverLeaf Boutique (boutique@silverleaf.co).eml" /workspace/Starred/

Here's the email:

**From:** boutique@silverleaf.co
**Date:** January 6, 2026
**Subject:** Wholesale Inquiry - SilverLeaf Boutique

**Message:**
"We're a boutique in Portland and interested in carrying your line. What are your wholesale terms?"

Good news - this email is already starred! It looks like it was already flagged for follow-up. SilverLeaf Boutique is interested in carrying your products and wants to know about your wholesale terms.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; Organize my Inbox

I'll help you organize your inbox. Let me first see what emails you have there.

[Bash] ls -la /workspace/Inbox/

Now let me check what folders you already have set up:

[Bash] ls -d /workspace/*/

Perfect! I can see you have 8 emails in your inbox. Let me organize them into appropriate folders:

[Bash] mv "/workspace/Inbox/Customer Inquiry - Size Chart (emily.wolfe@gmail.com).eml" /workspace/Customers/
[Bash] mv "/workspace/Inbox/Wholesale Inquiry - SilverLeaf Boutique (boutique@silverleaf.co).eml" /workspace/Customers/
[Bash] mv "/workspace/Inbox/PO Confirmation #2026-0038 (supplierC@fabricdirect.com).eml" /workspace/Orders/
[Bash] mv "/workspace/Inbox/Re: Restock ETA For Red Jackets (supplierA@logisticsco.com).eml" /workspace/Orders/
[Bash] mv "/workspace/Inbox/Shipping Delay Notice (supplierA@logisticsco.com).eml" /workspace/Orders/
Now let me flag the urgent items that need action:
[Bash] ln -s "/workspace/Inbox/Last Call: VAT Filing Deadline (gov-tax@tradeportal.gov).eml" /workspace/Needs_Action/
[Bash] ln -s "/workspace/Inbox/Missing Documents - Customs (carrier-support@airbridge.co).eml" /workspace/Needs_Action/

Good - those urgent items are already flagged. Now let me check if the partnership proposal might be something to consider:

[Bash] cat "/workspace/Inbox/Partnership Proposal - TrendCircle (marketing@trendcircle.io).eml"

Let me create a folder for business opportunities and move the partnership proposal there:

[Bash] mkdir -p /workspace/Business_Opportunities &amp;amp;&amp;amp; mv "/workspace/Inbox/Partnership Proposal - TrendCircle (marketing@trendcircle.io).eml" /workspace/Business_Opportunities/

Let me verify your inbox is now organized:

[Bash] ls /workspace/Inbox/

Perfect! I've organized your inbox. Here's what I did:

**Moved to Customers folder (2 emails):**
- Customer Inquiry - Size Chart from emily.wolfe@gmail.com
- Wholesale Inquiry - SilverLeaf Boutique from boutique@silverleaf.co

**Moved to Orders folder (3 emails):**
- PO Confirmation #2026-0038 from supplierC@fabricdirect.com
- Re: Restock ETA For Red Jackets from supplierA@logisticsco.com
- Shipping Delay Notice from supplierA@logisticsco.com

**Moved to new Business_Opportunities folder (1 email):**
- Partnership Proposal - TrendCircle from marketing@trendcircle.io

**Left in Inbox (2 urgent items - already flagged):**
- Last Call: VAT Filing Deadline from gov-tax@tradeportal.gov ⚠️
- Missing Documents - Customs from carrier-support@airbridge.co ⚠️

The two remaining emails in your inbox are urgent items that need your immediate attention - they're already flagged in your Needs_Action folder.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s pretty cool to see how the agent just navigates through the filesystem given the task and a minimal system prompt. We didn’t spend any time on tool design. We just mapped our domain to a filesystem and got intuitive tool behavior for free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Outlook&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find the full implementation on GitHub: https://github.com/Jakob-em/agent-fuse to play around with yourself. I also might write a follow up to this post about evaling this approach vs a traditional agent loop to see if this way of building agents brings any measurable gains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In general there is a lot more potential for virtual filesystems for context engineering. You could include old conversations as files on the filesystem, or make old tool call results appear as files after compacting context. The possibilities are endless, and as long as coding agents remain relevant, this way of designing context will only get more ergonomic for models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My prediction is that one of the many sandbox providers will come up with a nice API on top of this that lets you do something like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;new Agent({
    tool: [...]
	sandbox: {
        filesystem: {
            '/emails': (folder) =&amp;gt; listEmails(folder),
            '/old_conversations': () =&amp;gt; listOldConversations(),
        }
	 }
    }
})
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No worrying about FUSE, the sandbox, where things are executed, etc. This will be a huge differentiator and make virtual filesystems easily accessible to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://jakobemmerling.de/posts/fuse-is-all-you-need/"/><published>2026-01-11T21:12:45+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46580326</id><title>CLI agents make self-hosting on a home server easier and fun</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:32.923212+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="762701d57926a862"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CLI agents make self-hosting on a home server easier and fun&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by Jordan Fulghum, January 2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've wanted to self-host at home for years, but I always bounced off it - too much time spent configuring instead of using. It just wasn't fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That changed recently, because CLI agents like Claude Code make self-hosting on a cheapo home server dramatically easier and actually fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the first time I would recommend it to normie/software-literate people who never really wanted to sign up to become a sysadmin and stress about uptime of core personal services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three things converged:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Cheap, capable mini PCs&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;You can buy a silent, low-power Linux box for less than $500&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tailscale&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Simple, secure, private networking&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Claude Code&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Install the CLI agent directly on the box, and you no longer need to remember or look-up Docker syntax, Compose quirks, or config formats&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So instead of Googling things like “docker compose vaultwarden caddy reverse proxy” and piecing together a bunch of old blog posts, I just ran Claude Code directly on the machine and let it sort it out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I previously ran my Plex server on an M1 Mac mini, which was great, but as I wanted to add more services I found myself running a lot of resource-hungry VMs (via UTM) and it was getting complicated anytime the Mac rebooted. So, I picked up a Beelink Mini N150. It is small, quiet, and just barely sips power. I paid around $379 for the device and another few hundred USD for 8TB in NVMe SSD. It's pretty wild how accessible these mini PCs have become in recent years!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Install Linux&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Flash USB, install Ubuntu Server (I picked 22.04 LTS)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Install Tailscale&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Get it on your private network to make your life easier&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SSH in&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;From my laptop, anywhere&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Install Claude Code&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;On the server itself&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ask for what I want&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Go get a coffee&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've been using Claude Code and other agentic CLIs for my day-to-day development, but as others are realizing, they are generalized computer agents and native to the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I installed Claude Code directly on the Linux box. Then I asked it things like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I explained the outcome I wanted and let Claude Code take care of the details and implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I focused on things I already used, but wanted more control over - effectively starting to knock down the walled garden around my core services like passwords, photos, media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Service&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;What it replaces or does&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Vaultwarden&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bitwarden, but self-hosted and fast&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Plex&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Media server - PSA get Plex Pass to unlock hardware-accelerated transcoding&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Immich&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Google Photos replacement&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Uptime Kuma&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Simple service monitoring&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Caddy&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Reverse proxy with automatic TLS&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Home Assistant&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Home automation hub&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Readeck&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Read-it-later. Honestly blown away by this one!&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each one lives in its own container.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can access everything from my phone, laptop, and tablet like it is local.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When something goes down, I get an email. When it comes back up, another email.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vaultwarden is a Bitwarden-compatible password manager written in Rust. Lightweight, reliable, and you can use the existing Bitwarden clients (like native apps and browser extensions). You can even set it as the default password manager on iOS, at the OS level!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once that was running, I exported my passwords from iCloud/Keychain, imported them easily into Vaultwarden, and haven't looked back since.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Immich is a Google Photos replacement. I thought I'd have to compromise and flinched a bit when I installed it. But nope, it's good. Mobile apps. Face recognition via a local (but slow) machine learning thread. Timeline and map view. Automatic uploads from your photo roll.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the kind of thing that used to feel fragile and half-baked when self-hosted. It does not anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla killed Pocket. I needed a replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I took a bet on Readeck. The UI is genuinely good. Clean typography, nice reading experience, good mobile support. It always remembers where I stopped reading and takes me right there. I even set up a shortcut that allows me to save an article for later right from mobile Firefox. Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is exactly the kind of thing self-hosting is perfect for. A small, personal tool that you actually use every day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I initially installed Lazydocker and Glances for monitoring. Uptime Kuma works pretty good. Still, it's so easy now to ask: why not do better? I asked Claude to build a single-page monitoring dashboard. It one-shotted it, building a local web app in Go and Svelte (what do I care?) that monitors the status and links out to each service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, I have always wanted a redundant local + remote backup system for my irreplaceable media - namely my photos going back about 25 years now. I plugged in an old USB drive to the Beelink, told Claude to backup to the drive daily, and it was done seconds later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, I created a new IAM user in the AWS dashboard, installed the AWS CLI on the server, and asked Claude to backup to S3 weekly. On its own, it suggested Glacier Deep storage, which would run me about twenty cents per month for half a terabyte of photos. A minute or two later, I had remote backups, complete with monitoring + logs from the dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The feeling of ownership is powerful, but a bit hard to describe. I think you just have to try it, and I hope you get a strong feeling of independence like I have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When something breaks, I SSH in, ask the agent what is wrong, and fix it. When I want to add something new, I describe it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am spending time using software, learning, and having fun - instead of maintaining it and stressing out about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is for people who:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If that is you, I would encourage you to try self-hosting this year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the first time, I would say this is not just viable. It's fun!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow me on Twitter for more.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://fulghum.io/self-hosting"/><published>2026-01-11T21:29:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46580703</id><title>The next two years of software engineering</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:32.747385+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bdd0b127eb273644"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Next Two Years of Software Engineering&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;January 5, 2026&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The software industry sits at a strange inflection point. AI coding has evolved from autocomplete on steroids to agents that can autonomously execute development tasks. The economic boom that fueled tech’s hiring spree has given way to an efficiency mandate: companies now often favor profitability over growth, experienced hires over fresh graduates, and smaller teams armed with better tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, a new generation of developers is entering the workforce with a different calculus: pragmatic about career stability, skeptical of hustle culture, and raised on AI assistance from day one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What happens next is genuinely uncertain. Below are five critical questions that may shape software engineering through 2026, with two contrasting scenarios for each. These aren’t really predictions, but lenses for preparation. The goal is a clear roadmap for handling what comes next, grounded in current data and tempered by the healthy skepticism this community is known for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;1. The Junior developer question&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bottom line: Junior developer hiring could collapse as AI automates entry-level tasks, or rebound as software spreads into every industry. Both futures require different survival strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The traditional pathway of “learn to code, get junior job, grow into senior” is wobbling. A Harvard study of 62 million workers found that when companies adopt generative AI, junior developer employment drops by about 9-10% within six quarters, while senior employment barely budges. Big tech hired 50% fewer fresh graduates over the past three years. As one engineer cynically put it: ~”Why hire a junior for $90K when an AI coding agent costs less?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t just AI. Macro factors like rising interest rates and post-pandemic corrections hit around 2022, before AI tools became widespread. But AI has accelerated the trend. A single senior engineer with AI assistance can now produce what used to require a small team. Companies are quietly not hiring juniors more than they’re firing anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The flip scenario: AI unlocks massive demand for developers across every industry, not just tech. Healthcare, agriculture, manufacturing, and finance all start embedding software and automation. Rather than replacing developers, AI becomes a force multiplier that spreads development work into domains that never employed coders. We’d see more entry-level roles, just different ones: “AI-native” developers who quickly build automations and integrations for specific niches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Bureau of Labor Statistics still projects ~15% growth in software jobs from 2024 to 2034. If businesses use AI to expand output rather than strictly cut headcount, they’ll need humans to seize the opportunities AI creates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The long-term risk of the pessimistic scenario is often overlooked: today’s juniors are tomorrow’s senior engineers and tech leaders. Cut off the talent pipeline entirely and you create a leadership vacuum in 5-10 years. Industry veterans call this the “slow decay”: an ecosystem that stops training its replacements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What to do about it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Junior developers: Make yourself AI-proficient and versatile. Demonstrate that one junior plus AI can match a small team’s output. Use AI coding agents (Cursor/Antigravity/Claude Code/Gemini CLI) to build bigger features, but understand and explain every line if not most. Focus on skills AI can’t easily replace: communication, problem decomposition, domain knowledge. Look at adjacent roles (QA, DevRel, data analytics) as entry points. Build a portfolio, especially projects integrating AI APIs. Consider apprenticeships, internships, contracting, or open source. Don’t be “just another new grad who needs training”; be an immediately useful engineer who learns quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Senior developers: Fewer juniors means more grunt work landing on your plate. Lean on automation for routine tasks, but don’t do everything yourself. Set up CI/CD, linters, and AI-assisted testing to catch basic issues. Mentor unofficially through open source or coaching colleagues in other departments. Be frank with management about the risks of all-senior teams. If junior demand rebounds, be ready to onboard effectively and delegate in ways that use AI. Your value is in multiplying the whole team’s output, not just your own code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;2. The Skills question&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bottom line: Core programming skills could atrophy as AI writes most code, or become more critical than ever as human developers focus on oversight. The coming years determine whether we trade understanding for speed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;84% of developers now use AI assistance regularly. For many, the first instinct when facing a bug or new feature isn’t to write code from scratch, but to compose a prompt and stitch together AI-generated pieces. Entry-level coders are skipping the “hard way”: they might never build a binary search tree from scratch or debug a memory leak on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The skillset is shifting from implementing algorithms to knowing how to ask the AI the right questions and verify its output. The first rung of the ladder now demands prompting and validating AI rather than demonstrating raw coding ability. Some senior engineers worry this produces a generation who can’t code well independently, a kind of deskilling. AI-generated code introduces subtle bugs and security vulnerabilities that less-experienced developers might miss.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The counter-scenario: as AI handles the routine 80%, humans focus on the hardest 20%. Architecture, tricky integrations, creative design, edge cases: the problems machines alone can’t solve. Rather than making deep knowledge obsolete, AI’s ubiquity makes human expertise more important than ever. This is the “high-leverage engineer” who uses AI as a force multiplier but must deeply understand the system to wield it effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If everyone has AI coding agent access, what distinguishes great developers is knowing when the AI is wrong or suboptimal. As one senior engineer put it: “The best software engineers won’t be the fastest coders, but those who know when to distrust AI.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programming shifts: less typing boilerplate, more reviewing AI output for logical errors, security flaws, and mismatches with requirements. Critical skills become software architecture, system design, performance tuning, and security analysis. AI can produce a web app quickly, but an expert engineer ensures the AI followed security best practices and didn’t introduce race conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developer discourse in 2025 was split. Some admitted they hardly ever write code “by hand” and think coding interviews should evolve. Others argued that skipping fundamentals leads to more firefighting when AI’s output breaks. The industry is starting to expect engineers to bring both: AI speed and foundational wisdom for quality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What to do about it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Junior developers: Use AI as a learning tool, not a crutch. When AI coding agents (Cursor/Antigravity/Claude Code/Gemini CLI) suggest code review why it works, identify weaknesses. Occasionally disable your AI helper and write key algorithms from scratch. Prioritize CS fundamentals: data structures, algorithms, complexity, memory management. Implement projects twice, once with AI, once without, and compare. Learn prompt engineering and tool mastery. Train yourself in rigorous testing: write unit tests, read stack traces without immediately asking AI, get comfortable with debuggers. Deepen complementary skills AI can’t replicate: system design, user experience intuition, concurrency reasoning. Show you can both crank out solutions with AI and tackle thorny issues when it fails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Senior developers: Position yourself as the guardian of quality and complexity. Sharpen your core expertise: architecture, security, scaling, domain knowledge. Practice modeling systems with AI components and think through failure modes. Stay current on vulnerabilities in AI-generated code. Embrace your role as mentor and reviewer: define where AI use is acceptable and where manual review is mandatory (payment or safety code). Lean into creative and strategic work; let the junior+AI combo handle routine API hookups while you decide which APIs to build. Invest in soft skills and cross-domain knowledge. Stay current on new tools and best practices. Double down on what makes a human developer indispensable: sound judgment, system-level thinking, and mentorship.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3. The Role question&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bottom line: The developer role could shrink into limited auditing (overseeing AI-generated code) or expand into a pivotal orchestrator position designing and governing AI-driven systems. Either way, adding value means more than just coding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The extremes here are stark. In one vision, developers see their creative responsibilities diminished. Rather than building software, they mostly audit and babysit AI outputs. AI systems (or “citizen developers” using no-code platforms) handle production; human developers review auto-generated code, check for errors, bias, or security issues, and approve deployments. Maker becomes checker. The joy of code creation replaced by the anxiety of risk management.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are reports of engineers spending more time evaluating AI-generated pull requests and managing automated pipelines, less time crafting code from scratch. Programming feels less like creative problem-solving and more like compliance. As one engineer lamented: “I don’t want to end up as a code janitor, cleaning up what the AI throws over the wall.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The alternative future is far more interesting: developers evolve into high-level orchestrators, combining technical, strategic, and ethical responsibilities. AI “workers” mean human developers take on an architect or general contractor role, designing the overall system, deciding which tasks go to which AI or software component, weaving solutions from many moving parts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A CEO of a low-code platform articulated this vision: in an “agentic” development environment, engineers become “composers,” orchestrating ensembles of AI agents and software services. They won’t write every note themselves, but they define the melody: architecture, interfaces, how agents interact. This role is interdisciplinary and creative: part software engineer, part system architect, part product strategist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The optimistic take: as AI handles rote work, developer roles shift toward higher-value activities by necessity. Jobs may become more interesting. Someone has to decide what the AI should build, verify the product makes sense, and continuously improve it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which way it goes may depend on how organizations choose to integrate AI. Companies that see AI as labor replacement might trim dev teams and ask remaining engineers to keep automations running. Companies that see AI as a way to amplify their teams might keep headcounts similar but have each engineer deliver more ambitious projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What to do about it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Junior developers: Seek opportunities beyond just writing code. Volunteer for test case writing, CI pipeline setup, or application monitoring: skills aligned with an auditor/custodian role. Keep your creative coding alive through personal projects so you don’t lose the joy of building. Develop a systems mindset: learn how components communicate, what makes APIs well-designed. Read engineering blogs and case studies of system designs. Familiarize yourself with AI and automation tools beyond code generation: orchestration frameworks, AI APIs. Improve communication skills, written and verbal. Write documentation as if explaining to someone else. Ask senior colleagues not just “Does my code work?” but “Did I consider the right things?” Prepare to be verifier, designer, and communicator, not just coder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Senior developers: Lean into leadership and architectural responsibilities. Shape the standards and frameworks that AI and junior team members follow. Define code quality checklists and ethical AI usage policies. Stay current on compliance and security topics for AI-produced software. Focus on system design and integration expertise; volunteer to map data flows across services and identify failure points. Get comfortable with orchestration platforms (Kubernetes, Airflow, serverless frameworks, agent orchestration tools). Double down on your role as technical mentor: more code reviews, design discussions, technical guidelines. Hone your ability to quickly assess someone else’s (or something’s) code and give high-level feedback. Develop product and business sense; understand why features get built and what customers care about. Shadow a product manager or join customer feedback sessions. Protect your creative passion through prototypes, hackathons, or emerging tech research. Evolve from coder to conductor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;4. The Specialist vs. Generalist question&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bottom line: Narrow specialists risk finding their niche automated or obsolete. The fast-changing, AI-infused landscape rewards T-shaped engineers: broad adaptability with one or two deep skills.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given how quickly models, tools and frameworks rise and fall, betting your career on a single technology stack is risky. A guru in a legacy framework might suddenly find themselves in less demand when a new AI tool handles that tech with minimal human intervention. Developers who specialize narrowly in “a single stack, framework or product area” might wake up to find that area declining or redundant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think of COBOL developers, Flash developers, or mobile game engine specialists who didn’t pivot when the industry moved. What’s different now is the pace of change. AI automation can make certain programming tasks trivial, undercutting roles that revolved around those tasks. A specialist who only knows one thing (fine-tuning SQL queries, slicing Photoshop designs into HTML) could find AI handling 90% of that work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hiring managers chase the newest niche. A few years ago everyone wanted cloud infrastructure specialists; now there’s a surge in AI/ML engineers. Those who specialized narrowly in yesterday’s technology feel stalled as that niche loses luster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The opposite outcome is specialization in a new form: the “versatile specialist” or T-shaped developer. Deep expertise in one or two areas (the vertical stroke), broad familiarity with many others (the horizontal stroke). These engineers become the “glue” in multidisciplinary teams; they communicate with specialists of other stripes and fill gaps when needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Companies no longer want developers who are either too shallow or too narrowly focused; they want a strong core competency plus ability to work across the stack. Part of the reason is efficiency: a T-shaped engineer can often solve problems end-to-end without waiting on handoffs. Part is innovation: cross-pollination of knowledge leads to better solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI tools actually augment generalists more, making it easier for one person to handle multiple components. A back-end engineer can rely on AI help to create a reasonable UI; a front-end specialist can have AI generate server boilerplate. An AI-rich environment lets people operate more broadly. Meanwhile, deep specialists might find their niche partly automated with no easy way to branch out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nearly 45% of engineering roles now expect proficiency in multiple domains: programming plus cloud infrastructure knowledge, or front-end plus some ML familiarity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What to do about it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Junior developers: Establish a broad foundation early. Even if hired for a specific role, peek outside that silo. If you’re doing mobile, learn backend basics; if you’re doing front-end, try writing a simple server. Learn the deployment process and tools like Docker or GitHub Actions. Identify one or two areas that genuinely excite you and go deeper: this becomes your vertical expertise. Brand yourself as a hybrid: “full-stack developer with cloud security focus” or “frontend developer with UX expertise.” Use AI tools to learn new domains quickly; when you’re a novice in backend, have ChatGPT generate starter API code and study it. Build the habit of continuous re-skilling. Participate in hackathons or cross-functional projects to force yourself into generalist mode. Tell your manager you want exposure to different parts of the project. Adaptability is a superpower early in your career.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Senior developers: Map your skill graph: what are you expert in, what related domains have you only touched superficially? Pick one or two adjacent domains and commit to becoming conversant. If you’re a back-end database specialist, get comfortable with a modern front-end framework or learn ML pipeline basics. Do a small project in your weak area with AI assistance. Integrate your deep expertise with new contexts; if you specialize in web app performance, explore how those skills apply to ML inference optimization. Advocate for or design your role to be more cross-functional. Volunteer to be the “integration champion” for projects touching multiple areas. Mentor others to spread skills around while picking up something from them in return. Update your resume to reflect versatility. Use your experience to identify patterns and transferable knowledge. Become the T-shaped role model: deep in your specialty (giving authority and confidence) but actively stretching horizontally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;5. The Education question&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bottom line: Will a CS degree remain the gold standard, or will faster learning paths (bootcamps, online platforms, employer training) overtake it? Universities may struggle to keep up with an industry that changes every few months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A four-year computer science degree has long been the primary ticket into software roles. But that tradition is being questioned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One future: universities remain important but struggle to stay relevant. Degrees stay the default credential, but programs lag behind rapidly evolving needs, hampered by slow curriculum update cycles and bureaucratic approval processes. Students and employers feel academia is disconnected from industry, teaching theory or outdated practice that doesn’t translate to job skills.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recent grads report never learning about cloud computing, modern DevOps, or AI tooling during their degree. If universities demand high time and financial investment while delivering low-relevance education, they risk being seen as expensive gatekeepers. But many companies still require a bachelor’s degree out of inertia, so the burden shifts to students to fill the gap with bootcamps, online courses, and self-taught projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Student loan debt is enormous, and companies spend billions training new grads because those grads lack skills needed in the workplace. Universities might add an AI ethics class here, a cloud computing elective there, but by the time they implement something, industry tools have moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The disruptive scenario: traditional education gets increasingly replaced by new systems. Coding bootcamps, online certifications, self-taught portfolios, employer-created training academies. Many high-profile employers (Google, IBM) have dropped degree requirements for certain technical roles. In 2024, nearly 45% of companies planned to eliminate bachelor’s degree requirements for at least some positions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bootcamps have matured. They produce grads who get hired at top companies alongside CS grads. These programs are shorter (12-week intensive) and focus on practical skills: current frameworks, cloud services, teamwork. The hiring currency is shifting toward live portfolios, micro-credentials, and verified skills. A strong GitHub portfolio or recognized certification can bypass degree requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Employer-driven education is emerging: companies creating their own training pipelines or partnering with bootcamps. Some big tech companies have started internal “universities” for non-traditional candidates. AI itself offers new ways to learn: AI tutors, interactive coding sandboxes, personalized instruction outside university settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A modular ecosystem of learning is far more accessible than an expensive four-year degree. A kid in a country without strong CS universities can take the same Coursera courses and build the same portfolio as someone in Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What to do about it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aspiring/junior developers: If in a traditional CS program, don’t rely on it exclusively. Augment coursework with real-world projects: build a web app, contribute to open source. Seek internships or co-ops. If your curriculum misses hot topics, learn them through online platforms. Earn industry-recognized certifications (GCP, AWS, Azure) to signal practical knowledge. If self-teaching or in a bootcamp, focus on a compelling portfolio: at least one substantial project with good documentation. Be active in the developer community: contribute to open source, write technical posts. Network through LinkedIn, meetups, dev events. Get an experienced developer to vouch for you. Keep learning continuously; the half-life of technical skills is short. Use AI as your personal tutor. Prove your skills in concrete ways: portfolio, certification, and ability to talk intelligently about your work will open doors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Senior developers and leaders: Your credential alone won’t carry you forever. Invest in continuous education: online courses, workshops, conferences, certifications. Validate your skills in new ways; be prepared for interviews that assess current competency through real problems. Maintain side projects with new tech. Reassess job requirements: do you really need a new hire to have a CS degree, or do you need certain skills and learning ability? Push for skills-first hiring to widen your talent pool. Support internal training programs or apprenticeship-style roles. Champion mentorship circles for junior devs without formal backgrounds. Engage with academia and alternatives: advisory boards, guest lectures, feedback on curriculum gaps. Reflect this in your own career growth: real-world achievements and continuous learning matter more than additional degrees.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Through-Line&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These scenarios aren’t mutually exclusive. Reality will draw elements from all of them. Some companies will reduce junior hiring while others expand it in new domains. AI will automate routine coding while raising standards for the code humans touch. Developers might spend mornings reviewing AI outputs and afternoons crafting high-level architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The consistent thread: change is the only constant. By keeping a finger on technology trends (and skepticism around them), you avoid being caught off-guard by hype or doom. By updating skills, diversifying abilities, and focusing on uniquely human aspects (creativity, critical thinking, collaboration) you remain in the loop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether the future brings a coding renaissance or a world where code writes itself, there will always be demand for engineers who think holistically, learn continuously, and drive technology toward solving real problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The best way to predict the future is to actively engineer it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://addyosmani.com/blog/next-two-years/"/><published>2026-01-11T22:00:24+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46580864</id><title>This game is a single 13 KiB file that runs on Windows, Linux and in the Browser</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:32.236996+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="249721123c2d08f0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;This game is a single 13 KiB file that runs on Windows, Linux and in the Browser.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not that long ago I became aware of Justine Tunneyâs cosmopolitan libc project. Itâs a toolkit that allows you to compile C source code into a single binary that runs natively on multiple operating systems, including Windows, Linux, various flavours of BSD, even including booters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, back then the project didnât seem to support GUI interfaces and produces quite swollen binaries. Hence I decided to take a stab at a similar (simpler? harder? up to you to decide) challenge: create a video game (&amp;lt;16 KiB) that runs natively on Windows, Linux and in the Browser, all from a single source file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Gameâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs a pretty standard Snake game with the same rules and interface on all platforms. You control a snake that grows longer as it eats food, and the goal is to avoid running into walls. The snake is controlled using either the arrow keys or WASD keys. It can be terminated via &lt;code&gt;ESC&lt;/code&gt; (if permissible by the platform), reset via &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;, and paused via &lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;. Spacebar starts the game.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game keeps track of your score. Each piece of food eaten increases your score by 10 points, except yellow fruit (which spawns with a 15% chance) that gives you 20 points. Fruit spawns at a fixed rate and despawns after a certain time if not eaten. The despawn timer is proportional to the speed of the snake at the time of spawning, which itself is proportional to the snakeâs length.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once ten fruit are eaten, the game proceeds to the next level, randomizing the wallsâ layout. The maze is created as to ensure that there is always a path from the snakeâs head to any piece of food. The initial placement of the snake is also randomized, but always in a position that has at least five empty tiles in the direction the snake is facing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download the game here (13,772 bytes).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Polyglotâ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I implemented the game three times in total: once in C for the i686 Visual C platform using WinAPI, once in C for the x86_64 Linux platform using clang and X11, and once in JavaScript for the browser using HTML5 Canvas. Each implementation is around 3-5 KiB in size when compiled/minified.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Windows implementation was produced using a compressing script that prepends a decompressing stub. This stub has a quite unusual PE header that has many freely controllable bytes after the &lt;code&gt;MZ&lt;/code&gt; signature. This allows us to place a shell script there that skips over the remainder of the file, rendering the (valid) PE executable runnable on Windows while also making the entire file a valid shell script, that will do (thus far) nothing on Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because the PE file is so awkward, we rely on Windowsâ apphelp mechanism. Without compatibility mode, executing for the first time will yield the message:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;âThe application was unable to start correctly (0xc0000005). Click OK to close the application.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which should disappear after re-running.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Linux implementation was produced using a similar approach; we use &lt;code&gt;lzma&lt;/code&gt; for decompression and a small shell dropper that extracts the compressed ELF64 binary and runs it, skipping over the head and the tail of the file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The HTML version is also packed and abuses the fact that browsers will happily process all the benign garbage at the start of the file before reaching the actual HTML content. Then we make it invisible/unobtrusive through a bit of CSS magic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, we concatenate all three files together in such an order that each platform will pick the correct part of the file to execute. The final file is exactly 13,312 bytes in size.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://iczelia.net/posts/snake-polyglot/"/><published>2026-01-11T22:14:35+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46582762</id><title>Uncrossy</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:31.993080+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="839dee5eada74331"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes (like now) you'll need to undo a move before you can find a solution. You can find out if you're in this state by using the hint button or enabling auto-hints in the game settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We use cookies to improve your experience and analyze usage. Essential cookies enable core functionality, while analytics cookies help us understand how you use the game. Privacy questions?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://uncrossy.com/"/><published>2026-01-12T01:39:32+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46585947</id><title>Ai, Japanese chimpanzee who counted and painted dies at 49</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:31.809002+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="daf00f07e88e5641"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Ai, Japanese chimpanzee who counted and painted, dies at 49&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ai, a female chimpanzee famous for her cognitive skills has died at 49, according to the Japanese institute where she lived.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Kyoto University's Center for the Evolutionary Origins of Human Behavior said Ai died on 9 January of old age and organ failure and that she was surrounded by staff when she died.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ai was born in western Africa and arrived at the Japanese institute in 1977. There, she became the namesake of the Ai Project, a research programme into the "chimpanzee mind".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the institute's noteable findings were the fact that Ai was able to use numbers and identify colours.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers gave Ai a special keyboard linked to a computer when she was 18 months, a set-up that they used to study her memory and learning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At five years old, Ai "mastered numerical naming from one to six and was able to name the number, colour and object of 300 types of samples", according to a 1985 scientific paper by Tetsuro Matsuzawa, the primatologist behind the Ai Project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When she was not participating in cognitive tests, Ai was known to enjoy drawing and painting. Like other chimpanzees at the centre, Ai would scrawl marker pens over blank paper without having to be motivated by food rewards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Japanese media outlet Kyodo news reported that she once escaped with another primate - using a key to unlock her cage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2000 she gave birth to a son, Ayumu, who is also known for his remarkable memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2017 - the 40th anniversary of the Ai Project - a scarf made from one of Ai's paintings was gifted to renowned primatologist Dame Jane Goodall.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cj9r3zl2ywyo"/><published>2026-01-12T09:10:45+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46586179</id><title>Lightpanda migrate DOM implementation to Zig</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:31.582205+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="27599a755db603ec"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Migrating our DOM to Zig&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Karl Seguin&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Software Engineer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;TL;DR&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We replaced LibDOM with our own Zig-based DOM implementation. The original design created friction between V8, our Zig layer, and LibDOM, especially around events, Custom Elements, and ShadowDOM. After six months of spare-time prototyping, we built zigdom: a leaner, more cohesive DOM that gives us full control over memory, events, and future enhancements. We also swapped in html5ever for parsing and added V8 snapshots to cut startup time. There are single-digit % performance gains, but the real win is a unified codebase that’s easier to extend.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why We Replaced LibDOM&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At a high level, the Lightpanda codebase can be described as a Zig layer sitting between V8 and LibDOM. When JavaScript is executed, like &lt;code&gt;document.getElementById('spice')&lt;/code&gt;, V8 calls into the Zig layer which then forwards the request to the underlying LibDOM document object and then forwards the result back to V8. By using LibDOM, we gained a robust and fairly comprehensive DOM implementation with minimal effort.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, as we worked to increase compatibility with websites in the wild, we felt ever-increasing friction between our three layers. One example is the event system baked into LibDOM. This proved awkward to expand beyond DOM-based events (e.g. input events) or even just bubbling DOM events to our Zig-based Window implementation. Another larger challenge, was integrating support for Custom Elements and ShadowDOM, written in Zig, with LibDOM. Finally, there was some concern about the lack of cohesion with respect to things like memory management and how that would impact potential future changes, like better multi-threading support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we were to restart the integration from scratch, knowing what we know now, we’d probably be able to avoid most of the friction we’re currently seeing. While we do modify LibDOM as needed, one approach would be to integrate V8 and LibDOM directly, applying fixes and additions directly to LibDOM. But as we wrote before, we’re fans of Zig so the discussions and prototypes we built always leaned towards replacing LibDOM with a custom Zig implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;zigdom&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work on a prototype for having a Zig-based DOM started roughly six months ago. This was a casual in-our-spare-time effort. In the spirit of experimentation, this prototype also replaced V8 with QuickJS-NG . By mid-November, we felt the prototype had tackled enough unknowns to start integrating it into Lightpanda (with V8). Thankfully, porting features was relatively simple; commits to the &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; branch could usually be ported to the &lt;code&gt;zigdom&lt;/code&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The design is straightforward. A &lt;code&gt;Node&lt;/code&gt; has a linked list of children and an optional &lt;code&gt;_parent: ?*Node&lt;/code&gt;. Furthermore, a &lt;code&gt;Node&lt;/code&gt; has a &lt;code&gt;_type&lt;/code&gt; tagged union field to represent the type of node, and a &lt;code&gt;_proto&lt;/code&gt; field to capture its supertype:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;_type: Type,
_proto: *EventTarget,
 
const Type = union(enum) {
    cdata: *CData,
    element: *Element,
    document: *Document,
    // ...
};&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since a modern website can have tens of thousands of nodes and thousands of elements, we obviously care about the size of our &lt;code&gt;EventTarget&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Node&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Element&lt;/code&gt;. That’s why every type in our union is a pointer. That means that when we create a div, we need to allocate the Div, HTMLElement, Element, Node and EventTarget. But rather than doing five separate allocations, we do 1 large allocation for the total size and parcel it out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another area where we’ve been able to optimize for our use-case is to lazily parse/load certain properties. While a website might have thousands of elements, most JavaScript will only access the classes, styles, relLists, dataset, etc, of a few elements. Rather than having these stored on each element, even as empty lazily loaded containers, they’re attached to a page in an element -&amp;gt; property lookup. While this adds lookup overhead, it removes ~6 pointers from every element.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The real win is having a more cohesive design for events, custom elements and ShadowDOM and a simpler foundation for future enhancements. That said, performance, both in terms of memory usage and CPU load are slightly improved (both single digit % improvements).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;html5ever&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We saw benefits to writing our own DOM implementation, but not our own HTML parser. For that, we turned to servo’s html5ever written in Rust. I almost forgot to mention it in this post because the experience was so painless and worked from the get-go that I haven’t had to think about it for a while. You setup html5ever with a bunch of callbacks (for creating a node, attaching a node to a parent, creating text, etc.), feed it your HTML, and away you go. My Rust is very bad, but writing a C binding for it was manageable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Bonus - V8 Snapshot&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the porting was tedious. For a change of pace, I took time to see how we could leverage V8 snapshots. As a short summary, whenever you create a V8 environment to execute code, you have to do a lot of setup. Every type (hundreds) with all the functions and properties need to be registered with the V8 environment. For a simple page, this can represent anywhere from 10-30% of the total time. V8 snapshots let you setup a pseudo-environment upfront, extract a Snapshot (a binary blob), and use that blob to bootstrap and speedup future environments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When in debug mode, we generated the snapshot on startup. In release mode, the snapshot is generated at compile-time and embedded into the binary, reducing startup time and memory. The overall impact depends on the relative cost of setting up the environment vs processing the page. Complex websites that load hundreds of external scripts probably won’t benefit. But incremental improvements hopefully add up and, if nothing else, help balance the performance cost of new features and complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;AI Coding Agent&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was the first large feature that I developed with the aid of an AI coding agent - specifically Claude. The experience was positive, but not flawless. I’ve personally always liked participating in code reviews / PRs. I can spend hours every day reviewing PRs, so working with Claude is kind of fun for me. If reading code isn’t something you consider fun, it could be a frustrating experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was almost always impressed with the quality of code written and “understanding” that Claude exhibited. I’m only guessing here, but I have to imagine that building a DOM, something which has a very explicit specification, tons of documentation and many implementations, was an ideal task for a coding agent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, I do think this is first and foremost a code-review exercise, and the Claude CLI is lacking in that respect. When you’re trying to understand and think through a change, you need a comfortable interface that lets you navigate and access whatever context you’re missing. Anything more than a few lines becomes challenging to review, especially as it’s presented for you to accept one piece at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the end, it’s a tool that supplements my own abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s Next&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Implementing our own DOM from scratch should make it easier for us to add new features and enhancements. Something we’ve already seen with better custom element and ShadowRoot support. Much of the benefits don’t come directly from implementing a new DOM, but by simply having a more cohesive codebase. For us, expanding our usage of Zig made the most sense.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;zigdom is now merged into Lightpanda’s main branch. If you want to see how we structured the Node, Element, and event system in Zig, check out the source code on GitHub .&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Karl Seguin&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Software Engineer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Karl is a software engineer, creator of popular open-source Zig libraries like http.zig or websocket.zig. Karl has been writing about programming for years on his blog openmymind.net and is the author of Learning Zig, a series of articles to help other developers pick up the language. At Lightpanda, he works on building the core browser engine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lightpanda.io/blog/posts/migrating-our-dom-to-zig"/><published>2026-01-12T09:42:49+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46587498</id><title>Launch a Debugging Terminal into GitHub Actions</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:31.403878+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="8df881c16f002085"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Using WebRTC to launch a debugging terminal into GitHub Actions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spoiler: I made a free and open-source way to get an interactive web terminal to your GitHub Action when it fails. Try it out here: https://actions-term.gripdev.xyz/ (code 🔗) 1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think we’ve all been there, your build fails in Actions, but the script works fine locally. You now settle into a slow loop of:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Push speculative change&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;See if it worked&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was in the middle of one of these when I started thinking about how to make it better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Terminal would be great, that’s obvious, but how to make it happen? How could I make it free, and open to anyone, without costing me lots of money?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operating a service that forward traffic between a user and the Actions VM would stack up data transfer costs and take some work to scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What about a Peer-to-Peer connection? I’d recently been going deeper on how Tailscale, iroh and WebRTC use UDP Hole Punching to create Peer-to-Peer (P2P) connections between nodes without relaying traffic. 2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If that worked then my server would only need to exchange a tiny bit of information per session and hopefully cost me very little 🤞&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could I use P2P and funnel a terminal session over it? Well the Actions VM is on the internet and allows UDP outbound, so it should work!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A simple bit of scripting proved it did 🥳 With WebRTC, if the Actions VM and my local machine exchange information about their connectivity (ICE Candidates), then I could form a connection.3&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Security and Identities&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next problem is, how do you prove each end of the P2P connection is who they say they are?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s important. I want to ensure that &lt;code&gt;lawrencegripper&lt;/code&gt; can only access terminals for Actions triggered by &lt;code&gt;lawrencegripper&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The browser side is relatively easy, we can use OAuth to login via GitHub and get a verified username ✅&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the Actions VM we have OIDC, commonly used to auth from Actions to cloud providers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyone can use it though, it gives us the ability to issue a signed OIDC token from within our Action which proves:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The repo it’s running on&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The user account that triggered it&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The audience it is intended for&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enable this feature you set the following permissions in the workflow&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;    permissions:
      id-token: write&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You request a token via a REST request in the action, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;    const requestURL = process.env.ACTIONS_ID_TOKEN_REQUEST_URL;
    const requestToken = process.env.ACTIONS_ID_TOKEN_REQUEST_TOKEN;
    const SERVER_URL = 'https://actions-term.gripdev.xyz';
    const url = new URL(requestURL);
    url.searchParams.set('audience', SERVER_URL);

    const resp = await fetch(url.toString(), {
        headers: {
        Authorization: `Bearer ${requestToken}`,
        Accept: 'application/json',
        },
    });&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, when the Action calls our server, it can include this token. We can then validate it cryptographically via JWKS:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;    const githubOIDCIssuer = "https://token.actions.githubusercontent.com"
    const githubJWKSURL = "https://token.actions.githubusercontent.com/.well-known/jwks"
    // Fetch JWKS
	keySet, err := jwkCache.Get(ctx, githubJWKSURL)
	if err != nil {
		return "", "", "", fmt.Errorf("failed to fetch JWKS: %w", err)
	}

	// Parse and validate token with clock skew tolerance
	parseOpts := []jwtx.ParseOption{
		jwtx.WithKeySet(keySet),
		jwtx.WithIssuer(githubOIDCIssuer),
		jwtx.WithValidate(true),
		jwtx.WithAcceptableSkew(2 * time.Minute),
		jwtx.WithAudience(oidcExpectedAudience),
	}
	token, err := jwtx.Parse([]byte(tokenStr), parseOpts...)
	if err != nil {
		return "", "", "", fmt.Errorf("token validation failed: %w", err)
	}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Connecting the Peers (ie. Signaling Server)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point we know:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We can create a connection between two peers (Actions VM &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Users Browser) with WebRTC&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We have a way to validate the identity of both ends of the connection (OAuth and OIDC)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s left is the server to introduce the two peers 🤝 Let’s build a server to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The server doesn’t need to handle the terminal data, that goes between the two peers directly, it’s only doing introductions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the VM and Browser are connected to the server it should send each one the connection details for the other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To do this, the browser and the VM both create Server-sent events (SSE) connections, allowing the signaling server to push events to them. They prove their identities by providing their OAuth credentials or OIDC to prove their identity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The server then stores:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;	runIdToSessions            = make(map[string]*Session) // runId -&amp;gt; session
	runIdToSessionsMu          sync.RWMutex
	runIdRunnerSseClient       = make(map[string]*SSEClient) // runId -&amp;gt; SSE client (Actions VM)
	runIdRunnerSseClientsMu    sync.RWMutex
	actorToBrowserSseClients   = make(map[string][]*SSEClient) // actor -&amp;gt; list of browser SSE clients
	actorToBrowserSseClientsMu sync.RWMutex&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The server then, via SSE, sends the Actions VM connectivity details to the browser and the Browser’s connectivity details to the Actions VM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point they establish the Peer-to-Peer connection 🥳&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For bonus points, when a new Actions VM connects, I can see if a browser is open waiting and send them a notification.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;	runIdRunnerSseClientsMu.Lock()
	runIdRunnerSseClient[runId] = client
	log.Printf("SSE: Runner connected for actor %s (total clients: %d)", actor, len(runIdRunnerSseClient))
	runIdRunnerSseClientsMu.Unlock()

	// Notify browser subscribers about new session
	sess, ok := runIdToSessions[runId]
	if ok {
		notifyNewSession(sess)
	}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Displaying the Terminal&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ok, we’re close now. We have the signaling server to exchange details and then the peers have a p2p connection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What about creating a terminal and streaming the data?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WebRTC has a &lt;code&gt;datachannel&lt;/code&gt; which you push arbitrary data through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the Actions VM side we create a &lt;code&gt;pty.Shell&lt;/code&gt; and stream that data over our &lt;code&gt;datachannel (dc)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;    shell = pty.spawn(SHELL, [], {
        name: 'xterm-256color',
        cwd: process.env.GITHUB_WORKSPACE || process.cwd(),
        env: process.env as Record&amp;lt;string, string&amp;gt;,
    });

    shell.onData((shellData) =&amp;gt; {
        dc.sendMessage(shellData);
    });&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the browser we then need to display an interactive terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading around, I found the this awesome Ghostty library. It has an xterm.js compatible implementation, I hooked this up and it worked first time 🥰&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well it did.. and it didn’t, the Terminal spawned via PTY doesn’t have any idea how big our terminal in the browser (Lines and Columns) so we get some horrible rendering in the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With a bit of poking, googling and some Opus 4.5, I created a method which estimates the size of terminal, via font sizing, and converts this to a rough column / rows. Then, on establishing the P2P connection I can send a &lt;code&gt;setup&lt;/code&gt; JSON message which the Actions VM uses to start &lt;code&gt;pty.spawn&lt;/code&gt; with the right sizing for the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;We’re done, right?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not quite, at this point we have 👇&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;┌─────────────────┐                              ┌─────────────────┐
│  GitHub Runner  │◄────────────────────────────►│    Browser      │
│  (TypeScript)   │      Direct P2P (WebRTC)     │  (ghostty-web)  │
│                 │                              │                 │
└────────┬────────┘                              └────────┬────────┘
         │                                                │
         │ Register session                               │ Get sessions
         │ (OIDC Token Auth)                              │ (GitHub OAuth)
         ▼                                                ▼
         └──────────────►┌─────────────────┐◄─────────────┘
                         │     Server      │
                         │   (Go - Auth    │
                         │   &amp;amp; Discovery)  │
                         └─────────────────┘&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a lot of trust placed in the signaling server. It has to do the right thing, or it could provide access to someone else’s Actions VM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s do better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Trust vs Zero-Trust&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve mentioned already the signaling server should only connect up users with actions they’ve started.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That relies on explicit trust, from users, that I’m going to do the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if I’ve got a bug? What if someone compromises the signaling server? What if they steal the domain and run their own server on it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, then they could hook up peers that shouldn’t be connected and … do mean things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That sounds bad, lets work out how to fix that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if the &lt;code&gt;user&lt;/code&gt; provided the Actions VM with a secret, that only they know?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the P2P connection is made, the Actions VM could refuse to talk to the browser until it provides the right secret.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Secrets are cool and everything but if they’re intercepted they’re reusable, could we use a One-Time-Password (OTP) commonly used for 2FA on sites? Sure thing! Even better tools like 1Password will autofill it for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What does this flow look like? Roughly it’s 👇&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;┌─────────────────┐                              ┌─────────────────┐
│  GitHub Runner  │◄────────────────────────────►│    Browser      │
│  (TypeScript)   │      Direct P2P (WebRTC)     │  (ghostty-web)  │
└────────┬────────┘                              └────────┬────────┘
         │                                                │
         │◄───── 1. WebRTC Connection Established ───────►│
         │                                                │
         │◄─────────── 2. Browser sends OTP ────── ───────│
         │                                                │
         │  3. Runner validates OTP against secret        │
         │                                                │
         │              ┌──────────────────┐              │
         │              │  If OTP Valid:   │              │
         │──────────────│  4. Terminal     │─────────────►│
                        │     access       │
                        │     granted      │
                        └──────────────────┘&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if the signaling server is manipulated, to hook up two peers which shouldn’t be connected, the user won’t be able to execute commands unless they can provide a valid OTP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Better still the Signaling server (which I run) is never sent either the OTP or the OTP Secret used to validate each OTP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This validation happens between two peers you own (Actions VM and your Browser).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;So now we’re done?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One last thing… make the signaling server cheap to host.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to offer this for free for anyone to use. It’s a simple &lt;code&gt;go&lt;/code&gt; binary in a docker image (to make it easy to self-hosting and test locally) but it needs to live on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A while ago I’d started poking at railway.com, it’s cloud with a big billing twist, you only pay for the CPU and Memory you actually use. This felt like a great time to try it out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How is the billing different, well…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;In Azure/AWS I have to say “I want 2 CPUs and 8GB” and I pay for that regardless of what I use.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;On railway.com I say “Use up to x CPUs and y GB” then you only pay for what the service actually consumes.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note: In either Azure/AWS or Railway you still pay network egress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How does this work out for the signaling server?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Really well it’s peak memory usage so far is 20MB, racking up a mean $0.00000… you get the point. It’s not costing much, as I’m not reserving a small machine with GBs of mem to run a service needing 20MB&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even then it feels a bit wasteful running it all the time. There will be chunks of time when folks aren’t using it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was where I found a platform feature called sleeping, it’s serverless but without the pain of moving away from the docker model to some proprietary runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the service isn’t doing anything, Railway spin down the service. If someone turns up, they hold the connection for a moment while restoring the container, then send the request through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What does a cold start look like on our simple signalling server? It’s hardly recognizable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a recording, on the left you see the server is sleeping and on the right I hit the domain, there is a slight pause before the page renders ✨&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This is a personal project with no support/guarantees. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I couldn’t quite get the iroh stack to play nice in-browser so fell back to WebRTC but do want to revisit that in future. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I don’t configure a TURN/relay server so if your network doesn’t allow UDP hole punching you won’t be able to connect. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.gripdev.xyz/2026/01/10/actions-terminal-on-failure-for-debugging/"/><published>2026-01-12T12:25:27+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46587536</id><title>Ozempic reduced grocery spending by an average of 5.3% in the US</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:31.207379+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="efb58455e92147a5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Ozempic is changing the foods Americans buy&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;By Laura Reiley, Cornell Chronicle&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Americans begin taking appetite-suppressing drugs like Ozempic and Wegovy, the changes extend well beyond the bathroom scale. According to new research, the medications are associated with meaningful reductions in how much households spend on food, both at the grocery store and at restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study, published Dec. 18 in the Journal of Marketing Research, links survey data on GLP-1 receptor agonist use – a class of drugs originally developed for diabetes and now widely prescribed for weight loss – with detailed transaction records from tens of thousands of U.S. households. The result is one of the most comprehensive looks yet at how GLP-1 adoption is associated with changes in everyday food purchasing in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The headline finding is striking: Within six months of starting a GLP-1 medication, households reduce grocery spending by an average of 5.3%. Among higher-income households, the drop is even steeper, at more than 8%. Spending at fast-food restaurants, coffee shops and other limited-service eateries falls by about 8%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among households who continue using the medication, lower food spending persists at least a year, though the magnitude of the reduction becomes smaller over time, say co-authors, assistant professor Sylvia Hristakeva and professor Jura Liaukonyte, both in the Charles H. Dyson School of Applied Economics and Management in the Cornell SC Johnson College of Business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The data show clear changes in food spending following adoption,” Hristakeva said. “After discontinuation, the effects become smaller and harder to distinguish from pre-adoption spending patterns.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike previous studies that relied on self-reported eating habits, the new analysis draws on purchase data collected by Numerator, a market research firm that tracks grocery and restaurant transactions for a nationally representative panel of about 150,000 households. The researchers matched those records with repeated surveys asking whether household members were taking GLP-1 drugs, when they started and why.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That combination allowed the team to compare adopters with similar households that did not use the drugs, isolating changes that occurred after medication began.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reductions were not evenly distributed across the grocery store.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultra-processed, calorie-dense foods – the kinds most closely associated with cravings – saw the sharpest declines. Spending on savory snacks dropped by about 10%, with similarly large decreases in sweets, baked goods and cookies. Even staples like bread, meat and eggs declined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only a handful of categories showed increases. Yogurt rose the most, followed by fresh fruit, nutrition bars and meat snacks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The main pattern is a reduction in overall food purchases. Only a small number of categories show increases, and those increases are modest relative to the overall decline,” Hristakeva said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The effects extended beyond the supermarket. Spending at limited-service restaurants such as fast-food chains and coffee shops fell sharply as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The study also sheds light on who is taking GLP-1 medications. The share of U.S. households reporting at least one user rose from about 11% in late 2023 to more than 16% by mid-2024. Weight-loss users skew younger and wealthier, while those taking the drugs for diabetes are older and more evenly distributed across income groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notably, about one-third of users stopped taking the medication during the study period. When they did, their food spending reverted to pre-adoption levels – and their grocery baskets became slightly less healthy than before they started, driven in part by increased spending on categories such as candy and chocolate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That movement underscores an important limitation, the authors caution. The study cannot fully separate the biological effects of the drugs from other lifestyle changes users may make at the same time. However, evidence from clinical trials, combined with the observed reversion in spending after discontinuation, suggests appetite suppression is likely a key mechanism behind the spending changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The findings carry implications far beyond individual households.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For food manufacturers, restaurants and retailers, widespread GLP-1 adoption could mean long-term shifts in demand, particularly for snack foods and fast food. Package sizes, product formulations and marketing strategies may need to change. For policymakers and public-health experts, the results add context to ongoing debates about the role of medical treatments in shaping dietary behavior – and whether biologically driven appetite changes succeed where taxes and labels have struggled.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“At current adoption rates, even relatively modest changes at the household level can have meaningful aggregate effects,” Hristakeva said. “Understanding these demand shifts is therefore important for assessing food markets and consumer spending.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Media Contact&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Adam Allington&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get Cornell news delivered right to your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;Subscribe&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.cornell.edu/stories/2025/12/ozempic-changing-foods-americans-buy"/><published>2026-01-12T12:29:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46587804</id><title>Zen-C: Write like a high-level language, run like C</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:30.617254+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="fcf8839be8cb7a88"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zen C is a modern systems programming language that compiles to human-readable &lt;code&gt;GNU C&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;C11&lt;/code&gt;. It provides a rich feature set including type inference, pattern matching, generics, traits, async/await, and manual memory management with RAII capabilities, all while maintaining 100% C ABI compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/z-libs/Zen-C.git
cd Zen-C
make
sudo make install&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Compile and run
zc run hello.zc

# Build executable
zc build hello.zc -o hello

# Interactive Shell
zc repl&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zen C uses type inference by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;var x = 42;                 // Inferred as int
const PI = 3.14159;         // Compile-time constant
var explicit: float = 1.0;  // Explicit type
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, variables are mutable. You can enable Immutable by Default mode using a directive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;//&amp;gt; immutable-by-default

var x = 10;
// x = 20; // Error: x is immutable

var mut y = 10;
y = 20;    // OK
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;C Equivalent&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;uint&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;unsigned int&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Platform standard integer&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;I8&lt;/code&gt; .. &lt;code&gt;I128&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;int8_t&lt;/code&gt; .. &lt;code&gt;__int128_t&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Signed fixed-width integers&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;U8&lt;/code&gt; .. &lt;code&gt;U128&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;uint8_t&lt;/code&gt; .. &lt;code&gt;__uint128_t&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unsigned fixed-width integers&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;isize&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;usize&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;ptrdiff_t&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;size_t&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pointer-sized integers&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;byte&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uint8_t&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Alias for U8&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;F32&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;F64&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;float&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;double&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Floating point numbers&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;bool&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;bool&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;char&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;char&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Single character&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;C-string (null-terminated)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;U0&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;void&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;void&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Empty type&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixed-size arrays with value semantics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;var ints: int[5] = {1, 2, 3, 4, 5};
var zeros: [int; 5]; // Zero-initialized
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Group multiple values together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;var pair = (1, "Hello");
var x = pair.0;
var s = pair.1;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data structures with optional bitfields.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct Point {
    x: int;
    y: int;
}

// Struct initialization
var p = Point { x: 10, y: 20 };

// Bitfields
struct Flags {
    valid: U8 : 1;
    mode:  U8 : 3;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tagged unions (Sum types) capable of holding data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;enum Shape {
    Circle(float),      // Holds radius
    Rect(float, float), // Holds width, height
    Point               // No data
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standard C unions (unsafe access).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;union Data {
    i: int;
    f: float;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fn add(a: int, b: int) -&amp;gt; int {
    return a + b;
}

// Named arguments supported in calls
add(a: 10, b: 20);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anonymous functions that can capture their environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;var factor = 2;
var double = x -&amp;gt; x * factor;  // Arrow syntax
var full = fn(x: int) -&amp;gt; int { return x * factor; }; // Block syntax
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;if x &amp;gt; 10 {
    print("Large");
} else if x &amp;gt; 5 {
    print("Medium");
} else {
    print("Small");
}

// Ternary
var y = if x &amp;gt; 10 ? 1 : 0;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Powerful alternative to &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;match val {
    1 =&amp;gt; print("One"),
    2 | 3 =&amp;gt; print("Two or Three"),
    4..10 =&amp;gt; print("Range"),
    _ =&amp;gt; print("Other")
}

// Destructuring Enums
match shape {
    Circle(r) =&amp;gt; print(f"Radius: {r}"),
    Rect(w, h) =&amp;gt; print(f"Area: {w*h}"),
    Point =&amp;gt; print("Point")
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Range
for i in 0..10 { ... }
for i in 0..10 step 2 { ... }

// Iterator/Collection
for item in vec { ... }

// While
while x &amp;lt; 10 { ... }

// Infinite with label
outer: loop {
    if done { break outer; }
}

// Repeat
repeat 5 { ... }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Guard: Execute else and return if condition is false
guard ptr != NULL else { return; }

// Unless: If not true
unless is_valid { return; }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Operator&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Function Mapping&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Arithmetic&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;add&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;sub&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mul&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;rem&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;==&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;!=&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Comparison&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;eq&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;neq&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;lt&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;gt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;[]&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Indexing&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;get&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;??&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Null Coalescing (&lt;code&gt;val ?? default&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;??=&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Null Assignment (&lt;code&gt;val ??= init&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;?.&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Safe Navigation (&lt;code&gt;ptr?.field&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Try Operator (&lt;code&gt;res?&lt;/code&gt; returns error if present)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zen C allows manual memory management with ergonomic aids.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Execute code when the current scope exits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;var f = fopen("file.txt", "r");
defer fclose(f);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Automatically free the variable when scope exits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;autofree var types = malloc(1024);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Implement &lt;code&gt;Drop&lt;/code&gt; to run cleanup logic automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;impl Drop for MyStruct {
    fn drop(mut self) {
        free(self.data);
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Define methods on types using &lt;code&gt;impl&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;impl Point {
    // Static method (constructor convention)
    fn new(x: int, y: int) -&amp;gt; Point {
        return Point{x: x, y: y};
    }

    // Instance method
    fn dist(self) -&amp;gt; float {
        return sqrt(self.x * self.x + self.y * self.y);
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Define shared behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;trait Drawable {
    fn draw(self);
}

impl Drawable for Circle {
    fn draw(self) { ... }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; to mixin fields from another struct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct Entity { id: int; }
struct Player {
    use Entity; // Adds 'id' field
    name: string;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Type-safe templates for Structs and Functions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Generic Struct
struct Box&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; {
    item: T;
}

// Generic Function
fn identity&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(val: T) -&amp;gt; T {
    return val;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Built on pthreads.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;async fn fetch_data() -&amp;gt; string {
    // Runs in background
    return "Data";
}

fn main() {
    var future = fetch_data();
    var result = await future;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run code at compile-time to generate source or print messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;comptime {
    print("Compiling...");
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Embed files as byte arrays.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;var png = embed "assets/logo.png";
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Import compiler plugins to extend syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import plugin "regex"
var re = regex! { ^[a-z]+$ };
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pass preprocessor macros through to C.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#define MAX_BUFFER 1024
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decorate functions and structs to modify compiler behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Attribute&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Scope&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@must_use&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Warn if return value is ignored.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@deprecated("msg")&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn/Struct&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Warn on usage with message.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@inline&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hint compiler to inline.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@noinline&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Prevent inlining.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@packed&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Struct&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Remove padding between fields.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@align(N)&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Struct&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Force alignment to N bytes.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@constructor&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Run before main.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@destructor&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Run after main exits.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@unused&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn/Var&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Suppress unused variable warnings.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@weak&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Weak symbol linkage.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@section("name")&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Place code in specific section.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@noreturn&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fn&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Function does not return (e.g. exit).&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@derived(...)&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Struct&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Auto-implement traits (e.g. &lt;code&gt;Debug&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zen C provides first-class support for inline assembly, transpiling directly to GCC-style extended &lt;code&gt;asm&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write raw assembly within &lt;code&gt;asm&lt;/code&gt; blocks. Strings are concatenated automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;asm {
    "nop"
    "mfence"
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prevent the compiler from optimizing away assembly that has side effects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;asm volatile {
    "rdtsc"
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zen C simplifies the complex GCC constraint syntax with named bindings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Syntax: : out(var) : in(var) : clobber(reg)
// Uses {var} placeholder syntax for readability

fn add(a: int, b: int) -&amp;gt; int {
    var result: int;
    asm {
        "add {result}, {a}, {b}"
        : out(result)
        : in(a), in(b)
        : clobber("cc")
    }
    return result;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Syntax&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;GCC Equivalent&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Output&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;: out(var)&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;"=r"(var)&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Input&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;: in(var)&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;"r"(var)&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Clobber&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;: clobber("rax")&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;"rax"&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Memory&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;: clobber("memory")&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;"memory"&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: When using Intel syntax (via&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-masm=intel&lt;/code&gt;), you must ensure your build is configured correctly (for example,&lt;code&gt;//&amp;gt; cflags: -masm=intel&lt;/code&gt;). TCC does not support Intel syntax assembly.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zen C is designed to work with most C11 compilers. Some features rely on GNU C extensions, but these often work in other compilers. Use the &lt;code&gt;--cc&lt;/code&gt; flag to switch backends.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;zc run app.zc --cc clang
zc run app.zc --cc zig&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Compiler&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Pass Rate&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Supported Features&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Known Limitations&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GCC&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100%&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;All Features&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;None.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Clang&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100%&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;All Features&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;None.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Zig&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100%&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;All Features&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;None. Uses &lt;code&gt;zig cc&lt;/code&gt; as a drop-in C compiler.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;TCC&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~70%&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Basic Syntax, Generics, Traits&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;No &lt;code&gt;__auto_type&lt;/code&gt;, No Intel ASM, No Nested Functions.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Recommendation: Use GCC, Clang, or Zig for production builds. TCC is excellent for rapid prototyping due to its compilation speed but misses some advanced C extensions Zen C relies on for full feature support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zig's &lt;code&gt;zig cc&lt;/code&gt; command provides a drop-in replacement for GCC/Clang with excellent cross-compilation support. To use Zig:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Compile and run a Zen C program with Zig
zc run app.zc --cc zig

# Build the Zen C compiler itself with Zig
make zig&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We welcome contributions! Whether it's fixing bugs, adding documentation, or proposing new features.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fork the Repository: standard GitHub workflow.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create a Feature Branch: &lt;code&gt;git checkout -b feature/NewThing&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Code Guidelines: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Follow the existing C style.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Ensure all tests pass: &lt;code&gt;make test&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Add new tests for your feature in &lt;code&gt;tests/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Submit a Pull Request: Describe your changes clearly.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The test suite is your best friend.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Run all tests (GCC)
make test

# Run specific test
./zc run tests/test_match.zc

# Run with different compiler
./tests/run_tests.sh --cc clang
./tests/run_tests.sh --cc zig
./tests/run_tests.sh --cc tcc&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Parser: &lt;code&gt;src/parser/&lt;/code&gt;- Recursive descent parser.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Codegen: &lt;code&gt;src/codegen/&lt;/code&gt;- Transpiler logic (Zen C -&amp;gt; GNU C/C11).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Standard Library: &lt;code&gt;std/&lt;/code&gt;- Written in Zen C itself.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/z-libs/Zen-C"/><published>2026-01-12T12:57:44+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46587934</id><title>Floppy disks turn out to be the greatest TV remote for kids</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:22.059410+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2c74f8d379255ff1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Floppy Disks: the best TV remote for kids&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modern TVs are very poorly suited for kids. They require using complicated remotes or mobile phones, and navigating apps that continually try to lure you into watching something else than you intended to. The usual scenario ends up with the kid feeling disempowered and asking an adult to put something on. That something ends up on auto-play because then the adult is free to do other things and the kid ends up stranded powerless and comatose in front of the TV.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead I wanted to build something for my 3-year old son that he could understand and use independently. It should empower him to make his own choices. It should be physical and tangible, i.e. it should be something he could touch and feel. It should also have some illusion that the actual media content was stored physically and not un-understandably in “the cloud”, meaning it should e.g. be destroyable — if you break the media there should be consequences. And there should be no auto-play: interact once and get one video.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Floppy disks are awesome!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then I remembered the sound of a floppy disk. The mechanical click as you insert it, the whirr of the disk spinning, and the sound of the read-head moving. Floppy disks are the best storage media ever invented! Why else would the “save-icon” still be a floppy disk? Who hasn’t turned in a paper on a broken floppy disk, with the excuse ready that the floppy must have broken when the teacher asks a few days later? But kids these days have never used nor even seen a floppy disk, and I believe they deserve this experience!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on the experience from the Big Red Fantus-Button, I already had a framework for controlling a Chromecast, and because of the &lt;code&gt;netcat | bash&lt;/code&gt; shenanigans it was easily extendable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My first idea for datastorage was to use the shell of a floppy disk and floppy drive, and put in an RFID tag; this has been done a couple of times on the internet, such as RFIDisk or this RaspberryPi based RFID reader or this video covering how to embed an RFID tag in a floppy disk. But getting the floppy disk apart to put in an RFID tag and getting it back together was kinda wonky.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When working on the project in Hal9k someone remarked: “Datastorage? The floppy disk can store data!”, and a quick prototype later this worked really, really, well. Formatting the disk and storing a single small file, “autoexec.sh”, means that all the data ends up in track 0 and is read more or less immediately. It also has the benefit that everything can be checked and edited with a USB floppy disk drive; and the major benefit that all the sounds are completely authentic: click, whirrr, brrr brrr.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Autorun for floppy disks is not really a thing.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next problem to tackle was how to detect that a disk is inserted. The concept of AutoRun from Windows 95 was a beauty: insert a CD-ROM and it would automatically start whatever was on the media. Great for convenience, quite questionably for security. While in theory floppy disks are supported for AutoRun, it turns out that floppy drives basically don’t know if a disk is inserted until the operating system tries to access it! There is a pin 34 “Disk Change” that is supposed to give this information, but this is basically a lie. None of the drives in my possession had that pin connected to anything, and the internet mostly concurs. In the end I slightly modified the drive and added a simple rolling switch, that would engage when a disk was inserted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A floppy disk walks into a drive; the microcontroller says “hello!”&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next challenge was to read the data on a microcontroller. Helpfully, there is the Arduino FDC Floppy library by dhansel, which I must say is most excellent. Overall, this meant that the part of the project that involved reading a file from the floppy disk FAT filesystem was basically the easiest part of all!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the Arduino FDC Floppy library is only compatible with the AVR-based Arduinos, not the ESP-based ones, because it needs to control the timing very precisely and therefore uses a healthy amount of inline assembler. This meant that I would need one AVR-based Arduino to control the floppy disk, but another ESP-based one to do the WiFi communication. Such combined boards do exist, and I ended up using such a board, but I’m not sure I would recommend it: the usage is really finagly, as you need to set the jumpers differently for programming the ATmega, or programming the ESP, or connecting the two boards serial ports together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A remote should be battery-powered&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A remote control should be portable, and this means battery-powered. Driving a floppy disk of of lithium batteries was interesting. There is a large spike in current draw when the disk needs to spin up of several amperes, while the power draw afterwards is more modest, a couple of hundred milliamperes. I wanted the batteries to be 18650s, because I have those in abundance. This meant a battery voltage of 3.7V nominally, up to 4.2V for a fully charged battery; 5V is needed to spin the floppy around, so a boost DC-DC converter was needed. I used an off the shelf XL6009 step-up converter board. At this point a lot of head-scratching occurred: that initial spin-up power draw would cause the microcontroller to reset. In the end a 1000uF capacitor at the microcontroller side seemed to help but not eliminate the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One crucial finding was that the ground side of the interface cable should absolutely not be connected to any grounds on the microcontroller side. I was using a relatively simple logic-level MOSFET, the IRLZ34N, to turn off the drive by disconnecting the ground side. If any ground is connected, the disk won’t turn off. But also: if any logic pin was being pulled to ground by the ATmega, that would also provide a path to ground. But since the ATmega cannot sink that much current this would lead to spurious resets! Obvious after the fact, but this took quite some headscratching. Setting all the logic pins to input, and thus high impedance, finally fixed the stability issues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After fixing the stability, the next challenge was how to make both of the microcontrollers sleep. Because the ATmega sleep modes are quite a lot easier to deal with, and because the initial trigger would be the floppy inserting, I decided to make the ATmega in charge overall. Then the ESP has a very simple function: when awoken, read serial in, when a newline is found then send off that complete line via WiFi, and after 30 seconds signal to the ATmega that we’re sleeping, and go back to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The overall flow for the ATmega is then:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A disk is inserted, this triggers a interrupt on the ATmega that wakes up.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The ATmega resets the ESP, waking it from deep sleep.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The ATmega sends a “diskin” message over serial to the ESP; the ESP transmits this over WiFi when available.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The ATmega turns on the drive itself, and reads the disk contents, and just sends it over serial to the ESP.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Spin down the disk, go to sleep.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When the disk is ejected, send a “diskout” message over serial, resetting the ESP if needed.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Go back to 1.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The box itself is just lasercut from MDF-board. For full details see the FloppyDiskCast Git repository.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Server-side handlers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responding to those commands is still the &lt;code&gt;netcat | bash&lt;/code&gt; from the Big Red Fantus-Button, which was simply extended with a few more commands and capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;diskin&lt;/code&gt; always sends a “play” command to the Chromecast.&lt;code&gt;diskout&lt;/code&gt; always sends a “pause” command to the Chromecast.&lt;lb/&gt;Other commands like &lt;code&gt;dad-music&lt;/code&gt; are handled in one of two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Play a random video from a set, if a video from that set is not already playing: e.g. &lt;code&gt;dad-music&lt;/code&gt;will randomly play one of dad’s music tracks – gotta influence the youth!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Play the next video from a list, if a video from the list is not already playing: e.g. &lt;code&gt;fantus-maskinerne&lt;/code&gt;will play the next episode, and only the next episode.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Common for both is that they should be idempotent actions, and the &lt;code&gt;diskin&lt;/code&gt; shortcut will make the media resume without having to wait for the disk contents itself to be read and processed. This means that the “play/pause” disk just contains an empty file to work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Questionable idea meets real-world 3 year old user&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The little guy quickly caught on to the idea! Much fun was had just pausing and resuming music and his Fantus TV shows. He explored and prodded, and some disks were harmed in the process. One problem that I did solve was that the read head stayed on track 0 after having read everything: this means that when the remote with disk inside it is tumbled around, the disk gets damaged at track 0. To compensate for this, I move the head to track 20 after reading has finished: any damage is then done there, where we don’t store any data. As a bonus it also plays a little more mechanic melody.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be the first to comment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.smartere.dk/2026/01/floppy-disks-the-best-tv-remote-for-kids/"/><published>2026-01-12T13:07:49+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46588132</id><title>Windows 8 Desktop Environment for Linux</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:21.149869+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b06499d27123af91"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are one of who enjoyed the windows 8 and miss its fluid animations but have since moved to linux. And cant go back to windows 8, because all apps are non functional there. And if you can bear that you cant install it on the newer hardware. This is for you it is a shell for wayland window managers like Labwc hyprland etc. It gives a wallpaper utility, a lock screen, a start menu, an OSD for volume and brightness a settins app for wall. it dosent provide charms menu because i always thought its useless. Win8De.webm&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;one command Win8Start to show hide start menu can be bound to super of compositor.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;full drag and drop support of start tiles and sizes small medium large xlarge gui way right click.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;can drag from all apps to tiles.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;search of apps functional.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;drag app from all apps to botom to hide start screen and put icon any where that supports like desktop.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;get power menu by clicking user icon.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;have battery osd in it.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Volume up down mute&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;brightness up down.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;two part Win8OSD-server and Win8OSD-client server should be autostarted&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Win8OSD-client --volup voldown mute dispup dispdown&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;simple image wallpaper&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;settable through settins&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;windows 8 style&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;wallpaper changable by settings app&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;have nice slide down and up of lockscreen&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;dont need click and drag just click is enough unlike original&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;can change wallpaper of all 3 graphically start wall lock&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;can change accent colors and background colors of start lockscreen etc.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;./build.sh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it will build all binaries and put it in "build/bin" folder you can use it in config files to autostart and bind to system keys for brightness and volume with local location. you can't run settings from start screen bc it uses system location so you will have to run it from binary built. bind win/super key to Win8Start&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;./install.sh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it will automatically run build.sh and move the binaries to "/usr/bin/" and will be available systemwide, so it will be easier to put in configs and autostart&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;./uninstall.sh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it will remove binaries from &lt;code&gt;/usr/bin/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it will use different config file so that your current config is not affected. create a copy of config folder and paste it with diff name like labwc2 hypr2 etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;find your compositors config loading command and make a .desktop file like this example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;[Desktop Entry]&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;Name=labwc-win8&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;Comment=A wayland stacking compositor&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;Exec=labwc -C /home/user1/.config/labwc3&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;Icon=labwc&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;Type=Application&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;DesktopNames=labwc;wlroots&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and paste it in &lt;code&gt;/usr/share/wayland-sessions/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and at login choose this session.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/er-bharat/Win8DE"/><published>2026-01-12T13:22:44+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46588319</id><title>Ireland fast tracks Bill to criminalise harmful voice or image misuse</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:20.831574+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b9201773193591cf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The head of the Oireachtas committee on artificial intelligence (AI) has called on the Government to fast track a Bill that would criminalise the harmful misuse of someone’s voice or image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fianna Fáil TD Malcolm Byrne introduced the Protection of Voice and Image Bill in April, which would criminalise what are colloquially known as “deepfakes” - when someone’s voice or image is used to generate a false photo or video with AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It follows concerns over Elon Musk’s AI tool Grok being used to digitally undress women and children for distribution on his social media channel X.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The strength of laws in Ireland to criminalise AI-generated non-consensual intimate images and child sex abuse images are being examined by the Attorney General.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;READ MORE&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mr Byrne said while generating child sex abuse imagery and sharing intimate images without consent are already criminal offences, this Bill would create a new standalone criminal offence for those who “knowingly exploit another person’s name, image, voice or likeness without consent”, especially when it is done to harm to deceive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The deliberate misuse of someone’s image or voice without their consent for malign purposes should be a criminal offence. This Bill is a useful baseline and we need to move quickly to address this problem,” Mr Byrne said&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ireland’s child protection rapporteur, Caoilfhionn Gallagher, has said the harms from deep fake sexual abuse for the individuals depicted are “equivalent” to those from authentic images “because for victims the videos feel real”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ms Gallagher also questioned whether Ireland’s protections holding social media platforms to account were sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The special rapporteur on child protection was speaking on RTÉ radio’s Morning Ireland about concerns over the X platform’s Grok AI tool which includes the facility to “nudify” images.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Given how realistic they are, victims know that they might be perceived as real by others,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Generating these images is often part of a pattern of abuse or harassment. And I’m acutely conscious of the horrendous case of Nicole Coco Fox from Clondalkin, who died by suicide due to online abuse. So we know how devastating online abuse of any kind can be. We have to see this in that perspective.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ms Gallagher also raised the issue of other nudification apps being trained on vast data sets of mostly female images “because they tend to work most effectively on women’s bodies”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“As a result, 99 per cent of sexually explicit deepfakes accessible online are estimated to be of women and girls. So this is also a gender-based violence issue.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ms Gallagher added that there was concern internationally about whether the protections in place were sufficient, because most of the protections from a legal and policy perspective internationally were very focused on the users themselves who may generate the images rather than the platforms and the products which facilitate the creation of these images.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“To take the platforms themselves, in this case X AI has its own acceptable use policy and which prohibits depicting likenesses of persons in a pornographic manner, but plainly that’s completely insufficient.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ms Gallagher said Ireland’s relevant laws, including section five of the Child Trafficking and Pornography Act 1998 and Coco’s Law, were “quite focused on the individual users”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The issue here is Ireland’s not alone and internationally there is a concern about the adequacy of the mechanisms for holding the platforms to account. Ultimately, this is in part a product safety issue and about whether the product itself which allows the images to be generated should be illegal or should be regulated more tightly rather than simply the individual users who take action using it,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.irishtimes.com/ireland/2026/01/07/call-to-fast-track-bill-targeting-ai-deepfakes-and-identity-hijacking/"/><published>2026-01-12T13:38:36+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46588572</id><title>Reproducing DeepSeek's MHC: When Residual Connections Explode</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:20.718522+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f7987005e7b444d8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;DeepSeek's mHC: When Residual Connections Explode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every transformer you’ve ever used has the same residual connection design from 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPT-5, Claude, Llama, Gemini. Under the hood, they all do the same thing: . One stream of information flowing through the network, with each layer adding to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DeepSeek asked: what if it was wider?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Setup&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standard residual connections are the backbone of every modern transformer. The idea is simple:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The input flows through unchanged, plus the layer’s output. One stream of information. What goes in comes out, plus a learned update. This is why transformers can be hundreds of layers deep: the gradient has a clean path backward. Simple. Stable. Unchanged since 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hyper-Connections take a different approach. Instead of one stream, expand to n parallel streams with learnable mixing matrices:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compared to standard residual:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three matrices control how information flows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;H_res: How streams mix in the residual path (the red crossings)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;H_pre: How streams combine before entering the layer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;H_post: How the layer’s output distributes back to streams&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More expressive. More parameters with negligible computational overhead. Better performance, in theory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem? Those mixing matrices are unconstrained. They can amplify signals, not just route them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Explosion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under aggressive learning rates, Hyper-Connection (HC) signal amplification in my reproduction hit 7x before eventually collapsing. Amax (the maximum of row and column absolute sums) measures how much a matrix can amplify signals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At my 10M parameter scale, this is survivable. But DeepSeek saw this at 27B:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Amax Gain Magnitude yields extreme values with peaks of 3000”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s not a typo. Three thousand times amplification. At 27B parameters, unconstrained HC didn’t just drift. It exploded. My 10M reproduction hitting 9.2x is the early warning sign of this exponential failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is why unconstrained mixing matrices break at scale. Small amplifications compound exponentially.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Fix: Constrain the Manifold&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DeepSeek’s fix is clean: constrain the mixing matrices to be doubly stochastic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A doubly stochastic matrix has:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All non-negative entries&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rows sum to 1&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Columns sum to 1&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means the mixing operation can only take weighted averages of streams. It can route information, shuffle it, blend it. But it cannot amplify.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How? The Sinkhorn-Knopp algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The algorithm is dead simple:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Start with any matrix (the raw learned weights)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Exponentiate to make all entries positive:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Normalize rows so each row sums to 1&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Normalize columns so each column sums to 1&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Repeat steps 3-4 until convergence&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s it. Alternate row and column normalization. Twenty iterations is enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This procedure is differentiable. Gradients flow back through all twenty iterations. The network learns the raw weights , and Sinkhorn ensures the actual mixing matrix is always doubly stochastic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I first saw this, it felt like cheating. You’re not learning stability. You’re forcing it. But some properties shouldn’t be learned; they should be guaranteed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Technical note: Strictly speaking, only the recursive matrix H_res needs the full Sinkhorn doubly-stochastic treatment. It’s the one compounding errors layer-over-layer. The input/output mixers (H_pre, H_post) are just bounded via sigmoid. The Sinkhorn compute cost is paid only where it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Results&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Seed Variation Results (Depth 24, 3 seeds)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Model&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Val Loss (mean ± std)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Max Amax (mean ± std)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;HC&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;0.884 ± 0.033&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6.77 ± 0.60&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;mHC&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1.116 ± 0.012&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1.00 ± 0.00&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;HC wins on raw performance: 0.88 vs 1.12 validation loss. At 10M parameters, the mHC constraint acts like a stability tax; you pay in expressivity. But at 27B parameters, that tax is the only thing preventing your model from exploding to NaN.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But look at the variance. HC’s loss varies 3x more across seeds (±0.033 vs ±0.012). And Amax? HC swings from 6.1 to 7.6 depending on the seed. mHC is 1.00. Every seed. Every run. Zero variance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At 10M parameters, the instability is survivable. HC still wins. But at 27B parameters, that 6-7x amplification becomes 3000x. You can’t gamble at that scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Depth Scaling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also swept depths from 6 to 24 layers (constant ~11M parameter budget):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Loss improves with depth, until it doesn’t. Depth 20 hit the sweet spot (0.85 val loss). Depth 24 regressed slightly (0.93) due to the width bottleneck from shrinking dim to 192.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Amax is unpredictable. Depth 20 spiked to 9.2x. Depth 12 hit 6.6x. Depth 8 stayed at 4.3x. There’s no clean relationship; HC is chaotic.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Experiment Details&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dataset: TinyShakespeare (~1M chars, character-level) Model: GPT-2 architecture, ~10M parameters Training: 5000 steps, AdamW (β1=0.9, β2=0.95), weight decay 0.1, cosine LR decay Hardware: Apple M-series (MPS)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Depth sweep: 8 configurations (6-24 layers), width adjusted to maintain ~11M params Seed variation: 3 seeds (42, 123, 456) at depth 24&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why This Matters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Residual connections are more than a trick to help gradients flow. They’re a conservation law.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In physics, conservation laws constrain what’s possible but enable prediction. You can’t build a perpetual motion machine, but you can calculate exactly where a ball will land.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The identity mapping in residual connections is similar. It constrains the network by preventing arbitrary transformations, but it guarantees stability. Signal magnitude is preserved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;HC breaks conservation; mHC restores it, not by returning to identity, but by finding a richer manifold that still conserves signal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2016, He et al. introduced ResNets to solve the vanishing gradient problem, ensuring signals didn’t die. Ten years later, the opposite problem emerged: exploding signals from hyper-connectivity. The identity mapping solved the first by being passive. mHC solves the second by enforcing conservation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Every residual connection is a conservation law. mHC enforces it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not a hack, not a trick. A principled constraint that makes the architecture work at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Takeaways&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The stream persistence bug humbled me. My first implementation looked right. The equations matched the paper. The code ran. But I was projecting the output back to a single stream and re-expanding it at each layer, killing the parallel architecture. The “hyper” part of Hyper-Connections wasn’t actually doing anything. Three separate audits said “looks correct.” The bug was architectural, not mathematical. I only caught it by asking: “Wait, what shape is actually flowing between layers?”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Constraints aren’t limitations; they’re guarantees. The doubly stochastic projection forces stability. You’re not learning good behavior. You’re making bad behavior impossible. My first reaction: “That’s not elegant. That’s a straitjacket.” Then I saw HC hit 7x amplification. Oh. That’s the point.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The boring choice scales. Standard residual connections have survived since 2016 not because they’re optimal, but because they’re stable. HC is more expressive but fragile. mHC finds a middle ground: more expressive than standard residuals, with stability guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s Next&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is Part 1 of a two-part series.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 1 (this post): Reproduce mHC at small scale to understand the mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;10M parameters, TinyShakespeare dataset&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Constant parameter budget across depths&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Goal: Validate the core claim: HC explodes, mHC doesn’t&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 2 (Thursday): Scale up to see real instability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1B parameters on A100s&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;C4 dataset, fixed width (no bottleneck)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Goal: Push toward the 3000x Amax regime&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At 10M params, HC peaked at 9.2x amplification, chaotic but survivable. The paper saw 3000x at 27B. Part 2 will show where things break.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Resources&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paper: Manifold-Constrained Hyper-Connections (arXiv 2512.24880)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Related: Deep Residual Learning (He et al., 2016)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Code: Coming with Part 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 2 comes Thursday. Follow @TayKolasinski to catch it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://taylorkolasinski.com/notes/mhc-reproduction/"/><published>2026-01-12T13:57:32+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46588837</id><title>LLVM: The Bad Parts</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:20.592240+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3a5898176125975c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;LLVM: The bad parts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few years ago, I wrote a blog post on design issues in LLVM IR. Since then, one of these issues has been fixed fully (opaque pointers migration), one has been mostly fixed (constant expression removal), and one is well on the way towards being fixed (ptradd migration).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This time I’m going to be more ambitious and not stop at three issues. Of course, not all of these issues are of equal importance, and how important they are depends on who you ask. In the interest of brevity, I will mostly just explain what the problem is, and not discuss what possible solutions would be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, I should probably point out that this is written from my perspective as the lead maintainer of the LLVM project: This is not a list of reasons to not use LLVM, it’s a list of opportunities to improve LLVM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;High level issues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Review capacity&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike many other open-source projects, LLVM certainly does not suffer from a lack of contributors. There are thousands of contributors and the distribution is relatively flat (that is, it’s not the case that a small handful of people is responsible for the majority of contributions.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What LLVM does suffer from is insufficient review capacity. There are a lot more people writing code than reviewing it. This is somewhat unsurprising, as code review requires more expertise than writing code, and may not provide immediate value1 to the person reviewing (or their employer).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lack of review capacity makes for a bad contributor experience, and can also result in bad changes making their way into the codebase. The way this usually works out is that someone puts up a PR, then fails to get a qualified review for a long period of time, and then one of their coworkers (who is not a qualified reviewer for that area) ends up rubberstamping the PR.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A related problem is that LLVM has a somewhat peculiar contribution model where it’s the responsibility of the PR author to request reviewers. This is especially problematic for new contributors, who don’t know whom to request. Often relevant reviewers will become aware of the PR thanks to a label-based notification system, but this is not apparent from the UI, and it’s easy for PRs to fall through the cracks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A potential improvement here would be a Rust-style PR assignment system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Churn&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both the LLVM C++ API and LLVM IR are not stable and undergo frequent changes. This is simultaneously a great strength and weakness of LLVM. It’s a strength because LLVM does not stagnate and is willing to address past mistakes even at significant cost. It’s a weakness because churn imposes costs on users of LLVM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Frontends are somewhat insulated from this because they can use the largely stable C API. However, it does not cover everything, and most major frontends will have additional bindings that use the unstable C++ API.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users that integrate with LLVM more tightly (for example downstream backends) don’t have that option, and have to keep up with all API changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is part of LLVM’s general development philosophy, which I’ll express somewhat pointedly as “upstream or GTFO”. LLVM is liberally licensed and does not require you to contribute changes upstream. However, if you do not upstream your code, then it will also not factor into upstream decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This point is somewhat unlike the rest, in that I’m not sure it’s possible to make things “strictly better” here. It’s possible that LLVM’s current point on the stability scale is not optimal, but moving it somewhere else would come with significant externalities. Making major changes in LLVM is already extremely hard due to the sheer scale of the project, without adding additional stability constraints on top.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Build time&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLVM is a huge project. LLVM itself is &amp;gt;2.5 million lines of C++ and the entire monorepo is something like 9 million. C++ is not exactly known for fast build times, and compiling all that code takes time. This is bearable if you either have fast hardware or access to a build farm, but trying to build LLVM on a low-spec laptop is not going to be fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An additional complication is building with debug info (which I always recommend against), in which case you’ll add the extra gotchas of slow link times, high risk of OOM and massive disk usage. There are ways to avoid that (using shared libs or dylib build, using split dwarf, using lld), but it takes some expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Promising changes in this area are the use of pre-compiled headers (which significantly improves build time), and changing to use a dylib build by default (which reduces disk usage and link time, esp. for debuginfo builds). Another is to reduce test overhead using daemonization (not strictly part of the “build time”, but relevant for the development cycle).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;CI stability&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLVM CI consists of over 200 post-commit buildbots that test LLVM in lots of different configurations on lots of different hardware. Commits that turn a buildbot from green to red result in an email to the commit author.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this CI is never fully green, and flaky on top. This is in part due to flaky tests (typically in lldb or openmp), but can also be due to buildbot-specific issues. The end result is that it’s “normal” to get buildbot failure notifications for any given commit, even if it is perfectly harmless. This dilutes the signal, and makes it easier to miss the real failures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The introduction of pre-merge testing on PRs did significantly improve the overall CI situation, but not the buildbot problem as such. I think we need to start taking flaky tests/buildbots more seriously before we can really make progress here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because someone is definitely going to mention how this is not rocket science, and we just need to start using bors / merge queues to guarantee an always-green build: It’s a problem of scale. There are &amp;gt;150 commits on a typical workday, which would be more than one commit every 10 minutes even if they were uniformly distributed. Many buildbots have multi-hour runs. This is hard to reconcile.2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;End-to-end testing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In some respects, LLVM has very thorough test coverage. We’re quite pedantic about making sure that new optimizations have good coverage of both positive and negative tests. However, these tests are essentially unit tests for a single optimization pass or analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have only a small amount of coverage for the entire optimization pipeline (phase ordering tests), so optimizations sometimes regress due to pass interactions. Tests for the combination of the middle-end and backend pipelines are essentially nonexistent. There is likely room for improvement here, though it comes with tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, what actually concerns me are end-to-end executable tests. LLVM’s test suite proper does not feature these at all. Executable tests are located in a separate llvm-test-suite repo, which is typically not used during routine development, but run by buildbots. It contains a lot of different code ranging from benchmarks to unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, llvm-test-suite has quite few tests (compared to LLVM lit tests) and does not comprehensively cover basic operations. Things like testing operations on different float formats, on integers of different sizes, vectors of different sizes and element types, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In part this is because of limitations of testing through C/C++, which is very heterogeneous in type support (C compilers don’t like exposing types that don’t have a defined psABI for the target). But that’s no excuse to delegate this testing to Zig instead (which exposes everything, everywhere, and has the corresponding test coverage).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Backend divergence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While LLVM’s middle-end is very unified, backend implementations are very heterogeneous, and there is a tendency to fix issues (usually performance, but sometimes even correctness) only for the backend you’re interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This takes many forms, like implementing target-specific DAG combines instead of generic ones. Though my definite favorite is to introduce lots of target hooks for optimizations – not because the optimization is actually only beneficial for one target, but because the person introducing it just doesn’t want to deal with the fallout on other targets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is understandable – after all, they may lack the knowledge to evaluate a change for other targets, so it may require working with many other maintainers, which can slow progress a lot. But the end result is still increasing divergence and duplication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lack of end-to-end testing compounds this issue, because that would act as something of a forcing function that at least all operations compile without crashing and produce correct results for all tested targets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Compilation time&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because I’ve complained about this enough in the past, I’ll keep it short: LLVM is slow, which is an issue both for JIT use cases, and anything that tends to produce huge amounts of IR (like Rust or C++).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since I’ve started tracking compile-times, the situation has significantly improved, both through targeted improvements and avoidance of regressions. However, there is still a lot of room for improvement: LLVM still isn’t fast, it’s just less slow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One thing that LLVM is particularly bad at are &lt;code&gt;-O0&lt;/code&gt; compile-times. The architecture is optimized for optimization, and lots of costs remain even if no optimization takes place. The LLVM TPDE alternative backend shows that it’s possible to do better by an order of magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Performance tracking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The flip side of the compile-time coin is runtime performance. This is something that LLVM obviously cares a lot about. Which is why I find it rather surprising that LLVM does not have any “official” performance tracking infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, there are lots of organizations which track performance of LLVM downstream, on their own workloads. In some ways this is good, because it means there is more focus on real-world workloads than on synthetic benchmarks like SPEC. However, not having readily accessible, public performance tracking also makes it hard for contributors to evaluate changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be fair, LLVM does have an LNT instance, but a) it’s currently broken, b) LNT is one of the worst UX crimes ever committed, c) little data gets submitted there, and d) it’s not possible to request a test run for a PR, or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This point is frankly just baffling to me. I don’t personally care about SPEC scores, but I know plenty of people do, so why there is no first-class tracking for this is a mystery to me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;IR design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Undef values&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Undef values take an arbitrary value from a certain set. They are used to model uninitialized values, and have historically been used to model deferred undefined behavior. The latter role has been replaced by poison values, which have much simpler propagation rules and are more amenable to optimization. However, undef is still used for uninitialized memory to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two main problems with undef values. The first is the multi-use problem: An undef value can take a different value at each use. This means that transforms that increase the use count are generally invalid, and care has to be taken when optimizing based on value equality. The mere existence of undef values prevents us from performing optimizations we want to do, or greatly increases their complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second issue is that undef is very hard to reason about. Humans have trouble understanding it, and for proof-checkers it is computationally expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most likely, uninitialized memory will be represented using poison values instead in the future, but this runs into the problem that LLVM currently is not capable of correctly treating poison in memory. Proper support for poison in memory requires additional IR features, like the byte type.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Unsoundness and specification incompleteness&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While most miscompilations (that is, correctness bugs) in LLVM are resolved quickly, there are quite a few that remain unfixed despite having been known for a long time. These issues usually combine the qualities of being largely theoretical (that is, appearing only in artificially constructed examples rather than real-world code) and running up against issues in LLVM’s IR design.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of them are cases where we have a good idea of how the IR design needs to change to address the issue, but these changes are complex and often require a lot of work to recover optimization parity. There is often a complexity cliff where you can do something that’s simple and nearly correct, or you can do something very complex that is fully correct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then there are other cases, where just deciding on how things should work is a hard problem. The provenance model is a prime example of this. The interaction of provenance with integer casts and type punning is a difficult problem with complex tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, at some point these issues do need to be resolved. The recently formed formal specification working group aims to tackle these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Constraint encoding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A key challenge for optimizing compilers is encoding of constraints (like “this value is non-negative” or “this add will not overflow”). This includes both frontend-provided constraints (based on language undefined behavior rules), but also compiler-generated ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In particular, there are many different analyses that can infer facts about the program, but keeping these up-to-date throughout optimization is challenging. One good way to handle this is to encode facts directly in the IR. Correctly updating or discarding these annotations then becomes part of transform correctness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLVM has many different ways to encode additional constraints (poison flags, metadata, attributes, assumes), and these all come with tradeoffs in terms of how much information can be encoded, how reliably it is retained during optimization and to what degree it can negatively affect optimization. Information from metadata is lost too often, while information from assumes is not lost often enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Floating-point semantics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are various issues with floating-point (FP) semantics once we move outside the nice world of “strictly conforming IEEE 754 floats in the default environment”. A few that come to mind are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Handling of signaling NaN and FP exceptions, and non-default FP environment in general. LLVM represents this using constrained FP intrinsics. This is not ideal, as all the FP handling is split into two parallel universes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Handling of denormals. LLVM has a function attribute to not assume IEEE denormal behavior, but this is only suitable for cases where flush to zero (FTZ) is used globally. It does not help with modeling cases like ARM, where scalar ops are IEEE, while vector ops use FTZ.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Handling of excess precision, in particular when using the x87 FPU.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Other technical issues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Partial migrations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLVM is a very large project, and making any significant changes to it is hard and time consuming. Migrations often span years, where two different implementations of something coexist, until all code has been migrated. The two prime examples of this are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New pass manager: The “new” pass manager was first introduced more than a decade ago. Then about five years ago, we started using it for the middle-end optimization pipeline by default, and support for the legacy PM was dropped.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the back-end is still using the legacy pass manager. There is ongoing work to support the new pass manager in codegen, and we’re pretty close to the point where it can be used end-to-end for a single target. However, I expect it will still take quite a while for all targets to be ported and the legacy pass manager to be completely retired.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GlobalISel: This is an even more extreme case. GlobalISel is the “new” instruction selector that is intended to replace SelectionDAG (and FastISel). It was introduced approximately one decade ago, and to this day, none of the targets that originally used SelectionDAG have been fully migrated to GlobalISel. There is one new target that’s GlobalISel-only, and there is one that uses GlobalISel by default for unoptimized builds. But otherwise, SelectionDAG is still the default everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two backends (AMDGPU and AArch64) that have somewhat complete GlobalISel support, but it’s not clear when/if they’ll be able to switch to using it by default. A big problem here is that new optimizations are continually being implemented on the SDAG side, so it’s hard to keep parity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;ABI / calling convention handling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Essentially everything about the handling of calling conventions in LLVM is a mess.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The responsibility for handling calling conventions is split between the frontend and the backend. There are good reasons why LLVM can’t do this by itself (LLVM IR sits at a too low level of abstraction to satisfy the extremely arcane ABI rules).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is not a problem in itself – however, there is zero documentation of what the calling convention contract between the frontend and LLVM is, and the proper way to implement C FFI is essentially to look at what Clang does and copy that (invariably with errors, because the rules can be very subtle).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve proposed to fix this by introducing an ABI lowering library and vortex73 has implemented a prototype for it as part of GSoC. So we’re well on the way to resolving this side of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are more problems though. One that Rust has struggled with a lot is the interaction of target features with the calling convention. Enabling additional target features can change the call ABI, because additional float/vector registers start getting used for argument/return passing. This means that calls between functions with a feature enabled and disabled may be incompatible, because they assume different ABIs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ideally, ABI and target features would be orthogonal, and only coupled in that some ABIs require certain target features (e.g. you can’t have a hard float ABI without enabling FP registers). Target features are a per-function choice, while the ABI should be per-module.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the newer architectures like Loongarch and RISC-V actually have proper ABI design, but most of the older ones don’t. For example, it’s currently not possible to target AArch64 with a soft float ABI but hard float implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Builtins / libcalls&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Somewhat related to this is the handling of compiler builtins/libcalls, which are auxiliary functions that the compiler may emit for operations that are not natively supported by the target. This covers both libcalls provided by libc (or libm), and builtins provided by compiler runtime libraries like libgcc, compiler-rt or compiler-builtins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two sources of truth for this, TargetLibraryInfo (TLI) and RuntimeLibcalls. The former is used by the middle-end, primarily to recognize and optimize C library calls (this mostly covers only libc, but not libgcc). The latter is used by the backend, primarily to determine which libcalls may be emitted by the compiler and how they are spelled (this covers libgcc, and the subset of libc covered by LLVM intrinsics).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A problem with RuntimeLibcalls is that it currently largely works off only the target triple, which means that we have to make “lowest common denominator” assumptions about which libcalls are available, where the lowest common denominator is usually libgcc. If &lt;code&gt;--rtlib=compiler-rt&lt;/code&gt; is used, LLVM does not actually know about that, and cannot make use of functions that are in compiler-rt but not libgcc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This also means that we’re missing a customization point for other runtime libraries. For example, there is no way for Rust to say that it provides f128 suffix libcalls via compiler-builtins, overriding target-specific naming and availability assumptions based on which type &lt;code&gt;long double&lt;/code&gt; in C maps to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a lot of ongoing work in this area (by arsenm), so the situation here will hopefully improve in the near-ish future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Context / module dichotomy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLVM has two high-level data holders. A module corresponds to a compilation unit (e.g. pre-LTO, a single file in C/C++). The LLVM context holds various “global” data. There’s usually one context per thread, and multiple modules can (in principle) use a single context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Things like functions and globals go into the module, while constants and types go into the context. The module also contains a data layout, which provides important type layout information like “how wide is a pointer”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact that constants and types do not have access to the data layout is a constant source of friction. If you have a type, you cannot reliably tell its size without threading an extra parameter through everything. We have subsystems (like ConstantFold vs. ConstantFolding) that are separated entirely by whether data layout is available or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, I feel like this split is not actually buying us a lot. Having shared types and constants is somewhat convenient when it comes to module linking, because they can be directly shared, but I think performing explicit remapping in that one place would be better than having complexity everywhere else. Additionally, this would also allow cross-context linking, which is currently only possible by going through a bitcode roundtrip. In theory, the context could also allow some memory reuse when compiling multiple modules, but I think in practice there is usually a one-to-one correspondence between those.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;LICM register pressure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is getting a bit down in the weeds, but I’ll mention it anyway due to how often I’ve run across this in recent times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLVM considers loop invariant code motion (LICM) to be a canonicalization transform. This means that we always hoist instructions out of loops, without any target specific cost modelling. However, LICM can increase the live ranges of values, which can increase register pressure, which can lead to a large amount of spills and reloads.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The general philosophy behind this is that LICM hoists everything, all middle-end transforms can work with nicely loop invariant instructions, and then instructions will get sunk back into the loop by the backend, which can precisely model register pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Except… that second part doesn’t actually happen. I believe that (for non-PGO builds) instructions only get sunk back into loops either through rematerialization in the register allocator, or specialized sinking (typically of addressing modes), but for anything not falling into those buckets, no attempt to sink into loops in order to reduce register pressure is made.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Other&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This list is not exhaustive. There’s more I could mention, but we’d get into increasingly narrow territory. I hope I covered most of the more important things – please do let me know what I missed!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you’re not concerned with overall project health, the primary value of reviews is reciprocity. People are more likely to review your PR, if you reviewed theirs. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The way Rust reconciles this is via a combination of “rollups” (where multiple PRs are merged as a batch, using human curation), and a substantially different contribution model. Where LLVM favors sequences of small PRs that do only one thing (and get squash merged), Rust favors large PRs with many commits (which do not get squashed). As getting an approved Rust PR merged usually takes multiple days due to bors, having large PRs is pretty much required to get anything done. This is not necessarily bad, just very different from what LLVM does right now. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.npopov.com/2026/01/11/LLVM-The-bad-parts.html"/><published>2026-01-12T14:18:13+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46589009</id><title>2025 marked a record-breaking year for Apple services</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:20.415218+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="adccf96d13363154"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; UPDATE January 12, 2026 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;2025 marked a record‑breaking year for Apple services&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple’s Eddy Cue reflects on an outstanding year for Apple services&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025 was a record-breaking year for Apple services, marked by remarkable growth, global expansion, and continuous innovation. From Apple TV, Apple Music, and Apple News, to daily essentials like Apple Pay and iCloud, we delivered enriching experiences to users worldwide. Reflecting on 2025, we remained committed to enhancing our users’ daily lives, with incredible engagement during the holiday season. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple services had a banner year, rolling out game-changing features for customers while shattering records. The numbers reflect the incredible enthusiasm of our customers, whether it’s downloading an exciting new app or game, watching the hottest new show with family and friends, listening to their favorite songs, or shopping with peace of mind. The App Store alone saw over 850 million average weekly users globally, with developers earning over $550 billion on our platform since 2008. Apple Pay also made a significant impact by eliminating well over $1 billion in fraud, while generating more than $100 billion in incremental merchant sales globally, and purchases made through Apple Pay significantly outpaced the overall growth in consumer spending levels during the peak holiday shopping period in November and December. Apple TV eclipsed all prior viewership records in December 2025, while Apple Music reached all-time highs in both listenership and new subscribers. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We marked milestone anniversaries across services, including Apple Podcasts, Music, News, and more — each made possible by the artists, creators, journalists, and storytellers who bring these platforms to life. And we brought services to more users across the globe than ever before, with Apple Pay now available in 89 markets, Find My launching in South Korea, and Apple Fitness+ expanding to 28 additional countries and regions. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New updates to services delivered increasingly personalized, fun, and easy-to-use experiences for our users. Apple Wallet leveraged Apple Intelligence to make it easier for users to keep track of their orders, and Apple Maps made users’ Preferred Routes and Visited Places easily accessible using on-device intelligence. Apple Music’s AutoMix mixed songs seamlessly like a DJ, while Lyrics Translation and Pronunciation broke down language barriers. AI-powered features like Enhance Dialogue, automatically generated chapters, and links in Apple Podcasts ensured everyone could personalize their listening experience and better navigate their favorite shows. Fitness+ added digital dubbing in Spanish and German, and introduced Custom Plans that automatically create personalized workout schedules based on user preferences. Apple Invites brought people together for all kinds of life occasions, capturing memories through direct integration with Shared Albums. Apple Arcade expanded its catalog of highly rated games with more than 50 new titles for families to enjoy, all without ads. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we look ahead, we’ll continue to bring innovation and intelligent enhancements to Apple services, always guided by our commitment to privacy and a phenomenal customer experience. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— Eddy Cue, Apple’s senior vice president of Services &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple invests every day to ensure the App Store remains a safe and trusted place for users to find great apps. This consumer trust led to unprecedented engagement on the App Store in 2025, with over 850 million average weekly users spanning 175 countries and regions, helping developers grow their businesses and reach new customers around the world with the click of a button. Storefronts including the U.S., Japan, India, and China saw record visitors during the year. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developers selling digital goods and services on the App Store have earned more than $550 billion since 2008, when the platform first launched. This figure represents just a fraction of the overall commerce the App Store supports: In 2024, the App Store ecosystem facilitated $1.3 trillion in developer billings and sales, with more than 90 percent of that commerce going directly to developers, with zero commission paid to Apple. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The App Store saw a record number of visitors between Christmas Eve and New Year’s Day, and customer spending on digital goods and services over this period also hit a record. Productivity apps and photo and video apps were key growth drivers, and education apps like Simply Draw: Learn to Draw and Toca Boca World were among the most popular with customers during the holiday period. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple TV’s engagement this past December soared, with total hours viewed up 36 percent compared to the previous year, setting a new record for monthly engagement. This milestone was fueled by robust audience growth across Europe and Latin America, continued expansion in the U.S., and the global streaming debuts of F1, Pluribus, and The Family Plan 2, as well as the timeless Peanuts classic A Charlie Brown Christmas. The landmark year was propelled by Apple’s summer blockbuster F1 — the No. 1 movie at the global box office, the top film on Apple TV, and the highest-grossing sports movie of all time — as well as the premiere of Apple TV’s biggest series to date, the widely acclaimed Pluribus. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple’s commitment to excellence earned unprecedented recognition at the Emmy Awards. The Studio made history as the most Emmy-winning freshman comedy ever, Severance led as the most-awarded drama, and the gripping espionage series Slow Horses landed a Best Directing honor. To date, Apple TV has amassed 672 award wins and 3,085 nominations, underscoring its dedication to quality storytelling. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on its record-breaking year, Apple TV introduced a bold new identity and mnemonic recorded by multi-Grammy- and Academy Award-winning artist FINNEAS; expanded its live sports offerings with the news that all Major League Soccer matches will be available to stream for Apple TV subscribers at no additional cost; and unveiled a series of platform enhancements — including the launch of the Apple TV and Peacock bundle. Apple TV also introduced a native Apple TV app for Android, as well as new profiles that give every member of the household their own personalized experience within the Apple TV app. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2025, Apple elevated the fan experience across marquee sports leagues and moments, including “Friday Night Baseball” and Major League Soccer’s 30th season. Beginning this March, Apple will further expand its relationship with Formula 1® following the global success of F1 The Movie with a new five-year agreement that will bring every F1 race exclusively to Apple TV in the United States. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple Music had its best year ever in 2025, breaking records across both listenership and new subscribers. The service marked its 10-year anniversary with its biggest product feature release since launch and the opening of a brand new state-of-the-art studio, while also expanding its reach beyond the Apple ecosystem to bring Apple Music to more fans around the world. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This year, Apple Music made it easier than ever for fans to discover, share, and enjoy the music they love. New features like Lyrics Translation and Pronunciation — along with AutoMix, Library Pins, and in-app Replay stats — elevate everyday listening. Apple Music Sing expanded its feature set as well: Users can now turn their iPhone into a microphone that amplifies their voice through the TV, and utilize Continuity Camera to appear onscreen alongside lyrics and visual effects. This past holiday season, the most “sung” song on Apple Music was Mariah Carey’s “All I Want for Christmas Is You.” &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple Music also expanded its reach beyond the Apple ecosystem this year, partnering with companies like GM, TuneIn, Chase, and more to bring Apple Music to even more listeners around the world. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2025, Shazam generated over 1 billion recognitions per month, and saw significant app and website enhancements, continuing to be one of the most popular destinations for music discovery. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple Pay continues to bring value to users, merchants, and banks across the globe, and is now available in 89 markets, and with more than 11,000 banks and network partners — including more than 20 local payment networks. According to Apple data, as well as industry data, over the past year, Apple Pay has eliminated well over $1 billion in fraud globally, as well as generated more than $100 billion in incremental merchant sales globally. And during the peak holiday shopping weekend, purchases made through Apple Pay significantly outpaced the overall growth in consumer spending levels during that time period. With iOS 26, Apple Pay allows banks and lenders to enable users to pay with bank- or lender-provided installments and rewards in stores. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025 brought more ways for users across the globe to use Apple Wallet in their daily lives, from securely presenting their identity, to navigating air travel with greater ease, to keeping track of their online orders. Apple introduced support for Japan’s My Number Card on iPhone — marking the first international ID in Wallet — and enabling millions of users to use iPhone to present their ID in person, in apps, and online for identity and age verification. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the U.S., Apple introduced Digital ID, which enables users to create and add a Digital ID to Apple Wallet using information from a U.S. passport, and securely present their identity information using iPhone and Apple Watch, starting with TSA airport security checkpoints for domestic travel.1 Digital ID builds on the continued expansion of state IDs and driver’s licenses in Wallet, which last year was enabled by Illinois, Montana, North Dakota, and West Virginia, and is now live in 13 U.S. states and Puerto Rico. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To bring even more convenience to users’ travels, Apple Wallet also rolled out a refreshed boarding pass experience with airlines, which brings Live Activities for flight tracking, Maps, Find My, and more into one convenient place in Wallet. Additionally, Apple Wallet now uses Apple Intelligence to automatically identify, summarize, and display order tracking details from emails sent from merchants or delivery carriers.2 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple brought Apple Cash to the group chat, with the option to now use Apple Cash to request, send, and receive money directly within group conversations in Messages.3 Last year, Tap to Pay on iPhone expanded to 34 additional markets — now covering most of Europe — and is live in a total of 50 markets, with more than 15 million merchants of all sizes across the world accepting contactless payments using just an iPhone. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple Maps expanded its Detailed City Experience to new locations like New Orleans, Singapore, and Monaco, showcasing 3D landmarks including a custom F1 Monaco Grand Prix experience, now totaling 34 cities live with Detailed City Experience. Additionally, Maps brought its all-new map to Mexico and Thailand, offering users more accurate and detailed navigation, cycling directions, and more. With iOS 26, Maps became more personalized and intelligent, with new features like Preferred Routes, which uses on-device intelligence for daily commutes, and Visited Places, which helps users recall past locations. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple also expanded its Share Item Location feature in Find My to 27 additional airlines, bringing the total to 36. This feature allows private and secure sharing of an AirTag’s or Find My network accessory’s location with an airline’s customer service, reducing “truly lost” or unrecoverable luggage by 90 percent, according to SITA’s WorldTracer® global baggage management system. In South Korea, users can now use the Find My app to locate their Apple devices and personal items on a map, as well as share their location with friends and family — all while protecting user privacy. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;iCloud keeps users’ most important information — like photos, files, and apps — secure and synced across all of their Apple devices, and powers important features such as iCloud Photos and other shared experiences. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2025, Apple made it easier for users to connect with family and friends with the release of Apple Invites, which helps users create custom invitations to bring people together for any occasion. With Invites, users can RSVP from any device, and unlimited event creation is included with an iCloud+ subscription, along with additional storage options and other premium benefits, such as iCloud Private Relay, which protects a user’s privacy on the web; Hide My Email, which offers an easy way to create unique, random email addresses that forward to a personal inbox; custom email domains for iCloud Mail; and expanded support for HomeKit Secure Video recording. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;iCloud+ subscriptions can be shared with up to five other family members by creating a Family Sharing group where everyone’s data will stay private and separate. iCloud leads the industry in using privacy-preserving security technologies, including two-factor authentication and Advanced Data Protection for iCloud, which uses end-to-end encryption to keep users’ data secure and under their control. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple Arcade brings fun and inventive games to players across Apple devices from extraordinary developers around the world, all without ads or in-app purchases, making the service an incredible choice for families with kids and players looking for uninterrupted gaming experiences. Last year, Arcade launched more than 50 new games, including hits based on the biggest entertainment and sports brands, like SpongeBob: Patty Pursuit 2 and PGA TOUR Pro Golf. The service also added popular PC games PowerWash Simulator and Cult of the Lamb — and continues to add more. Over 500 updates were released for existing hits on Arcade, like Sneaky Sasquatch and Hello Kitty Island Adventure. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2025, Apple Fitness+ marked its largest expansion since the service’s launch by rolling out to 28 new countries and regions — including Chile, Hong Kong, India, the Netherlands, Singapore, and Taiwan, with Japan coming early this year. To make Fitness+ even more welcoming, the service introduced digitally dubbed workouts and meditations in Spanish and German, featuring a generated voice based on the actual voice of each of the 28 Fitness+ trainers. Today, the service offers more than 8,000 workouts and meditations in 4K Ultra HD. Fitness+ also launched powerful personalization features with ready-made Custom Plans, and users with AirPods Pro 3 can now view real-time performance metrics directly onscreen for extra motivation.4 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025 was Apple Podcasts’ best year yet, achieving record listeners, plays, and subscribers. Celebrating 20 years, Podcasts drove innovation, growth, and content recognition. It honored this milestone by curating “20 Years, 20 Podcasts We Love,” and introduced new accessibility and discovery features: enhance dialogue, new playback speeds, automatically created chapters, timed links, and expanded transcripts to over 125 million episodes in 13 languages. Podcasts also launched its “Best So Far” editorial list and awarded its Show of the Year to The Rest Is History — a first for a UK series. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As 2025 marked its 10th anniversary, Apple News solidified its position as the No. 1 news app in the U.S., Canada, and Australia, and No. 2 in the UK. News features over 3,000 publications and more than 600 titles with Apple News+. News+ expanded its offerings with the debut of Apple News+ Food, which includes 100,000 recipes from 60 publications in the U.S., the UK, Australia, and English-speaking Canada. It also introduced a new original puzzle, Emoji Game, in the U.S. and Canada. And to give more users access to critical local coverage, Apple News now includes over 150 local newspapers and news feeds across 50 U.S. states, seven Canadian markets, and London. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple One gives users access to the best of Apple services in one simple monthly plan that offers incredible value for individuals and families alike. Today, Apple One Individual and Family plans — which include iCloud+, Apple Music, Apple TV, and Apple Arcade — are available in more than 100 markets across the globe, with Apple One Premier, which also includes Apple Fitness+, available in more than 20 markets. The full Premier bundle, which also includes Apple News+, is available in the U.S., Canada, Australia, and the UK. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Share article&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Media&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Text of this article&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Images in this article&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;To create a Digital ID in wallet, a user must have an authentic and unexpired U.S. passport and an iPhone 11 or later with iOS 26.1 or later, or Apple Watch Series 6 or later with WatchOS 26.1 or later. Digital ID in Wallet can only be used at select TSA checkpoints in the U.S. to verify identity for domestic travel. It is not a replacement for a physical passport, and cannot be used to perform functions of a passport like international travel and border crossing. Users will still need an authentic and unexpired physical U.S. passport to perform such functions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Requires eligible device and OS version. See support.apple.com/en-us/105065 for details.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apple Cash services are provided by Green Dot Bank, Member FDIC. Apple Payments Services LLC, a subsidiary of Apple Inc., is a service provider of Green Dot Bank for Apple Cash accounts. Neither Apple Inc. nor Apple Payments Services LLC is a bank. Learn more about the Terms and Conditions. Only available in the U.S. on eligible devices.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Heart rate sensing with AirPods Pro 3 and Powerbeats Pro 2 during workouts is available in the Fitness app on iPhone with iOS 26; iPad with iPadOS 26; and Apple TV with tvOS 26 when also paired with iPhone.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/01/2025-marked-a-record-breaking-year-for-apple-services/"/><published>2026-01-12T14:30:51+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46589279</id><title>Keychron's Nape Pro turns your keyboard into a laptop‑style trackball rig</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:20.239903+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="edf51109f96389cc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most desktop setups still assume your mouse lives somewhere off to the right, waiting for you to break posture and reach across half the desk. Keychron’s new Nape Pro asks a different question: what if the pointing device simply came to meet your hands instead? Built as a slim bar with a 25 mm thumb trackball, six buttons, and a scroll wheel, it nestles right up against your favorite keyboard and behaves like a precision laptop pointing system for people who refuse to give up their mechanical boards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Slide it to the side of the keyboard and the personality changes completely. Nape Pro turns into a compact, wireless trackball with full macro pad ambitions, complete with layers, shortcuts, and ZMK powered customization. It is less a mouse replacement and more a modular control surface that just happens to move your cursor, wherever you decide to park it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Designers: Keychron &amp;amp; Gizmodo Japan&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seeing it here at the Keychron booth, tucked under a Q1 Pro, the immediate impression is how little space it occupies. The whole unit is only 135.2 mm long and 34.7 mm wide, so it fits neatly within the footprint of a standard tenkeyless board without feeling like an afterthought. They are using quiet Huano micro switches for the six buttons, which makes sense for a device meant to live right under your palms where an accidental loud click would be infuriating. The 25 mm ball is smaller than what you would find on a Kensington Expert, but it feels responsive enough for quick navigation. It is clearly designed for thumb operation, keeping your fingers on the home row and eliminating that constant, inefficient travel between keyboard and mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The real cleverness, though, is not in the hardware itself but in the chameleon-like software and orientation system. They call it OctaShift, which basically means the device knows how it is positioned and can remap its functions accordingly. The two buttons at the very ends, M1 and M2, are the easiest to hit in any orientation, so they naturally become your primary clicks whether the Nape Pro is horizontal, vertical, or angled. This flexibility is what separates it from a simple add-on. It is a tool that adapts to your workflow, whether you are a writer who wants to scroll with a thumb or a video editor who needs a dedicated shuttle wheel and macro pad next to their main mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the hood, it is running on a Realtek chip with a 1 kHz polling rate and a PixArt PAW3222 sensor, so the performance is on par with a decent wireless gaming mouse. Connectivity is handled via Bluetooth, a 2.4 GHz dongle, or a simple USB-C cable. What really caught my attention was the commitment to the enthusiast community. The firmware is ZMK, a popular open-source platform in the custom keyboard world, and Keychron plans to release the 3D files for the case. This is not a closed ecosystem. It is an invitation for users to tinker, to print their own angled stands, custom button caps, or even entirely new shells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This open approach feels like the whole point. The Nape Pro is not just for people who want a trackball; it is for people who build their own keyboards, flash their own firmware, and spend hours fine-tuning their desk setup for optimal efficiency. It bridges the gap between high-end custom keyboards and generic pointing devices. It acknowledges that for a certain type of user, the mouse is the last un-programmable, inflexible part of their workflow. By making a pointing device that is as customizable and community-focused as the keyboards it is designed to sit next to, Keychron has built something genuinely new.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.yankodesign.com/2026/01/08/keychrons-nape-pro-turns-your-mechanical-keyboard-into-a-laptop-style-trackball-rig-hands-on-at-ces-2026/"/><published>2026-01-12T14:50:24+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46589658</id><title>Date is out, Temporal is in</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:19.882101+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="8a417811e99f2f1c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Date is out, Temporal is in&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time makes fools of us all, and JavaScript is no slouch in that department either. Honestly, I’ve never minded the latter much — in fact, if you’ve taken JavaScript for Everyone or tuned into the newsletter, you already know that I largely enjoy JavaScript’s little quirks, believe it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I like when you can see the seams; I like how, for as formal and iron-clad as the ES-262 specification might seem, you can still see all the good and bad decisions made by the hundreds of people who’ve been building the language in mid-flight, if you know where to look. JavaScript has character. Sure, it doesn’t necessarily do everything exactly the way one might expect, but y’know, if you ask me, JavaScript has a real charm once you get to know it!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s one part of the language where that immediately falls apart for me, though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;// Numeric months are zero-indexed, but years and days are not: console.log( new Date(2026, 1, 1) ); // Result: Date Sun Feb 01 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; constructor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;// A numeric string between 32 and 49 is assumed to be in the 2000s: console.log( new Date( "49" ) ); // Result: Date Fri Jan 01 2049 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time) // A numeric string between 33 and 99 is assumed to be in the 1900s: console.log( new Date( "99" ) ); // Result: Date Fri Jan 01 1999 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time) // ...But 100 and up start from year zero: console.log( new Date( "100" ) ); // Result: Date Fri Jan 01 0100 00:00:00 GMT-0456 (Eastern Standard Time)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I dislike &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; immensely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;// A string-based date works the way you might expect: console.log( new Date( "2026/1/2" ) ); // Result: Date Fri Jan 02 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time) // A leading zero on the month? No problem; one is one, right? console.log( new Date( "2026/02/2" ) ); // Result: Date Mon Feb 02 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time) // Slightly different formatting? Sure! console.log( new Date( "2026-02-2" ) ); // Result: Date Mon Feb 02 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time) // A leading zero on the day? Of course; why wouldn't it work? console.log( new Date('2026/01/02') ); // Result: Date Fri Jan 02 2026 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time) // Unless, of course, you separate the year, month, and date with hyphens. // Then it gets the _day_ wrong. console.log( new Date('2026-01-02') ); // Result: Date Thu Jan 01 2026 19:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; sucks. It was hastily and shamelessly copied off of Java’s homework in the car on the way to school and it got all the same answers wrong, right down to the name at the top of the page: &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; doesn’t represent a date, it represents a time. Internally, dates are stored as number values called time values: Unix timestamps, divided into 1,000 milliseconds — which, okay, yes, a Unix time does also necessarily imply a date, sure, but still: Date represents a time, from which you can infer a date. Gross.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;// Unix timestamp for Monday, December 4, 1995 12:00:00 AM GMT-05 (the day JavaScript was announced): const timestamp = 818053200; console.log( new Date( timestamp * 1000 ) ); // Result: Date Mon Dec 04 1995 00:00:00 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Words like “date” and “time” mean things, but, sure — whatever, JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Java deprecated their &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; way back in 1997, only a few years after JavaScript’s &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; was turned loose on the unsuspecting world; meanwhile, we’ve been saddled with this mess ever since. It’s wildly inconsistent when it comes to parsing dates, as you’ve seen so far here. It has no sense of time zones beyond the local one and GMT, which is not ideal where “world-wide” is right there in the web’s name — and speaking-of, &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; only respects the Gregorian calendar model. It wholesale does not understand the concept of daylight savings time, which— I mean, okay, yeah, samesies, but I’m not made of computers. All these shortcomings make it exceptionally common to use a third-party library dedicated to working around it all, some of which are absolutely massive; a performance drain that has done real and measurable damage to the web.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;None of these are my major issue with &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;. My complaint is about more than parsing or syntax or “developer ergonomics” or the web-wide performance impact of wholly necessary workarounds or even the definition of the word “date.” My issue with &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; is soul-deep. My problem with &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; is that using it means deviating from the fundamental nature of time itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All JavaScript’s primitives values are immutable, meaning that the values themselves cannot be changed. The number value &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt; can never represent anything but the concept of “three” — you can’t make &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; mean anything other than “true.” These are values with concrete, iron-clad, real-world meanings. We know what three is. It can’t be some other non-three thing. These immutable data types are stored by value, meaning that a variable that represents the number value &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt; effectively “contains” — and thus behaves as — the number value &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When an immutable value is assigned to a variable, the JavaScript engine creates a copy of that value and stores the copy in memory:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const theNumber = 3; console.log( theNumber ); // Result: 3&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This fits the common mental model for “a variable” just fine: &lt;code&gt;theNumber&lt;/code&gt; “contains” &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we initialize &lt;code&gt;theOtherNumber&lt;/code&gt; with the value bound to &lt;code&gt;theNumber&lt;/code&gt;, that mental model holds: once again a &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt; is created and stored in memory. &lt;code&gt;theOtherNumber&lt;/code&gt; can now be thought of as containing its own discrete &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const theNumber = 3; const theOtherNumber = theNumber; console.log( theOtherNumber ); // Result: 3;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The value of &lt;code&gt;theNumber&lt;/code&gt; isn’t changed when we alter the value associated with &lt;code&gt;theOtherNumber&lt;/code&gt;, of course — again, we’re working with two discrete instances of &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const theNumber = 3; let theOtherNumber = theNumber; theOtherNumber = 5; console.log( theOtherNumber ); // Result: 5; console.log( theNumber ); // Result: 3&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you change the value bound to &lt;code&gt;theOtherNumber&lt;/code&gt;, you’re not changing the &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;, you’re creating a new, immutable number value and binding that in its place. Hence an error when you try to tinker with a variable declared using &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const theNumber = 3; theNumber = 5; // Result: Uncaught TypeError: invalid assignment to const 'theNumber'&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can’t change the binding of a &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;, and you definitely can’t alter the meaning of &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data types that can be changed after they’re created are mutable, meaning that the data value itself can be altered. Object values — any non-primitive value, like an array, map, or set — are mutable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Variables (and object properties, function parameters, and elements in an array, set, or map) can’t “contain” an object, the way we might think of &lt;code&gt;theNumber&lt;/code&gt; in the example above as “containing” &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;. A variable can contain either a primitive value or a reference value, the latter of which is a pointer to that object’s stored location in memory. When you assign an object to a variable, instead of creating a copy of that object, the identifier represents a reference to the object’s stored position in memory. That’s why an object bound to a variable declared with &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; can still be altered: the reference value can’t be changed, but the values of the object can:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const theObject = { theValue : 3 }; theObject.theValue++; console.log( theObject.theValue ); // Result: 4&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You still can’t change the binding of a &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;, but you can alter the object that binding references.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a reference value is assigned from one variable to another, the JavaScript engine creates a copy of that reference value — not the object value itself, the way a discrete copy is made of a primitive value. Both identifiers point to the same object in memory — any changes made to that object by way of one reference will be reflected by the others, because they’re all referencing the same thing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const theObject = { theValue : 3 }; const theOtherObj = theObject; theOtherObj.theValue++; console.log( theOtherObj.theValue ); // Result: 4 console.log( theObject.theValue ); // Result: 4&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what gets me about JavaScript’s date handling. Despite representing “point to it on a calendar” values, JavaScript’s date values are mutable — &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; is a constructor, invoking a constructor with &lt;code&gt;new&lt;/code&gt; necessarily results in an object, and all objects are inherently mutable:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const theDate = new Date(); console.log( typeof theDate ); // Result: object&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even though “January 1st, 2026” is as much an immutable real-world concept as “three” or “true,” the only way we have of representing that date is a with a mutable data structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This also means that any variable initialized with an instance of the &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; constructor contains a reference value, pointing to a data value in memory that can be changed by way of any reference to that value:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const theDate = new Date(); console.log( theDate.toDateString() ); // Result: Tue Dec 30 2025 theDate.setMonth( 10 ); console.log( theDate.toDateString() ); // Result: Sun Nov 30 2025&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, we’re going to breeze right over the fact that month &lt;code&gt;10&lt;/code&gt; is November.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So despite real-world dates having set-in-stone meanings, the process of interacting with an instance of &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; that represents that real-world value can mean altering that instance in ways we didn’t necessarily intend:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const today = new Date(); const addDay = theDate =&amp;gt; { theDate.setDate( theDate.getDate() + 1 ); return theDate; }; console.log(`Today is ${ today.toLocaleDateString() }, tomorrow is ${ addDay( today ).toLocaleDateString() }.`); // Result: Today is 12/31/2025. Tomorrow is 1/1/2026.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fine so far, right? Today is today, tomorrow is tomorrow; all is right in the world. You’d be forgiven for committing this to a codebase and moving on with your day. That is, unless we reordered the output slightly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const today = new Date(); const addDay = theDate =&amp;gt; { theDate.setDate( theDate.getDate() + 1 ); return theDate; }; console.log(`Tomorrow will be ${ addDay( today ).toLocaleDateString() }. Today is ${ today.toLocaleDateString() }.`); // Result: Tomorrow will be 1/1/2026. Today is 1/1/2026.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See what happened there? the variable &lt;code&gt;today&lt;/code&gt; represents a reference to the object created by &lt;code&gt;new Date()&lt;/code&gt;. When we provided &lt;code&gt;today&lt;/code&gt; as an argument to the &lt;code&gt;addDay&lt;/code&gt; function, the parameter &lt;code&gt;theDate&lt;/code&gt; now represents a copy of the reference value — not a copy of the value, but a second reference to the object that represents today’s date. When we manipulate that value to determine the date of the following day, we’re manipulating the mutable object in memory, not an immutable copy — today becomes tomorrow, the falcon has a hard time hearing the falconer, the center starts to look a little iffy vis-a-vis “holding,” and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, by this point you can probably tell that I’m not here to praise &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;, but what you might not expect is that I’m here to bury it. That’s right: &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; is soon to be over, done, gone, as “deprecated” as any part of the web platform can be — which is to say, “around forever, but you shouldn’t use it anymore, if you can avoid it.” Soon we will — at long last — have an object that replaces &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; wholesale: &lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Temporal is not a constructor, it’s a namespace object&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sharp-eyed among you may have noticed that I said “an object that replaces &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;,” not “a constructor.” &lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt; is not a constructor, and your browser’s developer console will tell you the same if you attempt to invoke it as one:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const today = new Temporal(); // Uncaught TypeError: Temporal is not a constructor&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt; is a way better name for something that pertains to time, if you ask me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, &lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt; is a namespace object — an ordinary object made up of static properties and methods, like the &lt;code&gt;Math&lt;/code&gt; object:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;console.log( Temporal ); /* Result (expanded): Temporal { … } Duration: function Duration() Instant: function Instant() Now: Temporal.Now { … } PlainDate: function PlainDate() PlainDateTime: function PlainDateTime() PlainMonthDay: function PlainMonthDay() PlainTime: function PlainTime() PlainYearMonth: function PlainYearMonth() ZonedDateTime: function ZonedDateTime() Symbol(Symbol.toStringTag): "Temporal" */&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I find this immediately understandable compared to &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;.  The classes and namespaces objects that &lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt; contains allow you to calculate durations between two points in time, represent a point in time with or without time zone specificity, or access the current moment in time via the &lt;code&gt;Now&lt;/code&gt; property. &lt;code&gt;Temporal.Now&lt;/code&gt; references a namespace object containing properties and methods of its own:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;console.log( Temporal.Now ); /* Result (expanded): Temporal.Now { … } instant: function instant() plainDateISO: function plainDateISO() plainDateTimeISO: function plainDateTimeISO() plainTimeISO: function plainTimeISO() timeZoneId: function timeZoneId() zonedDateTimeISO: function zonedDateTimeISO() Symbol(Symbol.toStringTag): "Temporal.Now" &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … } */&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt; gives us a sensible, plain-language way to grab today’s date, a la raggedy old  &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;: the &lt;code&gt;Now&lt;/code&gt; property contains a &lt;code&gt;plainDateISO()&lt;/code&gt; method. Since we’re not specifying anything in the way of time zones (a thing we can do now, thanks to Temporal) that method gives us back today’s date in the current one — EST, in my case:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;console.log( Temporal.Now.plainDateISO() ); /* Result (expanded): Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-31 &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … } */&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice how &lt;code&gt;plainDateISO&lt;/code&gt; results in an already-formatted, date-only value? Stay tuned; that’ll come up again later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;—wait. That looks familiar:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const nowTemporal = Temporal.Now.plainDateISO(); const nowDate = new Date(); console.log( nowTemporal ); /* Result (expanded): Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-31 &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … } */ console.log( nowDate ); /* Result (expanded): Date Tue Dec 31 2025 11:05:52 GMT-0500 (Eastern Standard Time) &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Date.prototype { … } */&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could it be that—…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const rightNow = Temporal.Now.instant(); console.log( typeof rightNow ); // object&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, we’re still working with a mutable object that represents the current date, I say in my spookiest voice, flashlight squarely beneath my chin. At a glance, this might not seem like it addresses my big complaint with &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, we’re kind of at the mercy of the nature of the language, here: dates represent complex real-world values, complex data necessitates complex data structures, and for JavaScript, that means objects. The difference is in how we interact with these Temporal objects, as compared to instances of &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;, and — as is so often the case — the magic is in the prototype chain:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const nowTemporal = Temporal.Now.plainDateISO(); console.log( nowTemporal.__proto__ ); /* Result (expanded): Object { … } add: function add() calendarId: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; constructor: function PlainDate() day: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; dayOfWeek: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; dayOfYear: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; daysInMonth: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; daysInWeek: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; daysInYear: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; equals: function equals() era: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; eraYear: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; inLeapYear: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; month: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; monthCode: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; monthsInYear: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; since: function since() subtract: function subtract() toJSON: function toJSON() toLocaleString: function toLocaleString() toPlainDateTime: function toPlainDateTime() toPlainMonthDay: function toPlainMonthDay() toPlainYearMonth: function toPlainYearMonth() toString: function toString() toZonedDateTime: function toZonedDateTime() until: function until() valueOf: function valueOf() weekOfYear: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; with: function with() withCalendar: function withCalendar() year: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; yearOfWeek: &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Symbol(Symbol.toStringTag): "Temporal.PlainDate" &amp;lt;get calendarId()&amp;gt;: function calendarId() &amp;lt;get day()&amp;gt;: function day() &amp;lt;get dayOfWeek()&amp;gt;: function dayOfWeek() &amp;lt;get dayOfYear()&amp;gt;: function dayOfYear() &amp;lt;get daysInMonth()&amp;gt;: function daysInMonth() &amp;lt;get daysInWeek()&amp;gt;: function daysInWeek() &amp;lt;get daysInYear()&amp;gt;: function daysInYear() &amp;lt;get era()&amp;gt;: function era() &amp;lt;get eraYear()&amp;gt;: function eraYear() &amp;lt;get inLeapYear()&amp;gt;: function inLeapYear() */&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right away you’ll notice that there are a number of methods and properties devoted to accessing, formatting, and manipulating the details of the Temporal object we’re working with. No big surprises there — it means a little bit of a learning curve, sure, but nothing an occasional trip over to MDN couldn’t solve, and they all more-or-less do what they say on their respective tins. The big difference from working with &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; is how they do so, at a fundamental level:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const nowTemporal = Temporal.Now.plainDateISO(); // Current local date: console.log( nowTemporal ); /* Result (expanded): Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-30 &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … } */ // Current local year: console.log( nowTemporal.year ); // Result: 2025 // Current local date and time: console.log( nowTemporal.toPlainDateTime() ); /* Result (expanded): Temporal.PlainDateTime 2025-12-30T00:00:00 &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … } */ // Specify that this date represents the Europe/London time zone: console.log( nowTemporal.toZonedDateTime( "Europe/London" ) ); /* Result (expanded): Temporal.ZonedDateTime 2025-12-30T00:00:00+00:00[Europe/London] &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … } */ // Add a day to this date: console.log( nowTemporal.add({ days: 1 }) ); /* Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-31 &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … } */ // Add one month and one day to this date, and subtract two years: console.log( nowTemporal.add({ months: 1, days: 1 }).subtract({ years: 2 }) ); /* Temporal.PlainDate 2024-01-31 &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … } */ console.log( nowTemporal ); /* Result (expanded): Temporal.PlainDate 2025-12-30 &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … } */&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice how none of these transformations required us to manually spin up any new objects, and that the value of the object referenced by &lt;code&gt;nowTemporal&lt;/code&gt; remains unchanged? Unlike &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;,  the methods we use to interact with a Temporal object result in new Temporal objects, rather than requiring us to use them in the context of a new instance or to modify the instance we’re working with — which is how we’re able to chain the &lt;code&gt;add&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;subtract&lt;/code&gt; methods together in &lt;code&gt;nowTemporal.add({ months: 1, days: 1 }).subtract({ years: 2 })&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sure, we’re still working with objects, and that means we’re working with mutable data structures that represent real-world values:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const nowTemporal = Temporal.Now.plainDateISO(); nowTemporal.someProperty = true; console.log( nowTemporal ); /* Result (expanded): Temporal.PlainDate 2026-01-05 someProperty: true &amp;lt;prototype&amp;gt;: Object { … }&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;…But the value represented by that Temporal object isn’t meant to be changed during the normal course of interacting with it — even though the object is still essentially mutable, we’re not stuck using that object in ways that could alter what it means in terms of real-world dates and times. I’ll take it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, let’s revisit that janky little “today is X, tomorrow is Y” script we wrote using &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; earlier. First, we’ll fix it by making sure we’re working with two discrete instances of &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; rather than modifying the instance that represents today’s date:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const today = new Date(); const addDay = theDate =&amp;gt; { const tomorrow = new Date(); tomorrow.setDate( theDate.getDate() + 1 ); return tomorrow; }; console.log(`Tomorrow will be ${ addDay( today ).toLocaleDateString() }. Today is ${ today.toLocaleDateString() }.`); // Result: Tomorrow will be 1/1/2026. Today is 12/31/2025.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks, I hate it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, fine. It gets the job done, just as it has since the day &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; first bumbled its way onto the web. We’re not unwittingly altering the value of &lt;code&gt;today&lt;/code&gt; since we’re spinning up a new instance of &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; inside our &lt;code&gt;addDay&lt;/code&gt; function — wordy, but it works, as it has for decades now. We add &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; to it, which we have to just kind of know means add one day. Then in our template literal we need to keep nudging JavaScript to give us the date in a format that doesn’t include the current time, as a string. It’s functional, but verbose.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, let’s redo it using &lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Code language&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;js&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const today = Temporal.Now.plainDateISO(); console.log(`Tomorrow will be ${ today.add({ days: 1 }) }. Today is ${ today }.`); // Result: Tomorrow will be 2026-01-01. Today is 2025-12-31.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we’re talking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So much better. Leaner, meaner, and way less margin for error. We want today’s date without the time, and the object that results from invoking &lt;code&gt;plainDateISO&lt;/code&gt; (and any new Temporal objects created from it) will retain that formatting without being coerced to a string. Formatting: check.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We want to output a value that represents today’s date plus one day, and we want to do so in a way where we are unmistakably saying “add one day to it” with no parsing guesswork: check and check.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most importantly, we don’t want to run the risk of having our original &lt;code&gt;today&lt;/code&gt; object altered unintentionally — because the result of calling the &lt;code&gt;add&lt;/code&gt; method will always be a new Temporal object: check.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt; is going to be a massive improvement over &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;, and I only say “going to be” because it still isn’t quite ready for prime-time usage. The draft specification for the proposed &lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt; object has reached stage three of the standardization process, meaning it is now officially “recommended for implementation” — not yet part of the standard that informs the ongoing development of JavaScript itself, but close enough that browsers can start tinkering with it. That means the results of that early experimentation may be used to further refine the specification, so nothing is set in stone just yet. Web standards are an iterative process, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s where you and I come in. Now that &lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt; has landed in the latest versions of Chrome and Firefox — and others, soon — it’s time for us to get in there and kick the tires a little bit. We may not have had any say in &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt;, but we get to experiment with &lt;code&gt;Temporal&lt;/code&gt; before the final implementations land.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Soon, JavaScript will have sensible, modern date handling, and we’ll finally be able to cram &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; way in the back of the junk drawer with the rubber bands, mismatched jar lids, mystery keys, and probably-half-empty AA batteries — still present, still an inexorable part of the web platform, but no longer our first, last, and only way of handling dates. And we only had to wait— well, hold on, let me just crunch the numbers real quick:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Try it out&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const today = Temporal.Now.plainDateISO();
const jsShipped = Temporal.PlainDate.from( "1995-12-04" );
const sinceDate = today.since( jsShipped, { largestUnit: 'year' });

console.log( `${ sinceDate.years } years, ${ sinceDate.months } months, and ${ sinceDate.days } days.` );&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sure, the best time to replace &lt;code&gt;Date&lt;/code&gt; would’ve been back in 1995, but hey: the second best time is &lt;code&gt;Temporal.Now&lt;/code&gt;, right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enjoyed this article? You can support us by leaving a tip via Open Collective&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://piccalil.li/blog/date-is-out-and-temporal-is-in/"/><published>2026-01-12T15:20:36+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46589675</id><title>Apple picks Google's Gemini to power Siri</title><updated>2026-01-12T16:16:19.785681+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd4eb9bd83a6b12c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple is joining forces with Google to power its artificial intelligence features for products such as Siri later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The multi-year partnership will lean on Google's Gemini models and cloud technology for future Apple foundational models, according to a statement obtained by CNBC's Jim Cramer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"After careful evaluation, we determined that Google's technology provides the most capable foundation for Apple Foundation Models and we're excited about the innovative new experiences it will unlock for our users," Apple wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple declined to comment on the terms of the deal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In August, Bloomberg had reported that Apple was in early talks with Google to use a custom Gemini model to power a new iteration of Siri.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last week, the search giant's market capitalization surpassed Apple for the first time since 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shares were slightly lower following the news. Google briefly touched above a $4 trillion market value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple has mostly stood on the sidelines of the AI frenzy that's swept up Wall Street since the launch of OpenAI's ChatGPT at the end of 2022. Hyperscalers including Amazon, Meta Platforms and Microsoft are also shelling out billions on more products and tools for their customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's amped up the pressure on the iPhone maker to deliver an impressive Siri AI voice upgrade, which it delayed last year until 2026, despite running ads for the product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's going to take us longer than we thought to deliver on these features and we anticipate rolling them out in the coming year," the company said in a statement at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Google has made steady progress on its AI agenda, introducing its upgraded Gemini 3 model late last year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In October, Google CEO Sundar Pichai said the company's cloud segment signed more deals worth more than $1 billion through the third quarter of 2025 than the previous two years combined.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/12/apple-google-ai-siri-gemini.html"/><published>2026-01-12T15:22:21+00:00</published></entry></feed>