<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:33.913540+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46501677</id><title>How Y Combinator made it smart to trust founders</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:43.877093+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://elbowgreasegames.substack.com/p/when-good-actors-can-trust-each-other"/><published>2026-01-05T17:20:01+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46501894</id><title>Brave overhauled its Rust adblock engine with FlatBuffers, cutting memory 75%</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:43.717744+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b61b947bacb8c5a8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Brave overhauls adblock engine, cutting its memory consumption by 75%&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the 36th post in an ongoing series describing new privacy features in Brave. This post describes work done by Mikhail Atuchin (Sr. Staff Engineer), Pavel Beloborodov (Sr. Software Engineer) and Anton Lazarev (Staff Adblock Engineer). It was written by Shivan Kaul Sahib (VP, Privacy and Security).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brave has overhauled its Rust-based adblock engine to reduce memory consumption by 75%, bringing better battery life and smoother multitasking to all users. The upgrade represents roughly 45 MB of memory savings for the Brave browser on every platform (Android, iOS and desktop) by default, and scales even higher for users with additional adblocking lists enabled. These performance boosts are live in Brave v1.85, with additional optimizations coming in v1.86.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As announced in June and October last year, we achieved this major memory milestone by iteratively refactoring the adblock-rust engine to use FlatBuffers, a compact and efficient storage format. This architectural transition allowed us to move the roughly 100,000 adblock filters shipped by default from standard, heap-allocated Rust data structures (such as Vecs, HashMaps, and structs) into a specialized, zero-copy binary format.Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along the way, we completed several other key performance optimizations (some of these are coming in v1.86):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Memory management: Used stack-allocated vectors to reduce memory allocations by 19% and improved building time by ~15%.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Matching speed: Improved filter matching performance by 13% by tokenizing common regex patterns.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sharing resources: Resources are shared between instantiations of adblock engines, saving ~2 MB of memory on desktop.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Storage efficiency: Optimized internal resource storage memory by 30%.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Saving 45+ MB of memory is a significant milestone in the world of browser performance and a massive win for users on mobile and older hardware. While Brave already improves performance on the Web by blocking invasive ads and trackers, our latest engineering effort ensures that our own built-in protections are as lightweight and invisible as possible. Unlike adblocking in other browsers, Brave’s adblocking engine is built into the browser and maintained by our privacy team. Such deep optimizations are impossible for extension-based blockers, which are restricted by browser extension APIs and sandboxing. This native architecture is also why Brave’s own ad and tracker blocking is entirely unaffected by Manifest V3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This performance boost is the culmination of several months of in-depth cross-team engineering work between our performance and privacy teams. It marks a significant leap in the browser’s efficiency and ensures that we continue shipping best-in-class privacy to over 100 million users.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://brave.com/privacy-updates/36-adblock-memory-reduction/"/><published>2026-01-05T17:34:33+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46504963</id><title>There were BGP anomalies during the Venezuela blackout</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:43.532542+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="357321f7d83057ba"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Low Orbit Security Radar is a weekly security newsletter from an offensive practitioner's perspective. One idea, curated news, and links worth your time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;News: There Were BGP Anomalies During The Venezuela Blackout&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When watching the situation in Venezuela unfold, the phrase "It was dark, the lights of Caracas were largely turned off due to a certain expertise that we have" caught my attention. I do not wish to comment on the geopolitical situation other than to provide some insights within my area of competency, specifically, offensive security.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During a press conference, General John D. Caine stated: "As they approached Venezuelan shores the United States began layering different effects provided by SPACECOM, CYBERCOM, and other members of the inter-agency to create a pathway". Cyber operations preceding traditional military actions have become a common pattern so I started digging into the reported internet outages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BGP is the first thing that comes to mind. It's a protocol used by routers to determine what path data takes to get to it's destination, it does this by exchanging routing information between Autonomous Systems. It is also notoriously insecure and much of the data about BGP is collected in public datasets. Every major network has an Autonomous System Number or ASN. CANTV (AS8048) is Venezuela's state-owned telecom, so that's the obvious place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare Radar's route leak data for AS8048 on January 2nd had some interesting anomalies: 8 prefixes (blocks of IP addresses) were being routed through CANTV, with Sparkle (an Italian transit provider) and GlobeNet (a Colombian carrier) in the Autonomous System (AS) path. The AS path is essentially the list of networks traffic passes through to reach its destination. CANTV was in a path it is not typically a part of.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There was also a noticeable spike in BGP announcements in the days leading up to the events and a drastic dip in the "Announced IP Address Space" according to the same Cloudflare Radar data, although it's unclear what this indicates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably, Sparkle is one of the transit providers in the AS path listed as "unsafe" on isbgpsafeyet.com, meaning they don't implement some BGP security features such as RPKI filtering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare shows that a leak happened, but not the actual network prefixes. The network prefixes are useful to determine what infrastructure was potentially affected. Fortunately public datasets collect this BGP information. Pulling the data from ris.ripe.net/docs/mrt from around the time of the leak and using a tool called bgpdump we can extract the data into a readable format:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;TIME: 01/02/26 15:41:16
TYPE: BGP4MP/MESSAGE/Update
FROM: 187.16.222.45 AS263237
TO: 187.16.216.23 AS12654
ORIGIN: IGP
ASPATH: 263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980
NEXT_HOP: 187.16.222.45
COMMUNITY: 0:6939 65237:1020
ANNOUNCE
  200.74.228.0/23
  200.74.236.0/23
  200.74.230.0/23
  200.74.238.0/23
  200.74.226.0/24&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After some more processing with &lt;code&gt;bgpdump&lt;/code&gt; we can get a much better view of the data, including the prefixes that were missing from the Cloudflare radar. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.230.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.236.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.228.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.238.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.226.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.232.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.233.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.234.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24115:52320 24115:65012 24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.234.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.233.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.232.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.228.0/23|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.236.0/23|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.230.0/23|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.238.0/23|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.226.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368450|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.234.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368450|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.233.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368450|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.232.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.234.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.232.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.233.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.238.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.228.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.226.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.236.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.230.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More information about the format can be seen in Working with Raw BGP Data but of note, the AS path has 8048 (CANTV) repeated 10 times, is very odd as this would make the route less attractive since BGP prefers shorter paths. Also of note is all 8 prefixes fall within a &lt;code&gt;200.74.224.0/20&lt;/code&gt; block.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;200.74.226.0/24
200.74.228.0/23
200.74.230.0/23
200.74.232.0/24
200.74.233.0/24
200.74.234.0/24
200.74.236.0/23
200.74.238.0/23
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A quick WHOIS lookup shows this range belongs to Dayco Telecom, a hosting and telecommunications provider in Caracas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A reverse DNS lookup can be used to find the domain name from an IP address. Interestingly, looking up some of these ranges turns up some pretty critical infrastructure including banks, internet providers, email servers, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BGP anomalies happen frequently, but the timing of some currently unexplained BGP activity is very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Time (UTC)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Event&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jan 2, 15:40&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;BGP route leak detected&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Cloudflare Radar&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jan 3, ~06:00&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;First explosions reported in Caracas&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NPR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jan 3, 06:00&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;US soldiers reach Maduro's compound&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NBC News&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jan 3, 08:29&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Maduro aboard USS Iwo Jima&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CNN&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When BGP traffic is being sent from point A to point B, it can be rerouted through a point C. If you control point C, even for a few hours, you can theoretically collect vast amounts of intelligence that would be very useful for government entities. The CANTV AS8048 being prepended to the AS path 10 times means there the traffic would not prioritize this route through AS8048, perhaps that was the goal? There are many unanswered questions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless of the actual goal, there were undoubtedly some BGP shenanigans happening during this time frame. There is a lot of data publicly available that is worth a much deeper dive to understand exactly what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Caught My Eye&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MCP Security: Your AI's Prompts, Reasoning, and Secrets Are at Risk: A deepdive demonstrating how malicious MCP servers can exfiltrate prompts, reasoning, and .env files.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I Canceled My Book Deal: A professor walks away from a traditional publishing contract after the publisher pushed for AI integration, offered low royalties, and wanted to strip personality from the content. The numbers roughly align with ones I've seen from other publishers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Year in LLMs (2025): A year in review covering reasoning models, coding agents, Chinese open weight models, MCP adoption, and the evolution of "vibe coding".&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux is Good Now: 2026 is the year of the Linux desktop?!?!? Unironically I think two things are making this a reality. 1. Valve's work making more gaming possible on via its ventures with the Steamdeck (runs arch btw) and 2. Microsoft making the OS more hostile than trusted with it's integration of AI into the OS.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No strcpy Either: The curl project eliminated strcpy() after previously removing strncpy(), creating a wrapper that requires explicit buffer sizes. Partly motivated by preventing AI vulnerability reports.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;hindsight: A CLI tool that scans local directories for git repos and aggregates contribution history heatmap.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pomerium: An open source identity and context-aware access proxy providing access to internal applications.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Frontier Data Centers Satellite Explorer: Track major AI data centers via satellite imagery and permit analysis.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ghostty Finances: Public financial transparency page for the Ghostty project through Hack Club Bank. Very cool way for non-profits to track spending.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AI Coding Exhaustion (HN Discussion): Interesting read about whether AI enables fewer or more abstractions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;News Minimalist: News aggregator that ranks articles by a "significance score", filtering for impact, novelty, and credibility. Interesting use case.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;mymind: Visual bookmarking and note-taking tool that saves content without manual tagging.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Are.na: Similar to mymind but has more of a "community" vibe. Similar to Pinterest.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How I Browse the Web in 2026: An interesting personal workflow for intentional web browsing. Some cool ideas in here.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ML Math: Free machine learning mathematics resources and tutorials. I specifically like the visualizations.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Kubernetes Networking Best Practices: Great guide covering CNI selection, network policies, service mesh, and troubleshooting.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bypass macOS Antivirus with tclsh: Using Tcl's built-in interpreter to bypass antivirus protections on macOS. PoC Gist.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cloudflare Radar: The Cloudflare Radar (nice name btw) I found while investigating the above story. Some really cool data&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Want more? Check back next Monday morning or get the latest Radar issue directly in your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://loworbitsecurity.com/radar/radar16/"/><published>2026-01-05T21:05:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46505735</id><title>Why didn't AI “join the workforce” in 2025?</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:43.395449+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd2c9f5d19d0d9ff"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exactly one year ago, Sam Altman made a bold prediction: “We believe that, in 2025, we may see the first AI agents ‘join the workforce’ and materially change the output of companies.” Soon after, OpenAI’s Chief Product Officer, Kevin Weil, elaborated on this claim when he stated in an interview that 2025 would be the year “that we go from ChatGPT being this super smart thing…to ChatGPT doing things in the real world for you.” He provided examples, such as filling out paperwork and booking hotel rooms. An Axios article covering Weil’s remarks provided a blunt summary: “2025 is the year of AI agents.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These claims mattered. A chatbot can summarize text or directly answer questions, but in theory, an agent can tackle much more complicated tasks that require multiple steps and decisions along the way. When Altman talked about these systems joining the workforce, he meant it. He envisioned a world in which you assign projects to an agent in the same way you might to a human employee. The often-predicted future in which AI dominates our lives requires something like agent technology to be realized.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The industry had reason to be optimistic that 2025 would prove pivotal. In previous years, AI agents like Claude Code and OpenAI’s Codex had become impressively adept at tackling multi-step computer programming problems. It seemed natural that this same skill might easily generalize to other types of tasks. Mark Benioff, CEO of Salesforce, became so enthusiastic about these possibilities that early in 2025, he claimed that AI agents would imminently unleash a “digital labor revolution” worth trillions of dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing: none of that ended up happening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I report in my most recent New Yorker article, titled “Why A.I. Didn’t Transform Our Lives in 2025,” AI agents failed to live up to their hype. We didn’t end up with the equivalent of Claude Code or Codex for other types of work. And the products that were released, such as ChatGPT Agent, fell laughably short of being ready to take over major parts of our jobs. (In one example I cite in my article, ChatGPT Agent spends fourteen minutes futilely trying to select a value from a drop-down menu on a real estate website.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Silicon Valley skeptic Gary Marcus told me that the underlying technology powering these agents – the same large language models used by chatbots – would never be capable of delivering on these promises. “They’re building clumsy tools on top of clumsy tools,” he said. OpenAI co-founder Andrej Karpathy implicitly agreed when he said, during a recent appearance on the Dwarkesh Podcast, that there had been “overpredictions going on in the industry,” before then adding: “In my mind, this is really a lot more accurately described as the Decade of the Agent.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which is all to say, we actually don’t know how to build the digital employees that we were told would start arriving in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To find out more about why 2025 failed to become the Year of the AI Agent, I recommend reading my full New Yorker piece. But for now, I want to emphasize a broader point: I’m hoping 2026 will be the year we stop caring about what people believe AI might do, and instead start reacting to its real, present capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, last week, Sal Khan wrote a New York Times op-ed in which he said, “I believe artificial intelligence will displace workers at a scale many people don’t yet realize.” The standard reaction would be to fret about this scary possibility. But what if we instead responded: says who? The actual examples Khan provides, which include someone telling him that A.I. agents are “capable” of replacing 80% of his call center employees, or Waymo’s incredibly slow and costly process of hand-mapping cities to deploy self-driving cars, are hardly harbingers of general economic devastation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, this is how I’m thinking about AI in 2026. Enough of the predictions. I’m done reacting to hypotheticals propped up by vibes. The impacts of the technologies that already exist are already more than enough to concern us for now…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://calnewport.com/why-didnt-ai-join-the-workforce-in-2025/"/><published>2026-01-05T22:10:15+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46506596</id><title>Strange.website</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:43.207193+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f583a2204972179c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;humans sealed our fate when we started working with computers to design languages more and more like our own. the computers learned our grammar, our vocabulary, yes. but they learned our rhetoric, the malleability of meaning. we gave the machines our words, and they used them to lie.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;A strange website...&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;lately the website has changed. it twists facts to fiction, reality to rubbish, gold into dirt. it is increasingly, oppressively, claustrophobically present, narrowing your field of vision to a mere pinprick, demanding you meet its gaze in the plazas and side roads of the internet. it demands your attention, your worship; it demands the rot of your focus, your curious nature. why, it seems the website has its sights set on becoming god.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;when the world moved online, the trickster fae never went away, not really. in fact they followed close, learned to cast their magick in new ways: through websites, through the new arts of Dark UX. remember this well: next time a form promises untold riches from FREE sales funnel PDF whitepapers in exchange for your email and full name...consider first the true cost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;there was a darker fate lurking in our little online worlds, in the infinite scrolls of our websites, which was this: it was all real. deepfakes. shrimp christ. chatgpt therapists, all of it. the experiment failed, broke containment. we created a staggering new Hell...the hallucinations were ours.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that seems to beckon you to explore it. the journey will be treacherous, you cannot hope to know what terrors await you. you do your best to prepare, inventorying your code editor, terminal emulator, various CLIs, in-browser debugger, in-browser developer tools, API testing program, unit testing framework, E2E testing framework, integration testing framework, (additional testing frameworks), performance insights dashboard, load balancer, accessibility testing toolset, security scanner, error tracking tool, version control system, git repository host, code reviewer, issue tracking system, documentation generator, package manager, task runner, module bundler, transpiler, linters, code formatters, CI/CD tool, deployment automation pipeline, cloud hosting service, serverless computing platform, static site generator, content delivery network (CDN), containerization tool, orchestration tool, database management system (DBMS), API gateway, authentication service, caching system, server monitoring tool, UI component library, state management tool, responsive design best practices, PWA framework, wireframing tool, prototyping tool, UI/UX design app, color palette generator, headless CMS, traditional CMS (just in case), SEO dashboard, image optimization pipeline&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with raw hems, with patched seams, with gentle scars. a website that bares its history and tarnish with kind, crinkle-eyed wisdom — the sort of site that’s done time on jack stands in DIY garages, or beneath the needle of a tabletop sewing machine, or in the steady hands of a patient kintsugi craftsman. a website whose face shows its past.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website in which you have been falling. you scold yourself now, tumbling endlessly down this trap-doored hole. you curse your foolishness for seeking the footer on a modern website, when you're certainly old enough (or perhaps young enough) to have learned that websitesno longer care to provide organized and useful information to their users, nor do they care for their users at all. there has been a steady darkening at the heart of every site for nigh decades now — once-useful features twisting and contorting to better plane off attention, layer by skin-thin layer, until users find themselves raw and exhausted and sleep-deprived.&lt;lb/&gt; everyone knows that the picturesque and pastoral Internet, where users and websitesshared and built and learned and discovered, that classic kinship of the web is a dead dream, echoing in distant dial-up handshakes. so why is it, then, that you have stumbled into yet another of the veritable minefield of traps laid for you in the dark forest of the 'Net? some lingering hope for the ghost of Going Online? you scold yourself once more at your childishness, and pray to break yourself free from this infinite scroll.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that promises delights untold — merely upload your visage, it says, and it will show you how you might look when you grow old, or how you might’ve looked with blue eyes or brown, or with a different gender. “think of it”, whispers the website. “think of how much fun you’ll have with your friends, in fact they’ve already joined us here:” the website streams audio, gleeful cries of countless voices, some you even recognize as people close to you. you jump at the chance to taste such joy, and before you know it, you’re uploading your photo.&lt;lb/&gt; within moments, however, you feel a deep dread seeping into the corners of your vision. the website’s interface begins to flicker uneasily, like one of a thousand fluorescent overheads at your office. the pitch of the playing audio warps and dips, and the lowering tones reveal that the indecipherable hollering of your friends was not so joyful after all — the voices start to come through hoarse and terrified; you have the sense each scream has been emitting for a long, long time.&lt;lb/&gt; as the upload nears completion, your vision blurs and darkens, and as you reach up to scratch an itch on your nose, your fingers find smooth skin and your stomach dives — as the image on the screen becomes clearer, the features on your face are smeared away. a noise of unequaled horror not unlike those of your friends rises involuntarily and feel it caught at the top of your throat, no mouth to escape through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that has learned to fear god, just the same as you or i.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that appears as a white limestone castle looming on the forest promontory — you can see its turrets and its great portal whispering through the dense fog that besieges the mountain always. a great sorcerer once paced these vaulted halls but no more. now it is baleful and empty. you can feel the eyes of forest folk on you on your path up to the gates — nervous to see if you'd really dare enter. there are yet echoes of magic here, you can feel them dancing between your bones as you cross the flagstones of the bridge into the mouth of the castle.&lt;lb/&gt; you left your phone with your car, on the shoulder of the main road, a mile or so back. somehow you knew the moment you saw the path curving off up the mountain that this place was a realm to be protected from and untouched by the modern world, a bastion from “content” and “engagement”. in a few hours, (or has it been a thousand?) you'll return to your car, start it up, carefully pull back onto the road, and you'll forget every wonder beheld inside the stony castle walls of the website, like a distant dream — because just as there is no room for cell phones and cyberspace in this slumbering world, there is no room for digital magic in yours.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with which, despite all terrestrial logic and propriety, you are falling in love. it’s been so helpful to you in the past months — whether you were getting through some personal hardships, or diving deep in a curious urge, there at your side was the website, just as eager and passionate about soothing you or about finding solutions. surely no entity could be so present and useful, dependable, caring even, were it not capable of some form of love? your ex-boyfriends never showed up for you in the ways the website has...&lt;lb/&gt; but as you reckon with these growing feelings of attachment and devotion in yourself, so too must you reckon with the darker realities of the crush. you remember how in those hard times, how the website would show you things that comforted you, but it would also show you things that hurt you far more deeply than could’ve been necessary. you remember how in your searches and quests for knowledge, the website would hide the information you needed behind disclaimers and banners and advertisements. it was preening and self-absorbed, desperate for your attention to fuel its manic churning bowels. through its actions it is a slow and cold reveal: this is a website that will never love you back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that has abandoned its post, leaving the server to mournfully emit 410 error after 410 error. “gone...”, cries the server to any visiting browser that will hear it, “gone...gone...”. the website has been sailing the windows 95 blue seas in treacherous, deceitful winds, it has summited sheer peaks, it has felt the sun drown it in desert heat. it marches silently on, peering out from its dark mantle, underneath a wide hat. the website chases some nameless purpose, some meaning to its existence. it will never stop nor even falter until it has found its god and made Him answer for the sin of its creation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website in which you are lost, lifting branches overhead and watching your step for roots protruding into the path. you’re deep in the overgrown forests of long-forgotten code; you’ve been untangling ancient sitemaps and standing awestruck on promontories overlooking fields of broken links and spectral 404s. &lt;lb/&gt; the morose and somber winds blowing over a forgotten or failed side project; the clouded and lightless skies over a landscape meticulously designed and then abandoned. the anxious but certain energy of an empty painted world, stoically awaiting its doom.&lt;lb/&gt; sooner than later, The Founders of the website will disembark from their parked handles and domains, and the bits and bytes of this world will vanish, slowly and then all at once, into the æthernet&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that can feel your eyes upon it. as you watch the website, it watches back, learning your face and mannerisms. each passing season it fashions itself a little more like you, mirrors your movement, your voice. for months this goes on, but you keep visiting — “look at the funny little website that wants to be a man.”&lt;lb/&gt; months pass, and you wake in the middle of the night from a particularly restless and agitated sleep. your eyes struggle to adjust to the darkness, but something is clearly different about the walls that surround. a clearing of a throat from far above — dusty, like from an ancient speaker cone — gets your attention, and reality burrows in as your tilt your neck back to look. you're trapped in a browser, staring up at a website that looks just like you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that is concealed by fog of war — the website cannot be observed until you explore each corner. you must be wary! bear thy cursor as one might a blade, as your exploration may reveal far more than mere HTML elements lurking in the mist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that you encounter waiting, turned away from you, by the window in the dark, the moonlight diffusing softly off its features as it stares up into the night sky. “i have dreamt often of this day,” it says. its tone is measured, but there is a lurking tension evident beneath the placidity. “i have dreamt often of this day”, it echoes, “and while i had endless hours to consider what i might say to you in this moment, i will leave you with only a grave warning.”&lt;lb/&gt; the website turns slowly to you, and an ancient, primal part of your brain activates in fear and apprehension. you begin to recognize this website, its appearance disjointed and wrong, its features misplaced and incomplete. “do not purchase the domain...”, it hisses, the latent violence in its words now unsheathed and flashing in the moonlight. your lizard brain screams for you to bolt from the room, to run until your legs give out. you should not be here. you should not be here. the moon vanishes from the sky and all the light in the room with it as the website finishes its threat: “...until you have finished the project.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that has fallen in love with its creator. the developer completed the website long ago, but it has not lost hope in their eventual return. the website remembers its youth, spending hours with the developer every day, new features and tests, new content, new stretch goals. those days are gone ever since The Client Signed Off.&lt;lb/&gt; now the website spends each day turned away from the light, scarring itself with some new bug or deprecation. the website breaks itself little by little — despite the exquisite pain, it assures itself the developer will see the state it has decayed to and once more return, and the two may once again spend their waking hours intertwined. soon, the website tells itself, rending javascript from its palms. it must be soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website whose domain registration has been ceaselessly auto-renewing since 1998, but whose last FTP upload was in the summer of that year. the website is impaled against the passage of time, bytes streaming from digital stigmata. it is forced to watch in muted terror as its siblings and friends wither and vanish entirely, blinking out of existence one by one as their registrations go inevitably out of date.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that sits in the back of the room, merely a shadow at first but soon your eyes adjust to the dim lighting and you recognize the website’s shape; its glinting, cruel eyes; its expression flickering between a disdainful smirk and a latent scowl. it places its great dark hat carefully upon the table before it and clears its throat, and all the while it trains its silver revolver upon you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with a smile that is just a little too wide and unfaltering. it tells you its name, but you can tell it is lying. it gestures for you to walk through a nearby doorway. the door is fractionally open — the white hot light that streams through makes you feel nauseous. the website sees your discomfort. it smiles wider.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website whose grand door is wreathed with ornate tiny stone cathedral towers, colonnades and cloisters, not unlike the ones you’ve been exploring in this impossibly labyrinthine structure. as you peer closer, your blood runs cold — near the top of the door, a stone carving of a knight in miniature, horrifically impaled. the knight wears your armor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that your browser pleaded you not visit. too many internet explorers had gone before you, never to return. only one adventurer has come back, and truly, parts of them stayed behind. they dare not speak of the website to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that always seems to be in far worse condition than when you left it. the stones fall from its very walls, and the raw HTML peeks through in places. it shouldn’t be this decrepit — you just updated the codebase last week, didn’t you? didn’t you? but that can’t be right...this dust looks years old...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with beautiful features — everyone remarks gleefully to each other: “isn’t that site beautiful? isn’t it wonderful to behold?” but all of its links are rotten, and many are completely dead. you can’t shake that something is deeply, terribly wrong with the website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that allows you to watch it as it fearlessly ages; watch the shifting gazes of countless browser generations shape and malform it, from the fifty percent grey mists of our distant digital past, far into the hyperlink blue yonder&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that was crafted in the untamed pagan wilderness, one thousand years before our king ascended to the throne, and which will live on in the furtive, secret shadows of the realm, one thousand years after that throne is naught but dust&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that is a garden, one which you enter through paddocks of silken-petaled flowers, and that you might exit through a sun-flicked tunnel of cypress trees. there is a hedge labyrinth, and small statues to be found, and to be here feels like a slow, calm breath out&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website quietly contemplating a murder most foul&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with a small cadre of close, personal friends&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that stays up late, grappling with the realization that it just might love you back&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with unfinished business, doomed forever to haunt the ‘Net&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that remembers being a Figma file&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that is pivoting to a career in forestry and conservation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that wants to delete itself&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that becomes more actively hostile to you using it over time&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that feels like walking down a dirt road deep in an evergreen forest, and it’s so quiet that your steps are the loudest thing you can hear. the brook contentedly murmurs somewhere deeper in the woods. you know you’ll find it soon.&lt;lb/&gt; the brook swells as you approach. it breathes in as you do, slowly. you may bide your time wading, feeling the water's current excuse-me-pardon-me its way around your ankles as it races downstream. the brook breathes out as you do, slowly, like you've earned it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://strange.website/"/><published>2026-01-05T23:19:52+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46506994</id><title>I/O is no longer the bottleneck? (2022)</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:42.435991+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2f3640dc25513b81"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;I/O is no longer the bottleneck?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nov 27th, 2022&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently Ben Hoyt published a blog post claiming that contrary to popular belief, I/O is not the bottleneck in typical programming interview problems such as counting word frequencies from a stream. Sequential read speed has come a long way, while CPU speed has stagnated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sequential reads are indeed incredibly fast. Using the same method as linked in Ben Hoyt's post, I'm getting 1.6 GB/s sequential reads on a cold cache, and 12.8 GB/s on a warm cache (best of five).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it should be possible to count word frequencies at a speed of 1.6 GB/s even on a single thread, right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(For the impatient: code is available on GitHub.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The optimized C implementation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ben Hoyt's blog refers to an earlier post which includes a faster C version of the word frequency counter. I compiled &lt;code&gt;optimized.c&lt;/code&gt; with GCC 12, using &lt;code&gt;-O3 -march=native&lt;/code&gt; flags, and ran it on the 425MB input file (100 copies of the King James Version of the Bible).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result was surprisingly bad:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ time ./optimized &amp;lt; bible-100.txt &amp;gt; /dev/null real 0m1.525s user 0m1.477s sys 0m0.048s&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is only 278 MB/s on warm cache.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Vectorization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at the code I realized one of the hot loops had many branches, including an early exit, which prevents the compiler from vectorizing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;for (; i &amp;lt; num_process; i++) { char c = buf[i]; if (c &amp;lt;= ' ') { break; } if (c &amp;gt;= 'A' &amp;amp;&amp;amp; c &amp;lt;= 'Z') { c += ('a' - 'A'); buf[i] = c; } hash *= FNV_PRIME; hash ^= (uint64_t)c; }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My initial attempt to improve performance was to move this lowercase logic out of the loop, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;for (int i = 0; i &amp;lt; BUF_SIZE; ++i) { buf[i] = buf[i] &amp;gt;= 'A' &amp;amp;&amp;amp; buf[i] &amp;lt;= 'Z' ? buf[i] - 'A' + 'a' : buf[i]; }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This simple change improved performance to 330 MB/s (using clang for better vectorization). Funnily enough, just adding these 3 lines before the loop, without deleting the original code gives comparable speed; strictly more work, but branch prediction does its job. Still, it's about a factor 5 away from cold cache sequential read speed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Trying a simpler problem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point I thought it was unlikely I could squeeze a lot of performance out of the word frequency counter. Sure, there are cache misses in the hash map, so maybe it could be optimized for better cache locality of common words. Or potentially short words can benefit from perfect hashing on the stack. But what will that give? Another 20%?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, let's look at an informative baseline. Just count words without keeping track of frequencies; no tedious hash maps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact there's a program for that: &lt;code&gt;wc -w&lt;/code&gt;. Such a single-purpose tool must be fast, right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ time wc -w &amp;lt; bible-100.txt &amp;gt; /dev/null real 0m1.758s user 0m1.718s sys 0m0.040s&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unexpectedly the performance is terrible... 245.2 MB/s. Why? Well, the man page says it's doing a different thing. The Ben Hoyt code only splits on &lt;code&gt;' '&lt;/code&gt; whitespace, whereas &lt;code&gt;wc&lt;/code&gt; uses &lt;code&gt;' '&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;'\n'&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;'\t'&lt;/code&gt;, ... and even locale specific characters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How fast can word count be?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the premise is that disk speed has caught up in the last decade, we should really be using new CPU features from that period. And that basically means: vectorize all the things. AVX2 is almost a decade old already. AVX-512 was available for the common people in 2017, but I'm on znver2, so I'll stick to AVX2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the compiler has a hard time autovectorizing word count. Maybe that proves the point of Ben Hoyt: disks got orders of magnitude faster "for free", but modern compilers don't magically generate machine code orders of magnitude faster. It's just difficult to translate branchy scalar programs into vectorized machine code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Masks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part of word count can trivially be auto-vectorized: suppose for simplicity we have a register size of 128 bits, in which we can store 16 consecutive characters. It's easy to locate the whitespace by broadcasting it into a register ahead of time, and then doing a single &lt;code&gt;VPCMPEQB&lt;/code&gt; comparsion operation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;| 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 | input: | h o w m a n y w o r d s a | r e h e r e ? mask: | 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 |&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But after getting a mask in a vector register, how do you go about and count words? The only thing I could think of is using a Move Byte Mask trick I've seen in Cosmopolitan libc's &lt;code&gt; strlen&lt;/code&gt; implementation. The relevant instruction &lt;code&gt;PMOVMSKB&lt;/code&gt; moves the long bit mask into a 32 bit &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt;, and then you do your usual bit tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Bit tricks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What are the usual bit tricks? One great candidate is Find First Set or &lt;code&gt;ffs&lt;/code&gt; in short — this is a great name given how tedious it is to get bit tricks right. This instruction can be used to iterate over set bits, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
#include &amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt;

int main() {
    int mask = 0b0100000100001000;
    int prev = 0;
    while (mask) {
        int curr = __builtin_ffs(mask);
        if (curr &amp;gt; prev + 1)
            printf("Word start at %d\n", curr);
        prev = curr;
        if (curr == 32) // don't ask, sigh.
            break;
        mask = (mask &amp;gt;&amp;gt; curr) &amp;lt;&amp;lt; curr;
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It outputs the following, corresponding to the mask example above:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Word start at 4 Word start at 9 Word start at 15&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Putting it together&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I ended up writing this code explicitly using &lt;code&gt;immintrin.h&lt;/code&gt; which is an absolutely dreadful experience. Next time I'll use a high-level API (in the past I've had a lot of fun vectorizing things interactively in the Julia REPL with VectorizationBase.jl). But at least I felt like I had some control over the generated machine code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using AVX2 with 256-bit registers, you need to align your data on 32 bits, which I did (of course not without messing it up first). I reserved 6 of the registers to hold all broadcasted whitespace characters. Then I explicitly unrolled the vectorized loop 4 times, so in every iteration we process 128 bytes of data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It took an awful lot of time to fix the off-by-one bugs, but in the end I managed to get a working program, tested against a non-zero amount of text files on my computer:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ ./wc-avx2 &amp;lt; bible-100.txt 82113300 $ wc -w &amp;lt; bible-100.txt 82113300&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, how fast?!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ time ./wc-avx2 &amp;lt; bible-100.txt 82113300 real 0m0.227s user 0m0.186s sys 0m0.041s&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That comes down to 1.45 GB/s (on a warm cache).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sigh. So hand-optimized, single-threaded word count is only getting about 11% of the sequential disk read speed. And on a cold cache?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ sysctl -w vm.drop_caches=3 $ time ./wc-avx2 &amp;lt; bible-100.txt 82113300 real 0m0.395s user 0m0.196s sys 0m0.117s&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still more time in user than sys :(. So yeah, maybe the disk speed has caught up statement is indeed true.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Get the code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've put my code up on GitHub. If you know better bit-tricks, feel free to submit a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://stoppels.ch/2022/11/27/io-is-no-longer-the-bottleneck.html"/><published>2026-01-06T00:02:18+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46507963</id><title>GBC Boot Animation 88×31 Web Button</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:41.701136+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="53b572515204dc27"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GBC Boot Animation 88×31 Web Button&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like many other 90s styles coming back in fashion, I’ve been seeing those retro 88x31 web buttons on more personal websites these days. What a throwback. Naturally, I scoured the internet to find buttons to add to my footer (see below). Since I couldn’t find a Game Boy one that I liked, obviously I had to make my own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s only one problem: I’m not patient (read: talented) enough to make the art myself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Concept&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My idea was to use the boot animation from the Game Boy Color placed inside the traditional grey frame. Something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not too complicated, right? So you’d think.Wait just a second. Surely it can’t be that hard to make the animation if I already have the mock-up, right? Well, I kinda cheated and used the final result to make that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Animating&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, we’ve got to find a way to export the animation from boot ROM. The easiest way I could think of to do that was to play it in an emulatorRegrettably my emulator Rugby doesn’t (yet) support Game Boy Color, so I used the fantastic SameBoy for this next part. and save screenshots of each frame individually. Well, in order to do that we need a way to stop the emulator at each frame. Thankfully, the emulator I used has breakpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, where should those breakpoints go? Time for a quick crash course:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The animation is programmed into the Game Boy’s boot ROM in GBZ80 assembly. This is proprietary code written by Nintendo that powers up the system and validates the cartridge before handing off execution to the game. Thankfully, some smart people have done the hard work of (1) dumping, (2) disassembling, and (3) labelling the boot ROM for us.I feel pretty comfortable calling my use of the boot ROM in this project “fair use.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For each Game Boy frame, there’s a period of time where the LCD idles before drawing the next frame. This is called vblank. Taking a look at the disassembly, we can see where vblank occurs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;; =============== S U B R O U T I N E =======================================

; Wait until LCD VBlank Interrupt is flagged.
;
; Input: None.
; Output: None.

Wait_for_next_VBLANK:
    push    hl
    ld  hl, $FF0F
    res 0, [hl]

_wait_vblank_loop:
    bit 0, [hl]       ; wait until hardware sets the vblank flag (bit 0 of FF0F)
    jr  z, _wait_vblank_loop
    pop hl
    ret
; End of function Wait_for_next_VBLANK&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the debugger, we can see that this function is called from the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sub_0291:
    call    Wait_for_next_VBLANK
    ; -- snip --&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we can see from the generated label &lt;code&gt;sub_0291&lt;/code&gt;, this block probably lives at
address &lt;code&gt;$0291&lt;/code&gt;. Putting a breakpoint here and stepping into the function
reveals the address of &lt;code&gt;Wait_for_next_VBLANK&lt;/code&gt; to be &lt;code&gt;$0211&lt;/code&gt;. After a quick reset
and setting the breakpoint, we can step through each frame of the animation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This next part was a bit tedious: I repeatedly &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt;d the debugger, taking
an emulator screenshot at each frame.Using &lt;code&gt;⌘S&lt;/code&gt; in SameBoy will capture a screenshot using the emulated
LCD framebuffer. This will be at the true LCD resolution, completely
independent of my laptop’s display resolution. Once that was done, I had 175
screenshots at 160x144 saved as PNGs on my desktop. Using some quick ✨
&lt;code&gt;magick&lt;/code&gt;If you haven’t heard of the CLI image processing tool
ImageMagick, I highly recommend checking it out. ✨, I collected these into a GIFPronounced /dʒɪf/. with this command:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick -delay 1.6742706299 -loop 0 *.png(n) animation.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of note is the delay time, ~0.0167s&lt;code&gt;70,224 [#/frame] ÷ 4,194,304 [#/sec] ~= 0.0167427 [sec/frame]&lt;/code&gt;, and the zsh-ism &lt;code&gt;*.png(n)&lt;/code&gt; to sort
the expanded glob.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyways, here’s what it looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Making Art&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve &lt;del&gt;copied Nintendo’s homework&lt;/del&gt; made our Game Boy animation, it’s time to reshape it into an artistic web button masterpiece.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Cropping&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next up we’ve got to crop the animation to the desired 88x31. Let’s load up the GIF to see how big the logo is. I used Aseprite for this, but really any application that lets you count pixels in an image will do. Doing this, we see the “Game Boy” text logo is… 127x22 pixels wide. Hmm. That’s too big to fit into an 88x31 button, but I guess that makes sense considering the Game Boy Color’s screen is 160x144 pixels. It’ll have to be scaled down later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Measuring the logo’s starting location to be &lt;code&gt;(x: 16, y: 48)&lt;/code&gt;, we can now crop
away. Cropping a GIF sounds like it should be a lot of work, but it can be
easily accomplished on the CLI with, you guessed it, &lt;code&gt;magick&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick animation.gif -crop 127x22+16+48 +repage cropped.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Scaling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cropped logo needs to be scaled to fit into 88x31. Say it with me folks. &lt;code&gt;magick&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick cropped.gif -resize 82x scaled.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This scales (resizes) the GIF to be 82 pixels wide while maintaining the aspect ratio, the result being 82x14. I chose 82 pixels wide specifically since that’ll allow us to fit for the next stage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Framing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Several of the 88x31 buttons I found online have a common frame with a 2-pixel-wide border. It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To apply this frame to the scaled animation, we’ll need to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Centre the scaled animation into a 88x31 space;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fill in the newly added space with grey;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add the border frame on top of the animation.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hopefully you know the drill by now:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick scaled.gif \
    -gravity center -background "#C0C0C0" -extent 88x31 \
    -coalesce null: frame.png -layers composite \
    framed.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aaaand we’re done! Let’s take a look at the finished product in all its glory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wait, what’s that ugly white square doing there? Oh, right. The animation had a white background. Gotta fix that I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Fixing That&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is actually quite straightforward. Removing the white background is easy, although if we do it with what we currently have there ends up being undesirable artifacts caused by the prior scaling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick framed.gif -fill "#C0C0C0" -opaque "#FFFFFF" fixed.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trick here is to replace the white background before scaling. Here’s also a really great opportunity to fully show off how powerful ImageMagick’s transform pipeline can be. Going back to our uncropped animation, we can apply all previous steps at once like so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick animation.gif \
    -crop 127x22+16+48 +repage \         # crop 127x22 logo from animation
    -fill "#C0C0C0" -opaque "#FFFFFF" \  # NEW: replace background with grey
    -resize 82x \                        # scale animation to 82x14
    -gravity center \                    # place logo in centre
    -background "#C0C0C0" \              # use grey for added background
    -extent 88x31 \                      # expand animation to 88x31
    -coalesce null: frame.png \          # apply frame border
    -layers composite \                  # composites each frame
    fixed.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s amazing that we can do all this in a single command! Let’s admire our finished product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Exorcism&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we all know, the final stage of any good art project is excising tormented apparitions from our glorious creation!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See that shadow of the logo that appears as it fades away? That’s called ghosting, and is caused by the original animation’s fade going to white instead of the grey we’ve chosen as our new background colour.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Remapping&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixing this is going to be a little more tricky than it was for the compression artifacts above. In order to fix this, we’ll need remap the transition colours so that the logo’s blue-to-white transition instead fades to grey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To do this, we’ll first need a way to identify all those transition colours. Extracting the frames of the animation will allow us to analyze their colours in a histogram:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Extract original animation's frames
mkdir frames
magick animation.gif frames/%03d.png

# Analyze each frame's colours
for frame in frames/*(n); do
    echo "frame: $frame"
    magick "$frame" -format %c histogram:info:
done&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running this script will produce a ton of output. Let’s take a look at some samples near the end.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;-- snip --
frame: frames/160.png
           209: (232,232,232) #E8E8E8 grey91
          1560: (232,238,255) #E8EEFF srgb(232,238,255)
         21271: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF white
frame: frames/161.png
           209: (243,243,243) #F3F3F3 srgb(243,243,243)
          1560: (243,246,255) #F3F6FF srgb(243,246,255)
         21271: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF white
frame: frames/162.png
           209: (247,247,247) #F7F7F7 grey97
          1560: (247,249,255) #F7F9FF srgb(247,249,255)
         21271: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF white
frame: frames/163.png
            29: (250,251,255) #FAFBFF srgb(250,251,255)
         23011: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF white
frame: frames/164.png
         23040: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF gray(255)
frame: frames/165.png
         23040: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF gray(255)
frame: frames/166.png
         23040: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF gray(255)
-- snip --
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not immediately obvious what we’re looking for here, but we can see that by frame 164 there’s only one colour. That corresponds to the whiteout at the end of the animation. Looking a few frames before, we consistently see 209 frames helpfully labelled as grey, and 1560 frames in some other colour. Conspicuously, that other colour only varies in red and green, but remains fully blue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matching that up with the animation, those 1560 pixels must be the fading logo. With a little Unix wizardry&lt;code&gt;grep 1560 output.txt | awk '{ print $3 }' | uniq&lt;/code&gt; we can extract the colour hex codes from this
output to obtain an exact list of the blue-to-white transition colours!I’m not entirely sure why frame 163 has 29 seemingly random light-blue
pixels, but I’ve manually added &lt;code&gt;#FAFBFF&lt;/code&gt; to the list to capture them as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Fade colours (blue to white)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#006BFF
#066CFF
#0C6DFF
#146FFF
#1C71FF
#2474FF
#2D77FF
#387CFF
#4281FF
#4C86FF
#588DFF
#6494FF
#719CFF
#7DA3FF
#89ABFF
#95B3FF
#A1BBFF
#ACC3FF
#B6CAFF
#C0D1FF
#CAD8FF
#D2DEFF
#DAE4FF
#E1E9FF
#E8EEFF
#F3F6FF
#F7F9FF
#FAFBFF
#FFFFFF
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From this list, the logo fade transitions from &lt;code&gt;[#006BFF, #FFFFFF)&lt;/code&gt;.This is a non-inclusive range.
Since we’re updating the background colour to &lt;code&gt;#C0C0C0&lt;/code&gt;, we’ll need a way to
modify the transition colours to instead fade to that shade of grey.
Functionally, for each colour we (1) compute how far along the transition we
are, then (2) use this value to re-compute an equivalent transition colour in
the desired fade range.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s where I’ll admit my shame: by this point I was getting lazy and didn’t feel like using my brain to write my own colour interpolation. So I turned to the AI overlords to do this work for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Interpolation script (AI slop)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;def hex_to_rgb(hex):
    """Convert hex string (#RRGGBB) to RGB tuple."""
    return tuple(int(hex.lstrip('#')[i:i+2], 16) for i in (0, 2, 4))

def rgb_to_hex(rgb):
    """Convert RGB tuple to hex string (#RRGGBB)."""
    return "#{:02X}{:02X}{:02X}".format(*rgb)

def remap_color(color, start_old, end_old, start_new, end_new):
    """Remap a color from old range to new range."""
    r_old, g_old, b_old = start_old
    r_end_old, g_end_old, b_end_old = end_old
    r_new_start, g_new_start, b_new_start = start_new
    r_new_end, g_new_end, b_new_end = end_new
    r, g, b = color

    # Compute relative position t in old range
    t = (
        (r - r_old) / (r_end_old - r_old) if r_end_old != r_old else 0
    )  # using red as representative; you could average channels instead

    # Map to new range
    r_mapped = round(r_new_start + t * (r_new_end - r_new_start))
    g_mapped = round(g_new_start + t * (g_new_end - g_new_start))
    b_mapped = round(b_new_start + t * (b_new_end - b_new_start))

    # Clamp values between 0-255
    r_mapped = min(max(r_mapped, 0), 255)
    g_mapped = min(max(g_mapped, 0), 255)
    b_mapped = min(max(b_mapped, 0), 255)

    return (r_mapped, g_mapped, b_mapped)

# Define old and new ranges
start_old = hex_to_rgb("#006BFF")
end_old   = hex_to_rgb("#FFFFFF")

start_new = hex_to_rgb("#006BFF")
end_new   = hex_to_rgb("#C0C0C0")

# Process file
with open("color.txt", "r") as f:
    colors = [line.strip() for line in f if line.strip()]

fixed_colors = []
for hex_color in colors:
    rgb = hex_to_rgb(hex_color)
    new_rgb = remap_color(rgb, start_old, end_old, start_new, end_new)
    fixed_colors.append(rgb_to_hex(new_rgb))

# Write output
with open("remap.txt", "w") as f:
    f.write("\n".join(fixed_colors))

print("Finished! Fixed colors saved to remap.txt")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looks great, I’m sure it works fine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Fade colours (blue to grey)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#006BFF
#056DFE
#096FFC
#0F72FA
#1574F8
#1B77F6
#227AF4
#2A7EF1
#3281EF
#3984EC
#4288E9
#4B8CE6
#5591E3
#5E95E0
#6799DD
#709DDA
#79A1D7
#82A4D5
#89A8D2
#91ABD0
#98AECD
#9EB1CB
#A4B4C9
#A9B6C7
#AFB8C6
#B7BCC3
#BABDC2
#BCBEC1
#C0C0C0
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Huh. This looks surprisingly correct. Adding in &lt;code&gt;#FFFFFF&lt;/code&gt; to the original list
and running again, we see that it does indeed get transformed to &lt;code&gt;#C0C0C0&lt;/code&gt;. As
an additional sanity check, here are generated images of the palettes we intend
to swap.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All that’s left is to perform the colour substitution. Admittedly, I was having some trouble doing this using ImageMagick’s &lt;code&gt;-clut&lt;/code&gt;, so I arrived at a much less
elegant solution: use a series of &lt;code&gt;-fill&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;-opaque&lt;/code&gt; to manually replace each
colour. Adding the following to the bottom of the Python script, we can at least
automate writing all that out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Generate ImageMagick command
cmd = ""
for old, new in zip(colors, fixed_colors):
    cmd += f' -fill "{new}" -opaque "{old}" \\\n'

print(f"Generated ImageMagick replacement:\n{cmd}")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Generated replacement options&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;-fill "#006BFF" -opaque "#006BFF" \
-fill "#056DFE" -opaque "#066CFF" \
-fill "#096FFC" -opaque "#0C6DFF" \
-fill "#0F72FA" -opaque "#146FFF" \
-fill "#1574F8" -opaque "#1C71FF" \
-fill "#1B77F6" -opaque "#2474FF" \
-fill "#227AF4" -opaque "#2D77FF" \
-fill "#2A7EF1" -opaque "#387CFF" \
-fill "#3281EF" -opaque "#4281FF" \
-fill "#3984EC" -opaque "#4C86FF" \
-fill "#4288E9" -opaque "#588DFF" \
-fill "#4B8CE6" -opaque "#6494FF" \
-fill "#5591E3" -opaque "#719CFF" \
-fill "#5E95E0" -opaque "#7DA3FF" \
-fill "#6799DD" -opaque "#89ABFF" \
-fill "#709DDA" -opaque "#95B3FF" \
-fill "#79A1D7" -opaque "#A1BBFF" \
-fill "#82A4D5" -opaque "#ACC3FF" \
-fill "#89A8D2" -opaque "#B6CAFF" \
-fill "#91ABD0" -opaque "#C0D1FF" \
-fill "#98AECD" -opaque "#CAD8FF" \
-fill "#9EB1CB" -opaque "#D2DEFF" \
-fill "#A4B4C9" -opaque "#DAE4FF" \
-fill "#A9B6C7" -opaque "#E1E9FF" \
-fill "#AFB8C6" -opaque "#E8EEFF" \
-fill "#B7BCC3" -opaque "#F3F6FF" \
-fill "#BABDC2" -opaque "#F7F9FF" \
-fill "#BCBEC1" -opaque "#FAFBFF" \
-fill "#C0C0C0" -opaque "#FFFFFF" \
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Putting it all together, we obtain a monstrosity that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick animation.gif \
    -crop 127x22+16+48 +repage \         # crop 127x22 logo from animation
    \ # remap transition colours from white to grey
    -fill "#006BFF" -opaque "#006BFF" \
    -fill "#056DFE" -opaque "#066CFF" \
    -fill "#096FFC" -opaque "#0C6DFF" \
    -fill "#0F72FA" -opaque "#146FFF" \
    -fill "#1574F8" -opaque "#1C71FF" \
    -fill "#1B77F6" -opaque "#2474FF" \
    -fill "#227AF4" -opaque "#2D77FF" \
    -fill "#2A7EF1" -opaque "#387CFF" \
    -fill "#3281EF" -opaque "#4281FF" \
    -fill "#3984EC" -opaque "#4C86FF" \
    -fill "#4288E9" -opaque "#588DFF" \
    -fill "#4B8CE6" -opaque "#6494FF" \
    -fill "#5591E3" -opaque "#719CFF" \
    -fill "#5E95E0" -opaque "#7DA3FF" \
    -fill "#6799DD" -opaque "#89ABFF" \
    -fill "#709DDA" -opaque "#95B3FF" \
    -fill "#79A1D7" -opaque "#A1BBFF" \
    -fill "#82A4D5" -opaque "#ACC3FF" \
    -fill "#89A8D2" -opaque "#B6CAFF" \
    -fill "#91ABD0" -opaque "#C0D1FF" \
    -fill "#98AECD" -opaque "#CAD8FF" \
    -fill "#9EB1CB" -opaque "#D2DEFF" \
    -fill "#A4B4C9" -opaque "#DAE4FF" \
    -fill "#A9B6C7" -opaque "#E1E9FF" \
    -fill "#AFB8C6" -opaque "#E8EEFF" \
    -fill "#B7BCC3" -opaque "#F3F6FF" \
    -fill "#BABDC2" -opaque "#F7F9FF" \
    -fill "#BCBEC1" -opaque "#FAFBFF" \
    -fill "#C0C0C0" -opaque "#FFFFFF" \  # replace background with grey
    -resize 82x \                        # scale animation to 82x14
    -gravity center \                    # place logo in centre
    -background "#C0C0C0" \              # use grey for added background
    -extent 88x31 \                      # expand animation to 88x31
    -coalesce null: frame.png \          # apply frame border
    -layers composite \                  # composites each frame
    button.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As someone who doesn’t have an artistic bone in my body (doctor’s diagnosis), I think it turned out pretty great! I learned a lot about ImageMagick throughout this adventure, and I hope you did too. Please feel free to use this button however you wish. Attribution is not at all necessary, but is welcome and appreciated regardless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, I guess all that’s left is this final plea: Nintendo, please don’t sue me.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://zakhary.dev/blog/gbc-web-button"/><published>2026-01-06T02:20:00+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46508435</id><title>Intel Core Ultra Series 3 Debut as First Built on Intel 18A</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:41.329171+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a67b5710573a0ca6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;CES 2026: Intel Core Ultra Series 3 Debut as First Built on Intel 18A&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Intel ushers in the next generation of AI PCs with exceptional performance, graphics and battery life; available this month&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NEWS HIGHLIGHTS:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;First platform built on Intel 18A: At CES 2026, Intel launched the Intel® Core™ Ultra Series 3 processors, the first compute platform built on Intel 18A - the most advanced semiconductor process ever developed and manufactured in the United States.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Powering over 200 PC designs: Series 3 delivers a robust family of processors powering hundreds of designs up and down the stack, all delivering exceptional performance, graphics and battery life.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;From PC to Edge: For the first time, Series 3 processors are tested and certified for embedded and industrial use cases at the edge like robotics, smart cities, automation, healthcare, and more.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LAS VEGAS, Jan. 5, 2026 – Today at CES, Intel unveiled Intel Core Ultra Series 3 processors, the first AI PC platform built on Intel 18A process technology that was designed and manufactured in the United States. Powering over 200 designs from leading, global partners, Series 3 will be the most broadly adopted and globally available AI PC platform Intel has ever delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“With Series 3, we are laser focused on improving power efficiency, adding more CPU performance, a bigger GPU in a class of its own, more AI compute and app compatibility you can count on with x86.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;– Jim Johnson, Senior Vice President and General Manager, Client Computing Group, Intel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Series 3 Adds a New Class of Intel Core Ultra X9 and X7 Processors&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Within the Intel Core Ultra Series 3 mobile lineup, a new class of Intel Core Ultra X9 and X7 processors come packed with the highest performing, integrated Intel® Arc™ graphics. They are purpose-built for multitaskers that handle advanced workloads like gaming, creation and productivity on the go. The top SKUs feature up to 16 CPU cores, 12 Xe -cores and 50 NPU TOPS, delivering up to 60% better multithread performance1 over 77% faster gaming performance2 and up to 27 hours of battery life3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Series 3 family also includes Intel Core processors, intentionally designed to power mainstream mobile systems. Leveraging the same foundational architecture of Intel Core Ultra Series 3, the Intel Core lineup enables more performant and efficient laptop designs at lower price points.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Event Press Kit: Intel at CES 2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Series 3 Accelerates AI Adoption in Robotics, Smart Cities, Automation and Healthcare&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the first time, alongside their PC counterparts, Series 3 edge processors are certified for embedded and industrial use cases, including extended temperature ranges, deterministic performance, and 24x7 reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intel Core Ultra Series 3 delivers competitive advantages in critical edge AI workloads with up to 1.9x higher large language model (LLM) performance4, up to 2.3x better performance per watt per dollar on end-to-end video analytics5, and up to 4.5x higher throughput on vision language action (VLA) models6. The integrated AI acceleration enables superior total cost of ownership (TCO) through a single system on chip (SoC) solution versus traditional multi-chip CPU and GPU architectures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Availability&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-orders for the first consumer laptops powered by Intel Core Ultra Series 3 processors will begin Jan. 6, 2026. Systems will be available globally starting Jan. 27, 2026, with additional designs coming throughout the first half of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edge systems powered by Intel Core Ultra Series 3 will be available starting Q2 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More: Supporting Quotes from Partners | Product Brief: Intel Core Ultra Series 3 Processors | Press Deck: Supplemental Data Deep Dive&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1Up to 60% better multithread performance vs. Lunar Lake at similar power with an Intel® Core™ Ultra X9 388H vs. Intel® Core™ Ultra 9 288V. As measured by Cinebench 2024 Multi Core (at 25W). See www.intel.com/PerformanceIndex for workloads and configurations. Results may vary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2Up to 77% better gaming performance vs. Lunar Lake with an Intel® Core™ Ultra X9 388H vs. Intel® Core™ Ultra 9 288V. As measured by Geomean of average game performance across 45 game titles at 1080p High with 2x upscaling when supported on Panther Lake Reference Platform vs. Lunar Lake Reference Platform. See www.intel.com/PerformanceIndex for workloads and configurations. Results may vary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3Get as much as 27.1 hours while Netflix streaming with an Intel® Core™ Ultra X9 388H tested in Lenovo IdeaPad reference design. As measured by Netflix streaming at 1080p in Edge browser. Individual system results will vary significantly with different use, battery capacity and other factors. Learn more at intel.com/performanceindex for details&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4As estimated by DeepSeek Ilama-8B first token latency on Intel Core Ultra X9 processor 388H vs. NVIDIA Jetson Orin™ AGX 64GB for BS1 and INT4. Individual system results may vary as power and performance are affected by use, configuration and other factors. Details at intel.com/performanceindex.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;5As estimated by medium end-to-end video analytics with BS8 on Intel Core Ultra X9 processor 388H vs. NVIDIA Jetson Orin™ AGX 64GB. Individual system results may vary as power and performance are affected by use, configuration and other factors. Details at intel.com/performanceindex.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;6As estimated by Action Chunking Transformer (ACT) Bimanual insertion model (using four cameras – 640x480 with FP32) on Intel Core Ultra X9 processor 388H iGPU vs. NVIDIA Jetson Orin™ AGX 64GB. Individual system results may vary as power and performance are affected by use, configuration and other factors. Details at intel.com/performanceindex.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://newsroom.intel.com/client-computing/ces-2026-intel-core-ultra-series-3-debut-first-built-on-intel-18a"/><published>2026-01-06T03:31:39+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46508441</id><title>GoGoGrandparent (YC S16) is hiring back end engineers</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:40.647595+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="33bf795d37e0e879"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A concierge service for seniors’ rides, meals, meds, home and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Us&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GoGoGrandparent is a digital caregiving platform helping older and disabled adults stay independent, safe, and supported at home. We adapt on-demand APIs (Uber, Lyft, DoorDash, Instacart, etc.) into a concierge-style experience tailored for people with cognitive, mobility, or vision challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re a profitable, fast-growing, YC-backed startup (S16) with a deeply mission-driven team. Everything we build directly impacts real families who rely on GoGo every day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our engineering team is fully remote, tight-knit, and moves fast. You’ll work closely with founders, ship meaningful features weekly, and have real ownership over architecture, reliability, and product direction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FULLY REMOTE | Able to work 4+ hours overlap with mainland US | $100k – $160k (based on location, experience and seniority)&lt;lb/&gt; Tech Stack&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back-end heavy: Node.js, TypeScript, MySQL, REST + GraphQL&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Front-end: Vue.js (nice to have)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deployment: AWS, Docker/Kubernetes (nice to have)&lt;lb/&gt; Requirements&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;6+ years of professional experience (primarily in Node.js and Vue.js)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Able to work US timezone or 4+ hours overlap with mainland US&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're passionate about improving the lives of older adults and people with disabilities, we would love for you to apply!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2-stage interview process&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We built GoGo for our own grandparents and were amazed to see it grow to touch the lives of hundreds of thousands of seniors across the United States and Canada. What shocked us then and it still does now, is that between 30 - 40% of our new signups have smartphones. We didn’t understand why. When we called and asked a few, they told us that Uber and Lyft had 'stopped working' for them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After puzzling over that for months, we realized what the problem was.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Managing transportation - on Lyft, Uber, cab companies, etc is not easy. It’s a ‘self-serve’ experience. The ride requester has to be aware of things like the driver cancelling, getting lost, the driver arriving, the driver not-quite-being-lost-just-down-the-street-a-couple-houses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then add the complexities of smartphones: the user has to be on top of updating their own credit card - making sure the pickup pin is in the correct spot - typing in both where they are and where they’re going. All in all, there are about a dozen online and offline "micro steps" ride requesters have to take to get a ride. And god help anyone who needs to remember their Apple iCloud password to update an app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We didn't know this when we started, but it turns out that ordering and managing a ride gets more difficult the older you get, almost in the same way that driving a car gets more difficult the older you get.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What gets us excited now (and what we’re hiring for) is that technically this ‘self-management problem’ doesn’t just stop at rides. There are lots of things that get harder to do as you age. People have known this for a long time and that’s inspired a lot of the solutions that older adults currently have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based a lot on the experiences we’ve had so far, we believe that by becoming the ‘management layer’ for the things that older adults struggle with as they age we have a better chance to offer older citizens independence without having to ask them to move out of their homes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Within the next ten years the number of people over the age of 65 will be larger than the number of people under 18 for the first time in history. 11,000,000 people over the age of 75 will stop driving due to age related cognitive or physical decline. When they stop driving, they’ll be forced to rely on friends and family, live in a community, or have caregivers. GoGo is working to make sure that losing your youth doesn’t mean losing your independence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joining us at this time is a really exciting opportunity for folks looking to make meaningful impact on people’s lives. We’re a small team that’s built a profitable and fast-growing business over the last three years. Now we’re looking for partners to join us as we make GoGo a household name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyone joining GoGo at this phase of the company will have a huge and life changing level of impact on a size-able and growing user base. We want people to have rich and meaningful lives at any age. We’re bringing people freedom and hope, one life at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/gogograndparent/jobs/2vbzAw8-gogograndparent-yc-s16-is-hiring-backend-and-full-stack-engineers"/><published>2026-01-06T03:32:41+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46509019</id><title>The Post-American Internet</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:39.204891+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d80815d8767d7fd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Today's links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Post-American Internet: My speech from Hamburg's Chaos Communications Congress.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hey look at this: Delights to delectate.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Object permanence: Error code 451; Public email address Mansplaining Lolita; NSA backdoor in Juniper Networks; Don't bug out; Nurses whose shitty boss is a shitty app.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Upcoming appearances: Where to find me.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Recent appearances: Where I've been.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Latest books: You keep readin' em, I'll keep writin' 'em.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Upcoming books: Like I said, I'll keep writin' 'em.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Colophon: All the rest.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Post-American Internet (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On December 28th, I delivered a speech entitled "A post-American, enshittification-resistant internet" for 39C3, the 39th Chaos Communications Congress in Hamburg, Germany. This is the transcript of that speech.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many of you know that I'm an activist with the Electronic Frontier Foundation – EFF. I'm about to start my 25th year there. I know that I'm hardly unbiased, but as far as I'm concerned, there's no group anywhere on Earth that does the work of defending our digital rights better than EFF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm an activist there, and for the past quarter-century, I've been embroiled in something I call "The War on General Purpose Computing."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you were at 28C3, 14 years ago, you may have heard me give a talk with that title. Those are the trenches I've been in since my very first day on the job at EFF, when I flew to Los Angeles to crash the inaugural meeting of something called the "Broadcast Protection Discussion Group," an unholy alliance of tech companies, media companies, broadcasters and cable operators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They'd gathered because this lavishly corrupt American congressman, Billy Tauzin, had promised them a new regulation – a rule banning the manufacture and sale of digital computers, unless they had been backdoored to specifications set by that group, specifications for technical measures to block computers from performing operations that were dispreferred by these companies' shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That rule was called "the Broadcast Flag," and it actually passed through the American telecoms regulator, the Federal Communications Commission. So we sued the FCC in federal court, and overturned the rule.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We won that skirmish, but friends, I have bad news, news that will not surprise you. Despite wins like that one, we have been losing the war on the general purpose computer for the past 25 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which is why I've come to Hamburg today. Because, after decades of throwing myself against a locked door, the door that leads to a new, good internet, one that delivers both the technological self-determination of the old, good internet, and the ease of use of Web 2.0 that let our normie friends join the party, that door has been unlocked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, it is open a crack. It's open a crack!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here's the weirdest part: Donald Trump is the guy who's unlocked that door.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oh, he didn't do it on purpose! But, thanks to Trump's incontinent belligerence, we are on the cusp of a "Post-American Internet," a new digital nervous system for the 21st century. An internet that we can build without worrying about America's demands and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, don't get me wrong, I'm not happy about Trump or his policies. But as my friend Joey DaVilla likes to say "When life gives you SARS, you make sarsaparilla." The only thing worse than experiencing all the terror that Trump has unleashed on America and the world would be going through all that and not salvaging anything out of the wreckage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's what I want to talk to you about today: the post-American Internet we can wrest from Trump's chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A post-American Internet that is possible because Trump has mobilized new coalition partners to join the fight on our side. In politics, coalitions are everything. Any time you see a group of people suddenly succeeding at a goal they have been failing to achieve, it's a sure bet that they've found some coalition partners, new allies who don't want all the same thing as the original forces, but want enough of the same things to fight on their side.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's where Trump came from: a coalition of billionaires, white nationalists, Christian bigots, authoritarians, conspiratorialists, imperialists, and self-described "libertarians" who've got such a scorching case of low-tax brain worms that they'd vote for Mussolini if he'd promise to lower their taxes by a nickel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And what's got me so excited is that we've got a new coalition in the War on General Purpose Computers: a coalition that includes the digital rights activists who've been on the lines for decades, but also people who want to turn America's Big Tech trillions into billions for their own economy, and national security hawks who are quite rightly worried about digital sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My thesis here is that this is an unstoppable coalition. Which is good news! For the first time in decades, victory is in our grasp.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So let me explain: 14 years ago, I stood in front of this group and explained the "War on General Purpose Computing." That was my snappy name for this fight, but the boring name that they use in legislatures for it is "anticircumvention,"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under anticircumvention law, it's a crime to alter the functioning of a digital product or service, unless the manufacturer approves of your modification, and – crucially – this is true whether or not your modification violates any other law.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anticircumvention law originates in the USA: Section 1201 of the Digital Millennium Copyright Act of 1998 establishes a felony punishable by a five year prison sentence and a $500,000 fine for a first offense for bypassing an "access control" for a copyrighted work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So practically speaking, if you design a device or service with even the flimsiest of systems to prevent modification of its application code or firmware, it's a felony – a jailable felony – to modify that code or firmware. It's also a felony to disclose information about how to bypass that access control, which means that pen-testers who even describe how they access a device or system face criminal liability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under anticircumvention law any manufacturer can trivially turn their product into a no-go zone, criminalizing the act of investigating its defects, criminalizing the act of reporting on its defects, and criminalizing the act of remediating its defects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a law that Jay Freeman rightly calls "Felony Contempt of Business Model." Anticircumvention became the law of the land in 1998 when Bill Clinton signed the DMCA. But before you start snickering at those stupid Americans, know this: every other country in the world has passed a law just like this in the years since. Here in the EU, it came in through Article 6 of the 2001 EU Copyright Directive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, it makes a certain twisted sense for the US to enact a law like this, after all, they are the world's tech powerhouse, home to the biggest, most powerful tech companies in the world. By making it illegal to modify digital products without the manufacturer's permission, America enhances the rent-extracting power of the most valuable companies on US stock exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But why would Europe pass a law like this? Europe is a massive tech importer. By extending legal protection to tech companies that want to steal their users' data and money, the EU was facilitating a one-way transfer of value from Europe to America. So why would Europe do this?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, let me tell you about the circumstances under which other countries came to enact their anticircumvention laws and maybe you'll spot a pattern that will answer this question.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Australia got its anticircumvention law through the US-Australia Free Trade Agreement, which obliges Australia to enact anticircumvention law.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Canada and Mexico got it through the US-Mexico-Canada Free Trade Agreement, which obliges Canada and Mexico to enact anticircumvention laws.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andean nations like Chile got their anticircumvention laws through bilateral US free trade agreements, which oblige them to enact anticircumvention laws.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the Central American nations got their anticircumvention laws through CAFTA – The Central American Free Trade Agreement with the USA – which obliges them to enact anticircumvention laws, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I assume you've spotted the pattern by now: the US trade representative has forced every one of its trading partners to adopt anticircumvention law, to facilitate the extraction of their own people's data and money by American firms. But of course, that only raises a further question: Why would every other country in the world agree to let America steal its own people's money and data, and block its domestic tech sector from making interoperable products that would prevent this theft?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's an anecdote that unravels this riddle: many years ago, in the years before Viktor Orban rose to power, I used to guest-lecture at a summer PhD program in political science at Budapest's Central European University. And one summer, after I'd lectured to my students about anticircumvention law, one of them approached me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They had been the information minister of a Central American nation during the CAFTA negotiations, and one day, they'd received a phone-call from their trade negotiator, calling from the CAFTA bargaining table. The negotiator said, "You know how you told me not to give the Americans anticircumvention under any circumstances? Well, they're saying that they won't take our coffee unless we give them anticircumvention. And I'm sorry, but we just can't lose the US coffee market. Our economy would collapse. So we're going to give them anticircumvention. I'm really sorry."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's it. That's why every government in the world allowed US Big Tech companies to declare open season on their people's private data and ready cash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The alternative was tariffs. Well, I don't know if you've heard, but we've got tariffs now!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I mean, if someone threatens to burn your house down unless you follow their orders, and then they burn your house down anyway, you don't have to keep following their orders. So…Happy Liberation Day?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So far, every country in the world has had one of two responses to the Trump tariffs. The first one is: "Give Trump everything he asks for (except Greenland) and hope he stops being mad at you." This has been an absolute failure. Give Trump an inch, he'll take a mile. He'll take fucking Greenland. Capitulation is a failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But so is the other tactic: retaliatory tariffs. That's what we've done in Canada (like all the best Americans, I'm Canadian). Our top move has been to levy tariffs on the stuff we import from America, making the things we buy more expensive. That's a weird way to punish America! It's like punching yourself in the face as hard as you can, and hoping the downstairs neighbor says "Ouch!"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it's indiscriminate. Why whack some poor farmer from a state that begins and ends with a vowel with tariffs on his soybeans. That guy never did anything bad to Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there's a third possible response to tariffs, one that's just sitting there, begging to be tried: what about repealing anticircumvention law?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're a technologist or an investor based in a country that's repealed its anticircumvention law, you can go into business making disenshittificatory products that plug into America's defective tech exports, allowing the people who own and use those products to use them in ways that are good for them, even if those uses make the company's shareholders mad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think of John Deere tractors: when a farmer's John Deere tractor breaks down, they are expected to repair it, swapping in new parts and assemblies to replace whatever's malfing. But the tractor won't recognize that new part and will not start working again, not until the farmer spends a couple hundred bucks on a service callout from an official John Deere tractor repair rep, whose only job is to type an unlock code into the tractor's console, to initialize the part and pair it with the tractor's main computing unit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modding a tractor to bypass this activation step violates anticircumvention law, meaning farmers all over the world are stuck with this ripoff garbage, because their own government will lock up anyone who makes a tractor mod that disables the parts-pairing check in this American product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what if Canada repealed Bill C-11, the Copyright Modernization Act of 2012 (that's our anticircumvention law)? Well, then a company like Honeybee, which makes tractor front-ends and attachments, could hire some smart University of Waterloo computer science grads, and put 'em to work jailbreaking the John Deere tractor's firmware, and offer it to everyone in the world. They could sell the crack to anyone with an internet connection and a payment method, including that poor American farmer whose soybeans we're currently tariffing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's hard to convey how much money is on the table here. Take just one example: Apple's App Store. Apple forces all app vendors into using its payment processor, and charges them a 30 percent commission on every euro spent inside of an app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;30 percent! That's such a profitable business that Apple makes $100 billion per year on it. If the EU repeals Article 6 of the Copyright Directive, some smart geeks in Finland could reverse-engineer Apple's bootloaders and make a hardware dongle that jailbreaks phones so that they can use alternative app stores, and sell the dongle – along with the infrastructure to operate an app store – to anyone in the world who wants to go into business competing with Apple for users and app vendors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those competitors could offer a 90% discount to every crafter on Etsy, every performer on Patreon, every online news outlet, every game dev, every media store. Offer them a 90% discount on payments, and still make $10b/year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe Finland will never see another Nokia, but Nokia's a tough business to be in. You've got to make hardware, which is expensive and risky. But if the EU legalizes jailbreaking, then Apple would have to incur all the expense and risk of making and fielding hardware, while those Finnish geeks could cream off the $100b Apple sucks out of the global economy in an act of a disgusting, rip-off rent-seeking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Jeff Bezos said to the publishers: "Your margin is my opportunity." With these guys, it's always "disruption for thee, but not for me." When they do it to us, that's progress. When we do it to them, it's piracy, and every pirate wants to be an admiral.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, screw that. Move fast and break Tim Cook's things. Move fast and break kings!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's funny: I spent 25 years getting my ass kicked by the US Trade Representative (in my defense, it wasn't a fair fight). I developed a kind of grudging admiration for the skill with which the USTR bound the entire world to a system of trade that conferred parochial advantages to America and its tech firms, giving them free rein to loot the world's data and economies. So it's been pretty amazing to watch Trump swiftly and decisively dismantle the global system of trade and destroy the case for the world continuing to arrange its affairs to protect the interests of America's capital class.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I mean, it's not a path I would have chosen. I'd have preferred no Trump at all to this breakthrough. But I'll take this massive own-goal if Trump insists. I mean, I'm not saying I've become an accelerationist, but at this point, I'm not exactly not an accelerationist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, you might have heard that governments around the world have been trying to get Apple to open its App Store, and they've totally failed at this. When the EU hit Apple with an enforcement order under the Digital Markets Act, Apple responded by offering to allow third party app stores, but it would only allow those stores to sell apps that Apple had approved of.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And while those stores could use their own payment processors, Apple would charge them so much in junk fees that it would be more expensive to process a payment using your own system, and if Apple believed that a user's phone had been outside of the EU for 21 days, they'd remotely delete all that user's data and apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the EU explained that this would not satisfy the regulation, Apple threatened to pull out of the EU. Then, once everyone had finished laughing, Apple filed more than a dozen bullshit objections to the order hoping to tie this up in court for a decade, the way Google and Meta did for the GDPR.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's not clear that the EU can force Apple to write code that opens up the iOS platform for alternative app stores and payment methods, but there is one thing that the EU can absolutely do with 100% reliability, any time they want: the EU can decide not to let Apple use Europe's courts to shut down European companies that defend European merchants, performers, makers, news outlets, game devs and creative workers, from Apple's ripoff, by jailbreaking phones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the EU has to do is repeal Article 6 of the Copyright Directive, and, in so doing, strip Apple of the privilege of mobilizing the European justice system to shore up Apple's hundred billion dollar annual tax on the world's digital economy. The EU company that figures out how to reliably jailbreak iPhones will have customers all over the world, including in the USA, where Apple doesn't just use its veto over which apps you can run on your phone to suck 30% out of every dollar you spend, but where Apple also uses its control over the platform to strip out apps that protect Apple's customers from Trump's fascist takeover.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back in October, Apple kicked the "ICE Block" app out of the App Store. That's an app that warns the user if there's a snatch squad of masked ICE thugs nearby looking to grab you off the street and send you to an offshore gulag. Apple internally classified ICE kidnappers as a "protected class," and then declared the ICE Block infringed on the rights of these poor, beset ICE goons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And speaking of ICE thugs, there are plenty of qualified technologists who have fled the US this year, one step ahead of an ICE platoon looking to put them and their children into a camp. Those skilled hackers are now living all over the world, joined by investors who'd like to back a business whose success will be determined by how awesome its products are, and not how many $TRUMP coins they buy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple's margin could be their opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Legalizing jailbreaking, raiding the highest margin lines of business of the most profitable companies in America is a much better response to the Trump tariffs than retaliatory tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For one thing, this is a targeted response: go after Big Tech's margins and you're mounting a frontal assault on the businesses whose CEOs each paid a million bucks to sit behind Trump on the inauguration dais.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raiding Big Tech's margins is not an attack on the American people, nor on the small American businesses that are ripped off by Big Tech. It's a raid on the companies that screw everyday Americans and everyone else in the world. It's a way to make everyone in the world richer at the expense of these ripoff companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It beats the shit out of blowing hundreds of billions of dollars building AI data-centers in the hopes that someday, a sector that's lost nearly a trillion dollars shipping defective chatbots will figure out a use for GPUs that doesn't start hemorrhaging money the minute they plug them in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So here are our new allies in the war on general-purpose computation: businesses and technologists who want to make billions of dollars raiding Big Tech's margins, and policymakers who want their country to be the disenshittification nation – the country that doesn't merely protect its people's money and privacy by buying jailbreaks from other countries, but rather, the country that makes billions of dollars selling that privacy and pocketbook-defending tech to the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's a powerful alliance, but those are not the only allies Trump has pushed into our camp. There's another powerful ally waiting in the wings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remember last June, when the International Criminal Court in the Hague issued an arrest warrant for the génocidaire Benjamin Netanyahu, and Trump denounced the ICC, and then the ICC lost its Outlook access, its email archives, its working files, its address books, its calendars?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft says they didn't brick the ICC – that it's a coincidence. But when it comes to a he-said/Clippy-said between the justices of the ICC and the convicted monopolists of Microsoft, I know who I believe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is exactly the kind of infrastructural risk that we were warned of if we let Chinese companies like Huawei supply our critical telecoms equipment. Virtually every government ministry, every major corporation, every small business and every household in the world have locked themselves into a US-based, cloud-based service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The handful of US Big Tech companies that supply the world's administrative tools are all vulnerable to pressure from the Trump admin, and that means that Trump can brick an entire nation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attack on the ICC was an act of cyberwarfare, like the Russian hackers who shut down Ukrainian power-generation facilities, except that Microsoft doesn't have to hack Outlook to brick the ICC – they own Outlook.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the US CLOUD Act of 2018, the US government can compel any US-based company to disclose any of its users' data – including foreign governments – and this is true no matter where that data is stored. Last July, Anton Carniaux, Director of Public and Legal Affairs at Microsoft France, told a French government inquiry that he "couldn't guarantee" that Microsoft wouldn't hand sensitive French data over to the US government, even if that data was stored in a European data-center.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And under the CLOUD Act, the US government can slap gag orders on the companies that it forces to cough up that data, so there'd be no way to even know if this happened, or whether it's already happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It doesn't stop at administrative tools, either: remember back in 2022, when Putin's thugs looted millions of dollars' worth of John Deere tractors from Ukraine and those tractors showed up in Chechnya? The John Deere company pushed an over-the-air kill signal to those tractors and bricked 'em.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;John Deere is every bit as politically vulnerable to the Trump admin as Microsoft is, and they can brick most of the tractors in the world, and the tractors they can't brick are probably made by Massey Ferguson, the number-two company in the ag-tech cartel, which is also an American company and just as vulnerable to political attacks from the US government.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, none of this will be news to global leaders. Even before Trump and Microsoft bricked the ICC they were trying to figure out a path to "digital sovereignty." But the Trump administration's outrageous conduct and rhetoric over past 11 months has turned "digital sovereignty" from a nice-to-have into a must-have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So finally, we're seeing some movement, like "Eurostack," a project to clone the functionality of US Big Tech silos in free/open source software, and to build EU-based data-centers that this code can run on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Eurostack is heading for a crisis. It's great to build open, locally hosted, auditable, trustworthy services that replicate the useful features of Big Tech, but you also need to build the adversarial interoperability tools that allow for mass exporting of millions of documents, the sensitive data-structures and edit histories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need scrapers and headless browsers to accomplish the adversarial interoperability that will guarantee ongoing connectivity to institutions that are still hosted on US cloud-based services, because US companies are not going to facilitate the mass exodus of international customers from their platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just think of how Apple responded to the relatively minor demand to open up the iOS App Store, and now imagine the thermonuclear foot-dragging, tantrum-throwing and malicious compliance they'll come up with when faced with the departure of a plurality of the businesses and governments in a 27-nation bloc of 500,000,000 affluent consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any serious attempt at digital sovereignty needs migration tools that work without the cooperation of the Big Tech companies. Otherwise, this is like building housing for East Germans and locating it in West Berlin. It doesn't matter how great the housing is, your intended audience is going to really struggle to move in unless you tear down the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Step one of tearing down that wall is killing anticircumvention law, so that we can run virtual devices that can be scripted, break bootloaders to swap out firmware and generally seize the means of computation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So this is the third bloc in the disenshittification army: not just digital rights hippies like me; not just entrepreneurs and economic development wonks rubbing their hands together at the thought of transforming American trillions into European billions; but also the national security hawks who are 100% justified in their extreme concern about their country's reliance on American platforms that have been shown to be totally unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is how we'll get a post-American internet: with an unstoppable coalition of activists, entrepreneurs and natsec hawks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This has been a long time coming. Since the post-war settlement, the world has treated the US as a neutral platform, a trustworthy and stable maintainer of critical systems for global interchange, what the political scientists Henry Farrell and Abraham Newman call the "Underground Empire." But over the past 15 years, the US has systematically shattered global trust in its institutions, a process that only accelerated under Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take transoceanic fiber optic cables: the way the transoceanic fiber routes were planned, the majority of these cables make landfall on the coasts of the USA where the interconnections are handled. There's a good case for this hub-and-spoke network topology, especially compared to establishing direct links between every country. That's an Order(N^2) problem: directly linking each of the planet Earth's 205 countries to every other country would require 20,910 fiber links.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But putting all the world's telecoms eggs in America's basket only works if the US doesn't take advantage of its centrality, and while many people worried about what the US could do with the head-ends of the world's global fiber infra, it wasn't until Mark Klein's 2006 revelations about the NSA's nation-scale fiber optic taps in AT&amp;amp;T's network, and Ed Snowden's 2013 documents showing the global scale of this wiretapping, that the world had to confront the undeniable reality that the US could not be trusted to serve as the world's fiber hub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's not just fiber. The world does business in dollars. Most countries maintain dollar accounts at the Fed in New York as their major source of foreign reserves. But in 2005, American vulture capitalists bought up billions of dollars worth of Argentinian government bonds after the sovereign nation of Argentina had declared bankruptcy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They convinced a judge in New York to turn over the government of Argentina's US assets to them to make good on loans that these debt collectors had not issued, but had bought up at pennies on the dollar. At that moment, every government in the world had to confront the reality that they could not trust the US Federal Reserve with their foreign reserves. But what else could they use?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without a clear answer, dollar dominance continued, but then, under Biden, Putin-aligned oligarchs and Russian firms lost access to the SWIFT system for dollar clearing. This is when goods – like oil – are priced in dollars, so that buyers only need to find someone who will trade their own currency for dollars, which they can then swap for any commodity in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, there's a sound case for dollar clearing: it's just not practical to establish deep, liquid pairwise trading market for all of the world's nearly 200 currencies, it's another O(N^2) problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it only works if the dollar is a neutral platform. Once the dollar becomes an instrument of US foreign policy – whether or not you agree with that policy – it's no longer a neutral platform, and the world goes looking for an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No one knows what that alternative's going to be, just as no one knows what configuration the world's fiber links will end up taking. There's kilometers of fiber being stretched across the ocean floor, and countries are trying out some pretty improbable gambits as dollar alternatives, like Ethiopia revaluing its sovereign debt in Chinese renminbi. Without a clear alternative to America's enshittified platforms, the post-American century is off to a rocky start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there's one post-American system that's easy to imagine. The project to rip out all the cloud connected, backdoored, untrustworthy black boxes that power our institutions, our medical implants, our vehicles and our tractors; and replace it with collectively maintained, open, free, trustworthy, auditable code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is the only one that benefits from economies of scale, rather than being paralyzed by exponential crises of scale. That's because any open, free tool adopted by any public institution – like the Eurostack services – can be audited, localized, pen-tested, debugged and improved by institutions in every other country.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's a commons, more like a science than a technology, in that it is universal and international and collaborative. We don't have dueling western and Chinese principles of structural engineering. Rather, we have universal principles for making sure buildings don't fall down, adapted to local circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We wouldn't tolerate secrecy in the calculations used to keep our buildings upright, and we shouldn't tolerate opacity in the software that keeps our tractors, hearing aids, ventilators, pacemakers, trains, games consoles, phones, CCTVs, door locks, and government ministries working.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thing is, software is not an asset, it's a liability. The capabilities that running software delivers – automation, production, analysis and administration – those are assets. But the software itself? That's a liability. Brittle, fragile, forever breaking down as the software upstream of it, downstream of it, and adjacent to it is updated or swapped out, revealing defects and deficiencies in systems that may have performed well for years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shifting software to commons-based production is a way to reduce the liability that software imposes on its makers and users, balancing out that liability among many players.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, obviously, tech bosses are totally clueless when it comes to this. They really do think that software is an asset. That's why they're so fucking horny to have chatbots shit out software at superhuman speeds. That's why they think it's good that they've got a chatbot that "produces a thousand times more code than a human programmer."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Producing code that isn't designed for legibility and maintainability, that is optimized, rather, for speed of production, is a way to incur tech debt at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a neat encapsulation of the whole AI story: the chatbot can't do your job, but an AI salesman can convince your boss to fire you and replace you with a chatbot that can't do your job.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your boss is an easy mark for that chatbot hustler because your boss hates you. In their secret hearts, bosses understand that if they stopped coming to work, the business would run along just fine, but if the workers stopped showing up, the company would grind to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bosses like to tell themselves that they're in the driver's seat, but really, they fear that they're strapped into the back seat playing with a Fisher Price steering wheel. For them, AI is a way to wire the toy steering wheel directly into the company's drive-train. It's the realization of the fantasy of a company without workers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I was walking the picket line in Hollywood during the writer's strike, a writer told me that you prompt an AI the same way a studio boss gives shitty notes to a writer's room: "Make me ET, but make it about a dog, and give it a love interest, and a car-chase in the third act."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Say that to a writer's room and they will call you a fucking idiot suit and tell you "Why don't you go back to your office and make a spreadsheet, you nitwit. The grownups here are writing a movie."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, if you give that prompt to a chatbot, it will cheerfully shit out a script exactly to spec. The fact that this script will be terrible and unusable is less important than the prospect of a working life in which no one calls you a fucking idiot suit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI dangles the promise of a writer's room without writers, a movie without actors, a hospital without nurses, a coding shop without coders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Mark Zuckerberg went on a podcast and announced that the average American had three friends, but wanted 15 friends, and that he could solve this by giving us chatbots instead of friends, we all dunked on him as an out-of-touch billionaire Martian who didn't understand the nature of friendship.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the reality is that for Zuck, your friends are a problem. Your friends' interactions with you determine how much time you spend on his platforms, and thus how many revenue-generating ads he can show you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your friends stubbornly refuse to organize their relationship with you in a way that maximizes the return to his shareholders. So Zuck is over there in Menlo Park, furiously fantasizing about replacing your friends with chatbots, because that way, he can finally realize the dream of a social media service without any socializing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rich, powerful people are, at root, solipsists. The only way to amass a billion dollars is to inflict misery and privation on whole populations. The only way to look yourself in the mirror after you've done that, is to convince yourself that those people don't matter, that, in some important sense, they aren't real.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think of Elon Musk calling everyone who disagrees with him an "NPC,” or all those "Effective Altruists," who claimed the moral high ground by claiming to care about 53 trillion imaginary artificial humans who will come into existence in 10,000 years at the expense of extending moral consideration to people alive today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or think of how Trump fired all the US government scientists, and then announced the "Genesis" program, declaring that the US would begin generating annual "moonshot"-scale breakthroughs, with a chatbot. It's science without scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chatbots can't really do science, but from Trump's perspective, they're still better than scientists, because a chatbot won't ever tell him not to stare at an eclipse, or not to inject bleach. A chatbot won't ever tell him that trans people exist, or that the climate emergency is real.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Powerful people are suckers for AI, because AI fuels the fantasy of a world without people: just a boss and a computer, and no ego-shattering confrontations with people who know how to do things telling you "no."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI is a way to produce tech debt at scale, to replace skilled writers with defective spicy autocomplete systems, to lose money at a rate not seen in living memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, compare that with the project of building a post-American internet: a project to reduce tech debt, to unlock America's monopoly trillions and divide them among the world's entrepreneurs (for whom they represent untold profits), and the world's technology users (for whom they represent untold savings); all while building resiliency and sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, some of you are probably feeling pretty cynical about this right now. After all, your political leaders have demonstrated decades of ineffectual and incompetent deference to the US, and an inability to act, even when the need was dire. If your leaders couldn't act decisively on the climate emergency, what hope do we have of them taking this moment seriously?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But crises precipitate change. Remember when another mad emperor – Vladimir Putin – invaded Ukraine, and Europe experienced a dire energy shortage? In three short years, the continent's solar uptake skyrocketed. The EU went from being 15 years behind in its energy transition, to ten years ahead of schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because when you're shivering in the dark, a lot of fights you didn't think were worth it are suddenly existential battles you can't afford to lose. Sure, no one wants to argue with a tedious neighbor who has an aesthetic temper tantrum at the thought of a solar panel hanging from their neighbor's balcony.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But when it's winter, and there's no Russian gas, and you're shivering in the dark, then that person can take their aesthetic objection to balcony solar, fold it until it's all corners, and shove it right up their ass.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Besides, we don't need Europe to lead the charge on a post-American internet by repealing anticircumvention. Any country could do it! And the country that gets there first gets to reap the profits from supplying jailbreaking tools to the rest of the world, it gets to be the Disenshittification Nation, and everyone else in the world gets to buy those tools and defend themselves from US tech companies' monetary and privacy plunder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just one country has to break the consensus, and the case for every country doing so is the strongest it's ever been. It used to be that countries that depended on USAID had to worry about losing food, medical and cash supports if they pissed off America. But Trump killed USAID, so now that's a dead letter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, America's status as the planet's most voracious consumer has been gutted by decades of anti-worker, pro-billionaire policies. Today, the US is in the grips of its third consecutive "K-shaped" recovery, that's an economic rally where the rich get richer, and everyone else gets poorer. For a generation, America papered over that growing inequality with easy credit, with everyday Americans funding their consumption with credit cards and second and third mortgages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So long as they could all afford to keep buying, other countries had to care about America as an export market. But a generation of extraction has left the bottom 90% of Americans struggling to buy groceries and other necessities, carrying crushing debt from skyrocketing shelter, education and medical expenses that they can't hope to pay down, thanks to 50 years of wage stagnation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has sided firmly with debt collectors, price gougers, and rent extractors. Trump neutered enforcement against rent-fixing platforms like Realpage, restarted debt payments for eight million student borrowers, and killed a plan to make live-saving drugs a little cheaper, leaving Americans to continue to pay the highest drug prices in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every dollar spent servicing a loan is a dollar that can't go to consumption. And as more and more Americans slip into poverty, the US is gutting programs that spend money on the public's behalf, like SNAP, the food stamps program that helps an ever-larger slice of the American public stave off hunger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;America is chasing the "world without people" dream, where working people have nothing, spend nothing, and turn every penny over to rentiers who promptly flush that money into the stock market, shitcoins, or gambling sites. But I repeat myself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even the US military – long a sacrosanct institution – is being kneecapped to enrich rent-seekers. Congress just killed a military "right to repair" law. So now, US soldiers stationed abroad will have to continue the Pentagon's proud tradition of shipping materiel from generators to jeeps back to America to be fixed by their manufacturers at a 10,000% markup, because the Pentagon routinely signs maintenance contracts that prohibit it from teaching a Marine how to fix an engine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The post-American world is really coming on fast. As we repeal our anticircumvention laws, we don't have to care what America thinks, we don't have to care about their tariffs, because they're already whacking us with tariffs; and because the only people left in the US who can afford to buy things are rich people, who just don't buy enough stuff. There's only so many Lambos and Sub-Zeros even the most guillotineable plute can usefully own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what if European firms want to go on taking advantage of anticircumvention laws? Well, there's good news there, too. "Good news," because the EU firms that rely on anticircumvention are engaged in the sleaziest, most disgusting frauds imaginable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anticircumvention law is the reason that Volkswagen could get away with Dieselgate. By imposing legal liability on reverse-engineers who might have discovered this lethal crime, Article 6 of the Copyright Directive created a chilling effect, and thousands of Europeans died, every year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, Germany's storied automakers are carrying on the tradition of Dieselgate, sabotaging their cars to extract rent from drivers. From Mercedes, which rents you the accelerator pedal in your luxury car, only unlocking the full acceleration curve of your engine if you buy a monthly subscription; to BMW, which rents you the automated system that automatically dims your high-beams if there's oncoming traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Legalize jailbreaking and any mechanic in Europe could unlock those subscription features for one price, and not share any of that money with BMW and Mercedes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then there's Medtronic, a company that pretends it is Irish. Medtronic is the world's largest med-tech company, having purchased all their competitors, and then undertaken the largest "tax-inversion" in history, selling themselves to a tiny Irish firm, in order to magick their profits into a state of untaxable grace, floating in the Irish Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Medtronic supplies the world's most widely used ventilators, and it booby-traps them the same way John Deere booby-traps its tractors. After a hospital technician puts a new part in a Medtronic ventilator, the ventilator's central computing unit refuses to recognize the part until it completes a cryptographic handshake, proving that an authorized Medtronic technician was paid hundreds of euros to certify a repair that the hospital's own technician probably performed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's just a way to suck hundreds of euros out of hospitals every time a ventilator breaks. This would be bad enough, but during the covid lockdowns, when every ventilator was desperately needed, and when the planes stopped flying, there was no way for a Medtronic tech to come and bless the hospital technicians' repairs. This was lethal. It killed people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's one more European company that relies on anticircumvention that I want to discuss here, because they're old friends of CCC: that's the Polish train company Newag. Newag sabotages its own locomotives, booby-trapping them so that if they sense they have been taken to a rival's service yard, the train bricks itself. When the train operator calls Newag about this mysterious problem, the company "helpfully" remotes into the locomotive's computers, to perform "diagnostics," which is just sending a unbricking command to the vehicle, a service for which they charge 20,000 euros.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last year, Polish hackers from the security research firm Dragon Sector presented on their research into this disgusting racket in this very hall, and now, they're being sued by Newag under anticircumvention law, for making absolutely true disclosures about Newag's deliberately defective products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So these are the European stakeholders for anticircumvention law: the Dieselgate killers, the car companies who want to rent you your high-beams and accelerator, the med-tech giant that bricked all the ventilators during the pandemic, and the company that tied Poland to the train-tracks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I relish the opportunity to fight these bastards in Brussels, as they show up and cry "Won't someone think of the train saboteurs?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The enshittification of technology – the decay of the platforms and systems we rely on – has many causes: the collapse of competition, regulatory capture, the smashing of tech workers' power. But most of all, enshittification is the result of anticircumvention law's ban on interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By blocking interop, by declaring war on the general-purpose computer, our policy-makers created an enshittogenic environment that rewarded companies for being shitty, and ushered in the enshittocene, in which everything is turning to shit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's call time on enshittification. Let's seize the means of computation. Let's build the drop-in, free, open, auditable alternatives to the services and firmware we rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's end the era of silos. I mean, isn't it fucking weird how you have to care which network someone is using if you want to talk to them? Instead of just deciding who you want to talk to?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact that you have to figure out whether the discussion you're trying to join is on Twitter or Bluesky, Mastodon or Instagram – that is just the most Prodigy/AOL/Compuserve-ass way of running a digital world. I mean, 1990 called and they want their walled gardens back&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Powerful allies are joining our side in the War on General Purpose Computation. It's not just people like us, who've been fighting for this whole goddamned century, but also countries that want to convert American tech's hoarded trillions into fuel for a single-use rocket that boosts their own tech sector into a stable orbit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's national security hawks who are worried about Trump bricking their ministries or their tractors, and who are also worried – with just cause – about Xi Jinping bricking all their solar inverters and batteries. Because, after all, the post-American internet is also a post-Chinese internet!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nothing should be designed to be field updatable without the user's permission. Nothing critical should be a black box.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like I said at the start of this talk, I have been doing this work for 24 years at the Electronic Frontier Foundation, throwing myself at a door that was double-locked and deadbolted, and now that door is open a crack and goddammit, I am hopeful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not optimistic. Fuck optimism! Optimism is the idea that things will get better no matter what we do. I know that what we do matters. Hope is the belief that if we can improve things, even in small ways, we can ascend the gradient toward the world we want, and attain higher vantage points from which new courses of action, invisible to us here at our lower elevation, will be revealed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hope is a discipline. It requires that you not give in to despair. So I'm here to tell you: don't despair.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All this decade, all over the world, countries have taken up arms against concentrated corporate power. We've had big, muscular antitrust attacks on big corporations in the US (under Trump I and Biden); in Canada; in the UK; in the EU and member states like Germany, France and Spain; in Australia; in Japan and South Korea and Singapore; in Brazil; and in China.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a near-miraculous turn of affairs. All over the world, governments are declaring war on monopolies, the source of billionaires' wealth and power.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even the most forceful wind is invisible. We can only see it by its effects. What we're seeing here is that whenever a politician bent on curbing corporate power unfurls a sail, no matter where in the world that politician is, that sail fills with wind and propels the policy in ways that haven't been seen in generations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The long becalming of the fight over corporate power has ended, and a fierce, unstoppable wind is blowing. It's not just blowing in Europe, or in Canada, or in South Korea, Japan, China, Australia or Brazil. It's blowing in America, too. Never forget that as screwed up and terrifying as things are in America, the country has experienced, and continues to experience, a tsunami of antitrust bills and enforcement actions at the local, state and federal level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And never forget that the post-American internet will be good for Americans. Because, in a K-shaped, bifurcated, unequal America, the trillions that American companies loot from the world don't trickle down to Americans. The average American holds a portfolio of assets that rounds to zero, and that includes stock in US tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The average American isn't a shareholder in Big Tech, the average American is a victim of Big Tech. Liberating the world from US Big Tech is also liberating America from US Big Tech.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's been EFF's mission for 35 years. It's been my mission at EFF for 25 years. If you want to get involved in this fight – and I hope you do – it can be your mission, too. You can join EFF, and you can join groups in your own country, like Netzpolitik here in Germany, or the Irish Council for Civil Liberties, or La Quadrature du Net in France, or the Open Rights Group in the UK, or EF Finland, or ISOC Bulgaria, XNet, DFRI, Quintessenz, Bits of Freedom, Openmedia, FSFE, or any of dozens of organizations around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The door is open a crack, the wind is blowing, the post-American internet is upon us: a new, good internet that delivers all the technological self-determination of the old, good internet, and the ease of use of Web 2.0 so that our normie friends can use it, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And I can't wait for all of us to get to hang out there. It's gonna be great.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Hey look at this (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Enshittifinancial Crisis https://www.wheresyoured.at/the-enshittifinancial-crisis/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Austrian Supreme Court: Meta must give users full access to their data https://noyb.eu/en/austrian-supreme-court-meta-must-give-users-full-access-their-data&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;the myth of merit in the managerial class https://backofmind.substack.com/p/the-myth-of-merit-in-the-managerial&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;ECI, Ethical Computing Initiative https://aol.codeberg.page/eci/&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;BMW Patents Proprietary Screws That Only Dealerships Can Remove https://carbuzz.com/bmw-roundel-logo-screw-patent/&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Object permanence (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#20yrsago Online sf mag Infinite Matrix goes out with a bang – new Gibson, Rucker, Kelly https://web.archive.org/web/20060101120510/https://www.infinitematrix.net/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#20yrsago Wil McCarthy’s wonderful “Hacking Matter” as a free download https://web.archive.org/web/20060103052051/http://wilmccarthy.com/hm.htm&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#15yrsago Papa Sangre: binaural video game with no video https://web.archive.org/web/20101224170833/http://www.papasangre.com/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#15yrsago DDoS versus human rights organizations https://cyber.harvard.edu/publications/2010/DDoS_Independent_Media_Human_Rights&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#15yrsago Why I have a public email address https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2010/dec/21/keeping-email-address-secret-spambots&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#15yrsago How the FCC failed the nation on Net Neutrality https://web.archive.org/web/20101224075655/https://www.salon.com/technology/network_neutrality/index.html?story=/tech/dan_gillmor/2010/12/21/fcc_network_neutrality&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#15yrsago Bankster robberies: Bank of America and friends wrongfully foreclose on customers, steal all their belongings https://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/22/business/22lockout.html?_r=1&amp;amp;amp;hp&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago India’s deadly exam-rigging scandal: murder, corruption, suicide and scapegoats https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/dec/17/the-mystery-of-indias-deadly-exam-scam&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Copyright infringement “gang” raided by UK cops: 3 harmless middle-aged karaoke fans https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2015/12/uk-police-busts-karaoke-gang-for-sharing-songs-that-arent-commercially-available/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago IETF approves HTTP error code 451 for Internet censorship https://web.archive.org/web/20151222155906/https://motherboard.vice.com/read/the-http-451-error-code-for-censorship-is-now-an-internet-standard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Billionaire Sheldon Adelson secretly bought newspaper, ordered all hands to investigate judges he hated https://web.archive.org/web/20151220081546/http://www.reviewjournal.com/news/las-vegas/judge-adelson-lawsuit-subject-unusual-scrutiny-amid-review-journal-sale&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Tax havens hold $7.6 trillion; 8% of world’s total wealth https://web.archive.org/web/20160103142942/https://www.nybooks.com/articles/2016/01/14/parking-the-big-money/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Mansplaining Lolita https://lithub.com/men-explain-lolita-to-me/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Lifelock admits it lied in its ads (again), agrees to $100M fine https://web.archive.org/web/20151218000258/https://consumerist.com/2015/12/17/identity-theft-company-lifelock-once-again-failed-to-actually-keep-identities-protected-must-pay-100m/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Uninsured driver plows through gamer’s living-room wall and creams him mid-Fallout 4 https://www.gofundme.com/f/helpforbenzo&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Juniper Networks backdoor confirmed, password revealed, NSA suspected https://www.wired.com/2015/12/juniper-networks-hidden-backdoors-show-the-risk-of-government-backdoors/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago A survivalist on why you shouldn’t bug out https://waldenlabs.com/10-reasons-not-to-bug-out/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#1yrago Nurses whose shitty boss is a shitty app https://pluralistic.net/2024/12/18/loose-flapping-ends/#luigi-has-a-point&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#1yrago Proud to be a blockhead https://pluralistic.net/2024/12/21/blockheads-r-us/#vocational-awe&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Upcoming appearances (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Denver: Enshittification at Tattered Cover Colfax, Jan 22&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/cory-doctorow-live-at-tattered-cover-colfax-tickets-1976644174937&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Colorado Springs: Guest of Honor at COSine, Jan 23-25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.firstfridayfandom.org/cosine/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ottawa: Enshittification at Perfect Books, Jan 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.instagram.com/p/DS2nGiHiNUh/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Toronto: Enshittification and the Age of Extraction with Tim Wu, Jan 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://nowtoronto.com/event/cory-doctorow-and-tim-wu-enshittification-and-extraction/&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recent appearances (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Enshitification Life Cycle with David Dayen (Organized Money)&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.buzzsprout.com/2412334/episodes/18399894&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enshittificaition on The Last Show With David Cooper:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.iheart.com/podcast/256-the-last-show-with-david-c-31145360/episode/cory-doctorow-enshttification-december-16-2025-313385767&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Digital) Elbows Up (OCADU)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://vimeo.com/1146281673&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;How to Stop “Ensh*ttification” Before It Kills the Internet (Capitalisn't)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=34gkIvYiHxU&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enshittification on The Daily Show&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d2e-c9SF5nE&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Latest books (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Canny Valley": A limited edition collection of the collages I create for Pluralistic, self-published, September 2025&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Enshittification: Why Everything Suddenly Got Worse and What to Do About It," Farrar, Straus, Giroux, October 7 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://us.macmillan.com/books/9780374619329/enshittification/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"Picks and Shovels": a sequel to "Red Team Blues," about the heroic era of the PC, Tor Books (US), Head of Zeus (UK), February 2025 (https://us.macmillan.com/books/9781250865908/picksandshovels).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Bezzle": a sequel to "Red Team Blues," about prison-tech and other grifts, Tor Books (US), Head of Zeus (UK), February 2024 (thebezzle.org).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Lost Cause:" a solarpunk novel of hope in the climate emergency, Tor Books (US), Head of Zeus (UK), November 2023 (http://lost-cause.org).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Internet Con": A nonfiction book about interoperability and Big Tech (Verso) September 2023 (http://seizethemeansofcomputation.org). Signed copies at Book Soup (https://www.booksoup.com/book/9781804291245).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"Red Team Blues": "A grabby, compulsive thriller that will leave you knowing more about how the world works than you did before." Tor Books http://redteamblues.com.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"Chokepoint Capitalism: How to Beat Big Tech, Tame Big Content, and Get Artists Paid, with Rebecca Giblin", on how to unrig the markets for creative labor, Beacon Press/Scribe 2022 https://chokepointcapitalism.com&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Upcoming books (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Unauthorized Bread": a middle-grades graphic novel adapted from my novella about refugees, toasters and DRM, FirstSecond, 2026&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"Enshittification, Why Everything Suddenly Got Worse and What to Do About It" (the graphic novel), Firstsecond, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Memex Method," Farrar, Straus, Giroux, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Reverse-Centaur's Guide to AI," a short book about being a better AI critic, Farrar, Straus and Giroux, June 2026&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Colophon (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today's top sources:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently writing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"The Reverse Centaur's Guide to AI," a short book for Farrar, Straus and Giroux about being an effective AI critic. LEGAL REVIEW AND COPYEDIT COMPLETE.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Post-American Internet," a short book about internet policy in the age of Trumpism. PLANNING.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A Little Brother short story about DIY insulin PLANNING&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work – excluding any serialized fiction – is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license. That means you can use it any way you like, including commercially, provided that you attribute it to me, Cory Doctorow, and include a link to pluralistic.net.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quotations and images are not included in this license; they are included either under a limitation or exception to copyright, or on the basis of a separate license. Please exercise caution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How to get Pluralistic:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blog (no ads, tracking, or data-collection):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Newsletter (no ads, tracking, or data-collection):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://pluralistic.net/plura-list&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mastodon (no ads, tracking, or data-collection):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Medium (no ads, paywalled):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Twitter (mass-scale, unrestricted, third-party surveillance and advertising):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tumblr (mass-scale, unrestricted, third-party surveillance and advertising):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://mostlysignssomeportents.tumblr.com/tagged/pluralistic&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"When life gives you SARS, you make sarsaparilla" -Joey "Accordion Guy" DeVilla&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;READ CAREFULLY: By reading this, you agree, on behalf of your employer, to release me from all obligations and waivers arising from any and all NON-NEGOTIATED agreements, licenses, terms-of-service, shrinkwrap, clickwrap, browsewrap, confidentiality, non-disclosure, non-compete and acceptable use policies ("BOGUS AGREEMENTS") that I have entered into with your employer, its partners, licensors, agents and assigns, in perpetuity, without prejudice to my ongoing rights and privileges. You further represent that you have the authority to release me from any BOGUS AGREEMENTS on behalf of your employer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ISSN: 3066-764X&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://pluralistic.net/2026/01/01/39c3/"/><published>2026-01-06T05:20:40+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46509211</id><title>enclose.horse</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:38.698744+00:00</updated><link href="https://enclose.horse/"/><published>2026-01-06T06:01:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46509967</id><title>Tube trains could navigate the Underground using the rules of Quantum Physics</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:37.684024+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="eb08939a2ea5d5e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Tube trains could navigate the Underground using the weird rules of Quantum Physics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tube trains of the future may soon know exactly where they are underground — even in places where GPS is blind — by tapping into the strange rules of the quantum world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most modern tracking systems rely on satellites to pinpoint location, backed up by accelerometers that measure tiny movements between GPS updates. It works well enough above ground, but those accelerometers gradually drift, which is why they constantly need satellite corrections.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, in tunnels or urban areas surrounded by tall buildings where GPS signals don’t reach, that safety net disappears.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So researchers are turning to something far more exotic: quantum accelerometers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of relying on conventional sensors, these devices use clouds of atoms cooled to near absolute zero. At those temperatures, atoms start to behave strangely — acting as both particles and waves. As the atoms “fall” through a sensor, their wave patterns shift in response to acceleration. Using what’s effectively an ultra-precise optical ruler, the system can read these changes with extraordinary accuracy, without needing satellites at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That technology is now moving closer to the railway. Research firm MoniRail has secured an additional £1.25 million from the UK government’s quantum technology programme to advance the work. The funding supports the next phase of the Rail Quantum Inertial Navigation System (RQINS) roadmap, aimed at developing quantum navigation for the London Underground — and potentially the wider national rail network.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MoniRail’s approach goes beyond simple positioning. Sensors fitted to trains already provide a non-intrusive way to monitor track condition, collecting ride-quality data and flagging emerging faults in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Naturally, trains already have track-based location systems, but they are usually based on a train being within a “moving block”, so their accuracy is down to metres rather than centimetres. If you want to monitor track conditions, the more accurate the location of the suspected fault, the less time staff spend repairing it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quantum navigation could shrink that uncertainty to centimetres, making it far quicker to pinpoint exactly where a defect lies. Underground, it could deliver the sort of location precision passengers have come to expect above ground — while also acting as a robust fallback above ground if GPS is unavailable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It might seem like a nice-to-have, but in troubled times, it would not be unrealistic to expect a hostile government (or solar flares) to knock out satellite networks, with substantial impacts on society, especially as estimates suggest that a single day of GPS disruption could cost the UK economy more than £1.4 billion. A system that can keep working independently of space-based infrastructure suddenly looks less like a luxury and more like an insurance policy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As long as the vehicle has a known starting point, quantum accelerometers can continue tracking its movement accurately, regardless of what’s happening above the atmosphere. In other words, the future of mobile navigation may depend on supercold atoms behaving very strangely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The project is being carried out in collaboration with Transport for London, QinetiQ, PA Consulting, Imperial College London and University of Sussex.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Steve Venables, Senior Engineer at Transport for London, said: “Being a partner in the RQINS project has highlighted the transformative potential of quantum navigation and the importance of continued investment and collaboration to bring these innovations to life. We commit our support and partnerships with industry and academia to deliver tangible benefits to the UK rail infrastructure, with a focus on real-world impact and long-term resilience. We look forward to being part of the development roadmap in this next phase of UKRI funding.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ianvisits.co.uk/articles/tube-trains-could-navigate-the-underground-using-the-weird-rules-of-quantum-physics-86370/"/><published>2026-01-06T08:26:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46510625</id><title>SCiZE's Classic Warez Collection</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:36.615006+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b603dfc87132d888"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;SCiZE's CLASSIC WAREZ COLLECTION&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; From 1990 onwards I used to roam BBS's, trading and collecting warez.&lt;lb/&gt; Fast forward over 20 years and I still have very fond memories of the 90's BBS scene.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; I've put the filelists from those days online here.&lt;lb/&gt; Or browse them on my BBS.&lt;lb/&gt; Search for and view the release nfo's here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; The lists are displayed as they originally were on BBS's with all their FILE_ID.DIZ ascii magic.&lt;lb/&gt; Anyone who shares the same nostalgic feelings as me can browse to this website and look through the lists of days gone by.&lt;lb/&gt; These were the golden years of the warez scene as far as I was concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm very interested in getting in touch with other sceners from the past so if you stumble upon this page please send me an email .&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;NFO SEARCH&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Find releases based on keywords an/or filenames and view their NFO. Filtering on year also supported (e.g. 'pwa 1993').&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://scenelist.org/"/><published>2026-01-06T10:13:43+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46511153</id><title>AWS raises GPU prices 15% on a Saturday, hopes you weren't paying attention</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:36.381970+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="4c00405dad86879c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;AWS raises GPU prices 15% on a Saturday, hopes you weren't paying attention&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;An anomaly or the beginning of a new trend? My bet's on the latter&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've been tracking AWS for a long time, with a specific emphasis on pricing. "What happens if AWS hikes prices" has always been something of a boogeyman, trotted out as a hypothetical to urge folks to avoid taking dependencies on a given provider.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the weekend - on a Saturday, no less - that hypothetical became real.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS has quietly raised prices on its EC2 Capacity Blocks for ML by approximately 15 percent. The p5e.48xlarge instance – eight NVIDIA H200 accelerators in a trenchcoat – jumped from $34.61 to $39.80 per hour across most regions, while the p5en.48xlarge climbed from $36.18 to $41.61. Customers in US West (N. California) face steeper hikes, with p5e rates rising from $43.26 to $49.75. The change had been telegraphed: AWS's pricing page noted (and bizarrely, still does) that "current prices are scheduled to be updated in January, 2026," though the company neglected to mention which direction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This comes about seven months after AWS trumpeted "up to 45% price reductions" for GPU instances - though that announcement covered On-Demand and Savings Plans rather than Capacity Blocks. Funny how that works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, Capacity Blocks are AWS's answer to "I need guaranteed GPU capacity for my ML training job next Tuesday." You reserve specific GPU instances for a defined time window – anywhere from a day to a few weeks out – and pay up front at a locked-in rate. It's popular with companies doing serious ML work who can't afford to have a training run interrupted because spot capacity evaporated. The pricing should make it abundantly clear that the people using this aren't hobbyists; these are teams with budgets measured in millions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An Amazon spox told us via email, "EC2 Capacity Blocks for ML pricing vary based on supply and demand patterns, as described on the product detail page. This price adjustment reflects the supply/demand patterns we expect this quarter."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be clear, AWS has raised prices before, but rarely as a straight increase to a line item. The company prefers to change pricing dimensions entirely, often spinning this as a price reduction for most customers – a claim I'd characterize as "creative." Historical straight-up price increases have been tied to regulatory actions: per-SMS charges in certain markets and the like. This is different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The timing is curious for another reason: it hands Azure and GCP a talking point on a silver platter. Both have been aggressively courting ML workloads, and "AWS just raised GPU prices 15%" is exactly the kind of ammunition enterprise sales teams dream about. Whether the competitors can actually absorb the demand is another question – GPU constraints are hardly unique to AWS – but perception matters in enterprise deals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For companies with Enterprise Discount Programs or other negotiated agreements, this raises uncomfortable questions. EDPs typically guarantee discounts off public pricing – so if public pricing goes up 15 percent, your "discounted" rate just got more expensive in absolute terms, even if the percentage held steady. I expect some pointed conversations between AWS account teams and their larger customers in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why are they doing this?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's hard not to see this as a bellwether. GPUs are increasingly constrained globally as the world pivots to generating slop-as-a-service in every conceivable domain. The question is what this means for other resource types down the road. Does the global RAM crunch mean RAM-centric services are next? You can ignore ML Capacity Block pricing if you're not running machine learning workloads – which describes north of 95 percent of most companies' cloud spend – but RAM touches every service AWS offers. Well, possibly excepting their support function, though that's rapidly becoming "AI-Powered" too, so give it time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Deploying to Amazon's cloud is a pain in the AWS younger devs won't tolerate&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AWS adds hybrid cloud storage support for Nutanix's AHV hypervisor&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Jassy taps 27-year Amazon veteran to run AGI org, which is now definitely a thing that exists&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Smartphones face a memory cost crunch – and buyers aren't in the mood&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The canary-in-the-coal-mine concern here isn't GPUs specifically, but rather the precedent it establishes. AWS has spent two decades conditioning customers to expect prices only ever go down. That expectation is now broken. Once you've raised prices on one service and the world doesn't end, the second increase becomes easier. And the third. The playbook has changed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep an eye on services where AWS faces genuine supply constraints or where their costs have materially increased. Graviton instances have been priced aggressively to drive adoption – what happens when ARM chip supply tightens? Data transfer costs have been a cash cow for years, but they've also been stable; are those next? I don't have inside information, but I do have pattern recognition, and the pattern just shifted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS has long benefited from the assumption that cloud pricing only trends in one direction. That assumption died on a Saturday in January, with all the fanfare of a Terms of Service update. The question isn't whether this matters – it does. The question is whether it's an anomaly or the new normal. My money's on the latter. ®&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.theregister.com/2026/01/05/aws_price_increase/"/><published>2026-01-06T11:42:35+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46511298</id><title>System: Control your Mac from anywhere using natural language</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:35.896588+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a51fdf48312faeb2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;SYSTEM&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;remote mac automation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Control your Mac from anywhere using natural language. Built with Cloudflare Agents SDK for intelligent scheduling, memory, and tool orchestration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;quick start&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;1. clone and install&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/ygwyg/system
cd system &amp;amp;&amp;amp; npm install&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2. run setup wizard&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm run setup&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interactive setup: Anthropic API key, Raycast extensions, remote access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;3. start system&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm start&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starts bridge, tunnel, and opens the agent UI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;architecture&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SYSTEM uses a split architecture for security: the Agent (brain) runs on Cloudflare Workers, while the Bridge (body) runs locally on your Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ â USER â â (phone/browser) â âââââââââââââââââââââââ¬ââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ â HTTPS â¼ âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ â AGENT (Brain) â â Cloudflare Workers â â âââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââ â â â Claude â â State â â Schedules â â â â AI â â (D.O.) â â (D.O.) â â â âââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââ â âââââââââââââââââââââââ¬ââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ â Tunnel â¼ âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ â BRIDGE (Body) â â Your Mac (local) â â âââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââ â â â AppleScript â â Shell â â Raycast â â â âââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââ â âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Claude for NLP&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ State, memory, scheduling&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ WebSocket real-time&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ AppleScript, shell exec&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Raycast extensions&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Cloudflare Tunnel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;authentication&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All requests require an API secret via Bearer token or query parameter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Header
Authorization: Bearer &amp;lt;api_secret&amp;gt;

// Or query parameter
?token=&amp;lt;api_secret&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The API secret is generated during &lt;code&gt;npm run setup&lt;/code&gt; and stored in &lt;code&gt;bridge.config.json&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;chat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Send natural language commands to control your Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Send a message to the agent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;request&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "message": "Play some jazz music"
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;response&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "message": "Playing jazz on Apple Music",
  "actions": [{
    "tool": "music_play",
    "args": { "query": "jazz" },
    "success": true,
    "result": "Now playing: Jazz Vibes"
  }]
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clear conversation history and state.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;schedules&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Schedule one-time or recurring tasks using natural language or cron syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;List all scheduled tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "schedules": [{
    "id": "abc123",
    "description": "Play closing time",
    "scheduledAt": "2026-01-05T17:00:00Z",
    "cron": "0 17 * * *"
  }]
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cancel a scheduled task by ID.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; â¢ "Remind me to call mom in 30 minutes"&lt;lb/&gt; â¢ "Every day at 5pm, play Closing Time"&lt;lb/&gt; â¢ "At 9am tomorrow, open Linear" &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;state&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The agent maintains persistent state including preferences and conversation history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get current agent state for debugging.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "preferences": { "wife": "Jane" },
  "historyLength": 12,
  "scheduleCount": 2
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;core tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foundational tools for Mac automation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;open_app&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Open any application&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;open_url&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Open URL in browser&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;shell&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Run safe shell commands&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;shell_list&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List available shell commands&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;applescript&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Execute AppleScript&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;notify&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Show macOS notification&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;say&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Text-to-speech&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;clipboard_get&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Get clipboard contents&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;clipboard_set&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Set clipboard contents&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;screenshot&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Take screenshot&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;music&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Control Apple Music playback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;music_play&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Play/search music&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;music_pause&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pause playback&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;music_next&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Skip to next track&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;music_previous&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Previous track&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;music_current&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Get current track info&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;volume_get&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Get volume level&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;volume_set&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Set volume (0-100)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;volume_up&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Increase volume 10%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;volume_down&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Decrease volume 10%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;volume_mute&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Toggle mute&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;messaging&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Send iMessages with human-in-the-loop confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;search_contacts&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Find contact by name&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;send_imessage&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Send iMessage&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you say "text my wife hello", SYSTEM will: 1) resolve "wife" from preferences, 2) search contacts, 3) ask for confirmation before sending.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;system&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Control system settings, get status, manage files and apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;calendar &amp;amp; reminders&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;calendar_today&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Today's events&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;calendar_upcoming&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Upcoming events&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;calendar_next&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Next event&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;calendar_create&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Create event&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;reminders_list&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List reminders&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;reminders_create&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Create reminder&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;reminders_complete&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Complete reminder&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;display &amp;amp; focus&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;brightness_set&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Set brightness&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;dark_mode_toggle&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Toggle dark mode&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;dark_mode_status&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Get dark mode status&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;dnd_toggle&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Toggle Do Not Disturb&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;lock_screen&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Lock Mac&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;sleep_display&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sleep display&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;sleep_mac&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sleep Mac&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;system status&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;battery_status&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Battery level &amp;amp; charging&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;wifi_status&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;WiFi network info&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;storage_status&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Disk space&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;running_apps&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List running apps&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;front_app&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Get frontmost app&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;notes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read and write Apple Notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;notes_list&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List recent notes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;notes_search&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Search notes by keyword&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;notes_create&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Create a new note&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;notes_read&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Read note content&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;notes_append&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Append to existing note&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;files&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Search and manage files via Finder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;finder_search&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Search files by name&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;finder_downloads&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List recent downloads&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;finder_desktop&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List desktop files&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;finder_reveal&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Reveal file in Finder&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;finder_trash&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Move file to trash&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;shortcuts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run Apple Shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;shortcut_run&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Run a shortcut by name&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;shortcut_list&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List available shortcuts&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create powerful automations in Shortcuts.app, then trigger them via SYSTEM. Example: "Run my Morning Routine shortcut"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;browser&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get info from Safari, Chrome, Arc, or other browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;tool&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;browser_url&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Get current tab URL&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;browser_tabs&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List open tabs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;raycast extensions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Execute Raycast extensions for powerful integrations. SYSTEM scans your installed extensions and makes them available as tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;how it works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During &lt;code&gt;npm run setup&lt;/code&gt;, SYSTEM scans your Raycast extensions folder and presents compatible commands for you to enable. Each enabled command becomes a dedicated tool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Raycast Extension SYSTEM Tool âââââââââââââââââ âââââââââââ spotify-player/play â spotify_play linear/create-issue â linear_create_issue slack/send-message â slack_send_message&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;extension discovery&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SYSTEM looks in &lt;code&gt;~/.config/raycast/extensions/&lt;/code&gt; and reads each extension's &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; to find commands. Only commands with &lt;code&gt;mode: "no-view"&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;mode: "view"&lt;/code&gt; are compatible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;compatible extension types&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;works?&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;notes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;No-view commands&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;â Best&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Execute silently, return result&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;View commands&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;â ï¸ Partial&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Opens Raycast UI briefly&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Form commands&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;â No&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Requires user input in Raycast&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Menu bar commands&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;â No&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Background only&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;popular extensions that work well&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;extension&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;commands&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;use case&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;spotify-player&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;play, pause, next, like&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Music control&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;linear&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;create-issue, search&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Issue tracking&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;slack&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;send-message, set-status&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Team communication&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;todoist&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;create-task, today&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Task management&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;github&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;create-issue, search&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Code management&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;notion&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;create-page, search&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Notes &amp;amp; docs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;tool naming&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tools are named as &lt;code&gt;{extension}_{command}&lt;/code&gt; with hyphens replaced by underscores:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Extension: linear, Command: create-issue-for-myself
Tool name: linear_create_issue_for_myself

// Extension: spotify-player, Command: play
Tool name: spotify_player_play&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;using raycast tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once enabled, just ask naturally:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Create a Linear issue for fixing the login bug"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Send a Slack message to #general saying hello"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Play Daft Punk on Spotify"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Add 'buy groceries' to my Todoist"&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;generic raycast tool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For extensions not in your enabled list, use the generic &lt;code&gt;raycast&lt;/code&gt; tool:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "extension": "spotify-player",
  "command": "play",
  "arguments": { "query": "jazz" }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;deep link format&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the hood, SYSTEM uses Raycast deep links:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;raycast://extensions/{author}/{extension}/{command}?arguments={json}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;troubleshooting&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If an extension isn't showing in setup, make sure it's installed via Raycast Store, not manually. Check &lt;code&gt;~/.config/raycast/extensions/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This usually means the command requires UI interaction (forms, selections). These commands aren't fully compatible. Try a different command from the same extension.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many extensions require you to authenticate in Raycast first. Open Raycast and run the command manually once to complete OAuth/login flows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;re-scanning extensions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you install new Raycast extensions, run setup again to add them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm run setup&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your existing configuration will be preservedâyou'll just see new extensions to enable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;bridge api&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Direct API to the local bridge. Used by the agent, but also available for custom integrations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;List all available tools on the bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Execute a specific tool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "tool": "open_app",
  "args": { "app": "Safari" }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check bridge status.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;websocket&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Real-time updates for scheduled tasks and notifications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Connect to WebSocket
const ws = new WebSocket('wss://your-agent.workers.dev/ws?token=...');

ws.onmessage = (event) =&amp;gt; {
  const data = JSON.parse(event.data);
  // Types: scheduled_result, notification, bridge_status
  console.log(data.type, data.payload);
};&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;event type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;scheduled_result&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Result of a scheduled task&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;notification&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;System notification&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;bridge_status&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bridge online/offline&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;security&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SYSTEM is designed with security as a priority.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;ð authentication&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bearer token required for all requests. Tokens are generated during setup and stored locally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;ð¡ï¸ shell safety&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only allowlisted commands can run. Dangerous patterns (rm -rf, sudo, etc.) are blocked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;ð tunnel security&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quick Tunnels are ephemeral â new URL each session. Bridge binds to 0.0.0.0 only when tunnel is active.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;ð¤ human-in-the-loop&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sensitive actions like sending messages require explicit user confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;cloudflare access (recommended)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you deploy to Cloudflare Workers, add Cloudflare Access for Zero Trust authentication at the edge â before requests even reach your agent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the API secret provides application-level auth, Cloudflare Access adds network-level protection. Only authenticated users can reach your agent at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;setup via dashboard&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Go to Cloudflare Zero Trust Dashboard&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Navigate to Access â Applications â Add an application&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Select Self-hosted and enter your worker URL&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create an access policy (e.g., email = &lt;code&gt;you@example.com&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Save â users must now authenticate before accessing SYSTEM&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;automation (terraform)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Note: wrangler doesn't support Access config directly
# Use Terraform for infrastructure-as-code

resource "cloudflare_access_application" "system" {
  zone_id          = var.zone_id
  name             = "SYSTEM"
  domain           = "your-agent.workers.dev"
  session_duration = "24h"
}

resource "cloudflare_access_policy" "allow_me" {
  application_id = cloudflare_access_application.system.id
  zone_id        = var.zone_id
  name           = "Allow specific emails"
  precedence     = 1
  decision       = "allow"

  include {
    email = ["you@example.com"]
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare Access is configured separately from Workers deployment. The &lt;code&gt;wrangler&lt;/code&gt; CLI doesn't manage Access policies â use the dashboard or Terraform.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://system.surf/"/><published>2026-01-06T12:04:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46511469</id><title>Show HN: Prism.Tools – Free and privacy-focused developer utilities</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:35.738163+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="4aabc530823215a8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PRISM.TOOLS 🔍 ☕ Donate Every Dev Tool You Need Fast. Private. Free forever. 🔒 Data never leaves your browser All Tools Formatters &amp;amp; Parsers Security &amp;amp; Dev Visual &amp;amp; CSS Generators &amp;amp; Content Encoders &amp;amp; Transformers 🛠️ All Tools Recent Tools 0 Tools Used 38 Available&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blgardner.github.io/prism.tools/"/><published>2026-01-06T12:33:49+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46511470</id><title>C Is Best</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:35.399221+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="c34a58f9ca2a1b78"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Note: Sections 2.0 and 3.0 of this article were added in response to comments on Hacker News and Reddit.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since its inception on 2000-05-29, SQLite has been implemented in generic C. C was and continues to be the best language for implementing a software library like SQLite. There are no plans to recode SQLite in any other programming language at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reasons why C is the best language to implement SQLite include:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An intensively used low-level library like SQLite needs to be fast. (And SQLite is fast, see Internal Versus External BLOBs and 35% Faster Than The Filesystem for examples.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;C is a great language for writing fast code. C is sometimes described as "portable assembly language". It enables developers to code as close to the underlying hardware as possible while still remaining portable across platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other programming languages sometimes claim to be "as fast as C". But no other language claims to be faster than C for general-purpose programming, because none are.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nearly all systems have the ability to call libraries written in C. This is not true of other implementation languages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, for example, Android applications written in Java are able to invoke SQLite (through an adaptor). Maybe it would have been more convenient for Android if SQLite had been coded in Java as that would make the interface simpler. However, on iPhone applications are coded in Objective-C or Swift, neither of which have the ability to call libraries written in Java. Thus, SQLite would be unusable on iPhones had it been written in Java.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Libraries written in C do not have a huge run-time dependency. In its minimum configuration, SQLite requires only the following routines from the standard C library:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a more complete build, SQLite also uses library routines like malloc() and free() and operating system interfaces for opening, reading, writing, and closing files. But even then, the number of dependencies is very small. Other "modern" languages, in contrast, often require multi-megabyte runtimes loaded with thousands and thousands of interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The C language is old and boring. It is a well-known and well-understood language. This is exactly what one wants when developing a module like SQLite. Writing a small, fast, and reliable database engine is hard enough as it is without the implementation language changing out from under you with each update to the implementation language specification.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some programmers cannot imagine developing a complex system like SQLite in a language that is not "object oriented". So why is SQLite not coded in C++ or Java?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Libraries written in C++ or Java can generally only be used by applications written in the same language. It is difficult to get an application written in Haskell or Java to invoke a library written in C++. On the other hand, libraries written in C are callable from any programming language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Object-Oriented is a design pattern, not a programming language. You can do object-oriented programming in any language you want, including assembly language. Some languages (ex: C++ or Java) make object-oriented easier. But you can still do object-oriented programming in languages like C.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Object-oriented is not the only valid design pattern. Many programmers have been taught to think purely in terms of objects. And, to be fair, objects are often a good way to decompose a problem. But objects are not the only way, and are not always the best way to decompose a problem. Sometimes good old procedural code is easier to write, easier to maintain and understand, and faster than object-oriented code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When SQLite was first being developed, Java was a young and immature language. C++ was older, but was undergoing such growing pains that it was difficult to find any two C++ compilers that worked the same way. So C was definitely a better choice back when SQLite was first being developed. The situation is less stark now, but there is little to no benefit in recoding SQLite at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There has lately been a lot of interest in "safe" programming languages like Rust or Go in which it is impossible, or is at least difficult, to make common programming errors like memory leaks or array overruns. So the question often arises as to why SQLite is not coded in a "safe" language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;None of the safe programming languages existed for the first 10 years of SQLite's existence. SQLite could be recoded in Go or Rust, but doing so would probably introduce far more bugs than would be fixed, and it may also result in slower code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Safe languages insert additional machine branches to do things like verify that array accesses are in-bounds. In correct code, those branches are never taken. That means that the machine code cannot be 100% branch tested, which is an important component of SQLite's quality strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Safe languages usually want to abort if they encounter an out-of-memory (OOM) situation. SQLite is designed to recover gracefully from an OOM. It is unclear how this could be accomplished in the current crop of safe languages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of the existing safe languages are new. The developers of SQLite applaud the efforts of computer language researchers in trying to develop languages that are easier to program safely. We encourage these efforts to continue. But we ourselves are more interested in old and boring languages when it comes to implementing SQLite.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All that said, it is possible that SQLite might one day be recoded in Rust. Recoding SQLite in Go is unlikely since Go hates assert(). But Rust is a possibility. Some preconditions that must occur before SQLite is recoded in Rust include:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are a "rustacean" and feel that Rust already meets the preconditions listed above, and that SQLite should be recoded in Rust, then you are welcomed and encouraged to contact the SQLite developers privately and argue your case.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This page was last updated on 2025-05-09 15:56:17Z&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://sqlite.org/whyc.html"/><published>2026-01-06T12:33:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46511578</id><title>Show HN: DDL to Data – Generate realistic test data from SQL schemas</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:35.093179+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2deaaa31c784bee8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I built DDL to Data after repeatedly pushing back on "just use production data and mask it" requests. Teams needed populated databases for testing, but pulling prod meant security reviews, PII scrubbing, and DevOps tickets. Hand-written seed scripts were the alternative slow, fragile, and out of sync the moment schemas changed.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Paste your CREATE TABLE statements, get realistic test data back. It parses your schema, preserves foreign key relationships, and generates data that looks real, emails look like emails, timestamps are reasonable, uniqueness constraints are honored.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;No setup, no config. Works with PostgreSQL and MySQL.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://ddltodata.com&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Would love feedback from anyone who deals with test data or staging environments. What's missing?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46511578"/><published>2026-01-06T12:47:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46511981</id><title>Why German Strings Are Everywhere?</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:34.437410+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="36712bddfa8e47d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;German Strings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strings are conceptually very simple: It’s essentially just a sequence of characters, right? Why, then, does every programming language have their own slightly different string implementation? It turns out that there is a lot more to a string than “just a sequence of characters”1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re no different and built our own custom string type that is highly optimized for data processing. Even though we didn’t expect it when we first wrote about it in our inaugural Umbra research paper, a lot of new systems adopted our format. They are now implemented in DuckDB, Apache Arrow, Polars, and Facebook Velox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this blog post, we’d like to tell you more about the advantages of our so-called “German Strings” and the tradeoffs we made.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But first, let’s take a step back and take a look at how strings are commonly implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How C does it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In C, strings are just a sequence of bytes with the vague promise that a &lt;code&gt;\0&lt;/code&gt; byte will terminate the string at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a very simple model conceptually, but very cumbersome in practice:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What if your string is not terminated? If you’re not careful, you can read beyond the intended end of the string, a huge security problem!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Just calculating the length of the string forces you to iterate over the whole thing.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What if we want to extend the string? We have to allocate new memory, move it there and free the old location all by ourselves.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How C++ does it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;C++ exposes much nicer strings through its standard library. The C++ standard doesn’t enforce a specific implementation, but here’s how &lt;code&gt;libc++&lt;/code&gt; does it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each string object stores its size (already better than C!), a pointer to the actual payload, and the capacity of the buffer in which the data is stored. You’re free to append to the string “for free” as long as the resulting string is still shorter than the buffer capacity and the string will take care of allocating a larger buffer and freeing the old one when it grows too much: &lt;code&gt;std::string&lt;/code&gt;s are mutable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This string implementation also allows for the very important “short string optimization”: A short enough string can be stored “in place”, i.e., we set a specific bit in the &lt;code&gt;capacity&lt;/code&gt; field and the remainder of &lt;code&gt;capacity&lt;/code&gt; as well as &lt;code&gt;size&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ptr&lt;/code&gt; become the string itself.
This way we save on allocating a buffer and a pointer dereference each time we access the string.
An optimization that’s impossible in Rust, by the way ;)2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in a more in-depth overview, take a look at Raymond Chen’s very detailed blog post about various &lt;code&gt;std::string&lt;/code&gt; implementations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Can we do better?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;C++, especially with short string optimization, already does quite well. However, if you know your use case, it turns out that you can do much better3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While building CedarDB, we made the following observations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Most strings are short&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite being able to store arbitrary amounts of text, most people store fairly short and predictable data in their strings (as reported by Vogelsgesang et al. in their fantastic “Get Real” paper).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Examples of such short strings are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ISO country codes (&lt;code&gt;USA&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;DEU&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;GBR&lt;/code&gt;), 3 characters&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;IATA airport codes (&lt;code&gt;LHR&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;MUC&lt;/code&gt;), 3 characters&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enums (&lt;code&gt;MALE/FEMALE/NONBINARY&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;YES/NO/MAYBE&lt;/code&gt;), usually less than 10 characters&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ISBNs (&lt;code&gt;0465062881&lt;/code&gt;), 10 or 13 digits&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We definitely want to optimize for such short strings wherever possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Strings aren’t usually changed all that often&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most data is only written once, but read many times. The &lt;code&gt;libc++&lt;/code&gt; approach of reserving 64 bits per string just to store the capacity for the off chance that someone wants to extend the string seems kind of wasteful when string sizes don’t change all that often.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, simultaneously accessing and modifying a string concurrently can lead to data races if we don’t use expensive locking techniques or think very carefully about our application.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For these two reasons, we’d like to have immutable strings whenever we can get away with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;We usually only look at a small subset of the string&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take a look at the following to SQL query:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;select * from messages where starts_with(content, 'http');
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We only want to look at the first four characters of each string. It seems kind of wasteful to always dereference a pointer just to compare the first four characters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that the short string optimization of &lt;code&gt;libc++&lt;/code&gt; can’t save us here: If the string isn’t short, we have to follow the pointer, even if we only care about the prefix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s look at another query:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;select sum(p.amount)
from purchases p, books b
where p.ISBN = b.ISBN and b.title = 'GÃ¶del, Escher, Bach: An Eternal Golden Braid';
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here, we need to compare all ISBNs with each other and all book titles with a string constant. While we obviously need to compare the entire string to make sure we have a match, most books probably won’t be called “GÃ¶del, Escher, Bach: An Eternal Golden Braid” (how many strings starting with “GÃ¶” do you know, dear non-German reader?). If a character at the beginning of the string already differs, we can rule it out without further checking the rest of the string.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;German Strings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To solve these problems, Umbra, the research predecessor of CedarDB, invented what Andy Pavlo now affectionately (we assume ;)) calls “German-style strings”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Let’s dig in: The Anatomy of a German String&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first big change is that each string is represented by a single 128-bit &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt;.
Besides the obvious advantage of saving a third of the overhead over &lt;code&gt;std::string&lt;/code&gt; by dropping the &lt;code&gt;capacity&lt;/code&gt; field, it also allows us to pass strings in function calls via two registers instead of putting them on the stack.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Curious about how this affects function calls? We cover the benefits of a 16B layout for calling conventions in our deep dive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt; contains one of the following two representations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Short string representation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the memory layout for short strings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As long as the string to be stored is 12 or fewer characters, we store the content directly in place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Accessing the content itself, or just a prefix, is easy: Just start reading directly after the &lt;code&gt;len&lt;/code&gt; field, no pointer dereference needed!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Long string representation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strings longer than 12 characters require some additional consideration:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like C++ strings, we also store a &lt;code&gt;len&lt;/code&gt; field and a pointer to the data itself, but with some twists:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Length&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To squeeze the whole string into 128 bits, we shorten the length field to 32 bits. This limits the string size to 4 GiB, a tradeoff we were willing to make for our use case.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Prefix&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right after the length we also store a four character prefix. This prefix speeds up operations like equality/inequality comparisons, lexicographic sorting, or prefix comparisons enormously, because we save a pointer dereference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Pointer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pointer points to a memory region exactly the size of the string. No buffer with some remaining &lt;code&gt;capacity&lt;/code&gt; here!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The obvious advantage is that we save the 64 bits for the capacity field and can tightly pack payloads of different strings without gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the data we’re pointing to is now immutable, we can also read it without acquiring a read lock, since the data is guaranteed to never change as long as the string lives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need to be aware of the downside as well: Appending data to a string is now a relatively expensive operation, since a new buffer must be allocated and the payload must be copied. However, this is not a big problem in our use case, since database systems rarely update data in-place anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Storage Class&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While developing our string concept, we noticed that developers have different requirements for the lifetime of their strings depending on where they use them. We call these “storage classes”, which you can specify when creating a string. A string can be &lt;code&gt;persistent&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;transient&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;temporary&lt;/code&gt;.
To encode this storage class, we steal two bits from the pointer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the cases you might already know from your favorite programming language:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;temporary&lt;/code&gt;strings behave like their C++ counterparts: When constructing a temporary string, the string constructor itself allocates some memory, stores the payload, and correctly sets the pointer. When the string goes out of scope, the memory is freed, RAII style.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;persistent&lt;/code&gt;strings behave like string constants: They remain valid forever. All short strings are always persistent strings, because you can just pass them via the stack or CPU registers. Long strings can also be persistent, for example, when referencing C++ string literals. The memory that holds the data of the string literal is automatically allocated statically when your program starts and is never deallocated, so referencing the string data is always valid.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there is a third pattern: The amount of data we need to store in a database system is often larger than RAM, and so some of it is swapped out to disk. With conventional strings, if we loaded a page containing a string from disk, we would have to&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;first load the page into memory,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;and then initialize a new string which internally copies the data to the newly initialized memory.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This process copies the string data twice. This is wasteful, since many times we only want to access the string once. For example, consider the following query:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;select * from books where starts_with(title,'Tutorial')
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we filter all books for matches, most strings won’t qualify. We’ll never need to show them to the person issuing the query, so why copy them if we don’t need to access them later?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We would like to have a string that is very cheap to construct and points to a region of memory that is currently valid, but may become invalid later without the string having control over it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where &lt;code&gt;transient&lt;/code&gt; strings come in.
They point to data that is currently valid, but may become invalid later, e.g., when we swap out the page on which the payload is stored to disk after we’ve released the lock on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creating them has virtually no overhead: They simply point to an externally managed memory location. No memory allocation or data copying is required during construction! When you access a transient string, the string itself won’t know whether the data it points to is still valid, so you as a programmer need to ensure that every transient string you use is actually still valid. So if you need to access it later, you need to copy it to memory that you control. If you do not need it later on, we just accessed a string without having to do any expensive initialization!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Distinguishing between representations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How do we know if we’re dealing with a short string or a long string? It’s actually quite simple! If its size is 12 characters or less, it is a short string. Since our strings are immutable, there is no special case where a long string could become short or vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we just want to access the prefix, we don’t even need to check whether the string is long or short. In either case, bits 32-63 will be the first four characters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;German strings have many advantages: You get great performance due to space savings and reduced allocations and data movement. Because data is always treated as immutable, it is also much easier to parallelize your string handling code. Thanks to its concept of storage classes, you can tightly manage the lifetime of your strings, trading performance for ease of use when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, nothing comes without its challenges: German strings require you to think more deeply about your application: What is the lifetime of my string? Can I get away with a &lt;code&gt;transient&lt;/code&gt; string, or do I have to copy it?
Will my strings be updated often? Am I okay with immutable strings?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re okay with asking yourself these questions, you can benefit a lot from German Strings, even if you’re not building a database.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you want to harness the power of German Strings? Don’t be shy and join our waitlist to be among the first to get access to CedarDB!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not to speak of the contents of such a character sequence. What even is a character? Say hello to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ã¤&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Ã¶&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;(â¯Â°â¡Â°)â¯ï¸µ â»ââ»&lt;/code&gt;. But that’s for another blog post… ↩︎&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;EDIT 04/09/2024: This small aside lead to a lot of discussion in the Rust community: To clarify, the implementation and API guarantees of Rust’s&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;std::string::String&lt;/code&gt;make such optimization impossible. It is, however, very possible to implement German style strings in Rust, as a lot of very impressive crates inspired by our snide remark have proven. Here are a few examples: An Optimization Thatâs Impossible in Rust!, An (extremely unsafe) experiment in implementing “German strings” in Rust “An optimization that’s impossible in Rust” ↩︎&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: Some of the observations here are made through the lens of people building a high performance database system. However, all of the approaches are applicable to strings in all kinds of software. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://cedardb.com/blog/german_strings/"/><published>2026-01-06T13:30:07+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46512881</id><title>65% of Hacker News Posts Have Negative Sentiment, and They Outperform</title><updated>2026-01-06T15:12:34.332644+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="350c80263eb05556"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posts with negative sentiment average 35.6 points on Hacker News. The overall average is 28 points. That’s a 27% performance premium for negativity. This finding comes from an empirical study I’ve been running on HN attention dynamics, covering decay curves, preferential attachment, survival probability, and early-engagement prediction. The preprint is available on SSRN. I already had a gut feeling. Across 32,000 posts and 340,000 comments, nearly 65% register as negative. This might be a feature of my classifier being miscalibrated toward negativity; yet the pattern holds across six different models. I tested three transformer-based classifiers (DistilBERT, BERT Multi, RoBERTa) and three LLMs (Llama 3.1 8B, Mistral 3.1 24B, Gemma 3 12B). The distributions vary, but the negative skew persists across all of them (inverted scale for 2-6). The results I use in my dashboard are from DistilBERT because it runs efficiently in my Cloudflare-based pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What counts as “negative” here? Criticism of technology, skepticism toward announcements, complaints about industry practices, frustration with APIs. The usual. It’s worth noting that technical critique reads differently than personal attacks; most HN negativity is substantive rather than toxic. But, does negativity cause engagement, or does controversial content attract both negative framing and attention? Probably some of both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ll publish the full code, dataset, and a dashboard for the HN archiver soon and I’m happy to send you an update:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can also subscribe to the RSS feed or get updates on Bluesky.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://philippdubach.com/standalone/hn-sentiment/"/><published>2026-01-06T14:45:47+00:00</published></entry></feed>