<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:50.527003+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45137525</id><title>I ditched Docker for Podman</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:58.121617+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://codesmash.dev/why-i-ditched-docker-for-podman-and-you-should-too"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45139088</id><title>Purposeful animations</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:57.853837+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f7eb51a5ad29df05"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;When done right, animations make an interface feel predictable, faster, and more enjoyable to use. They help you and your product stand out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But they can also do the opposite. They can make an interface feel unpredictable, slow, and annoying. They can even make your users lose trust in your product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So how do you know when and how to animate to improve the experience?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Step one is making sure your animations have a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Purposeful animations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before you start animating, ask yourself: what’s the purpose of this animation? &lt;lb/&gt;As an example, what’s the purpose of this marketing animation we built at Linear?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can view the full animation on linear.app/ai.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This animation explains how Product Intelligence (Linear’s feature) works. We could have used a static asset, but the animated version helps the user understand what this feature does, straight in the initial viewport of the page.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another purposeful animation is this subtle scale down effect when pressing a button. It’s a small thing, but it helps the interface feel more alive and responsive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sonner’s enter animation, on the other hand, has two purposes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;- Having a toast suddenly appear would feel off, so we animate it in.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;- Because it comes from and leaves in the same direction, it creates spatial consistency, making the swipe-down-to-dismiss gesture feel more intuitive.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;But sometimes the purpose of an animation might just be to bring delight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Morphing of the feedback component below helps make the experience more unique and memorable. This works as long as the user will rarely interact with it. It’ll then become a pleasant surprise, rather than a daily annoyance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press on the button to see it morph.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Used multiple times a day, this component would quickly become irritating. The initial delight would fade and the animation would slow users down.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How often users will see an animation is a key factor in deciding whether to animate or not. Let’s dive deeper into it next.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Frequency of use&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I use Raycast hundreds of times a day. If it animated every time I opened it, it would be very annoying. But there’s no animation at all. That’s the optimal experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To see it for yourself, try to toggle the open state of the menu below by using the buttons belowpressing &lt;code&gt;J&lt;/code&gt; and then &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;. Which one feels better if used hundreds of times a day?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I open Raycast, I have a clear goal in mind. I don’t expect to be “delighted”, I don’t need to be. I just want to do my work with no unnecessary friction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Think about what the user wants to achieve and how often they will see an animation. A hover effect is nice, but if used multiple times a day, it would likely benefit the most from having no animation at all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Imagine you interact with this list often during the day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Imagine you interact with this list often during the day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same goes for keyboard-initiated actions. These actions may be repeated hundreds of times a day, an animation would make them feel slow, delayed, and disconnected from the user’s actions. You should never animate them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since we can’t really use a keyboard on touch devices, you can press the buttons below to see how it feels with and without animation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To see it for yourself, focus on the input below and use arrow keys to navigate through the list. Notice how the highlight feels delayed compared to the keys you press. Now press (shift) and see how this interaction feels without animation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But even if your animation won’t be used too often and it fulfills a clear purpose, you still have to think about its speed…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Perception of speed&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unless you are working on marketing sites, your animations have to be fast. They improve the perceived performance of your app, stay connected to user’s actions, and make the interface feel as if it’s truly listening to the user.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To give you an example, a faster-spinning spinner makes the app seem to load faster, even though the load time is the same. This improves perceived performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which one works harder to load the data?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;180ms&lt;/code&gt; dropdown animation feels more responsive than a &lt;code&gt;400ms&lt;/code&gt; one:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click on the buttons to compare the speed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a rule of thumb, UI animations should generally stay under &lt;code&gt;300ms&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another example of the importance of speed: tooltips should have a slight delay before appearing to prevent accidental activation. Once a tooltip is open however, hovering over other tooltips should open them with no delay and no animation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This feels faster without defeating the purpose of the initial delay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radix UI and Base UI skip the delay once a tooltip is shown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radix UI and Base UI skip the delay once a tooltip is shown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building great interfaces&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The goal is not to animate for animation’s sake, it’s to build great user interfaces. The ones that users will happily use, even on a daily basis. Sometimes this requires animations, but sometimes the best animation is no animation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Knowing when to animate is just one of many things you need to know in order to craft great animations. If you’d like to dive deeper into the theory and practice of it, I’ve created a course that covers everything you need to know:&lt;/p&gt;Check out "Animations on the Web"&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://emilkowal.ski/ui/you-dont-need-animations"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45139656</id><title>Protobuffers Are Wrong (2018)</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:57.597293+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1c20d80c0e053ed4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Protobuffers Are Wrong&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve spent a good deal of my professional life arguing against using protobuffers. They’re clearly written by amateurs, unbelievably ad-hoc, mired in gotchas, tricky to compile, and solve a problem that nobody but Google really has. If these problems of protobuffers remained quarantined in serialization abstractions, my complaints would end there. But unfortunately, the bad design of protobuffers is so persuasive that these problems manage to leak their way into your code as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Ad-Hoc and Built By Amateurs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stop. Put away your email client that is half-way through writing me about how “Google is filled with the world’s best engineers,” and that “anything they build is, by definition, not built by amateurs.” I don’t want to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s just get this out of the way. Full disclosure: I used to work at Google. It was the first (but unfortunately, not the last) place I ever used protobuffers. All of the problems I want to talk about today exist inside of Google’s codebase; it’s not just a matter of “using protobuffers wrong” or some such nonsense like that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By far, the biggest problem with protobuffers is their terrible type-system. Fans of Java should feel right at home with protobuffers, but unfortunately, literally nobody considers Java to have a well-designed type-system. The dynamic typing guys complain about it being too stifling, while the static typing guys like me complain about it being too stifling without giving you any of the things you actually want in a type-system. Lose lose.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ad-hoc-ness and the built-by-amateurs-itude go hand-in-hand. So much of the protobuffer spec feels bolted on as an afterthought that it clearly was bolted on as an afterthought. Many of its restrictions will make you stop, scratch your head and ask “wat?” But these are just symptoms of the deeper answer, which is this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protobuffers were obviously built by amateurs because they offer bad solutions to widely-known and already-solved problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No Compositionality&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protobuffers offer several “features”, but none of them see to work with one another. For example, look at the list of orthogonal-yet-constrained typing features that I found by skimming the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;oneof&lt;/code&gt;fields can’t be&lt;code&gt;repeated&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;map&amp;lt;k,v&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;fields have dedicated syntax for their keys and values, but this isn’t used for any other types.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Despite &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;fields being able to be parameterized, no user-defined types can be. This means you’ll be stuck hand-rolling your own specializations of common data structures.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;fields cannot be&lt;code&gt;repeated&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;keys can be&lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt;s, but can not be&lt;code&gt;bytes&lt;/code&gt;. They also can’t be&lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt;s, even though&lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt;s are considered to be equivalent to integers everywhere else in the protobuffer spec.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;values cannot be other&lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;s.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This insane list of restrictions is the result of unprincipled design choices and bolting on features after the fact. For example, &lt;code&gt;oneof&lt;/code&gt; fields can’t be &lt;code&gt;repeated&lt;/code&gt; because rather than resulting in a coproduct type, instead the code generator will give you a product of mutually-exclusive optional fields. Such a transformation is only valid for a singular field (and, as we’ll see later, not even then.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The restriction behind &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; fields being unable to be &lt;code&gt;repeated&lt;/code&gt; is related, but shows off a different limitation of the type-system. Behind the scenes, a &lt;code&gt;map&amp;lt;k,v&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is desugared into something spiritually similar to &lt;code&gt;repeated Pair&amp;lt;k,v&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. And because &lt;code&gt;repeated&lt;/code&gt; is a magical language keyword rather than a type in its own right, it doesn’t compose with itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your guess is as good as mine for why an &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; can’t be used as a &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; key.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s so frustrating about all of this is a little understanding of how modern type-systems work would be enough to drastically simplify the protobuffer spec and simultaneously remove all of the arbitrary restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The solution is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make all fields in a message &lt;code&gt;required&lt;/code&gt;. This makes messages product types.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Promote &lt;code&gt;oneof&lt;/code&gt;fields to instead be standalone data types. These are coproduct types.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Give the ability to parameterize product and coproduct types by other types.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s it! These three features are all you need in order to define any possible piece of data. With these simpler pieces, we can re-implement the rest of the protobuffer spec in terms of them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, we can rebuild &lt;code&gt;optional&lt;/code&gt; fields:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
 product Unit // no fields
   }

&amp;lt;t&amp;gt; {
 coproduct Optional= 0;
   t    value = 1;
   Unit unset }&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building &lt;code&gt;repeated&lt;/code&gt; fields is simple too:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;t&amp;gt; {
 coproduct List= 0;
   Unit empty &amp;lt;t, List&amp;lt;t&amp;gt;&amp;gt; cons = 1;
   Pair}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, the actual serialization logic is allowed to do something smarter than pushing linked-lists across the network—after all, implementations and semantics don’t need to align one-to-one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Questionable Choices&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the vein of Java, protobuffers make the distinction between scalar types and message types. Scalars correspond more-or-less to machine primitives—things like &lt;code&gt;int32&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;bool&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt;. Messages, on the other hand, are everything else. All library- and user-defined types are messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two varieties of types have completely different semantics, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fields with scalar types are always present. Even if you don’t set them. Did I mention that (at least in proto31) all protobuffers can be zero-initialized with absolutely no data in them? Scalar fields get false-y values—&lt;code&gt;uint32&lt;/code&gt; is initialized to &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; for example, and &lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt; is initialized as &lt;code&gt;""&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s impossible to differentiate a field that was missing in a protobuffer from one that was assigned to the default value. Presumably this decision is in place in order to allow for an optimization of not needing to send default scalar values over the wire. Presumably, though the encoding guide makes no mention of this optimization being performed, so your guess is as good as mine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we’ll see when we discuss protobuffers’ claim to being god’s gift to backwards- and forwards-compatible APIs, this inability to distinguish between unset and default values is a nightmare. Especially if indeed it’s a design decision made in order to save one bit (set or not) per field.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contrast this behavior against message types. While scalar fields are dumb, the behavior for message fields is outright insane. Internally, message fields are either there or they’re not—but their behavior is crazy. Some pseudocode for their accessor is worth a thousand words. Pretend this is Java or something similar:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;private Foo m_foo;

public Foo foo {
// only if `foo` is used as an expression
   {
   get if (m_foo != null)
     return m_foo;
       else
     return new Foo();
       }
   
// instead if `foo` is used as an lvalue
   {
   mutable get if (m_foo = null)
     = new Foo();
       m_foo return m_foo;
     }
   }&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The idea is that if the &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; field is unset, you’ll see a default-initialized copy whenever you ask for it, but won’t actually modify its container. But if you modify &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt;, it will modify its parent as well! All of this just to avoid using a &lt;code&gt;Maybe Foo&lt;/code&gt; type and the associated “headaches” of the nuance behind needing to figure out what an unset value should mean.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This behavior is especially egregious, because it breaks a law! We’d expect the assignment &lt;code&gt;msg.foo = msg.foo;&lt;/code&gt; to be a no-op. Instead the implementation will actually silently change &lt;code&gt;msg&lt;/code&gt; to have a zero-initialized copy of &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; if it previously didn’t have one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike scalar fields, at least it’s possible to detect if a message field is unset. Language bindings for protobuffers offer something along the lines of a generated &lt;code&gt;bool has_foo()&lt;/code&gt; method. In the frequent case of copying a message field from one proto to another, iff it was present, you’ll need to write the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;if (src.has_foo(src)) {
.set_foo(src.foo());
   dst}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice that, at least in statically-typed languages, this pattern cannot be abstracted due to the nominal relationship between the methods &lt;code&gt;foo()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;set_foo()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;has_foo()&lt;/code&gt;. Because all of these functions are their own identifiers, we have no means of programmatically generating them, save for a preprocessor macro:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#define COPY_IFF_SET(src, dst, field) \
if (src.has_##field(src)) { \
  dst.set_##field(src.field()); \
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(but preprocessor macros are verboten by the Google style guide.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If instead all optional fields were implemented as &lt;code&gt;Maybe&lt;/code&gt;s, you’d get abstract-able, referentially transparent call-sites for free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To change tack, let’s talk about another questionable decision. While you can define &lt;code&gt;oneof&lt;/code&gt; fields in protobuffers, their semantics are not of coproduct types! Rookie mistake my dudes! What you get instead is an optional field for each case of the &lt;code&gt;oneof&lt;/code&gt;, and magic code in the setters that will just unset any other case if this one is set.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At first glance, this seems like it should be semantically equivalent to having a proper union type. But instead it is an accursed, unutterable source of bugs! When this behavior teams up with the law-breaking implementation of &lt;code&gt;msg.foo = msg.foo;&lt;/code&gt;, it allows this benign-looking assignment to silently delete arbitrary amounts of data!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What this means at the end of the day is that &lt;code&gt;oneof&lt;/code&gt; fields do not form law-abiding &lt;code&gt;Prism&lt;/code&gt;s, nor do messages form law-abiding &lt;code&gt;Lens&lt;/code&gt;es. Which is to say good luck trying to write bug-free, non-trivial manipulations of protobuffers. It is literally impossible to write generic, bug-free, polymorphic code over protobuffers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s not the sort of thing anybody likes to hear, let alone those of us who have grown to love parametric polymorphism—which gives us the exact opposite promise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Lie of Backwards- and Forwards-Compatibility&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the frequently cited killer features of protobuffers is their “hassle-free ability to write backwards- and forwards-compatible APIs.” This is the claim that has been pulled over your eyes to blind you from the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What protobuffers are is permissive. They manage to not shit the bed when receiving messages from the past or from the future because they make absolutely no promises about what your data will look like. Everything is optional! But if you need it anyway, protobuffers will happily cook up and serve you something that typechecks, regardless of whether or not it’s meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means that protobuffers achieve their promised time-traveling compatibility guarantees by silently doing the wrong thing by default. Of course, the cautious programmer can (and should) write code that performs sanity checks on received protobuffers. But if at every use-site you need to write defensive checks ensuring your data is sane, maybe that just means your deserialization step was too permissive. All you’ve managed to do is decentralize sanity-checking logic from a well-defined boundary and push the responsibility of doing it throughout your entire codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One possible argument here is that protobuffers will hold onto any information present in a message that they don’t understand. In principle this means that it’s nondestructive to route a message through an intermediary that doesn’t understand this version of its schema. Surely that’s a win, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Granted, on paper it’s a cool feature. But I’ve never once seen an application that will actually preserve that property. With the one exception of routing software, nothing wants to inspect only some bits of a message and then forward it on unchanged. The vast majority of programs that operate on protobuffers will decode one, transform it into another, and send it somewhere else. Alas, these transformations are bespoke and coded by hand. And hand-coded transformations from one protobuffer to another don’t preserve unknown fields between the two, because it’s literally meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pervasive attitude towards protobuffers always being compatible rears its head in other ugly ways. Style guides for protobuffers actively advocate against DRY and suggest inlining definitions whenever possible. The reasoning behind this is that it allows you to evolve messages separately if these definitions diverge in the future. To emphasize that point, the suggestion is to fly in the face of 60 years’ worth of good programming practice just in case maybe one day in the future you need to change something.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the root of the problem is that Google conflates the meaning of data with its physical representation. When you’re at Google scale, this sort of thing probably makes sense. After all, they have an internal tool that allows you to compare the finances behind programmer hours vs network utilization vs the cost to store \(x\) bytes vs all sorts of other things. Unlike most companies in the tech space, paying engineers is one of Google’s smallest expenses. Financially it makes sense for them to waste programmers’ time in order to shave off a few bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outside of the top five tech companies, none of us is within five orders of magnitude of being Google scale. Your startup cannot afford to waste engineer hours on shaving off bytes. But shaving off bytes and wasting programmers’ time in the process is exactly what protobuffers are optimized for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s face it. You are not Google scale and you never will be. Stop cargo-culting technology just because “Google uses it” and therefore “it’s an industry best-practice.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Protobuffers Contaminate Codebases&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If it were possible to restrict protobuffer usage to network-boundaries I wouldn’t be nearly as hard on it as a technology. Unfortunately, while there are a few solutions in principle, none of them is good enough to actually be used in real software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protobuffers correspond to the data you want to send over the wire, which is often related but not identical to the actual data the application would like to work with. This puts us in the uncomfortable position of needing to choose between one of three bad alternatives:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Maintain a separate type that describes the data you actually want, and ensure that the two evolve simultaneously.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pack rich data into the wire format for application use.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Derive rich information every time you need it from a terse wire format.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Option 1 is clearly the “right” solution, but its untenable with protobuffers. The language isn’t powerful enough to encode types that can perform double-duty as both wire and application formats. Which means you’d need to write a completely separate datatype, evolve it synchronously with the protobuffer, and explicitly write serialization code between the two. Seeing as most people seem to use protobuffers in order to not write serialization code, this is obviously never going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, code that uses protobuffers allows them to proliferate throughout the codebase. True story, my main project at Google was a compiler that took “programs” written in one variety of protobuffer, and spit out an equivalent “program” in another. Both the input and output formats were expressive enough that maintaining proper parallel C++ versions of them could never possibly work. As a result, my code was unable to take advantage of any of the rich techniques we’ve discovered for writing compilers, because protobuffer data (and resulting code-gen) is simply too rigid to do anything interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result is that a thing that could have been 50 lines of recursion schemes was instead 10,000 lines of ad-hoc buffer-shuffling. The code I wanted to write was literally impossible when constrained by having protobuffers in the mix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While this is an anecdote, it’s not in isolation. By virtue of their rigid code-generation, manifestations of protobuffers in languages are never idiomatic, nor can they be made to be—short of rewriting the code-generator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But even then, you still have the problem of needing to embed a shitty type-system into the targeted language. Because most of protobuffers’ features are ill-conceived, these unsavory properties leak into our codebases. It means we’re forced to not only implement, but also use these bad ideas in any project which hopes to interface with protobuffers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While it’s easy to implement inane things out of a solid foundation, going the other direction is challenging at best and the dark path of Eldrich madness at worst.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In short, abandon all hope ye who introduce protobuffers into your projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;To this day, there’s a raging debate inside Google itself about proto2 and whether fields should ever be marked as&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;required&lt;/code&gt;. Manifestos with both titles “&lt;code&gt;optional&lt;/code&gt;considered harmful” and “&lt;code&gt;required&lt;/code&gt;considered harmful.” Good luck sorting that out.↩︎&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/protos-are-wrong/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45140381</id><title>MentraOS – open-source Smart glasses OS</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:57.150329+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="d2f052307bbfb732"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Works with Even Realities G1, Mentra Mach 1, Mentra Live. See smart glasses compatibility list here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Mentra Store already has a ton of useful apps that real users are running everyday. Here are some apps already published by developers on the Mentra Store:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MentraOS is how developers build smart glasses apps. We handle the pairing, connection, data streaming, and cross-compatibility, so you can focus on creating amazing apps. Every component is 100% open source (MIT license).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cross Compatibility: Your app runs on any pair of smart glasses&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Speed: TypeScript SDK means you're making apps in minutes, not months&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Control: Access smart glasses I/O - displays, microphones, cameras, speakers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Distribution: Get your app in front of everyone using smart glasses&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The MentraOS Community is a group of developers, companies, and users dedicated to ensuring the next personal computer is open, cross-compatible, and user-controlled. That's why we're building MentraOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get involved, join the MentraOS Community Discord server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have questions or ideas? We'd love to hear from you!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Email: team@mentra.glass&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Discord: Join our community&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Twitter: Follow @mentralabs&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MentraOS is made by a community and we welcome PRs. Here's the Contributors Guide: docs.mentra.glass/contributing&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT License Copyright 2025 MentraOS Community&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/Mentra-Community/MentraOS"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45141636</id><title>Making a font of my handwriting</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:56.435881+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3714a019faa705f8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Making a font of my handwriting&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Published on&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently Iâve been on a small campaign to try to make my personal website moreâ¦ personal. Little ways to make it obvious itâs mine and personal, not just another piece of the boring corporate dystopia that is most of the web these days. I donât quite want to fully regress to the Geocities era and fill the screen with animated under construction GIFs, but I do want to capture some of that vibe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâd added some bits and pieces along those lines: floating images in articles now look like theyâre stuck to the page with sellotape, related post links have a wavy border that animates when you hover over them, and so on. Next, I wanted to change the heading fonts from a monospace font to something cursive, to resemble handwriting. Less terminal output, more handwritten letter. I couldnât find one I liked, though. So why not make my own? It canât be that hard, right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Failing to do it myself&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I set out to try to make the font myself using open source tools. After doing a bit of research, it seemed like the general approach was to create vectors of each character and then import them into a font editor. That seems to mean either Adobe Illustrator and FontLab (if you have too much money) or Inkscape and FontForge (if you like open source). I fall firmly into the latter category, so I grabbed my graphics tablet and opened Inkscape.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wrote out my first three letters: capital A, B and C. Saved them in Inkscape, and attempted to import them into FontForge. Then I remembered one crucial thing that had slipped my mind: I absolutely loathe using FontForge. Itâs a bit like when you open an old version of GIMP and get a bunch of weird looking windows floating all over the place; it feels like youâre fighting against the tool to do even the most basic operations. The difference is I have cause to edit images a lot more than I edit fonts, and GIMP has actually significantly improved their UI over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are the rough steps I went through with FontForge:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Launch Font Forge. It shows a weird bit of art in one window, and an open file dialog in another.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I donât want to open a file, so I close that dialog. The program exits.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Relaunch Font Forge, and realise that within the âOpen Fontâ dialog is a âNewâ button. Click it.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Get to the standard font-editing UI. Right-click on the âAâ looking for a way to import an SVG. Donât see one.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Click around a bit, exploring the menus. Everything feels a bit off. You canât open one menu then hover over the next to see its content, like basically every UI toolkit in existence. I think FontForge has eschewed QT and GTK in favour of doing things itself.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Find the âImportâ option in the File menu. Hope itâs for a single glyph not the whole font.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A file picker opens. Again itâs all a bit off from normal desktop conventions. Try to resize it, and just get blank gray space at the bottom.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Type the absolute path I want to go to in the text field.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Get a dialog saying âNot a bdf file /home/chris/etcâ. Press OK.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Get a dialog saying âCould not find a bitmap font inâ. Press OK.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Press Ctrl+L to see if that lets me enter a path. Click everything in the dialog to try to find a way to enter a path. Get annoyed. Give up. Click through folder-by-folder to get to where I want to be.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Get to the folder and donât see any files. Change the format to âSVGâ. Double-click the newly-visible SVG file.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Get a dialog saying âYou must select a glyph before you can import an image into itâ. Press OK.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The import dialog goes away, having not imported.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Select the glyph in the main tool area, then repeat the FileâImport dance.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Itâs actually there now! Open the glyph in the editor and see itâs a complete mess of BÃ©zier curves. I canât click what I want without accidentally moving a handle for an adjacent curve.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rage-quit.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâm sure FontForge is less anger inducing once youâre used to it. And you definitely could use it to build a font like this if you had much more patience than me. Iâd had enough of death-by-a-thousand-paper-cuts though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I briefly tried Inkscapeâs built-in support for making an SVG font. It annoyed me a lot less, but itâs fiddly: it seemed like each font had to be a single path, so you had to convert the glyphs to paths, then merge them correctly. If you merge them incorrectly then the wrong bits of your letters end up filled (like the inside of the âBâ). Path manipulation is getting towards the limit of my knowledge of vector editing, and it took a bit of trial and error for each letter that had more than a single stroke. I didnât fancy doing that for every letter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâm usually a big advocate of open source, but this was one of those painful times where it feels like it just falls short. Clunky, painful UI and processes where commercial tools just let you get on with your work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;You can exchange money for goods and services&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Iâd been looking for open source tutorials, I found many mentions of a closed source, hosted tool: Calligraphr. It has a free version with limitations (no ligatures, no variations, 75 glyphs per font), and a pro version for Â£8/month. Iâd normally balk at the idea of a subscription for this, but they have the perfect answer: you can make a one-time payment, and your account automatically downgrades back to free after a month. Itâs not a hidden option, either, itâs the most prominent button on the upgrade page. That made me happy to give them Â£8 to play around with the service for a month.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Calligraphr works by having you print templates, write out the letters, then scan them in. It does some magical processing to extract the glyphs, provides tools to tidy them up, align them, etc, and then produces a TTF file for you. You can see some of my completed templates here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Calligraphr has a nice UI to generate the templates, allowing you to select which glyphs to include. I added the âminimal Englishâ, âbasic punctuationâ and âLigaturesâ sets. That gave me four pages to fill out, and I did them all twice. That let me filter out versions that didnât work well, and have variants for some letters so the font wasnât too repetitive. Later on, I went back and added some custom ligatures based on blog post titles that didnât look quite right: âReâ, âToâ, âersâ, âeyâ, âhyâ, âraâ, âreâ and âtyâ. Ligatures like this help it look more natural: when we write we donât just stamp out identical letters regardless of their surroundings, instead they will connect to their neighbours, or overlap slightly, or even share a stroke.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I filled these templates in with a Sharpie, as I wanted a fairly informal, scrap-booky look, and it would also give good solid shapes that should be easy to pick out of the template. I scanned them with the âScan Documentâ function on my iPhone, and uploaded the PDFs to Calligraphr.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Iterating and tweaking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Calligraphr UI allows you to preview the font, but I found it a lot more useful to just download a copy and use it on a local copy of my website. That let me test it with real text, and see how itâd look at the different font sizes I use on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first version was not great. Despite the guidelines on the template, I apparently wasnât good at sticking to them. Some letters were floating way off the baseline, and some were sunken below. When those opposites met it looked terrible. Fortunately Calligraphr has a pretty easy tool to slide each letter up and down, and scale it up or down if needed, and you can see it next to other letters as you do it. It took a little bit of time to go through all the variants of all the letters, but the next version looked a lot better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another tweak I ended up doing was reducing the spacing between letters. The defaults Calligraphr uses are probably good for a blocky font, but I wanted to put the letters close together to give it more of a joined-up look. Again, this is an easy tool to use, you just drag the sides in or out as desired. While these tweaking steps were probably as fiddly as some of the Inkscape steps I refused to do earlier, theyâre a lot more rewarding as you see things improving with each one. Itâs a lot easier for me to commit time and effort to improving something thatâs already working reasonably, than put that time and energy into an unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later, I noticed that occasionally there would be a huge gap in a title. Not âthe kerning is slightly offâ but âthereâs enough room to park a busâ. It took me a while to figure out what was happening: a couple of glyphs hadnât been isolated perfectly and had picked up a few pixels from the template lines at the edge of their boxes. That meant the glyph had a width that covered the actual written glyph, a big gap, and then the rogue marks. At first, I fixed this by just adjusting the width, but that left the little pixels floating awkwardly down-sentence. The proper fix was to use the editing tool and simply delete them, and then Calligraphr snapped the width back to what it should be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These iterations took a while to do, but I just dipped in and out occasionally over the course of a week, so it didnât actually feel like too much work. I quite enjoy the process of refining things, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Result and a surprise&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If youâre viewing this post on my website[1], you can see the font in the headers, captions, and a few other places. Hereâs how it compares to my actual handwriting:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs not close enough to forge documents, but I think it definitely gets across my style, and thatâs exactly what I wanted. Itâs surprisingly legible even at smaller font sizes â I think the weight of the Sharpie helps here â and at Â£8 and a bit of manual work was a lot more economical than spending days wresting with open source tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few weeks after I put the finishing touches on the font, I got an e-mail from Calligraphr. As my account had lapsed back to the free version, I was no longer eligible for the âserver-side backupâ feature. So what did they do? They e-mailed me an exported copy! Itâs a JSON file with the properties of each glyph and a base64 encoded image. Not only can I re-upload this to Calligraphr if I resubscribe, I can probably hook something up to edit it should I ever need to. Iâm blown away by how pro-user Calligraphrâs business practices are. Theyâre up-front about pricing, donât try and get you stuck on an auto-renewing subscription, and automatically export your data. Itâs like a breath of fresh air compared to the barrage of dark patterns that other websites foist on us. If you want to make this kind of font, Iâd definitely recommend them just because of how nice they are.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;And I havenât changed everything since writing this postâ¦ â©ï¸&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Related posts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Escaping Spotify the hard way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the longest time I used Spotify for all my music needs. And I listen to a lot of music: sometimes actively, but mostly passively as background noise. I cancelled my premium subscription last December, and stopped using the service entirely. Why? Thereâs a bunch of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How I use Tailscale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâve been using Tailscale for around four years to connect my disparate devices, servers and apps together. I wanted to talk a bit about how I use it, some cool features you might not know about, and some stumbling blocks I encountered.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Ethics of LLMs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Iâve written about LLMs a few times recently, carefully dodging the issue of ethics each time. I didnât want to bog down the other posts with it, and I wanted some time to think over the issues. Now Iâve had time to think, itâs time to remove my head from the sand. There are a lot of different angles to consider, and a lot of it is more nuanced than is often presented. Itâs not all doom and gloom, and itâs also not the most amazing thing since sliced bread. Who would have thought?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;If all you have is a hammerâ¦&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I presume everyone is familiar with the idiom âif all you have is a hammer, everything looks like a nailâ. If not, well, there it is. Itâs generally used pejoratively about being single-minded, but I think it also gives a glimpse into something more interesting: mental and perceptual sets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently Iâve been on a small campaign to try to make my personal website moreâ¦ personal. Little ways to make it obvious itâs mine and personal, not just another piece of the boring corporate dystopia that is most of the web these days. I donât quite want to fully regress to the Geocities era and fill the screen with animated under construction GIFs, but I do want to capture some of that vibe.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://chameth.com/making-a-font-of-my-handwriting/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45142397</id><title>My Own DNS Server at Home – Part 1: IPv4</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:55.613463+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="67234351e5b0b027"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Posted:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;My Own DNS Server At Home - Part 1: IPv4&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;âItâs always DNSâ is a famous meme among network people. Name resolution is technically quite simple. Itâs âjustâ translating a hostname like &lt;code&gt;jan.wildeboer.net&lt;/code&gt; to an IP address. What could possibly go wrong? I am a radical optimist and detail-obsessed knowledge collector, so I decided to find out. As part of my goal to make my home network a little island of Digital Sovereignty, meaning that everything at home should JustWorkâ¢, even with no working internet connection, a DNS server is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Based on and extended from my gist Bind on Fedora 42 as DNS server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I admit, I have a lot of experience with DNS and BIND. But I still consider myself to be merely on the GoodEnoughâ¢ side of things. I know how to get DNS configured for my domains. And I want you to feel fearless too. The best place to fail with DNS is the network at home. It limits the impact :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So read this blog post either as report or as a HOWTO. Both ways can be fun!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my homelab I have a Raspberry Pi 4 that runs infrastructure services. DNS is one of them, my private CA (Certificate Authority) another. The CA runs as a container on Podman. For DNS I use Bind. It thus has to serve 3 networks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;192.168.1.0/24&lt;/code&gt;My home IPv4 network&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;172.16.0.0/16&lt;/code&gt;IPv4 Network on the second ethernet ports of my homelab servers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;10.88.0.0/16&lt;/code&gt;The (virtual) podman network&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It uses my Fritz box (7490) as forwarder, so I can resolve all hosts, including the DHCP entries that the Fritz Box hands out under its default local domain name &lt;code&gt;fritz.box&lt;/code&gt;. For my homelab however, I use the &lt;code&gt;homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; domain name. Thatâs what the Bind DNS server has to take care of.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;WARNING&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;I really should use the official&lt;code&gt;.internal&lt;/code&gt;TLD (Top Level Domain) for my homelab network, but I decided against it. This introduces the risk of name resolution problems, should someone offer a public&lt;code&gt;.jhw&lt;/code&gt;TLD in future. Itâs a risk I am willing to accept in exchange for using a 3 letter TLD at home. Donât be like me! Use&lt;code&gt;.internal&lt;/code&gt;instead. With that out of the way, letâs continue.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What we (well, I) have&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Letâs gather what I have in my home network.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;inf01.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;at&lt;code&gt;192.168.1.10&lt;/code&gt;: A Raspberry Pi 4 4GB, running Fedora 42 and podman with my Certificate Authority as a container that should be reachable as&lt;code&gt;ca.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;. See Be the LetsEncrypt in your homelab with step-ca for more details.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;3 ThinkCentre Tiny PCs in the &lt;code&gt;homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;zone, called hl01 (&lt;code&gt;192.168.1.11&lt;/code&gt;), hl02 (&lt;code&gt;192.168.1.12&lt;/code&gt;) and hl03 (&lt;code&gt;192.168.1.13&lt;/code&gt;), running RHEL10 (Red Hat Enterprise Linux)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A Fritz Box 7490 at &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.254&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Letâs install BIND on inf01&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need to do two things. Install BIND and some utilities on &lt;code&gt;inf01&lt;/code&gt; and open the firewall for DNS traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;dnf install bind bind-utils
firewall-cmd --add-service=dns --permanent
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That was easy enough :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Configure BIND&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To run BIND in the correct way, we need to work on 4 configuration files.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/etc/named.conf&lt;/code&gt;The main configuration file where we tell BIND on which networks it should listen and what zones it will serve.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/var/named/forward.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;The forward zone file that maps hostnames in the&lt;code&gt;homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;domain to IP addresses on my home network&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/var/named/reverse.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;The reverse zone for the&lt;code&gt;192.168.1.0/24&lt;/code&gt;network range, that looks a bit confusing, that does the opposite. It maps IP addresses to hostnames.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/var/named/reverse2.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;The second reverse zone for the&lt;code&gt;172.16.0.0/16&lt;/code&gt;network range.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Letâs start with &lt;code&gt;/etc/named.conf&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;//
// named.conf
//

options {
  listen-on port 53 { 127.0.0.1; 192.168.1.10; 172.16.1.10; 10.88.0.1; };
  listen-on-v6 port 53 { ::1; fdda:a4da:69a5:0:2783:8c26:b2f1:a6f7; };
  allow-query     { localhost; 192.168.1.0/24; 172.16.0.0/16; 10.88.0.0/16; };

  directory       "/var/named";

  dump-file       "/var/named/data/cache_dump.db";
  statistics-file "/var/named/data/named_stats.txt";
  memstatistics-file "/var/named/data/named_mem_stats.txt";
  secroots-file   "/var/named/data/named.secroots";
  recursing-file  "/var/named/data/named.recursing";

  forwarders { 192.168.1.254; };
  recursion yes;

  dnssec-validation no;

  managed-keys-directory "/var/named/dynamic";
  geoip-directory "/usr/share/GeoIP";

  pid-file "/run/named/named.pid";
  session-keyfile "/run/named/session.key";

  /* https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Changes/CryptoPolicy */
  include "/etc/crypto-policies/back-ends/bind.config";
};

logging {
        channel default_debug {
                file "data/named.run";
                severity dynamic;
        };
};

zone "." IN {
	type hint;
	file "named.ca";
};

zone "homelab.jhw" IN {
	type master;
	file "forward.homelab.jhw";
	allow-update { none; };
	allow-query { any; };
};

zone "1.168.192.in-addr.arpa" IN {
	type master;
	file "reverse.homelab.jhw";
	allow-update { none; };
	allow-query { any; };
};

zone "16.172.in-addr.arpa" IN {
        type master;
        file "reverse2.homelab.jhw";
        allow-update { none; };
        allow-query { any; };
};

include "/etc/named.rfc1912.zones";
include "/etc/named.root.key";
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first block declare the general options. Yes, it looks complicated and it is, but letâs walk you through every relevant line (the lines not mentioned are default entries that donât need to be changed).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;listen-on port 53 { 127.0.0.1; 192.168.1.10; 172.16.1.10; 10.88.0.1; };
listen-on-v6 port 53 { ::1; fdda:a4da:69a5:0:2783:8c26:b2f1:a6f7; };
allow-query     { localhost; 192.168.1.0/24; 172.16.0.0/16; 10.88.0.0/16; };
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here we tell BIND that it should listen for queries on port 53 on &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.10&lt;/code&gt;, the IPv4 address in my hoem network, &lt;code&gt;172.16.1.10&lt;/code&gt;, the second IPv4 address configured and &lt;code&gt;10.88.0.1&lt;/code&gt;, the virtual IPv4 address the Raspberry uses to bridge to the local podman containers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second line does the same for IPv6, but that is something we will discuss in Part 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The third line tells BIND from whom to accept queries. Essentially from everyone on the three IPv4 networks we are listening to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;directory       "/var/named";
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the directory where BIND will look for its zone files, that we will define later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;forwarders { 192.168.1.254; };
recursion yes;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now what if someone asks for a hostname that is outside of &lt;code&gt;homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;? In that case we tell BIND to forward that question to &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.254&lt;/code&gt;, our Fritz Box. We will allow recursion and cache results we get from our Fritz box to avoid unneeded traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;dnssec-validation no;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our simple setup will not bother with DNSSEC at the moment. Maybe we will have a Part 3 for that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OK. That was the options part. We will ignore the &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt; part and the &lt;code&gt;zone "." IN&lt;/code&gt; block.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next (and finally) we define three zone entries (and zone files). A forward zone called &lt;code&gt;homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; for our domain and two reverse zones for the IP addresses in the &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.0/24&lt;/code&gt; range called &lt;code&gt;1.168.192.in-addr.arpa&lt;/code&gt;. Yep. Thatâs 192.168.1 reversed. 1.168.192. Thatâs why itâs called the reverse zone ;) We also have &lt;code&gt;16.172.in-addr.arpa&lt;/code&gt; for the &lt;code&gt;172.16.0.0/16&lt;/code&gt; range. Letâs look at them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;zone "homelab.jhw" IN {
	type master;
	file "forward.homelab.jhw";
	allow-update { none; };
	allow-query { any; };
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs a zone, all right. Itâs the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; for this zone, meaning that this DNS server will be the Source of Truth to  answer all queries for the &lt;code&gt;homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; hostnames.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The exact mapping of all hostnames to IP addresses is in a file called &lt;code&gt;forward.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; in the directory &lt;code&gt;/var/named&lt;/code&gt;. Remember how we defined that path at the beginning in the &lt;code&gt;options&lt;/code&gt; part? Great! We also tell BIND that we do not allow dynamic updates for this zone, meaning that whatâs in the file is all we will look at. Finally we tell BIND that any machine in the network is allowed to ask for a reply.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;zone "1.168.192.in-addr.arpa" IN {
	type master;
	file "reverse.homelab.jhw";
	allow-update { none; };
	allow-query { any; };
};

zone "16.172.in-addr.arpa" IN {
        type master;
        file "reverse2.homelab.jhw";
        allow-update { none; };
        allow-query { any; };
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reverse zones with the weird looking zone names are almost the same, except that we define these in two files called &lt;code&gt;reverse.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; for the reverse lookup of the &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.0/24&lt;/code&gt; range and &lt;code&gt;reverse2.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; for the &lt;code&gt;172.16.0.0/16&lt;/code&gt; range. Why these zones have weird names will be explained later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So now we go to the zone files!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Forward zone for homelab.jhw&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The forward zone resolves names to IP addresses using A records (and other types like TXT, CAA and many more exist, but we wonât cover that in this post). It also contains CNAME entries, if you have services on one machine that should be reachable via more than one hostnames. In my homelab the CA (Certificate Authority) server is a container that runs on &lt;code&gt;inf01.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;, but should be reachable as &lt;code&gt;ca.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; in the home network. The CNAME entry does exactly that. It tells clients that when they want to talk to &lt;code&gt;ca.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; they can. By actually talking to &lt;code&gt;inf01.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now here is the big, important lessen for zone files. They have a serial number. Which MUST be incremented with every change. If you donât, weird things WILL happen. So:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;NEVER FORGET TO INCREASE THE SERIAL WITH EVERY CHANGE TO A ZONE FILE. OR RISK DNS HELL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;/var/named/forward.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$TTL 3600
@   IN  SOA     inf01.homelab.jhw. root.homelab.jhw. (
        2025082706  ;Serial
        3600        ;Refresh
        1800        ;Retry
        604800      ;Expire
        86400       ;Minimum TTL
)
@       IN  NS          inf01.homelab.jhw.
@       IN  A           192.168.1.10

inf01           IN  A     192.168.1.10
hl01            IN  A     192.168.1.11
hl02            IN  A     192.168.1.12
hl03            IN  A     192.168.1.13

ca              IN  CNAME inf01.homelab.jhw.

inf01-m         IN  A     172.16.1.10
hl01-m          IN  A     172.16.1.11
hl02-m          IN  A     172.16.1.12
hl03-m          IN  A     172.16.1.13
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, letâs go through this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$TTL 3600
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default Time To Live (TTL) for DNS entries is set at 3600 seconds. Thatâs 1 hour. This means that when a machine in the network gets a DNS reply, it will not ask again for the same thing until the TTL has passed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@   IN  SOA     inf01.homelab.jhw. root.homelab.jhw. (
        2025082706  ;Serial
        3600        ;Refresh
        1800        ;Retry
        604800      ;Expire
        86400       ;Minimum TTL
)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Start Of Authority (SOA) block. Here we say which DNS server is the owner of this domain. Itâs &lt;code&gt;inf01.homelab.jhw.&lt;/code&gt; (yes, that dot at the end is REALLY important). The &lt;code&gt;root.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; actually means &lt;code&gt;root@homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; and is the email address responsible for this domain. Donât think to much about why and what :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@       IN  NS          inf01.homelab.jhw.
@       IN  A           192.168.1.10
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first ârealâ DNS entries! They are special, as the &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt; indicates, which means they represent the domain itself. We first define the nameserver (again? yes, don*ât ask) as NS record. And right after that we define the &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; record as the IP address &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.10&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Did you notice that &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; at the end of &lt;code&gt;inf01.homelab.jhw.&lt;/code&gt;? Thatâs another VERY important thing. The TL;DR is that this final &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; tells DNS to stop doing fancy recursion and lookups. Just look for the hostname `inf01.homelab.jhw. Period. (pun intended). Donât care too much about this. Just remember:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EVERY HOSTNAME RECORD ENDS WITH A &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; YOU WILL FORGET THIS. YOU WILL FIX THIS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;inf01           IN  A     192.168.1.10
hl01            IN  A     192.168.1.11
hl02            IN  A     192.168.1.12
hl03            IN  A     192.168.1.13
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here come the &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; records for &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.0/24&lt;/code&gt;! We finally get to map hostnames to IP addresses. For real! It now is quite self-explanatory, isnât it? The hostname gets an A record that is the IP address in my local network. And as these are IP addresses, no &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; is needed at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ca              IN  CNAME inf01.homelab.jhw.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here is the CNAME record. Which maps the hostname &lt;code&gt;ca.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; to the Canonical NAME (CNAME) &lt;code&gt;inf01.homelab.jhw.&lt;/code&gt;. This is a hostname at the end! So it needs the &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; Period :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;inf01-m         IN  A     172.16.1.10
hl01-m          IN  A     172.16.1.11
hl02-m          IN  A     172.16.1.12
hl03-m          IN  A     172.16.1.13
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here we create another set of &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; records for the same machines, but this time in the &lt;code&gt;172.16.0.0/16&lt;/code&gt; range. This range is used for management stuff, hence the &lt;code&gt;-m&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And thatâs the gist of it. If you add a new machine to your network, configure it with an IP address (statically or with DHCP) and add it as an A record to the forward zone. Increment the serial and tell DNS to read the updated zone with &lt;code&gt;systemctl reload named&lt;/code&gt;. Done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Reverse zones for 192.168.1.0/24 and 172.16.0.0/16&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reverse zone maps IP addresses to hostnames. Often called the PTR or pointer record. You have to make sure that the entries here are synced to the forward zone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;NEVER FORGET TO INCREASE THE SERIAL WITH EVERY CHANGE TO A ZONE FILE. Or risk DNS hell.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the reverse zone for the &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.0/24&lt;/code&gt; range.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;/var/named/reverse.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$TTL 3600
@   IN  SOA     inf01.homelab.jhw. root.homelab.jhw. (
        2025082601  ;Serial
        3600        ;Refresh
        1800        ;Retry
        604800      ;Expire
        86400       ;Minimum TTL
)
@       IN  NS          inf01.homelab.jhw.
@       IN  PTR         homelab.jhw.
10      IN  PTR         inf01.homelab.jhw.
11      IN  PTR         hl01.homelab.jhw.
12      IN  PTR         hl02.homelab.jhw.
13      IN  PTR         hl03.homelab.jhw.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As this is more or less the same but the other way round, I will not go through everything but instead explain the differences. Itâs the reverse zone, so now we have &lt;code&gt;PTR&lt;/code&gt; (pointer) entries that map an IPv4 address in the &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.0/24&lt;/code&gt; range to hostnames. WITH A DOT AT THE END. DO NOT FORGET THE DOT!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As this is a /24 block, we only need to set the last digit of the IPv4 address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might wonder, where is &lt;code&gt;ca&lt;/code&gt; here? Well, itâs CNAME is &lt;code&gt;info1.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt; and that already is in this reverse zone. That is good enough. No separate entry needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also need the reverse zone for the &lt;code&gt;172.16.0.0/16&lt;/code&gt; range:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;/var/named/reverse2.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$TTL 3600
@   IN  SOA     inf01.homelab.jhw. root.homelab.jhw. (
        2025082901  ;Serial
        3600        ;Refresh
        1800        ;Retry
        604800      ;Expire
        86400       ;Minimum TTL
)
@       IN  NS          inf01.homelab.jhw.
@       IN  PTR         homelab.jhw.
10.1      IN  PTR         inf01-m.homelab.jhw.
11.1      IN  PTR         hl01-m.homelab.jhw.
12.1      IN  PTR         hl02-m.homelab.jhw.
13.1      IN  PTR         hl03-m.homelab.jhw.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looks deceivingly similar. But there is a big difference. This is a /16 network, so we have to define the last two parts of the IPv4 address. And as it is a reverse zone file, yep, we have to reverse it. So now we need &lt;code&gt;10.1&lt;/code&gt; to define the entry for &lt;code&gt;172.16.1.10&lt;/code&gt;, which is the hostname &lt;code&gt;inf01-m.homelab.jhw&lt;/code&gt;. WITH THE DOT AT THE END. AND DID YOU UPDATE THE SERIAL? :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Phew. Thatâs the config done!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A final check with the &lt;code&gt;named-checkconf&lt;/code&gt; command, which should say nothing when all files are OK. If not, it will tell you what is wrong so you get the chance to fix stuff. You did add all the &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; at the end of hostnames and you did update the serial of that zone file after you made changes, yes?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Start Bind&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only thing remaining is to start BIND. And persist it as a service, so it starts after every boot. Itâs DNS. It must always be available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;systemctl enable named
systemctl start named
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You most likely will make typos in your config. So do check with &lt;code&gt;named-checkconf &lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;systemctl status named&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;journalctl -u named&lt;/code&gt;. If something breaks, read this whole entry again. Find that missing &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; in a zone file. Increment the &lt;code&gt;serial&lt;/code&gt; that you forgot to do. You will get there. Donât give up!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Result&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Machines, containers etc can now be resolved in my home network. All with mow own DNS! Yay!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;% nslookup jhwfritz.fritz.box
Server:		192.168.1.10
Address:	192.168.1.10#53

Non-authoritative answer:
Name:	jhwfritz.fritz.box
Address: 192.168.1.254

% nslookup ca.homelab.jhw    
Server:		192.168.1.10
Address:	192.168.1.10#53

ca.homelab.jhw	canonical name = inf01.homelab.jhw.
Name:	inf01.homelab.jhw
Address: 192.168.1.10
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And now you should be able to &lt;code&gt;ping&lt;/code&gt; the machines with their hostname. ssh into them. Get certificates with the CA that runs in the podman container. Life is good!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed this post and could learn something new! Feel free to comment or send corrections vie the Toot linked below that collects the comments!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;COMMENTS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can use your Mastodon or other ActivityPub account to comment on this article by replying to the associated post.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://jan.wildeboer.net/2025/08/My-DNS-Part-1/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45142885</id><title>Anthropic agrees to pay $1.5B to settle lawsuit with book authors</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:55.404868+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/09/05/technology/anthropic-settlement-copyright-ai.html?unlocked_article_code=1.jk8.bTTt.Zir9wmtPaTp2&amp;smid=url-share"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45144337</id><title>The Universe Within 12.5 Light Years</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:54.824263+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b21697bf7e9b7625"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Universe within 12.5 Light Years&lt;lb/&gt;The Nearest Stars&lt;/head&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Number of stars within 12.5 light years = 33&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;About the Map&lt;/head&gt; This map shows all the star systems that lie within 12.5 light years of our Sun. Most of the stars are red dwarfs - stars with a tenth of the Sun's mass and less than one hundredth the luminosity. Roughly eighty percent of all the stars in the universe are red dwarfs, and the nearest star - Proxima - is a typical example. &lt;div&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell colspan="2" role="head"&gt;Additional Maps&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt; This is a diagram that zooms out from the Earth's orbit to the nearest star system. It tries to show just how large the distance to the nearest star really is.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Here is a map of all the known stars that lie within 20 light years plotted using the data provided below.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell colspan="2" role="head"&gt;Data and Catalogs&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt; There are over 100 stars within 20 light years. This is a list of the known stars that lie within this distance.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt; This is a page showing some simple animations of double, triple and quadruple star systems, to demonstrate how stars orbit each other.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Information on the Nearest Stars&lt;/head&gt;&lt;list rend="dl"&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Sun - Type=G2, Magnitude=-26.8, Distance=0.0000158 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;A typical yellow dwarf star. It has eight planets orbiting it.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Proxima Centauri - Type=M5, Magnitude=11.0, Distance=4.22 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;This dim red dwarf is the nearest star to the Sun, and it is a member of the Alpha Centauri system despite lying 0.24 light years from the main pair of stars, requiring over one million years to orbit them. Proxima was discovered in 1915 by Robert Innes and was at that time the least luminous star known. It is also a flare star - capable of brightening a magnitude or more in minutes.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Alpha Centauri A,B - Type=G2+K0, Magnitudes=0.0+1.4, Distance=4.39 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;Just slightly further from us than Proxima, lie the orange and yellow dwarf stars that make up Alpha Centauri. Orbiting each other in an 80 year period, together they make up one of the brightest objects in southern hemisphere skies. Seen from Alpha Centauri, the third member of the system, Proxima, is a dim (magnitude 4.8) star.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;Barnard's Star - Type=M5, Magnitude=9.6, Distance=5.94 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;Famous for having the largest proper motion of any star, this dim red dwarf travels 0.29 degrees against the background sky in a century. Discovered by E Barnard in 1916, it was thought in the 1960's to have a couple of unseen planets orbiting it, but later observations disproved this. In another 8000 years Barnard's Star will become the closest star to us.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-5"&gt;Wolf 359 - Type=M6, Magnitude=13.5, Distance=7.80 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-5"&gt;An excessively dim red dwarf discovered by Max Wolf in 1918. For 25 years it was the least luminous star known.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-6"&gt;Lalande 21185 - Type=M2, Magnitude=7.5, Distance=8.31 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-6"&gt;Recorded in JJ Lalande's star catalogue compiled in the 1790's, this is one of the brightest red dwarfs in the sky, but it still needs binoculars to see it. G Gatewood reported in 1996 the possible indications of a couple of Jupiter sized planets orbiting it but this remains unconfirmed.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-7"&gt;Sirius A,B - Type=A1+DA, Magnitudes=-1.4+8.4, Distance=8.60 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-7"&gt;This brilliant white star is the brightest star in the night sky and the most luminous star within 25 light years. Its white dwarf companion was first seen in 1852, the first white dwarf ever seen. The orbital period is 50 years.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-8"&gt;Luyten 726-8 A,B - Type=M5+M5, Magnitudes=12.4+13.3, Distance=8.73 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-8"&gt;This is a dim binary system consisting of two red dwarfs. The system is perhaps more famously known as UV Ceti, the variable-star name of the second star in the system. It is a famous flare star and can visibly brighten by several magnitudes as it ejects flares from its surface similar to the ones seen on the surface of the Sun, but far more energetic. Both stars require about 200 years to orbit each other.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-9"&gt;Ross 154 - Type=M4, Magnitude=10.4, Distance=9.69 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-9"&gt;A dim red dwarf. It is one of a number of nearby stars catalogued by Frank Ross in the 1930's. It is also a known flare star.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-10"&gt;Ross 248 - Type=M6, Magnitude=12.3, Distance=10.33 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-10"&gt;Another dim red dwarf.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-11"&gt;Epsilon Eridani - Type=K2, Magnitude=3.7, Distance=10.50 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-11"&gt;An orange dwarf star. This star was searched for signs of intelligent life with the Green Bank radio telescope in 1960. The results, predictably, were negative. The IRAS satellite detected a lot of dust orbiting this star indicating a possible forming solar system, and even more recently, (Aug 2000), a Jupiter sized planet has been detected orbiting this star at a distance of 3.2 AU (480 million km).&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-12"&gt;Lacaille 9352 - Type=M2, Magnitude=7.4, Distance=10.73 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-12"&gt;A fairly bright red dwarf which can easily be seen with binoculars, it was first recorded in Nicolas de Lacaille's catalogue of southern hemisphere stars compiled around 1752.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-13"&gt;Ross 128 - Type=M4, Magnitude=11.1, Distance=10.89 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-13"&gt;A dim red dwarf, also known as FI Vir - its variable star designation.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-14"&gt;Luyten 789-6 A,B,C - Type=M5+M5+M7, Magnitudes=13.3+13.3+14.0, Distance=11.1 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-14"&gt;There seems to be three red dwarfs in this system. The main pair orbiting each other in a 2 year period, and a dim third star orbiting the first at a very close range.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-15"&gt;Procyon A,B - Type=F5+DA, Magnitudes=0.4+10.7, Distance=11.41 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-15"&gt;A brilliant yellow-white star, and the eighth brightest star in the sky. With twice the diameter of the Sun, Procyon is also the largest star within 25 light years. Procyon is orbited by a white dwarf companion first seen optically in 1896. The orbital period is 41 years.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-16"&gt;61 Cygni A,B - Type=K5+K7, Magnitudes=5.2+6.1, Distance=11.41 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-16"&gt;This binary system of two orange dwarf stars is famous for being the first star ever to have its distance measured by F Bessel in 1838. Both stars are very similar but are widely separated (86 AU) requiring about 700 years to orbit each other.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-17"&gt;Struve 2398 A,B - Type=M4+M5, Magnitudes=8.9+9.7, Distance=11.6 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-17"&gt;A binary system of two red dwarfs named Struve 2398 from a catalogue of double stars published in 1827. This system is also known by the rather more boring name of BD+59°1915. The two stars are quite widely separated (50 AU) and orbit each other in a 450 year period.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-18"&gt;Groombridge 34 A,B - Type=M2+M6, Magnitudes=8.1+11.1, Distance=11.64 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-18"&gt;Another pair of red dwarfs, this system is usually called Groombridge 34 from an 1838 catalogue of northern stars or sometimes BD+43°44. Both stars are variable in brightness and have the variable star names of GX And and GQ And. Both stars lie far apart from each other (150 AU) and orbit each other in a 2500 year period.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-19"&gt;Giclas 51-15 - Type=M6, Magnitude=14.8, Distance=11.8 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-19"&gt;This excessively dim red dwarf is the least luminous star within 14 light years. It shines with just 0.01% of the Sun's luminosity.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-20"&gt;Epsilon Indi A,B,C - Type=K5+T1+T6, Magnitude=4.7, Distance=11.83 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-20"&gt;An orange dwarf. It is a similar star to Epsilon Eridani, although a little bit smaller and dimmer. Epsilon Indi is orbited by a pair of brown dwarfs - failed stars that are too small to burn. They were discovered in 2003 and they orbit each other in a 16 year period, and they are 1500 AU (220 billion km) from the main star and they require about 70 000 years to orbit it.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-21"&gt;Tau Ceti - Type=G8, Magnitude=3.5, Distance=11.90 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-21"&gt;The nearest, single, sun-like star. It was searched (unsuccessfully) for any signs of intelligent life in 1960, along with Epsilon Eridani.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-22"&gt;Luyten 372-58 - Type=M5, Magnitude=13.0, Distance=12.1 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-22"&gt;A very dim red dwarf. Although this star was catalogued decades ago, it has only recently had its distance determined with any accuracy.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-23"&gt;Luyten 725-32 - Type=M5, Magnitude=12.1, Distance=12.1 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-23"&gt;Another dim red dwarf.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dt-24"&gt;Luyten's Star - Type=M3, Magnitude=9.8, Distance=12.39 ly&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item rend="dd-24"&gt;A red dwarf. It is named after Willem Luyten who realised it was a nearby star in 1935. The star lies just 1.2 light years away from Procyon, but it is not associated with it.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt; Epsilon Eridani is orbited by a large planet which might look like this. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="http://www.atlasoftheuniverse.com/12lys.html"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45144900</id><title>Tesla changes meaning of 'Full Self-Driving', gives up on promise of autonomy</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:54.734846+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="adcd098cbd93d352"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tesla has changed the meaning of “Full Self-Driving”, also known as “FSD”, to give up on its original promise of delivering unsupervised autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since 2016, Tesla has claimed that all its vehicles in production would be capable of achieving unsupervised self-driving capability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CEO Elon Musk has claimed that it would happen by the end of every year since 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tesla has even sold a software package, known as “Full Self-Driving Capability” (FSD), for up to $15,000 to customers, promising that the advanced driver-assist system would become fully autonomous through over-the-air software updates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Almost a decade later, the promise has yet to be fulfilled, and Tesla has already confirmed that all vehicles produced between 2016 and 2023 don’t have the proper hardware to deliver unsupervised self-driving as promised.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Musk has been discussing the upgrade of the computers in these vehicles to appease owners, but there’s no concrete plan to implement it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While there’s no doubt that Tesla has promised unsupervised self-driving capabilities to FSD buyers between 2016 and 2023, the automaker has since updated its language and now only sells “Full Self-Driving (Supervised)” to customers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fine print mentions that it doesn’t make the vehicle “autonomous” and doesn’t promise it as a feature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In other words, people buying FSD today are not really buying the capability of unsupervised self-driving as prior buyers did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Tesla’s board has just submitted a new, unprecedented CEO compensation package for shareholders’ approval, which could give Musk up to $1 trillion in stock options pending the achievement of certain milestones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of these milestones is Tesla having “10 Million Active FSD Subscriptions.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At first glance, this would be hopeful for FSD buyers since part of Musk’s compensation would be dependent on delivering on the FSD promises.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, Tesla has changed the definition of FSD in the compensation package with an extremely vague one”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“FSD” means an advanced driving system, regardless of the marketing name used, that is capable of performing transportation tasks that provide autonomous or similar functionality under specified driving conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tesla now considers FSD only an “advanced driving system” that should be “capable of performing transportation tasks that prove autonomous or similar functionality”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The current version of FSD, which requires constant supervising by the driver, could easily fit that description.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Therefore, FSD now doesn’t come with the inital promise of Tesla owners being able to go to sleep in their vehicles and wake up at their destination – a promise that Musk has used to sell Tesla vehicles for years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Electrek’s Take&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The way Tesla discusses autonomy with customers and investors versus how it presents it in its court filings and legally binding documents is strikingly different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It should be worrying to anyone with an interest in this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this very vague description in the new CEO compensation package, Tesla could literally lower the price of FSD and even remove base Autopilot to push customers toward FSD and give Musk hundreds of billions of dollars in shares in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Top comment by CRisner&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whoop. There it is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just like the comment years ago that Tesla would “open their network to non-Tesla’s by the end of the year” caused folks to think that suddenly non-Tesla vehicles worldwide would be able to use their Supercharger network, by year end, it turns out that a few charging stations in Norway opened up their CSS Tesla chargers to non-Tesla cars.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So technically correct, and accurate, but nothing like everyone thought would happen, especially in the USA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I swear, anymore I feel its more interesting to wait for he “gotcha” from Tesla than it is to hear the intial announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So today, Tesla puts a metric in place for Musk to be paid that includes a specific number of FSD cars on the road, then they change the definition of FSD to basically mean the same thing as their current Autopilot system. Suddenly every single Tesla meets the “FSD” definition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brilliant move. Check. Wonder what the next move will be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s precedent for Tesla decreasing pricing on FSD. Initially, Musk said that Tesla would gradually increase the price of the FSD package as the features improved and approached unsupervised autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That was true for a while, but then Tesla started slashing FSD prices, which are now down $7,000 from their high in 2023:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trend is quite apparent and coincidentally began when Tesla’s sales started to decline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FSD is now a simple ADAS system without any promise of unsupervised self-driving. This might quite honestly be one of the biggest cases of false advertising or bait-and-switch ever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links. More.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://electrek.co/2025/09/05/tesla-changes-meaning-full-self-driving-give-up-promise-autonomy/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45145457</id><title>GLM 4.5 with Claude Code</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:54.354956+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="ccd2e51a790b4291"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;code&gt;thinking.type&lt;/code&gt;parameter (with &lt;code&gt;enabled&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;disabled&lt;/code&gt; settings), and dynamic thinking is enabled by default.
&lt;p&gt;Our most powerful reasoning model, with 355 billion parameters&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cost-Effective Lightweight Strong Performance&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;High Performance Strong Reasoning Ultra-Fast Response&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lightweight Strong Performance Ultra-Fast Response&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Free Strong Performance Excellent for Reasoning Coding &amp;amp; Agents&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;thinking.type&lt;/code&gt; parameter. This parameter supports two values: &lt;code&gt;enabled&lt;/code&gt; (enabled) and &lt;code&gt;disabled&lt;/code&gt; (disabled). By default, dynamic thinking is enabled.
&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://docs.z.ai/guides/llm/glm-4.5"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45145794</id><title>Developing a Space Flight Simulator in Clojure</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:53.591970+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="4c23b196c6d1b91"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Developing a Space Flight Simulator in Clojure&lt;/head&gt;05 Sep 2025&lt;p&gt;In 2017 I discovered the free of charge Orbiter 2016 space flight simulator which was proprietary at the time and it inspired me to develop a space flight simulator myself. I prototyped some rigid body physics in C and later in GNU Guile and also prototyped loading and rendering of Wavefront OBJ files. I used GNU Guile (a Scheme implementation) because it has a good native interface and of course it has hygienic macros. Eventually I got interested in Clojure because unlike GNU Guile it has multi-methods as well as fast hash maps and vectors. I finally decided to develop the game for real in Clojure. I have been developing a space flight simulator in Clojure for almost 5 years now. While using Clojure I have come to appreciate the immutable values and safe parallelism using atoms, agents, and refs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the beginning I decided to work on the hard parts first, which for me were 3D rendering of a planet, an atmosphere, shadows, and volumetric clouds. I read the OpenGL Superbible to get an understanding on what functionality OpenGL provides. When Orbiter was eventually open sourced and released unter MIT license here, I inspected the source code and discovered that about 90% of the code is graphics-related. So starting with the graphics problems was not a bad decision.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Software dependencies&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following software is used for development. The software libraries run on both GNU/Linux and Microsoft Windows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Clojure the programming language&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;LWJGL provides Java wrappers for various libraries &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;lwjgl-opengl for 3D graphics&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;lwjgl-glfw for windowing and input devices&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;lwjgl-nuklear for graphical user interfaces&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;lwjgl-stb for image I/O and using truetype fonts&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;lwjgl-assimp to load glTF 3D models with animation data&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Jolt Physics to simulate wheeled vehicles and collisions with meshes&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Fastmath for fast matrix and vector math as well as spline interpolation&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Comb for templating shader code&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Instaparse to parse NASA Planetary Constant Kernel (PCK) files&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Gloss to parse NASA Double Precision Array Files (DAF)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Coffi as a foreign function interface&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;core.memoize for least recently used caching of function results&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Apache Commons Compress to read map tiles from tar files&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Malli to add schemas to functions&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Immuconf to load the configuration file&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Progrock a progress bar for long running builds&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Claypoole to implement parallel for loops&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;tools.build to build the project&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;clj-async-profiler Clojure profiler creating flame graphs&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;slf4j-timbre Java logging implementation for Clojure&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deps.edn file contains operating system dependent LWJGL bindings. For example on GNU/Linux the deps.edn file contains the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to manage the different dependencies for Microsoft Windows, a separate Git branch is maintained.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Atmosphere rendering&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the atmosphere, Brunetonâs precomputed atmospheric scattering was used. The implementation uses a 2D transmittance table, a 2D surface scattering table, a 4D Rayleigh scattering, and a 4D Mie scattering table. The tables are computed using several iterations of numerical integration. Higher order functions for integration over a sphere and over a line segment were implemented in Clojure. Integration over a ray in 3D space (using fastmath vectors) was implemented as follows for example:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Precomputing the atmospheric tables takes several hours even though pmap was used. When sampling the multi-dimensional functions, pmap was used as a top-level loop and map was used for interior loops. Using java.nio.ByteBuffer the floating point values were converted to a byte array and then written to disk using a clojure.java.io/output-stream:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When launching the game, the lookup tables get loaded and copied into OpenGL textures. Shader functions are used to lookup and interpolate values from the tables. When rendering the planet surface or the space craft, the atmosphere essentially gets superimposed using ray tracing. After rendering the planet, a background quad is rendered to display the remaining part of the atmosphere above the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Templating OpenGL shaders&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is possible to make programming with OpenGL shaders more flexible by using a templating library such as Comb. The following shader defines multiple octaves of noise on a base noise function:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One can then for example define the function fbm_noise using octaves of the base function noise as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Planet rendering&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;To render the planet, NASA Bluemarble data, NASA Blackmarble data, and NASA Elevation data was used. The images were converted to a multi resolution pyramid of map tiles. The following functions were implemented for color map tiles and for elevation tiles:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;a function to load and cache map tiles of given 2D tile index and level of detail&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;a function to extract a pixel from a map tile&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;a function to extract the pixel for a specific longitude and latitude&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;The functions for extracting a pixel for given longitude and latitude then were used to generate a cube map with a quad tree of tiles for each face. For each tile, the following files were generated:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;A daytime texture&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;A night time texture&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;An image of 3D vectors defining a surface mesh&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;A water mask&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;A normal map&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Altogether 655350 files were generated. Because the Steam ContentBuilder does not support a large number of files, each row of tile data was aggregated into a tar file. The Apache Commons Compress library allows you to open a tar file to get a list of entries and then perform random access on the contents of the tar file. A Clojure LRU cache was used to maintain a cache of open tar files for improved performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At run time, a future is created, which returns an updated tile tree, a list of tiles to drop, and a path list of the tiles to load into OpenGL. When the future is realized, the main thread deletes the OpenGL textures from the drop list, and then uses the path list to get the new loaded images from the tile tree, load them into OpenGL textures, and create an updated tile tree with the new OpenGL textures added. The following functions to manipulate quad trees were implemented to realize this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Other topics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Solar system&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The astronomy code for getting the position and orientation of planets was implemented according to the Skyfield Python library. The Python library in turn is based on the SPICE toolkit of the NASA JPL. The JPL basically provides sequences of Chebyshev polynomials to interpolate positions of Moon and planets as well as the orientation of the Moon as binary files. Reference coordinate systems and orientations of other bodies are provided in text files which consist of human and machine readable sections. The binary files were parsed using Gloss (see Wiki for some examples) and the text files using Instaparse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Jolt bindings&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The required Jolt functions for wheeled vehicle dynamics and collisions with meshes were wrapped in C functions and compiled into a shared library. The Coffi Clojure library (which is a wrapper for Javaâs new Foreign Function &amp;amp; Memory API) was used to make the C functions and data types usable in Clojure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example the following code implements a call to the C function add_force:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here ::vec3 refers to a custom composite type defined using basic types. The memory layout, serialisation, and deserialisation for ::vec3 are defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Performance&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The clj-async-profiler was used to create flame graphs visualising the performance of the game. In order to get reflection warnings for Java calls without sufficient type declarations, *warn-on-reflection* was set to true.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore to discover missing declarations of numerical types, *unchecked-math* was set to :warn-on-boxed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To reduce garbage collector pauses, the ZGC low-latency garbage collector for the JVM was used. The following section in deps.edn ensures that the ZGC garbage collector is used when running the project with clj -M:run:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The option to use ZGC is also specified in the Packr JSON file used to deploy the application.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Building the project&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to build the map tiles, atmospheric lookup tables, and other data files using tools.build, the project source code was made available in the build.clj file using a :local/root dependency:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Various targets were defined to build the different components of the project. For example the atmospheric lookup tables can be build by specifying clj -T:build atmosphere-lut on the command line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following section in the build.clj file was added to allow creating an âUberjarâ JAR file with all dependencies by specifying clj -T:build uber on the command-line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To create a Linux executable with Packr, one can then run java -jar packr-all-4.0.0.jar scripts/packr-config-linux.json where the JSON file has the following content:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to distribute the game on Steam, three depots were created:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;a data depot with the operating system independent data files&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;a Linux depot with the Linux executable and Uberjar including LWJGLâs Linux native bindings&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;and a Windows depot with the Windows executable and an Uberjar including LWJGLâs Windows native bindings&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;When updating a depot, the Steam ContentBuilder command line tool creates and uploads a patch in order to preserve storage space and bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Future work&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the hard parts are mostly done, there are still several things to do:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;control surfaces and thruster graphics&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;launchpad and runway graphics&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;sound effects&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;a 3D cockpit&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;the Moon&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;a space station&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;It would also be interesting to make the game modable in a safe way (maybe evaluating Clojure files in a sandboxed environment?).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find the source code on Github. Currently there is only a playtest build, but if you want to get notified, when the game gets released, you can wishlist it here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let me know any comments and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Related blog posts&lt;/head&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Flight dynamics model for simulating Venturestar style spacecraft&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Test Driven Development with OpenGL&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Implementing GUIs using Clojure and LWJGL Nuklear bindings&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Procedural Volumetric Clouds&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Procedural generation of global cloud cover&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Reversed-Z Rendering in OpenGL&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Specifying Clojure function schemas with Malli&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Implement an Interpreter using Clojure Instaparse&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Orbits with Jolt Physics&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Getting started with the Jolt Physics Engine&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Create Blender bones and animate and import with Assimp&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.wedesoft.de/software/2025/09/05/clojure-game/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45146967</id><title>Rug pulls, forks, and open-source feudalism</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:53.347923+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="8f537952c92707bd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Rug pulls, forks, and open-source feudalism&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;[LWN subscriber-only content]&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;head&gt;Welcome to LWN.net&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The following subscription-only content has been made available to you by an LWN subscriber. Thousands of subscribers depend on LWN for the best news from the Linux and free software communities. If you enjoy this article, please consider subscribing to LWN. Thank you for visiting LWN.net!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like almost all human endeavors, open-source software development involves a range of power dynamics. Companies, developers, and users are all concerned with the power to influence the direction of the software — and, often, to profit from it. At the 2025 Open Source Summit Europe, Dawn Foster talked about how those dynamics can play out, with an eye toward a couple of tactics — rug pulls and forks — that are available to try to shift power in one direction or another.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Power dynamics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of history, Foster began, those in power have tended to use it against those who were weaker. In the days of feudalism, control of the land led to exploitation at several levels. In the open-source world, the large cloud providers often seem to have the most power, which they use against smaller companies. Contributors and maintainers often have less power than even the smaller companies, and users have less power yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have built a world where it is often easiest to just use whatever a cloud provider offers, even with open-source software. Those providers may not contribute back to the projects they turn into services, though, upsetting the smaller companies that are, likely as not, doing the bulk of the work to provide the software in question in the first place. Those companies can have a power of their own, however: the power to relicense the software. Pulling the rug out from under users of the software in this way can change the balance of power with regard to cloud providers, but it leaves contributors and users in a worse position than before. But there is a power at this level too: the power to fork the software, flipping the power balance yet again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Companies that control a software project have the power to carry out this sort of rug pull, and they are often not shy about exercising it. Single-company projects, clearly, are at a much higher risk of rug pulls; the company has all the power in this case, and others have little recourse. So one should look at a company's reputation before adopting a software project, but that is only so helpful. Companies can change direction without notice, be acquired, or go out of business, making previous assessments of their reputation irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem often comes down to the simple fact that companies have to answer to their investors, and that often leads to pressure to relicense the software they have created in order to increase revenue. This is especially true in cases where cloud providers are competing for the same customers as the company that owns the project. The result can be a switch to a more restrictive license aimed at making it harder for other companies to profit from the project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A rug pull of this nature can lead to a fork of the project — a rebellious, collective action aimed at regaining some power over the code. But a fork is not a simple matter; it is a lot of work, and will fail without people and resources behind it. The natural source for that is a large company; cloud providers, too, can try to shift power via a fork, and they have the ability to back their fork up with the resources it needs to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A relicensing event does not always lead to a popular fork; that did not happen with MongoDB or Sentry, for example. Foster said she had not looked into why that was the case. Sometimes rug pulls take other forms, such as when Perforce, after acquiring Puppet in 2022, moved it development and releases behind closed doors, with a reduced frequency of releases back to the public repository. That action kicked off the OpenVox fork.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Looking at the numbers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foster has spent some time analyzing rug pulls, forks, and what happens thereafter; a lot of the results are available for download as Jupyter notebooks. For each rug-pull event, she looked at the contributor makeup of the project before and after the ensuing fork in an attempt to see what effects are felt by the projects involved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2021, Elastic relicensed Elasticsearch under the non-free Server Side Public License (SSPL). Amazon Web Services then forked the project as OpenSearch. Before the fork, most of the Elasticsearch contributors were Elastic employees; that, unsurprisingly, did not change afterward. OpenSearch started with no strong contributor base, so had to build its community from scratch. As a result, the project has been dominated by Amazon contributors ever since; the balance has shifted slowly over time, but there was not a big uptick in outside contributors even after OpenSearch became a Linux Foundation project in 2024. While starting a project under a neutral foundation can help attract contributors, she said, moving a project under a foundation's umbrella later on does not seem to provide the same benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Terraform was developed mostly by Hashicorp, which relicensed the software under the non-free Business Source License in 2023. One month later, the OpenTofu fork was started under the Linux Foundation. While the contributor base for Terraform, which was almost entirely Hashicorp employees, changed little after the fork, OpenTofu quickly acquired a number of contributors from several companies, none of whom had been Terraform contributors before. In this case, users drove the fork and placed it under a neutral foundation, resulting in a more active developer community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2024, Redis was relicensed under the SSPL; the Valkey fork was quickly organized, under the Linux Foundation, by Redis contributors. The Redis project differed from the others mentioned here in that, before the fork, it had nearly twice as many contributors from outside the company as from within; after the fork, the number of external Redis contributors dropped to zero. All of the external contributors fled to Valkey, with the result that Valkey started with a strong community representing a dozen or so companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at how the usage of these projects changes is harder, she said, but there appears to be a correlation between the usage of a project and the number of GitHub forks (cloned repository copies) it has. There is typically a spike in these clones after a relicensing event, suggesting that people are considering creating a hard fork of the project. In all cases, the forks that emerged appeared to have less usage than the original by the "GitHub forks" metric; both branches of the fork continue to go forward. But, she said, projects that are relicensed do tend to show reduced usage, especially when competing forks are created under foundations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;What to do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This kind of power game creates problems for both contributors and users, she said; we contribute our time to these projects, and need them to not be pulled out from under us. There is no way to know when a rug pull might happen, but there are some warning signs to look out for. At the top of her list was the use of a contributor license agreement (CLA); these agreements create a power imbalance, giving the company involved the power to relicense the software. Projects with CLAs more commonly are subject to rug pulls; projects using a developers certificate of origin do not have the same power imbalance and are less likely to be rug pulled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One should also look at the governance of a project; while being housed under a foundation reduces the chance of a rug pull, that can still happen, especially in cases where the contributors are mostly from a single company. She mentioned the Cortex project, housed under the Cloud Native Computing Foundation, which was controlled by Grafana; that company eventually forked its own project to create Mimir. To avoid this kind of surprise, one should look for projects with neutral governance, with leaders from multiple organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Projects should also be evaluated on their contributor base; are there enough contributors to keep things going? Companies can help, of course, by having their employees contribute to the projects they depend on, increasing influence and making those projects more sustainable. She mentioned the CHAOSS project, which generates metrics to help in the judgment of the viability of development projects. CHAOSS has put together a set of "practitioner guides" intended to help contributors and maintainers make improvements within a project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the sustained rise of the big cloud providers, she concluded, the power dynamics around open-source software are looking increasingly feudal. Companies can use relicensing to shift power away from those providers, but they also take power from contributors when the pull the rug in this way. Those contributors, though, are in a better position than the serfs of old, since they have the ability to fork a project they care about, shifting power back in their direction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hazel Weakly asked if there are other protections that contributors and users might develop to address this problem. Foster answered that at least one company changed its mind about a planned relicensing action after seeing the success of the Valkey and OpenTofu forks. The ability to fork has the effect of making companies think harder, knowing that there may be consequences that follow a rug pull. Beyond that, she reiterated that projects should be pushed toward neutral governance. Dirk Hohndel added that the best thing to do is to bring more outside contributors into a project; the more of them there are, the higher the risk associated with a rug pull. Anybody who just sits back within a project, he said, is just a passenger; it is better to be driving.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foster's slides are available for interested readers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; [Thanks to the Linux Foundation, LWN's travel sponsor, for supporting my travel to this event.]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Index entries for this article&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Conference&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Open Source Summit Europe/2025&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Posted Sep 6, 2025 12:24 UTC (Sat) by immibis (subscriber, #105511) [Link] (7 responses) The confusion comes about because the OSI declared it to not be open source. But they are a corrupt institution. Their explanation[1] makes no reference to the license text whatsoever, only vague handwavey excuses that apply equally well to AGPL, and the members/sponsors of the OSI are primarily companies that sell cloud stuff and have a strong interest in preventing more software from using the SSPL. You can also check the license text itself and verify that it doesn't "discriminate against a field of endeavour". I recommend finding the plain text version, and diffing it against the AGPLv3. They differ only in the name of the license, and one short section. [1] https://opensource.org/blog/the-sspl-is-not-an-open-sourc... Posted Sep 6, 2025 13:15 UTC (Sat) by claudex (subscriber, #92510) [Link] (2 responses) Yeah, that's the section that is considered the issue to be able to use the software to provide the service. As it requires to publish all code that interact with the software, like monitoring, backup and storage code. That's a big difference with AGPL. &amp;gt; "Service Source Code" means the Corresponding Source for the Program or the modified version, and the Corresponding Source for all programs that you use to make the Program or modified version available as a service, including, without limitation, management software, user interfaces, application program interfaces, automation software, monitoring software, backup software, storage software and hosting software, all such that a user could run an instance of the service using the Service Source Code you make available. Posted Sep 6, 2025 14:15 UTC (Sat) by smurf (subscriber, #17840) [Link] (1 responses) "Service Source Code" means the Corresponding Source for the Program or the modified version, and the Corresponding Source for all programs that you use to make the Program or modified version available as a service, including, without limitation, management software, user interfaces, application program interfaces, automation software, monitoring software, backup software, storage software and hosting software, all such that a user could run an instance of the service using the Service Source Code you make available. Oops, you now cannot use a commercial backup system for which you don't have the source code in conjunction with the SSPL-licensed service you're offering. Also does "storage software" incorporate the firmware of your disk drive or not? far from clear just by reading this license, that "without limitation" clause does raise a red flag or three, doesn't it? Sorry to be blunt, but that kind of overbearing restrictive language is the antithesis of OSS. My conclusion is that anybody who proclaims the SSPL to be "free" either didn't read it or has an agenda. Or both. Posted Sep 6, 2025 15:09 UTC (Sat) by immibis (subscriber, #105511) [Link] Posted Sep 6, 2025 13:39 UTC (Sat) by DemiMarie (subscriber, #164188) [Link] Posted Sep 6, 2025 14:15 UTC (Sat) by jjs (guest, #10315) [Link] (2 responses) "9. License Must Not Restrict Other Software The license must not place restrictions on other software that is distributed along with the licensed software. For example, the license must not insist that all other programs distributed on the same medium must be open source software." By the terms of the SSPL, all other software that interacts with the SSPL'd software must be Open Source (https://webassets.mongodb.com/_com_assets/legal/SSPL-comp... - see Section 13). Violation of OSD #9 (which is derived from the Debian Social Contract Guidelines - https://www.debian.org/social_contract#guidelines). "But they are a corrupt institution." That's a serious allegation - feel free to provide verifiable evidence of that (and no, the fact that they have corporate sponsors doesn't make them corrupt. If it did, every non-profit in the world would be considered corrupt). Posted Sep 6, 2025 15:09 UTC (Sat) by immibis (subscriber, #105511) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Sep 6, 2025 15:52 UTC (Sat) by pbonzini (subscriber, #60935) [Link] The discrimination against fields of endeavor is also at least plausible. The AGPL instead only extends the circumstances under which you shall provide the sources. &lt;head&gt;SSPL is a free license&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;SSPL is a free license&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;SSPL is a free license&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;SSPL is a free license&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;SSPL is not a free license&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;SSPL is not a free license - Per Open Source Definition&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;SSPL is not a free license - Per Open Source Definition&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;SSPL is not a free license - Per Open Source Definition&lt;/head&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/1036465/e80ebbc4cee39bfb/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45148167</id><title>Let us git rid of it, angry GitHub users say of forced Copilot features</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:53.088621+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="36843119b7be6ce3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Let us git rid of it, angry GitHub users say of forced Copilot features&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Unavoidable AI has developers looking for alternative code hosting options&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the software developers who use Microsoft's GitHub, the most popular community discussion in the past 12 months has been a request for a way to block Copilot, the company's AI service, from generating issues and pull requests in code repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second most popular discussion – where popularity is measured in upvotes – is a bug report that seeks a fix for the inability of users to disable Copilot code reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both of these questions, the first opened in May and the second opened a month ago, remain unanswered, despite an abundance of comments critical of generative AI and Copilot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The author of the first, developer Andi McClure, published a similar request to Microsoft's Visual Studio Code repository in January, objecting to the reappearance of a Copilot icon in VS Code after she had uninstalled the Copilot extension.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft and GitHub, not to mention rivals like Google, have gone all-in on a technology that a sizable or at least vocal portion of their customers simply don't want. And with billions in capital expenditures to recoup, they're making it difficult to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During Microsoft's July 30, 2025 earnings call, CEO Satya Nadella said GitHub Copilot continued to exhibit strong momentum and had reached 20 million users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"GitHub Copilot Enterprise customers increased 75 percent quarter over quarter as companies tailor Copilot to their own codebases," said Nadella, noting that AI adoption has increased usage of GitHub over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I deeply resent that on top of Copilot seemingly training itself on my GitHub-posted code in violation of my licenses, GitHub wants me to look at (effectively) ads for this project I will never touch&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I've been for a while now filing issues in the GitHub Community feedback area when Copilot intrudes on my GitHub usage," McClure told The Register in an email. "I deeply resent that on top of Copilot seemingly training itself on my GitHub-posted code in violation of my licenses, GitHub wants me to look at (effectively) ads for this project I will never touch. If something's bothering me, I don't see a reason to stay quiet about it. I think part of how we get pushed into things we collectively don't want is because we stay quiet about it."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's not just the burden of responding to AI slop, an ongoing issue for Curl maintainer Daniel Stenberg. It's the permissionless copying and regurgitation of speculation as fact, mitigated only by small print disclaimers that generative AI may produce inaccurate results. It's also GitHub's disavowal of liability if Copilot code suggestions happen to have reproduced source code that requires attribution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's what the Servo project characterizes in its ban on AI code contributions as the lack of code correctness guarantees, copyright issues, and ethical concerns. Similar objections have been used to justify AI code bans in GNOME's Loupe project, FreeBSD, Gentoo, NetBSD, and QEMU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;McClure said she has been filing requests to opt out of Copilot for a few years now, but in the last six months, her posts have been attracting more community support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two issues, about the abovementioned Copilot menu in VS Code and the inability to block Copilot-generated issues and pull requests, she said, have continued to attract comments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"People keep finding these issues somehow and tacking on to them," McClure said. "Although Microsoft's been forcing the Copilot 'asks' into more and more places in the interface for a while, sometime this year they hit an inflection point where mass numbers of people don't feel like ignoring it anymore, where before they could shrug and ignore it or find the off switch."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the past month, she said, there's been a second change in the way people see GitHub – GitHub's demotion from distinct subsidiary to part of Microsoft's CoreAI group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bot shots: US Army enlists AI startup to provide target-tracking&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OpenAI eats jobs, then offers to help you find a new one at Walmart&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Boffins build automated Android bug hunting system&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Atlassian acquisition drives dream of AI-powered ChromeOS challenger&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Despite being a symbolic change, it seems to have galvanized the open source community from just complaining about Copilot to now actively moving away from GitHub," said McClure. "Many of my contacts in the open source community have been talking about plans to move from GitHub to Codeberg or a self-hosted Forgejo (Forgejo is the software used by Codeberg) over the last month, and the comments in those two always-busy GitHub threads have increasingly been people describing how Copilot is inspiring them to move to Codeberg as well."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Calls to shun Microsoft and GitHub go back a long way in the open source community, but moved beyond simmering dissatisfaction in 2022 when the Software Freedom Conservancy (SFC) urged free software supporters to give up GitHub, a position SFC policy fellow Bradley M. Kuhn recently reiterated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the developers participating in the issues raised by McClure and by others have said they intend to move away from GitHub over its stance on AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Today I rejected two Copilot-generated code suggestions on my PR," wrote a developer who posted to McClure's thread under the name Constantine. "This was very disturbing, so I started googling and found this discussion. I refuse using AI in the same way I don't take drugs or steal things - for me it's a matter of principle. So if this continues and Microsoft does not provide a way to opt out of AI for my repositories soon, I will move my code to a self-hosted solution and won't ever return to GitHub."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;McClure said she has been slowly shifting toward Codeberg over the past few months. "I haven't been proactively moving repos but whenever I make a change to a repo I clone it to Codeberg, post the change there, and replace my main branch on the GitHub repo with a relocation notice," she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Microsoft as a company has a running problem where they won't take no for an answer, whether with 'AI' or with any other product they want to ship," said McClure. "A favorite tactic of theirs recently is they will enable a thing by default and put an off switch, wait six months, and then slightly change or rename the feature you turned off, and create a new off switch you have to separately turn off. They did this with Bing in Windows 10 and now they're doing it with Copilot in their developer tools (and presumably Windows 11, I don't know, I don't use Windows 11)."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;McClure said that when Microsoft began adding Copilot to everything, starting with Android keyboard SwiftKey, she concluded that the situation would reprise the handling of Bing/Cortana in Windows 10 and turning it off would not be enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you really find Copilot unacceptable – and I do, Copilot is so much more noxious than Microsoft's previous forced bundlings – the only option is to stop using any Microsoft product that Copilot shows up in&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"If you really find Copilot unacceptable – and I do, Copilot is so much more noxious than Microsoft's previous forced bundlings – the only option is to stop using any Microsoft product that Copilot shows up in," she said. "I stopped using SwiftKey; I started migrating from desktop Windows to Linux when it became clear mandatory AI surveillance would be a core part of Win11. GitHub and, more sporadically, Visual Studio Code I have had to keep using because they're monopolies in a way even Windows isn't. The network effects (projects whose sole method of communication is GitHub, software whose only IDE integration is a VSCode plugin) are too strong."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Things have progressed as expected, McClure said, with Copilot buttons appearing in VS Code even when Copilot has been uninstalled and poorly labeled buttons that redirect to Copilot searches. She suggests people are starting to tire of the situation and that if it continues, it will weaken the network effects that keep developers tied to GitHub, accelerating further migration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"When this happens I have no idea if Microsoft will notice or care," said McClure. "The Copilot push at Microsoft appears to be completely top-down and the people at the top seem to have completely forgotten about conventional goals like customer retention. They want to pump up those 'AI' numbers, for whatever reason, and they view their customer base as just a resource to burn to get those metrics up."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GitHub did not respond to a request for comment. ®&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/05/github_copilot_complaints/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45148180</id><title>A Software Development Methodology for Disciplined LLM Collaboration</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:52.695641+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b9b354209f24abe"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disciplined AI Software Development Methodology © 2025 by Jay Baleine is licensed under CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A structured approach for working with AI on development projects. This methodology addresses common issues like code bloat, architectural drift, and context dilution through systematic constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI systems work on Question → Answer patterns. When you ask for broad, multi-faceted implementations, you typically get:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Functions that work but lack structure&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Repeated code across components&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Architectural inconsistency over sessions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Context dilution causing output drift&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;More debugging time than planning time&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The methodology uses four stages with systematic constraints and validation checkpoints. Each stage builds on empirical data rather than assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Planning saves debugging time. Planning thoroughly upfront typically prevents days of fixing architectural issues later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set up your AI model's custom instructions using AI-PREFERENCES.md. This establishes behavioral constraints and uncertainty flagging with &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Share METHODOLOGY.md with the AI to structure your project plan. Work together to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Define scope and completion criteria&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Identify components and dependencies&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Structure phases based on logical progression&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Generate systematic tasks with measurable checkpoints&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Output: A development plan following dependency chains with modular boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work phase by phase, section by section. Each request follows: "Can you implement [specific component]?" with focused objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;File size stays ≤150 lines. This constraint provides:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Smaller context windows for processing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Focused implementation over multi-function attempts&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Easier sharing and debugging&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Implementation flow:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Request specific component → AI processes → Validate → Benchmark → Continue
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The benchmarking suite (built first) provides performance data throughout development. Feed this data back to the AI for optimization decisions based on measurements rather than guesswork.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decision Processing: AI handles "Can you do A?" more reliably than "Can you do A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Context Management: Small files and bounded problems prevent the AI from juggling multiple concerns simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Empirical Validation: Performance data replaces subjective assessment. Decisions come from measurable outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Systematic Constraints: Architectural checkpoints, file size limits, and dependency gates force consistent behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Discord Bot Template - Production-ready bot foundation with plugin architecture, security, API management, and comprehensive testing. 46 files, all under 150 lines, with benchmarking suite and automated compliance checking. (View Project Structure)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;PhiCode Runtime - Programming language runtime engine with transpilation, caching, security validation, and Rust acceleration. Complex system maintaining architectural discipline across 70+ modules. (View Project Structure)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;PhiPipe - CI/CD regression detection system with statistical analysis, GitHub integration, and concurrent processing. Go-based service handling performance baselines and automated regression alerts. (View Project Structure)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can compare the methodology principles to the codebase structure to see how the approach translates to working code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Configure AI with AI-PREFERENCES.md as custom instructions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Share METHODOLOGY.md for planning session&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Collaborate on project structure and phases&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Generate systematic development plan&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Build Phase 0 benchmarking infrastructure first&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Work through phases sequentially&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Implement one component per interaction&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Run benchmarks and share results with AI&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Validate architectural compliance continuously&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Performance regression detection&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Architectural principle validation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Code duplication auditing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File size compliance checking&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dependency boundary verification&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use the included project extraction tool systematically to generate structured snapshots of your codebase:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;python scripts/project_extract.py&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Configuration Options:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;SEPARATE_FILES = False&lt;/code&gt;: Single THE_PROJECT.md file (recommended for small codebases)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;SEPARATE_FILES = True&lt;/code&gt;: Multiple files per directory (recommended for large codebases and focused folder work)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;INCLUDE_PATHS&lt;/code&gt;: Directories and files to analyze&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;EXCLUDE_PATTERNS&lt;/code&gt;: Skip cache directories, build artifacts, and generated files&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Output:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Complete file contents with syntax highlighting&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File line counts with architectural warnings (&lt;g-emoji&gt;⚠️&lt;/g-emoji&gt;for 140-150 lines,&lt;g-emoji&gt;‼️&lt;/g-emoji&gt;for &amp;gt;150 lines on code files)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tree structure visualization&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ready-to-share&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;output examples can be found here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use the tool to share a complete or partial project state with the AI system, track architectural compliance, and create focused development context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI Behavior: The methodology reduces architectural drift and context degradation compared to unstructured approaches. AI still needs occasional reminders about principles - this is normal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Development Flow: Systematic planning tends to reduce debugging cycles. Focused implementation helps minimize feature bloat. Performance data supports optimization decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Code Quality: Architectural consistency across components, measurable performance characteristics, maintainable structure as projects scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;What problem led you to create this methodology?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I kept having to restate my preferences and architectural requirements to AI systems. It didn't matter which language or project I was working on - the AI would consistently produce either bloated monolithic code or underdeveloped implementations with issues throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This led me to examine the meta-principles driving code quality and software architecture. I questioned whether pattern matching in AI models might be more effective when focused on underlying software principles rather than surface-level syntax. Since pattern matching is logic-driven and machines fundamentally operate on simple question-answer pairs, I realized that functions with multiple simultaneous questions were overwhelming the system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The breakthrough came from understanding that everything ultimately transpiles to binary - a series of "can you do this? → yes/no" decisions. This insight shaped my approach: instead of issuing commands, ask focused questions in proper context. Rather than mentally managing complex setups alone, collaborate with AI to devise systematic plans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;How did you discover these specific constraints work?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through extensive trial and error. AI systems will always tend to drift even under constraints, but they're significantly more accurate with structured boundaries than without them. You occasionally need to remind the AI of its role to prevent deviation - like managing a well-intentioned toddler that knows the rules but sometimes pushes boundaries trying to satisfy you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These tools are far from perfect, but they're effective instruments for software development when properly constrained.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;What failures or frustrations shaped this approach?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maintenance hell was the primary driver. I grew tired of responses filled with excessive praise: "You have found the solution!", "You have redefined the laws of physics with your paradigm-shifting script!" This verbose fluff wastes time, tokens, and patience without contributing to productive development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of venting frustration on social media about AI being "just a dumb tool," I decided to find methods that actually work. My approach may not help everyone, but I hope it benefits those who share similar AI development frustrations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;How consistently do you follow your own methodology?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since creating the documentation, I haven't deviated. Whenever I see the model producing more lines than my methodology restricts, I immediately interrupt generation with a flag: "&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;What happens when you deviate from it?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I become genuinely uncomfortable. Once I see things starting to degrade or become tangled, I compulsively need to organize and optimize. Deviation simply isn't an option anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Which principles do you find hardest to maintain?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not cursing at the AI when it drifts during complex algorithms! But seriously, it's a machine - it's not perfect, and neither are we.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;When did you start using AI for programming?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In August 2024, I created a RuneLite theme pack, but one of the plugin overlays didn't match my custom layout. I opened a GitHub issue (creating my first GitHub account to do so) requesting a customization option. The response was: "It's not a priority - if you want it, build it yourself."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I used ChatGPT to guide me through forking RuneLite and creating a plugin. This experience sparked intense interest in underlying software principles rather than just syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;How has your approach evolved over time?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I view development like a book: syntax is the cover, logic is the content itself. Rather than learning syntax structures, I focused on core meta-principles - how software interacts, how logic flows, different algorithm types. I quickly realized everything reduces to the same foundation: question and answer sequences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Large code structures are essentially chaotic meetings - one coordinator fielding questions and answers from multiple sources, trying to provide correct responses without mix-ups or misinterpretation. If this applies to human communication, it must apply to software principles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;What were your biggest mistakes with AI collaboration?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expecting it to intuitively understand my requirements, provide perfect fixes, be completely honest, and act like a true expert. This was all elaborate roleplay that produced poor code. While fine for single-purpose scripts, it failed completely for scalable codebases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I learned not to feed requirements and hope for the best. Instead, I needed to collaborate actively - create plans, ask for feedback on content clarity, and identify uncertainties. This gradual process taught me the AI's actual capabilities and most effective collaboration methods.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Why 150 lines exactly?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiple benefits: easy readability, clear understanding, modularity enforcement, architectural clarity, simple maintenance, component testing, optimal AI context retention, reusability, and KISS principle adherence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;How did you determine Phase 0 requirements?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From meta-principles of software: if it displays, it must run; if it runs, it can be measured; if it can be measured, it can be optimized; if it can be optimized, it can be reliable; if it can be reliable, it can be trusted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless of project type, anything requiring architecture needs these foundations. You must ensure changes don't negatively impact the entire system. A single line modification in a nested function might work perfectly but cause 300ms boot time regression for all users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By testing during development, you catch inefficiencies early. Integration from the start means simply hooking up new components and running tests via command line - minimal time investment with actual value returned. I prefer validation and consistency throughout development rather than programming blind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;How do you handle projects that don't fit the methodology?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I adapt them to fit, or if truly impossible, I adjust the method itself. This is one methodology - I can generate countless variations as needed. Having spent 6700+ hours in AI interactions across multiple domains (not just software), I've developed strong system comprehension that enables creating adjusted methodologies on demand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;What's the learning curve for new users?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I cannot accurately answer this question. I've learned that I'm neurologically different - what I perceive as easy or obvious isn't always the case for others. This question is better addressed by someone who has actually used this methodology to determine its learning curve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;When shouldn't someone use this approach?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're not serious about projects, despise AI, dislike planning, don't care about modularization, or are just writing simple scripts. However, for anything requiring reliability, I believe this is currently the most effective method.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You still need programming fundamentals to use this methodology effectively - it's significantly more structured than ad-hoc approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;---
config:
  layout: elk
  theme: neo-dark
---
flowchart TD
    A["Project Idea"] --&amp;gt; B["🤖 Stage 1: AI Configuration&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;AI-PREFERENCES.md Custom Instructions"]
    B --&amp;gt; C["Stage 2: Collaborative Planning&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Share METHODOLOGY.md"]
    C --&amp;gt; D["Define Scope &amp;amp; Completion Criteria"]
    D --&amp;gt; E["Identify Components &amp;amp; Dependencies"]
    E --&amp;gt; F["Structure Phases Based on Logic"]
    F --&amp;gt; G["Document Edge Cases - No Implementation"]
    G --&amp;gt; H["Generate Development Plan with Checkpoints"]
    H --&amp;gt; I["🔧 Stage 3: Phase 0 Infrastructure&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;MANDATORY BEFORE ANY CODE"]
    I --&amp;gt; J["Benchmarking Suite + Regression Detection"]
    J --&amp;gt; K["GitHub Workflows + Quality Gates"]
    K --&amp;gt; L["Test Suite Infrastructure + Stress Tests"]
    L --&amp;gt; M["Documentation Generation System"]
    M --&amp;gt; N["Centralized Configuration + Constants"]
    N --&amp;gt; O["📁 project_extract.py Setup&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Single/Multiple File Config"]
    O --&amp;gt; P["Initial Project State Extraction"]
    P --&amp;gt; Q["Share Context with AI"]
    Q --&amp;gt; R["Start Development Session&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Pre-Session Compliance Audit"]
    R --&amp;gt; S{"Next Phase Available?"}
    S -- No --&amp;gt; Z["Project Complete"]
    S -- Yes --&amp;gt; T["Select Single Component&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Target ≤150 Lines"]
    T --&amp;gt; U{"Multi-Language Required?"}
    U -- Yes --&amp;gt; V["Document Performance Justification&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Measurable Benefits Required"]
    V --&amp;gt; W["Request AI Implementation"]
    U -- No --&amp;gt; W
    W --&amp;gt; X{"AI Uncertainty Flag?"}
    X -- ⚠️ Yes --&amp;gt; Y["Request Clarification&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Provide Additional Context"]
    Y --&amp;gt; W
    X -- Clear --&amp;gt; AA["Stage 3: Systematic Implementation"]
    AA --&amp;gt; BB{"Automated Size Check&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;validate-phase Script"}
    BB -- &amp;gt;150 Lines --&amp;gt; CC["AUTOMATED: Split Required&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Maintain SoC Boundaries"]
    CC --&amp;gt; W
    BB -- ≤150 Lines --&amp;gt; DD["Incremental Compliance Check&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;DRY/KISS/SoC Validation"]
    DD --&amp;gt; EE{"Architectural Principles Pass?"}
    EE -- No --&amp;gt; FF["Flag Specific Violations&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Reference Methodology"]
    FF --&amp;gt; W
    EE -- Yes --&amp;gt; GG["📊 Stage 4: Data-Driven Iteration&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Run Benchmark Suite + Save Baselines"]
    GG --&amp;gt; HH["Compare Against Historical Timeline&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Regression Analysis"]
    HH --&amp;gt; II{"Performance Gate Pass?"}
    II -- Regression Detected --&amp;gt; JJ["Share Performance Data&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Request Optimization"]
    JJ --&amp;gt; W
    II -- Pass --&amp;gt; KK["Integration Test&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Verify System Boundaries"]
    KK --&amp;gt; LL{"Cross-Platform Validation?"}
    LL -- Fail --&amp;gt; MM["Address Deployment Constraints&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Real-World Considerations"]
    MM --&amp;gt; W
    LL -- Pass --&amp;gt; NN{"More Components in Phase?"}
    NN -- Yes --&amp;gt; T
    NN -- No --&amp;gt; OO["🚦 Phase Quality Gate&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Full Architecture Audit"]
    OO --&amp;gt; PP["Production Simulation&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Resource Cleanup + Load Test"]
    PP --&amp;gt; QQ{"All Quality Gates Pass?"}
    QQ -- No --&amp;gt; RR["Document Failed Checkpoints&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Block Phase Progression"]
    RR --&amp;gt; T
    QQ -- Yes --&amp;gt; SS["End Development Session&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Technical Debt Assessment"]
    SS --&amp;gt; TT["📁 Extract Updated Project State&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Generate Fresh Context"]
    TT --&amp;gt; UU["Phase Results Documentation&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Metrics + Outcomes + Timeline"]
    UU --&amp;gt; VV["Update Development Plan&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;Mark Phase Complete"]
    VV --&amp;gt; S
    WW["validate-phase&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;AUTOMATED: File Size + Structure"] -.-&amp;gt; BB
    XX["dry-audit&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;AUTOMATED: Cross-Module Duplication"] -.-&amp;gt; DD
    YY["CI/CD Workflows&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;AUTOMATED: Merge Gates"] -.-&amp;gt; GG
    ZZ["Performance Timeline&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;AUTOMATED: Historical Data"] -.-&amp;gt; HH
    AAA["Dependency Validator&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;AUTOMATED: Import Boundaries"] -.-&amp;gt; KK
    BBB["Architecture Auditor&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;AUTOMATED: SoC Compliance"] -.-&amp;gt; OO
    WW -. BUILD FAILURE .-&amp;gt; CC
    YY -. MERGE BLOCKED .-&amp;gt; JJ
    BBB -. AUDIT FAILURE .-&amp;gt; RR
    style Y fill:#7d5f00
    style CC fill:#770000
    style FF fill:#7d5f00
    style JJ fill:#7d5f00
    style MM fill:#770000
    style RR fill:#770000
&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/Varietyz/Disciplined-AI-Software-Development"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45148237</id><title>Qwen3 30B A3B Hits 13 token/s on 4xRaspberry Pi 5</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:52.280921+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="e5f2f2ebfa4d7c22"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;qwen3_30b.mov&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Setup&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Device: &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Benchmark&lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beta Was this translation helpful? Give feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Replies: 0 comments&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Sign up for free to join this conversation on GitHub. Already have an account? Sign in to comment &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;qwen3_30b.mov&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Setup&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Device: &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Benchmark&lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beta Was this translation helpful? Give feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/b4rtaz/distributed-llama/discussions/255"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45148944</id><title>We Hacked Burger King: How Auth Bypass Led to Drive-Thru Audio Surveillance</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:51.943881+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://bobdahacker.com/blog/rbi-hacked-drive-thrus/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45149049</id><title>996</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:51.701496+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2744b1079b2c7957"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;written on September 04, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Amazing salary, hackerhouse in SF, crazy equity. 996. Our mission is OSS.” — Gregor Zunic&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The current vibe is no drinking, no drugs, 9-9-6, […].” — Daksh Gupta&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The truth is, China’s really doing ‘007’ now—midnight to midnight, seven days a week […] if you want to build a $10 billion company, you have to work seven days a week.” — Harry Stebbings&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love work. I love working late nights, hacking on things. This week I didn’t go to sleep before midnight once. And yet…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also love my wife and kids. I love long walks, contemplating life over good coffee, and deep, meaningful conversations. None of this would be possible if my life was defined by 12 hour days, six days a week. More importantly, a successful company is not a sprint, it’s a marathon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And this is when this is your own company! When you devote 72 hours a week to someone else’s startup, you need to really think about that arrangement a few times. I find it highly irresponsible for a founder to promote that model. As a founder, you are not an employee, and your risks and leverage are fundamentally different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will always advocate for putting the time in because it is what brought me happiness. Intensity, and giving a shit about what I’m doing, will always matter to me. But you don’t measure that by the energy you put in, or the hours you’re sitting in the office, but the output you produce. Burning out on twelve-hour days, six days a week, has no prize at the end. It’s unsustainable, it shouldn’t be the standard and it sure as hell should not be seen as a positive sign of a company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve pulled many all-nighters, and I’ve enjoyed them. I still do. But they’re enjoyable in the right context, for the right reasons, and when that is a completely personal choice, not the basis of company culture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that all-nighter? It comes with a fucked up and unproductive morning the day after.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When someone promotes a 996 work culture, we should push back.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lucumr.pocoo.org/2025/9/4/996/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45149281</id><title>DuckDuckGo founder: AI surveillance should be banned</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:51.504177+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b608b3dea7679795"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;AI surveillance should be banned while there is still time.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the same privacy harms with online tracking are also present with AI, but worse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While chatbot conversations resemble longer search queries, chatbot privacy harms have the potential to be significantly worse because the inference potential is dramatically greater. Longer input invites more personal information to be provided, and people are starting to bare their souls to chatbots. The conversational format can make it feel like you’re talking to a friend, a professional, or even a therapist. While search queries reveal interests and personal problems, AI conversations take their specificity to another level and, in addition, reveal thought processes and communication styles, creating a much more comprehensive profile of your personality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This richer personal information can be more thoroughly exploited for manipulation, both commercially and ideologically, for example, through behavioral chatbot advertising and models designed (or themselves manipulated through SEO or hidden system prompts) to nudge you towards a political position or product. Chatbots have already been found to be more persuasive than humans and have caused people to go into delusional spirals as a result. I suspect we’re just scratching the surface, since they can become significantly more attuned to your particular persuasive triggers through chatbot memory features, where they train and fine-tune based on your past conversations, making the influence much more subtle. Instead of an annoying and obvious ad following you around everywhere, you can have a seemingly convincing argument, tailored to your personal style, with an improperly sourced “fact” that you’re unlikely to fact-check or a subtle product recommendation you’re likely to heed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is, all the privacy debates surrounding Google search results from the past two decades apply one-for-one to AI chats, but to an even greater degree. That’s why we (at DuckDuckGo) started offering Duck.ai for protected chatbot conversations and optional, anonymous AI-assisted answers in our private search engine. In doing so, we’re demonstrating that privacy-respecting AI services are feasible. But unfortunately, such protected chats are not yet standard practice, and privacy mishaps are mounting quickly. Grok leaked hundreds of thousands of chatbot conversations that users thought were private. Perplexity’s AI agent was shown to be vulnerable to hackers who could slurp up your personal information. Open AI is openly talking about their vision for a “super assistant” that tracks everything you do and say (including offline). And Anthropic is going to start training on your chatbot conversations by default (previously the default was off). I collected these from just the past few weeks!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It would therefore be ideal if Congress could act quickly to ensure that protected chats become the rule rather than the exception. And yet, I’m not holding my breath because it’s 2025 and the U.S. still doesn’t have a general online privacy law, let alone privacy enshrined in the Constitution as a fundamental right, as it should be. However, there does appear to be an opening right now for AI-specific federal legislation, despite the misguided attempts to ban state AI legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time is running out because every day that passes further entrenches bad privacy practices. Congress must move before history completely repeats itself and everything that happened with online tracking happens again with AI tracking. AI surveillance should be banned while there is still time. No matter what happens, though, we will still be here, offering protected services, including optional AI services, to consumers who want to reap the productivity benefits of online tools without the privacy harms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://gabrielweinberg.com/p/ai-surveillance-should-be-banned"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45149626</id><title>Oldest Recorded Transaction</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:51.314321+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a9cfeaf676b2dbc5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Oldest recorded transaction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other day I posted a tweet with this image which I thought was funny:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the oldest transaction database from 3100 BC - recording accounts of malt and barley groats. Considering this thing survived 5000 years (holy shit!) with zero downtime and has stronger durability guarantees than most databases today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I call it rock solid durability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This got me thinking, can I insert this date in today’s database? What is the oldest timestamp a database can support?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I checked the top three databases: MySQL, Postgres, and SQLite:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;MySQL&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1000 AD&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Postgres&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4713 BC&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SQLite&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4713 BC&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Too bad you cannot use MySQL for this. Postgres and SQLite support the Julian calendar and the lowest date is Jan 01, 4713 BC:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sales=# INSERT INTO orders VALUES ('4713-01-01 BC'::date);
INSERT 0 1
sales=# SELECT * FROM orders;
   timestamp
---------------
 4713-01-01 BC
(1 row)
sales=# INSERT INTO orders VALUES ('4714-01-01 BC'::date);
ERROR:  date out of range: "4714-01-01 BC"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wonder how people store dates older than this. Maybe if I’m a British Museum manager, and I want to keep &lt;del&gt;theft&lt;/del&gt; inventory details. How do I do it? As an epoch? Store it as text? Use some custom system? How do I get it to support all the custom operations that a typical &lt;code&gt;TIMESTAMP&lt;/code&gt; supports?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to aku, happy_shady, Mr. Bhat, and General Bruh for reading an early draft of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. Source of the image: Sumer civilization&lt;lb/&gt;2. I found this from the talk 1000x: The Power of an Interface for Performance by Joran Dirk Greef, CEO of TigerBeetle, timestamped @ 38:10.&lt;lb/&gt;3. The talk has other bangers too, like this or this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://avi.im/blag/2025/oldest-txn/"/></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45150759</id><title>Zuckerberg Caught in Revealing Hot Mic Moment During White House Dinner</title><updated>2025-09-06T17:06:51.058472+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2f58c64dd5b20fef"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's not unusual for tech company CEOs to make the journey to Washington, DC, and announce billion-dollar investments to curry favor with politicians in power. Apple CEO Tim Cook was in the Oval Office last month, a piece of Apple-shaped glass and a 24-karat gold base in hand, to pledge another $100 billion in US investment over the next four years, for a total of $600 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta CEO Mark Zuckerberg perhaps had that number on his mind this week when he joined his fellow Silicon Valley heavy hitters at the White House for a dinner with President Trump. Zuckerberg was seated next to the president, who at one point leaned over and asked him, "How much are you spending, would you say, over the next few years?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A flustered Zuckerberg responded, "Oh gosh, um, I mean, I think it's probably going to be something like, at least $600 billion through '28 in the US, yeah."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"That's a lot, that's a lot," Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is indeed. Once the discussion concluded, Zuckerberg leaned over to Trump to privately admit the president had caught him off guard. "I'm sorry I wasn't ready...I wasn't sure what number you wanted to go with," Zuckerberg said in a revealing moment caught on a hot mic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;This Tweet is currently unavailable. It might be loading or has been removed.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta would have to dramatically ramp up its AI spending to hit $600 billion in the next three years. During a July earnings call, Meta estimated its full-year 2025 total expenses to be between $114 billion and $118 billion. At the time, CFO Susan Li said Meta had not "kicked off our budgeting process for 2026." But the biggest cost drivers for next year will be infrastructure costs and employee compensation, she said. Li estimated a growth rate of 20% to 24% year-over-year, so $600 billion by 2028 would be quite ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Your Daily Dose of Our Top Tech News&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By clicking Sign Me Up, you confirm you are 16+ and agree to our Terms of Use and Privacy Policy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for signing up!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your subscription has been confirmed. Keep an eye on your inbox!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trump also quizzed the other CEOs on their AI investment plans. Google CEO Sundar Pichai said the company was already "well north of $100 billion" and would grow to $250 billion in the next two years. Microsoft CEO Satya Nadella said the company is close to $80 billion per year in the US, a number that's been consistent since at least January 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenAI Sam Altman was also there, but his online sparring partner, Elon Musk, did not get an invite, The Hill reports. Amazon CEO Andy Jassy was also not in attendance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Investment from all these companies will "build out data centers and infrastructure to power the next wave of innovation," Zuckerberg said at the White House dinner. However, getting power to those data centers remains a challenge, given the enormous amount of energy they consume.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trump says he's cutting red tape on electrical permits to make sure tech companies get what they need, while communities across the US are protesting the rapid growth of data centers near their homes, The Washington Post reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We’re making it very easy for you in terms of electric capacity and getting it for you, getting your permits," Trump said at the dinner, Bloomberg reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Electricity costs are skyrocketing along with data center growth. Monthly bills for the average household are set to increase 20% in 13 states in the Northeast, including Virginia, which has the highest concentration of data centers in the nation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Read the latest from Emily Forlini&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Honda Prelude Is Back After 24 Years, This Time As a Google-Backed Hybrid With Simulated Gear Shifts&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You Can Now Download the Tesla Robotaxi App, But It Only Does One Thing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apple's iPhone 17 Launch Event Set for Sept. 9: What to Expect and How to Watch&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Best AI Chatbots for 2025&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anthropic to Collect Your Chats, Coding Sessions to Train Claude AI&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;More from Emily Forlini&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.pcmag.com/news/zuckerberg-caught-in-revealing-hot-mic-moment-during-white-house-dinner"/></entry></feed>