<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:15.301712+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46426534</id><title>ManusAI Joins Meta</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:25.092702+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="107810b26991a538"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Manus Joins Meta for Next Era of Innovation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The news is out, and it's big: Manus is joining Meta.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This announcement is more than just a headline—it's validation of our pioneering work with General AI Agents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the launch, Manus has focused on building a general-purpose AI agent designed to help users tackle research, automation, and complex tasks. Through continuous product iteration, we’ve been working hard to make these capabilities more reliable and useful across a growing range of real-world use cases. In just a few months, our agent has processed more than 147 Trillion tokens and powered the creation of over 80 Million virtual computers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe in the potential of autonomous agents, and this development reinforces Manus’s role as an execution layer — turning advanced AI capabilities into scalable, reliable systems that can carry out end-to-end work in real-world settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our top priority is ensuring that this change won’t be disruptive for our customers. We will continue to sell and operate our product subscription service through our app and website. The company will continue to operate from Singapore.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our solution is driving value for millions of users worldwide today. With time, we hope to expand this subscription to the millions of businesses and billions of people on Meta’s platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Joining Meta allows us to build on a stronger, more sustainable foundation without changing how Manus works or how decisions are made,” said Xiao Hong, CEO of Manus. “We’re excited about what the future holds with Meta and Manus working together and we will continue to iterate the product and serve users that have defined Manus from the beginning.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://manus.im/blog/manus-joins-meta-for-next-era-of-innovation"/><published>2025-12-29T22:24:22+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46426624</id><title>Show HN: Stop Claude Code from forgetting everything</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:24.443797+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="aa6857fc6a9dbe21"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get smarter alongside your AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your intelligence shouldn't reset every conversation. Ensue is a persistent knowledge tree that grows with you - what you learn today enriches tomorrow's reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every conversation with an LLM starts from zero. You explain context, re-establish preferences, repeat decisions you've already made. Your knowledge doesn't compound.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ensue changes that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Your knowledge persists - Build a tree of intelligence that spans conversations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Context carries forward - Prior research, decisions, and insights inform new work&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You get smarter together - The LLM learns your thinking patterns, not just facts&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think of it as extended memory. When you ask about GPU inference, the LLM checks what you already know. When you make an architecture decision, it connects to past decisions in similar domains. Your accumulated knowledge becomes part of every conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;/plugin marketplace add https://github.com/mutable-state-inc/ensue-skill
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;/plugin install ensue-memory
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Restart Claude Code. The skill will guide you through setup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Variable&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;ENSUE_API_KEY&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Required. Get one at dashboard&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;ENSUE_READONLY&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Set to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; to disable auto-logging (session tracking, tool capture). Manual &lt;code&gt;remember&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;recall&lt;/code&gt; still works.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Disable auto-logging for a session
ENSUE_READONLY=true claude

# Or add to ~/.zshrc for permanent read-only mode
export ENSUE_READONLY=true&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;"remember my preferred stack is React + Postgres"
"what do I know about caching strategies?"
"check my research/distributed-systems/ notes"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Docs · Dashboard · Homepage · API: &lt;code&gt;https://api.ensue-network.ai&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/mutable-state-inc/ensue-skill"/><published>2025-12-29T22:30:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46427376</id><title>Parsing Advances</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:24.356197+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7fa4da19ee2f93dd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I find myself writing yet another toy parser, as one does during a Christmas break. It roughly follows Resilient LL Parsing Tutorial. Not because I need resilience, but mostly because I find producing a syntax tree and a collection of diagnostics a more natural fit for the problem than bailing out on the first error.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One practical pitfall with the approach is infinite loops/recursion. Resilience sometimes means not consuming a token, and, if you do that in a loop or a Pratt recursive call, you’ll get yourself an annoying to debug error:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a concrete example, you might parse function argument list using code like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The implicit contract here is that expression consumes at least one token, even if there are errors in the source code. If there’s some token that makes expression bail without consuming anything, the code loops forever, and you’ll need a debugger to get at the stack trace!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The way I solved this issue traditionally is via a combination of two techniques:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fuel: parser has a fuel: Cell&amp;lt;u32&amp;gt; field, which is decremented even by “readonly” lookahead methods, and topped up every time the parser consumes a token. Fuel is useful to make you parser crash somewhat cleanly, though the crash is typically still removed from problematic function by several stack frames.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second technique is to maintain a mental map of functions which always consume at least one token of input, and functions which might bail without consuming anything. And, whenever you write a loop or a recursive call, consult this map to be sure to call at least one token-consuming function. Hard and error prone!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, I think I’ve figured something better today! You can assert that parser did advance when you expect it to. The smaller benefit here is that if parser didn’t advance, you get an immediate error. The bigger benefit is that these asserts materialize the mental map of advancing functions in the source code, so it doesn’t have to be mental anymore!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This seems like an obvious idea in retrospect, but, well, took me more than one parser to figure it out!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concretely, I came up with the following base parser API:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here is the buggy function that lead to the error at the start of the article:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://matklad.github.io/2025/12/28/parsing-advances.html"/><published>2025-12-29T23:29:35+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46427586</id><title>Stranger Things creator says turn off "garbage" settings</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:23.811869+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7c689f7a39484e6b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stranger Things creator Ross Duffer offered a piece of advice to viewers who plan on watching the season 5 premiere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Instagram, Duffer guided fans through their TV settings so they could watch the new season of Stranger Things the way it was meant to be seen. He stated, "A little PSA before you watch tonight. I want to make sure that your TVs are set up properly." He proceeded to tell his followers to turn off all their settings, especially dynamic contrast, super resolution, edge enhancer, and color filter. He even described those features as "garbage."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Stranger Things creator then returns to the picture settings menu, pointing out that viewers should disable noise reduction, too. He also said that truemotion and smoothmotion are the biggest "offenders" and should be turned off most of all because they cause “the dreaded soap opera effect.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He explains that most televisions will fix many of these problems if you switch to their advanced viewing presets, such as Dolby Vision Movie Dark. However, even those modes aren’t perfect. He urges fans to manually confirm each setting is off and adds, “Whatever you do, do not switch anything on ‘vivid’ because it’s gonna turn on all the worst offenders. It’s gonna destroy the color, and it’s not the filmmaker’s intent.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Duffer’s advice highlights a conflict between technological advances and creators' goals. Features like the ones he mentioned are designed to appeal to casual viewers by making images appear sharper or more colorful, but they alter the original look of the content. By asking fans to turn these features off, he is stressing the importance of preserving the director’s vision.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stranger Things season 5, volume 1, is available to stream now on Netflix. Volume 2 will be released on December 25, 2025, and the finale on December 31, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Release Date&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;2016 - 2025-00-00&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Network&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;Netflix&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Showrunner&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;Matt Duffer, Ross Duffer&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Cast&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Jane 'Eleven' Hopper&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Mike Wheeler&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Directors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;Matt Duffer, Ross Duffer, Andrew Stanton, Frank Darabont, Nimród Antal, Uta Briesewitz&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Writers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;Kate Trefry, Jessie Nickson-Lopez, Jessica Mecklenburg, Alison Tatlock&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Genres&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;Drama, Mystery, Horror, Science Fiction&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;Creator(s)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;Matt Duffer, Ross Duffer&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://screenrant.com/stranger-things-creator-turn-off-settings-premiere/"/><published>2025-12-29T23:50:34+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46427920</id><title>MongoDB Server Security Update, December 2025</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:23.684732+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a4e75956e81f6bca"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At MongoDB, protecting our customers’ data is our highest priority. On December 12, 2025, the MongoDB Security Engineering team identified a security vulnerability, described in CVE-2025-14847, which impacts MongoDB Server. Within the security community, this vulnerability is informally referred to as “Mongobleed.” This blog post outlines the situation, our immediate response, and the key insights we’ve gathered so far. Security is an ongoing responsibility in modern software development for both software producers and consumers, and maintaining trust depends on how issues are identified, addressed, and communicated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This patched security vulnerability in the MongoDB Server products (Community and Enterprise) is not a breach or compromise of MongoDB, MongoDB Atlas (our managed MongoDB Server offering), or our systems. To maintain the highest levels of security, customers and users are advised to use the latest versions of MongoDB’s software that have been updated to address this vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vulnerability was discovered internally by MongoDB Security Engineering as part of our proactive and continuously evolving security program. Over the last several years, we have increased our investment in people, processes, and technology to analyse and improve our codebase continuously. This work is ongoing, and discoveries like this reinforce the importance of sustained focus in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because how and when we act matters as much as what we do, transparency around timing is important. The following timeline outlines our discovery, validation, remediation, and disclosure efforts from December 12 through December 23, 2025 (all times U.S. ET):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;December 12 at 19:00 – MongoDB Security Engineering detected the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;December 12–14 – We worked continuously to validate the issue and develop and test a fix.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;December 15-17 – We developed and tested our rollout plans to enable rapid and safe deployment at scale, and commenced patching the Atlas fleet.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;December 17 at 12:10 – We completed patching the majority of the Atlas fleet.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;December 17 at 21:00 – Atlas provides an optional feature called “maintenance windows” that provides customers control over when MongoDB applies routine software updates to their Atlas instances. We proactively notified Atlas customers with maintenance windows configured that we would perform an urgent patch the following day, as part of our established policy.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;December 18 – We patched the remainder of the Atlas fleet, including those with maintenance windows, and continued customer communications.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;December 19 – We published the vulnerability through the industry-standard CVE process as CVE-2025-14847.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;December 23 – We posted an update on MongoDB’s community forum, sharing the patch and details on how to update.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protecting customers was our top priority throughout this process. Tens of thousands of MongoDB Atlas customers and hundreds of thousands of Atlas instances were proactively patched within days. Because MongoDB manages Atlas, we were able to deploy critical security patches quickly and safely on behalf of customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In parallel with our Atlas remediation, we published patch versions of MongoDB for customers running MongoDB Enterprise Advanced. We also made available patched community builds and proactively notified Community Edition users through our community forum. Our goal was to ensure that all MongoDB users, whether running Atlas, Enterprise Advanced, or Community, had access to patches and clear guidance as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As with any operational event, this was another opportunity to learn, improve, and raise the bar. The software security space is rapidly evolving with new tools and techniques, and MongoDB will continue to evaluate and deploy new capabilities as part of our deep investment in security for our customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operating software and services securely at high scale is complex. Our responsibility is to continuously improve our products, act with urgency and transparency, and strengthen how we protect our customers. We appreciate the trust our customers place in MongoDB and remain committed to earning that trust every day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Jim Scharf, Chief Technology Officer, MongoDB&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.mongodb.com/company/blog/news/mongodb-server-security-update-december-2025"/><published>2025-12-30T00:23:47+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46428154</id><title>Outside, Dungeon, Town: Integrating the Three Places in Videogames (2024)</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:22.885207+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3c2214be1a840251"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Videogames, at least the kind I’m talking about (RPGs, adventure kinds of somewhat narrative videogames, Zelda games, Elden Ring, etc), have essentially three “places”:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Outside – Hyrule field. Most of the game is Outside, just running around in a grassy area or a snowy mountain. It’s kind of the glue between all of the elements but there can be all manner of things Outside. Outside is the most flexible, but it typically has the lowest density of monsters, NPCs, shops, etc.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dungeon – The sewers, the final boss’ castle, a factory full of monsters, or a literal dungeon. Dungeons have LOTS of monsters, treasure, and usually a boss. You go into a dungeon to kinda clear it, get the treasure, kill the boss. Dungeons rarely have NPCs or shops in them (Shiren the Wanderer is an exception that comes to mind).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Town – This is where most NPCs are, but also the highest concentration of “specific activities”. Towns are dense, there’s often shops, minigames, quests, etc. Kakariko Village from Ocarina of Time is one of my favorite towns. There are almost never fights in town – you are almost always entirely safe in town.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, any time you try to boil down reality into a nice neat little categorization system like this, you’re going to be missing a lot of details, but broadly speaking, I think this holds up pretty well. I’m playing through Final Fantasy VII Rebirth now (which I am loving) and it’s very clear in that game, whether you are in Outside, Dungeon or Town, pretty much at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Videogames are a language, and this pattern is an important building block in that language. It is kind of good that you know you’re always safe in town. It is kind of good that you know what you’re in for when entering a big scary difficult dungeon, and so on. So, I am not saying that we get rid of these designations, at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What I’m asking for&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I would love, though, is some more messiness in how they are implemented. Kakariko Village from Ocarina of Time is one of my favorite towns because there are some “grey area” parts, especially underground. It also has a dungeon, arguably inside it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would love a dungeon that connects to the back of someone’s house in a town. Or one part in town that is kind of more Outside-like, like a little forest in there. Or maybe something that’s like 50% dungeon, 50% town.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want the borders of these places to be a little blurrier. It always bothers me in newer games when I enter a dungeon and text pops up on the screen saying “Gorbath’s Cove” or something. Developers do that so that players get a little “check box” feeling, that they have checked another Location off of the List Of Locations, and gotten that much closer to 100%-ing the game. There’s not nothing to that, but it has a cost. The cost of this kind of “instancing” is that the player is sort of robbed of the feeling of discovering a place for themselves. When I first see a cave, I’m like, whoa, there’s a little cave!! But then I walk in and get an announcement, telling me that this is a known site, that my discovery isn’t special, and also that there are many places just like this one in this game.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am not really that impressed by the underworld of Tears of the Kingdom, specifically because it is so clearly “its own map”. I would much prefer that, throughout Hyrule, there was a network of messy underground areas. Maybe one cave system has a place where it connects to a dungeon, which connects also to a basement in some guy’s house in the middle of nowhere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The existence of these “three places” is a good thing for videogames and I am not saying that we abandon it. However, I think we should “break the rules” a lot more frequently, because a world that breaks the rules is a world that invites and cultivates a sense of wonder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hope to do a lot of this with my own game, Free Tiya Bannet, which I’m working on now. I want the first town to be, yes, a town. It does have shops, and you are mostly safe in most of it. But maybe there’s one area where you aren’t safe. Maybe there’s an underground part of it that is kind of a dungeon. Maybe it even connects to a secret definitely-dungeon, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Videogames, especially the higher budget games, have a tendency towards being conservative: making sure that everyone understands exactly what is happening at all times. I think this is a valid thing to care about, but I also think that, like all things, it’s a balancing act, and I think too many games have been falling on the too-conservative part of the spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://keithburgun.net/outside-dungeon-town-integrating-the-three-places-in-videogames/"/><published>2025-12-30T00:54:34+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46428206</id><title>100x (YC S22) Is Hiring a Front End Engineer</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:22.496524+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bdbb174c5dac2469"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Location: Bangalore, India (Koramangala) Compensation: Competitive Salary + Significant Equity (YC Standard) Founders: Shardul Lavekar (ex-Airtel AI, ex-Ola) &amp;amp; Parth Mudgal (ex-Flipkart, ex-Ola)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At 100x.bot, we are building the interface for this future. We are not just another "AI Wrapper." We are a deep-tech company backed by Y Combinator, Accel, and Inventus, solving the hardest problem in automation: making browser agents reliable, fast, and accessible to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Most AI agents today are slow, expensive, and hallucinate frequently because they "think too hard" about every click. We take a different approach: "Record once, Automate forever." We combine the deterministic speed of record-and-replay technology with the semantic intelligence of LLMs to create agents that utilize self-healing DOM maps to navigate the chaotic web with human-like resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Opportunity: More Than Just UI We are looking for a Frontend Craftsperson to join our core engineering team in Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is not a role for someone who just wants to center divs or convert Figma files into React components. We are looking for an engineer who can architect the client-side experience for autonomous agents. You will be building the "cockpit" from which users control their digital workforce.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;What You Will Architect The Agent Visualization Engine: You will build complex, interactive graph-based interfaces that visualize agent workflows. Users need to see the logic flow—loops, conditionals, and "self-healing" events—in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dynamic MCP Interfaces: You will build systems that dynamically generate UIs based on Model Context Protocol schemas. If an MCP server exposes a new tool, your UI should instantly adapt to support it, without a code deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;High-Performance Streaming UI: Our agents generate massive logs (DOM snapshots, network events, execution traces). You will use virtualization (e.g., react-window) and atomic state management (Zustand/Jotai) to render these streams at 60fps, ensuring the UI never lags behind the bot.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The "Recorder" Experience: You will refine our Chrome Extension overlay, ensuring it injects cleanly into any third-party website (using Shadow DOM encapsulation) to capture user intent without breaking the host page.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Tech Stack We run a modern, type-safe stack designed for velocity and reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Frontend: React, TypeScript, Next.js&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Styling: Tailwind CSS (with Shadow DOM handling)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;State: Zustand / TanStack Query (for high-frequency updates)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Protocol: Model Context Protocol (MCP), WebSockets, Chrome Extension APIs&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Who You Are A React Expert (2+ Years): You understand the React reconciliation algorithm inside out. You know why useEffect is dangerous for high-frequency data and how to use useRef or useSyncExternalStore to optimize performance.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;TypeScript Native: You don't just use any. You write robust, generic types that mirror complex backend schemas. You are comfortable sharing types between the extension background script and the UI.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A "Craftsperson": You care about micro-interactions. You understand that trust is built through UI feedback—a loading spinner, a hover state, a smooth transition. You take pride in building developer tools that feel like magic.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Systems Thinker: You can reason about asynchronous systems. You understand race conditions, websocket reconnections, and the complexity of communicating between a Content Script, a Background Worker, and a React UI.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;High Agency: In a small YC team, nobody will hand you a ticket. You will identify problems, design solutions, and ship them.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Why Join 100x.bot? Work on the Bleeding Edge. You will be a pioneer in the space of AI Agents.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;YC Culture: We move fast. We ship daily. We value product instincts over bureaucracy. You will have significant ownership and equity.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Complex Engineering: You won't be bored. You are building a browser automation engine, a recording studio, and an IDE—all in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Work directly with Shardul and Parth to shape the product roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;How to Apply Email me your GitHub and a link to a complex UI you have built.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note: We value actual build history over resumes/degress. Show us something that proves you are a craftsperson.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46428206"/><published>2025-12-30T01:00:03+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46428496</id><title>Hacking Washing Machines [video]</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:20.730558+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b41e325c1ac906ec"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Severin von Wnuck-Lipinski and Hajo Noerenberg&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Almost everyone has a household appliance at home, whether it's a washing machine, dishwasher, or dryer. Despite their ubiquity, little is publicly documented about how these devices actually work or how their internal components communicate. This talk takes a closer look at proprietary bus systems, hidden diagnostic interfaces, and approaches to cloud-less integration of appliances from two well-known manufacturers into modern home automation systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modern home appliances may seem simple from the outside, but inside they contain complex electronic systems, proprietary communication protocols, and diagnostic interfaces rarely documented outside the manufacturer. In this talk, we'll explore the challenges of reverse-engineering these systems: from analyzing appliance control boards and internal communication buses to decompiling and modifying firmware to better understand device functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We'll also look at the security mechanisms designed to protect diagnostic access and firmware readout, and how these protections can be bypassed to enable deeper insight into device operation. Finally, this talk will demonstrate how the results of this research can be used to integrate even legacy home appliances into popular home automation platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This session combines examples and insights from the reverse-engineering of B/S/H/ and Miele household appliances.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Licensed to the public under http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Download&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Video&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;These files contain multiple languages.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This Talk was translated into multiple languages. The files available for download contain all languages as separate audio-tracks. Most desktop video players allow you to choose between them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please look for "audio tracks" in your desktop video player.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://media.ccc.de/v/39c3-hacking-washing-machines"/><published>2025-12-30T01:40:49+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46430558</id><title>Charm Ruby – Glamorous Terminal Libraries for Ruby</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:20.512920+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="45ce1477af0f3686"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Bubbletea&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build terminal UIs from the future, today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A powerful TUI framework using the Elm Architecture. Handle keyboard, mouse, and window events with commands for side effects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "bubbletea"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
 ██████╗██╗  ██╗ █████╗ ██████╗ ███╗   ███╗
██╔════╝██║  ██║██╔══██╗██╔══██╗████╗ ████║
██║     ███████║███████║██████╔╝██╔████╔██║
██║     ██╔══██║██╔══██║██╔══██╗██║╚██╔╝██║
╚██████╗██║  ██║██║  ██║██║  ██║██║ ╚═╝ ██║
       ╚═════╝╚═╝  ╚═╝╚═╝  ╚═╝╚═╝  ╚═╝╚═╝     ╚═╝  RUBY
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Ruby bindings and ports of the beloved Charm terminal libraries.&lt;lb/&gt; Build glamorous TUIs, style terminal output, create beautiful forms,&lt;lb/&gt; and make your Ruby CLIs sparkle. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem install bubbletea lipgloss bubbles glamour&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build terminal UIs from the future, today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A powerful TUI framework using the Elm Architecture. Handle keyboard, mouse, and window events with commands for side effects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "bubbletea"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Bubble Tea component toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-built components: Spinner, Progress, Timer, TextInput, TextArea, Viewport, List, Table, FilePicker, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "bubbles"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Track clickable regions in terminal UIs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mark zones with IDs, check mouse coordinates, and handle click events in your Bubble Tea applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "bubblezone"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your terminal style and layout toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Borders, padding, margins, colors (hex, ANSI, adaptive), tables, lists, trees, and layout utilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "lipgloss"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The stylesheet-driven markdown renderer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Render markdown in your terminal with built-in themes (dark, light, dracula), custom styles via DSL, and emoji support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "glamour"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Terminal charts for beautiful data viz.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sparkline, Barchart, LineChart, WaveLineChart, StreamLineChart (real-time), and TimeSeriesLineChart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "ntcharts"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simple, powerful forms in the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Input, Text, Select, MultiSelect, Confirm, Note, Spinner. Built-in validation, themes, and a block-based DSL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "huh", github: "marcoroth/huh-ruby"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A tool for glamorous shell scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ruby wrapper with idiomatic API: input, write, choose, filter, confirm, file, pager, spin, style, format. Bundles the gum binary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "gum"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A physics-based animation library.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Damped harmonic oscillator (Spring), projectile motion, Point &amp;amp; Vector math, and frame rate helpers for smooth UI animations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gem "harmonica"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add the gems you need to your Gemfile:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Gemfile

# Core TUI framework
gem "bubbletea"

# Styling
gem "lipgloss"

# Components
gem "bubbles"

# Markdown rendering
gem "glamour"

# Shell scripts
gem "gum"

# Animations
gem "harmonica"

# Charts
gem "ntcharts"

# Mouse tracking
gem "bubblezone"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A simple Bubbletea app with Lipgloss styling:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;require "bubbletea"
require "lipgloss"

class HelloWorld
  include Bubbletea::Model

  def initialize
    @style = Lipgloss::Style.new
      .border(:rounded)
      .border_foreground("#7D56F4")
      .padding(1, 2)
  end

  def init = [self, nil]

  def update(message)
    case message
    when Bubbletea::KeyMessage
      return [self, Bubbletea.quit] if message.to_s == "q"
    end

    [self, nil]
  end

  def view
    @style.render("Hello, Charm Ruby!\n\nPress q to quit")
  end
end

Bubbletea.run(HelloWorld.new)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;require "bubbletea"
require "lipgloss"

class Counter
  include Bubbletea::Model

  def initialize
    @count = 0
    @style = Lipgloss::Style.new
      .bold(true)
      .foreground("#FF6B6B")
  end

  def update(message)
    case message
    when Bubbletea::KeyMessage
      case message.to_s
      when "q", "ctrl+c"
        return [self, Bubbletea.quit]
      when "up" then @count += 1
      when "down" then @count -= 1
      end
    end

    [self, nil]
  end

  def view
    @style.render("Count: #{@count}\n\nPress q to quit")
  end
end

Bubbletea.run(Counter.new)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;require "bubbletea"
require "bubbles"

class LoadingApp
  include Bubbletea::Model

  def initialize
    @spinner = Bubbles::Spinner.new
  end

  def init
    [self, @spinner.tick]
  end

  def update(message)
    case message
    when Bubbletea::KeyMessage
      case message.to_s
      when "q", "ctrl+c"
        return [self, Bubbletea.quit]
      end
    end

    @spinner, command = @spinner.update(message)

    [self, command]
  end

  def view
    "#{@spinner.view} Loading..."
  end
end

Bubbletea.run(LoadingApp.new)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;require "huh"

form = Huh.form(
  Huh.group(
    Huh.input
      .key("name")
      .title("What's your name?")
      .placeholder("Enter name..."),

    Huh.select
      .key("color")
      .title("Favorite color?")
      .options(*Huh.options(
        "Red", "Green", "Blue"
      ))
  )
).with_theme(Huh::Themes.charm)

form.run

puts "Hello, #{form["name"]}!"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;require "lipgloss"

headers = ["Name", "Language", "Stars"]

rows = [
  ["bubbletea", "Ruby", "✨"],
  ["lipgloss", "Ruby", "💄"],
  ["glamour", "Ruby", "✨"]
]

table = Lipgloss::Table.new
  .headers(headers)
  .rows(rows)
  .border(:rounded)

puts table.render&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;require "glamour"

markdown = &amp;lt;&amp;lt;~MD
  # Hello Glamour :sparkles:

  This is **bold** and *italic*.

  - Item one
  - Item two
  - Item three

  ```ruby
  puts "Hello, World!"
  ```
MD

puts Glamour.render(markdown,
  style: "dark",
  width: 80,
  emoji: true
)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;require "ntcharts"

chart = Ntcharts::Streamlinechart.new(60, 12)

loop do
  chart.push(Math.sin(Time.now.to_f) * 4 + 5)

  print "\e[H\e[2J"
  puts chart.render
  sleep 0.1
end&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These Ruby gems are ports and bindings of the original Go libraries from Charm. They bring the same elegant APIs and glamorous terminal experiences to Ruby developers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some gems use native C extensions that link to compiled Go shared libraries, while others are pure Ruby implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://charm-ruby.dev/"/><published>2025-12-30T07:36:38+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46431028</id><title>Go Away Python</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:19.675679+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="5f7ec79370d86d1d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;lorentz app blog experiments&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://lorentz.app/blog-item.html?id=go-shebang"/><published>2025-12-30T08:50:44+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46431560</id><title>Netflix: Open Content</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:19.408527+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="235793111fd515b3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Netflix, we are always exploring ways to make our content look and sound even better. To provide a common reference for prototyping bleeding-edge technologies within entertainment, technology and academic circles without compromising the security of our original and licensed programming, we've developed test titles oriented around documentary, live action, and animation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many open source assets are available from each project listed below. Our hope is this will encourage more experimentation, learning, and discovery that will benefit the whole industry. Many of these titles are also streaming on Netflix and are best enjoyed with any HDR configured device with your Premium subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can download single files directly through your web browser, but for large files and long frame sequences, you may wish to use command line tools. Guidance is included below. Ad Blockers may cause errors in your downloading process, so try turning it off if you have issues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our open source content is available under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve had great success remastering titles like Knights of Sidonia, Flavours of Youth and Godzilla from SDR to HDR over the last few years. But what if we increase the resolution and create anime with HDR in mind from conception? Working with Japan's Production I.G, we set out to create the first 4K HDR Atmos anime short and discover what would need to change in anime workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read more about Sol Levante in the Netflix Tech Blog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;HDR10 2020 ST2084 UHD 24fps 1000nit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DolbyVision PQ/P3 D65 UHD 24fps IMF&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Atmos ADM and DAMF files&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ProTools Final Mix Session and Mastered Session&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4K HDR 16bit P3/PQ D65 Dolby Vision 2.9 XML + VDM&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Animatics, storyboard, selected After Effects projects, PSDs, and TGA in-betweens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A live action test piece, Nocturne was shot at 120fps and sought to investigate footage with spatially complex scenes that mimic other professionally generated content to challenge codecs on both the encoding and decoding sides. This piece was also mastered in Dolby Vision and Atmos.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;120fps Video Display Master&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;60fps Video Display Master&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ADM WAV File&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upon noticing the contrast in dark shadows against the bright sky and sparks from a welder working on a new Netflix building, the encoding team acquired a Sony PMW-F55 and the AXS-R5 RAW recorder to shoot 16-bit RAW SQ and produce Sparks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sparks was shot 4K HFR and finished at 4000 nits using ACES. Read more about Sparks on the Netflix Tech Blog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4K P3 PQ 4000nits Dolby Vision IMF&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;HDR10 1000nit PQ 2020 image sequence&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4K P3/PQ 4000nits EXR&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4K P3/PQ 4000nits EXR Dolby Vision metadata&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ACES 59.94fps image sequence&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original Camera Files&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following the industry shift from “more pixels” to “better pixels,” we produced Meridian, our first test title to tell a story. Meridian was mastered in Dolby Vision high dynamic range (HDR) with a P3-D65 color space and PQ (perceptual quantizer) transfer function. It also contained a Dolby Atmos mix, multiple language tracks, and subtitles. You can read more about Meridian on Variety.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UHD IMF&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zipped UHD VDM&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UHD 4k 5994 HDR P3/PQ (mp4)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UHD VDM Image Sequence&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dolby Atmos Metadata File&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Atmos BWAV ADM&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TIFF Sequence&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We felt a need to include animated content in our test title library, so we partnered with Blender Foundation and Fotokem’s Keep Me Posted to re-grade Cosmos Laundromat, an award-winning short film in Dolby Vision HDR.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cosmos Laundromat is an Open Movie project created by Blender Studio and directed by Mathieu Auvray. The film was made entirely in Blender, an open source 3D content creation tool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2k 24p HDR P3/PQ (mp4)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EXR to TIFF Nuke Script File&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EXR Sequence&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chimera is technically comparable to El Fuente, but its scenes are more representative of existing titles on Netflix. The dinner scene attempts to recreate a codec-challenging sequence from House of Cards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prior to Chimera, there wasn’t any open source 4K test material that exhibited real world live action material.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DCI 4k 2398p HDR P3/PQ&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DCI 4k 5994p HDR P3/PQ&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TIFF Sequence: DCI 4k 2398p&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TIFF Sequence: DCI 4k 5994p&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the demand for more pixels increased, so did appropriate test content. Documentary short El Fuente was shot in Mexico by a local DP at 4K at both 48 and 59.94 fps to meet increasing resolution and frame rate requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Boat: 4096x2160 60fps 10bit 420 (YUV4Mpeg format)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FoodMarket: 4096x2160 60fps 10bit 420 (YUV4Mpeg format)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The assets on this page can be browsed on the Netflix OpenContent bucket here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;http://download.opencontent.netflix.com/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can download single files directly through your web browser on each page, but for large files and long frame sequences, you may wish to use command line tools such as aws cli. Instructions are posted on their website. After installation, you should be able to download the public assets. Try running these sample commands. If the download is interrupted, you can run the same command immediately and aws cli will resume the download where it left off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download a single file (0.7 kB):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Usage: aws s3 cp --no-sign-request &amp;lt;s3 URI&amp;gt; &amp;lt;local destination&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example: aws s3 cp --no-sign-request s3://download.opencontent.netflix.com/TechblogAssets/Sparks/sparks_license.txt .&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sync entire directory (1406.1 MB):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Usage: aws s3 sync --no-sign-request &amp;lt;s3 URI&amp;gt; &amp;lt;local destination&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example: aws s3 sync --no-sign-request s3://download.opencontent.netflix.com/TechblogAssets/CosmosLaundromat/encodes/ .&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The download links on this page will bring you to the root directory for that title's assets. You may need to navigate around to find the folder you want.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last updated 2022-04-26&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://opencontent.netflix.com/"/><published>2025-12-30T10:11:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46432057</id><title>Nicolas Guillou, French ICC judge sanctioned by the US and “debanked”</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:19.206803+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="edf032a6356510c3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nicolas Guillou, a French judge at the International Criminal Court (ICC), was sanctioned by the United States under a decision made by Donald Trump on August 20. The US Treasury Department justified the action, stating that "Guillou is being designated for ruling to authorize the ICC's issuance of arrest warrants for Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and former Minister of Defense Yoav Gallant." Both men are indicted for war crimes and crimes against humanity for their roles in the destruction of the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, six judges and three prosecutors from the ICC, including Chief Prosecutor Karim Khan, have been sanctioned by the US. In an interview with Le Monde, the judge explained the impact of these measures on his work and daily life. Without commenting on ongoing cases, he called on European authorities to activate a mechanism that could limit the impact of US restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What is the purpose of the American sanctions mechanism?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially, it was created to address human rights violations, counter terrorism and combat drug trafficking. Today, nearly 15,000 individuals are on the US sanctions list, mostly members of Al-Qaeda, the Islamic State group (IS), mafia organizations and the leaders of authoritarian regimes. Among this long list are nine ICC judges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have 81.05% of this article left to read. The rest is for subscribers only.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/international/article/2025/11/19/nicolas-guillou-french-icc-judge-sanctioned-by-the-us-you-are-effectively-blacklisted-by-much-of-the-world-s-banking-system_6747628_4.html"/><published>2025-12-30T11:13:30+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46432311</id><title>Non-Zero-Sum Games</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:18.775279+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b8854dca448ee835"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hi, I'm Non-Zero-Sum James, your companion on this exploration of win-win games and how they are essential for a better future. Each week we'll explore a new aspect of game theory, moral philosophy, ethical economics and artificial intelligence—looking to solve the complex problems we face in our world together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the posts are connected through the lens of non-zero-sum games, but they fall into a few broad categories. You can start your journey with whatever appeals to you:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"It is well to remember that the entire universe, with one trifling exception, is composed of others."&lt;lb/&gt;—John Holmes&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your thoughts and contributions are welcome. Share, debate, and co-create in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nonzerosum.games/"/><published>2025-12-30T11:42:55+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46432451</id><title>Crimson (YC X25) is hiring founding engineers in London</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:18.341198+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9c99af386544742c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Crimson is the AI platform for high-stakes litigation. We're working with top law firms in the UK and US to streamline how complex disputes are run. Our platform drafts pleadings and submissions, analyzes judgments and orders, summarizes transcripts and locates key evidence in seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We're a team of three co-founders with deep technical and domain expertise. Our users are lawyers who trust us with their most sensitive case files. They care about security, accuracy, reliability and speed, and so do we.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We're looking for an exceptional full-stack engineer to join us as one of our first employees. You'll ship production code from day one and own major features end-to-end. That means talking to users, scoping the problem, building the solution and improving it over time.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;What you'll do&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Contribute to the entire stack, from cloud infrastructure to prompting to UX (Python backend, Next.js with TypeScript frontend, PostgreSQL, SOTA LLMs. Deployed to Azure via IaC (Bicep) with CI/CD pipelines powered by GitHub Actions)&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Collaborate closely with users to understand how lawyers work and what they need&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Architect and scale document ingestion and processing pipelines to power fast, accurate search and data extraction for large volumes of legal documents&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Develop intelligent, multi-step agent workflows that can autonomously handle complex legal tasks - from surfacing key testimony across depositions to generating fact chronologies and auto-detecting inconsistencies in opposing counsel’s filings&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Design and bring to life intuitive AI-native user experiences tailored to litigation workflows&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Improve system performance, stability and observability as we scale&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Help shape our engineering culture and team - from best practices to hiring and mentorship&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is for you if …&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You’re driven, self-directed and exceptionally capable&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You’re obsessed with building outstanding products for demanding users&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You’re excited to work on hard problems, take ownership and push things through&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You have high agency and a bias for shipping&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You have excellent product judgement, communication skills and attention to detail&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Bonus points if you have an interest in legal tech&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Why join us&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Over the next few years, the legal industry will change beyond recognition. You’ll be at the heart of that change, helping us build a category-defining company&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;We’re backed by YC and other top investors&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;We’re working with major UK and US law firms&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You’ll get ownership, equity and the opportunity to shape the business and lead engineering teams&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Details&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Location: London (minimum 3 days/week in our office near Bank)&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Salary: £80-120k&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Meaningful equity&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Contact: tell us about things you’ve built by emailing founders [at] crimson [dot] law. Please include a link to your LinkedIn profile. We’ll get back to you within 24h.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/crimson/jobs/kCikzj1-founding-engineer-full-stack"/><published>2025-12-30T12:00:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46432791</id><title>Groq investor sounds alarm on data centers</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:18.137204+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.axios.com/2025/12/29/groq-alex-davis-data-center-concerns"/><published>2025-12-30T12:47:41+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46432862</id><title>Times New American: A Tale of Two Fonts</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:17.633906+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bec4a14217f20d83"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Times New American: A Tale of Two Fonts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A less romantic truth is that aesthetic standards rarely travel alone; power tends to follow in their wake. An episode at the U.S. State Department this month makes exactly this point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On December 9, Secretary of State Marco Rubio issued a memo titled “Return to Tradition” that required all State Department documents to switch back to 14-point Times New Roman, overturning a Biden-era directive from 2023 that had turned to 15-point Calibri.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Frankly, most people likely view both of these simply as “standard typefaces” without distinguishing much difference between them. So why would an institution of the State Department’s scale bother, twice in three years, to take a stance on something as seemingly trivial as a default typeface?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;John Gruber, an Apple-sphere blogger with a well-known appetite for political commentary, obtained the full text of Rubio’s memo and published it. 1 (It is worth reading first.) Rubio’s rationale, in simplified form, has three parts. First, serif typefaces are said to better communicate professionalism, formality, and authority in official documents (¶¶ 6–8). Second, using a serif typeface is aligning with the White House, the courts, and the State Department’s own historical practice (¶ 9). Third, the 2023 decision was a “cosmetic” gesture associated with diversity, equity, inclusion, and accessibility (DEIA) politics, and the reversion a correction to that (¶ 10).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commentary on American partisan politics is beyond the scope of this article. Still, in neutral terms, Trump’s second term has been marked by an unusually rapid and sweeping effort to repeal or reverse the prior administration’s policies, with DEIA among the earliest targets. The memo itself cites Executive Order 14151, signed on the first day of the term, that instructed federal agencies to terminate all DEIA-related activities, offices, positions, policies, programs, and contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That makes the political element of this typography decision fairly plain: it coheres with, and signals loyalty to, a broader anti-DEIA agenda. The remaining question is whether it is only politics. Put differently, how persuasive are Rubio’s first two, ostensibly nonpolitical claims about design and conventions? Or are they merely pretexts?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To recap, a serif typeface is one with extra decorative strokes, or “serifs,” at the ends of main strokes. A popular narrative links serifs to stone inscriptions: Roman craftsmen would sketch letter outlines on stone and carve along them; at stroke endings and corners, the chisel work flared outward, leaving the small protrusions we now call serifs. That lineage likely underwrites the memo’s association of serifs with “tradition,” “formality,” and “ceremony.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, most people don’t actually know this history, and many cannot reliably distinguish serif from sans-serif in the first place. The general public doesn’t perceive serif typefaces as professional and authoritative, a priori, before prioritizing their use in formal settings. Instead, people first observe that government, academia, and corporate workplaces disproportionately use serif faces — or are trained to use them — and only then infer that serifs must mean professionalism and authority.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if we limit ourselves to design and historical considerations, Times New Roman, despite being a serif typeface, possesses little of the “professional, solemn, and authoritative” aura. The typeface was designed in 1931 for The Times of London, and newspaper typefaces are typically engineered to print cleanly on cheap paper, conserve space, and support rapid scanning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those goals are visible in the details. The strokes of Times New Roman are relatively thin (leaving tolerance for ink spread on newsprint), the letterforms are narrow, and the x-height (the height of the lowercase “x”) is comparatively large. There is nothing inherently wrong with such functional design; it simply doesn’t map neatly onto the “traditional” look of older serifs. On a modern, high-resolution display, the typeface can appear spindly, more utilitarian than ceremonial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, the stronger explanation for Times New Roman’s long reign isn’t aesthetic excellence, but practicality and inertia. Times New Roman was among the small set of typefaces bundled with early versions of Windows. It was also promoted as “web-safe,” meaning webmasters could reasonably assume it would render properly across platforms. In the early era of digitalization, choosing Times New Roman was often less a deliberate endorsement than a default imposed by limited options. Over time, the habit hardened into a standard, and institutions began to require it without much reflection, effectively borrowing their own authority to confer authority upon the typeface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professionals who genuinely focus on typography have advised against Times New Roman. For example, type designer Matthew Butterick eloquently comments:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When Times New Roman appears in a book, document, or advertisement, it connotes apathy. It says, “I submitted to the typeface of least resistance.” Times New Roman isn’t a typeface choice so much as the absence of a typeface choice, like the blackness of deep space isn’t a color. To look at Times New Roman is to gaze into the void.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit, in its formatting advice for lawyers, specifically cautions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Typographic decisions should be made for a purpose. The Times of London chose the typeface Times New Roman to serve an audience looking for a quick read. Lawyers don’t want their audience to read fast and throw the document away; they want to maximize retention. Achieving that goal requires a different approach — different typefaces, different column widths, different writing conventions. Briefs are like books rather than newspapers. The most important piece of advice we can offer is this: read some good books and try to make your briefs more like them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As for the other U.S. official bodies Rubio cites in the memo, many don’t actually use Times New Roman either. The Supreme Court’s rules require booklet-format filings to be set in the Century family, and its own opinions are typeset in Century Schoolbook from that family. Originating in the 19th century, the typeface features more expansive proportions, balanced stroke contrast, and an elegant form, exuding a far more assertive presence than Times New Roman. As the name suggests, it also began life as a textbook face, optimized for legibility. With proper typesetting, it reads far better than a haphazardly produced Word document set in Times New Roman.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at the legislature, the official PDFs of U.S. Congressional bills use Cheltenham for titles and De Vinne for body text. De Vinne, first released in 1902, shares similarities in style with Century Schoolbook but features stronger stroke contrast and more decorative serifs, giving it an “engraved” quality. Objectively speaking, this design borders on being a display typeface — imagine the logotype of Harper’s Bazaar, Didot — and is somewhat tiring to read in body text. But when it comes to conveying ceremony and solemnity, it’s far more qualified than Times New Roman. (After a bill is enacted into law, it will be typeset in New Century Schoolbook.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even the Trump administration, to which Rubio pledges allegiance, contradicts the “serif tradition” by using a fashionable tall, high-contrast serif (Instrument Serif) on the White House website. It may look a bit mannered by government standards — an impression no less bolstered by its bombastic rhetoric — but it does manage to appear assertive and emphatic. Swap in Times New Roman and “AMERICA IS BACK” would read more like a mutter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thus, the design and historical reasons cited in Rubio’s memo don’t hold up. The formality and authority of serif typefaces are largely socially constructed, and Times New Roman’s origin story and design constraints don’t express these qualities. If Times New Roman carries authority at all, it’s primarily borrowed from the authority of institutions that have adhered to it. If the sincere goal were to “return to tradition” by returning to a serif, there are many choices with deeper pedigree and more fitting gravitas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, it might sound as though the argument is trending toward a defense of the Department’s earlier choice: Calibri. Unfortunately, Calibri is also a poor fit for formal contexts. While seriousness and authority aren’t the exclusive province of serifs, Calibri does little to convey those traits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Typographically, Calibri is a humanist sans-serif. Such typefaces tend to have open, rounded forms and generous apertures (look at the wide openings in letters like a, c, e, and s). Calibri takes that softness especially far: terminals are visibly rounded, and many letters appear almost handwritten, to the extent that its designer described its quality as “warm and soft.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s nothing inherently wrong with this style, but one would hardly want an official document or legal contract to appear “warm and soft.” That is why I have long disliked Microsoft’s decision to make Calibri the default Office typeface starting with Office 2007. A default body typeface should be neutral and versatile, not exude a temperature. (Microsoft replaced Calibri with Aptos as the default in 2023, but inertia being what it is, Aptos still appears relatively rarely in the wild.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be fair, the State Department’s 2023 change was justified less as a matter of taste than as an accessibility and inclusion initiative. That is, to make documents easier to read for individuals with various physical and cognitive conditions. This goal is commendable in itself, but the means were, at best, loosely connected to the end, much like many inclusive measures that were once fashionable in U.S. politics and business in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, Calibri was not designed with accessibility in mind. It was commissioned by Microsoft to promote its ClearType technology, with the design objective of appearing clear on the low-resolution displays of its time. This means it prioritizes smoothness under specific sub-pixel rendering techniques, rather than ensuring the glyphs are easy to tell apart. If accessibility were truly the goal, one might select a typeface created for that purpose. For example, Atkinson Hyperlegible addresses character differentiation by adding serifs, exaggerating shapes, and slanting strokes, making it legible even under low-vision conditions. In contrast, Calibri has no anti-ambiguity design: the uppercase &lt;code&gt;I&lt;/code&gt; and lowercase &lt;code&gt;l&lt;/code&gt; are nearly identical. So much for “accessibility.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Furthermore, accessibility doesn’t depend solely on a document’s appearance but more on its internal structure and presentation mechanisms. For instance, the W3C’s Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) state that accessible content should be perceivable, operable, understandable, and robust. This means that documents should have proper semantic structure (so tools like screen readers can interpret content correctly), support customizable layouts and fonts, and be compatible with various applications and devices. If these principles were met, the specific font used would matter little, as users can access the content with their preferred tools in their preferred manner. Conversely, if a document is technically crude, like a scanned PDF — as many official documents are — the use of an “inclusive” font is merely self-congratulatory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If one insisted on a sans-serif for official writing, there are many better candidates than Calibri: Frutiger (common in airport wayfinding), Myriad (used by Apple for years), the cool and serious Univers (or a well-set Helvetica Neue), or contemporary neutral workhorses like Inter. If a “made in America” signal mattered, Public Sans (funded under the 21st Century Integrated Digital Experience Act passed during Trump’s first term) and used by many U.S. government websites is also a good option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Therefore, Rubio’s criticism that the previous move was “cosmetic,” while being politically charged, isn’t entirely unfounded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Taken together, the Department had previously pursued a defensible goal with a poorly matched design intervention and landed on an ill-fitting typeface. Now, for political motives, it has reversed that decision and returned to a bland, unremarkable default. Between the two, Times New Roman may be the lesser evil: it is more widely recognized, and it doesn’t clash with the official context as overtly as Calibri does. Still, Rubio, or whoever drafted the memo for him, could have been more candid. There was no need to dress up a political gesture with faux-erudite claims or to lavish praise on a mediocre typeface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because Times New Roman just will not make America great again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The authenticity of the text cannot be independently verified, of course. It is, however, consistent with reports from reputable media outlets. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://hsu.cy/2025/12/times-new-american/"/><published>2025-12-30T12:56:07+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46432916</id><title>Fucking Approachable Swift Concurrency</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:17.358861+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7470a7176c2d9444"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Fucking Approachable&lt;lb/&gt;Swift Concurrency&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally understand async/await, Tasks, and why the compiler keeps yelling at you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Huge thanks to Matt Massicotte for making Swift concurrency understandable. Put together by Pedro Piñera. Found an issue? [email protected]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the tradition of fuckingblocksyntax.com and fuckingifcaseletsyntax.com&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Async Code: async/await&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of what apps do is wait. Fetch data from a server - wait for the response. Read a file from disk - wait for the bytes. Query a database - wait for the results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before Swift's concurrency system, you'd express this waiting with callbacks, delegates, or Combine. They work, but nested callbacks get hard to follow, and Combine has a steep learning curve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;async/await&lt;/code&gt; gives Swift a new way to handle waiting. Instead of callbacks, you write code that looks sequential - it pauses, waits, and resumes. Under the hood, Swift's runtime manages these pauses efficiently. But making your app actually stay responsive while waiting depends on where code runs, which we'll cover later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An async function is one that might need to pause. You mark it with &lt;code&gt;async&lt;/code&gt;, and when you call it, you use &lt;code&gt;await&lt;/code&gt; to say "pause here until this finishes":&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;func fetchUser(id: Int) async throws -&amp;gt; User {
    let url = URL(string: "https://api.example.com/users/\(id)")!
    let (data, _) = try await URLSession.shared.data(from: url)  // Suspends here
    return try JSONDecoder().decode(User.self, from: data)
}

// Calling it
let user = try await fetchUser(id: 123)
// Code here runs after fetchUser completes&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your code pauses at each &lt;code&gt;await&lt;/code&gt; - this is called suspension. When the work finishes, your code resumes right where it left off. Suspension gives Swift the opportunity to do other work while waiting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Waiting for them&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if you need to fetch several things? You could await them one by one:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;let avatar = try await fetchImage("avatar.jpg")
let banner = try await fetchImage("banner.jpg")
let bio = try await fetchBio()&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But that's slow - each waits for the previous one to finish. Use &lt;code&gt;async let&lt;/code&gt; to run them in parallel:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;func loadProfile() async throws -&amp;gt; Profile {
    async let avatar = fetchImage("avatar.jpg")
    async let banner = fetchImage("banner.jpg")
    async let bio = fetchBio()

    // All three are fetching in parallel!
    return Profile(
        avatar: try await avatar,
        banner: try await banner,
        bio: try await bio
    )
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each &lt;code&gt;async let&lt;/code&gt; starts immediately. The &lt;code&gt;await&lt;/code&gt; collects the results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;await needs async&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can only use &lt;code&gt;await&lt;/code&gt; inside an &lt;code&gt;async&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Managing Work: Tasks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Task is a unit of async work you can manage. You've written async functions, but a Task is what actually runs them. It's how you start async code from synchronous code, and it gives you control over that work: wait for its result, cancel it, or let it run in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's say you're building a profile screen. Load the avatar when the view appears using the &lt;code&gt;.task&lt;/code&gt; modifier, which cancels automatically when the view disappears:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct ProfileView: View {
    @State private var avatar: Image?

    var body: some View {
        avatar
            .task { avatar = await downloadAvatar() }
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If users can switch between profiles, use &lt;code&gt;.task(id:)&lt;/code&gt; to reload when the selection changes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct ProfileView: View {
    var userID: String
    @State private var avatar: Image?

    var body: some View {
        avatar
            .task(id: userID) { avatar = await downloadAvatar(for: userID) }
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the user taps "Save", create a Task manually:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Button("Save") {
    Task { await saveProfile() }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if you need to load the avatar, bio, and stats all at once? Use a &lt;code&gt;TaskGroup&lt;/code&gt; to fetch them in parallel:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;try await withThrowingTaskGroup(of: Void.self) { group in
    group.addTask { avatar = try await downloadAvatar(for: userID) }
    group.addTask { bio = try await fetchBio(for: userID) }
    group.addTask { stats = try await fetchStats(for: userID) }
    try await group.waitForAll()
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tasks inside a group are child tasks, linked to the parent. A few things to know:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cancellation propagates: cancel the parent, and all children get cancelled too&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Errors: a thrown error cancels siblings and rethrows, but only when you consume results with &lt;code&gt;next()&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;waitForAll()&lt;/code&gt;, or iteration&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Completion order: results arrive as tasks finish, not the order you added them&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Waits for all: the group doesn't return until every child completes or is cancelled&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is structured concurrency: work organized in a tree that's easy to reason about and clean up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Where Things Run: From Threads to Isolation Domains&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So far we've talked about when code runs (async/await) and how to organize it (Tasks). Now: where does it run, and how do we keep it safe?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Most apps just wait&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most app code is I/O-bound. You fetch data from a network, await a response, decode it, and display it. If you have multiple I/O operations to coordinate, you resort to tasks and task groups. The actual CPU work is minimal. The main thread can handle this fine because &lt;code&gt;await&lt;/code&gt; suspends without blocking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But sooner or later, you'll have CPU-bound work: parsing a giant JSON file, processing images, running complex calculations. This work doesn't wait for anything external. It just needs CPU cycles. If you run it on the main thread, your UI freezes. This is where "where does code run" actually matters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Old World: Many Options, No Safety&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before Swift's concurrency system, you had several ways to manage execution:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Approach&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;What it does&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Tradeoffs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Thread&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Direct thread control&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Low-level, error-prone, rarely needed&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GCD&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Dispatch queues with closures&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Simple but no cancellation, easy to cause thread explosion&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;OperationQueue&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Task dependencies, cancellation, KVO&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;More control but verbose and heavyweight&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Combine&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Reactive streams&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Great for event streams, steep learning curve&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of these worked, but safety was entirely on you. The compiler couldn't help if you forgot to dispatch to main, or if two queues accessed the same data simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Problem: Data Races&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A data race happens when two threads access the same memory at the same time, and at least one is writing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;var count = 0

DispatchQueue.global().async { count += 1 }
DispatchQueue.global().async { count += 1 }

// Undefined behavior: crash, memory corruption, or wrong value&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data races are undefined behavior. They can crash, corrupt memory, or silently produce wrong results. Your app works fine in testing, then crashes randomly in production. Traditional tools like locks and semaphores help, but they're manual and error-prone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Concurrency amplifies the problem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The more concurrent your app is, the more likely data races become. A simple iOS app might get away with sloppy thread safety. A web server handling thousands of simultaneous requests will crash constantly. This is why Swift's compile-time safety matters most in high-concurrency environments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Shift: From Threads to Isolation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swift's concurrency model asks a different question. Instead of "which thread should this run on?", it asks: "who is allowed to access this data?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is isolation. Rather than manually dispatching work to threads, you declare boundaries around data. The compiler enforces these boundaries at build time, not runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Under the hood&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swift Concurrency is built on top of libdispatch (the same runtime as GCD). The difference is the compile-time layer: actors and isolation are enforced by the compiler, while the runtime handles scheduling on a cooperative thread pool limited to your CPU's core count.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Three Isolation Domains&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. MainActor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;@MainActor&lt;/code&gt; is a global actor that represents the main thread's isolation domain. It's special because UI frameworks (UIKit, AppKit, SwiftUI) require main thread access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@MainActor
class ViewModel {
    var items: [Item] = []  // Protected by MainActor isolation
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you mark something &lt;code&gt;@MainActor&lt;/code&gt;, you're not saying "dispatch this to the main thread." You're saying "this belongs to the main actor's isolation domain." The compiler enforces that anything accessing it must either be on MainActor or &lt;code&gt;await&lt;/code&gt; to cross the boundary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;When in doubt, use @MainActor&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For most apps, marking your ViewModels with &lt;code&gt;@MainActor&lt;/code&gt; is the right choice. Performance concerns are usually overblown. Start here, optimize only if you measure actual problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2. Actors&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An actor protects its own mutable state. It guarantees that only one piece of code can access its data at a time:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;actor BankAccount {
    var balance: Double = 0

    func deposit(_ amount: Double) {
        balance += amount  // Safe: actor guarantees exclusive access
    }
}

// From outside, you must await to cross the boundary
await account.deposit(100)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actors are not threads. An actor is an isolation boundary. The Swift runtime decides which thread actually executes actor code. You don't control that, and you don't need to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3. Nonisolated&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Code marked &lt;code&gt;nonisolated&lt;/code&gt; opts out of actor isolation. It can be called from anywhere without &lt;code&gt;await&lt;/code&gt;, but it cannot access the actor's protected state:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;actor BankAccount {
    var balance: Double = 0

    nonisolated func bankName() -&amp;gt; String {
        "Acme Bank"  // No actor state accessed, safe to call from anywhere
    }
}

let name = account.bankName()  // No await needed&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Approachable Concurrency: Less Friction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Approachable Concurrency simplifies the mental model with two Xcode build settings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;SWIFT_DEFAULT_ACTOR_ISOLATION&lt;/code&gt;=&lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt;: Everything runs on MainActor unless you say otherwise&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;SWIFT_APPROACHABLE_CONCURRENCY&lt;/code&gt;=&lt;code&gt;YES&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;code&gt;nonisolated&lt;/code&gt;async functions stay on the caller's actor instead of jumping to a background thread&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New Xcode 26 projects have both enabled by default. When you need CPU-intensive work off the main thread, use &lt;code&gt;@concurrent&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Runs on MainActor (the default)
func updateUI() async { }

// Runs on background thread (opt-in)
@concurrent func processLargeFile() async { }&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The Office Building&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think of your app as an office building. Each isolation domain is a private office with a lock on the door. Only one person can be inside at a time, working with the documents in that office.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt;is the front desk - where all customer interactions happen. There's only one, and it handles everything the user sees.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;actor&lt;/code&gt;types are department offices - Accounting, Legal, HR. Each protects its own sensitive documents.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;nonisolated&lt;/code&gt;code is the hallway - shared space anyone can walk through, but no private documents live there.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can't just barge into someone's office. You knock (&lt;code&gt;await&lt;/code&gt;) and wait for them to let you in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Can Cross Isolation Domains: Sendable&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Isolation domains protect data, but eventually you need to pass data between them. When you do, Swift checks if it's safe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think about it: if you pass a reference to a mutable class from one actor to another, both actors could modify it simultaneously. That's exactly the data race we're trying to prevent. So Swift needs to know: can this data be safely shared?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The answer is the &lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt; protocol. It's a marker that tells the compiler "this type is safe to pass across isolation boundaries":&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sendable types can cross safely (value types, immutable data, actors)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Non-Sendable types can't (classes with mutable state)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Sendable - it's a value type, each place gets a copy
struct User: Sendable {
    let id: Int
    let name: String
}

// Non-Sendable - it's a class with mutable state
class Counter {
    var count = 0  // Two places modifying this = disaster
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Making Types Sendable&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swift automatically infers &lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt; for many types:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Structs and enums with only &lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt;properties are implicitly&lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Actors are always &lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt;because they protect their own state&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;@MainActor&lt;/code&gt;types are&lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt;because MainActor serializes access&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For classes, it's harder. A class can conform to &lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt; only if it's &lt;code&gt;final&lt;/code&gt; and all its stored properties are immutable:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;final class APIConfig: Sendable {
    let baseURL: URL      // Immutable
    let timeout: Double   // Immutable
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have a class that's thread-safe through other means (locks, atomics), you can use &lt;code&gt;@unchecked Sendable&lt;/code&gt; to tell the compiler "trust me":&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;final class ThreadSafeCache: @unchecked Sendable {
    private let lock = NSLock()
    private var storage: [String: Data] = [:]
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;@unchecked Sendable is a promise&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The compiler won't verify thread safety. If you're wrong, you'll get data races. Use sparingly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Approachable Concurrency: Less Friction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Approachable Concurrency, Sendable errors become much rarer:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If code doesn't cross isolation boundaries, you don't need Sendable&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Async functions stay on the caller's actor instead of hopping to a background thread&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The compiler is smarter about detecting when values are used safely&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enable it by setting &lt;code&gt;SWIFT_DEFAULT_ACTOR_ISOLATION&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;SWIFT_APPROACHABLE_CONCURRENCY&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;YES&lt;/code&gt;. New Xcode 26 projects have both enabled by default. When you do need parallelism, mark functions &lt;code&gt;@concurrent&lt;/code&gt; and then think about Sendable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Photocopies vs. Original Documents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back to the office building. When you need to share information between departments:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Photocopies are safe - If Legal makes a copy of a document and sends it to Accounting, both have their own copy. They can scribble on them, modify them, whatever. No conflict.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Original signed contracts must stay put - If two departments could both modify the original, chaos ensues. Who has the real version?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt; types are like photocopies: safe to share because each place gets its own independent copy (value types) or because they're immutable (nobody can modify them). Non-&lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt; types are like original contracts: passing them around creates the potential for conflicting modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How Isolation Is Inherited&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You've seen that isolation domains protect data, and Sendable controls what crosses between them. But how does code end up in an isolation domain in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you call a function or create a closure, isolation flows through your code. With Approachable Concurrency, your app starts on &lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt;, and that isolation propagates to the code you call, unless something explicitly changes it. Understanding this flow helps you predict where code runs and why the compiler sometimes complains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Function Calls&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you call a function, its isolation determines where it runs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@MainActor func updateUI() { }      // Always runs on MainActor
func helper() { }                    // Inherits caller's isolation
@concurrent func crunch() async { }  // Explicitly runs off-actor&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Approachable Concurrency, most of your code inherits &lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt; isolation. The function runs where the caller runs, unless it explicitly opts out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Closures&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Closures inherit isolation from the context where they're defined:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@MainActor
class ViewModel {
    func setup() {
        let closure = {
            // Inherits MainActor from ViewModel
            self.updateUI()  // Safe, same isolation
        }
        closure()
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is why SwiftUI's &lt;code&gt;Button&lt;/code&gt; action closures can safely update &lt;code&gt;@State&lt;/code&gt;: they inherit MainActor isolation from the view.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Tasks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;Task { }&lt;/code&gt; inherits actor isolation from where it's created:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@MainActor
class ViewModel {
    func doWork() {
        Task {
            // Inherits MainActor isolation
            self.updateUI()  // Safe, no await needed
        }
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is usually what you want. The task runs on the same actor as the code that created it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Breaking Inheritance: Task.detached&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes you want a task that doesn't inherit any context:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@MainActor
class ViewModel {
    func doHeavyWork() {
        Task.detached {
            // No actor isolation, runs on cooperative pool
            let result = await self.expensiveCalculation()
            await MainActor.run {
                self.data = result  // Explicitly hop back
            }
        }
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Task.detached is usually wrong&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Swift team recommends Task.detached as a last resort. It doesn't inherit priority, task-local values, or actor context. Most of the time, regular &lt;code&gt;Task&lt;/code&gt; is what you want. If you need CPU-intensive work off the main actor, mark the function &lt;code&gt;@concurrent&lt;/code&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Walking Through the Building&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you're in the front desk office (MainActor), and you call someone to help you, they come to your office. They inherit your location. If you create a task ("go do this for me"), that assistant starts in your office too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only way someone ends up in a different office is if they explicitly go there: "I need to work in Accounting for this" (&lt;code&gt;actor&lt;/code&gt;), or "I'll handle this in the back office" (&lt;code&gt;@concurrent&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Putting It All Together&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's step back and see how all the pieces fit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swift Concurrency can feel like a lot of concepts: &lt;code&gt;async/await&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Task&lt;/code&gt;, actors, &lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt;, isolation domains. But there's really just one idea at the center of it all: isolation is inherited by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Approachable Concurrency enabled, your app starts on &lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt;. That's your starting point. From there:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Every function you call inherits that isolation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Every closure you create captures that isolation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Every &lt;code&gt;Task { }&lt;/code&gt;you spawn inherits that isolation&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don't have to annotate anything. You don't have to think about threads. Your code runs on &lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt;, and the isolation just propagates through your program automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you need to break out of that inheritance, you do it explicitly:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;@concurrent&lt;/code&gt;says "run this on a background thread"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;actor&lt;/code&gt;says "this type has its own isolation domain"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Task.detached { }&lt;/code&gt;says "start fresh, inherit nothing"&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And when you pass data between isolation domains, Swift checks that it's safe. That's what &lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt; is for: marking types that can safely cross boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's it. That's the whole model:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Isolation propagates from &lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt;through your code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You opt out explicitly when you need background work or separate state&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sendable guards the boundaries when data crosses between domains&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the compiler complains, it's telling you one of these rules was violated. Trace the inheritance: where did the isolation come from? Where is the code trying to run? What data is crossing a boundary? The answer is usually obvious once you ask the right question.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Where to Go From Here&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The good news: you don't need to master everything at once.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most apps only need the basics. Mark your ViewModels with &lt;code&gt;@MainActor&lt;/code&gt;, use &lt;code&gt;async/await&lt;/code&gt; for network calls, and create &lt;code&gt;Task { }&lt;/code&gt; when you need to kick off async work from a button tap. That's it. That handles 80% of real-world apps. The compiler will tell you if you need more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you need parallel work, reach for &lt;code&gt;async let&lt;/code&gt; to fetch multiple things at once, or &lt;code&gt;TaskGroup&lt;/code&gt; when the number of tasks is dynamic. Learn to handle cancellation gracefully. This covers apps with complex data loading or real-time features.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Advanced patterns come later, if ever. Custom actors for shared mutable state, &lt;code&gt;@concurrent&lt;/code&gt; for CPU-intensive processing, deep &lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt; understanding. This is framework code, server-side Swift, complex desktop apps. Most developers never need this level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Start simple&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don't optimize for problems you don't have. Start with the basics, ship your app, and add complexity only when you hit real problems. The compiler will guide you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Watch Out: Common Mistakes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Thinking async = background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// This STILL blocks the main thread!
@MainActor
func slowFunction() async {
    let result = expensiveCalculation()  // Synchronous work = blocking
    data = result
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;async&lt;/code&gt; means "can pause." The actual work still runs wherever it runs. Use &lt;code&gt;@concurrent&lt;/code&gt; (Swift 6.2) or &lt;code&gt;Task.detached&lt;/code&gt; for CPU-heavy work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Creating too many actors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Over-engineered
actor NetworkManager { }
actor CacheManager { }
actor DataManager { }

// Better - most things can live on MainActor
@MainActor
class AppState { }&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need a custom actor only when you have shared mutable state that can't live on &lt;code&gt;MainActor&lt;/code&gt;. Matt Massicotte's rule: introduce an actor only when (1) you have non-&lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt; state, (2) operations on that state must be atomic, and (3) those operations can't run on an existing actor. If you can't justify it, use &lt;code&gt;@MainActor&lt;/code&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Making everything Sendable&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not everything needs to cross boundaries. If you're adding &lt;code&gt;@unchecked Sendable&lt;/code&gt; everywhere, step back and ask if the data actually needs to move between isolation domains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Using MainActor.run when you don't need it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Unnecessary
Task {
    let data = await fetchData()
    await MainActor.run {
        self.data = data
    }
}

// Better - just make the function @MainActor
@MainActor
func loadData() async {
    self.data = await fetchData()
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;MainActor.run&lt;/code&gt; is rarely the right solution. If you need MainActor isolation, annotate the function with &lt;code&gt;@MainActor&lt;/code&gt; instead. It's clearer and the compiler can help you more. See Matt's take on this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Blocking the cooperative thread pool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// NEVER do this - risks deadlock
func badIdea() async {
    let semaphore = DispatchSemaphore(value: 0)
    Task {
        await doWork()
        semaphore.signal()
    }
    semaphore.wait()  // Blocks a cooperative thread!
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swift's cooperative thread pool has limited threads. Blocking one with &lt;code&gt;DispatchSemaphore&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;DispatchGroup.wait()&lt;/code&gt;, or similar calls can cause deadlocks. If you need to bridge sync and async code, use &lt;code&gt;async let&lt;/code&gt; or restructure to stay fully async.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Creating unnecessary Tasks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Unnecessary Task creation
func fetchAll() async {
    Task { await fetchUsers() }
    Task { await fetchPosts() }
}

// Better - use structured concurrency
func fetchAll() async {
    async let users = fetchUsers()
    async let posts = fetchPosts()
    await (users, posts)
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're already in an async context, prefer structured concurrency (&lt;code&gt;async let&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;TaskGroup&lt;/code&gt;) over creating unstructured &lt;code&gt;Task&lt;/code&gt;s. Structured concurrency handles cancellation automatically and makes the code easier to reason about.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Cheat Sheet: Quick Reference&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Keyword&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;What it does&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;async&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Function can pause&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;await&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pause here until done&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;Task { }&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Start async work, inherits context&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;Task.detached { }&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Start async work, no inherited context&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@MainActor&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Runs on main thread&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;actor&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Type with isolated mutable state&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;nonisolated&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Opts out of actor isolation&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;Sendable&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Safe to pass between isolation domains&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@concurrent&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Always run on background (Swift 6.2+)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;async let&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Start parallel work&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;TaskGroup&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Dynamic parallel work&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Further Reading&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Matt Massicotte's Blog (Highly Recommended)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A Swift Concurrency Glossary - Essential terminology&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;An Introduction to Isolation - The core concept&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When should you use an actor? - Practical guidance&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Non-Sendable types are cool too - Why simpler is better&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://fuckingapproachableswiftconcurrency.com/en/"/><published>2025-12-30T13:01:51+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46433029</id><title>no strpy either</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:16.938961+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="8202bb45bad1df9a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some time ago I mentioned that we went through the curl source code and eventually got rid of all &lt;code&gt;strncpy&lt;/code&gt;() calls.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;strncpy() is a weird function with a crappy API. It might not null terminate the destination and it pads the target buffer with zeroes. Quite frankly, most code bases are probably better off completely avoiding it because each use of it is a potential mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In that particular rewrite when we made strncpy calls extinct, we made sure we would either copy the full string properly or return error. It is rare that copying a partial string is the right choice, and if it is, we can just as well &lt;code&gt;memcpy&lt;/code&gt; it and handle the null terminator explicitly. This meant no case for using strlcpy or anything such either.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;But strcpy?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;strcpy however, has its valid uses and it has a less bad and confusing API. The main challenge with strcpy is that when using it we do not specify the length of the target buffer nor of the source string.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is normally not a problem because in a C program &lt;code&gt;strcpy&lt;/code&gt; should only be used when we have full control of both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But normally and always are not necessarily the same thing. We are but all human and we all do mistakes. Using strcpy implies that there is at least one or maybe two, buffer size checks done prior to the function invocation. In a good situation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over time however – let’s imagine we have code that lives on for decades – when code is maintained, patched, improved and polished by many different authors with different mindsets and approaches, those size checks and the function invoke may glide apart. The further away from each other they go, the bigger is the risk that something happens in between that nullifies one of the checks or changes the conditions for the strcpy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Enforce checks close to code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make sure that the size checks cannot be separated from the copy itself we introduced a string copy replacement function the other day that takes the target buffer, target size, source buffer and source string length as arguments and only if the copy can be made and the null terminator also fits there, the operation is done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This made it possible to implement the replacement using memcpy(). Now we can completely ban the use of strcpy in curl source code, like we already did strncpy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using this function version is a little more work and more cumbersome than strcpy since it needs more information, but we believe the upsides of this approach will help us have an oversight for the extra pain involved. I suppose we will see how that will fare down the road. Let’s come back in a decade and see how things developed!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;void curlx_strcopy(char *dest,&lt;lb/&gt;size_t dsize,&lt;lb/&gt;const char *src,&lt;lb/&gt;size_t slen)&lt;lb/&gt;{&lt;lb/&gt;DEBUGASSERT(slen &amp;lt; dsize);&lt;lb/&gt;if(slen &amp;lt; dsize) {&lt;lb/&gt;memcpy(dest, src, slen);&lt;lb/&gt;dest[slen] = 0;&lt;lb/&gt;}&lt;lb/&gt;else if(dsize)&lt;lb/&gt;dest[0] = 0;&lt;lb/&gt;}&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;AI slop&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An additional minor positive side-effect of this change is of course that this should effectively prevent the AI chatbots to report strcpy uses in curl source code and insist it is insecure if anyone would ask (as people still apparently do). It has been proven numerous times already that strcpy in source code is like a honey pot for generating hallucinated vulnerability claims.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, this will just make them find something else to make up a report about, so there is probably no net gain. AI slop is not a game we can win.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2025/12/29/no-strcpy-either/"/><published>2025-12-30T13:14:40+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46433035</id><title>Win32 is the stable Linux ABI</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:16.302207+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6d9f191ef947343c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The future of the Linux desktop can look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; I'd just like to interject for a moment. What you're refering to as Linux, is in fact, Win32/Linux, or as I've recently taken to calling it, &lt;del&gt;loss32&lt;/del&gt; Win32 plus Linux. Linux is not an operating system unto itself, but rather another free component of a fully functioning system made useful by WINE, the ReactOS userland, and other vital system components comprising a full OS as defined by Microsoft. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A dream of a Linux distribution where the entire desktop environment is Win32 software running under WINE. A completely free and open-source OS where you can just download .exe files and run them, for the power user who isn't necessarily a Unixhead, or just for someone who thinks this sounds fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ReactOS tries to reimplement the Windows NT kernel, and that has always been its Achilles heel, holding it back from a hardware compatibility and stability standpoint. The loss32 concept is to achieve a similar-feeling end result to ReactOS, but built on a more usable foundation, using components known to work well (the Linux kernel, WINE, everything that glues those together, and a sprinkling of ReactOS userland niceties). As a bonus, the OS would still technically be a Linux distro, so it would be possible to run Linux software when necessary, something ReactOS can't do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes. I can't tell you how many times the ability to just download a goddamn .exe file and run it in WINE has saved my ass. Seemingly every creative project I undertake eventually requires downloading some piece of software which is either impossible or impractical to rebuild myself, and whose Linux and macOS ports no longer work or never existed. There's more than three decades of Win32 software â .exe files! â that can run in WINE or (of course) on Windows. No other ABI has that kind of compatibility record. WINE can even run Win16 stuff too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The really cool thing about Win32 is it's also the world's stable ABI. There's lots of fields of software where the GNU/Linux and POSIX-y offerings available are quite limited and generally poor in quality, e.g. creative software and games. Win32 gives you access to a much larger slice of humanity's cultural inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes! That's just stable WINE running on Debian 13. There's a lot of rough edges you can't see in the screenshot that make it somewhat uncomfortable for use for the time being. The goal of the project is to fix many of the rough edges and package up this environment in an easily installable form.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for asking! This website was written by hikari_no_yume on 2025-12-29, who is currently at 39C3 (I'm usually at the assembly called â ask for me there!). You can email me, or you can lurk in #loss32 on irc.libera.chat. I'd especially like to hear from you if you know things about or would be willing to help with:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://loss32.org/"/><published>2025-12-30T13:15:05+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46433117</id><title>MH370 vanished in 2014.New search aims to find answers families desperately want</title><updated>2025-12-30T13:51:15.828038+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="34808a1206a1379a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;MH370 vanished in 2014. A new search aims to find answers families desperately want&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Malaysia Airlines flight MH370 took off from Kuala Lumpur heading for Beijing on March 8, 2014 — and vanished.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, nearly 12 years later, a new search is set to begin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is the new search likely to find new evidence more than a decade after the flight went missing? And with satellite technology how does a commercial aircraft disappear? This is what we know.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;'Goodnight, Malaysian three seven zero'&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The disappearance of flight MH370 with 239 people on board remains one of the world's most baffling aviation mysteries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Boeing 777 went missing on its way from Kuala Lumpur to Beijing on March 8, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were seven Australians, more than 150 Chinese and 50 Malaysians on the flight, as well as citizens of France, Indonesia, India, the United States, Ukraine and Canada.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Satellite data analysis showed the plane most likely crashed somewhere in the southern Indian Ocean, off the coast of Western Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, two major searches failed to come up with any significant findings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last radio transmission from the plane was about 40 minutes after it took off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Captain Zaharie Ahmad Shah signed off with "Goodnight, Malaysian three seven zero" as the plane entered Vietnamese airspace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Soon after, its transponder was turned off, which meant it could not be easily tracked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Military radar showed the plane left its planned flight path to fly back over northern Malaysia and Penang Island and then out into the Andaman Sea towards the tip of the Indonesian island of Sumatra.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It then turned south and all contact was lost.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Could new tech find lost jet?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A deep-sea hunt for the plane was planned to start on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The search will be carried out by US-based marine robotics company Ocean Infinity, which signed a new "no find, no fee" contract with the Malaysian government, which agreed to pay $100 million — but only if the wreckage is discovered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Charitha Pattiaratchi, a professor of coastal oceanography at the University of Western Australia, has been involved with the search for MH370 since 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ocean Infinity is expected to search for 55 days in a remote part of the southern Indian Ocean and will use technology that didn't exist during earlier attempts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Pattiaratchi told Radio National that Ocean Infinity had conducted a search several years ago from ship Seabed Constructor, using autonomous underwater vehicles to search parts of the seabed in the southern Indian Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Now they have gone up a notch ... and they have built new ships, which are much more efficient," he said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Also, the technology in the sonar and analysis has improved."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ocean Infinity will be searching for large pieces of debris, Professor Pattiaratchi said, like engines and other big, heavy parts of the aircraft that are more likely to still be intact.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It took almost 100 years to find the Titanic and they did know where it went down, so it is not an easy challenge," he said.&lt;/p&gt;Loading...&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How did earlier MH370 searches go?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Malaysia, Australia and China launched an underwater search of 120,000 square kilometres of the southern Indian Ocean, based on data from automatic connections between a satellite and the plane.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The search, which cost about $200 million, was called off after two years in January 2017, with no trace of the plane found.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Malaysia accepted a "no cure, no fee" offer from Ocean Infinity for a three-month search.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That search covered 112,000 square kilometres north of the original target area and also proved fruitless, ending in May 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What has been found?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 30 pieces of suspected aircraft debris have been collected along the coast of Africa and on islands in the Indian Ocean, but only three wing fragments were confirmed to be from MH370.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of the debris was used in drift pattern analysis in the hopes of narrowing down the aircraft's possible location.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A 495-page report into MH370's disappearance, published in July 2018, said the Boeing 777's controls were likely deliberately manipulated to take it off course, but investigators could not determine who was responsible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report also highlighted mistakes made by the Kuala Lumpur and Ho Chi Minh City air traffic control centres and issued recommendations to avoid a repeat incident.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Investigators stopped short of offering any conclusions about what happened to MH370, saying that it depended on finding the plane's wreckage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;MH370 conspiracy theories&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The inability to locate MH370's crash site has fuelled conspiracy theories ranging from mechanical error or a remote-controlled crash, to more bizarre explanations like an alien abduction, an organ-harvesting ring, a crash in the Cambodian jungle and a Russian plot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent years, some aviation experts have said the most likely explanation was that the plane was deliberately taken off course by an experienced pilot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But investigators have said there was nothing suspicious in the background, financial affairs, training and mental health of either captain Zaharie Shah or second pilot Fariq Abdul Hamid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neither had any apparent motive for intentionally taking the plane off course.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another theory was that Boeing had filed a US patent in February 2003 for a system that could remove all controls from pilots and allow remote operators to fly and land an aircraft at a predetermined location to foil hijacking attempts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But Boeing confirmed in 2018 it had never installed such a system on any aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In early 2018, when Ocean Infinity was searching for MH370 in the Indian Ocean, it also became the subject of a conspiracy after the Seabed Constructor turned off its Automatic Identification System for several days, preventing online observers from tracking its movements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No evidence of terrorism or fire has been found on any of the recovered debris and no terrorist group has claimed responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Theories about what happened range from hijacking to cabin depressurisation and power failure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was no distress call, no ransom demand, no evidence of technical failure or severe weather.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The families of the 239 people onboard Malaysia Airlines flight MH370 have been searching for answers since the plane went missing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ABC, Reuters&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-12-30/mh370-search-resumes-for-malaysia-airlines-missing-plane/106186962"/><published>2025-12-30T13:26:20+00:00</published></entry></feed>