<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:53.371299+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45600132</id><title>A magnetic field orientation that changes the fundamental design of motors</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:59.385514+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7969109f3031b5d3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;A Magnetic Field Orientation that Changes the Fundamental Design of Electric motors.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"/&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;ParaNetic magnet produces magnetic field distinctly different from traditional permanent or electromagnets. Unlike conventional magnets, which have a single north and south pole, a ParaNetic magnet features a unique polarity configuration: it can generate two north poles with a south pole sandwiched between them, or two south poles with a north pole in between. This is described as a "virtual" or "projected" magnet, meaning it’s not a physical object in the traditional sense but rather a magnetic field effect created by a specific arrangement of electromagnets or permanent magnets..&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The ParaNetic Magnet - A Deep Dive&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"/&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;This unusual three-pole structure allows the ParaNetic magnet to interact with magnetic fields in ways standard magnets cannot. For example, objects can pass completely through its magnetic field, including the transition points where the poles switch, which isn’t possible with typical magnets where these boundaries are internal. This property, along with the ability to link multiple ParaNetic magnets in linear or circular layouts, forms the basis for advanced applications like the ParaNetic electric motor.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"/&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;ParaNetic motors leverages both sides of the rotor and stator magnetic fields simultaneously, boosting efficiency, torque, and performance while reducing heat compared to conventional designs. The ParaNetic magnet’s design also enables unique functionalities, such as suspending permanent magnets at the polarity switch points with high precision, which has potential uses in valves, transducers, and even ion propulsion systems.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Learn More About The ParaNetic Magnetic Field&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h6"&gt;Demonstration of the ParaNetic Magnetic Field&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Demonstration of ParaNetic Magnetic Suspension&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Applications for the ParaNetic Magnetic Field&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Electric motors with improved efficiency, smaller size, better power-to-weight, and increased torque.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Miniaturized transducers - essentially turning today’s technology inside out.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Speakers with high fidelity in a micro footprint.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Linear acceleration such as carrier launch systems with significantly improved size and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Magnetic valves deliver very specific doses by eliminating friction and wear.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Extremely sensitive sensors for use in imaging and detection.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Magnetic brakes and bearings.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Magnetic springs and shock absorbers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;And many more applications.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The ParaNetic Motor and Magnet&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Electric motor has revolutionized countless industries by providing efficient and reliable propulsion. However, traditional electric motors often exhibit limitations in terms of their magnetic field configurations and utilization. In contrast, the ParaNetic electric motor and its associated ParaNetic magnet, offer unique characteristics and advantages that set them apart from conventional motor designs. The following explores the advantages of the ParaNetic electric motor and delves into the distinctive features of the ParaNetic magnet. THE THREE POLE MAGNET - Unlike the poles produced by an ordinary magnet, which consists of a single north and south pole, the ParaNetic magnet boasts a unique polarity configuration. It generates two north poles with a south pole sandwiched in-between, or alternatively, two south poles with a single north pole. This characteristic sets it apart from conventional magnets and opens new possibilities for motor design and functionality. LINEAR OR CIRCULAR LAYOUT - An unlimited number of ParaNetic magnets can be linked together in a straight line for linear motion, or in a circle to form the foundation of the ParaNetic motor. A VIRTUAL MAGNET - One of the unique differences of the ParaNetic magnet is the ability to pass an object completely through its magnetic fields, including the boundary points where the fields switch from one pole to another. This is not the case with either a permanent or electromagnet. THE PARANETIC ADVANTAGE - The most important advantage of the ParaNetic motor is its ability to utilize both sides of the rotor's and stator's magnetic fields simultaneously. By harnessing both sides of the fields at the same time, the ParaNetic motor achieves superior performance, increased torque output, produces less heat, and achieves enhanced efficiency. CAPTURE AND SUSPEND - Another Unique feature of the ParaNetic magnet is its remarkable ability to capture and suspend permanent magnets at the locations where these polarities switch. This property finds practical application in the creation of transducers, which is not covered in this presentation. FIVE -TO-ONE RATIO - The ParaNetic magnet harnesses the power of five individual electromagnets, interacting with one permanent magnet to generate rotational power. This stands in contrast to traditional permanent magnet motors that use a single electromagnet, interacting with a single permanent magnet. Because the ParaNetic magnet utilizes the combined power of five individual electromagnets, the amount of current needed to generate an equivalent magnetic field is reduced. By reducing the current flowing through the coils, the ParaNetic motor generates less heat, increasing the efficiency of the motor. In comparison, a rim drive motor, with its reliance on a single electromagnetic coil, interacting with a single permanent magnet, requires significantly higher currents, leading to increased heat production in the coils and decreased overall efficiency. HOLLOW-CORE PERMANENT MAGNET ROTOR - The rotor portion of the ParaNetic motor incorporates permanent magnets with hollow cores. These hollow cores serve a dual purpose. First, they allow the permanent magnet to be secured to the rotor portion of the motor, and second, they redistribute the strength of the magnetic field away from the middle of the magnet and towards the edges. As a result, the magnetic field of these permanent magnets are stronger at their edges where they pass closest to the five electromagnets. This distribution of the magnetic field to the edges enhances the ParaNetic motor's overall performance and ensures optimal utilization of the magnetic fields. SUMMARY - The ParaNetic motor and its associated ParaNetic magnet offer numerous advantages, as well as unique characteristics that set it apart from traditional electric motor designs. As motor technology continues to advance, the ParaNetic electric motor will stand at the forefront of innovation, offering a promising future for efficient and sustainable propulsion in many industries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How Does a Magnet Work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if you cut a bar magnet in half, you won't be able to remove its poles. It will only result in the production of two magnets, each of which will have a north pole that is attracted to the south pole of the other magnet, and vice versa. Magnets are beneficial for a wide variety of tasks due to their inherent quality of attraction, which explains why they may be attached to everything from a refrigerator to a party invitation to being used in medical imaging. But where do these polar opposites come from? What is the function of the magnet's north and south poles? Magnets are considered to be "one of the deepest mysteries in physics." Even though magnets have been used by humans for thousands of years, there are still many things that scientists do not understand about how they function. The movement of electrons provides the simplest explanation for why magnets have poles to attract and repel magnetic fields. Atoms are the fundamental building blocks of all matter, including magnets. The positively charged nucleus of every atom is encircled by one or more electrons, which have a negative charge. Every one of these electrons produces its very own little magnetic field, which is referred to by researchers as a "spin." When a sufficient number of these weak magnetic fields are aligned in the same direction, the substance in question will acquire its own magnetic properties. The concept of the "spin" of an electron can be considered somewhat conceptual. Since it is much too small to be visible even with a microscope, the spinning of an electron has never been observed by human eyes. However, physicists are aware that electrons possess a magnetic field due to the fact that they have measured it. Additionally, if the electron were spinning, this field might be formed as a result of its motion. If you were to change the direction that the spin was going, the magnetic field would also change. When it is conceivable, electrons will pair up so that their spins will cancel each other out, which will result in an atom having no overall magnetism. On the other hand, this cannot take place in some elements like iron. Because of the quantity of electrons and the way they are arranged around the nucleus, every iron atom will have at least one unpaired electron, which will result in the production of a very weak magnetic field. These separate magnetic fields are pointing in a variety of unpredictable directions within a substance that has not been magnetized. In that state, they largely nullify each other out, which results in the material not being magnetic as a whole. However, if the conditions are correct, the minuscule magnetic fields that exist at the subatomic level can align themselves so that they point in the same direction. One way to think about this is as the difference between a throng of people who are aimlessly meandering about and a mob of people who have organized themselves and are all looking the same direction. Because the accumulation of these extremely minute magnetic fields results in a larger magnetic field, the material in question transforms into a magnet. Permanent magnets include a significant portion of the magnets utilized in day-to-day life, such as those found on refrigerators. Because of some external force, the magnetic fields of many of the atoms that make up the material have become permanently aligned in these materials. For example, this could have occurred as a result of the material being placed inside of a more intense magnetic field. Electricity is typically responsible for producing those more intense magnetic fields. Because magnetic fields are produced by the motion of electrical charges, electricity and magnetism are inextricably bound together at their most fundamental level. Because of this, an electron that is spinning will have a magnetic field. However, scientists also have the ability to harness electricity in order to produce extremely potent magnets. When a sufficient amount of current is passed through a coil of wire, a highly powerful magnetic field is produced, which continues to exist for as long as the current is flowing. In the field of physics research, these electromagnets are frequently utilized. In addition to that, you can find them in medical equipment like magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) devices. The planet also possesses its very own magnetic field, which is what allows a compass needle to point in the right direction. The end of a magnet that, if it were allowed to spin freely, would point toward the north pole of the earth is what scientists mean when they refer to the north pole of a magnet. However, from a more scientific point of view, this indicates that the magnetic north pole on Earth is actually the magnetic south pole because like poles attract and opposing poles repel. It is generally accepted in the field of physics that the lines of the magnetic field create a complete loop by flowing forth from the north pole of the magnet and back into the south pole of the magnet. Physicists have also discovered alternative configurations of magnetic poles, such as quadrupoles, in which both north and south magnetic poles are combined and organized in a square pattern. But there is still a challenge to overcome: no one has yet discovered a magnetic monopole. Electrons and protons are examples of electric monopoles, which means that each of these subatomic particles carries only a single electric charge, which can be either positive or negative. However, electrons and other particles share a characteristic in that they have two magnetic poles. The fact that they are fundamental particles also means that they cannot be subdivided any further. This disparity between the way particles act electrically and magnetically has piqued the interest of a great deal of scientists, and some of them view the discovery of a particle that possesses a single magnetic pole as the holy grail of their field. The physical rules that we currently comprehend could be called into question if this phenomenon was discovered.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The ParaNetic Magnetic Field&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Did you know that magnets play a crucial role in the development of next-generation electric aircraft? As the aviation industry embraces the shift toward sustainable propulsion, next-generation electric motors have emerged as a key technology for powering these aircraft. The electric motor offers numerous advantages over traditional combustion engines, including higher efficiency, reduced emissions, and quieter operation. Magnets, in particular, are key to building these electric motors, and until recently, every magnet has had a single north and south pole. The configuration of magnets within a motor plays a vital role in its performance and the arrangement of the magnets within the rotor and stator determines the motor's speed, efficiency, and torque output. Engineers strive to optimize these magnetic fields to ensure the smooth and efficient operation of a motor. The recent discovery of the ParaNetic magnet opens up a wide number of exciting possibilities in designing next-generation electric motors for aircraft. The unique polarity configuration of the ParaNetic magnet, with two north poles and a sandwiched south pole (or vice versa), offers distinct advantages over the single north and south pole magnet. The major advantage of the ParaNetic magnet lies in its ability to utilize both sides of the rotor's and stator's magnetic fields simultaneously. This results in increased torque, reduced heat generation, and higher efficiency compared to motor designs using conventional magnets. In the context of electric aircraft, the importance of magnets in electric motors cannot be overstated. They contribute to the lightweight and efficient design of the motors, ultimately impacting the aircraft's performance and range. By harnessing the power of magnets and incorporating innovative magnet technologies like the ParaNetic magnet, engineers can push the boundaries of these next-generation electric motors, enabling more efficient and sustainable aviation. As electric aircraft technology continues to evolve, ongoing research and development efforts are focused on optimizing motor design, improving manufacturing, and refining rotor/stator configurations to maximize efficiency and power output. In Conclusion: As advancements in magnet technology like the ParaNetic magnet continue, electric aircraft will benefit from the development of next-generation, high-performing electric motors, paving the way for a cleaner and more sustainable aviation industry. To see a demo of the ParaNetic magnet drop us a note.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The ParaNetic Motor&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ParaNetics Electric Motor: Revolutionizing Electric Propulsion In the ever-evolving world of electric propulsion, ParaNetics has emerged as a game-changer with its innovative electric motor technology. The ParaNetics electric motor, powered by the unique ParaNetic magnetic field, promises to revolutionize the way we think about electric motors and their applications in various industries, including aviation, automotive, and submersibles. The ParaNetic Magnetic Field: A Breakthrough in Magnetics At the heart of the ParaNetics electric motor is the ParaNetic magnetic field, a groundbreaking discovery that sets it apart from traditional magnetic fields. Unlike conventional permanent magnets, which have a single north and south pole, the ParaNetic magnet is a “projected” or “virtual magnet” with two north poles and a single south pole sandwiched in between1. This unique configuration allows for a more efficient and powerful magnetic field, which is crucial for the performance of electric motors. How the ParaNetic Motor Works The ParaNetic motor leverages this unique magnetic field to create a highly efficient and powerful electric motor. Traditional electric motors, whether brushed, brushless, or induction, typically use only one side of the magnetic field generated by their electromagnets. In contrast, the ParaNetic motor uses both sides of the electromagnet’s field simultaneously. When an electromagnet is placed between two ParaNetic magnets, one side of the electromagnet attracts while the other repels, creating a powerful and efficient motor1. This dual interaction between the electromagnet and the ParaNetic magnetic fields allows for significant improvements in motor design and performance. The ability to use both sides of the magnetic field simultaneously results in higher torque and efficiency, making the ParaNetic motor an ideal choice for various applications. Applications of the ParaNetic Motor The versatility of the ParaNetic motor makes it suitable for a wide range of applications. Here are some of the key areas where this innovative motor technology is making an impact: 1. Electric Aircraft The aviation industry is constantly seeking ways to reduce its carbon footprint and improve efficiency. The ParaNetic motor offers a promising solution with its high torque and efficiency, making it an ideal choice for electric aircraft. The unique magnetic field configuration allows for more powerful and efficient propulsion systems, which can significantly enhance the performance of electric aircraft2. 2. Submersibles Submersibles require powerful and efficient motors to navigate underwater environments. The ParaNetic motor’s ability to use both sides of the magnetic field simultaneously makes it an excellent choice for submersible applications. Its high torque and efficiency can improve the performance and reliability of submersibles, making them more effective in various underwater tasks2. 3. Automotive Industry The automotive industry is rapidly transitioning towards electric vehicles (EVs) to reduce emissions and improve efficiency. The ParaNetic motor’s unique design and high efficiency make it a perfect fit for EVs. Its ability to generate high torque with minimal energy consumption can enhance the performance and range of electric vehicles, making them more appealing to consumers3. The Future of Electric Propulsion The ParaNetics electric motor represents a significant advancement in electric propulsion technology. Its unique magnetic field configuration and ability to use both sides of the magnetic field simultaneously set it apart from traditional electric motors. As industries continue to seek more efficient and powerful propulsion systems, the ParaNetic motor is poised to play a crucial role in shaping the future of electric propulsion. With its potential to revolutionize the aviation, automotive, and submersible industries, the ParaNetic motor is a testament to the power of innovation and the endless possibilities of magnetic technology. As ParaNetics continues to develop and refine this groundbreaking motor, we can expect to see even more exciting advancements in the world of electric propulsion. In conclusion, the ParaNetics electric motor is not just a technological marvel; it is a glimpse into the future of electric propulsion. Its unique design and unparalleled efficiency make it a game-changer in the industry, and its potential applications are vast and varied. As we move towards a more sustainable and efficient future, the ParaNetic motor will undoubtedly play a pivotal role in driving this transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Advantages of the ParaNetic Motor&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ParaNetic Motor: A Leap Forward in Electric Motor Technology In the realm of electric motor innovation, the ParaNetic motor, developed by ParaNetics, is making waves with its groundbreaking design and efficiency. This motor introduces a novel approach to generating rotational force, promising significant advancements in performance and energy efficiency. Harnessing the Power of Multiple Electromagnets The core of the ParaNetic motor’s innovation lies in its ParaNetic Field Projector. Unlike traditional Rim Drive motors that use a single electromagnetic coil interacting with a single permanent magnet, the ParaNetic motor employs five electromagnets working in unison with a single permanent magnet. This configuration creates a more powerful and efficient rotational force, setting a new standard in motor technology. Enhanced Efficiency with Lower Current and Less Heat One of the most compelling advantages of the ParaNetic motor is its ability to generate a strong magnetic field with significantly less current. By combining the power of five electromagnets into one cohesive magnetic field, the motor requires less current, which translates to less heat generation. This reduction in heat not only boosts the motor’s efficiency but also enhances its longevity, making it a highly reliable option for various applications. Innovative Hollow Core Magnet Design The ParaNetic motor features a unique hollow core design for its permanent magnets. This design pushes the magnetic force to the edges of the magnet, closer to the five electromagnets. The hollow core serves two essential purposes: it secures the magnet to the rotor and redistributes the magnetic field strength from the center to the edges. This strategic redistribution maximizes the interaction between the permanent magnet and the electromagnets, resulting in a more efficient motor. Unique Magnetic Field Configuration The parabolic orientation of the five electromagnets in the ParaNetic Field Projector allows their fields to combine, creating a unique magnetic field. This field can consist of two north poles with a south pole in the middle, or two south poles with a north pole in the middle, depending on the direction of the current flow. This flexibility in magnetic field configuration provides greater control over the motor’s operation, optimizing performance under various conditions. Dual-Sided Magnetic Field Utilization A standout feature of the ParaNetic motor is its ability to utilize both sides of the rotor and stator magnetic fields simultaneously. This dual-sided approach enables the motor to push and pull at the same time, significantly enhancing its torque output and overall performance. This capability sets the ParaNetic motor apart from traditional motors, making it a superior choice for demanding applications. Versatility in Design The ParaNetic Ver 6 motor takes versatility to the next level by incorporating three separate motors into a single unit. This design eliminates the need for multiple motors to be mounted on each corner of a quadcopter, simplifying the overall design and reducing weight. This innovation makes the ParaNetic motor an ideal choice for applications requiring compact and efficient motor solutions. In conclusion, the ParaNetic motor represents a significant leap forward in electric motor technology. Its innovative design and unique magnetic field configuration offer numerous advantages, including higher efficiency, lower heat generation, and enhanced performance. As industries continue to seek more efficient and reliable motor solutions, the ParaNetic motor is poised to become a game-changer in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.paranetics.com/copy-of-home"/><published>2025-10-16T00:29:11+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45617948</id><title>Show HN: I'm making a detective game built on Wikipedia</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:59.229641+00:00</updated><link href="https://detective.wiki/"/><published>2025-10-17T15:34:04+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45621557</id><title>Code from MIT's 1986 SICP video lectures</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:58.673843+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a5619a2afc97f391"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT lectures on Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs, as taught in 1986 by Gerald Sussman and Harold Abelson, are available online in youtube and MIT OCW's website. The videos are available in 240p/360p: very poor quality for visualizing the code in the slides. In addition to that, the camera won't fixate on the board for long, making it extremely difficult to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project's intent is to make the lectures' code and content readable (unlike the slide below) and available in digital format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried to maintain consistency of notation, comments and indentation throughout the lectures. Much of the original indentation on the slides was maintained, except for when I was able to improve readability by changing it. Lecture breaks are also noted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every &lt;code&gt;SLIDE&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;TERMINAL&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;BOARD&lt;/code&gt; content is marked with the time of appearance. E.g.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;;# SLIDE 0:00:00
    ... slide content
;# END SLIDE
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I have added comments and remarks throughout the code to help comprehension.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Though all files have extension .scm, their content represent a literal transcription of the slides, some of which isn't code. They're expected to fail to compile in all Scheme interpreters.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I have fixed the code on a few, rare occasions. In all of them I've noted the correction using a colon followed by an exclamation mark. Notice that ';!' was also used, once or twice, in the lecture slides.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;it's clearly readable&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;it's not code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;its content isn't "textable"&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Standardize syntax and style across the transcription files.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/felipap/sicp-code"/><published>2025-10-17T20:18:54+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45623509</id><title>Results from blood test for 50 cancers</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:58.564267+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bfeba1279a839e42"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Exciting results from blood test for 50 cancers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A blood test for more than 50 types of cancer could help speed up diagnosis, according to a new study.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Results of a trial in North America show that the test was able to identify a wide range of cancers, of which three-quarters don't have any form of screening programme.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More than half the cancers were detected at an early stage, where they are easier to treat and potentially curable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Galleri test, made by American pharmaceutical firm Grail, can detect fragments of cancerous DNA that have broken off a tumour and are circulating in the blood. It is currently being trialled by the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trial followed 25,000 adults from the US and Canada over a year, with nearly one in 100 getting a positive result. For 62% of these cases, cancer was later confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lead researcher Dr Nima Nabavizadeh, associate professor of radiation medicine at Oregon Health &amp;amp; Science University, said the data showed that the test could "fundamentally change" their approach to cancer screening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He explained that it could help detect many types of cancer "earlier, when the chance of successful treatment or even cure are the greatest".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The test correctly ruled out cancer in over 99% of those who tested negative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When combined with breast, bowel, lung and cervical screening it increased the number of cancers detected overall seven-fold.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Crucially, three-quarters of cancers detected were those which have no screening programme such as ovarian, liver, stomach, bladder and pancreatic cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The blood test correctly identified the origin of the cancer in nine out of 10 cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These impressive results suggest the blood test could eventually have a major role to play in diagnosing cancer earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But scientists not involved in the research say more evidence is needed to show whether the blood test reduces deaths from cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clare Turnbull, professor of translational cancer genetics at The Institute of Cancer Research, London, said: "Data from randomised studies, with mortality as an endpoint, will be absolutely essential to establish whether seemingly earlier-stage detection by Galleri translates into benefits in mortality."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The topline results are to be released at the European Society for Medical Oncology congress in Berlin on Saturday, but the full details have yet to be published in a peer-reviewed journal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Much will depend on the results of a three-year trial involving 140,000 NHS patients in England, which will be published next year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The NHS has previously said that if the results are successful, it would extend the tests to a further one million people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sir Harpal Kumar, president of biopharma at Grail called the results "very compelling".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking to BBC Radio 4's Today programme, he said: "The vast majority of people who die from cancer do so because we find their cancers too late."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many cancers are found when they are "already very advanced" he added, explaining that the aim is to "shift to earlier detection, when we have the chance to use treatments that are much more effective and potentially curative".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Naser Turabi of Cancer Research UK cautioned that further research is needed to "avoid overdiagnosing cancers that may not have caused harm".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The UK National Screening Committee will "play a critical role in reviewing the evidence and determining whether these tests should be adopted by the NHS," he added.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c205g21n1zzo"/><published>2025-10-17T23:54:40+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45632429</id><title>A laser pointer at 2B FPS [video]</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:57.852677+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7055905545553646"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Press Copyright Contact us Creators Advertise Developers Terms Privacy Policy &amp;amp; Safety How YouTube works Test new features NFL Sunday Ticket © 2025 Google LLC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o4TdHrMi6do"/><published>2025-10-19T06:42:19+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45640226</id><title>Space Elevator</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:57.746591+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://neal.fun/space-elevator/"/><published>2025-10-20T04:42:08+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45640838</id><title>AWS multiple services outage in us-east-1</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:57.300487+00:00</updated><link href="https://health.aws.amazon.com/health/status?ts=20251020"/><published>2025-10-20T07:22:28+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45643163</id><title>Alibaba Cloud says it cut Nvidia AI GPU use by 82% with new pooling system</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:57.105754+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="69989c3d8f16dad1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Alibaba Cloud says it cut Nvidia AI GPU use by 82% with new pooling system— up to 9x increase in output lets 213 GPUs perform like 1,192&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A paper presented at SOSP 2025 details how token-level scheduling helped one GPU serve multiple LLMs, reducing demand from 1,192 to 213 H20s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alibaba Cloud claims its new Aegaeon pooling system reduces the number of Nvidia GPUs required to serve large language models by 82% during a multi-month beta test inside its Model Studio marketplace. The result, published in a peer-reviewed paper presented at the 2025 ACM Symposium on Operating Systems (SOSP) in Seoul, suggests that cloud providers may be able to extract significantly more inference capacity from existing silicon, especially in constrained markets like China, where the supply of Nvidia's latest H20s remains limited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike training-time breakthroughs that chase model quality or speed, Aegaeon is an inference-time scheduler designed to maximize GPU utilization across many models with bursty or unpredictable demand. Instead of pinning one accelerator to one model, Aegaeon virtualizes GPU access at the token level, allowing it to schedule tiny slices of work across a shared pool. This means one H20 could serve several different models simultaneously, with system-wide “goodput” — a measure of effective output — rising by as much as nine times compared to older serverless systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The system was tested in production over several months, according to the paper, which lists authors from both Peking University and Alibaba’s infrastructure division, including CTO Jingren Zhou. During that window, the number of GPUs needed to support dozens of different LLMs — ranging in size up to 72 billion parameters — fell from 1,192 to just 213.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the paper does not break down which models contributed most to the savings, reporting by the South China Morning Post says the tests were conducted using Nvidia’s H20, one of the few accelerators still legally available to Chinese buyers under current U.S. export controls.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alibaba says the gains came from two main techniques: Packing multiple models per GPU, and using a token-level autoscaler to dynamically allocate compute as output is generated, rather than reserving resources at the request level. In benchmarks, Aegaeon beat the goodput of ServerlessLLM and MuxServe by margins ranging from 1.5 times to 9 times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether those savings translate outside Alibaba’s stack remains to be seen. Alibaba Cloud’s paper does not specify the exact network fabric used in the beta test, but we know the company offers its own eRDMA elastic RDMA network and has a record of building highly‑integrated GPU serving stacks, suggesting the results may depend on an optimized, vertically integrated environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless, the result is likely to attract interest from other hyperscalers looking to stretch scarce accelerator fleets as inference demand continues to spike.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow Tom's Hardware on Google News, or add us as a preferred source, to get our latest news, analysis, &amp;amp; reviews in your feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Luke James is a freelance writer and journalist. Although his background is in legal, he has a personal interest in all things tech, especially hardware and microelectronics, and anything regulatory.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.tomshardware.com/tech-industry/semiconductors/alibaba-says-new-pooling-system-cut-nvidia-gpu-use-by-82-percent"/><published>2025-10-20T12:31:22+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45644328</id><title>BERT is just a single text diffusion step</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:56.958254+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="35106edd82bc1c52"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A while back, Google DeepMind unveiled Gemini Diffusion, an experimental language model that generates text using diffusion. Unlike traditional GPT-style models that generate one word at a time, Gemini Diffusion creates whole blocks of text by refining random noise step-by-step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I read the paper Large Language Diffusion Models and was surprised to find that discrete language diffusion is just a generalization of masked language modeling (MLM), something we’ve been doing since 2018. The first thought I had was, “can we finetune a BERT-like model to do text generation?” I decided to try a quick proof of concept out of curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;NOTE: After I wrote the article I stumbled upon the paper DiffusionBERT which does essentially the same thing but with more rigorous testing! Check it out if this post interested you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Short History of Transformers#&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The original Transformer architecture, introduced in 2017, was an encoder-decoder model. In 2018, researchers realized that the encoder and decoder components of the model could be separated (with the advent of BERT and GPT), and two distinct families of models were created:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Encoder-only models (BERT-style, bidirectional)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Encoder models used masked language modeling (MLM) as a training objective: randomly mask out a subset of tokens of each input and train the encoder to reconstruct the missing tokens (fill in the blanks). The model sees the entire (partially masked) context at once and learns bidirectional representations. This architecture excelled at tasks requiring a full‐sentence (or paragraph) representation (e.g., classification and retrieval).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Decoder-only models (GPT-style, autoregressive)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decoder models used next‐token prediction as a training objective: at each position $t$, predict the token at position $t + 1$ given all tokens up to $t$ as context. Only the left context is used to predict future values (unidirectional). This architecture excelled at generative tasks where you produce text one token at a time, such as open‐ended generation, summarization, and translation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originally, BERT saw immediate use in tasks such as classification, whereas GPT-style models didn’t become popular until later (due to initial limited capabilities). Eventually, the generation capabilities of autoregressive (decoder) transformers vastly improved. The general training objective of “next token prediction” means a much larger space of use cases when compared to encoder models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Discrete Language Diffusion Models#&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Diffusion models were first popularized in image generation. In image generation, diffusion models gradually add Gaussian noise to an image (forward process) and then train a neural network to iteratively denoise it (reverse process). A high‐level summary of continuous diffusion with images is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Forward process: Start from a clean image x₀, then add small amounts of (usually Gaussian) noise at each timestep until you end up with near‐pure noise.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reverse process: Train a model (often a U‐Net) to predict the noise at each timestep, gradually recovering the original image in discrete denoising steps.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applying this idea to language means we need a way to add noise to text and then remove it in stages. The simplest way to do this is a masking‐based noise process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Forward (masking) process:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;At timestep t = 0, you have a fully uncorrupted text sequence.&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;At each subsequent timestep t &amp;gt; 0, randomly replace a fraction of tokens with a special &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;token according to a pre‐defined schedule (e.g., gradually increasing the masked proportion from 0% to 100%).&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;By the final timestep T, the entire sequence may be masked (all tokens are &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Reverse (denoising) process:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Train a model (often a standard Transformer encoder) to predict the original token IDs given a partially masked sequence at timestep t.&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;This is akin to performing masked language modeling at varying mask rates: at early timesteps, only a few tokens are masked (easy to predict); at later timesteps, many tokens are masked (harder).&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;By chaining together predictions from high‐mask‐rate back down to zero, you can recover (or generate) a full sequence.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this discrete text diffusion framework, the model learns a likelihood bound on the data distribution by optimizing a sum of denoising losses over all timesteps, rather than a single MLM objective at a fixed mask probability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we can see, BERT’s masked language modeling objective is the same training objective as text diffusion, but just for a subset of masking rates. By introducing variable masking rates (from 0 to 1) and a scheduled sequence of denoising steps (inspired by diffusion theory), we can transform BERT’s masked language modeling objective into a full generative procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;RoBERTa Diffusion#&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2019, RoBERTa was released. It was essentially just an enhancement of the original BERT model, with better hyperparameters, data training size, and a more simple training objective (MLM only, removed next sentence prediction).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here we use the HuggingFace &lt;code&gt;transformers&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dataset&lt;/code&gt; libraries to pull in the original RoBERTa weights, tokenizer, and the Trainer class to easily finetune the model on the WikiText dataset.
The main code (full code here) looks like this below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Load and tokenize dataset and instantiate the model
dataset = load_dataset("wikitext", "wikitext-2-raw-v1")
tokenizer = RobertaTokenizerFast.from_pretrained("roberta-base")
model = RobertaForMaskedLM.from_pretrained("roberta-base")

# Create the training args and Trainer instance
training_args = TrainingArguments(
    output_dir="finetuned-roberta-diffusion",
    overwrite_output_dir=True,
    num_train_epochs=NUM_EPOCHS,
    per_device_train_batch_size=BATCH_SIZE,
    save_strategy="epoch",
    save_total_limit=1,
    logging_steps=200,
)

trainer = Trainer(
    model=model,
    args=training_args,
    train_dataset=tokenized["train"],
    eval_dataset=tokenized["validation"],
    data_collator=diffusion_collator, # custom implementation
    tokenizer=tokenizer,
)

# Train &amp;amp; save
trainer.train()
trainer.save_model("finetuned-roberta-diffusion")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently we have 10 diffusion steps, so we randomly sample a percentage $p$ out of &lt;code&gt;mask_probs&lt;/code&gt; (1.0, 0.9, 0.9, &amp;amp;mldr;, 0.1) and mask that percent of the tokens each batch.
The custom &lt;code&gt;diffusion_collator&lt;/code&gt; function (see code here) samples one mask-probability &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;mask_probs&lt;/code&gt; per batch and sets each token to &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; probability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be able to condition the generation on a “prompt”, we currently never mask the first 16 tokens. That means that during training, each step will always have the first 16 tokens as context for generation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simplified code for the &lt;code&gt;diffusion_collator&lt;/code&gt; looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;  def diffusion_collator(examples):
      batch = tokenizer.pad(examples, return_tensors="pt")

      # Randomly select masking probability for this batch
      mask_prob = random.choice([1.0, 0.9, 0.8, 0.7, 0.6, 0.5, 0.4, 0.3, 0.2, 0.1])

      # Never mask the first PREFIX_LEN tokens (preserved context)
      maskable_positions = batch.input_ids[:, PREFIX_LEN:]

      # Create random mask for the chosen probability
      mask = torch.rand(maskable_positions.shape) &amp;lt; mask_prob

      # Apply masking
      batch.input_ids[:, PREFIX_LEN:][mask] = tokenizer.mask_token_id
      batch.labels = batch.input_ids.clone()

      return batch&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For inference, we start with an input which is a tensor of size 256 (since we are generating blocks of 256 tokens). The first 16 positions are the token ids that correspond to the prompt, and the last 240 are just &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tokens. We iterate through the denoising schedule and each step, we generate a prediction and then remask the sequence again. The process looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Step 0: [PREFIX] &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; ...     (100% masked)
Step 1: [PREFIX] will &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; over &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; control ...        (90% masked)
Step 2: [PREFIX] will begin &amp;lt;mask&amp;gt; greater control ...      (80% masked)
...
Step 10: [PREFIX] will begin to assert greater control ...  (0% masked - DONE)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simplified code for generation looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Generate text through iterative denoising
for step, mask_prob in enumerate(mask_probs):
    # Forward pass: predict masked tokens
    with torch.no_grad():
        outputs = model(input_ids=input_ids, attention_mask=attention_mask)
        predictions = outputs.logits  # shape: (1, MAX_LEN, vocab_size)

    # For each masked position, sample from top-k/top-p filtered distribution
    for pos in range(PREFIX_LEN, MAX_LEN):
        if input_ids[0, pos] == tokenizer.mask_token_id:
            logits = predictions[0, pos, :]
            # Apply top-k and top-p filtering
            filtered_logits = top_k_top_p_filtering(logits, top_k=TOP_K, top_p=TOP_P)
            probs = F.softmax(filtered_logits, dim=-1)
            # Sample token
            sampled_token = torch.multinomial(probs, 1)
            input_ids[0, pos] = sampled_token

    # Re-mask a portion of non-prefix tokens for next iteration
    if mask_prob &amp;gt; 0:
        mask_indices = torch.rand(MAX_LEN - PREFIX_LEN) &amp;lt; mask_prob
        input_ids[0, PREFIX_LEN:][mask_indices] = tokenizer.mask_token_id&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is an example output generation of the fine-tuned model after training on an H200 for 30 minutes (the first line is the initial prompt):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Following their victory in the French and Indian War, Britain began to assert
greater...

...dominion over Europe beginning about the early 19th. There conflict took
place on the island, between British and Irish Ireland. British officials 
administered British Ireland, a Celtic empire under the control of the Irish 
nationalist authorities, defined as a dominion of Britain. As the newly Fortic 
states acquired independent and powerful status, many former English colonies
played their part in this new, British @-@ controlled colonial system. Following
this period the Non @-@ Parliamentaryist Party won its influence in Britain in 
1890, led by the support of settlers from the Irish colonies. Looking inwards, 
Sinclair, Lewis questioned, and debated the need to describe " The New Britain "&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The output looks surprisingly coherent! Most of the quirks present are actually just quirks from the formatting of WikiText (spaces around punctuation &lt;code&gt;"&lt;/code&gt;, turning hyphens &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt; into &lt;code&gt;@-@&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below is a comparison between our diffusion model and GPT-2:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We see GPT-2’s output is more coherent and slightly faster (~9 seconds vs ~13) but I’m pleasantly surprised with how good my simple implementation was. It is a good proof of concept, and with new approaches like AR-Diffusion and Skip-Step Diffusion (and a more optimized implementation), the quality and speed can be drastically improved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion#&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve seen that masked language models like RoBERTa, originally designed for fill-in-the-blank tasks, can be repurposed into fully generative engines by interpreting variable-rate masking as a discrete diffusion process. By gradually corrupting text with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;MASK&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tokens and training the model to iteratively denoise at increasing mask intensities, we effectively turn the standard MLM objective into a step-by-step generation procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even without architectural changes, a fine-tuned RoBERTa can generate coherent looking text after slightly modifying the training objective, validating the idea that BERT-style models are essentially just text diffusion models trained on one masking rate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://nathan.rs/posts/roberta-diffusion/"/><published>2025-10-20T14:31:16+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45645120</id><title>Show HN: I created a cross-platform GUI for the JJ VCS (Git compatible)</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:56.690519+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="10bd79eb74913531"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Releases Roadmap JUDO The full-featured GUI for JJ VCS (works with Git repos too!) macOS Download for macOS Windows Download for Windows Linux (Ubuntu/Debian) Download for Linux Restore your repo to any point in time with the Operation Log. Undo and redo any change. View combined diffs of multiple commits, or the diff between commits Apply or revert hunks of any diff, files, commits, or even multiple commits at once Use custom revsets to select which commits are shown. Filter by descriptions, authors, ancestry, and more. Drag and drop rebase Duplicate, split, abandon, revert, absorb, squash, and more Keep your bookmarks managed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://judojj.com"/><published>2025-10-20T15:35:19+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45645349</id><title>Production RAG: what I learned from processing 5M+ documents</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:56.449011+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9bf95f134d9a6771"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've spent the last 8 months in the RAG trenches, I want to share what actually worked vs. wasted our time. We built RAG for Usul AI (9M pages) and an unnamed legal AI enterprise (4M pages).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Langchain + Llamaindex&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We started out with youtube tutorials. First Langchain → Llamaindex. Got to a working prototype in a couple of days and were optimistic with the progress. We run tests on subset of the data (100 documents) and the results looked great. We spent the next few days running the pipeline on the production dataset and got everything working in a week — incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Except it wasn't, the results were subpar and only the end users could tell. We spent the following few months rewriting pieces of the system, one at a time, until the performance was at the level we wanted. Here are things we did ranked by ROI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What moved the needle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Query Generation: not all context can be captured by the user's last query. We had an LLM review the thread and generate a number of semantic + keyword queries. We processed all of those queries in parallel, and passed them to a reranker. This made us cover a larger surface area and not be dependent on a computed score for hybrid search.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reranking: the highest value 5 lines of code you'll add. The chunk ranking shifted a lot. More than you'd expect. Reranking can many times make up for a bad setup if you pass in enough chunks. We found the ideal reranker set-up to be 50 chunk input -&amp;gt; 15 output.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chunking Strategy: this takes a lot of effort, you'll probably be spending most of your time on it. We built a custom flow for both enterprises, make sure to understand the data, review the chunks, and check that a) chunks are not getting cut mid-word or sentence b) ~each chunk is a logical unit and captures information on its own&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metadata to LLM: we started by passing the chunk text to the LLM, we ran an experiment and found that injecting relevant metadata as well (title, author, etc.) improves context and answers by a lot.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Query routing: many users asked questions that can't be answered by RAG (e.g. summarize the article, who wrote this). We created a small router that detects these questions and answers them using an API call + LLM instead of the full-blown RAG set-ups.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Our stack&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vector database: Azure -&amp;gt; Pinecone -&amp;gt; Turbopuffer (cheap, supports keyword search natively)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Document Extraction: Custom&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chunking: Unstructured.io by default, custom for enterprises (heard that Chonkie is good)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Embedding: text-embedding-large-3, haven't tested others&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reranker: None -&amp;gt; Cohere 3.5 -&amp;gt; Zerank (less known but actually good)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;LLM: GPT 4.1 -&amp;gt; GPT 5 -&amp;gt; GPT 4.1, covered by Azure credits&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Going Open-source&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We put all our learning into an open-source project: agentset-ai/agentset under an MIT license. Feel free to reach out if you have any questions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.abdellatif.io/production-rag-processing-5m-documents"/><published>2025-10-20T15:55:36+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45646691</id><title>TernFS – an exabyte scale, multi-region distributed filesystem</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:56.158278+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="65ba0c171fb742d2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;TernFS — an exabyte scale, multi-region distributed filesystem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;September 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XTX is an algorithmic trading firm: it builds statistical models that produce price forecasts for over 50,000 financial instruments worldwide. We use those forecasts to make trades. As XTX's research efforts to build better models ramped up, the demand for resources kept increasing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The firm started out with a couple of desktops and an NFS server, and 10 years later ended up with tens of thousands of high-end GPUs, hundreds of thousands of CPUs, and hundreds of petabytes of storage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As compute grew, storage struggled to keep up. We rapidly outgrew NFS first and existing open-source and commercial filesystems later. After evaluating a variety of third-party solutions, we made the decision to implement our own filesystem, which we called TernFS[1].&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have decided to open source our efforts: TernFS is available as free software on our public GitHub. This post motivates TernFS, explains its high-level architecture, and then explores some key implementation details. If you just want to spin up a local TernFS cluster, head to the README.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Another filesystem?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's a reason why every major tech company has developed its own distributed filesystem — they're crucial to running large-scale compute efforts, and liable to cause intense disruption if they malfunction. [2]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XTX was in the same position, so we designed TernFS to be a one-stop solution for most of our storage needs, going from relatively 'cold' storage of raw market data to short-lived random-access data used to communicate between GPU jobs running on our cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TernFS:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Is designed to scale up to tens of exabytes, trillions of files, millions of concurrent clients.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Stores file contents redundantly to protect against drive failures.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Has no single point of failure in its metadata services.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Supports file snapshot to protect against accidental file deletion.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Can span across multiple regions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Is hardware agnostic and uses TCP/IP to communicate.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Utilizes different types of storage (such as flash vs. hard disks) cost effectively.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Exposes read/write access through its own API over TCP and UDP, and a Linux kernel filesystem module.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Requires no external service and has a minimal set of build dependencies. [3]&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Specifically, C++ and Go are needed to build the various TernFS components.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The C++ and Go processes depend on a handful of vendored libraries, most notably RocksDB for C++.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Naturally, there are some limitations, the main ones being:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Files are immutable — once they're written they can't be modified.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TernFS should not be used for tiny files — our median file size is 2MB.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The throughput of directory creation and removal is significantly constrained compared to other operations.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TernFS is permissionless, deferring that responsibility to other services.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We started designing TernFS in early 2022 and began putting it into production in summer 2023. By mid-2024 all of our machine learning efforts were driven out of TernFS, and we're migrating the rest of the firm's storage needs onto it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As of September 2025, our TernFS deployment stores more than 500PB across 30,000 disks, 10,000 flash drives, and three data centres. At peak we serve multiple terabytes per second. To this day, we haven't lost a single byte.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;High-level overview&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that the stage is set, we're ready to explain the various components that make up TernFS. TernFS' core API is implemented by four services:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metadata shards store the directory structure and file metadata.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The cross-directory coordinator (or CDC) executes cross-shard transactions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Block services store file contents.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The registry stores information about all the other services and monitors them.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
 A ──► B means "A sends requests to B" 
                                       
                                       
 ┌────────────────┐                    
 │ Metadata Shard ◄─────────┐          
 └─┬────▲─────────┘         │          
   │    │                   │          
   │    │                   │          
   │ ┌──┴──┐                │          
   │ │ CDC ◄──────────┐     │          
   │ └──┬──┘          │     │          
   │    │             │ ┌───┴────┐     
   │    │             └─┤        │     
 ┌─▼────▼────┐          │ Client │     
 │ Registry  ◄──────────┤        │     
 └──────▲────┘          └─┬──────┘     
        │                 │            
        │                 │            
 ┌──────┴────────┐        │            
 │ Block Service ◄────────┘            
 └───────────────┘

&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the next few sections, we'll describe the high-level design of each service and then give more background on other relevant implementation details.[4]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that TernFS' multi-region capabilities are orthogonal to much of its high-level design, and they're therefore explained separately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Metadata&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To talk about metadata, we first need to explain what metadata is in TernFS. The short answer is: 'everything that is not file contents.' The slightly longer answer is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Directory entries, including all files and directory names.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File metadata including creation/modification/access time, logical file size, and so on.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The mapping between files and the blocks containing their contents.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Other ancillary data structures to facilitate maintenance operations.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TernFS' metadata is split into 256 logical shards. Shards never communicate with each other. This is a general principle in TernFS: each service is disaggregated from the others, deferring to the clients to communicate with each service directly.[5]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are some exceptions — most notably the shards execute requests from the CDC, and all services check into the registry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A logical shard is further split into five physical instances, one leader and four followers, in a typical distributed consensus setup. The distributed consensus engine is provided by a purpose-built Raft-like implementation, which we call LogsDB, while RocksDB is used to implement read/write capabilities within a shard instance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently all reads and writes go through the leader, but it would be trivial to allow clients to read from followers, and with a bit more effort to switch to a write-write setup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;    ┌─────────┐ ┌─────────┐       ┌───────────┐ 
    │ Shard 0 │ │ Shard 1 │  ...  │ Shard 255 │ 
    └─────────┘ │         │       └───────────┘ 
            ┌───┘         └───────────────────┐ 
            │                                 │ 
            │                  ┌────────────┐ │ 
            │ ┌───────────┐    │ Replica 0  │ │ 
            │ │           ◄────► (follower) │ │ 
 ┌────────┐ │ │ Replica 3 ◄──┐ └────────────┘ │ 
 │ Client ├─┼─► (leader)  ◄─┐│ ┌────────────┐ │ 
 └────────┘ │ │           ◄┐│└─► Replica 1  │ │ 
            │ └───────────┘││  │ (follower) │ │ 
            │              ││  └────────────┘ │ 
            │              ││  ┌────────────┐ │ 
            │              │└──► Replica 2  │ │ 
            │              │   │ (follower) │ │ 
            │              │   └────────────┘ │ 
            │              │   ┌────────────┐ │ 
            │              └───► Replica 4  │ │ 
            │                  │ (follower) │ │ 
            │                  └────────────┘ │ 
            └─────────────────────────────────┘ 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Splitting the metadata into 256 shards from the get-go simplifies the design, given that horizontal scaling of metadata requires no rebalancing, just the addition of more metadata servers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For instance, our current deployment can serve hundreds of petabytes and more than 100,000 compute nodes with just 10 metadata servers per data centre, with each server housing roughly 25 shard leaders and 100 shard followers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given that the metadata servers are totally decoupled from one another, this means that we can scale metadata performance by 25× trivially, and by 100× if we were to start offloading metadata requests to followers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TernFS shards metadata by assigning each directory to a single shard. This is done in a simple round-robin fashion by the cross-directory coordinator. Once a directory is created, all its directory entries and the files in it are housed in the same shard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This design decision has downsides: TernFS assumes that the load will be spread across the 256 logical shards naturally. This is not a problem in large deployments, given that they will contain many directories, but it is something to keep in mind.[6]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Cross-directory transactions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of the metadata activity is contained within a single shard:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File creation, same-directory renames, and deletion.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Listing directory contents.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Getting attributes of files or directories.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, some operations do require coordination between shards, namely directory creation, directory removal, and moving directory entries across different directories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cross-directory coordinator (CDC) performs these distributed transactions using a privileged metadata shard API. The CDC transactions are stateful, and therefore the CDC uses RocksDB and LogsDB much like the metadata shards themselves to persist its state safely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt; ┌────────┐    ┌──────────┐ ┌───────────┐ 
 │ Client ├─┐  │ Shard 32 │ │ Shard 103 │ 
 └────────┘ │  └────────▲─┘ └─▲─────────┘ 
 ┌─────┬────┼───────────┼─────┼─┐         
 │ CDC │  ┌─▼──────┐    │     │ │         
 ├─────┘  │ Leader ├────┴─────┘ │         
 │        └─────▲──┘            │         
 │              │               │         
 │       ┌──────┴───────┐       │         
 │       │              │       │         
 │ ┌─────▼────┐    ┌────▼─────┐ │         
 │ │ Follower │ .. │ Follower │ │         
 │ └──────────┘    └──────────┘ │         
 └──────────────────────────────┘   
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The CDC executes transactions in parallel, which increases throughput considerably, but it is still a bottleneck when it comes to creating, removing, or moving directories. This means that TernFS has a relatively low throughput when it comes to CDC operations.[7]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Block services, or file contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In TernFS, files are split into chunks of data called blocks. Blocks are read and written to by block services. A block service is typically a single drive (be it a hard disk or a flash drive) storing blocks. At XTX a typical storage server will contain around 100 hard disks or 25 flash drives — or in TernFS parlance 100 or 25 block services.[8]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read/write access to the block service is provided using a simple TCP API currently implemented by a Go process. This process is hardware agnostic and uses the Go standard library to read and write blocks to a conventional local file system. We originally planned to rewrite the Go process in C++, and possibly write to block devices directly, but the idiomatic Go implementation has proven performant enough for our needs so far.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The registry&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final piece of the TernFS puzzle is the registry. The registry stores the location of each instance of service (be it a metadata shard, the CDC, or a block storage node). A client only needs to know the address of the registry to mount TernFS — it'll then gather the locations of the other services from it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In TernFS all locations are IPv4 addresses. Working with IPv4 directly simplifies the kernel module considerably, since DNS lookups are quite awkward in the Linux kernel. The exception to this rule is addressing the registry itself, for which DNS is used.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The registry also stores additional information, such as the capacity and available size of each drive, who is a follower or a leader in LogsDB clusters, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Predictably, the registry itself is a RocksDB and LogsDB C++ process, given its statefulness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Going global&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TernFS tries very hard not to lose data, by storing both metadata and file contents on many different drives and servers. However, we also want to be resilient to the temporary or even permanent loss of one entire data centre. Therefore, TernFS can transparently scale across multiple locations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The intended use for TernFS locations is for each location to converge to the same dataset. This means that each location will have to be provisioned with roughly equal resources.[9] Both metadata and file contents replication are asynchronous. In general, we judge the event of losing an entire data centre rare enough to tolerate a time window where data is not fully replicated across locations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Metadata replication is set up so that one location is the metadata primary. Write operations in non-primary locations pay a latency price since they are acknowledged only after they are written to the primary location, replicated, and applied in the originating location. In practice this hasn't been an issue since metadata write latencies are generally overshadowed by writing file contents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is no automated procedure to migrate off a metadata primary location — again, we deem it a rare enough occurrence to tolerate manual intervention. In the future we plan to move from the current protocol to a multi-master protocol where each location can commit writes independently, which would reduce write latencies on secondary locations and remove the privileged status of the primary location.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;File contents, unlike metadata, are written locally to the location the client is writing from. Replication to other locations happens in two ways: proactively and on-demand. Proactive replication is performed by tailing the metadata log and replicating new file contents. On-demand replication happens when a client requests file content which has not been replicated yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Important Details&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we've laid down the high-level design of TernFS, we can talk about several key implementation details that make TernFS safer, more performant, and more flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Talking to TernFS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Speaking TernFS' language&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most direct way to talk to TernFS is by using its own API. All TernFS messages are defined using a custom serialization format we call bincode. We chose to develop a custom serialization format since we needed it to work within the confines of the Linux kernel and to be easily chopped into UDP packets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We intentionally kept the TernFS API stateless, in the sense that each request executes without regard to previous requests made by the same client. This is in contrast to protocols like NFS, whereby each connection is very stateful, holding resources such as open files, locks, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A stateless API dramatically simplifies the state machines that make up the TernFS core services, therefore simplifying their testing. It also forces each request to be idempotent, or in any case have clear retry semantics, since they might have to be replayed, which facilitates testing further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It also allows the metadata shards and CDC API to be based on UDP rather than TCP, which makes the server and clients (especially the kernel module) simpler, due to doing away with the need for keeping TCP connections. The block service API is TCP based, since it is used to stream large amounts of contiguous data, and any UDP implementation would have to re-implement a reliable stream protocol. The registry API is also TCP-based, given that it is rarely used by clients, and occasionally needs to return large amounts of data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the TernFS API is simple out-of-the-box, we provide a permissively licensed Go library implementing common tasks that clients might want to perform, such as caching directory policies and retrying requests. This library is used to implement many TernFS processes that are not part of the core TernFS services, such as scrubbing, garbage collection, migrations, and the web UI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Making TernFS POSIX-shaped&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the Go library is used for most ancillary tasks, some with high performance requirements, the main way to access TernFS at XTX is through its Linux kernel module.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is because, when migrating our machine learning workflows to TernFS, we needed to support a vast codebase working with files directly. This not only meant that we needed to expose TernFS as a normal filesystem, but also that said normal filesystem API needed to be robust and performant enough for our machine learning needs.[10]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For this reason, we opted to work with Linux directly, rather than using FUSE. Working directly with the Linux kernel not only gave us the confidence that we could achieve our performance requirements but also allowed us to bend the POSIX API to our needs, something that would have been more difficult if we had used FUSE.[11]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The main obstacle when exposing TernFS as a 'normal' filesystem is that TernFS files are immutable. More specifically, TernFS files are fully written before being 'linked' into the filesystem as a directory entry. This is intentional: it lets us cleanly separate the API for 'under construction' files and 'completed files', and it means that half-written files are not visible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However this design is essentially incompatible with POSIX, which endows the user with near-absolute freedom when it comes to manipulating a file. Therefore, the TernFS kernel module is not POSIX-compliant, but rather exposes enough POSIX to allow many programs to work without modifications, but not all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In practice this means that programs which write files left-to-right and never modify the files' contents will work out-of-the-box. While this might seem very restrictive, we found that a surprising number of programs worked just fine.[12] Programs that did not follow this pattern were modified to first write to a temporary file and then copy the finished file to TernFS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While we feel that writing our own kernel module was the right approach, it proved to be the trickiest part of TernFS, and we would not have been able to implement it without some important safety checks in the TernFS core services.[13]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;S3 gateway&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Almost all the storage-related activity at XTX is due to our machine-learning efforts, and for those purposes the TernFS' kernel module has served us well. However, as TernFS proved itself there, we started to look into offering TernFS to the broader firm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doing so through the kernel module presented multiple challenges. For starters installing a custom kernel module on every machine that needed to reach TernFS is operationally cumbersome. Moreover, while all machine-learning happens in clusters housed in the same data centre as TernFS itself, we wanted to expose TernFS in a way that's more amenable to less local networks, for instance by removing the need for UDP. Finally, TernFS does not have any built-in support for permissions or authentication, which is a requirement in multi-tenant scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To solve all these problems, we implemented a gateway for TernFS, which exposes a TernFS subtree using the S3 API. The gateway is a simple Go process turning S3 calls into TernFS API calls. The S3 gateway is not currently open sourced since it is coupled to authentication services internal to XTX, but we have open sourced a minimal S3 gateway to serve as a starting point for third-party contributors to build their own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We've also planned an NFS gateway to TernFS, but we haven't had a pressing enough need yet to complete it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The web UI and the JSON interface&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, a view of TernFS is provided by its web UI. The web UI is a stateless Go program which exposes most of the state of TernFS in an easy-to-use interface. This state includes the full filesystem contents (both metadata and file contents), the status of each service including information about decommissioned block services, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moreover, the web UI also exposes the direct TernFS API in JSON form, which is very useful for small scripts and curl-style automation that does not warrant a full-blown Go program.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Directory Policies&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To implement some of the functionality we'll describe below, TernFS adopts a system of per-directory policies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Policies are used for all sorts of decisions, including:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How to redundantly store files.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;On which type of drive to store files.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How long to keep files around after deletion.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each of the topics above (and a few more we haven't mentioned) correspond to a certain policy tag. The body of the policies are stored in the metadata together with the other directory attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Policies are inherited: if a directory does not contain a certain policy tag, it transitively inherits from the parent directory. TernFS clients store a cache of policies to allow for traversal-free policy lookup for most directories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Keeping blocks in check&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A filesystem is no good if it loses, leaks, corrupts, or otherwise messes up its data. TernFS deploys a host of measures to minimize the chance of anything going wrong. So far, these have worked: we've never lost data in our production deployment of TernFS. This section focuses on the measures in place to specifically safeguard files' blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Against bitrot, or CRC32-C&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first and possibly most obvious measure consists of aggressively checksumming all TernFS' data. The metadata is automatically checksummed by RocksDB, and every block is stored in a format interleaving 4KiB pages with 4byte CRC32-C checksums.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CRC32-C was picked since it is a high-quality checksum and implemented on most modern silicon.[14] It also exhibits some desirable properties when used together with Reed-Solomon coding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Peter Cawley's fast-crc32 repository provides a general framework to compute CRC32-C quickly, together with state-of-the-art implementations for x86 and aarch64 architectures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4KiB was picked since it is the read boundary used by Linux filesystems and is fine-grained while still being large enough to render the storage overhead of the 4byte checksums negligible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interleaving the CRCs with the block contents does not add any safety, but it does improve operations in two important ways. First, it allows for safe partial reads: clients can demand only a few pages from a block which is many megabytes in size and still check the reads against its checksum. Second, it allows scrubbing files locally on the server which hosts the blocks, without communicating with other services at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Storing files redundantly, or Reed-Solomon codes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We've been talking about files being split into blocks, but we haven't really explained how files become blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first thing we do to a file is split it into spans. Spans are at most 100MiB and are present just to divide files into sections of a manageable size.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then each span is divided into D data blocks, and P parity blocks. D and P are determined by the corresponding directory policy in which the file is created. When D is 1, the entire contents of the span become a single block, and that block is stored D+P times. This scheme is equivalent to a simple mirroring scheme and allows it to lose up to P blocks before losing file data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While wasteful, mirroring the entire contents of the file can be useful for very hot files, since TernFS clients will pick a block at random to read from, thereby sharing the read load across many block services. And naturally files which we do not care much for can be stored with D = 1 and P = 0, without any redundancy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, most files will not be stored using mirroring but rather using Reed-Solomon coding. Other resources can be consulted to understand the high-level idea and the low-level details of Reed-Solomon coding, but the gist is it allows us to split a span into D equally sized blocks (some padding might be necessary), and then generate P blocks of equal size such that up to any P blocks can be lost while retaining the ability to reconstruct all the other blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As mentioned, D and P are fully configurable, but at XTX we tend to use D = 10 and P = 4, which allows us to lose up to any four drives for any file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Drive type picking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We now know how to split files into a bunch of blocks. The next question is: which drives to pick to store the blocks on. The first decision is which kind of drive to use. At XTX we separate drives into two broad categories for this purpose — flash and spinning disks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When picking between these two, we want to balance two needs: minimizing the cost of hardware by utilizing hard disks if we can [15], and maximizing hard disk productivity by having them reading data most of the time, rather than seeking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To achieve that, directory policies offer a way to tune how large each block will be, and to tune which drives will be picked based on block size. This allows us to configure TernFS so that larger files that can be read sequentially are stored on hard disks, while random-access or small files are stored on flash. [16]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently this system is not adaptive, but we found that in practice it's easy to carve out sections of the filesystem which are not read sequentially. We have a default configuration which assumes sequential reads and then uses hard disks down to roughly 2.5MB blocks, below which hard disks stop being productive enough and blocks start needing to be written to flash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Block service picking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OK, we now know what type of drive to select for our files, but we still have tens of thousands of individual drives to pick from. Picking the 'right' individual drive requires some sophistication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that drive failures or unavailability are often correlated. For instance, at XTX a single server handles 102 spinning disks. If the server is down, faulty, or needs to be decommissioned, it'll render its 102 disks temporarily or permanently unavailable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's therefore wise to spread a file's blocks across many servers. To achieve this, each TernFS block service (which generally corresponds to a single drive) has a failure domain. When picking block services in which to store the blocks for a given file, TernFS will make sure that each block is in a separate failure domain. In our TernFS deployment a failure domain corresponds to a server, but other users might wish to tie it to some other factor as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TernFS also tries hard to avoid write bottlenecks by spreading the current write load across many disks. Moreover, since new drives can be added at any time, it tries to converge to a situation where each drive is roughly equally filled by assigning writing more to drives with more available space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mechanically this is achieved by having each shard periodically request a set of block services to use for writing from the registry. When handing out block services to shards, the registry selects block services according to several constraints:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It never gives block services from the same failure domain to the same shard&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It minimizes the variance in how many shards each block service is currently assigned to&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It prioritizes block services which have more available space.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then when a client wants to write a new span, requiring D+P blocks, the shard simply selects D+P block services randomly amongst the ones it last received from the registry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One concept currently absent from TernFS is what is often known as 'copyset replication'. When assigning disks to files at random (even with the caveat of failure domains) the probability of rendering at least one file unreadable quickly becomes a certainty as more and more drives fail:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Copysets reduce the likelihood of data loss occurring by choosing blocks out of a limited number of sets of drives, as opposed to picking the drives randomly. This dramatically reduces the probability of data loss[17]. They are generally a good idea, but we haven't found them to be worthwhile, for a few reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that while copysets reduce the failure probability, they do not (and cannot) reduce the expected amount of data loss. That is, instead of a large probability of a relatively small amount of data loss we have a very small probability of a catastrophic loss.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, evacuating a 20TB drive takes just a few minutes, and in the presence of multiple failed drives the migrator process evacuates first the files which are present in multiple failed drives to get ahead of possible data loss. This means that for TernFS to lose data within a single data centre tens of drives would have to fail within a matter of seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More importantly, our TernFS deployment is replicated across three data centres. This replication eliminates the chance of losing data due to 'independent' drive failures — thousands of drives would need to fail at once. Obviously, data centre wide events can cause a large proportion of the drives within it to fail, but having such an event in three data centres at once is exceedingly unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, copysets are not without drawbacks or complications. Assigning drives at random is an optimal strategy when it comes to evacuating drives quickly, since the files with blocks in the drives to be evacuated will be evenly spread over the rest of the filesystem, and since we only ever need to replace the failed blocks given that we're not constrained by fitting the new set of blocks in predetermined copysets. This means that the evacuation procedure will not be bottlenecked by drive throughput, which is what enables evacuation to finish in a matter of minutes. Moreover, the algorithm to distribute drives to shards is significantly simpler and more flexible than if it needed to care about copysets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, users that wish to deploy TernFS within a single data centre might wish to implement some form of copyset replication. Such a change would be entirely contained to the registry and would not change any other component.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Block Proofs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We now have a solid scheme to store files redundantly (thanks to Reed-Solomon codes) and protect against bitrot (thanks to the checksums). However, said schemes are only as good as their implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As previously mentioned, TernFS clients communicate their intention to write a file to metadata servers, the metadata servers select block services that the blocks should be written to, and the clients then write the blocks to block services independently of the metadata services. The same happens when a client wants to erase blocks: the client first communicates its intentions to delete the blocks to the right metadata shard and then performs the erasing itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This poses a challenge. While verifying the correctness of the core TernFS services is feasible, verifying all clients is not, but we'd still like to prevent buggy clients from breaking key invariants of the filesystem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Buggy clients can wreak havoc in several ways:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They can leak data by writing blocks to block services that are not referenced anywhere in the metadata.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They can lose data by erasing blocks which are still referenced in metadata.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They can corrupt data by telling the metadata services they'll write something and then writing something else.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We address all these points by using what we call block proofs. To illustrate how block proofs work, it's helpful to go through the steps required to write new data to a file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When a client is creating a file, it'll do so by adding its file spans one-by-one. For each span the client wants to add it sends an 'initiate span creation' request to the right metadata shard. This request contains both the overall checksum of the span, and the checksum of each block in it (including parity blocks).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The metadata shard checks the consistency of the checksum of the span and of its blocks, something it can do thanks to some desirable mathematical properties of CRCs.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The shard picks block services for the blocks to be written in and returns this information to the client together with a signature for each 'block write' instruction.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The client forwards this signature to the block services, which will refuse to write the block without it. Crucially, the cryptographic signature ranges over a unique identity for the block (ensuring we only write the block we mean to write), together with its checksum, ensuring we don't write the wrong data.[18]&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;After committing the block to disk, the block service returns a 'block written' signature to the client.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Finally, the client forwards the block written signature back to the shard, which certifies that the span has been written only when it has received the signatures for all the blocks that make up the span. [19]&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This kind of scheme was described more generally in a separate blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, when a client wants to delete a span, it first asks the metadata shard to start doing so. The metadata shard marks the span as 'in deletion' and returns a bunch of 'block erase' signatures to the client. The client then forwards the signatures to the block services that hold the blocks, which delete the blocks, and return a 'block erased' signature. The clients forward these signatures back to the metadata shards, which can then forget about the span entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We use AES to generate the signatures for simplicity but note that the goal here is not protecting ourselves from malicious clients — just buggy ones. The keys used for the signature are not kept secret, and CRC32-C is not a secure checksum. That said, we've found this scheme enormously valuable in the presence of complex clients. We spent considerable efforts making the core services very simple so we could then take more implementation risks in the clients, with the knowledge that we would have a very low chance of corrupting the filesystem itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Scrubbing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, if things go wrong, we need to notice. The most common failure mode for a drive is for it to fail entirely, in which case our internal hardware monitoring system will pick it up and migrate from it automatically. The more insidious (and still very common) case is a single sector failing in a drive, which will only be noticed when we try to read the block involving that sector.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is acceptable for files which are read frequently, but some files might be very 'cold' but still very important.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider the case of raw market data taps which are immediately converted to some processed, lossy format. While we generally will use the file containing the processed data, it's paramount to store the raw market data forever so that if we ever want to include more information from the original market data, we can. So important cold files might go months or even years without anyone reading them, and in the meantime, we might find that enough blocks have been corrupted to render them unreadable.[20]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make sure this does not happen, a process called the scrubber continuously reads every block that TernFS stores, and replaces blocks with bad sectors before they can cause too much damage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Snapshots and garbage collection&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We've talked at length about what TernFS does to try to prevent data loss due to hardware failure or bugs in clients. However, the most common type of data loss is due to human error — the &lt;code&gt;rm —rf / home/alice/notes.txt&lt;/code&gt; scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To protect against these scenarios, TernFS implements a lightweight snapshotting system. When files or directories are deleted, their contents aren't actually deleted. Instead, a weak reference to them is created. We call such weak references snapshot directory entries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Snapshot entries are not be visible through the kernel module or the S3 gateway, but are visible through the direct API, and at XTX we have developed internal tooling to easily recover deleted files through it.[21] Deleted files are also visible through the TernFS web UI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given that 'normal' file operations do not delete files, but rather make them a snapshot, the task of freeing up space is delegated to an external Go process, the garbage collector. The garbage collector traverses the filesystem and removes expired snapshots, which involves deleting their blocks permanently. Snapshot expiry is predictably regulated by directory policies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Keeping TernFS healthy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This last section covers how we (humans of XTX) notice problems in TernFS, and how TernFS self-heals when things go wrong — both key topics if we want to ensure no data loss and notice performance problems early.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Performance metrics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TernFS exposes a plethora of performance metrics through the HTTP InfluxDB line protocol. While connecting TernFS to a service which ingests these metrics is optional, it is highly recommended for any production service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moreover, the kernel module exposes many performance metrics itself through DebugFS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both types of metrics, especially when used in tandem, have proved invaluable to resolve performance problems quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Logging and alerts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TernFS services log their output to files in a simple line-based format. The internal logging API is extremely simple and includes support for syslog levels out-of-the-box. At XTX we run TernFS as normal systemd services and use journalctl to view logs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As with metrics, the kernel module includes various logging facilities as well. The first type of logging is just through dmesg, but the kernel module also includes numerous tracepoints for low-overhead opt-in logging of many operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TernFS is also integrated with XTX's internal alerting system, called XMon, to page on call developers when things go wrong. XMon is not open source, but all the alerts are also rendered as error lines in logs. [22] We plan to eventually move to having alerts feed off performance metrics, which would make them independent from XMon, although we don't have plans to do so in the short-term.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Migrations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, there's the question of what to do when drives die — and they will die, frequently, when you have 50,000 of them. While drives dying is not surprising, we've been surprised at the variety of different drive failures. [23] A malfunctioning drive might:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Produce IO errors when reading specific files. This is probably due to a single bad sector.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Produce IO errors when reading or writing anything. This might happen because enough bad sectors have gone bad and the drive cannot remap them, or for a variety of other reasons.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Return wrong data. This is usually caught by the built-in error correction codes in the hard drives, but not always.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lie about data being successfully persisted. This can manifest in a variety of ways: file size being wrong on open, file contents being partially zero'd out, and so on.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Disappear from the mount list, only to reappear when the machine is rebooted, but missing some data.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When clients fail to read from a drive, they'll automatically fall back on other drives to reconstruct the missing data, which is extremely effective in hiding failures from the end-user. That said, something needs to be done about the bad drives, and done quickly to avoid permanent data loss.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The TernFS registry allows marking drives as faulty. Faulty drives are then picked up by the migrator, a Go process which waits for bad drives and then stores all its blocks onto freshly picked block services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TernFS also tries to mark drives as bad automatically using a simple heuristic based on the rate of IO errors the drive is experiencing. The number of drives automatically marked as faulty is throttled to avoid having this check go awry and mark the whole cluster as faulty, which would not be catastrophic but would still be messy to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moreover, drives that are faulty in subtle ways might not be picked up by the heuristics, which means that occasionally a sysadmin will need to mark a drive as faulty manually, after which the migrator will evacuate them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At XTX we feel strongly about utilizing our resources efficiently. When it comes to software, this means having software that gets close to some theoretical optimum when it comes to total cost of ownership. This culture was borne out by competing hard for technological excellence when doing on-exchange trading at first, and by our ever-growing hardware costs as our business has grown later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Such idealized tools might not exist or be available yet, in which case we're happy to be the tool makers. TernFS is a perfect example of this and we're excited to open source this component of our business for the community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Crucially, the cost of implementation of a new solution is often overblown compared to the cost of tying yourself to an ill-fitting, expensive third-party solution. Designing and implementing a solution serving exactly your needs allows for much greater simplicity. If the requirements do change, as often happens, changes can be implemented very quickly, again only catering to your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, we believe that TernFS' set of trade-offs are widely shared across many organizations dealing with large-scale storage workloads, and we hope we'll contribute to at least slowing down the seemingly constant stream of new filesystems.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.xtxmarkets.com/tech/2025-ternfs/#posix-shaped"/><published>2025-10-20T17:36:16+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45646958</id><title>x86-64 Playground – An online assembly editor and GDB-like debugger</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:55.891137+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="aefedf1ae8255dda"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;x86-64 Playground is a web app for experimenting and learning x86-64 assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Playground web app provides an online code editor where you can write, compile, and share assembly code for a wide range of popular assemblers such as GNU As, Fasm and Nasm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike traditional onlide editors, this playground allows you to follow the execution of your program step by step, inspecting memory and registers of the running process from a GDB-like interface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can bring your own programs! Drag and drop into the app any x86-64-Linux static executable to run and debug it in the same sandboxed environment, without having to install anything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The app is for anyone that wants to run amd64 assembly snippets or inspect the inner workings of simple Linux ELF files.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has been designed with the academic world of binary exploitation in mind; The debugger interface offers visualizations similar to the GDB+PwnGDB debugger plugin, and all the controls are labelled with the respective GDB commands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Combined with Compiler Explorer, this app provides a noise-free environment to learn the basics behind the inner workings of a Linux process. When you are ready, it includes the guides and resources necessary to keep experimenting on your own linux environment, with the actual GDB debugger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have you ever seen a responsive debugger? The app places the mobile experience at the center of its design, and can be embedded in any web page to add interactivity to technical tutorials or documentations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow the guide to embed in your website both the asm editor and debugger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The app is open-source, and available on Github. It's powered by the Blink Emulator, which emulates an x86-64-Linux environment entirely client side in your browser. This means that all the code you write, or the excutables you debug are never sent to the server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;everything runs in your browser, and once the Web App loads it will work without an internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://x64.halb.it/"/><published>2025-10-20T17:55:18+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45647166</id><title>Claude Code on the web</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:55.738822+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7f0c0efeffb1c2ef"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Claude Code on the web&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we're introducing Claude Code on the web, a new way to delegate coding tasks directly from your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now in beta as a research preview, you can assign multiple coding tasks to Claude that run on Anthropic-managed cloud infrastructure, perfect for tackling bug backlogs, routine fixes, or parallel development work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Run coding tasks in parallel&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Code on the web lets you kick off coding sessions without opening your terminal. Connect your GitHub repositories, describe what you need, and Claude handles the implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each session runs in its own isolated environment with real-time progress tracking, and you can actively steer Claude to adjust course as it’s working through tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Claude Code running in the cloud, you can now run multiple tasks in parallel across different repositories from a single interface and ship faster with automatic PR creation and clear change summaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Flexible for every workflow&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The web interface complements your existing Claude Code workflow. Running tasks in the cloud is especially effective for:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Answering questions about how projects work and how repositories are mapped&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bugfixes and routine, well-defined tasks&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Backend changes, where Claude Code can use test-driven development to verify changes&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also use Claude Code on mobile. As part of this research preview, we’re making Claude Code available on our iOS app so developers can explore coding with Claude on the go. It’s an early preview, and we hope to quickly refine the mobile experience based on your feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Security-first cloud execution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every Claude Code task runs in an isolated sandbox environment with network and filesystem restrictions. Git interactions are handled through a secure proxy service that ensures Claude can only access authorized repositories—helping keep your code and credentials protected throughout the entire workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also add custom network configuration to choose what domains Claude Code can connect to from its sandbox. For example, you can allow Claude to download npm packages over the internet so that it can run tests and validate changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read our engineering blog and documentation for a deep dive on Claude Code’s sandboxing approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Getting started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Code on the web is available now in research preview for Pro and Max users. Visit claude.com/code to connect your first repository and start delegating tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloud-based sessions share rate limits with all other Claude Code usage. Explore our documentation to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-code-on-the-web"/><published>2025-10-20T18:12:23+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45649178</id><title>Today is when the Amazon brain drain sent AWS down the spout</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:55.536366+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d28b35914248ecf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Today is when the Amazon brain drain finally sent AWS down the spout&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;When your best engineers log off for good, don’t be surprised when the cloud forgets how DNS works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;column "It's always DNS" is a long-standing sysadmin saw, and with good reason: a disproportionate number of outages are at their heart DNS issues. And so today, as AWS is still repairing its downed cloud as this article goes to press, it becomes clear that the culprit is once again DNS. But if you or I know this, AWS certainly does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so, a quiet suspicion starts to circulate: where have the senior AWS engineers who've been to this dance before gone? And the answer increasingly is that they've left the building — taking decades of hard-won institutional knowledge about how AWS's systems work at scale right along with them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What happened?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS reports that on October 20, at 12:11 AM PDT, it began investigating “increased error rates and latencies for multiple AWS services in the US-EAST-1 Region.” About an hour later, at 1:26 AM, the company confirmed “significant error rates for requests made to the DynamoDB endpoint” in that region. By 2:01 AM, engineers had identified DNS resolution of the DynamoDB API endpoint for US-EAST-1 as the likely root cause, which led to cascading failures for most other things in that region. DynamoDB is a "foundational service" upon which a whole mess of other AWS services rely, so the blast radius for an outage touching this thing can be huge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a result, much of the internet stopped working: banking, gaming, social media, government services, buying things I don't need on Amazon.com itself, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS has given increasing levels of detail, as is their tradition, when outages strike, and as new information comes to light. Reading through it, one really gets the sense that it took them 75 minutes to go from "things are breaking" to "we've narrowed it down to a single service endpoint, but are still researching," which is something of a bitter pill to swallow. To be clear: I've seen zero signs that this stems from a lack of transparency, and every indication that they legitimately did not know what was breaking for a patently absurd length of time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that for those 75 minutes, visitors to the AWS status page (reasonably wondering why their websites and other workloads had just burned down and crashed into the sea) were met with an "all is well!" default response. Ah well, it's not as if AWS had previously called out slow outage notification times as an area for improvement. Multiple times even. We can keep doing this if you'd like.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The prophecy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS is very, very good at infrastructure. You can tell this is a true statement by the fact that a single one of their 38 regions going down (albeit a very important region!) causes this kind of attention, as opposed to it being "just another Monday outage." At AWS's scale, all of their issues are complex; this isn't going to be a simple issue that someone should have caught, just because they've already hit similar issues years ago and ironed out the kinks in their resilience story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you reach a certain point of scale, there are no simple problems left. What's more concerning to me is the way it seems AWS has been flailing all day trying to run this one to ground. Suddenly, I'm reminded of something I had tried very hard to forget.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of 2023, Justin Garrison left AWS and roasted them on his way out the door. He stated that AWS had seen an increase in Large Scale Events (or LSEs), and predicted significant outages in 2024. It would seem that he discounted the power of inertia, but the pace of senior AWS departures certainly hasn't slowed — and now, with an outage like this, one is forced to wonder whether those departures are themselves a contributing factor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can hire a bunch of very smart people who will explain how DNS works at a deep technical level (or you can hire me, who will incorrect you by explaining that it's a database), but the one thing you can't hire for is the person who remembers that when DNS starts getting wonky, check that seemingly unrelated system in the corner, because it has historically played a contributing role to some outages of yesteryear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When that tribal knowledge departs, you're left having to reinvent an awful lot of in-house expertise that didn't want to participate in your RTO games, or play Layoff Roulette yet again this cycle. This doesn't impact your service reliability — until one day it very much does, in spectacular fashion. I suspect that day is today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AWS outage exposes Achilles heel: central control plane&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Major AWS outage across US-East region breaks half the internet&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Amazon spills plan to nuke Washington...with X-Energy mini-reactors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Amazon turns James Bond into the Man Without the Golden Gun&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The talent drain evidence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is The Register, a respected journalistic outlet. As a result, I know that if I publish this piece as it stands now, an AWS PR flak will appear as if by magic, waving their hands, insisting that "there is no talent exodus at AWS," a la Baghdad Bob. Therefore, let me forestall that time-wasting enterprise with some data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It is a fact that there have been 27,000+ Amazonians impacted by layoffs between 2022 and 2024, continuing into 2025. It's hard to know how many of these were AWS versus other parts of its Amazon parent, because the company is notoriously tight-lipped about staffing issues.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Internal documents reportedly say that Amazon suffers from 69 percent to 81 percent regretted attrition across all employment levels. In other words, "people quitting who we wish didn't."&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The internet is full of anecdata of senior Amazonians lamenting the hamfisted approach of their Return to Office initiative; experts have weighed in citing similar concerns.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you were one of the early employees who built these systems, the world is your oyster. There's little reason to remain at a company that increasingly demonstrates apparent disdain for your expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;My take&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a tipping point moment. Increasingly, it seems that the talent who understood the deep failure modes is gone. The new, leaner, presumably less expensive teams lack the institutional knowledge needed to, if not prevent these outages in the first place, significantly reduce the time to detection and recovery. Remember, there was a time when Amazon's "Frugality" leadership principle meant doing more with less, not doing everything with basically nothing. AWS's operational strength was built on redundant, experienced people, and when you cut to the bone, basic things start breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to be very clear on one last point. This isn't about the technology being old. It's about the people maintaining it being new. If I had to guess what happens next, the market will forgive AWS this time, but the pattern will continue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS will almost certainly say this was an "isolated incident," but when you've hollowed out your engineering ranks, every incident becomes more likely. The next outage is already brewing. It's just a matter of which understaffed team trips over which edge case first, because the chickens are coming home to roost. ®&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/20/aws_outage_amazon_brain_drain_corey_quinn/"/><published>2025-10-20T20:50:03+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45650792</id><title>Old Computer Challenge – Modern Web for the ZX Spectrum</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:55.343699+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="a76899312b36a4a4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025/10/19&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Table of contents&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last year I participated in the OCC challenge and between work and personal life I totally forgot about it, luckily I saw a post online of someone doing the challenge and remembered about it. I didn’t want to miss this year challenge as it was fun learning something new last year, so hopefully its not too late.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This years challenge it was a DIY, you could create your own OCC challenge. So I thought it’d be fun to try to recreate a website and navigation for the ZX Spectrum using BASIC and the limited graphics capabilities of the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, in this case the hardware is the ZX Spectrum, though I must say that I used an emulator (Fuse) to test and run my code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ZX Spectrum image resolution is 256x192 pixels, so the space is very limited. The colour palette is made up of 8 colors, with a “brighter” variation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this in mind I had to design a website for the ZX Spectrum and how you’d navigate with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So given the hardware and limitations I thought that I’d first do Google, since they have a simple design and is I’d say well known by everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The image below, is what Googles homepage would look like.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’d access their services listed by pressing the first letter of that service, in case there is more than 1 with the same letter you’d use another letter or simply add a second page of services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case you can access Search by pressing “S”. It will simply prompt for your search and in this case I searched for “How to run LLM on a microprocessor” and you’d navigate through the different results by going pressing “w” (up) or “s” (down).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hacker news is text heavy content, so it makes it “easy” to design it for the ZX Spectrum as its graphics capabilities are kinda limited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you can see, you’ll be able to see your username and the amount of points you have in the top bar and in this case I decided that navigation would be done “less” interactively and you’ll access posts by simply selecting the number (1 to 6). If you want to go to the second page of posts you can press “M” and if you want to submit you press “S”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So if we select the first post by pressing 1, we’ll load more details about the post and the comment section.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll see the title, user that posted it, time and the comment section with the amount of comments, in this case 42. The problem with the comment section is that some comment threads can go deep and have different branches as multiple users will reply. So in this case what I thought was to simply navigate the top level comments with “M” for the next comment and “B” to go back to the previous top level comment. I guess you could add a “[R]eply” option, to reply to the comment you are seeing on screen and navigating through the comment replies, you’d press something like “C” and you’ll enter a page of the child comments of the parent comment. The only problem with this is that because the screen is so tiny and limited, that most of the time you’ll only be able to see 1 comment at a time and when posts have 300 comments, navigating them is going to be hard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And this is what submitting a new link would look like, you’d simply “edit” the different fields and then “S"ubmit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Personally I had fun doing this, I didn’t have to spend a lot of time researching before doing that as I had already done a lot of that work in last year challenge, so I could focus on what I wanted to do. You can check the source code and try it yourself in my repository https://codeberg.org/0x00cl/Web-ZX&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are videos of the interactions in the ZX Spectrum&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://0x00.cl/blog/2025/occ-2025/"/><published>2025-10-20T23:40:25+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45652307</id><title>60k kids have avoided peanut allergies due to 2015 advice, study finds</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:55.201681+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd451175ad948489"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Some 60,000 kids have avoided peanut allergies due to landmark 2015 advice, study finds&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A decade after a landmark study proved that feeding peanut products to young babies could prevent development of life-threatening allergies, new research finds the change has made a big difference in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About 60,000 children have avoided developing peanut allergies after guidance first issued in 2015 upended medical practice by recommending introducing the allergen to infants starting as early as 4 months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"That's a remarkable thing, right?" said Dr. David Hill, an allergist and researcher at Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, and author of a study published Monday in the medical journal Pediatrics. Hill and colleagues analyzed electronic health records from dozens of pediatric practices to track diagnoses of food allergies in young children before, during and after the guidelines were issued.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I can actually come to you today and say there are less kids with food allergy today than there would have been if we hadn't implemented this public health effort," he added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Our findings have relevance from those of us who treat patients to those caring for infants, and more awareness, education and advocacy could further increase the positive results we observed in this study," he continued. "Future studies could potentially explore specific feeding practices that help us better understand the timing, frequency and dose of foods that optimize protection against food allergies."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The researchers found that peanut allergies in children ages 0 to 3 declined by more than 27% after guidance for high-risk kids was first issued in 2015 and by more than 40% after the recommendations were expanded in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The effort hasn't yet reduced an overall increase in food allergies in the U.S. in recent years. About 8% of children are affected, including more than 2% with a peanut allergy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Peanut allergy is caused when the body's immune system mistakenly identifies proteins in peanuts as harmful and releases chemicals that trigger allergic symptoms, including hives, respiratory symptoms and, sometimes, life-threatening anaphylaxis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For decades, doctors had recommended delaying feeding children peanuts and other foods likely to trigger allergies until age 3. But in 2015, Gideon Lack at King's College London published the groundbreaking Learning Early About Peanut Allergy, or LEAP, trial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lack and colleagues showed that introducing peanut products in infancy reduced the future risk of developing food allergies by more than 80%. Later analysis showed that the protection persisted in about 70% of kids into adolescence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study immediately sparked new guidelines urging early introduction of peanuts — but putting them into practice has been slow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only about 29% of pediatricians and 65% of allergists reported following the expanded guidance issued in 2017, surveys found.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confusion and uncertainty about the best way to introduce peanuts early in life led to the lag, according to a commentary that accompanied the study. Early on, medical experts and parents alike questioned whether the practice could be adopted outside of tightly controlled clinical settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The data for the analysis came from a subset of participating practice sites and may not represent the entire U.S. pediatric population, noted the commentary, led by Dr. Ruchi Gupta, a child allergy expert at Northwestern University.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the new research offers "promising evidence that early allergen introduction is not only being adopted but may be making a measurable impact," the authors concluded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Advocates for the 33 million people in the U.S. with food allergies welcomed signs that early introduction of peanut products is catching on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"This research reinforces what we already know and underscores a meaningful opportunity to reduce the incidence and prevalence of peanut allergy nationwide," said Sung Poblete, chief executive of the nonprofit group Food Allergy Research &amp;amp; Education, or FARE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new study emphasizes the current guidance, updated in 2021, which calls for introducing peanuts and other major food allergens between four and six months, without prior screening or testing, Hill said. Parents should consult their pediatricians about any questions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It doesn't have to be a lot of the food, but little tastes of peanut butter, milk-based yogurt, soy-based yogurts and tree butters," he said. "These are really good ways to allow the immune system exposure to these allergenic foods in a safe way."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tiffany Leon, 36, a Maryland registered dietician and director at FARE, introduced peanuts and other allergens early to her own sons, James, 4, and Cameron, 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At first, Leon's own mother was shocked at the advice to feed babies such foods before the age of 3, she said. But Leon explained how the science had changed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"As a dietician, I practice evidence-based recommendations," she said. "So when someone told me, 'This is how it's done now, these are the new guidelines,' I just thought, 'OK, well, this is what we're going to do.'"&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/peanut-allergies-60000-kids-avoided-2015-advice/"/><published>2025-10-21T03:53:20+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45652859</id><title>Practical Scheme</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:54.920228+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="c343dacf9eb15a95"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This page is a collection of libraries and extensions to use Scheme as a production tool. By "production tools" I mean the tools to process daily chores for systems engineers and programmers---parsing files, generate reports, watching processes, providing small GUI wrappers, and all sorts of those things. Currently I'm using Perl for those purpose, but I'm always longing to use Scheme for them. So I started this page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most stuffs in this site are done as my private project at home, except the ones explicitly stated otherwise. I upload libraries even in its alpha/beta stage, since I'd like to test and use them at work, too. In a way, my primary interest is to make my life happier. No warranty comes with them, as usual, but it'll be nice if somebody else finds they are useful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you can read Japanese, visit the Japanese page which contains some translations of Lisp/Scheme related articles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wrote a Wiki Clone in Scheme (Gauche). Come and try it: WiLiKi.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Applications and tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scheme-related stand alone programs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Gauche - Current version 0.9.15 (2024/04/24)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;An R7RS Scheme implementation aimed at a handy script engine. Quick startup, built-in system interface, and native multilingual support are some of the goals.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;WiLiKi - Current version 0.6.2 (2014/11/28)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A wiki engine written in Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Chaton - Current version&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A Comet-based Webchat system.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;escm - Current version 1.1 (2014/11/28)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A filter program which copies the input text to output, with processing embedded Scheme expressions. This program itself is independent from any Scheme implementation; you can use your favorite one. Useful to process text files with a bit of dynamic parts. This page itself is processed by escm to embed information such as the update time of libraries, and synchronize with Japanese version. A complete new version of escm, named aescm, is being developed by TAGA Yoshitaka ( http://sourceforge.net/projects/escm/)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Libraries and Extensions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following libraries and extensions are written for Gauche. See here for libraries written for STk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Gauche-gl - Download Document Current version 0.6 (2014/08/09)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;OpenGL binding for Gauche. Supports most of OpenGL 1.0 to 4.1 APIs (including OpenGL Shading Language API), and some of GLU and GLUT API. Requires Gauche 0.9.4 or later.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Gauche-gtk2 - Download Document Current version 0.6.1 (2022/3/20)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;GTK2 binding for Gauche.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Documents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Scheme Cross Reference&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A cross reference of library procedures of various Scheme implementations. Updated constantly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Shooting A Moving Target--- An Experience In Developing A Production Tracking Database&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;An application of CommonLisp in practice. (yeah, it's not Scheme... anyway, I put it here).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Tracking Assets in the Production of 'Final Fantasy : The Spirits Within'&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A follow-up of the article above, a kind of post-mortem of the production.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;Gluing Things Together - Scheme in the Real-time CG Content Production&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A paper presented at International Lisp Conference 2002 at San Francisco, October 2002. (there's also a pdf version).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-5"&gt;Efficient floating-point number handling for dynamically typed scripting languages (pdf)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-5"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A paper presented at Dynamic Language Symposium 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-6"&gt;Schemer's Way&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-6"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Trying to explain Scheme's merits to non-Scheme programmers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Other Resources&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This list no way covers everything, but you can follow links in those links.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Schemers.org&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;A good anchor point to collect information of Scheme. You can get R*RS, the language standard. The site is also a center of SRFI's--- Scheme Request For Implementation---which provides common interface of libraries across various implementations.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;SCM&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;A compact, fast and portable implementation of Scheme interpreter.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;SLIB&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;A large collection of portable Scheme libraries. The contents spans from small utilities complements the standard conformance, to the full-featured relational database.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;Programming Languages by Dai Inukai&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;Scheme-related documents by Dai Inukai, the author of "Nyuumon Scheme (Scheme Primer)" in Japan. Check this out if you're interested in processing Japanese in Scheme.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-5"&gt;Bigloo&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-5"&gt;A scheme system with compiler and integrated development environment. If you're planning to write an enterprise software rather than just a bunch of scripts, look at it.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-6"&gt;Guile&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-6"&gt;GNU adopted Scheme for the base of extension language several years ago. The effort became Guile. If you have one of popular Linux distributions, you may already have it.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-7"&gt;scsh&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-7"&gt;I haven't used this one much, but looks good if you're looking for a tool to do syste programming.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-8"&gt;The Internet Scheme Repository&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-8"&gt;As the name suggests.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-9"&gt;Kawa - the Java-based Scheme System&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-9"&gt;A Scheme environment written in Java by Per Bothner. Scheme code is compiled to Java bytecode, hence has the property "write once run everywhere".&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://practical-scheme.net/index.html#docs"/><published>2025-10-21T05:47:39+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45653143</id><title>Language Support for Marginalia Search</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:54.382565+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f210038521b88b84"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the big ambitions for the search engine this year has been to enable searching in more languages than English, and a pilot project for this has just been completed, allowing experimental support for German, French and Swedish.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These changes are now live for testing, but with an extremely small corpus of documents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the search engine has been up to this point built with English in mind, some anglo-centric assumptions made it into its code. A lot of the research on search engines generally seems to embed similar assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As this is a domain rife with unknown unknowns, the ambition for this pilot was to implement support for just a few additional languages in order to get a feel for how much work would be required to support more languages in general, as well as to assess how much the index grows when this is done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though it was fully understood upfront that supporting all languages in one go is unrealistic, as some languages are more different than others and require significant additional work. Human language is surprisingly disparate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A language like Japanese, for example, has not only multiple alphabets, but embeds character width in unicode; on top of that the language doesn’t put spaces between words. As such the language requires special normalization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Latin, on the other hand, has dozens of forms for each word, and the words can often be reordered without significantly changing the meaning of a sentence. On the one hand this makes the grammatical analysis of the language somewhat easier since the words announce their function in the sentence fairly unambiguously, but on the other you probably need to store the text in a lemmatized form, and then strongly de-prioritize word order when matching.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google’s bungled handling of Russian was supposedly why Yandex was able to eke out a foothold in that market.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What needs changing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The search engine’s language processing chain is fairly long, but the most salient parts go something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text is extracted from the HTML&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Language is identified using fasttext&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text is broken into sentences&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Words are lowercased and Unicode is normalized&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sentences are stemmed and POS-tagged&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sentences, with stemming and POS-tag data is fed into keyword extraction algorithms&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Keywords are mapped to positions and HTML tags&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Important keywords are identified using TF-IDF (using stemmed forms)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Important keywords are identified using grammar patterns (POS-tags)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Important keywords are identified using other heuristics&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Keywords are hashed&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stemming is an imperfect way of getting a base form of a word, though generally such algorithms have a great number of flaws, so that e.g. universe and university seem to be the same word. This is only used in tf-idf calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part-of-Speech (POS) tagging is a grammatical annotation process where the role of each word is as best possible identified. This helps identify named entities, subjects, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both of these processes needless to say require some awareness of the language being acted upon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These “important keywords” are used to assign documents to a special index that helps with recall by ensuring these documents are included in the set that is ranked before the execution timer runs out. This is not strictly necessary, and in some cases such as where POS-tagging is not possible, can be disabled, partially or as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The normalization step is subject to cultural differences that do not translate. In English you’d probably expect to find the metal band TrÃ¶jan, typing “trojan”. In Swedish these are different letters entirely that should not match, the former means “the shirt”, the latter “trojan” in the Homeric or IT-security sense. Though a Swedish person would likely also say that they should be able to find mÃ¼(e)sli with the keyword “musli”, but a German-speaker would disagree and say that u and Ã¼ are clearly not the same.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There also exists a bootstrapping problem, as the statistical model used to calculate TF-IDF is based on documents in the index. Since almost all of the documents in the index up until this point have been in English, term frequencies for the newly added languages are missing. This breaks TF-IDF, as used in identifying important keywords, until a new model can be constructed. Thankfully the BM-25 model used in ranking is robust to this, as it relies on live data from the index itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The basic approach to parametrize language handling selected was to inject a language definition object, from which language appropriate logic is accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is configurable via XML. Here XML was chosen because it arguably has the best built-in validation support, making it a fantastic use case for a self-contained configuration file like this one, where late validation would be very annoying to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Much of the configuration file consists of various grammatical patterns used to identify important keywords based on the role of a word in a sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;ngrams type="noun"&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;VBG&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;RB VBG&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NNP* JJ)&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NN* JJ) NN*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NN* JJ) (NN* JJ) NN*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NN* JJ) (NN* JJ) (NN* JJ) NN*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NNP* JJ) (NNP* IN TO CC) NNP*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NNP* JJ) (NNP* IN TO CC) DT NNP*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;pospattern&amp;gt;(NNP* JJ) (NNP* IN TO CC) (NNP* IN TO CC) NNP*&amp;lt;/pospattern&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ngrams&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An expression like &lt;code&gt;(NN* JJ) (NN* JJ) NN*&lt;/code&gt; is interpreted as&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Any tag starting with &lt;code&gt;NN&lt;/code&gt;, or the tag&lt;code&gt;JJ&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Any tag starting with &lt;code&gt;NN&lt;/code&gt;, or the tag&lt;code&gt;JJ&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Any tag starting with &lt;code&gt;NN&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Previously these patterns were hard coded, and finding a performant alternative implementation took some effort. A bit mask approach was selected, as it allows for some very basic bit-level concurrency that drastically reduces the number of branches needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as grammatical analysis goes, the approach used by the search engine is pretty medieval, but it does do a fairly good job at what it sets out to do, and as a result, one thing it is generally pretty good at is finding websites about some topic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In some ways the imperfections introduced by the old-fashioned way of approaching language processing is almost helpful in bringing in more relevant results, as they tend to capture more variations of the words related to the topic of the document.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are more places that need minor language dependent behavior changes that are glossed over here, both in the language processing pipeline discussed above, and in the query parser, though in the interest of keeping this update from becoming an overly verbose git diff, these will be glossed over.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Tooling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To help make sense of this, a test tool was built that runs the language processing pipeline in isolation, and outputs annotated intermediate results for human inspection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work in this domain poses special problems that all but demand human testing. Machine testing can be good for catching regressions or getting access to some code for easier debugging, but natural language has so many nuances that any test suite is woefully inadequate compared to a pair of human eyeballs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has already helped refine the algorithms used to identify important keywords in English, which wasn’t the intent of building the tool, but its immediate consequence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Integration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Integrating the new multi-language search data into the system poses some design considerations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One option would be to stick everything in one big index, and then filter results based on language during or after ranking. The strength of this is that it becomes possible to search in any language without specifying it upfront.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The drawbacks of the one-index approach is that it grows the index, which makes all queries slower; it also grows the number of keywords in the lexicon, which is something that we generally want to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The way the search engine handles mapping keywords to numeric ids is to use a hash algorithm. Not a hash table, but the output of the hash algorithm itself. This seems absolutely unhinged at first glance, but works remarkably well as long as the lexicon stays small enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hash collisions do happen on rare occasions, but they need to happen between words where the words actually appear in the same documents to be a problem, generally leading to the ranking algorithm having to trudge through irrelevant documents and performing worse as a result of wasting its time budget.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Massively expanding the lexicon like we would if we were to mingle the documents increases the likelihood there will be an actual problem arising from these rare false positives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we stick every keyword from every language in the same index, a different problem arises, namely that homophones exist across different languages, meaning that the index lookup needs to wade through irrelevant documents that are trivially unrelated to the query.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The words &lt;code&gt;salt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lag&lt;/code&gt;, if they appear in the same document in English likely selects documents relating to esports, whereas in Swedish they select for documents relating to food preservation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The alternative option is to separate the indexes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The drawback here is that you must specify the language upfront, and querying in all languages becomes very expensive, as it executing multiple queries, though the desired language of the search results are generally known beforehand so this is a relatively small concern that, at best, affects a small number of machine-access use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since it has far fewer problems, and promises to be faster and more accurate, this approach was selected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In practice this was implemented as language-specific keyword-document mappings, that point into a common file containing document lists.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially the indexes were constructed from a common journal file, which was consumed repeatedly, but this turned out to be slow, and a partitioned approach was selected instead, with one journal per language. This almost completely removes any overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Outcome&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The changes discussed above have been implemented, and upon evaluation seems to work reasonably well, though evaluation has somewhat run into a dead end, as the index itself is extremely small for the newly added languages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The experience of small index is devious as it may just mean poor recall, though looking at the documents database for one index partition, this is about 12% of the index, it really is quite small!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;iso&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;document count&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;en&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;112,846,397&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;de&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7,623,983&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;fr&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4,852,759&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sv&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1,020,962&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To verify this is not due some silent, catastrophic processing error, the proportions were compared against the number of documents found in the 50 GB document sample used in testing, using a simplified process that only does language identification.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;iso&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;document count&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;en&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11,497,571&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;de&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;614,311&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;fr&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;409,877&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;es&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;267,408&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ja&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;217,599&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;nl&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;196,130&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&amp;amp;mldr;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&amp;amp;mldr;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sv&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;67,670&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proportions aren’t identical, but in the same general ballpark. The small size of the sample, along with the uneven distribution and apparent rarity of these documents adequately explains the disparity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lack of documents in languages other than English is likely due to how the index has been grown, by following and adding links from English websites. These occasionally lead to bilingual websites, and on rare occasions to websites completely in a different language, though it seems reasonable most websites that are not at least partially in English sees few or no links from English-language websites.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adding to the problem, up until fairly recently the index wasn’t really growing very much at all, only through manual submissions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond a certain point, meaningfully growing the index by just following links became difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most known domains are dead, so merely adding more domains to the list of websites to crawl only serves to pollute the database with junk data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order to get around this, and reach the goal of indexing a billion documents, a new process was built to visit candidate websites to verify that they are in fact real and on-line, before assigning them to an index partition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The process has been running for almost a quarter, and has managed to identify about 800,000 viable new domains in that time window. (This has brought the document total up to 969M documents. So very nearly there now!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Web search is unusual in how often you run into these extremely long running processes that need to cook for months, sometimes up to a year before they really begin to pay off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll have to see whether building this new process was so prescient it ends up being sufficient to identify and add new domains in more languages, as links from the newly processed Swedish, French and German websites have been added to the domain database, or if some sort of manual seeding or targeted selection process is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems plausible it will at least begin to remedy the data starvation, as the rate of successful domain discovery has shot up significantly since processing links from the documents processed in the newly added languages, and many of the new domains are indeed from &lt;code&gt;.de&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.se&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.fr&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;.ch&lt;/code&gt; domains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For now we’ll have to wait and see how the data-set evolves. It is difficult to further refine the multi-language aspect of the search data with a data-set this small.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.marginalia.nu/log/a_126_multilingual/"/><published>2025-10-21T06:48:53+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45653350</id><title>Show HN: I'm rewriting a web server written in Rust for speed and ease of use</title><updated>2025-10-21T08:45:53.576978+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="fdb285ba2972be9c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would you like to use stable version of Ferron? Visit Ferron 1.x website&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ferron is a fast web server with automatic TLS certificate management, easy configuration, and rock-solid security — so you can go live in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Command unavailable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch, as Ferron serves a website with automatic TLS setup in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite powering much of the internet, popular web servers (such as Apache and NGINX) weren't designed for ease of use, security, or modern developer experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you spent hours configuring a web server just to set up a website? NGINX configs can become verbose, even for something as common as a high-performance reverse proxy. Apache's directives can be hard to navigate too, with many options that can make simple tasks needlessly hard.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many popular web servers (including Apache and NGINX) are written in programming languages and use libraries that aren't designed for memory safety. This caused many issues, such as Heartbleed in OpenSSL, putting servers at unnecessary risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apache's architecture can struggle under modern workloads, often underperforming compared to newer, leaner servers. This means wasted resources and slower response times for your website visitors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Designed with modern web hosting needs in mind, Ferron combines speed, security, and ease of use in one powerful package.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thoroughly optimized for speed with support for high concurrency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Built with memory safety as a priority, eliminating common security vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Automatic SSL/TLS certificate acquisition and renewal with Let's Encrypt integration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simple, intuitive configuration with sensible, secure defaults and comprehensive documentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advanced reverse proxy capabilities with support for load balancing and health checks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Built-in support for modern API patterns including WebSockets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discover how Ferron simplifies the process of securing your website with HTTPS through automatic TLS management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ferrondemo&lt;/code&gt; of your domain name (for example, &lt;code&gt;ferrondemo.example.com&lt;/code&gt;) to either:&lt;p&gt;You will notice how Ferron manages the TLS certificate for your subdomain automatically.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not working? Check your DNS settings and ensure that the subdomain is correctly pointing to the IP address or CNAME provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ferron can outperform other popular web servers in performance benchmark tests across different workloads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Higher is better | Benchmarks run on AMD Ryzen 5 8600G, 32GB RAM, with the &lt;code&gt;ferrbench -c 1000 -d 60s -t 12 -h https://localhost --http2&lt;/code&gt; command | Benchmarks performed on September 19, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Higher is better | Benchmarks run on AMD Ryzen 5 8600G, 32GB RAM, with the &lt;code&gt;ferrbench -c $CONCURRENCY -d 5s -t 12 -h https://localhost --http2&lt;/code&gt; command | Benchmarks performed on September 25, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lower is better | Benchmarks run on AMD Ryzen 5 8600G, 32GB RAM, with the &lt;code&gt;ferrbench -c $CONCURRENCY -d 5s -t 12 -h https://localhost --http2&lt;/code&gt; command | Benchmarks performed on September 25, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Higher is better | Benchmarks run on AMD Ryzen 5 8600G, 32GB RAM, with the &lt;code&gt;ferrbench -c 100 -d 60s -t 12 -h https://localhost --http2&lt;/code&gt; command | Benchmarks performed on June 13, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get started with Ferron in minutes. Choose your preferred platform and installation method.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Command unavailable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ferron has simple, intuitive configuration, compared to more complex configurations of some popular web servers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;server {
    listen 80;
    listen 443 ssl http2;

    server_name example.com;
    server_tokens off;

    # Assuming you use Certbot for automatic certificate management
    ssl_certificate /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/fullchain.pem;
    ssl_certificate_key /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/privkey.pem;

    root /var/www/html;
    gzip on;

    location / {
        try_files $uri $uri/ =404;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;// TLS certificate is obtained automatically by Ferron
example.com {
    root "/var/www/html"
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;upstream backend {
    server localhost:3000;
    keepalive 32;
}

server {
    listen 80;
    listen 443 ssl http2;

    server_name example.com;
    server_tokens off;

    # Assuming you use Certbot for automatic certificate management
    ssl_certificate /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/fullchain.pem;
    ssl_certificate_key /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/privkey.pem;

    location / {
        proxy_pass http://backend/;
        proxy_http_version 1.1;
        proxy_set_header Upgrade $http_upgrade;
        proxy_set_header Connection 'upgrade';
        proxy_set_header Host $host;
        proxy_cache_bypass $http_upgrade;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;// TLS certificate is obtained automatically by Ferron
example.com {
    proxy "http://localhost:3000"
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;server {
    listen 80;
    listen 443 ssl http2;

    server_name example.com;
    server_tokens off;

    # Assuming you use Certbot for automatic certificate management
    ssl_certificate /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/fullchain.pem;
    ssl_certificate_key /etc/letsencrypt/live/example.com/privkey.pem;

    root /var/www/html;
    index index.php index.html index.htm;

    location / {
        gzip on;
        try_files $uri $uri/ =404;
    }

    location ~ \.php$ {
        fastcgi_split_path_info ^(.+\.php)(/.+)$;
        fastcgi_pass unix:/var/run/php/php-fpm.sock;
        set $path_info $fastcgi_path_info;
        fastcgi_param PATH_INFO $path_info;
        fastcgi_index index.php;
        # The "fastcgi.conf" is located in the NGINX configuration directory (at least on Debian-based systems)
        include fastcgi.conf;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;// TLS certificate is obtained automatically by Ferron
example.com {
    root "/var/www/html"
    // Check if the PHP-FPM socket file is accessible by the web server user, often "ferron"
    fcgi_php "unix:///var/run/php/php-fpm.sock"
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don't take our word for it — hear from the system administrators and developers who use Ferron every day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I suspect that people don't like changing web servers, and perhaps that's why it took the industry so long to move away from Apache. Ferron actually looks great â great performance, automatic TLS, easy reverse proxy configuration and more. Congrats on shipping this!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may want to check out what Ferron is doing. I've been using it for a few months. Highly recommend. (...) Significantly easier to set up than nginx, and by far the most effortless auto TLS integration. (...) Highly recommend using the v2 docker images though. It now uses KDL for configuration, which is much cleaner than YAML. The syntax is versatile enough that you can create a custom DSL of sorts. Ferron uses it to replicate if statements, and uses them to filter access by IP or headers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Join many sysadmins and developers using Ferron to serve websites faster, more securely, and with less overhead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://ferron.sh/"/><published>2025-10-21T07:26:57+00:00</published></entry></feed>