<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><id>hnrss.org/frontpage</id><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:56.009331+00:00</updated><link href="https://news.ycombinator.com/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator><subtitle>Hacker News RSS</subtitle><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45322135</id><title>Why your outdoorsy friend suddenly has a gummy bear power bank</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:03.614168+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="6e4c575fa8a6d42e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like many backpackers, I’m a sicko. I have weighed all my gear in order to maintain a spreadsheet for pack weight on every trip I’m on. I’ve spent more money than I care to think about in order to drop pounds, or even ounces. This is why I’m the proud new owner of a power bank that looks like a toy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why your outdoorsy friend suddenly has a gummy bear power bank&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s… ultralight?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s… ultralight?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s the Haribo-licensed gummy bear power bank. It’s the lightest-ever 20,000mAH power bank, it’s got a gummy-bear themed built-in USB-C cord, and it’s taking over the ultralight backpacking world. The specs say it weighs 9.9 ounces — and in a world where ounces count, that’s a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultralight culture seems a little nuts to the uninitiated. Probably most people do not measure every piece of equipment they carry for weekend backpacking trips. But when you are hiking more than 10 miles a day, especially if you are walking up mountains, you start looking for stuff to get rid of — because even being two pounds lighter is a tremendous relief. The “ideal” baseweight for ultralighters is below 10 pounds, though below 20 is considered respectable. If you’re hiking more than 100 miles, every ounce counts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ultralight movement is why a lot of backpackers wear trail runners instead of hiking boots, and why a lot of tents now incorporate hiking poles so users don’t have to carry separate poles for freestanding tents. Since 1991, when Ray Jardin published The PCT Hikers Handbook, lots of new companies specializing in the lightest possible equipment have sprung up — as have online communities like r/ultralight. In these communities, there’s a ritual called the “shakedown,” where users post their packs and other people tell them how to cut weight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So of course this community was first to the exciting new world of gummy bear charging.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The previous preferred 20k powerbank was a Nitecore build. It’s a serious-looking black box built out of carbon fiber; it costs about $100 and tips the scale at 10.3 ounces. My goofy toy power bank costs $23; it weighed slightly more than the promised specs at 9.95 ounces. It has pass-through charging, just like the Nitecore and allows for fast charging, too. This is like discovering a Volkswagen Beetle can out-haul a Tesla Cybertruck.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And when I say it’s sweeping the backpacking world, I don’t just mean online. I got a text from my Appalachian-trail hiking buddy just last week — he’d weighed his new Haribo bank against his old Anker bank, and the Haribo won. He included photos and everything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In writing this post, I was trying to figure out why this exists at all. That was how I discovered there’s a whole Haribo line — a mouse, a wall charger, earbuds, charging cables, and a wireless powerbank. It appears to be a brand collab that was crowdfunded in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the power bank won’t charge through the built-in gummy bear cable, so you’ll have to carry a USB-C cable to get juice on a resupply stop. But still, from the people who brought you “bread bags on your feet to stay dry when it’s raining,” there’s a new ridiculous outdoor device winning hearts and minds. I haven’t done capacity testing yet, but if it does what the specs promise, the most hard-core battery pack an ultralighter can buy is decorated with gummy bears.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Most Popular&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anker’s latest sleep buds can silence snoring&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Amazon, Google, and Microsoft warn employees to rush back to the US&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why PlayStation and Xbox are no longer about the station or the box&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why your outdoorsy friend suddenly has a gummy bear power bank&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trump’s H-1B visa fee isn’t just about immigration, it’s about fealty&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.theverge.com/tech/781387/backpacking-ultralight-haribo-power-bank"/><published>2025-09-21T12:31:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45322819</id><title>I forced myself to spend a week in Instagram instead of Xcode</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:03.114871+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3bcc78561ea6cefc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;I forced myself to spend a week in Instagram instead of Xcode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;This is what happens when you ban yourself from coding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Let’s set the stage:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The Lagree Buddy app has enough quality features that this is an actual, useful thing that I feel comfortable promoting &amp;amp; charging money for.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;There are more features I want to build, but they’re bigger features and are still weeks from releasing (because I need to QA them in the real world).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Since the hard paywall and overhauled onboarding (discussed here), there has been a noticeable increase in purchases (woohoo! see chart below)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Given the information above, I figured I should try an experiment.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;What if I spent every business hour on marketing/distribution instead of coding and building more features?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That felt so uncomfortable to even say out loud because it meant spending a week on social media and talking to people about the app. But it also meant not hiding inside the code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So here’s a detailed (but slightly stream of consciousness) recap of how that week went.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Day 1 || Monday, August 25th&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If any influencers out there want to give me some tips on how to IG correctly, please do. But my current thought process is to craft a story arc for one day. And then to break that arc into 4-6 posts, to be posted every 3 hours or so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I do this because I don’t want it to feel salesy or spammy. So I at least inject some sort of narrative. So today’s story arc was:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Working on new feature at home, but oh no! it’s broken!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Thought I fixed it and took it to class, but oh no! still broken!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I found out why it was broken, explained it, and took it into another class …&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;FIXED.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;FIXED 2.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;FIXED 3.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also spent the day reaching out to new studios &amp;amp; trainers I saw wearing Apple Watches. Sent out 10 today and got 2 responses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Day 2 || Tuesday, August 26th&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I bought a Microformer last week, so let’s use the thing for some content!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I signed up for Lagreeing at Home, found an instructor with an Apple Watch, snapped a lot of photos, and got busy creating and scheduling another story arc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I almost immediately got a response from Lagreeing at Home about collabing, and I’d have to say… that’s a pretty big win. Lagreeing at Home was born out of the pandemic and has been an incredible presence in the Lagree community, so hearing some affirmation from them is a fantastic feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wanted to do more cold DM’s to studios and trainers today, too, but sometimes the Apple Gods say “try again tomorrow” (wheel of death! see below).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Day 3 || Wednesday, August 27th&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s only been two days, but I’ve been struggling with the actual creation of content itself. Struggling might be the wrong word… underestimate? I underestimated the amount of work it takes!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I planned everything out on Monday. But then you have to obviously create the stuff, and all of that takes so long! So today, today is going to be an FAQ series. But the question is how to create it creatively so it’s not just social media slop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And after playing with a basic Q&amp;amp;A and not liking how it looked (aka ugly and sales-y) ... I went hunting on Reddit and found this incredible tool (Postfully) to create fake text messages and came up with this for my Q&amp;amp;A instead:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Day 4 || Thursday, August 28th&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I signed up for THE Sebastian Lagree’s class on Sunday. Three reasons why:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I want to show him the app in person&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I’m running out of content and I need some photos of a new studio 😅&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I’m getting sick of social media and wanted to do something in real life loll&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I needed a break from creating content, so I cheated and repurposed my IG stories into TikTok videos. But I didn’t want to give up on my mission, so I fell back on cold messaging studios and trainers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Getting any response is a nice feeling, but this message back from new studio Hold Fitness was incredible! She saw my original post on Reddit from 6 months ago!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Day 5 || Friday, August 29th&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am absolutely ITCHING to get back to the code!!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I am trying to stick to my mission for the week and am racking my brain on what content to come up without sounding repetitive or spammy. Thank goodness I went to class yesterday and took a bunch of b-roll footage because an idea quickly formed that felt different enough from everything before it this week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This might have been the hardest day to stick to this challenge. Because everything inside of me was screaming:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“CAN WE FOR THE LOVE OF GOD GET OFF OF SOCIAL MEDIA AND DO SOMETHING PRODUCTIVE LIKE BUILD MORE FEATURES.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the thing that I had to constantly remind myself of is that this is productive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build it and they will come is a fallacy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have to tell people about the damn thing. It just doesn’t feel productive because you’re over here churning and burning things that feel like they have a shelf-life of 24 hours (if even that). And sending out cold DM’s and hoping for 1 or 2 responses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Day 6 || Saturday, August 30th&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Day of rest. &lt;lb/&gt;Sorry, not sorry.&lt;lb/&gt;But I did not code, so the challenge is still intact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Day 7 || Sunday August 31th&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sebastian Lagree day!!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I drove to Brentwood to take a class from SEBASTIAN LAGREE himself. I was pretty nervous because I wasn’t sure if he was going to think my app was stupid or if it was weird, but he honestly couldn’t have been nicer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He’s also an insanely good instructor, which seems obvious, but when you only see someone on IG as an “influencer”, you’re not entirely sure what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But his class was f-ing legit. But be warned, it may or may not be 60 minutes long 😂. Most classes I’ve taken are 45 minutes, but if you like to get there early (like I do), he will start the class early and end the class late and have you BURNING. My max HR hit 172, and I was sore for a week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also had an entire plan of going home and editing/posting the content from this day, but like I said, I was sore for a week. So, the immediate aftermath of this class was me just lying down on the couch. No content was edited, posted, or thought about for the rest of the day loll.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Footnote: Because I’m always looking at people’s wrists for Apple Watches in class now, I couldn’t help but notice the lady next to me. Most people wear a fitness tracker in class or nothing at all. But this lady next to me was rocking this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;End of Week Results &amp;amp; Takeaways&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cold DMs actually work (sometimes). I sent maybe 30-40 messages total and got 4-5 meaningful responses. That's not amazing, but it's infinitely better than the zero responses you get when you never reach out at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marketing opens doors that code never could. Sebastian seeing my app in person matters more than any feature I could have shipped that week. You can't build your way into someone's awareness - you have to actually show up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can't analytics your way to relationships. The numbers didn't move (see chart below), but the connections did. Having Lagreeing at Home and Sebastian Lagree be aware of the app and the person behind the app should pay dividends in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Content creation is way harder than I thought. As an engineer, I assumed making an Instagram story would take 10 minutes. Turns out creating something that doesn't look like garbage takes a couple of hours. And doing it daily? Forget about it. I planned a whole week of content on Monday and ended up creating everything day-of because I completely underestimated the work involved.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.pixelpusher.club/p/i-forced-myself-to-spend-a-week-in"/><published>2025-09-21T14:00:16+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45323027</id><title>Unified Line and Paragraph Detection by Graph Convolutional Networks (2022)</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:02.980108+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d9db40ad4d580ca"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Cryptography and Security&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 7 Mar 2025 (v1), last revised 8 Sep 2025 (this version, v15)]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:The Beginner's Textbook for Fully Homomorphic Encryption&lt;/head&gt;View PDF&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:Fully Homomorphic Encryption (FHE) is a cryptographic scheme that enables computations to be performed directly on encrypted data, as if the data were in plaintext. After all computations are performed on the encrypted data, it can be decrypted to reveal the result. The decrypted value matches the result that would have been obtained if the same computations were applied to the plaintext data.&lt;lb/&gt;FHE supports basic operations such as addition and multiplication on encrypted numbers. Using these fundamental operations, more complex computations can be constructed, including subtraction, division, logic gates (e.g., AND, OR, XOR, NAND, MUX), and even advanced mathematical functions such as ReLU, sigmoid, and trigonometric functions (e.g., sin, cos). These functions can be implemented either as exact formulas or as approximations, depending on the trade-off between computational efficiency and accuracy.&lt;lb/&gt;FHE enables privacy-preserving machine learning by allowing a server to process the client's data in its encrypted form through an ML model. With FHE, the server learns neither the plaintext version of the input features nor the inference results. Only the client, using their secret key, can decrypt and access the results at the end of the service protocol. FHE can also be applied to confidential blockchain services, ensuring that sensitive data in smart contracts remains encrypted and confidential while maintaining the transparency and integrity of the execution process. Other applications of FHE include secure outsourcing of data analytics, encrypted database queries, privacy-preserving searches, efficient multi-party computation for digital signatures, and more.&lt;lb/&gt;As this book is an open project (this https URL), we welcome FHE experts to join us as collaborators to help expand the draft.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Submission history&lt;/head&gt;From: Ronny Ko [view email]&lt;p&gt;[v1] Fri, 7 Mar 2025 04:29:11 UTC (33 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v2] Thu, 13 Mar 2025 15:18:50 UTC (5,237 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v3] Fri, 14 Mar 2025 03:22:13 UTC (5,239 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v4] Sun, 13 Apr 2025 13:14:01 UTC (5,258 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v5] Sat, 26 Apr 2025 18:20:16 UTC (5,275 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v6] Sun, 4 May 2025 15:31:10 UTC (5,302 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v7] Mon, 12 May 2025 17:20:32 UTC (5,099 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v8] Tue, 20 May 2025 16:04:22 UTC (5,062 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v9] Mon, 26 May 2025 03:42:34 UTC (5,062 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v10] Sun, 1 Jun 2025 08:45:01 UTC (4,570 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v11] Sun, 8 Jun 2025 04:45:52 UTC (4,571 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v12] Mon, 30 Jun 2025 13:04:04 UTC (4,570 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v13] Mon, 7 Jul 2025 09:54:47 UTC (4,570 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v14] Wed, 13 Aug 2025 04:21:08 UTC (4,570 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v15] Mon, 8 Sep 2025 05:39:49 UTC (4,570 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05136"/><published>2025-09-21T14:26:10+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45323207</id><title>DXGI debugging: Microsoft put me on a list</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:02.462774+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="260f8913c3239dc4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;DXGI debugging: Microsoft put me on a list&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why does Space Station 14 crash with ANGLE on ARM64? 6 hours later…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So. I’ve been continuing work on getting ARM64 builds out for Space Station 14. The thing I was working on yesterday were launcher builds, specifically a single download that supports both ARM64 and x64. I’d already gotten the game client itself running natively on ARM64, and it worked perfectly fine in my dev environment. I wrote all the new launcher code, am pretty sure I got it right. Zip it up, test it on ARM64, aaand…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game client crashes on Windows ARM64. Both in my VM and on Julian’s real Snapdragon X laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Debugging: logs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The client logs are empty. They suspiciously cut out right after SDL is initialized.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course it isn’t that easy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Debugging: pulling WinDbg out of the shed&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given that there’s no logs, this has to be a native crash. That means it’s WinDbg time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So at first I decided to start &lt;code&gt;Space Station 14 Launcher.exe&lt;/code&gt; directly through WinDbg. This is annoying because I have to go into child processes (with &lt;code&gt;.childdbg 1&lt;/code&gt;) twice, and for some reason there’s a lot of waiting, but it does work…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game crashes in &lt;code&gt;USER32!GetDC&lt;/code&gt; on an illegal instruction, somewhere after SDL does something. I barely glanced at the disassembly but it made no sense to me, so I just assumed there’s some UB happening and didn’t think much of it. After all, why would the implementation of &lt;code&gt;GetDC()&lt;/code&gt; have broken assembly?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(3148.35e4): Illegal instruction - code c000001d (first chance)
(3148.35e4): Unknown exception - code c000041d (!!! second chance !!!)
*** WARNING: Unable to verify checksum for C:\Users\Luna\Downloads\SS14.Launcher_Windows\bin_arm64\loader\SDL3.DLL
USER32!GetDC+0x8:
00007ff9`f7be9548 ee8e1db0 ???
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WinDbg was also unable to pull stack frames from C# code. It did, thankfully, clearly communicate why this was. Yep, it’s our friend &lt;code&gt;mscordaccore&lt;/code&gt; again!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CLRDLL: Consider using ".cordll -lp &amp;lt;path&amp;gt;" command to specify .NET runtime directory.
CLRDLL: Consider using ".cordll -lp &amp;lt;path&amp;gt;" command to specify .NET runtime directory.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, my attempts to actually follow said instructions were completely fruitless, giving this error:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;0:027:ARM64EC&amp;gt; .cordll -lp C:\Users\Luna\Downloads\SS14.Launcher_Windows\dotnet_arm64\shared\Microsoft.NETCore.App\9.0.9
CLRDLL: Consider using ".cordll -lp &amp;lt;path&amp;gt;" command to specify .NET runtime directory.
CLR DLL status: ERROR: Unable to load DLL C:\Users\Luna\Downloads\SS14.Launcher_Windows\dotnet_arm64\shared\Microsoft.NETCore.App\9.0.9\mscordaccore_AMD64_arm64_9.0.925.41916.dll, Win32 error 0n87
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why is it trying to run an &lt;code&gt;AMD64&lt;/code&gt; binary? Wait is WinDbg not natively compiled for ARM64? Sigh. Let’s just do it without C# debugging, I can probably manage based off the SDL stack trace. So I pull &lt;code&gt;SDL3.pdb&lt;/code&gt; from our server, drop it next to &lt;code&gt;SDL3.dll&lt;/code&gt;, and then use the UI to reload the symbols. And that gets us a bit further, we now have proper function names for SDL3!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I double click one of the entries in the UI’s stack trace view. And the entire debugger breaks. Stack trace view goes empty. Every action I try to make causes more of these errors to be printed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Machine is not a possible execution machine
Unable to get current machine context, HRESULT 0x8000FFFF
Machine is not a possible execution machine
Unable to get current machine context, HRESULT 0x8000FFFF
Machine is not a possible execution machine
Unable to get current machine context, HRESULT 0x8000FFFF
Machine is not a possible execution machine
Machine is not a possible execution machine
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now even WinDbg is broken??&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Googling these errors gave nothing useful. One of them gave not a single result. After just pondering the error for a moment, I thought “wait, why is the command prompt still saying &lt;code&gt;ARM64EC&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;? ARM64EC is for emulation, but the active debugger processes (&lt;code&gt;SS14.Launcher.exe&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;SS14.Loader.exe&lt;/code&gt;) are both native ARM64.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turns out that it’s because I started &lt;code&gt;Space Station 14 Launcher.exe&lt;/code&gt; directly. You see, that executable is x64 native, and its only job is to set up the .NET environment and launch the actual ARM64 executable. Something about starting the debugging session with that program causes WinDbg to get extremely confused when later looking at the child processes it spawns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From this point on I just started launching &lt;code&gt;SS14.Launcher.exe&lt;/code&gt; directly1. This means I wasn’t setting up the same &lt;code&gt;DOTNET_ROOT&lt;/code&gt; (because WinDbg can’t set environment variables when launching things… yes really), but this didn’t really matter. This fixed both the “Machine is not a possible execution machine” errors and the issues with showing C# stack traces. I guess WinDbg is compiled for ARM64 after all, and it just decided to run an x64 debug host when you start debugging an x64 application. Fair enough I guess?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Debugging: what’s SDL doing?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After figuring out all of the above, we could really get started. I also opted to swap out &lt;code&gt;SDL3.dll&lt;/code&gt; with a locally-built copy, so that the debugger could locate source files2. What SDL is doing is pretty straight forward: the first time the window is shown, it clears the background with GDI commands:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I mean… this is like, fine, right? I mean I don’t know much about this code, but why would this crash on ARM but not x64??? The window is valid. &lt;code&gt;GetDC()&lt;/code&gt; is an extremely fundamental Win32 function call. If there was something broken with it, my OS would not be usable. What the fuck is going on?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;if (ShouldClearWindowOnEraseBackground(data))&lt;/code&gt; allows it to be disabled via a hint, which can be specified by environment variable. This fixes the crash… until you open a second OS window, then SDL3 calls &lt;code&gt;GetDC()&lt;/code&gt; once again and that crashes. Not a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I checked the actual &lt;code&gt;USER32!GetDC&lt;/code&gt; again, and this time I actually paid attention to the disassembly code instead of glossing over it. What the fuck? &lt;code&gt;pacibsp&lt;/code&gt; is missing at the start. It’s loading an address for a jump that only jumps to the next instruction, which is invalid. In some runs, said instruction was instead a broken &lt;code&gt;x26&lt;/code&gt;-relative &lt;code&gt;str&lt;/code&gt; instruction that AV’d because the register was all zeroes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point let’s introduce the villain. You might have noticed it in the call stack: &lt;code&gt;DXGI!My_GetDC&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For those who aren’t well-versed in DirectX stuff: DXGI is a fundamental part of DirectX ever since DirectX 10 (Vista). For those who have never modded a game before: a detour is a hack that injects instructions into other functions at runtime, to do evil shit. Why the hell is Microsoft using this in DXGI?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Debugging: DXGI despair&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through the debugging adventure, I ended up putting a breakpoint on every call to &lt;code&gt;USER32!GetDC&lt;/code&gt;. The first few calls are fine, but then the last one, the one that crashes, is not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point I got really desperate. “Asking in low-level programming Discords”-level desperate. I ended up asking for help in the DirectX Discord (yes, there’s an official DirectX Discord, and there’s many MS employees in there).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Jesse Natalia from the DirectX Discord for responding swiftly to my messages in there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After some back and forth there, I wanted to catch DXGI in the act. Maybe that would tell me something, I don’t know. So with a simple &lt;code&gt;ba w4 USER32!GetDC&lt;/code&gt;, I put a hardware breakpoint for whenever something would write to &lt;code&gt;USER32!GetDC&lt;/code&gt;. I did have to awkwardly “run the program for just a little bit” because &lt;code&gt;USER32.dll&lt;/code&gt; isn’t loaded immediately at program startup.3&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While writing this blog post I realized there is an intelligent way to do this. It’s called &lt;code&gt;sxe ld USER32.dll&lt;/code&gt;. I’ve literally written about it in this blog before. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now this is very interesting. The bottom of the stack trace is quite expected: SDL creates a window, uses ANGLE’s EGL implementation for this, that does a bunch of stuff, and eventually creates a DXGI swapchain. But then what is &lt;code&gt;UpgradeSwapEffect&lt;/code&gt;? And why is it installing a detour?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ah, I already know what this is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Optimizing windowed games: flip model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right. So. DirectX.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you create a DirectX swapchain, you specify an “effect”, which falls into two categories: “bitblt” and “flip”. To make a long story short: bitblt is the “original” one, while flip is the much more modern one added in Windows 84. It’s more efficient and performant, and all software should be using it. Furthermore, on modern versions of Windows and with a GPU supporting “Multiplane Overlays”, flip model actually enables windowed games to be displayed with zero additional latency over “exclusive” fullscreen mode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, many games never get updated, or they’re stuck on an ancient version. And many of these games don’t care. So in Windows 11, Microsoft added “Optimizations for windowed games”, which forcibly enables flip model on games that are still using bitblt. Why does DXGI need to install detours for this? Probably some compatibility shit with the bitblt model. I don’t have any deep knowledge of how Win32 GDI stuff works, but it’s not hard for me to imagine there’s some interplay here they need to take care of. I can also confirm that disabling the feature in Windows’ settings menu fixes the crash!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re wondering why SS14 isn’t using flip model: it’s because we can’t. We’re not creating the swapchain directly, ANGLE is. And ANGLE is continuing to use &lt;code&gt;SWAP_EFFECT_SEQUENTIAL&lt;/code&gt;. I actually once experimented with SS14 managing the swapchain, but this ran into some ANGLE limitations and I never got around to ironing out all the edge cases and crashes. I’d rather just spend the brain power on ditching OpenGL, rather than trying to continue working with this broken API.5.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So here we are. The entire debugging story so far, you’re like, “surely Microsoft didn’t break DXGI on ARM64, huh???” But now it’s becoming plausible. There’s barely any native ARM64 Windows games, and surely none that are using bitblt swapchains. And guess what, you don’t even need &lt;code&gt;GetDC()&lt;/code&gt; for modern DirectX games. SDL does it because it’s heavily designed for OpenGL. Most games run in x64 emulation, and that presumably works fine. Everything adds up to it being possible this just genuinely fell under the radar at Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This should be pretty easy to verify in a minimal example. I cloned an old DirectX SDK sample, updated it to be compiled for ARM64, added some &lt;code&gt;GetDC()&lt;/code&gt; calls, aaand… nope, no crash. Then I spent quite a while trying various stuff: comparing the swapchain creation code with that of ANGLE, changing various parameters, verifying whether the detour was being installed (it wasn’t). But eventually, I did find it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s the filename.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course it’s the goddamn filename.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;I’m on a list&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It only happens when the program is called &lt;code&gt;SS14.Loader.exe&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final piece of the puzzle. It didn’t happen in a dev environment because then the exe isn’t named &lt;code&gt;SS14.Loader.exe&lt;/code&gt;. Microsoft only enables “Optimizations for windowed games” on a specific list of games. And guess what, none of those select games are on ARM64, at least until I was unfortunate enough to port mine. How did we get on the list? Who knows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft put me on a list, that ships with every Windows install. And this list actually broke my game. Achievement unlocked!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Addendum: why ANGLE, and about OpenGL on Windows ARM64&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traditionally, OpenGL on Windows has been implemented by the 3 IHVs (Nvidia, AMD, Intel). If they didn’t explicitly go out of their way to add it to their drivers, you’d have no OpenGL beyond 1.0. Those new Snapdragon X devices, however, use Microsoft’s new-ish “OpenGL on D3D12” driver. It’s actually part of Mesa!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem with Space Station 14 is that said driver is broken for us, causing severe graphical artifacts and flickering. I had been aware of this for years, because the same driver is used for the GPU acceleration of WSL2, but I never bothered to report it 😬. So for the purpose of porting SS14 to ARM64 Windows, I decided to just immediately force on ANGLE on Qualcomm devices, and call it a day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I didn’t know until yesterday is that the OpenGL on D3D12 driver does not ship with Qualcomm’s drivers! It’s on the Microsoft store! I can even install it in my VM and get it to emulate OpenGL on top of DirectX’s software renderer (WARP), just like I had been doing with ANGLE. I’ve finally bothered to report the graphical issues, so hopefully it gets fixed eventually. If it does get fixed, Microsoft Store distribution means it shouldn’t take too long to trickle down to users, and then we can stop enforcing ANGLE on Qualcomm devices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Space Station 14, I will say that this means I’ll be postponing official Windows ARM64 support for now. At least until either bug (OpenGL on D3D12 or ARM64 DXGI detours) are fixed. Or when I finally rewrite the renderer to drop OpenGL, that’s also an option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Addendum: clarifications&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(This bit added a few hours after publishing)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“Why not just rename the &lt;code&gt;.exe&lt;/code&gt;on ARM”: what I didn’t mention is that Steamworks does not support ARM64 Linux or Windows, at the moment. That means ARM64 builds will not be on Steam regardless, and I didn’t feel like going through even more the effort to add a workaround, just to improve performance for that 0.001% of people playing the game on a Snapdragon X device while also downloading from our website. And God forbid Microsoft updates the list later based on a bulk import of some random filenames and catches the new name too. The game already works when emulated, so I’m leaving it there until Windows is fixed.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Debugging&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;SS14.Loader.exe&lt;/code&gt;directly would be a pain in the ass because it needs like a dozen arguments and environment variables configured by the launcher. I’d rather not. ↩︎&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I assume there’s a way to configure WinDbg to load these if the paths don’t line up properly… but I wouldn’t know how. Lol. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is because, being a .NET app, most native libraries are dynamically loaded at runtime. Only libraries that are direct dependencies of the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;.exe&lt;/code&gt;are available in the “initial debugger break” period before the program really starts. ↩︎&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you were one of those people that held onto Windows 7 for as long as possible, this is the kind of shit you were missing out on. Seriously, 8.1 was fine. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Fuck EGL especially. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://slugcat.systems/post/25-09-21-dxgi-debugging-microsoft-put-me-on-a-list/"/><published>2025-09-21T14:45:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45324343</id><title>Timesketch: Collaborative forensic timeline analysis</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:02.262093+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="f7201de7e5f62665"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Timesketch is an open-source tool for collaborative forensic timeline analysis. Using sketches you and your collaborators can easily organize your timelines and analyze them all at the same time. Add meaning to your raw data with rich annotations, comments, tags and stars.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is not an official Google product (experimental or otherwise), it is just code that happens to be owned by Google.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/google/timesketch"/><published>2025-09-21T16:43:19+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45324349</id><title>Sj.h: A tiny little JSON parsing library in ~150 lines of C99</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:01.726468+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="afd877d9ee5a4e03"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A tiny little JSON parsing library&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;~150 lines of C99&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Zero-allocations with minimal state&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Error messages with &lt;code&gt;line:column:&lt;/code&gt;location&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No number parsing: &lt;code&gt;strtod&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;atoi&lt;/code&gt;? Handle them how you want&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No string parsing: bring your own unicode surrogate pair handling (or don't)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A small program to load a rectangle from a JSON string into a &lt;code&gt;Rect&lt;/code&gt; struct:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;char *json_text = "{ \"x\": 10, \"y\": 20, \"w\": 30, \"h\": 40 }";

typedef struct { int x, y, w, h; } Rect;

bool eq(sj_Value val, char *s) {
    size_t len = val.end - val.start;
    return strlen(s) == len &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !memcmp(s, val.start, len);
}

int main(void) {
    Rect rect = {0};

    sj_Reader r = sj_reader(json_text, strlen(json_text));
    sj_Value obj = sj_read(&amp;amp;r);

    sj_Value key, val;
    while (sj_iter_object(&amp;amp;r, obj, &amp;amp;key, &amp;amp;val)) {
        if (eq(key, "x")) { rect.x = atoi(val.start); }
        if (eq(key, "y")) { rect.y = atoi(val.start); }
        if (eq(key, "w")) { rect.w = atoi(val.start); }
        if (eq(key, "h")) { rect.h = atoi(val.start); }
    }

    printf("rect: { %d, %d, %d, %d }\n", rect.x, rect.y, rect.w, rect.h);
    return 0;
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See the demo folder for further usage examples.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is free and unencumbered software released into the public domain. See LICENSE for details.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/rxi/sj.h"/><published>2025-09-21T16:43:45+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45326690</id><title>Procedural Island Generation (VI)</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:01.560509+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9968ebcc5b77ecfe"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Procedural Island Generation (VI)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the final installment of our procedural island generation series. After building the mesh foundation (Part I), painting elevation hints (Part II), adding mountain detail (Part III), simulating hydrology (Part IV), and colouring the terrain with our biome ramp (Part V), it is time to package the result. CartoKit finishes by baking the terrain into a compact mesh, visualising it through an egui viewer, and exporting artefacts for other tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The journey from mathematical representation to visual output ends with three components:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Terrain::from_terrain&lt;/code&gt;– a baked mesh carrying elevation, moisture, biome, and river metadata.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The debug renderer &amp;amp; viewer – CPU rasterisers that turn the data into diagnostic images.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Export helpers – GLB export, PNG captures, and GIF generation built on the same primitives.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s look at each piece.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Baked Terrain Output&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Terrain::from_terrain&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;src/terrain.rs:368&lt;/code&gt;) distils the incremental &lt;code&gt;TerrainBuilder&lt;/code&gt; state into a reusable asset. The bake step:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Keeps only faces whose centroids lie inside the unit square, trimming the guard ring used during generation.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Copies vertex elevation and moisture into mesh attributes so downstream tools can query them directly.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tags every face with average elevation, a &lt;code&gt;TerrainType&lt;/code&gt;(land vs. ocean), and the coarse&lt;code&gt;BiomeType&lt;/code&gt;classification introduced in Part V.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Marks edges as regular, coastline, or river and stores river-flow magnitudes when a &lt;code&gt;RiverSystem&lt;/code&gt;is present.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The baked mesh is still a &lt;code&gt;TopoMesh&lt;/code&gt;, meaning we retain the halfedge connectivity that made the earlier stages convenient. When you call &lt;code&gt;Terrain::from_terrain(&amp;amp;builder)&lt;/code&gt;, you get a self-contained structure that is ready for export or further processing without touching the heavy generation code again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;CPU Debug Renderer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of CartoKit’s imagery is rendered on the CPU. The &lt;code&gt;cartokit::debug&lt;/code&gt; module contains a suite of rasterisers—triangle fill, watertight line drawing, paint-map sampling, rainfall heatmaps—that output directly into &lt;code&gt;image::RgbaImage&lt;/code&gt; buffers. The viewer’s &lt;code&gt;DisplayRenderer&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;examples/viewer/display_modes.rs&lt;/code&gt;) wires those helpers together:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mesh modes (&lt;code&gt;SeedPoints&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Delaunay&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Voronoi&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Quads&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;FinalTriangulation&lt;/code&gt;) call&lt;code&gt;draw_topokit_mesh&lt;/code&gt;with optional vertex overlays.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Scalar fields (&lt;code&gt;TriangleElevation&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;DistanceField&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Rainfall&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Humidity&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;RiverFlow&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Biome&lt;/code&gt;) delegate to&lt;code&gt;draw_triangles_opt&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;draw_regions_opt&lt;/code&gt;with palette swaps.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Noise visualisations reuse the same pipeline, just swapping in different &lt;code&gt;TriangleProperty&lt;/code&gt;variants.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because everything renders to software images, the viewer behaves the same on every platform, and the exported screenshots and GIFs are bit-for-bit identical to what you see on screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Interactive Viewer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;cartokit_viewer&lt;/code&gt; example wraps those images in an egui/eframe interface:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The right-hand parameter panel exposes seeds, Bridson separation, rainfall, and river controls, regenerating the terrain whenever you tweak them.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The “Paint Terrain” mode lets you brush elevation hints onto the 128×128 paint map; the next regeneration integrates those hints into the terrain.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Display modes cover the full pipeline: seed classification, mesh structure, mountain distance fields, rainfall, humidity, river diagnostics, biome colours, and the final shaded map.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Animation tools (&lt;code&gt;examples/viewer/animation.rs&lt;/code&gt;) let you scrub parameters over time and queue frame exports.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each frame, the viewer renders the active mode into an &lt;code&gt;RgbaImage&lt;/code&gt;, uploads it as an egui texture, and then recycles the same image for exports. There is no separate rendering path—what you export is exactly what you preview.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Export Helpers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three helpers in &lt;code&gt;examples/viewer/export.rs&lt;/code&gt; turn the baked data into files:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// 1. Bake + GLB export via MeshKit
display::export_mesh(&amp;amp;terrain_builder, seed);

// 2. One PNG per display mode
display::export_all_images(seed, &amp;amp;modes, |mode| renderer.render(mode));

// 3. Thumbnail tiles for quick comparisons
display::export_all_images_tile(seed, &amp;amp;modes, |mode| renderer.render(mode));
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;export_mesh&lt;/code&gt;clones the baked&lt;code&gt;Terrain&lt;/code&gt;, rescales coordinates for GLTF’s Y‑up convention, and calls&lt;code&gt;meshkit::io::save_mesh&lt;/code&gt;to produce a&lt;code&gt;.glb&lt;/code&gt;file that loads cleanly in Blender or other viewers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;export_all_images&lt;/code&gt;walks every display mode and drops the rendered PNGs into&lt;code&gt;exports/images_seed_&amp;lt;seed&amp;gt;/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;export_all_images_tile&lt;/code&gt;cuts out the top-left 1/8×1/8 tile from each image—handy for diffing or documentation thumbnails.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For animated parameter studies, &lt;code&gt;examples/viewer/gif_export.rs&lt;/code&gt; converts a list of pre-rendered frames into a looping GIF, with options for downsampling, FPS, and output directory naming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Performance Snapshot&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generation times were covered in the earlier posts (≈80 ms for the default 27 K-site map on a modern desktop). The finishing steps add little overhead:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Stage&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Time (2048×2048 render)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;Terrain::from_terrain&lt;/code&gt; bake&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~6 ms&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CPU render – biome view&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~8 ms&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GLB export (&lt;code&gt;meshkit::io::save_mesh&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~15 ms&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;PNG capture per display mode&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5–10 ms&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GIF encoding (20 frames @ 1024²)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~9 ms&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Numbers vary with map resolution and active mode (mesh overlays with AA lines take longer than simple heatmaps), but everything remains comfortably interactive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Future Directions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With a solid foundation in place, the obvious extensions are clear:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GPU shading – real-time lighting, water reflections, and atmospheric effects on top of the baked mesh.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mesh decimation – level-of-detail generation or streaming tiles for massive worlds.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Additional exporters – heightmaps, splatmaps, or direct integrations for Unity/Unreal/Godot.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dynamic overlays – weather, vegetation instancing, or settlement placement driven by the existing attributes.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These items all build on the baked &lt;code&gt;Terrain&lt;/code&gt; structure and export scaffolding we now have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through six posts we moved from random seeds to a fully packaged island:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Poisson disk sampling and dual meshes establish the geometric scaffold.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A paint map and layered noise sculpt elevation.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hydrology adds rivers and erosion cues.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A simple elevation/moisture colormap paints believable biomes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The baked &lt;code&gt;Terrain&lt;/code&gt;, debug renderer, and export helpers ship the result.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The complete system generates a richly annotated island in under a tenth of a second and provides everything you need to inspect, tweak, and export it. The modular architecture welcomes experimentation—swap out any component and the rest of the pipeline keeps working.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for following along. I hope CartoKit inspires your own explorations into procedural worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Valuable Resources&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MeshKit – Halfedge library used throughout the project&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;EGUI – Immediate-mode GUI powering the viewer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;glTF 2.0 – Asset format we export to&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Red Blob Games: Polygonal Map Generation – Foundational reading for the dual-mesh approach&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://brashandplucky.com/2025/09/28/procedural-island-generation-vi.html"/><published>2025-09-21T21:11:57+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45326740</id><title>Lightweight, highly accurate line and paragraph detection</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:01.260075+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2c9c2528d5d592af"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 17 Mar 2022]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:Unified Line and Paragraph Detection by Graph Convolutional Networks&lt;/head&gt;View PDF&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:We formulate the task of detecting lines and paragraphs in a document into a unified two-level clustering problem. Given a set of text detection boxes that roughly correspond to words, a text line is a cluster of boxes and a paragraph is a cluster of lines. These clusters form a two-level tree that represents a major part of the layout of a document. We use a graph convolutional network to predict the relations between text detection boxes and then build both levels of clusters from these predictions. Experimentally, we demonstrate that the unified approach can be highly efficient while still achieving state-of-the-art quality for detecting paragraphs in public benchmarks and real-world images.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.09638"/><published>2025-09-21T21:18:14+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45326754</id><title>Show HN: Tips to stay safe from NPM supply chain attacks</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:00.754196+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1c111a5d8ce32b00"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The NPM ecosystem is no stranger to compromises12, supply-chain attacks3, malware45, spam6, phishing7, incidents8 or even trolls9. In this repository, I have consolidated a list of information you might find useful in securing yourself against these incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Feel free to submit a Pull Request, or reach out to me on Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This repository covers &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;bun&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;deno&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;pnpm&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt; and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;On&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;, by default, a new dependency will be installed with the Caret&lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt;operator. This operator installs the most recent&lt;code&gt;minor&lt;/code&gt;or&lt;code&gt;patch&lt;/code&gt;releases. E.g.,&lt;code&gt;^1.2.3&lt;/code&gt;will install&lt;code&gt;1.2.3&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;1.2.4&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;1.3.0&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;1.6.2&lt;/code&gt;, etc. See https://docs.npmjs.com/about-semantic-versioning and try out the npm SemVer Calculator (https://semver.npmjs.com). To avoid installing freshly compromised packages, it is often advised to pin exact versions (e.g.,&lt;code&gt;"my-package": "1.2.3"&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's how to use the save exact flag to pin exact version in various package managers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install --save-exact react

pnpm add --save-exact react

yarn add --save-exact react

bun add --exact react

deno add npm:react@19.1.1&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can also update this setting in configuration files (e.g., &lt;code&gt;.npmrc&lt;/code&gt;), with either &lt;code&gt;save-exact&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;save-prefix&lt;/code&gt; alike key and value pairs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm config set save-exact=true

pnpm config set save-exact true

yarn config set defaultSemverRangePrefix ""&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;bun&lt;/code&gt;, the config file is &lt;code&gt;bunfig.toml&lt;/code&gt; and corresponding config is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;[install]
exact = true&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, our direct dependencies also have their own dependencies (transitive dependencies). Even if we pin our direct dependencies, their transitive dependencies might still use broad version range operators (like&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt;or&lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt;). The solution is to override the transitive dependencies: https://docs.npmjs.com/cli/v11/configuring-npm/package-json#overrides&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;, if we have the following &lt;code&gt;overrides&lt;/code&gt; field:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "dependencies": {
    "library-a": "^3.0.0"
  },
  "overrides": {
    "lodash": "4.17.21"
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Let's assume that &lt;code&gt;library-a&lt;/code&gt;'s&lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;has a dependency on&lt;code&gt;"lodash": "^4.17.0"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Without the &lt;code&gt;overrides&lt;/code&gt;section,&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;might install&lt;code&gt;lodash@4.17.22&lt;/code&gt;(or any of the latest&lt;code&gt;4.x.x&lt;/code&gt;versions) as a transitive dependency of&lt;code&gt;library-a&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;However, by adding &lt;code&gt;"overrides": { "lodash": "4.17.21" }&lt;/code&gt;, we are telling&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;that anywhere&lt;code&gt;lodash&lt;/code&gt;appears in the dependency tree, it must be resolved to exactly version&lt;code&gt;4.17.21&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;pnpm&lt;/code&gt;, we can also define the &lt;code&gt;overrides&lt;/code&gt; field in the &lt;code&gt;pnpm-workspace.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file: https://pnpm.io/settings#overrides&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt;, the &lt;code&gt;resolutions&lt;/code&gt; field is introduced before the &lt;code&gt;overrides&lt;/code&gt; field, and it also offers a similar functionality: https://yarnpkg.com/configuration/manifest#resolutions&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "resolutions": {
    "lodash": "4.17.21"
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# yarn also provide a cli to set the resolution: https://yarnpkg.com/cli/set/resolution
yarn set resolution &amp;lt;descriptor&amp;gt; &amp;lt;resolution&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;bun&lt;/code&gt;, it supports either the &lt;code&gt;overrides&lt;/code&gt; field or the &lt;code&gt;resolutions&lt;/code&gt; field: https://bun.com/docs/install/overrides&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;deno&lt;/code&gt;, see denoland/deno#28664 for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ensure to commit package managers lockfiles to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;and share between different environments. Different lockfiles are:&lt;code&gt;package-lock.json&lt;/code&gt;for&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;pnpm-lock.yaml&lt;/code&gt;for&lt;code&gt;pnpm&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;bun.lock&lt;/code&gt;for&lt;code&gt;bun&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;yarn.lock&lt;/code&gt;for&lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;deno.lock&lt;/code&gt;for&lt;code&gt;deno&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;p&gt;In automated environments such as continuous integration and deployments, we should install the exact dependencies as defined in the lockfile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm ci

bun install --frozen-lockfile

yarn install --frozen-lockfile

deno install --frozen&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;deno&lt;/code&gt;, we can also set the following in a &lt;code&gt;deno.json&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "lock": {
    "frozen": true
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lifecycle scripts are special scripts that happen in addition to the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pre&amp;lt;event&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;post&amp;lt;event&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, and&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;event&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;scripts. For instance,&lt;code&gt;preinstall&lt;/code&gt;is run before&lt;code&gt;install&lt;/code&gt;is run and&lt;code&gt;postinstall&lt;/code&gt;is run after&lt;code&gt;install&lt;/code&gt;is run. See how npm handles the "scripts" field: https://docs.npmjs.com/cli/v11/using-npm/scripts#life-cycle-scripts&lt;p&gt;Lifecycle scripts are a common strategy from malicious actors. For example, the "Shai-Hulud" worms3 edit the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;file to add a&lt;code&gt;postinstall&lt;/code&gt;script that would then steal credentials.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm config set ignore-scripts true --global

yarn config set enableScripts false&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;bun&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;deno&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;pnpm&lt;/code&gt;, they are disabled by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can combine many of the flags above. For example, the following &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; command would install only production dependencies as defined in the lockfile and ignore lifecycle scripts:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;npm ci --omit=dev --ignore-scripts&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can set a delay to avoid installing newly published packages. This applies to all dependencies, including transitive ones. For example,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pnpm v10.16&lt;/code&gt;introduced the&lt;code&gt;minimumReleaseAge&lt;/code&gt;option: https://pnpm.io/settings#minimumreleaseage, which defines the minimum number of minutes that must pass after a version is published before pnpm will install it. If&lt;code&gt;minimumReleaseAge&lt;/code&gt;is set to&lt;code&gt;1440&lt;/code&gt;, then pnpm will not install a version that was published less than 24 hours ago.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pnpm config set minimumReleaseAge &amp;lt;minutes&amp;gt;

# only install packages published at least 1 day ago
npm install --before="$(date -v -1d)"

yarn config set npmMinimalAgeGate &amp;lt;minutes&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;pnpm&lt;/code&gt;, there's also a &lt;code&gt;minimumReleaseAgeExclude&lt;/code&gt; option to exclude certain packages from the minimum release age.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;, there is a proposal to add &lt;code&gt;minimumReleaseAge&lt;/code&gt; option and &lt;code&gt;minimumReleaseAgeExclude&lt;/code&gt; option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt;, config options &lt;code&gt;npmMinimalAgeGate&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;npmPreapprovedPackages&lt;/code&gt; are implemented since &lt;code&gt;v4.10.0&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;bun&lt;/code&gt;, it is discussed here: oven-sh/bun#22679&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For &lt;code&gt;deno&lt;/code&gt;, an draft proposal is here: denoland/deno#30752&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Renovate CLI (https://github.com/renovatebot/renovate) also includes a &lt;code&gt;minimumReleaseAge&lt;/code&gt; config option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Step Security (https://www.stepsecurity.io) introduced a NPM Package Cooldown Check feature to fail any PR that adds a recently published package.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the latest LTS version of&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;nodejs&lt;/code&gt;, we can use the Permission model to control what system resources a process has access to or what actions the process can take with those resources. However, this does not provide security guarantees in the presence of malicious code. Malicious code can still bypass the permission model and execute arbitrary code without the restrictions imposed by the permission model.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read about the Node.js permission model: https://nodejs.org/docs/latest/api/permissions.html&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# by default, granted full access
node index.js

# restrict access to all available permissions
node --permission index.js

# enable specific permissions
node --permission --allow-fs-read=* --allow-fs-write=* index.js

# use permission model with `npx`
npx --node-options="--permission" &amp;lt;package-name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno enables permissions by default. See https://docs.deno.com/runtime/fundamentals/security/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# by default, restrict access
deno run script.ts

# enable specific permission
deno run --allow-read script.ts&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Bun, the permission model is currently discussed here and here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;has a low barrier for publishing packages, the ecosystem quickly grew to be the biggest package registry with over 5 million packages to date10. But not all packages are created equal. There are small utility packages8 that are downloaded as dependencies when we could write them ourselves and raise the question of "have we forgotten how to code?11"&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Between &lt;code&gt;nodejs&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;bun&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deno&lt;/code&gt;, developers can use many of their modern features instead of relying on third-party libraries. The native modules may not provide the same level of functionality, but they should be considered whenever possible. Here are few examples:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;NPM libraries&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Built-in modules&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;axios&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;node-fetch&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;got&lt;/code&gt;, etc&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;native&lt;code&gt;fetch&lt;/code&gt; API&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;jest&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mocha&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ava&lt;/code&gt;, etc&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;node:test&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;node:assert&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;bun test&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deno test&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;nodemon&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;chokidar&lt;/code&gt;, etc&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;node --watch&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;bun --watch&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deno --watch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;dotenv&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;dotenv-expand&lt;/code&gt;, etc&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;node --env-file&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;bun --env-file&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deno --env-file&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;typescript&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ts-node&lt;/code&gt;, etc&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;node --experimental-strip-types&lt;/code&gt;12, native to &lt;code&gt;deno&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;bun&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;esbuild&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;rollup&lt;/code&gt;, etc&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;bun build&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deno bundle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;prettier&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;eslint&lt;/code&gt;, etc&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;deno lint&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deno fmt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some resources that you might find useful:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://obsidian.md/blog/less-is-safer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://kashw1n.com/blog/nodejs-2025&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://lyra.horse/blog/2025/08/you-dont-need-js&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://blog.greenroots.info/10-lesser-known-web-apis-you-may-want-to-use&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://github.com/you-dont-need/You-Dont-Need-Momentjs&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://docs.npmjs.com/about-two-factor-authentication&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two factor authentication (2FA) adds an extra layer of authentication to your&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;account. 2FA is not required by default, but it is a good practice to enable it.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# ensure that 2FA is enabled for auth and writes (this is the default)
npm profile enable-2fa auth-and-writes&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://docs.npmjs.com/about-access-tokens#about-granular-access-tokens&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;An access token is a common way to authenticate to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;when using the API or the&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;CLI.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm token create # for a read and publish token
npm token create --read-only # for a read-only token
npm token create --cidr=[list] # for a CIDR-restricted read and publish token
npm token create --read-only --cidr=[list] # for a CIDR-restricted read-only token&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Restrict token to specific packages, scopes, and organizations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Set a token expiration date&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Limit token access based on IP address ranges (CIDR notation)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Select between read-only or read and write access&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don't use the same token for multiple purposes&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://docs.npmjs.com/generating-provenance-statements&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The provenance attestation is established by publicly providing a link to a package's source code and build instructions from the build environment. This allows developers to verify where and how your package was built before they download it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The publish attestations are generated by the registry when a package is published by an authorized user. When an npm package is published with provenance, it is signed by Sigstore public good servers and logged in a public transparency ledger, where users can view this information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, here's what a provenance statement look like on the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;vue&lt;/code&gt;package page: https://www.npmjs.com/package/vue#provenance&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To establish provenance, use a supported CI/CD provider (e.g., GitHub Actions) and publish with the correct flag:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm publish --provenance&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To publish without evoking the &lt;code&gt;npm publish&lt;/code&gt; command, we can do one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Set &lt;code&gt;NPM_CONFIG_PROVENANCE&lt;/code&gt;to&lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;in CI/CD environment&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;provenance=true&lt;/code&gt;to&lt;code&gt;.npmrc&lt;/code&gt;file&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;publishConfig&lt;/code&gt;block to&lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;"publishConfig": {
  "provenance": true
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Limiting the files in an npm package helps prevent malware by reducing the attack surface, and it avoids accidental leaking of sensitive data&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;files&lt;/code&gt; field in &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; is used to specify the files that should be included in the published package. Certain files are always included, see: https://docs.npmjs.com/cli/v11/configuring-npm/package-json#files for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "name": "my-package",
  "version": "1.0.0",
  "main": "dist/index.js",
  "files": ["dist", "LICENSE", "README.md"]
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;.npmignore&lt;/code&gt; file can also be used to exclude files from the published package.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It will not override the &lt;code&gt;"files"&lt;/code&gt; field, but in subdirectories it will.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;.npmignore&lt;/code&gt; file works just like a &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;. If there is a &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file, and &lt;code&gt;.npmignore&lt;/code&gt; is missing, &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;'s contents will be used instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can run &lt;code&gt;npx pack --dry-run&lt;/code&gt; to see the contents that will be included in the published version of the package.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; npx pack --dry-run
npm notice Tarball Contents
npm notice 1.1kB LICENSE
npm notice 1.9kB README.md
npm notice 108B index.js
npm notice 700B package.json
npm notice Tarball Details&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, run &lt;code&gt;npm publish --dry-run&lt;/code&gt; to see what would be happen when we run the publish command.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Private package registries are a great way for organizations to manage their own dependencies, and can acts as a proxy to the public&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;registry. Organizations can enforce security policies and vet packages before they are used in a project.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some private registries that you might find useful:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub Packages https://docs.github.com/en/packages/working-with-a-github-packages-registry/working-with-the-npm-registry&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Verdaccio https://github.com/verdaccio/verdaccio&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vlt https://www.vlt.sh/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;JFrog Artifactory https://jfrog.com/integrations/npm-registry&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sonatype: https://help.sonatype.com/en/npm-registry.html&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Many package managers provide audit functionality to scan your project's dependencies for known security vulnerabilities, show a report and recommend the best way to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm audit # audit dependencies
npm audit fix # automatically install any compatible updates
npm audit signatures # verify the signatures of the dependencies

pnpm audit
pnpm audit --fix

bun audit

yarn npm audit
yarn npm audit --recursive # audit transitive dependencies&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GitHub offers several services that can help protect against &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; malwares, including:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dependabot: This tool automatically scans your project's dependencies, including &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;packages, for known vulnerabilities.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Software Bill of Materials (SBOMs): GitHub allows you to export an SBOM for your repository directly from its dependency graph. An SBOM provides a comprehensive list of all your project's dependencies, including transitive ones (dependencies of your dependencies).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Code Scanning: Code scanning can also help identify potential vulnerabilities or suspicious patterns that might arise from integrating compromised &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;packages.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Warning&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you spot vulnerabilities or issues in NPM or Github, please report them using the following links:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Socket.dev is a security platform designed to protect JavaScript projects by scanning and securing dependencies from malicious and vulnerable code. It offers various tools such as GitHub App, "Safe NPM" CLI tool, Web Extension, and VSCode Extension. Watch their talk on AI powered malware hunting at scale, Jan 2025 for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Snyk offers a suite of tools to fix vulnerabilities in open source dependencies, including a CLI to run vulnerability scans on local machine, IDE integrations to embed into development environment, and API to integrate with Snyk programmatically. For example, you can test public npm packages before use or create automatic PRs for known vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maintainer burnout is a significant problem in the open-source community. Many popular&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;packages are maintained by volunteers who work in their spare time, often without any compensation. Over time, this can lead to exhaustion and a lack of motivation, making them more susceptible to social engineering where a malicious actor pretends to be a helpful contributor and eventually injects malicious code.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2018, the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;event-stream&lt;/code&gt;package was compromised due to the maintainer giving access to a malicious actor13. Another example outside the JavaScript ecosystem is the XZ Utils incident14 in 2024 where a malicious actor worked for over three years to attain a position of trust.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;OSS donations also help create a more sustainable model for open-source development. Foundations can help support the business, marketing, legal, technical assistance and direct support behind hundreds of open source projects that so many rely upon15.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the JavaScript ecosystem, the OpenJS Foundation (https://openjsf.org) was founded in 2019 from a merger of JS Foundation and Node.js Foundation. But here are few platforms where you can also directly donate to OSS maintainers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub Sponsors https://github.com/sponsors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Open Collective https://opencollective.com&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Thanks.dev https://thanks.dev&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://www.aikido.dev/blog/npm-debug-and-chalk-packages-compromised ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://socket.dev/blog/ongoing-supply-chain-attack-targets-crowdstrike-npm-packages ↩ ↩2&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://www.reversinglabs.com/blog/malicious-npm-patch-delivers-reverse-shell ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://socket.dev/blog/north-korean-apt-lazarus-targets-developers-with-malicious-npm-package ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb-node/security/advisories/GHSA-w62p-hx95-gf2c ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://openssf.org/blog/2024/04/15/open-source-security-openssf-and-openjs-foundations-issue-alert-for-social-engineering-takeovers-of-open-source-projects/ ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://github.com/bodadotsh/npm-security-best-practices"/><published>2025-09-21T21:19:47+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45327059</id><title>My new Git utility `what-changed-twice` needs a new name</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:00.484862+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7612e86254321f17"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Archive:&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Subtopics:&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Comments disabled&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Sun, 21 Sep 2025&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt; My new git utility `what-changed-twice` needs a new name &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;As I have explained in the past, my typical workflow is to go along commiting stuff that might or might not make sense, then clean it all up at the end, doing multiple passes with &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;What is Fred for? I have a couple of uses for it so far.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Often as I work I'll produce a chain of commits that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It often happens that I will modify a file on Monday, modify it some more on Tuesday, correct a spelling error on Wednesday. I might have made 7 sets of changes to the main file, of which 4 are related, 2 others are related to each other but not to the other 4, and the last one is unrelated to any of the rest. When a file has changed more than once, I need to see what changed and then group the changes into related sets.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Some files changed only once, and I don't need to think about those at this stage. Later I can go back and split up those commits if it seems to make the history clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Fred takes the output of &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It finds which files were modified in which commits, and it prints a report about any file that was modified in more than one commit:&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The report is in two parts. At the top, the path of each file that changed more than once in the log, and the (highly-abbreviated) commit IDs of the commits in which it changed. For example, &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Now I can look to see what else changed in those three commits:&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;then look at the changes to &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;and then decide if there are any changes I might like to squash together.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Many other files changed on the branch, but I only have to concern myself with four.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;There's bonus information too. If a commit is not mentioned in the report, then it only changed files that didn't change in any other commit. That means that in a rebase, I can move that commit literally anywhere else in the sequence without creating a conflict. Only the commits in the report can cause conflicts if they are reordered.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;I write most things in Python these days, but this one seemed to cry out for Perl. Here's the code.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Hmm, maybe I'll call it &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;[Other articles in category /prog/git] permanent link&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.plover.com/2025/09/21/#what-changed-twice"/><published>2025-09-21T21:59:12+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45327199</id><title>How can I influence others without manipulating them?</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:36:00.085301+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="b482039d8bacd597"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We influence others every day, whether we intend to or not. Sometimes it is through the way we argue, sometimes through the way we listen, and sometimes simply through the story we tell about what matters. Influence is not the property of the few who hold authority. It is the currency of all relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The word persuasion often carries with it the scent of manipulation, as though one person is moving another toward something they do not really want. But there is another way to hold it. Influence can be understood as an invitation. It is the art of meeting people where they are, of entering their world with respect, and of opening a door that they might choose to walk through with us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This article invites you to consider five doors of influence: Rationalising, Asserting, Negotiating, Inspiring, and Bridging. Each opens a different path into relationship and commitment. Each has its gifts. Each, when overused, can become a wall instead of a door.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The practice is not to master all five overnight, but to grow our awareness and our range. Persuasion is not a personality trait. It is a skill. It asks us to listen, to notice, and to choose consciously how we invite others.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Our own doorway: The blind spot of preference&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of us have a default style of persuasion. Perhaps you lean on facts. Perhaps you rely on conviction. Perhaps you search for compromise, tell stories, or call on the voices of others. None of these is wrong. Each is a doorway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet our default does more than shape how we speak. It shapes how we see. If I lean on data, I may hear someone’s story as weak rather than inspiring. If I favour conviction, I may interpret hesitation as lack of commitment, when it might be an opening for negotiation. If I thrive on inspiration, I may dismiss detail-oriented questions as nit-picking rather than as a real need for clarity. If I am most comfortable with bridging, I may feel uneasy with those who are direct and independent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our own doorway becomes a filter. It colours what we pay attention to, what we dismiss, and how we react. The danger is that we mistake difference for resistance. We think they are being difficult, when in fact they are simply standing at another door.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Becoming aware of our preference allows us to pause. Instead of defending our own style, we can ask: What is the invitation they are offering me through their language and behaviour? Which door are they holding open that I have overlooked because I was guarding my own?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Influence begins with this act of humility. The willingness to see that the door we most trust may not be the one others are waiting at.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once we recognise our blind spot, we are ready to notice the variety of doors available to us. Influence is not one way, it is five ways. Each has its own language, its own gifts, and its own risks. Rationalising, Asserting, Negotiating, Inspiring, and Bridging are not personality types but choices. At any moment, we can choose to knock on a different door, depending on where others are standing and what the moment requires.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What follows is a closer look at each door. how to recognise it, how to walk through it well, and how to avoid turning it into a wall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Rationalising: The door of logic&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rationalising is the style that seeks to persuade through facts, evidence, and analysis. It appeals to those who are comforted by structure and clarity. When someone asks for data, compares benchmarks, or worries about risk and performance, they are standing at the rational door.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This style has its strengths. It reassures the finance director who needs a business case. It appeals to the engineer who wants proof that the system will not fail. It builds trust with the analyst who measures quality by what can be verified.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enter this door well, we come prepared. We gather our facts. We organise our thinking into a clear flow: problem, options, evidence, recommendation. We know the return on investment, the efficiency gains, the quality improvements. We anticipate objections and hold evidence ready to meet them. We present data not as a weapon but as a gift of clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet logic alone is not enough. Overused, it can become cold and detached. The person across from us may long for empathy, but we bury them in numbers. They may seek relationship, but we offer them a chart. Rationalising can easily turn into proving a point rather than creating understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Reflection questions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Which metrics or outcomes matter most to this person, and have I framed my case in those terms, for example ROI, risk, quality or efficiency?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What is my one-page flow: problem, options, evidence, recommendation?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Which objections are most likely, and what independent sources will I cite to address them?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Where will a chart or comparison clarify, and where could visuals overwhelm?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What level of evidence would be enough for this decision, and how will I check for overload signals in the moment?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Where might I be using facts to prove a point rather than to build shared understanding?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• If they are not data-driven, which second door will I pivot to after I test for fit?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What jargon should I remove to keep the message precise and clear?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Asserting: The door of conviction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Asserting persuades through confidence, authority, and clarity. It is the voice that speaks directly and without hesitation. It is the person who values decisiveness, who prefers a straight line over a winding explanation, who respects those who stand their ground.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You recognise this style when someone expresses strong opinions with little hesitation, when they challenge ideas and expect you to do the same, when they respond best to conviction rather than ambiguity. For them, clarity is a form of respect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enter this door well, we speak with confidence. We choose firm language, declarative statements, uncluttered by qualifiers. We are direct and concise. We know our boundaries, and we state them. We are ready with anchor points: two or three firm reasons why our proposal matters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The temptation, though, is to confuse assertiveness with aggression. Overused, asserting becomes domineering. It silences others. It leaves no room for dialogue. It builds resistance where it meant to build respect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Reflection questions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What exactly am I asking for in one clear sentence?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What is non-negotiable, and what is flexible?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What two or three anchor reasons will I use to support my position?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• How will I signal credibility without drifting into name-dropping or status plays?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What does matching their energy look like while staying respectful and calm?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Where will I deliberately pause to listen so I do not over-talk the room?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What early signals tell me I am tipping into pressure, and how will I de-escalate?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• If directness stalls the dialogue, what is my next door to try?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Negotiating: The door of balance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Negotiating persuades by finding common ground. It seeks the middle path, the workable solution, the compromise that honours both sides. It is rooted in the belief that influence is not about victory but about mutual benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You notice this style in those who raise concerns gently, who suggest meeting halfway, who speak in terms of “what if” and “could we.” They are pragmatic. They value win–win outcomes. They prefer flexibility over confrontation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enter this door well, we listen closely to uncover the real concern beneath the stated one. We protect what matters most to us while staying open to trade-offs. We come with options. We ask open-ended questions. We remain collaborative, treating the conversation as joint problem-solving.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But compromise has its dangers. Overused, negotiation turns into unnecessary concession. We may be seen as weak or uncertain. Others may begin every conversation expecting us to bend. We may give away value before fully exploring our own position.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Reflection questions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What is the real concern beneath what is being said, and how will I surface it with open questions?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Which larger goals or principles am I protecting, and what are my red lines?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What tradables or creative options can I offer that create value without giving away too much?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What do I expect in return for each concession?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• How will I hold a respectful, collaborative tone so we stay in joint problem solving?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• At what point would compromise become drift, and how will I name that threshold?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• If others expect automatic concessions from me, how will I reset expectations early?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What alternative door will I use if bargaining signals are not present?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Inspiring: The door of vision&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inspiring persuades through story, metaphor, and imagination. It calls people to something larger than themselves. It shifts the focus from what is practical to what is possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You know you are with an inspiring type when they disengage from technical talk but light up at mention of purpose or possibility. They ask about impact and legacy. They respond to stories and metaphors. They look for meaning, not just measurement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enter this door well, we tell relevant stories. We use vivid language and imagery. We connect ideas to values and aspirations. We speak with authenticity and passion. We invite others to imagine: What if you could? What would it feel like if…?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet inspiration without grounding can lose its way. Overused, it becomes idealistic, disconnected from reality, heavy with promise and light on delivery. Listeners may nod politely but ask for numbers that never come. Trust fades when vision is not matched by action.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Reflection questions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What specific story from their world will make this possibility feel real and credible?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What image or analogy will help them visualise success?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Which values or purpose of theirs does this idea serve, for example impact, legacy, innovation or customer experience?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What is the smallest concrete next step that grounds the vision?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Where will I invite imagination with a genuine what if question, then check for practical concerns?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What numbers or proof points should I have ready if they ask for them?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• How will I keep my tone authentic so enthusiasm does not outpace deliverables?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• If inspiration lands politely but without commitment, which door will I move to next?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Bridging: The door of relationship&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bridging persuades through connection and social proof. It is the style that builds trust by involving others, by leaning on shared experience, by showing that someone else has walked this path before.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You recognise it when someone asks, “Who else is doing this?” or seems hesitant until they hear a peer’s endorsement. They value rapport and trust more than unknown data. They commit when they see others they respect committing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enter this door well, we bring in mutual contacts. We offer testimonials and case studies. We emphasise shared goals. We give before we ask, offering help, making introductions, extending reciprocity. We are warm and attentive, because this style rests on human connection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But here too lies a danger. Overused, bridging makes us dependent on others. We may delay decisions, waiting for third-party validation. We may undermine our own authority, deferring to outside voices instead of speaking for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Reflection questions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Who do they already trust that I can appropriately involve, and how will I make that connection?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Which case study or testimonial best mirrors their context?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• How will I frame our shared goals so alignment is explicit?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What value can I offer first, for example a helpful introduction or insight, before asking for commitment?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• How will I keep momentum without waiting for every third party to weigh in?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Where do I need to speak in my own voice so I do not over-rely on others’ validation?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• What is my plan to sustain the relationship beyond this single decision?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• If bridging slows progress, which door should I try to regain decisiveness?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Living the paradox of influence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each of these five doors, Rationalising, Asserting, Negotiating, Inspiring, and Bridging, offers a path into relationship. Each works best when it honours the person we hope to influence rather than serving only our own habits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The paradox is that any of them, when overused, becomes a wall. Logic turns cold. Conviction turns harsh. Compromise turns weak. Vision turns empty. Relationship turns dependent. What begins as invitation can end as imposition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The practice is not to abandon our natural style but to notice when it no longer serves. To ask: Which doorway is this person already standing at? What language are they using? What energises them? What shuts them down?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Influence then becomes less about pressing harder on the door we know, and more about walking around to the door they are holding open.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Persuasion is not about clever tactics or manipulation. It is about presence. It is about listening for what matters to others and choosing consciously how we invite them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The question that remains for each of us is simple: Which door will you choose to knock on in your next conversation?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you have any tips or advice? What has worked for you? Do you have any recommended resources to explore? Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Influenced by&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The five doors of influence: Rationalising, Asserting, Negotiating, Inspiring, and Bridging, are my synthesis, but several bodies of work have shaped them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Gary Yukl’s research on leadership influence tactics, which identified patterns such as rational persuasion, pressure, exchange, inspirational appeals, and coalition tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Robert Cialdini’s principles of persuasion, especially authority, social proof, reciprocity, and consistency, which continue to show how people respond to influence in practice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Negotiation practice and theory, from both organisational behaviour research and classic works on principled negotiation, which highlight the importance of mutual benefit and trade-offs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• Leadership and change literature, including Peter Block’s writings on community and invitation, which shape the idea of influence as a relational act rather than a manipulative one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• My own work with leadership teams, where repeated practice has confirmed that leaders tend to default to one or two styles, often without realising the limits this creates in how they see and respond to others.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These streams converge in the five doors. They are not meant as a new theory, but as a practical frame that leaders can hold in the moment, to choose how they wish to invite others.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://andiroberts.com/leadership-questions/how-to-influence-others-without-manipulating"/><published>2025-09-21T22:20:16+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45327417</id><title>Why is Venus hell and Earth an Eden?</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:59.725602+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="7719f9695df445ba"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mark Belan/Quanta Magazine&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Venus is arguably the worst place in the solar system. A cloak of carbon dioxide suffocates the planet, subjecting its surface to skull-crushing pressure. Sulfuric acid rains down through the sickly yellow sky but never reaches the lava-licked ground. Venus is so hot — hot enough to melt lead — that the acid rain evaporates as it’s falling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The planet’s extreme inhospitality is at the heart of one of the most beguiling mysteries in planetary science. Venus and Earth formed at the same time, from the same geologic building blocks, in pretty much the same part of the solar system. They’re even the same size. So why is Venus a hellscape, and Earth a garden?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A common refrain in the scientific community is that Venus is just several steps ahead — that it represents the end state of all large rocky planets, including Earth. The hypothesis is that these planets eventually lose the ability to sequester planet-warming greenhouse gases in their geologic underbelly. When those gases then accumulate in the atmosphere, the world enters a runaway greenhouse state — like the boiling hot Venusian climate. “Over the years, we’d always heard about Venus being a preview into Earth’s future,” said Stephen Kane, a planetary astrophysicist at the University of California, Riverside.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But is that long-held assumption true? In hundreds of millions or billions of years, will Earth’s climate go the way of Venus’, transitioning from a temperate world into a catastrophic hothouse? Kane and his colleagues have been trying to find out. Venus and Earth are often referred to as twins, with Venus being the evil one of the pair. In their Reuniting Twins project, the scientists have developed a digital model of Earth that combines solar physics, volcanology, plate tectonics and climate science. They’ve been pushing their model Earth to its extremes, trying every plausible way to break it and make it into Venus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As well as exploring what went so wrong on the second rock from the sun, this work speaks to a query closer to home, said Paul Byrne, a planetary scientist at Washington University in St. Louis who was not directly involved with the project: “How long is Earth habitable for?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Planetary Whodunit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Forecasting Earth’s future requires an understanding of Venus’ past. Long ago, Venus might not have been too different from how Earth is now. Spacecraft surveys and telescope observations have revealed the existence of a rare, heavy form of water in the Venusian atmosphere — a telltale sign that regular water used to be abundant on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers debate how that water resided there. One possibility is that the water on young Venus formed steam that wafted above the magma sea covering the newborn planet’s surface. That water vapor, a potent greenhouse gas, would have pushed the world into a scorching-hot greenhouse state not long after its birth. Alternatively, Venus’ initial, planetwide magma sea might have cooled and hardened into a crust quickly enough for liquid water — maybe even an ocean’s worth of water — to flow across it. If that is true, then what happened to all that water?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2020, Michael Way, a planetary scientist and climate modeler at NASA’s Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York, looked at two possibilities for how a Venusian ocean could have boiled away.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first hypothesis points to the sun, which, as it ages and burns through its hydrogen fuel, blasts out ever more sunlight, subjecting nearby planets — including Venus, which sits closer to the sun than we do — to an increasingly intense blaze. Planetary scientists estimate that by about a billion years after the solar system’s birth, the gradually brightening sun would have been able to efficiently vaporize any liquid water on Venus. Water vapor would then have flooded the Venusian atmosphere, potentially causing intensive global warming; this warming might have been exacerbated further by volcanoes off-gassing carbon dioxide. The combination might have pushed Venus into a runaway greenhouse state.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a nice story. But according to Way’s models, the theory that the sun broke Venus by evaporating its oceans has problems. Venus spins very slowly on its axis, and one day there is equivalent to 116 Earth days, or nearly four months. If the planet’s dayside initially held liquid oceans, that water’s evaporation would have formed thick clouds. Those prodigious, persistent dayside clouds would have reflected sunlight, keeping Venus cooler than it otherwise might have been and actually preventing a runaway greenhouse effect and unrestrained global warming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Way thinks that a more plausible suspect in Venus’ demise is a form of ruinous volcanism. In its own storied past, Earth experienced prolonged eruptions of lava in single regions, known as large igneous provinces (LIPs), that lasted for hundreds of thousands and perhaps millions of years. Each of these events injected copious carbon dioxide into the atmosphere and made the world, for a time, extremely hot. One LIP 252 million years ago triggered the worst recorded mass extinction in Earth’s history, almost sterilizing the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortunately for life, after each of these LIP events, Earth gradually drew that excess carbon dioxide deep into its rocky bowels, and the planet cooled back down. It accomplished this through a process called subduction: When tectonic plates collide, one plate can descend below the other, drawing seawater rich in dissolved carbon dioxide into the abyssal depths. That carbon remains sequestered in the lower mantle for epochal lengths of time; some of it eventually erupts back into the atmosphere via volcanism. That, in a nutshell, is how Earth’s global thermostat is regulated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s possible that back when there was water on Venus, it also had Earth-like plate tectonics with major subduction zones. But the system wasn’t widespread or large-scale enough to save it from a planetary immolation — especially if several LIP events occurred at roughly the same time. Way’s models show that several concurrent LIPs could have thrown vast quantities of carbon dioxide into Venus’ atmosphere, warming the world so severely that much of its liquid water boiled away into the sky, accelerating the warming further. With no oceans to speak of, all that carbon dioxide could not be reabsorbed. Moreover, water is an enabler of subduction: It lowers the melting point of rocks, allowing tectonic plates to more easily bend and break. And so, with no water left at the surface, major subduction zones would grind to a halt, preventing the entombment of carbon dioxide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other scientists tend to agree with Way’s assessment: The sun alone cannot be responsible for making Venus the awful place it is today. “I really do think you need multiple extreme volcanic episodes … to get there,” said Anna Gülcher, a planetary scientist at the University of Bern in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to Break the World&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While studying Venus and its runaway greenhouse wasteland, Kane became morbidly curious: Could the same fate befall Earth? “What if we shut down the carbon cycle on Earth?” he said. “Could you produce a Venus?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To find out, he and his team built a virtual world-destroying machine. “Everybody loves a post-apocalyptic or doomsday scenario, provided it’s 5 billion years in our future,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Courtesy of Stephen Kane&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first step was to fast-forward their model of Earth about 3.5 billion years, to when the sun and planets will be 8 billion years old. At that point, the sun will shine brighter than it does today, and Earth’s atmosphere will receive the same level of roasting-hot starlight that Venus did when it was just 1 billion years old. Back then, it’s thought, Venus would have been at a tipping point: either temperate and waterlogged, or burnt to a crisp. The 8 billion-year-old sun will push Earth to a similar, climatic knife-edge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The team’s model suggests that in 3.5 billion years, Earth’s oceans could begin evaporating and become heat-trapping water vapor in the atmosphere. That could be sufficient to kill off Earth’s major subduction zones, since without water, there might be no subduction (plus, there would be less water for carbon dioxide to dissolve into in the first place). “We’re losing the ability to draw back that CO2 into the Earth’s mantle. So it just builds up,” said Michelle Hill of Stanford University, a member of the Reuniting Twins project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The shutdown of major subduction zones would mean that the Earth’s tectonic plates stop clashing and jostling about. Instead, they would form a near-united rocky shell around the hot mantle. For a time, the mantle would get hotter, since the shell around it would trap heat generated by radioactively decaying compounds inside it. As heat accumulates in the interior, the Earth in Kane’s simulations would experience an uptick in volcanism lasting for about 15 million years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This period, known as a “stagnant lid regime,” adds even more carbon dioxide to the sky. But the eruptive spike is short-lived. The mantle cools down and the crust thickens until it becomes nearly impermeable to any major carbon-erupting volcanism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So 15 million years after its stagnant lid forms, Earth will have reached a new equilibrium. Occasional spurts of volcanism would still happen. (Likewise, scientists have found compelling evidence that Venus is volcanically active today.) But Kane explained that these sporadic eruptions aren’t expected to add much carbon to the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At that point, the team’s simulations stop. How Venus-like is their model of the future Earth?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;USGS&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;There’s No Place Like Venus&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If or when Earth’s large-scale subduction shuts off in about 3.5 billion years, kneecapping the planet’s ability to bury carbon, Kane and his team’s simulations indicate that the carbon dioxide level in the atmosphere will rise anywhere from 0.1 bars to 0.8 bars. (For reference, the total atmospheric pressure at sea level today is 1 bar, and roughly 0.04% of that, or 0.042 bars, comes from carbon dioxide.) Even in their best-case scenario of a 0.1-bar rise in carbon dioxide, Earth’s surface temperature surpasses 100 degrees Celsius (212 degrees Fahrenheit). The same happens at 0.8 bars, but far more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Either way, the surface of the world becomes literally boiling hot. Earth will “turn into a post-runaway greenhouse state,” Kane said. “The surface temperature will be too hot for any water. It’ll all boil away.” Nothing sitting on the world’s skin would survive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, Earth won’t get close to the state that Venus is in today. “It’d be Venus lite,” Kane said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Venus has a 93-bar atmosphere consisting of 96.5% carbon dioxide. Kane and his colleagues’ doomsday machine, no matter how hard they push it, cannot take Earth to those levels. “I was surprised by that,” he said. Because the mantle is sealed off by a stagnant lid, volcanism drops, protecting Earth from a Venus-style roasting better than he thought.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Independent scientists have praised the Reuniting Twins project for challenging prior assumptions and adding significantly to the discussion about the terminal state of rocky planets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I like their idea,” Way said, adding that the team’s version of a future Earth “doesn’t sound unreasonable.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“You end up with a world that’s stinkingly hot,” said Byrne, the Washington University planetary scientist. But, he said, the possibility that it may not be Venusian levels of hot is intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kane’s team acknowledged that their model hasn’t considered LIP-style mega-eruptions, and that these events could feasibly add a bounty of trapped carbon to the atmosphere at any point in the future. Maybe Earth gets unlucky and experiences multiple, simultaneous LIP events (though this grows less likely over time, Kane said, as the mantle cools and its churning slows). If so, that scenario could push Earth to be more like Venus than the team’s model suggests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Uncertainties abound. But if Kane’s team is even broadly correct, it suggests that Venus has a uniquely grim history. Something — perhaps an inundation of lava — burned that planet to the bone. Earth, meanwhile, has so far been unable to bring about its own destruction. Let’s hope that remains the case long into the future.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/why-is-venus-hell-and-earth-an-eden-20250915/"/><published>2025-09-21T22:56:31+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45328247</id><title>How I, a beginner developer, read the tutorial you, a developer, wrote for me</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:59.276354+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="96781013d7103f19"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How I, a non-developer, read the tutorial you, a developer, wrote for me, a beginner&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Hello! I am a developer. Here is my relevant experience: I code in Hoobijag and sometimes jabbernocks and of course ABCDE++++ (but never ABCDE+/^+ are you kidding? ha!) and I like working with Shoobababoo and occasionally kleptomitrons. I’ve gotten to work for Company1 doing Shoobaboo-ing code things and that’s what led me to the Snarfus. So, let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About this tutorial&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I first started doing Very Simple Thing2 with Snarfus, but the more I used it the more I saw the potential! Despite the jaggle of the chromus, it’s really multi-purpose. And that’s what led me to argyling the pintafore with the quagmire instead of the hoobastank! I know, crazy. But it was kind of working, and actually a lot of fun… Until I hit a big roadblock: the fisterfunk will NOT talk to the shamrock portal or even send beep-boops back to the Snarfus! Of course, you know what that means3 — Now the entire hoob-tunnel is clogged with gramelions. Unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I almost gave up but then I realized: If I connect the backside Snarfus stagnator to the backside shamrock Klingon troglodyte emulater, it’s good! Everything beep-boops and ding-dongs and I get the Actual Topic of the Tutorial, which lets me do the Very Simple Thing the way I want after all! Pretty cool4.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So here’s how to set it up:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In the terminal, ajkl;gawgor;iqeg;iJLkqen. wl;R aw;oeiga 4648664 arjarwgj;llj;ja fadgfgajkljl; wlj;sdjk;lfas&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Next go to folder/hidden/deep/in/the/file/system/surprise!.file and copy the contents of the file. If it’s not there, it might be in library/library/library/llibrary/liiiiiibrarrrary/llllliiiiibrary/hidden/hidden/hiding/you can’t find me/hidden/nope/never/hahahahereiam.file.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Now go back to the terminal and paste in the file contents, then type in 64A786AGR45JAR; rdja;jg [[]][[]][[]][[]]][[]()()()()()()()()(){{}{}{}|{}{|}{}{|}{ ////////////////!! !!!! !! //// !!! agjlkargji;lwej;OI [ASRGASG[]ASGDASG[]EAEadgasg[]EAGE[edaga][]ahgr-0-0=-0-=0-=0=0-0=-0-=0=-0-=0=-0=-0!!!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Boop!5&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Open Snarfus and upload the file you just made.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Just for shits and giggles, you can de-sham the chronostatiomatrix by running —()()(]]asdg a=-do —cd go cd stay —sususudododo baby shark—][] but that’s optional.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;That’s it!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let me know how it goes for you. I’d love to hear if anybody uses this approach with GewGawGamma or ometer2.7.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I probably should recognize Company because it seems illustrious but I do not recognize Company or know what they do. ↵&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;It is not simple. ↵&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I do not know what that means. ↵&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;It is cool. I don’t really understand how, but I believe it. I’m glad you know how to do it. ↵&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The first 3 steps will take me approximately 7 hours and 193 internet searches to complete. When I finally get to Boop! it will be really satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This is meant in good fun. I really appreciate the folks who take time to share their knowledge and write up tutorials and give tips and so on. ↵&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://anniemueller.com/posts/how-i-a-non-developer-read-the-tutorial-you-a-developer-wrote-for-me-a-beginner"/><published>2025-09-22T01:27:34+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45328335</id><title>Pointer Tagging in C++: The Art of Packing Bits into a Pointer</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:59.091539+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://vectrx.substack.com/p/pointer-tagging-in-c-the-art-of-packing"/><published>2025-09-22T01:46:37+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45328537</id><title>DSM Disorders Disappear in Statistical Clustering of Psychiatric Symptoms (2024)</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:58.714104+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="9602139429a56df3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;DSM Disorders Disappear in Statistical Clustering of Psychiatric Symptoms&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Whither Major Depression?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Reconstructing Psychopathology: A data-driven reorganization of the symptoms in DSM-5” by Miri Forbes, et al. (was available as a preprint at the time of writing this post, later published in Clinical Psychological Science) is a brilliantly designed and innovative study of the quantitative structure of psychopathology with important ramifications for our understanding of psychiatric classification. No one has conducted a study quite like this before, and the results are remarkable. It takes place in the context of the development of Hierarchical Taxonomy of Psychopathology (HiTOP) which is a dimensional, hierarchical, and quantitative approach to the classification of mental disorders, and relies on identification of patterns of covariation among symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study is based on a large online survey, with participants recruited from a variety of sources, resulting in a socio-demographically diverse sample size of 14.8K participants. Participants could opt to complete a mini, short, medium, or long version of the questionnaire. The survey consisted of items based on individual symptoms derived from DSM-5. Symptoms were written in first person and past tense, as close to the DSM phrasing as possible but devoid of information about symptom onset, duration, frequency, and severity. Importantly, survey items were presented to participants in a random order. This randomness is important because in prior studies questions about symptoms were not asked or presented in a random manner. They have been asked using symptom questionnaires that cluster symptoms together in ways influenced by the diagnostic manuals or using a structured clinical interview that adopts the DSM organization. Asking about symptoms in a random order ensures that their co-occurrence is not artificially influenced by the order in which questions are asked. The survey went through multiple rounds of pilot testing, and in the end, 680 items were included. Participants reported how true each symptom statement was for them in the past 12 months on a five-point scale from Not at all true (Never) to Perfectly true (Always). Participants were told to think about their experiences across a wide variety of contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The responses were subjected to two statistical clustering methods: iclust and Ward’s hierarchical agglomerative clustering. Clusters were accepted for further analysis when both methods agreed. This was intended to ensure that there were no idiosyncrasies arising from reliance on one method. This resulted in 139 clusters (“syndromes”) and 81 solo symptoms. Higher-order constructs were identified using hierarchical principal components analysis and hierarchical clustering. The sample was divided into a primary sample (11.8K) and a hold-out sample (3K) to examine the robustness of results. The final classification was based on points of agreement between samples and methods.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final high order structure included 8 spectra: Externalizing, Harmful Substance Use, Mania/Low Detachment, Thought Disorder, Somatoform, Eating Pathology, Internalizing, and Neurodevelopmental and Cognitive Difficulties. 27 subfactors were identified. As an example, within the internalizing spectrum, the 4 subfactors were: Distress, Social Withdrawal, Dysregulated Sleep and Trauma, and Fear. Similar to earlier literature, a single overarching dimension also emerged. This has been described before as the “p-factor” (general psychopathology factor), but Forbes et al. chose to call it the “Big Everything” to avoid reifying it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So here it is, an empirically derived hierarchical clustering of individual symptoms across the range of psychopathology:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The end result has a prominent convergence with the existing HiTOP model, with some points of divergence that would be important for future revisions of HiTOP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;An important thing to note is that many classic DSM disorders do not emerge as identifiable syndromes in these analyses. &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Due to the symptom heterogeneity of DSM constructs, they are either broken down into smaller homogenous syndromes or they merge into higher-order clusters such as subfactors and spectra. (And this is the case not just in this particular study, but has been the case in prior analyses on which the HiTOP model is based—even though those exploratory symptom-level analyses had been conducted using measures based on DSM/ICD.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is much to discuss in this paper, but for illustrative purposes, I’ll focus on the case of depression and some other internalizing disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Major depressive disorder” (MDD) is one of the most common and recognizable disorders in psychiatry. Hundreds of thousands of people are diagnosed with MDD every day. Every medical student is taught the SIGECAPS symptoms that constitute the diagnostic criteria of depression, and across many clinics, people fill out the PHQ-9 screening questionnaire based on those symptoms. Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) and Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) are similarly common diagnoses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What does it mean that MDD, GAD, and PTSD do not show up as coherent and distinctive symptom clusters in statistical analysis?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the internalizing spectrum as it appears in Forbes et al. 2023:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the depressed mood and anhedonia cluster:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are the self-derogation, suicidality, and guilt/shame proneness clusters:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is something statistically distinctive about the clusters labeled as ‘depressed mood and anhedonia,’ ‘self-derogation,’ ‘suicidality,’ ‘guilt/shame proneness,’ ‘morning depression,’ ‘emotional lability,’ etc., but there is nothing statistically distinctive about the combination of 9 symptoms that we recognize as diagnostic criteria for depression:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;So, what is going on here?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Obviously, people present with symptoms associated with major depression, and they report these symptoms if they are asked about them. That isn’t in doubt. What is in doubt is whether there is anything statistically special about this symptom combination.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All syndromes in the ‘Distress’ subfactor are correlated with each other, so people would present with various combinations of the syndromes, with some inclusion of symptoms/syndromes from other subfactors and spectra (since they are all correlated at a higher level).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ms. Jones may experience:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Depressed mood and anhedonia&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Morning depression&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Self-derogation&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Suicidality&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Guilt/Shame&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Early sleep and awakening&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mr. Jamal may experience:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Depressed mood and anhedonia&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Irritability&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Emotional lability&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Psychomotor agitation&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Insomnia&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Anxiousness&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ms. Freeman may experience:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Depressed mood and anhedonia&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;General cognitive difficulties&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Distractibility&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Psychomotor impairment&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Suspiciousness&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Psychological panic&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Guilt/Shame&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All three meet MDD symptom criteria, but they all show varying combinations of more fundamental (statistically homogenous) syndromic clusters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MDD indexes a varying and heterogenous subset of symptoms/syndromes, and what is common about these varying subsets is that depressed mood and/or anhedonia are prominent aspects of the presentation. In a similar manner, GAD indexes a varying and heterogenous subset of symptoms/syndromes, and what is common about these varying subsets is that pervasive anxiety is a prominent aspect of the presentation. And PTSD indexes a varying and heterogenous subset of symptoms/syndromes, and what is common about these varying subsets is that traumatic intrusions and avoidance are prominent aspects of the presentation. The subsets that constitute MDD, GAD, and PTSD all overlap, which is why these heterogenous categories dissolve when statistical homogeneity is sought. (This is also one reason why the reliability for MDD and GAD was so low in DSM-5 field trials.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can see in the figure below how MDD dissolves into homogenous elements that map onto ‘Distress,’ ‘Neurocognitive Impairment,’ ‘Dysregulated Sleep,’ and ‘Dysregulated Eating.’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ken Kendler notes in his historical review of depression symptoms and the DSM:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“… the author examines how well DSM-5 symptomatic criteria for major depression capture the descriptions of clinical depression in the post-Kraepelin Western psychiatric tradition as described in textbooks published between 1900 and 1960. Eighteen symptoms and signs of depression were described, 10 of which are covered by the DSM criteria for major depression or melancholia. For two symptoms (mood and cognitive content), DSM criteria are considerably narrower than those described in the textbooks. Five symptoms and signs (changes in volition/motivation, slowing of speech, anxiety, other physical symptoms, and depersonalization/derealization) are not present in the DSM criteria. Compared with the DSM criteria, these authors gave greater emphasis to cognitive, physical, and psychomotor changes, and less to neurovegetative symptoms. These results suggest that important features of major depression are not captured by DSM criteria. This is unproblematic as long as DSM criteria are understood to index rather than constitute psychiatric disorders. However, since DSM-III, our field has moved toward a reification of DSM that implicitly assumes that psychiatric disorders are actually just the DSM criteria. That is, we have taken an index of something for the thing itself.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DSM criteria for MDD are an index, but what is the thing itself? If Forbes et al. are correct, the thing itself isn’t a fixed, stable entity but consists of variable and heterogenous subsets of internalizing and neurocognitive symptoms. And each time we use MDD as an index, we index something different. (Different from but overlapping with other instances.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DSM criteria for MDD are an index, but what is the thing itself? If Forbes et al. are correct, the thing itself isn’t a fixed, stable entity but consists of variable and heterogeneous subsets of internalizing and neurocognitive symptoms. And each time we use MDD as an index, we index something different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are some important limitations to note with regards to the Forbes et al. survey. It relies only on self-reported symptoms, and features requiring clinician observation are missing; symptoms are decontextualized (e.g., insomnia due to substance withdrawal isn’t differentiated from insomnia due to anxiety); all symptoms were assessed using a 12-month time scale, even though different symptom patterns exist at different time scales.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Forbes et al. themselves note,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“It will also be essential to understand which aspects of these results—particularly the fine-grained levels of the structure—are robust to other approaches to measurement (i.e., using alternative measures, time frames, multi-method or multi-informant approaches, as well as within-person assessment) and across intersectional conceptualizations of identity (e.g., in a variety of sociodemographic and culturally and linguistically diverse samples).”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See also:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.psychiatrymargins.com/p/traditional-dsm-disorders-dissolve?r=2wyot6&amp;triedRedirect=true"/><published>2025-09-22T02:24:50+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45328545</id><title>Seattle, Tech Boomtown, Grapples with a Future of Fewer Tech Jobs</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:58.428612+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/seattle-tech-amazon-microsoft-jobs-95f2db27"/><published>2025-09-22T02:26:22+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45328702</id><title>Jet-Nemotron: Efficient Language Model with Post Neural Architecture Search</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:58.122683+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="1c8c340ae593848e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Computation and Language&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 21 Aug 2025 (v1), last revised 8 Sep 2025 (this version, v2)]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:Jet-Nemotron: Efficient Language Model with Post Neural Architecture Search&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:We present Jet-Nemotron, a new family of hybrid-architecture language models, which matches or exceeds the accuracy of leading full-attention models while significantly improving generation throughput. Jet-Nemotron is developed using Post Neural Architecture Search (PostNAS), a novel neural architecture exploration pipeline that enables efficient model design. Unlike prior approaches, PostNAS begins with a pre-trained full-attention model and freezes its MLP weights, allowing efficient exploration of attention block designs. The pipeline includes four key components: (1) learning optimal full-attention layer placement and elimination, (2) linear attention block selection, (3) designing new attention blocks, and (4) performing hardware-aware hyperparameter search. Our Jet-Nemotron-2B model achieves comparable or superior accuracy to Qwen3, Qwen2.5, Gemma3, and Llama3.2 across a comprehensive suite of benchmarks while delivering up to 53.6x generation throughput speedup and 6.1x prefilling speedup. It also achieves higher accuracy on MMLU and MMLU-Pro than recent advanced MoE full-attention models, such as DeepSeek-V3-Small and Moonlight, despite their larger scale with 15B total and 2.2B activated parameters.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Submission history&lt;/head&gt;From: Han Cai [view email]&lt;p&gt;[v1] Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:59:08 UTC (810 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v2] Mon, 8 Sep 2025 02:44:54 UTC (771 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Current browse context: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;cs.CL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15884"/><published>2025-09-22T03:00:32+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45328828</id><title>South Korea's President says US investment demands would spark financial crisis</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:57.862164+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="222e99dd24a39b8d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SEOUL, Sept 22 (Reuters) - South Korea's economy could fall into crisis rivalling its 1997 meltdown if the government accepts current U.S. demands in stalled trade talks without safeguards, President Lee Jae Myung told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seoul and Washington verbally agreed to a trade deal in July in which the U.S. would lower President Donald Trump's tariffs on South Korean goods in exchange for $350 billion in investment from South Korea, among other measures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sign up here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They have yet to put the agreement to paper because of disputes over how the investments would be handled, Lee said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Without a currency swap, if we were to withdraw $350 billion in the manner that the U.S. is demanding and to invest this all in cash in the U.S., South Korea would face a situation as it had in the 1997 financial crisis," he said through a translator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In an interview in his office on Friday, Lee also spoke about a huge U.S. immigration raid that detained hundreds of Koreans, as well as Seoul's relations with rival North Korea, neighbouring giant China and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But trade and defence talks with the U.S., South Korea's military ally and a top economic partner, are overshadowing a trip Lee makes from Monday to New York, where he will address the United Nations General Assembly and be the first South Korean president to chair a meeting of the Security Council.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;PRAISES TRUMP'S HANDLING OF HYUNDAI RAID&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lee, a liberal, took office in a June snap election after his conservative predecessor, Yoon Suk Yeol, was removed from office and jailed for briefly imposing martial law. Lee has sought to calm the country and its economy and said he plans to use his U.S. visit to tell the world that "democratic Korea is back".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lee met Trump for their first summit in August, saying he had built a strong personal tie with the U.S. leader, despite not agreeing on a joint statement or concrete announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This month Trump's administration rocked South Korea with the arrest of more than 300 South Korean workers at a Hyundai Motor battery plant in Georgia, with federal officials accusing them of immigration violations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lee said South Koreans were naturally angered by the "harsh" treatment of the workers - the Trump administration published images of them in shackles - and has warned it could make companies wary of investing in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But he said the raid would not undermine the bilateral alliance, praising Trump for offering to let the workers stay. Lee said he did not believe it was directed by Trump but was the result of overzealous law enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I do not believe this was intentional, and the U.S. has apologised for this incident, and we have agreed to seek reasonable measures in this regard and we are working on them," he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lee's office says there is no plan for him to meet Trump in New York and that the trade talks are not on the visit's agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;STUMBLING BLOCK IN TRADE TALKS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick has said South Korea should follow Japan's deal with the United States. He said Seoul either needs to accept the deal or pay the tariffs, using the Trump administration's depiction of foreign governments paying the levies, which are instead paid by U.S. importers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lee, asked if he would walk away from the deal, said: "I believe that between blood allies, we will be able to maintain the minimum amount of rationality."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;South Korea has proposed a foreign exchange swap line with the U.S. to reduce the shock of the investments on the local market for the won currency. Lee did not address how likely the U.S. was to agree or whether that would be enough for the deal to go forward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He said South Korea is different from Japan, which struck a trade deal with the U.S. in July. Tokyo has more than double South Korea's $410 billion foreign exchange reserves, an international currency in the yen and a swap line with the United States, Lee said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seoul and Washington have said in writing that any investment projects must be commercially viable, but working out the details is proving difficult, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Reaching detailed agreements that guarantee commercial reasonableness is now the central task - yet it also remains the biggest obstacle," Lee said. Proposals during working level talks provide no assurance of commercial viability, making it hard to bridge the gap, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trump says the investments will be "selected" by him and controlled by the U.S., meaning Washington would have discretion over where the money will be invested.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Lee policy adviser Kim Yong-beom said in July that South Korea had added a safety mechanism to reduce financing risk, including supporting commercially feasible projects rather than providing unconditional financial support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lee said South Korea and the United States do not disagree on increasing Seoul's contributions toward its own defence, bolstered by 28,500 U.S. troops on the Korean peninsula, but that Washington wants to keep security and trade talks separate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We should end this unstable situation as soon as possible," he said, when asked whether talks could extend into next year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;TENSIONS WITH NORTH KOREA, CHINA, RUSSIA&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lee has sought to reduce tensions with nuclear-armed North Korea. Pyongyang has rebuffed the South's overtures, and Lee said he was not optimistic about the prospect of inter-Korean talks for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During their meeting, Lee encouraged Trump to try to meet again with North Korean leader Kim Jong Un during Trump's trip next month for an Asia-Pacific summit Lee will host in the South.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lee told Reuters his government does not have detailed information on the status of any talks between Washington and Pyongyang. "It is our judgement that they are not engaging in concrete conversations," he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He said he shares his predecessor Yoon's view that North Korea's military cooperation with Russia is a significant threat to South Korea's security. But he said it is not enough to respond in a simplistic way to the issue, which must be addressed through dialogue and coordination.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The North Korean leader and Russian President Vladimir Putin stood shoulder to shoulder this month in Beijing when Chinese President Xi Jinping hosted them at a massive military parade and summit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lee said there is increasing confrontation between a socialist camp of countries and a capitalist, democratic camp that includes Seoul, and South Korea's geography threatens to place it on the frontier of any conflict with the other camp.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He said there is an escalatory spiral of rivalry and tensions where South Korea, Japan and the United States deepen cooperation and China, Russia, and North Korea work more closely together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"This is a very dangerous situation for Korea, and we must find an exit ramp out of the escalating military tensions," Lee said. "We must find a way for peaceful coexistence."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reporting by Josh Smith, Hyunjoo Jin and Heejung Jung; Additional reporting by Cynthia Kim; Writing by Josh Smith; Editing by William Mallard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our Standards: The Thomson Reuters Trust Principles.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://www.reuters.com/world/china/south-koreas-president-lee-says-us-investment-demands-would-spark-financial-2025-09-21/"/><published>2025-09-22T03:30:31+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45329127</id><title>Privacy and Security Risks in the eSIM Ecosystem [pdf]</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:57.065981+00:00</updated><content/><link href="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/usenixsecurity25-motallebighomi.pdf"/><published>2025-09-22T04:35:27+00:00</published></entry><entry><id>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45329414</id><title>Download Responsibly</title><updated>2025-09-22T07:35:56.377307+00:00</updated><content>&lt;doc fingerprint="2ce57d957d222cce"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10.09.2025 | Frederik Ramm&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This month we’ve ramped up the infrastructure behind the download server, and downloads should now be available earlier&lt;lb/&gt; and faster. There’s also a small technical change in that requests for a “…latest” file will now be answered with a&lt;lb/&gt; HTTP redirect to the specific latest version (see previous blog post).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would like to use this opportunity to appeal to users of the download server to “download responsibly”. We want&lt;lb/&gt; to continue offering this service as powerful and as convenient as possible within our means. We want everyone&lt;lb/&gt; to have easy access to the latest OSM data in a form that is useful to them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every now and then, people break things for others. There have been individual clients downloading the exact same&lt;lb/&gt; 20-GB file 100s of times per day, for several days in a row. (Just the other day, one user has managed to download almost 10,000 copies of the italy-latest.osm.pbf file in 24 hours!) Others download every single file we have on the&lt;lb/&gt; server, every day. There’s a limit to the outgoing network bandwidth, and behaviour like this means that&lt;lb/&gt; things are slowing down for everyone. Also, when we block an IP range for abuse, innocent third parties can be affected. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s three concrete appeals to users of the download server:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. If you want data for the whole planet, don’t download it piecemeal from us – simply get the planet file from planet.openstreetmap.org and you’re done!&lt;lb/&gt; 2. If you want a large region (like Europe or North America) updated daily, use the excellent pyosmium-up-to-date program which will automatically determine the age of your local file and update it by downloading the latest changes; this saves something like 98% of network traffic compared to a fresh download, and is faster.&lt;lb/&gt; 3. If you automate anything with regard to our download server, monitor what your script is doing or build in appropriate catches so that you don’t end up downloading the same file 1000 times just because your disk is full or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Happy downloading!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</content><link href="https://blog.geofabrik.de/index.php/2025/09/10/download-responsibly/"/><published>2025-09-22T05:33:54+00:00</published></entry></feed>