<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 18:14:01 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>The universal weight subspace hypothesis</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05117</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3c1d2c0bdef3808e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Machine Learning&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 4 Dec 2025 (v1), last revised 6 Dec 2025 (this version, v2)]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:The Universal Weight Subspace Hypothesis&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:We show that deep neural networks trained across diverse tasks exhibit remarkably similar low-dimensional parametric subspaces. We provide the first large-scale empirical evidence that demonstrates that neural networks systematically converge to shared spectral subspaces regardless of initialization, task, or domain. Through mode-wise spectral analysis of over 1100 models - including 500 Mistral-7B LoRAs, 500 Vision Transformers, and 50 LLaMA-8B models - we identify universal subspaces capturing majority variance in just a few principal directions. By applying spectral decomposition techniques to the weight matrices of various architectures trained on a wide range of tasks and datasets, we identify sparse, joint subspaces that are consistently exploited, within shared architectures across diverse tasks and datasets. Our findings offer new insights into the intrinsic organization of information within deep networks and raise important questions about the possibility of discovering these universal subspaces without the need for extensive data and computational resources. Furthermore, this inherent structure has significant implications for model reusability, multi-task learning, model merging, and the development of training and inference-efficient algorithms, potentially reducing the carbon footprint of large-scale neural models.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Submission history&lt;/head&gt;From: Prakhar Kaushik [view email]&lt;p&gt;[v1] Thu, 4 Dec 2025 18:59:58 UTC (14,316 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v2] Sat, 6 Dec 2025 04:42:07 UTC (14,321 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Current browse context: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;cs.LG&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; IArxiv Recommender (What is IArxiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46199623</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:16:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>30 Year Anniversary of WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness</title><link>https://www.jorsys.org/archive/december_2025.html#newsitem_2025-12-09T07:42:19Z</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="be435c9aabb33e50"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has now been 30 years since WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness was released. After the great response to Warcraft: Orcs and Humans, released in November 1994, Blizzard began working on Warcraft II: Tides of Darkness. Development stared in the first months of 1995, and the game was released in North America and Australia on December 9, 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While WarCraft: Orcs and Humans had laid the foundations of the series — arguably even for the RTS genre at a whole — it was really WarCraft II that took things to new heights. More units could be selected at once, the player could right-click to issue commands, naval and aerial combat was introduced, and buildings and units could be upgraded. The graphics were more vivid and visually appealing, and features like the Fog of War was introduced, where you could only see in the vicinity of your own units — unlike in the first game, where you could indefinitely see any area you had previously visited, you now had to continuously scout the map.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many things still resembled the first game. The two factions — the Humans and the Orcs — were balanced through their similarites. For every unit and building of one faction, the other had one that was functionally equivalent, and so the sides largely mirrored each other. The only real differences lay in the spells available to their higher-level units. In that regard, the clear winners were the Orcs, who had a tremendous advantage thanks to the incredibly powerful and unbalanced Bloodlust spell of the Ogre-Magi.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is quite impressive that Blizzard managed to release a title of such quality in such a short span of time, especially considering that the overall design and gameplay evolved during development. Originally, Blizzard’s concept blended modern and fantasy elements, such as fighter pilots being ambushed by a fire-breathing dragon. In the Alpha version (it is still probably floating around somewhere on the Internet) which was given to magazines for review shortly before the game's release, players could, for example mine rocks, which acted as an additional required resource.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Several versions and bundles of WarCraft II were released over the years:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness, originally written for DOS, though it had a Windows launch screen and ran well under Windows 95. A Macintosh version was also released. The DOS version supported multiplayer games via null modem cable, modem, or IPX, while Mac players could also play via TCP/IP or AppleTalk.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: Beyond the Dark Portal, the expansion, released in April 1996.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft: Battle Chest, released in 1996, was a bundle which included WarCraft: Orcs and Humans, WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness, and WarCraft II: Beyond the Dark Portal.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: The Dark Saga, released in 1997, was a port for the Sega Saturn and PlayStation consoles by Electronic Arts, including the campaigns from both Tides of Darkness and Beyond the Dark Portal.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: Battle.net Edition, released in 1999, ported the game's code to Microsoft Windows, fixed some minor bugs, and enabled multiplayer support via Blizzard's online service, Battle.net.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II Battle Chest, released in 1999, included the Battle.net Edition and its official strategy guide.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: Remastered, released in November 2024, is modern remaster of Tides of Darkness and Beyond the Dark Portal, with improved graphics and updated controls.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness received enthusiastic reviews, elevating Blizzard to the top ranks alongside Westwood Studios, id Software, and LucasArts. The rivalry between Blizzard's series and Westwood Studios' Command and Conquer series helped fuel the RTS boom of the late 1990s. PC Gamer US named WarCraft II the best game of 1995, calling it an "easy" choice and writing that "Warcraft II stand[s] out — way out — as the most impressive, most entertaining, game of 1995". The editors also awarded it Best Multi-Player Game of 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WarCraft II was notable for the large number of third-party utilities created for it. Quickly, Daniel Lemberg reverse-engineered and published the map file (*.pud) format and wrote the first third-party map editor, War2xEd, which could do multiple things that the bundled map editor could not, such as editing unit attributes. Blizzard apparently began using War2xEd internally, and it influenced their decision to later ship a feature-rich map editor with StarCraft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, Alexander Cech and Daniel Lemberg reverse-engineered the game data format, the WAR archives. Alexander Cech went on to make a hugely important tool called Wardraft, which allowed users to browse and modify the contents of the WAR archives. This enabled extensive game modifications, known as "Total Conversions". Many such projects gained popularity and remained in development for a long time, notable examples being DeathCraft: Twilight of Demons, War of the Ring, Editor's Total Conversion, Funcraft and Rituals of Rebirth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of these utilities and conversions have long since faded into obscurity, but their legacy lives on. They impacted Blizzard's desicion to bundle ever more powerful editors and trigger systems into StarCraft and later WarCraft III, which in turn later spawned entire games such as Dota (which began as a WarCraft III map). Hopefully, someday (soon?) we can host some of the Total Conversions here at Jorvik Systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a personal anecdote, I vividly remember two defining moments related to the game. I was young when it came out, and my dad's friend had pirated it; somehow the game ended up on our computer. I was too young to speak English at the time, and the interface was confusing to me, so a relative helped me understand the basics — how to make peons construct buildings, how to control units, and how to navigate around the map. I hadn't played computer games much before then, but from that moment on, I was arguably obsessed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A second strong memory came a few months later, at my friend Erik's house, on his Intel 486 PC. He was experimenting with the WarCraft II map editor, which I hadn't known existed, and I was blown away. I simply could not believe that Blizzard would ship such a tool with the game; to me, it meant that people could essentially create their own games by designing entirely new scenarios. It is quite possible that my fascination with modding was born in that very moment. We probably went outside to play shortly afterward, which I found incredibly lame — we had at our disposal the most powerful tool I could imagine, so why were we not inside using it?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46202921</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 09:13:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Joy of Playing Grandia, on Sega Saturn</title><link>https://www.segasaturnshiro.com/2025/11/27/the-joy-of-playing-grandia-on-sega-saturn/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b78dd71e0a31439d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Renaissance Period&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are living through a Saturn renaissance. Buckets of titles previously locked away in Japan are seeing new audiences, thanks to the herculean efforts of small but dedicated teams of enthusiast translators, removing the veil of Japanese illiteracy from before our tired eyes. Interestingly, the majority of efforts are being directed at the games with the biggest scripts, and no other genre was as impacted by the language barrier as the text-heavy, story-driven RPG. Over a dozen quality titles are now playable in English. The Saturn is, once again, ascendant…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Ain’t life Grand?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enter Grandia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What hasn’t been said about Grandia? In the run-up to its late 1997 release, the game enjoyed significant worldwide coverage in the gaming press, not least because some positioned it as the anti-FF7 title. Hot on the heels of the remaster of Lunar: Silver Star Story and hailing from respected software house Game Arts, featuring state of the art fully 3D environments, a score by notable composer Noriyuki Iwadare, sound effects produced by Skywalker Sound… Grandia was indeed shaping up to be one of the premier JRPG experiences of the 5th generation. There was serious talk of bringing the game out West — Working Designs was touted as the favoured house to do the honors, owing to their strong partnership with Game Arts, but the game’s massive script would have meant a late 1998 release by even the speediest conversion standards of the time. By then, the Western Saturn retail market had collapsed, and despite a shrinking but fervently dedicated base of Saturn fans holding on to hope of seeing the title cross the ocean, the game wound up locked away in Japan, forever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;NEVER say Forever&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Game Arts subsequently ported Grandia to the PlayStation, dropping it in Japan in the summer of 1999. Sony speedily localized the game for Western release later that same year… but we aren’t going to focus too much on the PlayStation version here because, at the time of writing, PlayStation discs don’t boot on your SEGA Saturn. It’s the Saturn game that we are concerned with. For us Saturn stalwarts, we had to wait to the mid-2020s for an intrepid team led by TrekkiesUnite113 to transplant the PlayStation’s English script into the Saturn code. By then, the game was decades old, not to mention re-released and ‘re-mastered’ on modern platforms. So, why translate Grandia for the Saturn, when multiple other English options exist?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because Grandia is Best on Saturn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How do you do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set in an age of discovery at the dawn of the industrial revolution, Grandia initially tells the tale of young Justin — a 14-year-old fearless adolescent who can’t help but dream of adventure. When he isn’t playing at “hero” with his town friends, he’s dreaming of great expeditions to find the lost civilization of Angelou. He is joined by his friend Sue — an 8-year-old girl whose maturity belies her age, and who tries desperately to keep young Justin in line. Justin’s mom Lily runs the local Seagull Restaurant and does her best to raise Justin into a respectable young man… though in her youth, she was a scrappy pirate herself. In her heart, she knows her audacious spark has passed on to her son, and that Justin will one day take up the adventurer’s mantle and take off on a grand adventure of his own, so she does her best to prepare him for when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She gives Justin a Spirit Stone — a remnant of the Angelou civilization and a memento of his long-lost father — and in doing so, helps kick off a fantastic voyage that sees young Justin explore, learn, overcome all manner of obstacles, and ultimately, grow and become the hero that he always imagined himself to be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During his quest, Justin encounters fascinating characters, both friend and foe. From quiet folk in sleepy villages to rambunctious youngsters eager for their own slice of adventure; from military platoons led by the most beautiful — but hopelessly shallow — lady sergeants to cunning merchants, towering warriors, alluring mermaids and ferocious dragons… Justin encounters them all, and for good or ill, manages to change the course of their lives in ways both subtle and grand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Justin, Sue, and Feena are the first three playable characters in Grandia. Young Sue tries to keep Justin in line, while Feena searches for the true meaning of being an adventurer – with Justin slowly moving from admiring her to showing her the way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game is clever in pulling the player in for a ride that for a very long while feels very lighthearted and innocent. Even as Justin’s adventure begins in earnest and the player is exposed to antagonists, mysteries, undercurrents and intrigues, Justin can’t help but distill it back to the very pure essence of boyhood adventure. Mysterious tower causing problems for a nearby village for years? No problem, Justin will fix it! A dragon from a nearby volcano terrorizing the locals? Justin’s got this. A ghost ship sailing in to harass a passenger steamer? Justin is the answer, in the same way that, as youngsters, we all knew – we knew! – that WE were the heroes, and that WE would save the day, armed only with our courage and our grand imaginations. It was our duty, after all. We had it in us to go forth boldly, and change the world (and naturally, all before being called home for dinner).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This point is driven home by Justin’s insatiable desire to uncover the mystery of his Spirit Stone, and the ancient Angelou civilization. After an unfortunate but entirely predictable mishap in the local museum, followed by a mysterious revelation in the nearby Sult Ruins, Justin’s curiosity is ignited, and his drive for real adventure becomes indomitable. Meanwhile, forces are at work that care not for Justin’s explorations, and inevitably, the lad finds himself pitted against the Garlyle Forces and some of its top commanders. Their aims are complex and their operations span the world, and this scope creates a wonderful juxtaposition with Justin’s innocent demeanor and singular focus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;On Screen!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Fifth Generation of consoles marked the rise of 3D graphics, but some genres made the leap easier than others. This shift was a struggle for RPGs, with many excellent titles continuing to employ 2D visuals, albeit in richer color and more sophisticated detail than seen in previous generations. Early attempts at the 3D RPG (Virtual Hydlide) highlighted how difficult it was to run this style of game on the hardware of the time without wrecking the framerate or keeping textures from looking like a checkerboard mess. Dungeon crawlers (Shining the Holy Ark) were among the first titles to get the 3D right, though the player’s scope of movement was very restricted. Finally, some fantasized that “3D” meant pre-rendered backgrounds and copious FMV clips, with the only real 3D being battle scenes. Ahem!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia took the traditional overhead RPG view and transformed the landscapes into fully realized 3D polygonal playfields that can be rotated and zoomed at will. Character and enemy sprites are then overlain on the 3D world to make the scenes come to life. The addition of the third dimension affords the use of depth in the environments: hills, cliffs, and valleys; minecar rails that ran higher or lower relative to other tracks, and so on. In this way, the player initially feels right at home with a view that looks comfortably familiar, but must quickly learn to constantly rotate the viewpoint to catch enemies in hiding, spy treasures only visible from certain angles, judge heights, and evaluate other geometric details to plot their best course forward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia wastes no time in getting gamers used to this new visual paradigm. One of the game’s first quests sees local frenemy Gantz challenge Justin and Sue to locate the three Legendary Treasures: the fabled helmet (Iron Pot), the storied shield (Pot Lid), and of course, the legendary (Wooden) Sword. The player must traverse all of Parm, climbing down river walkways, checking in enclosed spaces, and chasing down Gantz’s little brother to prove they are up to Gantz’ task — and in the process, get used to the game’s then-new control scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 3D is very well put together, both technical and artistically. The level of detail is truly phenomenal, from the tiniest objects and details, especially in the ‘in-town’ game sections. Justin is able to interact with some of the innocuous scenery — for example he can knock brooms over, disturb piles of plates, or bump into bells and chimes — just as any real, overly excited 14-year-old might clumsily do as they ran along. Animations, from little weathervanes rotating to laundry fluttering on a clothesline, to puffs of smoke coming up from fires or chimneys, all accentuate the feeling that these are real, living, bustling places. The level of detail, and all of it in 3D, is really special.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The coders at Game Arts made excellent use of the Saturn’s unique hardware when realizing Grandia’s locales. Where appropriate, textured infinite planes are used to draw floors, and they not only look good but also dramatically cut down on the usage of polygons in drawing the scene, leaving that much more in the processing budget to spend on other visual details. In later sections, those infinite planes take on a distortion effect to create some very cool-looking water flows — look for them initially in Parm’s pier, and later in places like the snowy Laine Village or the mysterious Castle of Dreams. The water shimmers as the player rotates their view to create a truly stunning effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game’s characters and enemies are all represented by sprites that animate quite well and take viewpoints into account as the player rotates the camera. In yet more attention to detail, the sprites darken and then lighten again as the player moves in and out of shadowed areas — an impressive little detail that accentuates the visuals even further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trio of General Baal, Colonel Mullen, and Leen is introduced in the game’s opening scene, and all three are more than they appear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The care that Game Arts took in crafting the visuals is commendable and Grandia comes off as one of the very best-looking 3D RPGs for the system, but Game Arts was perhaps a mite too ambitious. There are sections of the game where the framerate really chugs. Now, it must be acknowledged that low framerates were a hallmark of many 3D games in the 32-bit era, so some of this is to be expected, but the more detail Grandia is trying to show you, the more you will feel the Saturn huffing and puffing to get the job done. The game’s 3D framerate is not high at the best of times but it is passable, so it’s somewhat of a relief that the areas where it truly takes a dive aren’t too common.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pump up the Jam!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Game Arts’ attention to detail extends to the sound department. For Grandia, Game Arts commissioned Skywalker Sound to handle the game’s sound effects. The result is positional sound — effects like running water, crackling fire, etc. will fade in and out as Justin and co. move closer in or further away from the source. Often, if the effect is important, it will also somewhat dampen the volume of the BGM as it plays out. Additionally, the effects will pan left or right depending on the source, and especially as the player rotates the camera. These effects may be subtle, but they are very well implemented and add to the game’s overall polish.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game’s soundtrack was composed by Noriyuki Iwadare and is both varied and excellent. Iwadare’s use of instruments appropriate to the on-screen action is uncanny — for example, running around Parm we are treated to an industrial sounding theme, perfect for the town’s motif. The varied use of strings, drums and winds is frankly excellent and lends to the atmosphere, imitating the clang of metal and steel which so permeates the city. Equally impressive is that the music somehow manages to be exciting or somber or poignant without ever sounding overly (excuse the wordplay) grandiose. This keeps the soundtrack in line with the game’s more lighthearted narrative. Of course, where appropriate, the soundtrack does take on that epic quality. The desperate tones that play when the Garlyle forces appear contrast so well with the carefree, upbeat “Off Runs Sue” tune. Mullen’s theme is at once wistful and ambitious, and even the theme from the Sult Ruins dungeon is perfectly mood-setting. Multiple Grandia soundtracks have been released since the game’s debut and the soundtrack is universally praised.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How it Plays Out&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia’s gameplay, like so many RPGs before it, is split into two major gameplay slices: exposition-laden town sections and combat-focused dungeons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Players will spend a fair bit of time in the ‘in-town’ sections of the game. Here, you will wander around, take in the scenery, interact with the NPCs of the area, and almost always, find a quest that must be completed. A quick word about the NPCs — there are quite a number of them in each town, and everyone has something interesting to say… and almost always, each NCP has at least two separate conversation sequences to offer, making for a truly large amount of story to soak in. And it’s all entirely optional! It’s completely possible to make one’s way through Grandia with only minimal NCP interaction, but the option to enhance the adventure with these extensive NPC interactions is always there, as each character will present a unique view or focused response.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Predictably, the towns are filled with shops, though Grandia keeps things rather simple — there is but one general store which carries weapons, armor, accessories, and even magic all under the same roof. Buy, sell or trade up to the latest gear which gradually increases in the stat boosts it confers to your characters. Additionally, each town typically has one or more important locales, such as mayors’ offices or the chambers of village chiefs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is typically an inn or other house where the party can take rest, and at certain points in the game, resting triggers a shared meal scene that sees Justin break bread with his party mates. These meal scenes offer up critical dialogue, which the gamer can extend or keep short at their whim. When the critical conversation has been had, a bedtime icon will appear over Justin’s character sprite, and if the player is quite finished listening to the party chatter, they can select it to end the meal and get some rest. These mealtime conversations serve not only to flesh out what the party must tackle next, but also to offer a glimpse into the inner thoughts of the individual characters as they share their opinions, hopes and fears. Like so much in the game, Grandia implements this character exposition in a way that allows the player to decide how much of it to take in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The visuals in the town sections really stand out. The Saturn manages to shift not only impressive amounts of polygons for the various structures, but also vivid and complex textures. This technical prowess is coupled with lush and imaginative art direction, resulting in each locale feeling complete and distinct. The dense, humid and green surrounds of Luc Village, nestled deep within the Misty Forest and inhabited by humanoid creatures contrasts sharply with the seaside port town of Dight with its cerulean waves gently rolling in onto its sandy shores. Milda’s hometown village of Laine is covered in snow, and the ancient Zil Padon is an architectural wonder with a central fountain in the middle of the Savanna desert. Game Arts very clearly discarded their standard world building cookie cutters, and their efforts shine through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once a locale has been explored, it will appear as a selectable destination on a gorgeous, hand-drawn high-resolution world map. Exiting an area often brings our party to this world map, and the next destination can be selected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the towns serve to heal the party, upgrade equipment, and advance the story, then the dungeons of the game offer treasure hunting, exploration, and of course, combat! Dungeons in Grandia range from literal underground labyrinths to above-ground forest mazes, to even large open plains that Justin et al. must traverse. Some of the more noteworthy settings include scaling a giant wall that keeps the world divided into two separate societies, negotiating the bowels of a ghost ship which appears out of nowhere to molest a transcontinental steamer, and even conquering the inside of an unstable volcano that’s inhabited by an ancient dragon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here, the player really must use their L and R buttons to shift the 3D landscape around, to find all the nooks of treasure or paths forward. Some areas feature set pieces that Justin and party can activate — for example, knocking over a loose pillar to bridge a gap. These are usually indicated by an exclamation point icon when the party nears the set piece.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the while, treasure both great and small litters the landscape… but so do enemies! Enemies are visible in the dungeons and so can be avoided to an extent, but if Justin and party come in contact with an enemy, combat ensues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Grandia Grinder Alert!&lt;lb/&gt;Grind for Experience Points Using Environmental Damage!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are YOU a Grandia grinder?? Some sections of the game will deal damage to Justin and party outside of combat. First noticed in the Dom Ruins, rock faces painted into some of the dungeon walls will cause mild HP damage by springing out and poking the party when the party doesn’t want to be poked! The player can then use heal magic and spam this process to quickly increase Water magic levels. Although definitely a grind, it’s much faster than earning those experience points via combat. A few other areas in the game present similar opportunities — such as the basement in the Castle of Dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A New Kind of Kombat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia introduced an all-new combat system to the RPG genre, though it could be said to be a variant of other similar RPG battle systems. Essentially, all battle participants have icons that continuously move along a universal IP Gauge, until they reach the Command point. Here, the player will enter from a selection of commands which includes attacking, using an item or a spell, guarding, or even retreating. They then wait to reach the very end of the gauge to execute their selected action, and the more experienced the character, the faster that point is reached. A ton of strategy is introduced here as during this waiting period between selecting an action and executing it, they are vulnerable to both Cancels and Counterattacks from their opponents. Unlike many contemporary RPGs where the instinct is to simply unleash physical and magical attacks in a turn-based order, the player can take advantage of these waiting periods to cancel out incoming enemy attacks and push them back on their IP gauge. The system will take some getting used to, but can be used to devastating effect, especially in the more drawn-out boss battles. It is entirely possible to strategically get in a half-dozen actions by each character and prevent a boss from retaliating during the entire sequence, by carefully timing attacks. This makes combat a lot more involved and exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are also advantages to catching an enemy unawares — player characters start much further ahead on their IP Gauge, with the reverse being true if Justin’s party is ambushed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Players have a range of actions they can take when their IP Gauge is full, from the standard fare of using items, defending, running away, or even inspecting an enemy (is that slug-monster male or female, for example*).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nana, Saki, and Mio are Mullen’s three she-sergeants. Serving as comedic relief, they are nevertheless quite capable opponents in battle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;By Your Powers Combined… I Am Captain Planet!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earth. Fire. Wind. Water. These are the elemental forces that move the world, and most characters can master them! Learning magic in Grandia first requires that the party finds a Mana Egg. These rare items can then be exchanged in a shop for magic for a single character of your choice. That party member then learns the basics of your chosen magic element.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inside of the four elements, magic spells are further split into levels, from one to three, to indicate their potency. Level 1 spells are your most basic spells and are what a character starts off with should they buy magic with their mana egg. Players that use magic in combat will gain skill points in that particular element, and those skill points are applied to all spells of that element, regardless of spell level — so, use a Level 1 Fire spell, and all levels of your Fire magic gain skill. Spell skill progression is represented by five red stars that fill up like a gauge, turning yellow as they gain experience. Greater experience shortens casting time (which, remember, is a vulnerable time as your spell can be cancelled by an opponent) and at higher levels, allows your character to learn combined element magic spells. All magic spells consume MP making them a limited resource, though a character’s overall MP capacity will grow with experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outside of magic, each character can also execute special attacks that are unique to them. These attacks are usually more devastating than standard attacks and sometimes require that the character is using a particular weapon class. These, too, gain skill points represented by five red stars that slowly build up to yellow, though special attacks consume SP (skill points). SP works much the same way as MP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Grandia Grinder Alert!&lt;lb/&gt;Rare Enemies Give High XP&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Typically, the game’s monsters do a good job of seeking you out, but there are occasional difficult-to-catch enemies to be found as well. Notice, for instance, the Chameleon enemies in the Virgin Forest. These green creatures are shy and are hard to catch and engage. But persist, and finish them off for a huge load of experience points — well worth a grinding sesh or three.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Experience Required&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia has a complex (for the time) experience points system, which is cleverly segmented into several categories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To start, each playable character has a set of basic stats that slowly increase as they gain experience. Hit Points (HP) are your standard measure of health and these increase at level-ups. SP are your skill points, which increase the speed and potency of your special attacks, as well as unlock new special attacks as you accumulate experience. Finally, the same is true of the more traditional magic points (MP), with the difference between SP and MP being that special attacks are individualized whereas magic attacks are more common amongst party members and can be bought in exchange for Mana Eggs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As they adventure, Justin and company will occasionally find items that slightly boost a particular stat on a permanent basis. These items are rare indeed, but as with life, incremental gains tend to compound until the effects are undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most traditionally, defeating enemies grants experience points and accumulating the required amount grants characters a level-up, which slightly increases basic stats. Experience gained and gold / treasure collected is displayed on an after-battle screen. It is this type of XP that most contemporary RPGs concerned themselves with. Grandia ups the complexity a bit by introducing leveling for magic and skills, and further mixes things up by employing different weapon classes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Justin and company are each capable of wielding a few different types of weapons, of which there are seven in total, ranging from swords to maces to staffs to bows. Each weapon class has its advantages and disadvantages, be it speed of use (from Command input to Execution on the IP gauge), to range, to overall damage dealt. As party members use their weapons, they gain experience in those weapon types, separately from their character experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, Grandia features basic character experience points which boosts common stats, magic experience which results in spells being cast faster and the learning of higher-level spells for various element types, skill experience for faster execution of special attacks, and weapon experience points which increase how well a character will handle that weapon type. Cleverly, these different experience categories are implemented in such a way as to make it entirely possible for gamers to completely ignore this aspect of the game should they so fancy. Because the system is automated, gamers can pay all of it little heed and still progress and have a great time with the game. Alternately, gamers can dive right into the finer points of the system to make those minor tweaks to get their characters to exactly the state they prefer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mysterious Liete awaits at Alent. The enigmatic Puffy accompanies Sue wherever she goes. Lastly, Darlin is one of the many non-human denizens of Grandia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Go with the Flow&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia allows up to four playable characters to form Justin’s party at any one time. As the story progresses, some of the main characters will permanently step away from the adventure, for reasons practical and dramatic alike. One such parting in particular tugs at the heartstrings — it is nothing quite as dramatic as the year’s earlier death of Aeris (Aerith) from that big RPG on Sony’s lesser 32-bit machine, but it somehow feels more relatable, and more impactful. Players ought not be surprised by the need for tissues to manage an unexpected tear or two. And here, too, Grandia innovates: a portion of a departing playable character’s magic and weapon experience points are stored in the stashing place, to be retrieved and applied to whatever character you see fit. This strengthens their legacy in your party, as well as provide a practical reason not to neglect building up a character just because they may eventually leave the party. A nice touch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Is It Perfect?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grand as it sounds, the game isn’t without a few small flaws. Story-wise, players will be left wanting to know more about Justin’s father and how he came to be the keeper of his Spirit Stone. He is mentioned often in the early stages of the game, but as Justin’s adventure takes off, that arc never completes. Likewise for General Baal — we eventually learn his motivations, but not so much why he has become who he is today. A really well put together villain is one with whom we can empathise; someone whose circumstance we can understand. Both with Justin’s unnamed father and with Baal, there is a feeling that we are reading a book and that the answers lie just ahead, but despite some teasing, Grandia never lets us turn the page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Technically, the game’s 3D is solid and varied, with plenty of minor details and meticulous textures, especially in the town sections. Blending VDP2-drawn planes with solid geometry and animated sprites means the world of Grandia is beautifully rendered, but that comes at the cost of an oft-stuttering framerate. The more of Grandia’s world we are allowed to see at once, the more the framerate suffers. Now, these were the formative years of 3D gaming, but at times, that framerate simply chugs, and it’s noticeable to the point of distraction. Thankfully, for most of the game, the framerate sits comfortably in the ‘acceptable’ space, but you won’t get through the game without feeling the Saturn sweat as it works to display all that Grandia’s artists wanted you to see.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of 3D, the game often requires the shifting of camera angles when exploring. When in long dungeons or any other large space, this can quickly become disorienting, and the player will lose their sense of direction. The game compensates somewhat for this with the addition of the compass, though its implementation is somewhat clumsy as rather than point north, it points to an exit or other objective. There is also lookout points called Dungeon Scopes, where the player is given a bird’s eye view of their current location from a default ‘north is up’ viewpoint. This helps orientating, but those lookout points are few and far between and using them tends to break up the game’s flow. Players may well find themselves keeping their camera shifting to a minimum as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lastly, a technical note: Grandia sure gives the Saturn’s laser a workout, and there are some clever pre-loading techniques implemented to keep the game flowing as smoothly as possible. The cost here is that Grandia is very sensitive to disc quality. Those that have burnt their English-patched game onto CDs and are playing on real Saturn hardware may well find the game freeze, especially in battle when calling various spells. This is VERY annoying, especially as dungeon save points are sparse, and it is not uncommon to be in the heat of a battle only to have everyone freeze with the reset button being the only escape. This is remedied by using an ODE solution that omits discs entirely, but the game’s sensitivity to the quality of your CD-R burn needs to be called out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Final Word&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia is great. The visuals are gorgeous, the music is appropriately evocative, the combat is frenetically strategic, and the story is well paced. Tough battles and surprise plot twists await intrepid gamers, and sub-plots occasionally weave their way into the adventure, too — especially in sections where we briefly leave Justin. On occasion, players will follow Colonel Mullen with Feena, explore the mysterious past of Mullen’s attaché Leen, or even soak in the comedic antics of the three beautiful Garlyle generals Mio, Nana, and Saki.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, Grandia a delight to play. A total joy… but one that demands an intense time commitment. A player Justin’s age surely has the time, but what about those of us that are well into adulting? Some sections of the game, especially the longer dungeons, have few opportunities to save one’s game. In that sense, the game is a total hardcore, traditional JRPG. It is not easily digested in small play sessions, so playing Grandia is committing a huge slice of one’s discretionary time budget.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yet, perhaps paradoxically, playing Grandia has a way of making one feel young again. Grandia is grand in the same way we ourselves felt grand as youngsters — that, armed with a stick we’ve just picked up and nothing more than our imagination, our wits, and our indomitable spirit, we could go forth boldly and change the world. That’s the beauty of a main character like Justin — he is not yet jaded; he has not yet borne the burden of grown-up problems on his shoulders. In many ways, we were all Justin (or Sue!) at one point, and the game shines a light on that part of us that is now long behind (most of) us. Perhaps the most memorable aspect of Grandia is that it allows us, for a moment all too brief, to once again be that young boy or girl full of optimism and energy, and in today’s complex and stressful world, that feels simply wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Three Optional Dungeons&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia is generally a well-balanced affair, with experience accumulating at the right rate for players to progress in the game. That said, the world of Grandia plays host to three completely optional dungeons meant solely for increasing character abilities and experience — and goes so far as to explicitly point out that these areas are not part of the game’s story and are entirely optional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first such dungeon can be found just west of the first section of the Zil Desert. It’s a large, very dark brown multi-leveled maze with the only save point being at the entrance. The enemies are tougher than one would expect at this point in the game, but nothing is impossible for Justin et al. The key here is to find the four Soldier’s Souls, which grants access to the treasures of the dungeon, at the very end, past the boss. The boss is a remix of a previous boss from Feena’s failed wedding to Pakon and packs quite a punch. The main prize here is the excellent Godspeed Knife, which adds a huge ACT boost, to massively speed up the user’s IP gauge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second optional dungeon is also found to the west but is accessible from the second part of the Zil Desert. This dungeon is very small but has perhaps the most charm. Justin and company are greeted by a mysterious Lady at the castle entrance, begging for help but also warning of a curse on the castle. Once inside, there are several rooms to visit and loot to collect. Really simplistic and set to lure the player to lower their guard, just in time to battle the formidable Lord’s Ghost boss. This guy’s TOUGH, with strong multi-character attacks and cancelling moves. Take him down to claim the awesome Lightning Sword, which gives a 50 ATK boost and, as an elemental sword, has the Zap! spell built in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final optional dungeon is the mother of all dungeons in Grandia. Found tucked away in the Savanna Wilderness and accessible via a secret passage, the Tower of Temptation consists of an outside area and 12 (!) floors of punishing combat. Of course, the only save point is at the very start of the outside area, though Justin can activate a couple of shortcuts through the tower as he makes progress, so that backtracking to heal and save is a bit easier. Interestingly, the starting area is surrounded by six Zero Weapons – one of each kind of weapons that grants a 0 ATK value — ideal for training weapons on weaker enemies, as these will do nearly no damage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia Grinder Mini-Alert: many enemies in the Tower drop stat-increasing items, making this an ideal place to pull it all out and go for that growth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each floor of the Tower features maze sections, hidden doors, powerful enemies, and of course, switches to hit. Simply by making one’s way through the tower will increase the party’s levels, as there is so much battling to do. It is not uncommon to spend hours in the Tower, so it’s a welcome fact that the Tower is entirely optional. The final three floors are all boss — yes, there are three bosses to fight in a row. No saving, no healing. The final of the three bosses is tough as nails, but the reward is well worth it — NINE amazing items to pick up, including two items from the Grinder’s Gear™ premium collection: the Astral Miracle and the Ethereal Miracle, both accessories that double weapon or magic experience gained. VERY useful, but they better be, considering the pain just endured to complete the Tower of Temptation!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Universe is Grand…ia&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia went on to sell bucket-loads in Japan, especially during release week. It received a Digital Museum DLC-style disc, got a port on the mass-market PlayStation including a PS Greatest Hits re-release, and finally, a PlayStation English localization in 1999. The series continued in 2000 with the excellent Grandia 2 on Dreamcast, which itself was later poorly ported to Sony’s killer of dreams, the PlayStation 2. That system would also see the less-well received Grandia 3, which would spell the end of the main series’ run. The series also saw several spin-off games such as Grandia Xtreme and Grandia Online. Additionally, the first Grandia was recently remade for modern consoles with the release of the Grandia HD Collection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;*Note: you cannot inspect monsters’ genders in battle. That was just a joke. Also there is no Grinder’s Gear in Grandia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;I’m Not Crying, You’re Crying!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A bit of a personal story… The above screenshot is my favorite scene in all of Grandia. See, the game does a brilliant job of bringing us back to the days of youthful adventures where nothing at all was impossible, and despite whatever danger beset us, we knew deep down that in the end, we would be all right. But in the most subtle of ways, Grandia also covers personal growth and the passage of time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At some point, deep into the adventure, 8-year-old Sue gets tired. At first, she temporarily leaves the party whilst recuperating at a local sick house, with everyone hoping (and the player confidently knowing) that she will get better. But… she doesn’t. She puts on a brave face and re-joins the party, going on one final quest. As the gamer, I kept looking for the herb or special item that I could find to cure her, but no such moment ever came. There never was any single wound or ailment that Sue suffered, it’s just that one day, she simply… got tired, and ultimately, had to leave the party. She was a trooper through the entire adventure; completely indispensable she was, but there was a sunset to her time on the grand adventure, and she ended up leaving far too soon for my liking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In real life, this sometimes happens, too. People in our orbit — strong, vibrant people, whom we believe will be with us forever — sometimes, unexpectedly, undeservedly… get tired, and have to quit the great adventure. Sometimes they are even younger than us, or in better health than us, or benefitting from any number of other factors that make their leaving seem senseless and cruelly unfair. It’s a reminder of the finite nature of life, and that sometimes we are living oh so naively and innocently through what we will later call the best times of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes, we get a chance to say our goodbyes before they depart us, and this is something Justin and Feena were able to share with Sue. With tears in her eyes, even as she bade farewell, she wished for Justin to follow his dreams and complete his long quest to find Angelou. It’s this that ties all of these sentiments together, for me. We all get older. We all leave our childhood behind us and begin to lead our adult lives in earnest. Our carefree days of questing and playing our days away, confident that in the end, everything will be all right, are replaced by planning, worrying, pressure, stress, failure, and other harsh realities of life. Here, Sue reminds us of the importance of not forgetting our dreams. We may not have the time or the energy that we did then, but whatever the obstacles, we must always go boldly in the direction of our dreams, hand-in-hand with those who love us, for we, too, will one day exit the adventure. In our final moments, what sweeter satisfaction could there be than to warmly smile at those who walked with us, and to look back on our journey with pride.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46203138</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 09:48:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ZX Spectrum Next on the Internet: Xberry Pi ESP01 and Pi Zero Upgrades</title><link>https://retrogamecoders.com/zx-spectrum-next-on-the-internet-xberry-pi-esp01-and-pi-zero-upgrades/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e1ce3412480c97fa"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m enjoying my Xberry Pi ZX Spectrum Next, but I have to say the ‘simple’ upgrade of getting it onto Wifi via the cheap and cheerful ESP 8266 was not fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While I had every intention of setting up my Speccy keyboard on the board’s matrix connector, I need to wait for a socket of the correct pitch. It turns out the Xberry Pi needs 0.2mm spacing and I have none in my parts box. Instead I figured do the other main upgrades, namely add a Pi Zero “accelerator” and the Wifi upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ZX Next Pi Zero Accelerator Upgrade&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fully expecting the Pi Zero to be the thing that caused me trouble, I was shocked that not only my soldering had gone perfectly but also the flashing of the SD card.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So many community members had advised to use a highly specific Pi Zero, I thought my spare board would be wrong. But it worked first time!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My pin header made the soldering trickier than usual, maybe it soaked a lot of heat? Just remember the header needs to go on the ‘wrong’ side and take your time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Pi Zero upgrade is hardly used currently but the ZX Next team keep hinting at future utility, and at least one game is in development that uses it as a kind of math coprocessor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So after running a TZX file and some SID tunes, I moved on to the ESP figuring I would have everything done quick as a flash. Pardon the pun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Adding Wifi to the Next&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Next can come with Wifi already installed apparently, and some Xberry bundles come with one as standard, but the chosen module is an ESP 01 / 8266 which is something I have on hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s precious little documentation for this kind of thing out there, but I did find YouTube videos that made everything look very straightforward. That should have been the first red flag!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;None of them showed installing the correct ESP firmware, what baud rate the Next expects, or even attaching the ESP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I picked out a board I was confident was working fine, attached it, successfully ran the ESP Updater.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After it confirmed the update, I tried to connect to wifi using the built-in Next menu item …. and failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact the ESP Updater did its thing suggests also the board was fine therefore I tried and failed all the many ways to get the “driver” to install.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I quickly started to hate this “Installing Driver…” message. There is no indication if anything is happening when it gets stuck there for ages, but other times it quickly quits back to the menu, again with no feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert: Even with everything now ‘working’, it often takes a lot more attempts than you would expect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To save anyone else the bother I went through, and potentially Future Chris, the key was to NOT update the ESP 01 firmware. Just use whatever your board came with by default. My working firmware is not even listed on the ESP Updater repo …&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I rummaged around and found another ESP board that had never had its firmware flashed. Using a breadboard I confirmed it was working and responding to AT commands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;CircuitPython Code to Communicate with ESP01 via UART&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
import board,binascii
import adafruit_pio_uart
# Define the UART pins (example using GP16 for TX and GP17 for RX)
# The actual pins depend on your specific wiring/board configuration.
UART_TX = board.GP16
UART_RX = board.GP17
# Initialize the UART connection
# The baudrate for the ESP01 is typically 115200
uart = adafruit_pio_uart.UART(UART_TX, UART_RX, baudrate=115200)

def send(s):
    uart.write(s+'\r\n')
    print(uart.read(255).decode())
send('AT+RST')
send('AT')
send('AT+GMR')
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This code allows you to hook the ESP01 up to pins 16 and 17 for UART, and 3.3v and GND.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Wifi on the ZX Spectrum Next … Finally!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again it didn’t work on the ZX Next right away, but I persisted and finally signs of life!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hope this helps someone else out there! I found it incredibly frustrating but now I am back to having fun with my ZX Next experience rather than regretting my choices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seems life might have been easier if a Pi Zero W was used instead of a Pi and an ESP8266, or even an ESP32, but perhaps there is a good reason they went with the little old ESP01.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46203499</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 10:52:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: AlgoDrill – Interactive drills to stop forgetting LeetCode patterns</title><link>https://algodrill.io</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46203581</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 11:09:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Brent's Encapsulated C Programming Rules (2020)</title><link>https://retroscience.net/brents-c-programming-rules.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a6789b19a8451298"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Brent's Encapsulated C Programming Rules&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below are some rules that I have developed over a long period of time writing fully encapsulated C programs. C is my favorite language and I love the freedom and exploration it allows me. I also love that it is so close to Assembly and I love writing assembly for much of the same reasons!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE: You may see references to ‘perfect encapsulation’ throughout. I offer both a ‘performance’ and a ‘pure encapsulation’ approach to C here (first two headers). So feel free to interpret the rest of the rules based on the approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JMP&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pure encapsulation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No encapsulation performance&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Memory ownership&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Avoid void*&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t over-complicate strings&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t over-complicate stdlib&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use utf8 strings&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t use char for memory array, use uint8_t&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use standard bool&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t use static or global variables&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Prefer inline over macro&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Test your functions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Write functions to do one thing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t write systems, write modular pieces (think UNIX)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Warnings are errors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If there is a standard, use it&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use float epsilon for 0 checking&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Zero set your structs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Big types first&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;More to come&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pure encapsulation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the great things about C is that it allows for “pure encapsulation”. What this means is that you can explain all the intent of your code through the header file and the developer who uses your lib/code never has to look at the actual implementations of the code. Now to take this a step further, well all know that C supports the &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt; keyword to group data, and we can also make the members of a struct hidden completely from the developer using the library. For example, we could declare the following header and C files:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;vec3.h&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#ifndef VEC3_H
#define VEC3_H

struct Vec3;

#endif
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;vec3.c&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include "vec3.h"

struct Vec3 {
	float x;
	float y;
	float z;
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you can see in the above code sample, if you were just to have the header file, you would not know that this vector is implemented using 3 &lt;code&gt;floats&lt;/code&gt;. This is very important for pure encapsulation. With this, you can completely control the behavior of the struct and it’s contents using readable functions and not worry about the developer using the code directly mutating the members of your &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt;. Now that you’ve created pure encapsulation, you are able to feel safe knowing that developers can’t new up the struct or abuse it’s contents from anywhere other than through the code you’ve written in your &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;No encapsulation performance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the flaws with pure encapsulation is that you can see a drop in performance. Having a bunch of functions to get inner members of a structure also blocks the compiler from optimizing it’s best. Member hiding is not usually because we don’t trust the end developer with the secrets of our structures, but is often so they don’t make mistakes by changing things they shouldn’t. Also member hiding helps so that we can easily update our code without changing the interface that developers rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That being said, if we are dealing with performance critical code, or just want extra optimization by our compiler (and/or to write less code); we can expose the members of our structure. However, let’s be smart about exposing these members so that developers don’t accidentally make mistakes with their new found power.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;, our best friend in this scenario. We can not only mark our members as &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; before their type, but also after their type. The general rule of thumb to remember is, if it is a pointer, the &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; goes after the type, otherwise put it before the type. In the simple example below, you can see how pointers have the &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; after, and the rest have &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; before their type declaration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct Employer {
	char* const name;
	const int years;
};

struct Employee {
	struct Employer* const employer;
	char* const name;
	const int age;
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this way we are able to expose the fields of the struct to the rest of the code for compiler optimizations, ease of access, etc; while also being able to prevent developers from directly assigning/changing the values of those fields. The obvious downside to this is that you will need to either create a macro, or manually cast assign the fields to change them in the implementation C file. I would recommend, if you are using C17, to use &lt;code&gt;_Generic&lt;/code&gt; and macros so you can create a single &lt;code&gt;#define OVERRIDE(field)&lt;/code&gt; type of macro and have the compiler throw if it finds an un-expected type. Of course, if you don’t want to use a macro, you can also create separate &lt;code&gt;inline&lt;/code&gt; functions to do the same (just might be harder to manage). Below is an example of how we can tell the compiler we want to explicitly change the value in the implementation c file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// employee.c file

void employee_set_age(struct Employee* employee, int newAge) {
	// Cast away the const and set it's value, the compiler should optimize this for you
	*(int*)&amp;amp;employee-&amp;gt;age = newAge;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Memory ownership&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With perfect encapsulation you are most of the way towards having good memory ownership. If you purely encapsulate your structs the only way for a developer to create a new instance of the struct would be through functions you create yourself. From this point you can create the &lt;code&gt;new&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;free&lt;/code&gt; functions to manage the memory of your struct. Below is an example building upon the previous code sample.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;vec3.h&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#ifndef VEC3_H
#define VEC3_H

struct Vec3;

struct Vec3* Vec3_new();
void Vec3_free(struct Vec3* vector);
void Vec3_print(struct Vec3* vector);

#endif
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;vec3.c&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include "vec3.h"
#include &amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt;

struct Vec3 { /* ... */ };

struct Vec3* Vec3_new()
{
	struct Vec3* v = malloc(sizeof(struct Vec3));
	v-&amp;gt;x = 0.0F;
	v-&amp;gt;y = 0.0F;
	v-&amp;gt;z = 0.0F;
	return v;
}

void Vec3_free(struct Vec3* vector)
{
	free(vector);
}

void Vec3_print(struct Vec3* vector)
{
	printf("&amp;lt;%f, %f, %f&amp;gt;", vector-&amp;gt;x, vector-&amp;gt;y, vector-&amp;gt;z);
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Above you can see that we encapsulate the creation, usage, and freeing of our &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt;. You would think, well with this, what else do we need to know about memory management? Well there is one more thing, more of a rule that you must follow more than anything else. The thing that declares the memory is the thing that should free the memory. We see this in action above, the &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; file that creates the memory in turn has a function for freeing the memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now let’s look at another example using a &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; to represent a string function. Here we have a function that takes a string and clones it (wrong way):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;char* strclone(const char* str)
{
	size_t len = strlen(s) + 1;
	char* clone = malloc(len);
	memcpy(clone, str, len);
	return clone;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now what is wrong with the memory management on this code? Answer, we are using &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt; to create memory and then return the string. Let’s take a look at the developer using this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;char* str = "Hello Brent!\0";
char* cpy = strclone(str);
printf(cpy);
free(cpy);	// Allowed?
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How is the developer suppose to know that they are to free the &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt;? For all they know the &lt;code&gt;strclone&lt;/code&gt; uses some-sort of pooling functionality to re-use a pool of memory, we can’t free that otherwise you risk seg-faulting. What is a better version of this?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;void strclone(const char* str, char** outCpy)
{
	size_t len = strlen(s) + 1;
	*outCpy = malloc(len);
	memcpy(outCpy, str, len);
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now with this version we make it explicit that the developer should manage their own object that they pass in. We use the hint name out as a prefix to the argument name to let them know memory will be allocated for this input variable. What does this look like to the developer?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;char* str = "Hello Brent!\0";
char* cpy;
strclone(str, &amp;amp;cpy);
printf(cpy);
free(cpy);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at this version, the developer knows they are in charge of freeing the &lt;code&gt;cpy&lt;/code&gt;, this is because they declare the variable in the first place, rather than being assigned from a function. If the developer follows our rule (The thing that declares the memory is the thing that should free the memory), they declared the variable/pointer so they should be the ones freeing it. Now I know you can argue all sorts of alternative setups for the return value, but the fact of the matter is that passing in a pointer to a pointer is much more clear of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Avoid void*&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One stigma people have against C is the use of &lt;code&gt;void*&lt;/code&gt;, some think it is necessary, some use it to solve problems quickly through the path of least resistance, I say that there are very few cases when &lt;code&gt;void*&lt;/code&gt; is acceptable and most of the time your current problem isn’t it. Like &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;void*&lt;/code&gt; is a lazy solution to a problem and causes all kinds of un-necessary runtime checking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In most cases you should create a &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt; that explicitly defines what type is accepted or stored. The biggest advantage of this approach is that you put the compiler to work for you. There are all sorts of compile-time checks that will prevent you from doing something you shouldn’t do. Also your IDE will be much more helpful when trying to navigate code as the IDE, nor the compiler, have any idea where a void* comes from or what it points to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t over-complicate strings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I want to live in the 2020 era of programming, that means I probably will wind up using more than one library to solve a problem. My new problem is that people think it is cute to typedef &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; to some other name and only accept that name in their code. In the era of UTF8, that is completely un-necessary and makes me have to do a lot of senseless casting. If you want to encapsulate that you are using a string (so I don’t know it) then cool, do that, but &lt;code&gt;typedef unsigned char* string&lt;/code&gt; is not it. Please stick to the good ol’ &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; for strings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t over-complicate stdlib&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TBD&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Use utf8 strings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Talking about strings, I’d like to point out that UTF-8 is fully compatible with ASCII, this means we don’t need special functions for special characters or non English characters. All of our usual suspects of functions work on UTF-8 such as &lt;code&gt;fopen&lt;/code&gt;! There are some helpful other things we can use thanks to compilers such as placing &lt;code&gt;u8&lt;/code&gt; in front of an in-line string:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;char* utf8 = u8"Hello World!";
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So in closing on the UTF-8 topic, please stop using &lt;code&gt;wchar_t&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;char16_t&lt;/code&gt;, and all those other variants (except when you are forced to, due to 3rd party libraries). With that, I’ll leave you with this helper function to get you started:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;size_t utf8len(const char* const str) {
    size_t len = 0;
    for (size_t i = 0; *str != 0; ++len) {
        int v0 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x80) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 7;
        int v1 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x40) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 6;
        int v2 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x20) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 5;
        int v3 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x10) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 4;
        str += 1 + v0 * v1 + v0 * v1 * v2 + v0 * v1 * v2 * v3;
    }
    return len;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE 1: A simplified version of this was proposed by Max Brauer on Stack Overflow to be:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;size_t utf8len(const char* str) {
    size_t len = 0;
    for (size_t i = 0; *str != 0; ++len) {
        int v01 = ((*str &amp;amp; 0x80) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 7) &amp;amp; ((*str &amp;amp; 0x40) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 6);
        int v2 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x20) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 5;
        int v3 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x10) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 4;
        str += 1 + ((v01 &amp;lt;&amp;lt; v2) | (v01 &amp;amp; v3));
    }
    return len;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE 2: This does not validate the utf8 string. I am not fond of making the length function also validate the string, for that we should create a separate method for validation. Using this table I found on Wikipedia we can construct a validation function (also this table was used for the length function).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;bool utf8valid(const char* const str) {
    if (str == NULL)
        return false;
    const char* c = str;
    bool valid = true;
    for (size_t i = 0; c[0] != 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; valid;) {
        valid = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x80) == 0
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xE0) == 0xC0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80)
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xF0) == 0xE0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[2] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80)
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xF8) == 0xF0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[2] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[3] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80);
        int v0 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x80) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 7;
        int v1 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x40) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 6;
        int v2 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x20) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 5;
        int v3 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x10) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 4;
        i += 1 + v0 * v1 + v0 * v1 * v2 + v0 * v1 * v2 * v3;
        c = str + i;
    }
    return valid;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE 3: Based on the same simplification previously discussed, this would become:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;bool utf8valid(const char* const str) {
    if (str == NULL)
        return false;
    const char* c = str;
    bool valid = true;
    for (size_t i = 0; c[0] != 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; valid;) {
        valid = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x80) == 0
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xE0) == 0xC0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80)
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xF0) == 0xE0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[2] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80)
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xF8) == 0xF0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[2] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[3] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80);
        int v01 = ((*str &amp;amp; 0x80) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 7) &amp;amp; ((*str &amp;amp; 0x40) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 6);
        int v2 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x20) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 5;
        int v3 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x10) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 4;
        i += 1 + ((v01 &amp;lt;&amp;lt; v2) | (v01 &amp;amp; v3));
        c = str + i;
    }
    return valid;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE 4: Something that developers trip on is the file encoding for their source file. Be sure you are using UTF-8 encoding for your source file when typing UTF-8 strings directly into your source code. If you use the wrong encoding, the compiler may compile the inline string with the incorrect encoding, even with the &lt;code&gt;u8&lt;/code&gt; prefix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t use char for memory array, use uint8_t&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In making code readable, you should only use &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;unsigned char*&lt;/code&gt; for strings (character arrays). If you want a block of bytes/memory pointer, then you should use &lt;code&gt;uint8_t*&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;uint8_t&lt;/code&gt; is part of &lt;code&gt;stdint.h&lt;/code&gt;. This makes the code much more readable where memory is represented as an unsighned 8-bit array of numbers (byte array). Now you can trust when you see a &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; that it is referring to a UTF-8 (or ASCII) character array (text).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Use standard bool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one is easy:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include &amp;lt;stdbool.h&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t make defines for &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;False&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;FALSE&lt;/code&gt; and it’s true counterpart, please just use the standard library.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t use static or global variables&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So &lt;code&gt;static&lt;/code&gt; functions are fine, they are great for breaking up functions to be readable. However, &lt;code&gt;static&lt;/code&gt; variables are bad and almost always not needed. Remember that we are living in a world where our CPUs are not getting faster, they are just coming in larger quantities. Always think about threadability and controlling mutation. Even with a variable that is static to a &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; file and not global, you never know if someone is using threads to call your functions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Prefer inline over macro&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Functions that are &lt;code&gt;inline&lt;/code&gt; are much more readable, work better with your IDE code searching, and are much more readable when you get errors/warnings from the compiler. Some macros are great, don’t ban them altogether, but do consider if you can do what you need through an inline function first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Test your functions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;C is beautiful in the fact that you don’t need unit test frameworks to fully test your code. It’s lack of objects and hidden state make it even better for testing. If you create a function, make a test for it and give it your known test case arguments. Did I mention that I love not having to have a big complicated mocking library to fully test my code? If your function takes in a complicated struct for some reason, feel free to &lt;code&gt;define&lt;/code&gt; out/in a test function for creating the struct you expect to be testing (do NOT comprimise perfect encapsulation for the sake of testing).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Write functions to do one thing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, this isn’t a C only thing, but make sure your functions are not creating large call stacks. Feel free to use &lt;code&gt;static&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;static inline&lt;/code&gt; local functions to break up the readability of large functions if you just can’t seem to make functions do a single thing (for performance for example).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t write systems, write modular pieces (think UNIX)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t write big complicated systems to cover many problems, even if things are losely related in many ways. It is better to break up your code into useful functional pieces and cleverly put them together to have complex behavior. The beauty of Unix is that you can get many things done through many small programs pieced together. In the same way, you should develop useful functions that can be pieced together through data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Warnings are errors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one is a bit short. The idea is simple, warnings are errors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make sure ALL warnings are enabled (&lt;code&gt;/Wall&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make sure that you turn on warnings as errors&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: If you copied some source code from the internet that you need and it is producing warnings, turn it into a lib and use the lib, do not comprimise your code for other people’s un-checked code. You’d be surprised how many popular libraries fail warnings as errors test (often they develop assuming 32-bit code).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;If there is a standard, use it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was touched on before with &lt;code&gt;stdbool.h&lt;/code&gt;, but if there is a standard function or type, use it. Use things like &lt;code&gt;int32_t&lt;/code&gt; over just &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt; hoping that &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt; will be 32-bit. If there is a standard function for doing something, don’t re-invent the wheel. Wrapping standard functions such as &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;free&lt;/code&gt; I would consider a necessary evil if you are creating tools to detect memory leaks and the like though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Use float epsilon for 0 checking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First of all, don’t check a floating point value against &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;0.0F&lt;/code&gt;. Instead check it against Epsilon like in the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include &amp;lt;math.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;float.h&amp;gt;

int main(void)
{
	float x = 1.0F;
	x -= 1.0F;
	if (fabsf(x) &amp;lt;= FLT_EPSILON)
	{
		// ... The value is basically 0, do some stuff
	}
	return 0;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alternatively you can choose a fractionally small number like &lt;code&gt;0.0001F&lt;/code&gt; to check against if that is your cup of tea as well. The reason is floating point precision errors (which you probably know or have heard of by now). I enjoy &lt;code&gt;FLT_EPSILON&lt;/code&gt; because it is part of the &lt;code&gt;float.h&lt;/code&gt; lib and a standard for everyone to use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Zero Set Your Structs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One thing that would get me when developing in C is pointers inside of objects not being set to &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt;. Now I know I speak about hating that the idea of &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt; exists, but when working with other people’s code it is impossible for you not to run into a situation where you need to set a pointer to &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt;, pass a &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt; or check a pointer against &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt;. So do yourself a favor and always use &lt;code&gt;calloc&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;memset(&amp;amp;thing, 0, sizeof(thing))&lt;/code&gt; if it isn’t a pointer or new memory). Of course this doesn’t ban the use of &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt;, in fact you should continue to use it on buffers, but as programmers, we have a problem with not touching code that works and you think it is fine to just add in that extra field, but if it is a pointer and you don’t initialize it to &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt; where needed, you’re in for a world of hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Big types first&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you create a structure, put the biggest types at the top of your struct and the smallest types at the bottom. Platforms like the x86 will magically help you with this (at a cost), but other platforms (like ARM) will generate SEGFALT if you don’t properly do this. This is because of padding in a struct. If you put a &lt;code&gt;bool&lt;/code&gt; as the first field and a &lt;code&gt;int32_t&lt;/code&gt; as the second field in a struct, like the one below, you will have a problem where you pack 1 byte, then 4 bytes into the struct, effectively having a 5 byte struct. The problem here is that the CPU is optimized to read along memory boundaries. When you &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt;, you won’t get an odd memory address for example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct Bad {
	bool first;
	int32_t second;
};

struct Good {
	int32_t first;
	bool second;
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More to come&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are inevitably more things I’ve forgotten about, but I’ve written this all in one sitting so this is good enough for now until I can update!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46203611</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 11:16:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Oliver Sacks Put Himself into His Case Studies. What Was the Cost?</title><link>https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/12/15/oliver-sacks-put-himself-into-his-case-studies-what-was-the-cost</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b6d197fda2b78777"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Oliver Sacks arrived in New York City, in September, 1965, he wore a butter-colored suit that reminded him of the sun. He had just spent a romantic week in Europe travelling with a man named Jenö Vincze, and he found himself walking too fast, fizzing with happiness. “My blood is champagne,” he wrote. He kept a letter Vincze had written him in his pocket all day, feeling as if its pages were glowing. Sacks had moved to New York to work as a fellow in neuropathology at the Albert Einstein College of Medicine, in the Bronx, and a colleague observed that he was “walking on air.” Every morning, he carefully polished his shoes and shaved. He adored his bosses. “I smile like a lighthouse in all directions,” he wrote Vincze.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks was thirty-two, and he told Vincze that this was his first romantic relationship that was both physical and reciprocal. He felt he was part of a “two man universe,” seeing the world for the first time—“seeing it clear, and seeing it whole.” He wandered along the shipping piers on the Hudson River, where gay men cruised, with a notebook that he treated as a diary and as an endless letter to Vincze. “To watch life with the eyes of a homosexual is the greatest thing in the world,” Vincze had once told Sacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks’s mother, a surgeon in London, had suspected that her son was gay when he was a teen-ager. She declared that homosexuality was an “abomination,” using the phrase “filth of the bowel” and telling him that she wished he’d never been born. They didn’t speak of the subject again. Sacks had moved to America—first to California and then, after five years, to New York—because, he wrote in his journal, “I wanted a sexual and moral freedom I felt I could never have in England.” That fall, during Yom Kippur, he decided that, rather than going to synagogue to confess “to the total range of human sin,” a ritual he’d grown up with, he’d spend the night at a bar, enjoying a couple of beers. “What I suppose I am saying, Jenö, is that I now feel differently about myself, and therefore about homosexuality as a whole,” he wrote. “I am through with cringing, and apologies, and pious wishes that I might have been ‘normal.’ ” (The Oliver Sacks Foundation shared with me his correspondence and other records, as well as four decades’ worth of journals—many of which had not been read since he wrote them.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In early October, Sacks sent two letters to Vincze, but a week passed without a reply. Sacks asked his colleagues to search their mailboxes, in case the letter had been put in the wrong slot. Within a few days, however, he had given up on innocent explanations. He began dressing sloppily. He stopped coming to work on time. He had sex with a series of men who disgusted him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After two weeks, Vincze, who was living in Berlin, sent a letter apologizing for his delayed reply and reiterating his love. He explained that he was so preoccupied by thoughts of Sacks that he felt as if he were living in a “Klaudur,” a German word that Vincze defined as a “spiritual cell.” He seems to have misspelled Klausur, which refers to an enclosed area in a monastery, but Sacks kept using the misspelled word, becoming obsessed with it. “It ramifies in horrible associations,” he wrote Vincze. “The closing of a door. Klaudur, claustrophobia, the sense of being shut in.” Sacks had long felt as if he were living in a cell, incapable of human contact, and this word appeared to be all he needed to confirm that the condition was terminal. The meaning of the word began morphing from “spiritual cell” to “psychotic cage.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The intimacy Sacks had rejoiced in now seemed phony, a “folie à deux”—a two-person delusion. His doubts intensified for a month, then he cut off the relationship. “I must tear you out of my system, because I dare not be involved,” he told Vincze, explaining that he barely remembered how he looked, or the sound of his voice. “I hope I will not be taken in like this again, and that—conversely—I will have the strength and clarity of mind to perceive any future such relationships as morbid at their inception, and to abort the folly of their further growth.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two months later, Sacks felt himself “slipping down the greased path of withdrawal, discontent, inability to make friends, inability to have sex, etc. etc. towards suicide in a New York apartment at the age of 32.” He took enormous amounts of amphetamines, to the point of hallucinating. A family friend, a psychiatrist who worked with Anna Freud, urged him to find a psychoanalyst. She wrote him that his homosexuality was “a very ‘secondary phenomenon’ ”: he was attracted to men as “a substitute for veering uncertainties of what/whom you could love other than as ‘idealizations’ of yourself.” A few weeks later, he started therapy with Leonard Shengold, a young psychiatrist who was deeply immersed in Manhattan’s psychoanalytic culture. “I think he is very good, and he has at least a very considerable local reputation,” Sacks wrote his parents, who helped to pay for the sessions, three times a week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks had elevated yet hazy ambitions at the time: he wanted to be a novelist, but he also wanted to become the “Galileo of the inward,” he told a mentor, and to write the neurological equivalent of Sigmund Freud’s “Interpretation of Dreams.” He worked in wards with chronically ill and elderly patients who had been warehoused and neglected, and his prospects within academic medicine looked dim. “Have you published anything lately?” his father wrote him, in 1968. “Or have you found yourself temperamentally incapacitated from doing so?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Sacks began therapy, “my initial and ultimate complaint was of fixity—a feeling of not-going,” he wrote in his journal. He regarded Shengold as “a sort of analytic machine.” But gradually Sacks came to feel that “I love him, and need him; that I need him—and love him.” He had planned to stay in New York City only for a few years, but he kept delaying his return to England so that he could reach “a terminable point in my analysis.” Shengold, who would eventually publish ten books about psychoanalysis, wrote that therapy requires a “long period of working through”—a term he defined as the “need to repeat emotional conflicts over and over in life” until the patient has the “freedom to own what is there to be felt.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks saw Shengold for half a century. In that time, Sacks became one of the world’s most prominent neurologists and a kind of founding father of medical humanities—a discipline that coalesced in the seventies, linking healing with storytelling. But the freedom that Shengold’s analysis promised was elusive. After Vincze, Sacks did not have another relationship for forty-four years. He seemed to be doing the “working through” at a remove—again and again, his psychic conflicts were displaced onto the lives of his patients. He gave them “some of my own powers, and some of my phantasies too,” he wrote in his journal. “I write out symbolic versions of myself.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During Sacks’s neurology internship, in San Francisco, his childhood friend Eric Korn warned him that the residents at his hospital could sense he was gay. “For God’s sake, exercise what seems to you immoderate caution,” Korn wrote, in 1961. “Compartmentalize your life. Cover your tracks. Don’t bring in the wrong sort of guests to the hospital, or sign your name and address to the wrong sort of register.” He encouraged Sacks to read “Homosexuality: Disease or Way of Life?,” a best-selling book by Edmund Bergler, who argued that homosexuality was an “illness as painful, as unpleasant and as disabling as any other serious affliction,” but one that psychoanalysis could cure. “The book is full of interest,” Korn wrote. “He claims a potential 100% ‘cures’ (a term he chooses to employ because he knows it teases) which is worth investigating perhaps.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Freud characterized homosexuality as a relatively normal variant of human behavior, but when psychoanalysis came to the United States, in the postwar years, homophobia took on new life. The historian Dagmar Herzog has described how, in the U.S., “reinventing psychoanalysis and reinventing homophobia went hand in hand.” Faced with men who persisted in their love for other men, American analysts commonly proposed celibacy as a stopgap solution. In the historian Martin Duberman’s memoir “Cures,” he writes that his psychoanalyst instructed him to “take the veil”—live celibately—so that he could be cured of his desire for men. Duberman agreed to these terms. The best he could get, he thought, was sublimation: instead of enjoying an “affective life,” he would make “some contribution to the general culture from which I was effectively barred.” Sacks, who was closeted until he was eighty, also followed this course.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shengold had portraits of Charles Dickens, William Shakespeare, and Sigmund Freud in his office, on the Upper East Side. Like Sacks, he came from a literary Jewish family. He seemed deeply attuned to Sacks’s creative life, which took the form of ecstatic surges of literary inspiration followed by months of sterility and depression. “Do your best to enjoy and to work—it is the power of your mind that is crucial,” Shengold wrote when Sacks was on a visit with his family in England. Sacks wrote in his journal that he’d dreamed he overheard Shengold telling someone, “Oliver is lacking in proper self-respect; he has never really appreciated himself, or appreciated others’ appreciation of him. And yet, in his way, he is not less gifted than Auden was.” Sacks woke up flushed with embarrassment and pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike many of his contemporaries, Shengold was not a doctrinaire thinker, but he was still susceptible to psychoanalytic fashions. Reflecting on how he might have viewed living openly as a gay man at that time, Shengold’s daughter, Nina, told me, “I don’t know that was a door that Dad necessarily had wide open.” In several books and papers, Shengold, a prolific reader of Western literature, tried to understand the process by which troubled people sublimate their conflicts into art. In his 1988 book, “Halo in the Sky: Observations on Anality and Defense,” Shengold wrote about the importance of transforming “anal-sadistic drives”—he used the anus as a metaphor for primitive, dangerous impulses—into “adaptive and creative ‘making.’ ” When Sacks read the book, he wrote in his journal that it “made me feel I was ‘lost in anality’ (whatever this means).”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before Vincze, Sacks had been in love with a man named Mel Erpelding, who once told him, Sacks wrote, that he “oozed sexuality, that it poured out through every pore, that I was alive and vibrant with sexuality (a positive-admiring way of putting things), but also that I was reeking and toxic with it.” (Erpelding, who ended up marrying a woman, never allowed his relationship with Sacks to become sexual.) In his early years of therapy, in the late sixties, Sacks resolved that he would give up both drugs and sex. It’s doubtful that Shengold encouraged his celibacy, but he may have accepted that sexual abstinence could be productive, at least for a time. Richard Isay, the first openly gay member of the American Psychoanalytic Association, said that, in the seventies, he’d “rationalized that maturity and mental health demanded the sublimation of sexual excitement in work.” Sacks told a friend, “Shengold is fond of quoting Flaubert’s words ‘the mind has its erections too.’ ”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Sacks, writing seemed almost physiological, like sweating—an involuntary response to stimuli. He routinely filled a whole journal in two days. “Should I then put down my pen, my interminable Journal (for this is but a fragment of the journal I have kept all my life),” he asked, “and ‘start living’ instead?” The answer was almost always no. Sometimes Sacks, who would eventually publish sixteen books, wrote continuously in his journal for six hours. Even when he was driving his car, he was still writing—he set up a tape recorder so that he could keep developing his thoughts, which were regularly interrupted by traffic or a wrong turn. Driving through Manhattan one day in 1975, he reflected on the fact that his closets, stuffed with pages of writing, resembled a “grave bursting open.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the late sixties, Sacks had become, he wrote, “almost a monk in my asceticism and devotion to work.” He estimated that he produced a million and a half words a year. When he woke up in the middle of the night with an erection, he would cool his penis by putting it in orange jello. He told Erpelding, “I partly accept myself as a celibate and a cripple, but partly—and this is . . . the wonder of sublimation—am able to transform my erotic feelings into other sorts of love—love for my patients, my work, art, thought.” He explained, “I keep my distance from people, am always courteous, never close. For me (as perhaps for you) there is almost no room, no moral room.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I have some hard ‘confessing’ to do—if not in public, at least to Shengold—and myself,” Sacks wrote in his journal, in 1985. By then, he had published four books—“Migraine,” “Awakenings,” “A Leg to Stand On,” and “The Man Who Mistook His Wife for a Hat”—establishing his reputation as “our modern master of the case study,” as the Times put it. He rejected what he called “pallid, abstract knowing,” and pushed medicine to engage more deeply with patients’ interiority and how it interacted with their diseases. Medical schools began creating programs in medical humanities and “narrative medicine,” and a new belief took hold: that an ill person has lost narrative coherence, and that doctors, if they attend to their patients’ private struggles, could help them reconstruct a new story of their lives. At Harvard Medical School, for a time, students were assigned to write a “book” about a patient. Stories of illness written by physicians (and by patients) began proliferating, to the point that the medical sociologist Arthur Frank noted, “ ‘Oliver Sacks’ now designates not only a specific physician author but also a . . . genre—a distinctively recognizable form of storytelling.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But, in his journal, Sacks wrote that “a sense of hideous criminality remains (psychologically) attached” to his work: he had given his patients “powers (starting with powers of speech) which they do not have.” Some details, he recognized, were “pure fabrications.” He tried to reassure himself that the exaggerations did not come from a shallow place, such as a desire for fame or attention. “The impulse is both ‘purer’—and deeper,” he wrote. “It is not merely or wholly a projection—nor (as I have sometimes, ingeniously-disingenuously, maintained) a mere ‘sensitization’ of what I know so well in myself. But (if you will) a sort of autobiography.” He called it “symbolic ‘exo-graphy.’ ”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks had “misstepped in this regard, many many times, in ‘Awakenings,’ ” he wrote in another journal entry, describing it as a “source of severe, long-lasting, self-recrimination.” In the book, published in 1973, he startled readers with the depth of his compassion for some eighty patients at Beth Abraham Hospital, in the Bronx, who had survived an epidemic of encephalitis lethargica, a mysterious, often fatal virus that appeared around the time of the First World War. The patients had been institutionalized for decades, in nearly catatonic states. At the time, the book was met with silence or skepticism by other neurologists—Sacks had presented his findings in a form that could not be readily replicated, or extrapolated from—but, to nonspecialists, it was a masterpiece of medical witnessing. The Guardian would name it the twelfth-best nonfiction book of all time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks spent up to fifteen hours a day with his patients, one of the largest groups of post-encephalitic survivors in the world. They were “mummified,” like “living statues,” he observed. A medicine called L-dopa, which elevates the brain’s dopamine levels, was just starting to be used for Parkinson’s disease, on an experimental basis, and Sacks reasoned that his patients, whose symptoms resembled those of Parkinson’s, could benefit from the drug. In 1969, within days of giving his patients the medication, they suddenly “woke up,” their old personalities intact. Other doctors had dismissed these patients as hopeless, but Sacks had sensed that they still had life in them—a recognition that he understood was possible because he, too, felt as if he were “buried alive.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In “Awakenings,” Sacks writes about his encounters with a man he calls Leonard L. “What’s it like being the way you are?” Sacks asks him the first time they meet. “Caged,” Leonard replies, by pointing to letters of the alphabet on a board. “Deprived. Like Rilke’s ‘Panther’ ”—a reference to a poem by Rainer Maria Rilke about a panther pacing repetitively in cramped circles “around a center / in which a mighty will stands paralyzed.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Sacks was struggling to write his first book, “Migraine,” he told a friend that he felt like “Rilke’s image of the caged panther, stupefied, dying, behind bars.” In a letter to Shengold, he repeated this image. When Sacks met Leonard, he jotted down elegant observations in his chart (“Quick and darting eye movements are at odds with his general petrified immobility”), but there is no mention of Leonard invoking the Rilke poem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the preface to “Awakenings,” Sacks acknowledges that he changed circumstantial details to protect his patients’ privacy but preserved “what is important and essential—the real and full presence of the patients themselves.” Sacks characterizes Leonard as a solitary figure even before his illness: he was “continually buried in books, and had few or no friends, and indulged in none of the sexual, social, or other activities common to boys of his age.” But, in an autobiography that Leonard wrote after taking L-dopa, he never mentions reading or writing or being alone in those years. In fact, he notes that he spent all his time with his two best friends—“We were inseparable,” he writes. He also recalls raping several people. “We placed our cousin over a chair, pulled down her pants and inserted our penises into the crack,” he writes on the third page, in the tone of an aging man reminiscing on better days. By page 10, he is describing how, when he babysat two girls, he made one of them strip and then “leaped on her. I tossed her on her belly and pulled out my penis and placed it between her buttocks and started to screw her.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In “Awakenings,” Sacks has cleansed his patient’s history of sexuality. He depicts him as a man of “most unusual intelligence, cultivation, and sophistication”—the “ ‘ideal’ patient.” L-dopa may have made Leonard remember his childhood in a heightened sexual register—his niece and nephew, who visited him at the hospital until his death, in 1981, told me that the drug had made him very sexual. But they said that he had been a normal child and adolescent, not a recluse who renounced human entanglement for a life of the mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks finished writing “Awakenings” rapidly in the weeks after burying his mother, who’d died suddenly, at the age of seventy-seven. He felt “a great open torrent—and release,” he wrote in his journal. “It seems to be surely significant that ‘Awakenings’ finally came forth from me like a cry after the death of my own mother.” He referred to the writing of the book as his “Great Awakening,” the moment he “came out.” He doesn’t mention another event of significance: his patients had awakened during the summer of the Stonewall riots, the beginning of the gay-rights movement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shengold once told Sacks that he had “never met anyone less affected by gay liberation.” (Shengold supported his own son when he came out as gay, in the eighties.) Sacks agreed with the characterization. “I remain resolutely locked in my cell despite the dancing at the prison gates,” he said, in 1984.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In “Awakenings,” his patients are at first overjoyed by their freedom; then their new vitality becomes unbearable. As they continue taking L-dopa, many of them are consumed by insatiable desires. “L-DOPA is wanton, egotistical power,” Leonard says in the book. He injures his penis twice and tries to suffocate himself with a pillow. Another patient is so aroused and euphoric that she tells Sacks, “My blood is champagne”—the phrase Sacks used to describe himself when he was in love with Vincze. Sacks begins tapering his patients’ L-dopa, and taking some of them off of it completely. The book becomes a kind of drama about dosage: an examination of how much aliveness is tolerable, and at what cost. Some side effects of L-dopa, like involuntary movements and overactivity, have been well documented, but it’s hard not to wonder if “Awakenings” exaggerates the psychological fallout—Leonard becomes so unmanageable that the hospital moves him into a “punishment cell”—as if Sacks is reassuring himself that free rein of the libido cannot be sustained without grim consequence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After “Awakenings,” Sacks intended his next book to be about his work with young people in a psychiatric ward at Bronx State Hospital who had been institutionalized since they were children. The environment reminded Sacks of a boarding school where he had been sent, between the ages of six and nine, during the Second World War. He was one of four hundred thousand children evacuated from London without their parents, and he felt abandoned. He was beaten by the headmaster and bullied by the other boys. The ward at Bronx State “exerted a sort of spell on me,” Sacks wrote in his journal, in 1974. “I lost my footing of proper sympathy and got sucked, so to speak, into an improper ‘perilous condition’ of identification to the patients.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shengold wrote several papers and books about a concept he called “soul murder”—a category of childhood trauma that induces “a hypnotic living-deadness, a state of existing ‘as if’ one were there.” Sacks planned to turn his work at Bronx State into a book about “ ‘SOUL MURDER’ and ‘SOUL SURVIVAL,’ ” he wrote. He was especially invested in two young men on the ward whom he thought he was curing. “The miracle-of-recovery started to occur in and through their relation to me (our relation and feelings to each other, of course),” he wrote in his journal. “We had to meet in a passionate subjectivity, a sort of collaboration or communication which transcended the Socratic relation of teacher-and-pupil.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a spontaneous creative burst lasting three weeks, Sacks wrote twenty-four essays about his work at Bronx State which he believed had the “beauty, the intensity, of Revelation . . . as if I was coming to know, once again, what I knew as a child, that sense of Dearness and Trust I had lost for so long.” But in the ward he sensed a “dreadful silent tension.” His colleagues didn’t understand the attention he was lavishing on his patients—he got a piano and a Ping-Pong table for them and took one patient to the botanical garden. Their suspicion, he wrote in his journal, “centred on the unbearability of my uncategorizability.” As a middle-aged man living alone—he had a huge beard and dressed eccentrically, sometimes wearing a black leather shirt—Sacks was particularly vulnerable to baseless innuendo. In April, 1974, he was fired. There had been rumors that he was molesting some of the boys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That night, Sacks tore up his essays and then burned them. “Spite! Hate! Hateful spite!” he wrote in his journal shortly after. “And now I am empty—empty handed, empty hearted, desolate.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The series of events was so distressing that even writing about it in his journal made Sacks feel that he was about to die. He knew that he should shrug off the false accusations as “vile idle gossip thrown by tiddlers and piddlers,” he wrote. But he couldn’t, because of “the parental accusation which I have borne—a Kafka-esque cross, guilt without crime, since my earliest days.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The historian of medicine Henri Ellenberger observed that psychiatry owes its development to two intertwined dynamics: the neuroses of its founders—in trying to master their own conflicts, they came to new insights and forms of therapy—and the prolonged, ambiguous relationships they had with their patients. The case studies of these relationships, Ellenberger wrote, tended to have a distinct arc: psychiatrists had to unravel their patients’ “pathogenic secret,” a hidden source of hopelessness, in order to heal them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks’s early case studies also tended to revolve around secrets, but wonderful ones. Through his care, his patients realized that they had hidden gifts—for music, painting, writing—that could restore to them a sense of wholeness. The critic Anatole Broyard, recounting his cancer treatment in the Times Magazine in 1990, wrote that he longed for a charismatic, passionate physician, skilled in “empathetic witnessing.” In short, he wrote, a doctor who “would resemble Oliver Sacks.” He added, “He would see the genius of my illness.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It speaks to the power of the fantasy of the magical healer that readers and publishers accepted Sacks’s stories as literal truth. In a letter to one of his three brothers, Marcus, Sacks enclosed a copy of “The Man Who Mistook His Wife for a Hat,” which was published in 1985, calling it a book of “fairy tales.” He explained that “these odd Narratives—half-report, half-imagined, half-science, half-fable, but with a fidelity of their own—are what I do, basically, to keep MY demons of boredom and loneliness and despair away.” He added that Marcus would likely call them “confabulations”—a phenomenon Sacks explores in a chapter about a patient who could retain memories for only a few seconds and must “make meaning, in a desperate way, continually inventing, throwing bridges of meaning over abysses,” but the “bridges, the patches, for all their brilliance . . . cannot do service for reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks was startled by the success of the book, which he had dedicated to Shengold, “my own mentor and physician.” It became an international best-seller, routinely assigned in medical schools. Sacks wrote in his journal,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He pondered the phrase “art is the lie that tells the truth,” often attributed to Picasso, but he seemed unconvinced. “I think I have to thrash this out with Shengold—it is killing me, soul-killing me,” he wrote. “My ‘cast of characters’ (for this is what they become) take on an almost Dickensian quality.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks once told a reporter that he hoped to be remembered as someone who “bore witness”—a term often used within medicine to describe the act of accompanying patients in their most vulnerable moments, rather than turning away. To bear witness is to recognize and respond to suffering that would otherwise go unseen. But perhaps bearing witness is incompatible with writing a story about it. In his journal, after a session with a patient with Tourette’s syndrome, Sacks describes the miracle of being “enabled to ‘feel’—that is, to imagine, with all the powers of my head and heart—how it felt to be another human being.” Empathy tends to be held up as a moral end point, as if it exists as its own little island of good work. And yet it is part of a longer transaction, and it is, fundamentally, a projection. A writer who imagines what it’s like to exist as another person must then translate that into his own idiom—a process that Sacks makes particularly literal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I’ll tell you what you are saying,” Sacks told a woman with an I.Q. of around 60 whose grandmother had just died. “You want to go down below and join your dead grandparents down in the Kingdom of Death.” In the conversation, which Sacks recorded, the patient becomes more expressive under the rare glow of her doctor’s sustained attention, and it’s clear that she is fond of him. But he is so excited about her words (“One feels that she is voicing universal symbols,” he says in a recording, “symbols which are infinite in meaning”) that he usurps her experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I know, in a way, you don’t feel like living,” Sacks tells her, in another recorded session. “Part of one feels dead inside, I know, I know that. . . . One feels that one wants to die, one wants to end it, and what’s the use of going on?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I don’t mean it in that way,” she responds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I know, but you do, partly,” Sacks tells her. “I know you have been lonely all your life.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The woman’s story is told, with details altered, in a chapter in “Hat” titled “Rebecca.” In the essay, Rebecca is transformed by grief for her grandmother. She reminds Sacks of Chekhov’s Nina, in “The Seagull,” who longs to be an actress. Though Nina’s life is painful and disappointing, at the end of the play her suffering gives her depth and strength. Rebecca, too, ends the story in full flower. “Rather suddenly, after her grandmother’s death,” Sacks writes, she becomes decisive, joining a theatre group and appearing to him as “a complete person, poised, fluent,” a “natural poet.” The case study is presented as an ode to the power of understanding a patient’s life as a narrative, not as a collection of symptoms. But in the transcripts of their conversations—at least the ones saved from the year that followed, as well as Sacks’s journals from that period—Rebecca never joins a theatre group or emerges from her despair. She complains that it’s “better that I shouldn’t have been born,” that she is “useless,” “good for nothing,” and Sacks vehemently tries to convince her that she’s not. Instead of bearing witness to her reality, he reshapes it so that she, too, awakens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the most prominent nonfiction writers of Sacks’s era (Joseph Mitchell, A. J. Liebling, Ryszard Kapuściński) also took liberties with the truth, believing that they had a higher purpose: to illuminate the human condition. Sacks was writing in that spirit, too, but in a discipline that depends on reproducible findings. The “most flagrant example” of his distortions, Sacks wrote in his journal, was in one of the last chapters of “Hat,” titled “The Twins,” about twenty-six-year-old twins with autism who had been institutionalized since they were seven. They spend their days reciting numbers, which they “savored, shared” while “closeted in their numerical communion.” Sacks lingers near them, jotting down the numbers, and eventually realizes that they are all prime. As a child, Sacks used to spend hours alone, trying to come up with a formula for prime numbers, but, he wrote, “I never found any Law or Pattern for them—and this gave me an intense feeling of Terror, Pleasure, and—Mystery.” Delighted by the twins’ pastime, Sacks comes to the ward with a book of prime numbers which he’d loved as a child. After offering his own prime number, “they drew apart slightly, making room for me, a new number playmate, a third in their world.” Having apparently uncovered the impossible algorithm that Sacks had once wished for, the twins continue sharing primes until they’re exchanging ones with twenty digits. The scene reads like a kind of dream: he has discovered that human intimacy has a decipherable structure, and identified a hidden pattern that will allow him to finally join in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before Sacks met them, the twins had been extensively studied because of their capacity to determine the day of the week on which any date in the calendar fell. In the sixties, two papers in the American Journal of Psychiatry provided detailed accounts of the extent of their abilities. Neither paper mentioned a gift for prime numbers or math. When Sacks wrote Alexander Luria, a Russian neuropsychologist, about his work with the twins, in 1973, he also did not mention any special mathematical skills. In 2007, a psychologist with a background in learning theory published a short article in the Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders, challenging Sacks’s assertion that these twins could spontaneously generate large prime numbers. Because this is not something that humans can reliably do, Sacks’s finding had been widely cited, and was theoretically “important for not only psychologists but also for all scientists and mathematicians,” the psychologist wrote. (The psychologist had contacted Sacks to ask for the title of his childhood book of prime numbers, because he couldn’t find a book of that description, but Sacks said that it had been lost.) Without pointing to new evidence, another scientist wrote in Sacks’s defense, describing his case study as “the most compelling account of savant numerosity skills” and arguing, “This is an example of science at the frontier, requiring daring to advance new interpretations of partial data.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the publication of “Hat,” when Sacks was fifty-two years old, he wrote his friend Robert Rodman, a psychoanalyst, that “Shengold suggested, with some hesitancy, some months ago, that I should consider going deeper with him.” He added, “He also observes that I don’t complain, say, of sexual deprivation—though this is absolute.” At first, Sacks was worried that Shengold was preparing to dismiss him from treatment: “I’ve done all I can for you—now manage on your own!” Then he felt hopeful that he didn’t need to assume that “boredom-depression-loneliness-cutoffness” would define the rest of his life. He was also moved that, after twenty years, Shengold still considered him “worth extra work.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Sacks was shaken by the idea that they’d only been skimming the surface. He looked back through his notebooks and noticed “a perceptible decline in concern and passion,” which he felt had also dulled the quality of his thought. “Is the superficiality of my work, then, due to superficiality of relationships—to running away from whatever has deeper feeling and meaning?” he asked Rodman. “Is this perhaps spoken of, in a camouflaged way, when I describe the ‘superficialization’ of various patients?” As an example, he referenced an essay in “Hat” about a woman with a cerebral tumor. She was intelligent and amusing but seemed not to care about anyone. “Was this the ‘cover’ of some unbearable emotion?” he writes in the essay.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks felt that Shengold was the reason he was still alive, and that he should go further with him. “What have I to lose?” he asked Rodman. But, he wrote, “what one has to lose, of course, may be just that quasi-stable if fragile ‘functioning’ . . . so there is reason to hesitate.” Going deeper would also mean more fully submitting to someone else’s interpretation, experiencing what he asked of his own patients; Rodman proposed that Sacks was “afraid of the enclosure of analysis, of being reduced and fixed with a formulated phrase.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the early eighties, Lawrence Weschler, then a writer for The New Yorker, began working on a biography of Sacks. Weschler came to feel that Sacks’s homosexuality was integral to his work, but Sacks didn’t want his sexuality mentioned at all, and eventually asked him to stop the project. “I have lived a life wrapped in concealment and wracked by inhibition, and I can’t see that changing now,” he told Weschler. In his journal, Sacks jotted down thoughts to share with Weschler on the subject: “My ‘sex life’ (or lack of it) is, in a sense irrelevant to the . . . sweep of my mind.” In another entry, he wrote that the Freudian term “sublimation” diminished the process he’d undergone. When he was still having sex, as a young man in California, he used to sheath his body in leather gear, so he was “totally encased, enclosed,” his real self sealed in a kind of “black box.” He wrote, “I have, in a sense, ‘outgrown’ these extraordinary, almost convulsive compulsions—but this detachment has been made possible by incorporating them into a vast and comprehending view of the world.” (Weschler became close friends with Sacks, and, after Sacks died, published a “biographical memoir” titled “And How Are You, Dr. Sacks?”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s unclear whether Sacks did “go deeper” with Shengold. In the late eighties, Sacks wrote in his journal that he was “scared, horrified (but, in an awful way, accepting or complaisant) about my non-life.” He likened himself to a “pithed and gutted creature.” Rather than living, he was managing a kind of “homeostasis.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1987, Sacks had an intense friendship with a psychiatrist named Jonathan Mueller, with whom he briefly fell in love. Mueller, who was married to a woman, told me that he did not realize Sacks had romantic feelings for him. Sacks eventually moved on. But he felt that the experience had altered him. “I can read ‘love stories’ with empathy and understanding—I can ‘enter into them’ in a way which was impossible before,” he wrote in his journal. He perceived, in a new light, what it meant for his patients in “Awakenings” to glimpse the possibility of “liberation”: like him, he wrote, they were seeking “not merely a cure but an indemnification for the loss of their lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the nineties, Sacks seemed to ask less of himself, emotionally, in relation to his patients. He had started working with Kate Edgar, who’d begun as his assistant but eventually edited his writing, organized his daily life, and became a close friend. (Shengold had encouraged Sacks to find someone to assist with his work. “The secretary is certainly an important ‘ego-auxiliary,’ ” he wrote him in a letter.) Edgar was wary about the way Sacks quoted his patients—they were suspiciously literary, she thought—and she checked to make sure he wasn’t getting carried away. She spent hours with some of his patients, and, she told me, “I never caught him in anything like that, which actually surprises me.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weschler told me that Sacks used to express anxiety about whether he’d distorted the truth. Weschler would assure him that good writing is not a strict account of reality; there has to be space for the writer’s imagination. He said he told Sacks, “Come on, you’re extravagantly romanticizing how bad you are—just as much as you were extravagantly romanticizing what the patient said. Your mother’s accusing voice has taken over.” Weschler had gone to Beth Abraham Hospital to meet some of the patients from “Awakenings” and had been shaken by their condition. “There’s a lot of people shitting in their pants, drooling—the sedimentation of thirty years living in a warehouse,” he said. “His genius was to see past that, to the dignity of the person. He would talk to them for an hour, and maybe their eyes would brighten only once—the rest of the time their eyes were cloudy—but he would glom onto that and keep talking.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After “Hat,” Sacks’s relationship with his subjects became more mediated. Most of them were not his patients; many wrote to him after reading his work, recognizing themselves in his books. There was a different power dynamic, because these people already believed that they had stories to tell. Perhaps the guilt over liberties he had taken in “Hat” caused him to curb the impulse to exaggerate. His expressions of remorse over “making up, ‘enhancing,’ etc,” which had appeared in his journals throughout the seventies and eighties, stopped. In his case studies, he used fewer and shorter quotes. His patients were far more likely to say ordinary, banal things, and they rarely quoted literature. They still had secret gifts, but they weren’t redeemed by them; they were just trying to cope.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In “An Anthropologist on Mars,” from 1992, a book of case studies about people compensating for, and adapting to, neurological conditions, some of the richest passages are the ones in which Sacks allows his incomprehension to become part of the portrait. In a chapter called “Prodigies,” he wants badly to connect with a thirteen-year-old boy named Stephen, who is autistic and has an extraordinary ability to draw, but Stephen resists Sacks’s attempts at intimacy. He will not allow himself to be romanticized, a refusal that Sacks ultimately accepts: “Is Stephen, or his autism, changed by his art? Here, I think, the answer is no.” In this new mode, Sacks is less inclined to replace Stephen’s unknowable experience with his own fantasy of it. He is open about the discomfort, and even embarrassment, of his multiple failures to reach him: “I had hoped, perhaps sentimentally, for some depth of feeling from him; my heart had leapt at the first ‘Hullo, Oliver!’ but there had been no follow-up.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mort Doran, a surgeon with Tourette’s syndrome whom Sacks profiled in “Anthropologist,” told me that he was happy with the way Sacks had rendered his life. He said that only one detail was inaccurate—Sacks had written that the brick wall of Doran’s kitchen was marked from Doran hitting it during Tourette’s episodes. “I thought, Why would he embellish that? And then I thought, Maybe that’s just what writers do.” Doran never mentioned the error to Sacks. He was grateful that Sacks “had the gravitas to put it out there to the rest of the world and say, ‘These people aren’t all nuts or deluded. They’re real people.’ ”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The wife in the title story of “Hat” had privately disagreed with Sacks about the portrayal of her husband, but for the most part Sacks appeared to have had remarkable relationships with his patients, corresponding with them for years. A patient called Ray, the subject of a 1981 piece about Tourette’s syndrome, told me that Sacks came to his son’s wedding years after his formal treatment had ended. Recalling Sacks’s death, he found himself suddenly crying. “Part of me left,” he said. “Part of my self was gone.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A year after “Awakenings” was published, Sacks broke his leg in Norway, and Leonard L. and his mother wrote him a get-well letter. Thirty-two patients added their names, their signatures wavering. “Everybody had been counting the days for your return, so you can imagine the turmoil when they heard the news,” Leonard’s mother wrote. She explained that “most of the patients are not doing so well without your help and interest.” She added that Leonard “isn’t doing too well either.” When Leonard learned that Sacks wouldn’t be back, she said, “he shed enough tears to fill a bucket.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks spoke of “animating” his patients, as if lending them some of his narrative energy. After living in the forgotten wards of hospitals, in a kind of narrative void, perhaps his patients felt that some inaccuracies were part of the exchange. Or maybe they thought, That’s just what writers do. Sacks established empathy as a quality every good doctor should possess, enshrining the ideal through his stories. But his case studies, and the genre they helped inspire, were never clear about what they exposed: the ease with which empathy can slide into something too creative, or invasive, or possessive. Therapists—and writers—inevitably see their subjects through the lens of their own lives, in ways that can be both generative and misleading.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In his journal, reflecting on his work with Tourette’s patients, Sacks described his desire to help their illness “reach fruition,” so that they would become floridly symptomatic. “With my help and almost my collusion, they can extract the maximum possible from their sickness—maximum of knowledge, insight, courage,” he wrote. “Thus I will FIRST help them to get ill, to experience their illness with maximum intensity; and then, only then, will I help them get well!” On the next line, he wrote, “IS THIS MONSTROUS?” The practice came from a sense of awe, not opportunism, but he recognized that it made him complicit, as if their illness had become a collaboration. “An impulse both neurotic and intellectual (artistic) makes me get the most out of suffering,” he wrote. His approach set the template for a branch of writing and thinking that made it seem as if the natural arc of illness involved insight and revelation, and even some poetry, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In his journals, Sacks repeatedly complained that his life story was over. He had the “feeling that I have stopped doing, that doing has stopped, that life itself has stopped, that it is petering out in a sort of twilight of half-being,” he wrote, in 1987. His journals convey a sense of tangible boredom. He transcribed long passages from philosophers and theologists (Simone Weil, Søren Kierkegaard, Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz, Dietrich Bonhoeffer) and embarked on disquisitions on the best definition of reality, the “metabolism of grace,” the “deep mystery of incubation.” His thoughts cast outward in many directions—notes for a thousand lectures—then tunnelled inward to the point of non-meaning. “Where Life is Free, Immaterial, full of Art,” he wrote, “the laws of life, of Grace, are those of Fitness.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks proposed various theories for why he had undergone what he called “psychic death.” He wondered if he had become too popular, merely a fuzzy symbol of compassionate care. “Good old Sacks—the House Humanist,” he wrote, mocking himself. He also considered the idea that his four decades of analysis were to blame. Was it possible, he wrote, that a “vivisection of inner life, however conceived, however subtle and delicate, may in fact destroy the very thing it examines?” His treatment with Shengold seemed to align with a life of “homeostasis”—intimacy managed through more and more language, in a contained, sterile setting, on Monday and Wednesday mornings, from 6:00 to 6:45 A.M. They still referred to each other as “Dr. Sacks” and “Dr. Shengold.” Once, they ran into each other at a chamber concert. They were a few rows apart, but they didn’t interact. Occasionally, Shengold told his children that he “heard from the couch” about a good movie or play, but he never shared what happened in his sessions. They inferred that Sacks was their father’s patient after reading the dedication to him in “Hat.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Sacks aged, he felt as if he were gazing at people from the outside. But he also noticed a new kind of affection for humans—“homo sap.” “They’re quite complex (little) creatures (I say to myself),” he wrote in his journal. “They suffer, authentically, a good deal. Gifted, too. Brave, resourceful, challenging.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps because love no longer appeared to be a realistic risk—he had now entered a “geriatric situation”—Sacks could finally confess that he craved it. “I keep being stabbed by love,” he wrote in his journal. “A look. A glance. An expression. A posture.” He guessed that he had at least five, possibly ten, more years to live. “I want to, I want to ••• I dare not say. At least not in writing.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2008, Sacks had lunch with Bill Hayes, a forty-seven-year-old writer from San Francisco who was visiting New York. Hayes had never considered Sacks’s sexuality, but, as soon as they began talking, he thought, “Oh, my God, he’s gay,” he told me. They lingered at the table for much of the afternoon, connecting over their insomnia, among other subjects. After the meal, Sacks wrote Hayes a letter (which he never sent) explaining that relationships had been “a ‘forbidden’ area for me—although I am entirely sympathetic to &lt;del&gt;(indeed wistful and perhaps envious about)&lt;/del&gt; other people’s relationships.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A year later, Hayes, whose partner of seventeen years had died of a heart attack, moved to New York. He and Sacks began spending time together. At Sacks’s recommendation, Hayes started keeping a journal, too. He often wrote down his exchanges with Sacks, some of which he later published in a memoir, “Insomniac City.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s really a question of mutuality, isn’t it?” Sacks asked him, two weeks after they had declared their feelings for each other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Love?” Hayes responded. “Are you talking about love?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Yes,” Sacks replied.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sacks began taking Hayes to dinner parties, although he introduced him as “my friend Billy.” He did not allow physical affection in public. “Sometimes this issue of not being out became very difficult,” Hayes told me. “We’d have arguments, and I’d say things like ‘Do you and Shengold ever talk about why you can’t come out? Or is all you ever talk about your dreams?’ ” Sacks wrote down stray phrases from his dreams on a whiteboard in his kitchen so that he could report on them at his sessions, but he didn’t share what happened in therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kate Edgar, who worked for Sacks for three decades, had two brothers who were gay, and for years she had advocated for gay civil rights, organizing Pride marches for her son’s school. She intentionally found an office for Sacks in the West Village so that he would be surrounded by gay men living openly and could see how normal it had become. She tended to hire gay assistants for him, for the same reason. “So I was sort of plotting on that level for some years,” she told me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2013, after being in a relationship with Hayes for four years—they lived in separate apartments in the same building—Sacks began writing a memoir, “On the Move,” in which he divulged his sexuality for the first time. He recounts his mother’s curses upon learning that he was gay, and his decades of celibacy—a fact he mentions casually, without explanation. Edgar wondered why, after so many years of analysis, coming out took him so long, but, she said, “Oliver did not regard his relationship with Shengold as a failure of therapy.” She said that she’d guessed Shengold had thought, “This is something Oliver has to do in his own way, on his own time.” Shengold’s daughter, Nina, said that, “for my dad to have a patient he loved and respected finally find comfort in identifying who he’d been all his life—that’s growth for both of them.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few weeks after finishing the manuscript, Sacks, who’d had melanoma of the eye in 2005, learned that the cancer had come back, spreading to his liver, and that he had only months to live. He had tended toward hypochondria all his life, and Edgar thought that the diagnosis might induce a state of chronic panic. Since he was a child, Sacks had had a horror of losing things, even irrelevant objects. He would be overcome by the “feeling that there was a hole in the world,” he wrote in his journal, and the fear that “I might somehow fall through that hole-in-the-world, and be absolutely, inconceivably lost.” Edgar had dealt for decades with his distress over lost objects, but she noticed that now, when he misplaced things, he didn’t get upset. He had an uncharacteristic ease of being.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2015, before Shengold went on his annual summer break, Sacks said to Edgar, “If I’m alive in September when Shengold returns, I’m not sure I need to go back to my sessions.” They had been seeing each other for forty-nine years. Sacks was eighty-two; Shengold was eighty-nine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Sacks was struggling with his third book, “A Leg to Stand On,” which was about breaking his leg and his frustration that his doctors wouldn’t listen to him, he wrote in his journal that Shengold had suggested (while apologizing for the corniness of the phrase) that the book should be “a message of love”—a form of protest against the indifference that so many patients find in their doctors. Shengold may have been giving Sacks permission to see their own relationship—the one place in which Sacks felt an enduring sense of recognition and care—as a hidden subject of the book. Extending Shengold’s idea, Sacks wrote, of his book, “The ‘moral’ center has to do with . . . the irreducible ultimate in doctor-patient relations.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In August, two weeks before Sacks died, he and Shengold spoke on the phone. Shengold was with his family at a cottage in the Finger Lakes region of central New York, where he spent every summer. Nina told me, “We all gathered in the living room of that little cottage and put my father on speakerphone. Oliver Sacks was clearly on his deathbed—he was not able to articulate very well. Sometimes his diction was just gone. Dad kept shaking his head. He said, ‘I can’t understand you. I’m so sorry, I can’t understand you.’ ” At the end of the call, Shengold told Sacks, “It’s been the honor of my life to work with you,” and said, “Goodbye, Oliver.” Sacks responded, “Goodbye, Leonard.” It was the first time they had ever used each other’s first names. When they hung up, Shengold was crying.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After Sacks died, Shengold started closing down his practice. “It was the beginning of the end for him,” his son David told me. “He had lost most of his colleagues. He was really the last of his generation.” Nina said, “I do think part of why my father lived so long and was able to work so long was because of that relationship. That feeling of affection and kindred spirit was lifesaving.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In “Awakenings,” when describing how Leonard L.—his “ ‘ideal’ patient”—initially responded to L-dopa, Sacks characterizes him as “a man released from entombment” whose “predominant feelings at this time were feelings of freedom, openness, and exchange with the world.” He quotes Leonard saying, “I have been hungry and yearning all my life . . . and now I am full.” He also says, “I feel saved. . . . I feel like a man in love. I have broken through the barriers which cut me off from love.’ ”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For years, Sacks had tested the possibility of awakenings in others, as if rehearsing, or outsourcing, the cure he had longed to achieve with Shengold. But at the end of his life, like an inside-out case study, he inhabited the story he’d imagined for his patients. “All of us entertain the idea of another sort of medicine . . . which will restore us to our lost health and wholeness,” he wrote, in “Awakenings.” “We spend our lives searching for what we have lost; and one day, perhaps, we will suddenly find it.” ♦&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46204853</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 13:45:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mistral Releases Devstral 2 (72.2% SWE-Bench Verified) and Vibe CLI</title><link>https://mistral.ai/news/devstral-2-vibe-cli</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2d578ecf80ffd806"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;██████████████████&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;██████████████████&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;██████████████████&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;██████████████████&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;██████████████████&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;██████████████████&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;██████████████████&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;██████████████████&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;██████████████████&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mistral Vibe CLI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;State-of-the-art, open-source agentic coding models and CLI agent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;█░ Date: Dec 9, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;█░ Category: Research&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;█░ Author: Mistral AI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Content&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we're releasing Devstral 2—our next-generation coding model family available in two sizes: Devstral 2 (123B) and Devstral Small 2 (24B). Devstral 2 ships under a modified MIT license, while Devstral Small 2 uses Apache 2.0. Both are open-source and permissively licensed to accelerate distributed intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral 2 is currently free to use via our API.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are also introducing Mistral Vibe, a native CLI built for Devstral that enables end-to-end code automation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Highlights.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Devstral 2: SOTA open model for code agents with a fraction of the parameters of its competitors and achieving 72.2% on SWE-bench Verified.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Up to 7x more cost-efficient than Claude Sonnet at real-world tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Mistral Vibe CLI: Native, open-source agent in your terminal solving software engineering tasks autonomously.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Devstral Small 2: 24B parameter model available via API or deployable locally on consumer hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Compatible with on-prem deployment and custom fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Devstral: the next generation of SOTA coding.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral 2 is a 123B-parameter dense transformer supporting a 256K context window. It reaches 72.2% on SWE-bench Verified—establishing it as one of the best open-weight models while remaining highly cost efficient. Released under a modified MIT license, Devstral sets the open state-of-the-art for code agents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral Small 2 scores 68.0% on SWE-bench Verified, and places firmly among models up to five times its size while being capable of running locally on consumer hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral 2 (123B) and Devstral Small 2 (24B) are 5x and 28x smaller than DeepSeek V3.2, and 8x and 41x smaller than Kimi K2—proving that compact models can match or exceed the performance of much larger competitors. Their reduced size makes deployment practical on limited hardware, lowering barriers for developers, small businesses, and hobbyists.hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Built for production-grade workflows.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral 2 supports exploring codebases and orchestrating changes across multiple files while maintaining architecture-level context. It tracks framework dependencies, detects failures, and retries with corrections—solving challenges like bug fixing and modernizing legacy systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The model can be fine-tuned to prioritize specific languages or optimize for large enterprise codebases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We evaluated Devstral 2 against DeepSeek V3.2 and Claude Sonnet 4.5 using human evaluations conducted by an independent annotation provider, with tasks scaffolded through Cline. Devstral 2 shows a clear advantage over DeepSeek V3.2, with a 42.8% win rate versus 28.6% loss rate. However, Claude Sonnet 4.5 remains significantly preferred, indicating a gap with closed-source models persists.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Devstral 2 is at the frontier of open-source coding models. In Cline, it delivers a tool-calling success rate on par with the best closed models; it's a remarkably smooth driver. This is a massive contribution to the open-source ecosystem.” — Cline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Devstral 2 was one of our most successful stealth launches yet, surpassing 17B tokens in the first 24 hours. Mistral AI is moving at Kilo Speed with a cost-efficient model that truly works at scale.” — Kilo Code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral Small 2, a 24B-parameter model with the same 256K context window and released under Apache 2.0, brings these capabilities to a compact, locally deployable form. Its size enables fast inference, tight feedback loops, and easy customization—with fully private, on-device runtime. It also supports image inputs, and can power multimodal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Mistral Vibe CLI.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mistral Vibe CLI is an open-source command-line coding assistant powered by Devstral. It explores, modifies, and executes changes across your codebase using natural language—in your terminal or integrated into your preferred IDE via the Agent Communication Protocol. It is released under the Apache 2.0 license.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vibe CLI provides an interactive chat interface with tools for file manipulation, code searching, version control, and command execution. Key features:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Project-aware context: Automatically scans your file structure and Git status to provide relevant context&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Smart references: Reference files with @ autocomplete, execute shell commands with !, and use slash commands for configuration changes&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Multi-file orchestration: Understands your entire codebase—not just the file you're editing—enabling architecture-level reasoning that can halve your PR cycle time&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Persistent history, autocompletion, and customizable themes.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can run Vibe CLI programmatically for scripting, toggle auto-approval for tool execution, configure local models and providers through a simple config.toml, and control tool permissions to match your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Get started.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral 2 is currently offered free via our API. After the free period, the API pricing will be $0.40/$2.00 per million tokens (input/output) for Devstral 2 and $0.10/$0.30 for Devstral Small 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve partnered with leading, open agent tools Kilo Code and Cline to bring Devstral 2 to where you already build.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mistral Vibe CLI is available as an extension in Zed, so you can use it directly inside your IDE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Recommended deployment for Devstral.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral 2 is optimized for data center GPUs and requires a minimum of 4 H100-class GPUs for deployment. You can try it today on build.nvidia.com. Devstral Small 2 is built for single-GPU operation and runs across a broad range of NVIDIA systems, including DGX Spark and GeForce RTX. NVIDIA NIM support will be available soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devstral Small runs on consumer-grade GPUs as well as CPU-only configurations with no dedicated GPU required.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For optimal performance, we recommend a temperature of 0.2 and following the best practices defined for Mistral Vibe CLI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Contact us.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re excited to see what you will build with Devstral 2, Devstral Small 2, and Vibe CLI!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Share your projects, questions, or discoveries with us on X/Twitter, Discord, or GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;We’re hiring!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in shaping open-source research and building world-class interfaces that bring truly open, frontier AI to users, we welcome you to apply to join our team.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46205437</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 14:45:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>My favourite small hash table</title><link>https://www.corsix.org/content/my-favourite-small-hash-table</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ead9f4510877030b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;My favourite small hash table&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm the kind of person who thinks about the design and implementation of hash tables. One design which I find particularly cute, and I think deserves a bit more publicity, is Robin Hood open-addressing with linear probing and power-of-two table size. If you're not familiar with hash table terminology, that might look like a smorgasbord of random words, but it should become clearer as we look at some actual code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To keep the code simple to start with, I'm going to assume:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Keys are randomly-distributed 32-bit integers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Values are also 32-bit integers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If the key &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;is present, its value is not&lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The table occupies at most 32 GiB of memory.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each slot in the table is either empty, or holds a key and a value. The combination of properties (1) and (2) allows a key/value pair to be stored as a 64-bit integer, and property (3) means that the 64-bit value &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; can be used to represent an empty slot (some hash table designs also need a special value for representing tombstones, but this design doesn't need tombstones). Combining a key and a value into 64 bits couldn't be easier: the low 32 bits hold the key, and the high 32 bits hold the value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The structure for the table itself needs a pointer to the array of slots, the length of said array, and the number of non-empty slots. As the length is always a power of two, it's more useful to store &lt;code&gt;length - 1&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;length&lt;/code&gt;, which leads to &lt;code&gt;mask&lt;/code&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;length&lt;/code&gt;, and property (4) means that &lt;code&gt;mask&lt;/code&gt; can be stored as 32 bits. As the load factor should be less than 100%, we can assume &lt;code&gt;count &amp;lt; length&lt;/code&gt;, and hence &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt; can also be 32 bits. This leads to a mundane-looking:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct hash_table_t {
  uint64_t* slots;
  uint32_t mask;
  uint32_t count;
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Property (1) means that we don't need to hash keys, as they're already randomly distributed. Every possible key &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; has a "natural position" in the slots array, which is just &lt;code&gt;K &amp;amp; mask&lt;/code&gt;. If there are collisions, the slot in which a key actually ends up might be different to its natural position. The "linear probing" part of the design means that if &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; cannot be in its natural position, the next slot to be considered is &lt;code&gt;(K + 1) &amp;amp; mask&lt;/code&gt;, and if not that slot then &lt;code&gt;(K + 2) &amp;amp; mask&lt;/code&gt;, then &lt;code&gt;(K + 3) &amp;amp; mask&lt;/code&gt;, and so on. This leads to the definition of a "chain": if &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; is some key present in the table, &lt;code&gt;CK&lt;/code&gt; denotes the sequence of slots starting with &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;'s natural position and ending with &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;'s actual position. We have the usual property of open-addressing: none of the slots in &lt;code&gt;CK&lt;/code&gt; are empty slots. The "Robin Hood" part of the design then imposes an additional rather interesting property: for each slot &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;CK&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Score(S.Index, S.Key) â¥ Score(S.Index, K)&lt;/code&gt;, where:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;S.Index&lt;/code&gt;is the index of&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;in the&lt;code&gt;slots&lt;/code&gt;array (not the index of it in&lt;code&gt;CK&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;S.Key&lt;/code&gt;is the key present in slot&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;(i.e. the low 32 bits of&lt;code&gt;slots[S.Index]&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Score(Index, Key)&lt;/code&gt;is&lt;code&gt;(Index - Key) &amp;amp; mask&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These properties give us the termination conditions for the lookup algorithm: for a possible key &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;, we look at each slot starting from &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;'s natural position, and either we find &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;, or we find an empty slot, or we find a slot with &lt;code&gt;Score(S.Index, S.Key) &amp;lt; Score(S.Index, K)&lt;/code&gt;. In either of the latter two cases, &lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt; cannot have been present in the table. In the function below, &lt;code&gt;Score(S.Index, K)&lt;/code&gt; is tracked as &lt;code&gt;d&lt;/code&gt;. In a language with a modern type system, the result of a lookup would be &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;Value&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, but if sticking to plain C, property (3) can be used to make something similar: the 64-bit result is zero if the key is absent, and otherwise the value is in the low 32 bits of the result (which may themselves be zero, but the full 64-bit result will be non-zero). The logic is thus:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;uint64_t table_lookup(hash_table_t* table, uint32_t key) {
  uint32_t mask = table-&amp;gt;mask;
  uint64_t* slots = table-&amp;gt;slots;
  for (uint32_t d = 0;; ++d) {
    uint32_t idx = (key + d) &amp;amp; mask;
    uint64_t slot = slots[idx];
    if (slot == 0) {
      return 0;
    } else if (key == (uint32_t)slot) {
      return (slot &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 32) | (slot &amp;lt;&amp;lt; 32);
    } else if (((idx - (uint32_t)slot) &amp;amp; mask) &amp;lt; d) {
      return 0;
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If using a rich 64-bit CPU architecture, many of the expressions in the above function are cheaper than they might initially seem:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;slots[idx]&lt;/code&gt;involves zero-extending&lt;code&gt;idx&lt;/code&gt;from 32 bits to 64, multiplying it by&lt;code&gt;sizeof(uint64_t)&lt;/code&gt;, adding it to&lt;code&gt;slots&lt;/code&gt;, and then loading from that address. All this is a single instruction on x86-64 or arm64.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;key == (uint32_t)slot&lt;/code&gt;involves a comparison using the low 32 bits of a 64-bit register, which is a completely standard operation on x86-64 or arm64.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;(slot &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 32) | (slot &amp;lt;&amp;lt; 32)&lt;/code&gt;is a rotation by 32 bits, which again is a single instruction on x86-64 or arm64.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if using riscv64, things are less good:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If the &lt;code&gt;Zba&lt;/code&gt;extension is present,&lt;code&gt;sh3add.uw&lt;/code&gt;is a single instruction for zero-extending&lt;code&gt;idx&lt;/code&gt;from 32 bits to 64, multiplying it by&lt;code&gt;sizeof(uint64_t)&lt;/code&gt;, and adding it to&lt;code&gt;slots&lt;/code&gt;. If not, each step is a separate instruction, though the zero-extension can be eliminated with a slight reformulation to encourage the compiler to fold the zero-extension onto the load of&lt;code&gt;table-&amp;gt;mask&lt;/code&gt;(as riscv64 usually defaults to making sign-extension free, in contrast to x86-64/arm64 which usually make zero-extension free). Regardless, the load is always its own instruction.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;key == (uint32_t)slot&lt;/code&gt;hits a gap in the riscv64 ISA: it doesn't have any 32-bit comparison instructions, so this either becomes a 32-bit subtraction followed by a 64-bit comparison against zero, or promotion of both operands from 32 bits to 64 bits followed by a 64-bit comparison.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If the &lt;code&gt;Zbb&lt;/code&gt;extension is present, rotations are a single instruction. If not, they're three instructions, and so it becomes almost worth reworking the slot layout to put the key in the high 32 bits and the value in the low 32 bits.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moving on from lookup to insertion, there are various different options for what to do when the key being inserted is already present. I'm choosing to show a variant which returns the old value (in the same form as &lt;code&gt;table_lookup&lt;/code&gt; returns) and then overwrites with the new value, though other variants are obviously possible. The logic follows the same overall structure as seen in &lt;code&gt;table_lookup&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;uint64_t table_set(hash_table_t* table, uint32_t key, uint32_t val) {
  uint32_t mask = table-&amp;gt;mask;
  uint64_t* slots = table-&amp;gt;slots;
  uint64_t kv = key + ((uint64_t)val &amp;lt;&amp;lt; 32);
  for (uint32_t d = 0;; ++d) {
    uint32_t idx = ((uint32_t)kv + d) &amp;amp; mask;
    uint64_t slot = slots[idx];
    if (slot == 0) {
      // Inserting new value (and slot was previously empty)
      slots[idx] = kv;
      break;
    } else if ((uint32_t)kv == (uint32_t)slot) {
      // Overwriting existing value
      slots[idx] = kv;
      return (slot &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 32) | (slot &amp;lt;&amp;lt; 32);
    } else {
      uint32_t d2 = (idx - (uint32_t)slot) &amp;amp; mask;
      if (d2 &amp;lt; d) {
        // Inserting new value, and moving existing slot
        slots[idx] = kv;
        table_reinsert(slots, mask, slot, d2);
        break;
      }
    }
  }
  if (++table-&amp;gt;count * 4ull &amp;gt;= mask * 3ull) {
    // Expand table once we hit 75% load factor
    table_rehash(table);
  }
  return 0;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To avoid the load factor becoming too high, the above function will sometimes grow the table by calling this helper function:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;void table_rehash(hash_table_t* table) {
  uint32_t old_mask = table-&amp;gt;mask;
  uint32_t new_mask = old_mask * 2u + 1u;
  uint64_t* new_slots = calloc(new_mask + 1ull, sizeof(uint64_t));
  uint64_t* old_slots = table-&amp;gt;slots;
  uint32_t idx = 0;
  do {
    uint64_t slot = old_slots[idx];
    if (slot != 0) {
      table_reinsert(new_slots, new_mask, slot, 0);
    }
  } while (idx++ != old_mask);
  table-&amp;gt;slots = new_slots;
  table-&amp;gt;mask = new_mask;
  free(old_slots);
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both of &lt;code&gt;table_set&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;table_rehash&lt;/code&gt; make use of a helper function which is very similar to &lt;code&gt;table_set&lt;/code&gt;, but doesn't need to check for overwriting an existing key and also doesn't need to update &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;void table_reinsert(uint64_t* slots, uint32_t mask, uint64_t kv, uint32_t d) {
  for (;; ++d) {
    uint32_t idx = ((uint32_t)kv + d) &amp;amp; mask;
    uint64_t slot = slots[idx];
    if (slot == 0) {
      slots[idx] = kv;
      break;
    } else {
      uint32_t d2 = (idx - (uint32_t)slot) &amp;amp; mask;
      if (d2 &amp;lt; d) {
        slots[idx] = kv;
        kv = slot;
        d = d2;
      }
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That covers lookup and insertion, so next up is key removal. As already hinted at, this hash table design doesn't need tombstones. Instead, removing a key involves finding the slot containing that key and then shifting slots left until finding an empty slot or a slot with &lt;code&gt;Score(S.Index, S.Key) == 0&lt;/code&gt;. This removal strategy works due to a neat pair of emergent properties:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If slot &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;has&lt;code&gt;Score(S.Index, S.Key) != 0&lt;/code&gt;, it is viable for&lt;code&gt;S.Key&lt;/code&gt;to instead be at&lt;code&gt;(S.Index - 1) &amp;amp; mask&lt;/code&gt;(possibly subject to additional re-arranging to fill the gap formed by moving&lt;code&gt;S.Key&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If slot &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;has&lt;code&gt;Score(S.Index, S.Key) == 0&lt;/code&gt;, and&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;is part of some chain&lt;code&gt;CK&lt;/code&gt;, then&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;is at the very start of&lt;code&gt;CK&lt;/code&gt;. Hence it is viable to turn&lt;code&gt;(S.Index - 1) &amp;amp; mask&lt;/code&gt;into an empty slot without breaking any chains.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This leads to the tombstone-free removal function, which follows the established pattern of returning either the old value or zero:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;uint64_t table_remove(hash_table_t* table, uint32_t key) {
  uint32_t mask = table-&amp;gt;mask;
  uint64_t* slots = table-&amp;gt;slots;
  for (uint32_t d = 0;; ++d) {
    uint32_t idx = (key + d) &amp;amp; mask;
    uint64_t slot = slots[idx];
    if (slot == 0) {
      return 0;
    } else if (key == (uint32_t)slot) {
      uint32_t nxt = (idx + 1) &amp;amp; mask;
      --table-&amp;gt;count;
      while (slots[nxt] &amp;amp;&amp;amp; ((slots[nxt] ^ nxt) &amp;amp; mask)) {
        slots[idx] = slots[nxt];
        idx = nxt;
        nxt = (idx + 1) &amp;amp; mask;
      }
      slots[idx] = 0;
      return (slot &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 32) | (slot &amp;lt;&amp;lt; 32);
    } else if (((idx - (uint32_t)slot) &amp;amp; mask) &amp;lt; d) {
      return 0;
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final interesting hash table operation is iterating over all keys and values, which is just an array iteration combined with filtering out zeroes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;void table_iterate(hash_table_t* table, void(*visit)(uint32_t key, uint32_t val)) {
  uint64_t* slots = table-&amp;gt;slots;
  uint32_t mask = table-&amp;gt;mask;
  uint32_t idx = 0;
  do {
    uint64_t slot = slots[idx];
    if (slot != 0) {
      visit((uint32_t)slot, (uint32_t)(slot &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 32));
    }
  } while (idx++ != mask);
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That wraps up the core concepts of this hash table, so now it is time to revisit some of the initial simplifications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If keys are 32-bit integers but are not randomly-distributed, then we just need an invertible hash function from 32 bits to 32 bits, the purpose of which is to take keys following ~any real-world pattern and emit a ~random pattern. The &lt;code&gt;table_lookup&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;table_set&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;table_remove&lt;/code&gt; functions gain &lt;code&gt;key = hash(key)&lt;/code&gt; at the very start but are otherwise unmodified (noting that if the hash function is invertible, hash equality implies key equality, hence no need to explicitly check key equality), and &lt;code&gt;table_iterate&lt;/code&gt; is modified to apply the inverse function before calling &lt;code&gt;visit&lt;/code&gt;. If hardware CRC32 / CRC32C instructions are present (as is the case on sufficiently modern x86-64 and arm64 chips), these can be used for the task, although their inverses are annoying to compute, so perhaps not ideal if iteration is an important operation. If CRC32 isn't viable, one option out of many is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If keys and values are larger than 32 bits, then the design can be augmented with a separate array of key/value pairs, with the design as shown containing a 32-bit hash of the key and the array index of the key/value pair. To meet property (3) in this case, either the hash function can be chosen to never be zero, or "array index plus one" can be stored rather than "array index". It is not possible to make the hash function invertible in this case, so &lt;code&gt;table_lookup&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;table_set&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;table_remove&lt;/code&gt; do need extending to check for key equality after confirming hash equality. Iteration involves walking the separate array of key/value pairs rather than the hash structure, which has the added benefit of iteration order being related to insertion order rather than hash order. As another twist on this, if keys and values are variably-sized, then the design can instead be augmented with a separate array of bytes, with key/value pairs serialised somewhere in that array, and the hash structure containing a 32-bit hash of the key and the byte offset (within the array) of the key/value pair.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, a design can only stretch so far. If you're after a concurrent lock-free hash table, look elsewhere. If you can rely on 128-bit SIMD instructions being present, you might instead want to group together every 16 key/value pairs, keep an 8-bit hash of each key, and rely on SIMD to perform 16 hash comparisons in parallel. If you're building hardware rather than software, it can be appealing to have multiple hash functions, each one addressing its own SRAM bank. There is no one-size-fits-all hash table, but I've found the one shown here to be good for a lot of what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46205461</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 14:47:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kaiju – General purpose 3D/2D game engine in Go and Vulkan with built in editor</title><link>https://github.com/KaijuEngine/kaiju</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d71a40118926331e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kaiju is a 2D/3D game engine written in Go (Golang) backed by Vulkan. The goal of the engine is to use a modern, easy, systems level programming language, with a focus on simplicity, to create a new kind of game engine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📄 2D / 🧊 3D Game Engine&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🪟 Windows&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🐧 Linux&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🤖 Android (NEW, support now functional)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🍎 Mac (support is currently WIP)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🤖👉⌨️ Local AI (LLM) interop&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;g-emoji&gt;⚠️&lt;/g-emoji&gt;🚧🏗️👷♂️ Work in progress, under heavy development&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🚚 Faster builds than other game engines&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🔥 Better performance than other game engines (9x faster than Unity out of the box)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;💾 Less memory than other engines&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mailing list &amp;lt;- Recommended for detailed updates&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Discord server&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Brent Farris on X/Twitter&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The current version of the base engine renders extremely fast, faster than most would think a garbage collected language could go. In my testing a release mode build of a game in Unity with nothing but a black background and a cube runs at about 1,600 FPS. In Kaiju, the same thing runs at around 5,400 FPS on the same machine. In fact, a complete game, with audio, custom cursors, real time PBR rendering with real time shadows, UI, and more runs at 2,712 FPS (in "debug" mode) screenshots or it didn't happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love C, and because I love C and found out that Ken Thompson played a part in designing Go, I gave Go a chance. It has been such a joy to use and work with I decided to port my C game engine to Go. Go is a modern system-level language that allows me to write code the way I want to write code and even have the opportunity to do some crazy things if I want to (no strings attached). Also the simplicity and "just works" of writing Assembly code was a great boost to my happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's more, it's a language that other developers can easily learn and jump right into extending the engine/editor. No need for developers to re-figure out some bespoke macros or crazy templating nonsense. It's flat, easy, straight forward, and the foot-gun is hidden behind some walls, but there if you want it. Furthermore, developers can write their games in Go directly, no need for some alternative language that is different from the engine code (but we'll include Lua for modding).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am creating this section because I get asked about it when I mention "Go", possibly not realizing that most public game engines use a garbage collector (GC).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The GC is actually a feature I'm happy with (shocker coming from a C guy). Well, the reason is simple, if you're going to make a game engine that the public will use and needs to be stable, you need a garbage collector. Unity has C# (and possibly an internal GC as well), Unreal has a GC (and it could use a tune up if you ask me), Godot has a GC albeit their scripting language or when you use C#. It is actually very important for public engines to have a GC because people are only human and make a lot of mistakes, mistakes they'll blame on you (the engine developer) before they blame themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coincidentally, the overall design I have for the engine plays very well with the GC and last I measured, I have a net-0 heap allocation while running (may need a new review). If you don't abuse the GC, you shouldn't generally feel it, it runs concurrently as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'll be the first to admit, I think the developers of Go can create a better GC than I can, and probably better than Unreal and Unity too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though the engine is production ready, the editor is not, feel free to join and contribute to its development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the latest updates, please join the Discord or check my Twitter/X.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please review the Ad-Hoc editor readme&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please see the documentation on how to get started and compile the engine&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46205519</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 14:51:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Gemini Pro 3 hallucinates the HN front page 10 years from now</title><link>https://dosaygo-studio.github.io/hn-front-page-2035/news</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a461ad970e1c7920"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Y Hacker News new | past | comments | ask | show | jobs | submit login 1. First successful telemetry from Starship HLS-9 on the Sea of Tranquility ( spacex.com ) 894 points by muskwatch 4 hours ago | hide | 312 comments 2. A 100% Rust kernel is now upstream in Linux 7.4 ( kernel.org ) 402 points by rust_evangelist 6 hours ago | hide | 156 comments 3. Why I still write raw code instead of prompting the compiler ( nostalgic-coder.io ) 128 points by oldtimer99 3 hours ago | hide | 89 comments 4. Running LLaMA-12 7B on a contact lens with WASM ( arxiv.org ) 67 points by edge_compute 2 hours ago | hide | 14 comments 5. Show HN: AlgoDrill – Interactive drills to stop forgetting LeetCode patterns ( algodrill.io ) 243 points by persistence_is_key 5 hours ago | hide | 98 comments 6. ITER achieves net positive energy for 20 consecutive minutes ( nature.com ) 1205 points by physics_lover 12 hours ago | hide | 402 comments 7. Restoring a 2024 Framework Laptop: A retrospective ( ifixit.com ) 56 points by retro_fix 4 hours ago | hide | 22 comments 8. Google kills Gemini Cloud Services ( killedbygoogle.com ) 530 points by dang_fan 15 hours ago | hide | 330 comments 9. Visualizing the 5th dimension with WebGPU 2.0 ( graphics-shader.net ) 88 points by webgl_wizard 7 hours ago | hide | 12 comments 10. Launch HN: Nia (YC W36) – Give context to autonomous coding agents ( trynia.ai ) 112 points by founder_jane 10 hours ago | hide | 45 comments 11. Debian 18 "Trixie" released ( debian.org ) 312 points by apt_get 14 hours ago | hide | 78 comments 12. Is it time to rewrite sudo in Zig? ( github.com ) 45 points by ziggy42 3 hours ago | hide | 60 comments 13. EU passes "Right to Human Verification" Act ( europa.eu ) 670 points by policy_wonk 1 day ago | hide | 290 comments 14. Reverse Engineering the Neuralink V4 Bluetooth Protocol ( brain-hacks.org ) 220 points by cyborg_sec 8 hours ago | hide | 55 comments 15. Post-Silicon Computing: An Intro to Photonic Circuits ( mit.edu ) 99 points by lightspeed 6 hours ago | hide | 18 comments 16. FDA approves over-the-counter CRISPR for lactose intolerance ( fda.gov ) 415 points by bio_hacker 16 hours ago | hide | 211 comments 17. SQLite 4.0 Release Notes ( sqlite.org ) 800 points by drh 20 hours ago | hide | 140 comments 18. Ask HN: How do you prevent ad-injection in AR glasses? 320 points by glasshole2 11 hours ago | hide | 102 comments 19. Jepsen: NATS 4.2 (Still losing messages?) ( jepsen.io ) 88 points by aphyr_bot 9 hours ago | hide | 33 comments 20. Playing GTA VI on a RISC-V Cluster ( youtube.com ) 45 points by tlyleung 2 hours ago | hide | 16 comments 21. Why functional programming is the future (again) ( haskell.org ) 102 points by monad_lover 7 hours ago | hide | 65 comments 22. Microsoft Office 365 prices increase to $40/user/month ( officewatch.com ) 900 points by taubek 1 day ago | hide | 600 comments 23. Emulating Windows 10 in the browser ( bellard.org ) 341 points by qemu_fan 19 hours ago | hide | 50 comments 24. Let's put Tailscale on a SpaceX Starlink Dish ( tailscale.com ) 250 points by net_hacker 20 hours ago | hide | 45 comments 25. Manual: Deep Fakes detection for Seniors ( aarp.org ) 122 points by concerned_grandson 21 hours ago | hide | 77 comments 26. IBM to acquire OpenAI (Rumor) ( bloomberg.com ) 120 points by stock_watcher 1 day ago | hide | 338 comments 27. The unexpected return of server-side rendering ( htmx.org ) 147 points by bikenaga 19 hours ago | hide | 48 comments 28. How to build a Faraday Cage for your bedroom ( privacy-first.com ) 267 points by tinfoil_hat 22 hours ago | hide | 49 comments 29. AI progress is stalling. Human equivalence was a mirage ( garymarcus.com ) 485 points by skeptic_ai 14 hours ago | hide | 416 comments 30. Show HN: A text editor that doesn't use AI ( github.com ) 270 points by pure_coder 22 hours ago | hide | 105 comments More Guidelines | FAQ | Lists | API | Security | Legal | Apply to YC | Contact Search:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46205632</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 15:00:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI needs more power than the grid can deliver – supersonic tech can fix that</title><link>https://boomsupersonic.com/flyby/ai-needs-more-power-than-the-grid-can-deliver-supersonic-tech-can-fix-that</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="16d2b440c19c9c2a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By: Blake Scholl, Founder &amp;amp; CEO, Boom Supersonic&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It started, as many things do these days, by scrolling on X.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was reading post after post about the power crisis hitting AI data centers—GPU racks sitting idle, waiting not on chips, but on electricity. I texted with Sam Altman—who confirmed power was indeed a major constraint. I pinged our engineering team—and found that they already had the outline of a plan to build a power turbine based on our Symphony supersonic engine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After a few conversations, it became clear: AI didn’t just need more turbines—it needed a new and fundamentally better turbine. Symphony was the perfect new engine to accelerate AI in America. About three months later, we had a signed deal for 1.21 gigawatts and had started manufacturing the first turbine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we’re announcing Superpower, our new 42‑megawatt natural gas turbine, along with a $300M funding round and Crusoe as our launch customer. And most importantly: this marks a turning point. Boom is now on a self-funded path to both Superpower and the Overture supersonic airliner.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to share the real story of how this happened—and why supersonic technology is exactly what America’s energy crisis demands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;America Doesn’t Have 10–15 Years to Solve Its Power Problem the Old Way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’ve been paying attention, you know the U.S. is in a genuine energy crunch. GPU racks are idling because they can’t get power. Data centers are fighting over substations and interconnection queues. Meanwhile China is adding power capacity at a wartime pace—coal, gas, nuclear, everything—while America struggles to get a single transmission line permitted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI won’t wait for us to fix the grid. And the United States simply doesn’t have 10–15 years to build out power infrastructure the old way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hyperscalers have already moved to their own Plan B: behind‑the‑meter power plants. You’ve seen XAI’s Colossus I and II in Memphis. OpenAI’s Stargate I in Abilene. These projects are powered by arrays of aeroderivative natural-gas turbines—which are, fundamentally, modified jet engines from the 1970s. There’s something brilliant in this approach: the transition from gigantic “frame” turbines to arrays of mid-size “aeroderivative” turbines mirrors the computing industry’s shift from mainframes to blade servers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem? The “blade servers” of the energy world are old tech and they’re sold out. Because the most popular “aeroderivative” turbines are based on subsonic jet engines, they’re happiest when the outside air temperature is -50°F—like it is when going Mach 0.8 at 30,000 feet. As outside temperatures rise, there is no option but to throttle back the engines—or else the turbine blades literally melt down. These turbines begin losing power at about 50°F and by the time it’s 110°—as often happens in popular data center locations like Texas—30% of generation capacity is lost. Nonetheless, major manufacturers all have backlogs through the rest of the decade and none is building a new-generation advanced-technology turbine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;A Supersonic Engine Core Makes the Perfect Power Turbine&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we designed the Symphony engine for Overture, we built something no one else has built this century: a brand-new large engine core optimized for continuous, high‑temperature operation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A subsonic engine is built for short bursts of power at takeoff. A supersonic engine is built to run hard, continuously, at extreme thermal loads. Symphony was designed for Mach 1.7 at 60,000 feet, where effective temperatures reach 160°F—not the frigid -50°F conditions where legacy subsonic engines operate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This gives Superpower several critical advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Full power even with high ambient heat – Where legacy turbines lose 20–30% at 110°F, Superpower maintains its full 42MW output without derate.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Waterless operation – Legacy turbines need huge quantities of water for cooling to avoid thermal derate in hot environments. Superpower doesn’t. It stays at full output, water‑free.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cloud‑native control and monitoring. Superpower inherits the telemetry and operations stack we built for XB‑1. Every turbine streams real‑time performance data, supports remote control, and flags anomalies before customers ever notice.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Superpower and Symphony are based on virtually identical turbine engines. Both share the identical core (HPC and HPT) and a slightly tuned low spool. In the place of Symphony’s hollow-core titanium fan, Superpower adds two additional compressor stages plus a three-stage free power turbine connected to a high-efficiency generator on its own shaft. Additionally, the engines use slightly different fuel nozzles, Symphony’s optimized for Jet A vs. Superpower’s for natural gas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Scaling Production the Supersonic Way: Vertical Integration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The legacy aerospace supply chain is congested. When the mission is urgent and the supply chain congested, you build the supply chain. The new Superpower Superfactory starts with a simple vision: raw materials in one side of the building, gigawatts of completed power turbine packages out the other side. We’ve already started making the first parts—and much of the production equipment to support 2GW/yr is on order. With this new financing we’re ready to accelerate further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If America wants to build at the speed AI requires, vertical integration isn’t optional. We’re standing up our own foundry and our own large scale CNC machining capability. We’ll have more to share on the Superpower Superfactory in early 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Scaling Production the Supersonic Way: Vertical Integration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Superpower is sort of like our Starlink moment, the strongest accelerant we’ve ever had toward our core mission of making Earth dramatically more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fastest way to a certified, passenger-carrying Symphony engine is to run its core for hundreds of thousands of hours in the real world, powering Earth’s most demanding AI data centers. Every hour a Superpower turbine spins is an hour of validation for Symphony. Every gigawatt we deliver strengthens our vertical integration and manufacturing capability. And with Superpower profitability funding the remainder of the aircraft program, we’ve done something rare in aerospace: created a self-sustaining path to a new airliner.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Superpower also reminds me of what Boom is at our core: a team willing to take on what others say is impossible, to do with a small team what big companies might not even attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46206277</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 15:51:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ask HN: Should "I asked $AI, and it said" replies be forbidden in HN guidelines?</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46206457</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b847b1477d243da4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As various LLMs become more and more popular, so does comments with "I asked Gemini, and Gemini said ....".&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While the guidelines were written (and iterated on) during a different time, it seems like it might be time to have a discussion about if those sort of comments should be welcomed on HN or not.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;- https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46164360&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;- https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46200460&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;- https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46080064&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Personally, I'm on HN for the human conversation, and large LLM-generated texts just get in the way of reading real text from real humans (assumed, at least).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;What do you think? Should responses that basically boil down to "I asked $LLM about $X, and here is what $LLM said:" be allowed on HN, and the guidelines updated to state that people shouldn't critique it (similar to other guidelines currently), or should a new guideline be added to ask people from refrain from copy-pasting large LLM responses into the comments, or something else completely?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46206457</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 16:02:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Handsdown one of the coolest 3D websites</title><link>https://bruno-simon.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e43305f6f9f2bf3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;00:00:000&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Server currently offline. Scores can't be saved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My name is Bruno Simon, and I'm a creative developer (mostly for the web).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is my portfolio. Please drive around to learn more about me and discover the many secrets of this world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And don't break anything!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Audio&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Quality&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;I'm stuck!&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Reset&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Renderer&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Server&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;WASD or ARROWS&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Move around&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SHIFT&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Boost&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CTRL LEFT or B&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Brake&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SPACE&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jump&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ENTER&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Interact&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Map&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;L&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mute&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Post a whisper&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;R&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Respawn&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NUM KEYS/NUM PAD&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Activate hydraulics&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;LEFT CLICK (DRAG)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Move camera&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;H&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Honk&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;One finger&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Move the car&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Two fingers&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Move camera / zoom&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tap (on the car)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jump&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;B&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Boost&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Y&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jump&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;X&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Brake&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;A&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Interact / Exit&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;LT L2&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Accelerate&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;RT R2&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Backward accelerate&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;LB / RB L1 / R1&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hydraulics&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Joystick Left&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Turn wheels&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Joystick Left (press)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Honk&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Joystick Right&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Move camera&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Joystick Right (press)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Zoom in/out&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Select&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Reset&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Start&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pause&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Server currently offline. Scores can't be saved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Resets in&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whispers are messages left by visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; - Everyone can see them&lt;lb/&gt; - New whispers remove old ones (max 30)&lt;lb/&gt; - One whisper per user&lt;lb/&gt; - Choose a flag&lt;lb/&gt; - No slur!&lt;lb/&gt; - Max 30 characters &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Server currently offline&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Thank you for visiting my portfolio! &lt;lb/&gt;If you are curious about the stack and how I built it, hereâs everything you need to know. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Three.js is the library Iâm using to render this 3D world. &lt;lb/&gt;It was created by mr.doob (X, GitHub), followed by hundreds of awesome developers, one of which being Sunag (X, GitHub) who added TSL, enabling the use of both WebGL and WebGPU, making this portfolio possible. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; If you want to learn Three.js, I got you covered with this huge course. &lt;lb/&gt;It contains everything you need to start building awesome stuff with Three.js (and much more). &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Iâve been making devlogs since the very start of this portfolio and you can find them on my Youtube channel. &lt;lb/&gt;Even though the portfolio is out, Iâm still working on the last videos so that the series is complete. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; The code is available on GitHub under MIT license. Even the Blender files are there, so have fun! &lt;lb/&gt;For security reasons, Iâm not sharing the server code, but the portfolio works without it. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; The music you hear was made especially for this portfolio by the awesome Kounine (Linktree). &lt;lb/&gt;They are now under CC0 license, meaning you can do whatever you want with them! &lt;lb/&gt;Download them here. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â Bruno&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Server currently offline. Scores can't be saved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Come hang out with the community, show us your projects and ask us anything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contact me directly.&lt;lb/&gt;I have to warn you, I try to answer everyone, but it might take a while.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46206531</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 16:06:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Launch HN: Mentat (YC F24) – Controlling LLMs with Runtime Intervention</title><link>https://playground.ctgt.ai</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46207017</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 16:37:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Clearspace (YC W23) Is Hiring a Founding Designer</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/clearspace/jobs/yamWTLr-founding-designer-at-clearspace</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b782896e8d09edc5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eliminate compulsive phone usage&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Clearspace&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clearspace is building the intentionality layer of the internet. Our mission is to build technology as effective at protecting human attention as social media is at exploiting it (infinite scrolling, short-form feeds, manipulative notifications, etc). Our category defining mobile app has been featured on Huberman Lab, New York Times Wirecutter, NPR Marketplace, Forbes, TBPN.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People that want a better relationship with their devices have nowhere to turn except for willpower. We are building an agent that achieves this on all devices by processing and filtering network traffic based on natural language rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About The Role&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are looking for a lead designer with strong aesthetic intuition and an obsession with designing through every inch of the user journey. You will be asked to bring pixel perfect designs to life across several different platforms, if you don’t love the process of designing this is not the role for you. You will be talking to users often and asked to speak to the overall brand direction at Clearspace.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualifications&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nice to Have&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Clearspace we help people reduce compulsive phone usage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We exist to protect people's attention from the exploits of modern technology platforms and make space for the things that matter to them most.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe the technology to protect someones attention should be just as sophisticated and effective as the tech that is exploiting it and are building a world-class engineering team to arm the world with a comprehensive attention protection stack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46207360</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 17:01:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PeerTube is recognized as a digital public good by Digital Public Goods Alliance</title><link>https://www.digitalpublicgoods.net/r/peertube</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="95773f811edde224"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;PeerTube&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Verified DPG&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Owner&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Framasoft&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Type&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;backend, mobile, web&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Licence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AGPL-3.0&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Last evaluated&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;07.10.2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Origin country&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;France&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Release date&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;DPG since&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Description&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PeerTube is a tool for hosting, managing, and sharing videos or live streams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Core Components Assessed/Included Repositories&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following repositories were submitted by the solution and included in our evaluation. Any repositories, add-ons, features not included in here were not reviewed by us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Feature&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Scale of the Solution*&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Connected members&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;N/A&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Participated Programs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;N/A&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Available Languages&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Esperanto, English, Slovenčina, Gàidhlig, العربية, Norsk, Magyar, Deutsch, Toki Pona, Euskara, Polski, Português (Portugal), Suomi, Tiếng Việt, Italiano, فارسی, Español, Taqbaylit, 简体中文（中国）, Hrvatski, ελληνικά, Occitan, украї́нська мо́ва, Français, ไทย, Türkçe, 繁體中文（台灣）, 日本語, Galego, Íslenska, Svenska, Nederlands, Pусский, bokmål, Čeština, Shqip, Català, Português (Brasil), Norsk nynorsk&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Organisations using it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;French Ministry of National Education (~100K videos), Italy’s National Research Council, a few French alternative media, the Weißensee Kunsthochschule in Berlin, as well as the Universität der Künste in the same city, a few universities worldwide, the Blender and Debian projects, and various activist groups&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;* This information is self-reported and updated annually&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Github insights&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learn how this product has met the requirements of the DPG Standard by exploring the indicators below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Application Details&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;DPG ID&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;GID0092472&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Status&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;DPG&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Date Created&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;2025-08-11&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Date Submitted&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;2025-08-25&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Date Reviewed&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;2025-10-07&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Date of Expiry&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;2026-10-07&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Application Log Details&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Timestamp&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Activity&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025-10-07 08:40:13&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ricardo Torres (L2 Reviewer) submitted their review of PeerTube (152) and found it to be a DPG&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025-10-07 08:40:12&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;System unmarked PeerTube (12958) as a nominee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025-10-07 08:40:07&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ricardo Torres (L2 Reviewer) passed 4. Platform Independence for PeerTube (12958)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025-10-07 08:40:02&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ricardo Torres (L2 Reviewer) moved PeerTube (12958) to under review&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025-10-07 08:38:21&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ricardo Torres (L2 Reviewer) finished consultation on 4. Platform Independence for PeerTube (12958)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46207464</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 17:08:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>If you're going to vibe code, why not do it in C?</title><link>https://stephenramsay.net/posts/vibe-coding.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="af2319bf33f607dd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;If You’re Going to Vibe Code, Why Not Do It in C?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stephen Ramsay&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or hell, why not do it in x86 assembly?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s get a few things out of the way before I go any further with this seemingly impertinent thought, because it’s nowhere near as snarky as it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, I don’t particularly like vibe coding. I love programming, and I have loved it since I made my first tentative steps with it sometime back in the mid-to-late 90s. I love programming so much, it always feels like I’m having too much fun for it to count as real work. I’ve done it professionally, but I also do it as a hobby. Someone apparently once said, “Do what you love and you’ll never work a day in your life.” That’s how I feel about writing code. I’ve also been teaching the subject for twenty-five years, and I can honestly say I am as excited about the first day of the semester now as I was when I first started. I realize it’s a bit precious to say so, but I’ll say it anyway: Turning non-programmers into programmers is my life’s work. It is the thing of which I am most proud as a college professor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vibe coding makes me feel dirty in ways that I struggle to articulate precisely. It’s not just that it feels like “cheating” (though it does). I also think it takes a lot of the fun out of the whole thing. I sometimes tell people (like the aforementioned students) that programming is like doing the best crossword puzzle in the world, except that when you solve it, it actually dances and sings. Vibe coding robs me of that moment, because I don’t feel like I really did it at all. And even though to be a programmer is to live with a more-or-less permanent set of aporias (you don’t really understand what the compiler is doing, really—and even if you do, you probably don’t really understand how the virtual memory subsystem works, really), it’s satisfying to understand every inch of my code and frustrating—all the way to the borderlands of active anxiety—not quite understanding what Claude just wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this leads me to my second point, which I must make as clearly and forcefully as I can. Vibe coding actually works. It creates robust, complex systems that work. You can tell yourself (as I did) that it can’t possibly do that, but you are wrong. You can then tell yourself (as I did) that it’s good as a kind of alternative search engine for coding problems, but not much else. You are also wrong about that. Because when you start giving it little programming problems that you can’t be arsed to work out yourself (as I did), you discover (as I did) that it’s awfully good at those. And then one day you muse out loud (as I did) to an AI model something like, “I have an idea for a program…” And you are astounded. If you aren’t astounded, you either haven’t actually done it or you are at some stage of grief prior to acceptance. Perfect? Hardly. But then neither are human coders. The future? I think the questions answers itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But to get to my impertinent question…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early on in my love affair with programming, I read Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs, which I now consider one of the great pedagogical masterpieces of the twentieth century. I learned a great deal about programming from that book, but among the most memorable lessons was one that appears in the second paragraph of the original preface. There, Hal Abelson and Gerald Sussman make a point that hits with the force of the obvious, and yet is very often forgotten:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[W]e want to establish the idea that a computer language is not just a way of getting a computer to perform operations but rather that it is a novel formal medium for expressing ideas about methodology. Thus, programs must be written for people to read, and only incidentally for machines to execute.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been repeating some version of this to my students ever since. Computers, I remind them, do not need the code to be “readable” or “ergonomic” for humans; they only need it to be readable and ergonomic for a computer, which is a considerably lower bar.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every programming language—including assembly language—was and is intended for the convenience of humans who need to read it and write it. If a language is innovative, it is usually not because it has allowed for automatic memory management, or concurrency, or safety, or robust error checking, but because it has made it easier for humans to express and reason about these matters. When we extol the virtues of this or that language—Rust’s safety guarantees, C++’s “no-cost abstractions,” or Go’s approach to concurrency—we are not talking about an affordance that the computer has gained, but about an affordance that we have gained as programmers of said computer. From our standpoint as programmers, object-oriented languages offer certain ways to organize our code—and, I think Abelson and Sussman would say, our thinking—that are potentially conducive to the noble treasures of maintainability, extensibility, error checking, and any number of other condign matters. From the standpoint of the computer, this little OO kink of ours seems mostly to indicate a strange affinity for heap memory. “Whatevs!” (says the computer). And pick your poison here, folks: functional programming, algebraic data types, dependent types, homoiconicity, immutable data structures, brace styles… We can debate the utility of these things, but we must understand that we are primarily talking about human problems. The set of “machine problems” to which these matters correspond is considerably smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So my question is this: Why vibe code with a language that has human convenience and ergonomics in view? Or to put that another way: Wouldn’t a language designed for vibe coding naturally dispense with much of what is convenient and ergonomic for humans in favor of what is convenient and ergonomic for machines? Why not have it just write C? Or hell, why not x86 assembly?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, at this point, you will want to say that the need for human understanding isn’t erased entirely thereby. Some version of this argument has merit, but I would remind you that if you are really vibe coding for real you already don’t understand a great deal of what it is producing. But if you look carefully, you will notice that it doesn’t struggle with undefined behavior in C. Or with making sure that all memory is properly freed. Or with off-by-one errors. It sometimes struggles to understand what it is that you actually want, but it rarely struggles with the actual execution of the code. It’s better than you are at keeping track of those things in the same way that a compiler is better at optimizing code than you are. Perfect? No. But as I said before…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is C the ideal language for vibe coding? I think I could mount an argument for why it is not, but surely Rust is even less ideal. To say nothing of Haskell, or OCaml, or even Python. All of these languages, after all, are for people to read, and only incidentally for machines to execute. They are practically adorable in their concern for problems that AI models do not have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I suppose what I’m getting at, here, is that if vibe coding is the future of software development (and it is), then why bother with languages that were designed for people who are not vibe coding? Shouldn’t there be such a thing as a “vibe-oriented programming language?” VOP. You read it here first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One possibility is that such a language truly would be executable pseudocode beyond even the most extravagant fever dreams of the most earnest Pythonistas; it shows you what it’s doing in truly pseudo code, but all the while it’s writing assembly. Or perhaps it’s something like the apotheosis of literate programming. You write a literary document “expressing ideas about methodology,” and the AI produces machine code (and a kind of literary critical practice evolves around this activity, eventually ordering itself into structuralist and post-structuralist camps. But I’m getting ahead of myself). Perhaps your job as a programmer is mostly running tests that verify this machine code (tests which have also been produced by AI). Or maybe a VOPL is really a certain kind of language that comes closer to natural language than any existing programming language, but which has a certain (easily learned) set of idioms and expressions that guide the AI more reliably and more quickly toward particular solutions. It doesn’t have goroutines. It has a “concurrency slang.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now obviously, the reason a large language model focused on coding is good at Javascript and C++ is precisely because it has been trained on billions of lines of code in those languages along with countless forum posts, StackOverflow debates, and so on. Bootstrapping a VOPL presents a certain kind of difficulty, but then one also suspects that LLMs are already being trained in some future version of this language, because so many programmers are already groping their way toward a system like this by virtue of the fact that so many of them are already vibe coding production-level systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t know how I feel about all of this (see my first and second points above). It saddens me to think of “coding by hand” becoming a kind of quaint Montessori-school stage in the education of a vibe coder—something like the contour drawings we demand from future photoshopers or the balanced equations we insist serve as a rite of passage for people who will never be without a calculator to the end of their days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, there is something exciting about the birth of a computational paradigm. It wasn’t that long ago, in the grand scheme of things, that someone realized that rewiring the entire machine every time you wanted to do a calculation (think ENIAC, circa 1945) was a rather suboptimal way to do things. And it is worth recalling that people complained when the stored-program computer rolled around (think EDVAC, circa 1951). Why? Well, the answer should be obvious. It was less reliable. It was slower. It removed the operator from the loop. It threatened specialized labor. It was conceptually impure. I’m not kidding about any of this. No less an authority than Grace Hopper had to argue against the quite popular idea that there was no way anyone could ever trust a machine to write instructions for another machine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Same vibe, as the kids say.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keywords: programming, AI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last Modified: 2025-12-07T16:29:42:-0600&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46207505</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 17:11:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Private Equity Is Changing Housing</title><link>https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/2025/12/private-equity-housing-changes/685138/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="49c9e0d11d93a7d2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How Private Equity Is Changing Housing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In some communities, corporations control more than 20 percent of properties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Listen to more stories on the Noa app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have a housing crisis, as you probably, painfully, know. Wouldn’t you like to have someone to blame for it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The United States is short 4 million housing units, with a particular dearth of starter homes, moderately priced apartments in low-rises, and family-friendly dwellings. Interest rates are high, which has stifled construction and pushed up the cost of mortgages. As a result, more Americans are renting, and roughly half of those households are spending more than a third of their income on shelter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This crisis has many causes: restrictive zoning codes, arcane permitting processes, excessive community input, declining construction productivity, expensive labor, and expensive lumber. And, some say, the aggressive entry of private equity into the housing market. Institutional investors have bought up hundreds of thousands of American homes since the start of the coronavirus pandemic, outbidding families and pushing up rents—a trend lamented by everyone from Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez to J. D. Vance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Casting private equity as a central villain in the country’s real-estate tragedy makes intuitive sense. Who’s going to win in a bidding war for a three-bedroom in a suburb of Cincinnati: a single-income family with a scrabbled-together 10 percent down payment or a Wall Street LLC offering cash? Still, housing economists and policy analysts have argued that institutional investors have played at most a bit part. Supply constraints began cropping up on the coasts a generation ago, if not earlier, whereas Wall Street started buying up significant numbers of homes only after the Great Recession and especially after the pandemic. Moreover, even if big investors are purchasing thousands of homes, they don’t own significant numbers of homes compared with small-scale landlords and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet in some markets, the balance has shifted. Last month, the Lincoln Institute of Land Policy and the Center for Geospatial Solutions published a report showing that corporations now own a remarkable one in 11 residential real-estate parcels in the 500 urban counties with data robust enough to analyze. In some communities, they control more than 20 percent of properties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I figured that big investors might be picking up vacation rentals in Colorado and expensive apartment buildings in the Bay Area and the Acela Corridor. They are, the report’s authors told me. But these investors are pouring the most money into “buy low, rent high” neighborhoods: communities, many of them in the South and the Rust Belt, where large shares of families can’t afford a mortgage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“They’re pulling all the starter homes off of the market in low-income, high-minority-density neighborhoods,” George McCarthy, the president of the Lincoln Institute, told me—a trend that is intensifying the country’s yawning racial wealth and homeownership gaps. In Cleveland, corporations own 17.5 percent of residential real-estate parcels. In the city’s East Side, which contains many predominantly Black neighborhoods, just one in five homebuyers in 2021 took out a mortgage. The rest—many investors, presumably—paid in cash or took out a loan from a non-traditional financier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Baltimore’s majority-Black McElderry Park and Ellwood Park/Monument neighborhoods, owner-occupants made just 13 percent of purchases in 2022. In a majority-white neighborhood not far away, owner-occupants bought more than 80 percent of homes that same year, and out-of-state corporations owned less than 1 percent of residential parcels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The report made me see the country’s real-estate crisis in a different light. Private-equity firms and other deep-pocketed investors aren’t why Seattle and Boston are unaffordable. Those cities have had shortage-driven housing crises that have intensified over decades. The firms aren’t why many towns in the Mountain West have seen jumps in home values and a corresponding increase in homelessness, displacement, and eviction. In those communities, white-collar emigrants from big cities have arrived and outbid locals. But investor money is distorting the housing market in communities with low wages and decent-enough housing supply, pushing thousands of Black and Latino families off the property ladder. Tens of thousands of workers who would like to invest in a home are instead stuck paying rent, and putting up with the associated uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While not all corporate landlords are bad landlords, some are bad landlords. Corporations are more likely to threaten to evict and to actually evict their tenants. They are also prone to skimping on maintenance and upkeep. “At the neighborhood level, when more than half of the properties are owned by outside investors—when you’ve now flipped that neighborhood from being primarily homeowner driven to investor driven—that matters, because homeowners behave very differently, politically and otherwise,” McCarthy said. An out-of-state investment firm might be less likely than a longtime resident or a local property manager to plant shade trees and demand safe sidewalks, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In response to the rising corporate ownership of homes, a variety of politicians have pushed for policy fixes. In New York, Governor Kathy Hochul has proposed legislation barring firms from bidding on single-family or two-family homes for the first 75 days they are on the market. Washington State is contemplating capping the number of units that corporations can own. Other legislators have suggested revoking tax benefits from large-scale owners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;McCarthy said that caps probably would not work well: Corporations might simply set up multiple entities to get around the rules and keep purchasing properties, for instance. “It’s just not going to fly,” he said. But he supports treating firms that own more than 10 properties in a given jurisdiction as commercial owners rather than residential owners, subjecting them to higher property-tax rates and higher taxes on their capital gains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If nothing is done, what’s happening to majority-Black communities in Ohio and Virginia and Georgia and Michigan might start happening in communities around the country. Private equity might not be causing the housing crisis, but corporate owners could end up making it a lot worse for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46207727</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 17:26:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Detail, a Bug Finder</title><link>https://detail.dev/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2bc4b01297a9fcdf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Your codebase is full of bugs.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Let us show you.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deep scans of your codebase that find bugs youâll be glad to know about. Security vulnerabilities, data loss, billing mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Daniel Worku&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CTO @ StarSling&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;We have Graphite, Codex, Cubic, Gemini and Cursor Bugbot running on PRs and the results from our Detail scan still gave me a minor heart attack.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;See it on Open Source&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How It Works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Add your repo.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Detail will clone it to a secure sandbox and confirm we can build your code properly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Detail exercises your code.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Detail runs thousands of checks and diagnostics, looking for bugs and selecting the most significant ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Receive bugs.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Detail sends you a writeup for each bug we find. Delivered to Linear, Jira, GitHub Issues, or email.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Enterprise Friendly&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;SOC 2 Type II Certified&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Highest standards of compliance with industry best practices. Audit report available upon request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Zero Data Retention&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All code and usage data can be purged based on your requirements. Our model providers retain nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46207852</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 17:35:35 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>