<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 16:45:06 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Floor796</title><link>https://floor796.com/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46401612</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 13:13:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gpg.fail</title><link>https://gpg.fail</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="902c8e970565f1c4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Slides, pocs and patches soon!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"in the hurry of leaving i forgot the sites src at home, sorry, had to rewrite the whole thing. expect a nicer site by tomorrow. im patching as we speak." &lt;lb/&gt; - reaper (&amp;lt;- to blame)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multiple Plaintext Attack on Detached PGP Signatures in GnuPG&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GnuPG Accepts Path Separators and Path Traversals in Literal Data "Filename" Field&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cleartext Signature Plaintext Truncated for Hash Calculation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Encrypted message malleability checks are incorrectly enforced causing plaintext recovery attacks&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Memory Corruption in ASCII-Armor Parsing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trusted comment injection (minisign)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cleartext Signature Forgery in the NotDashEscaped header implementation in GnuPG&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OpenPGP Cleartext Signature Framework Susceptible to Format Confusion&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GnuPG Output Fails To Distinguish Signature Verification Success From Message Content&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cleartext Signature Forgery in GnuPG&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Radix64 Line-Truncation Enabling Polyglot Attacks&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GnuPG may downgrade digest algorithm to SHA1 during key signature checking&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GnuPG Trust Packet Parsing Enables Adding Arbitrary Subkeys&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trusted comment Injection (minisign)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403200</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 17:05:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Windows 2 for the Apricot PC/Xi</title><link>https://www.ninakalinina.com/notes/win2apri/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="159ee95f3da634d7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Windows 2 for the Apricot PC/Xi&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(and Word, and Excel, and so much more) by Nina Kalinina, December 27th, 2025 (rev. 1.02 2025-12-27)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I bought my first Apricot PC about three years ago, when I realised I wanted an 8086-based computer. At the time, I knew nothing about it and simply bought it because it looked rad and the price was low. I had no idea that it was not IBM PC-compatible, and that there were very few programs available for it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have been on a quest to get a modern-ish word processor and spreadsheet program for it ever since. Which eventually made me "port" Windows 2 on it. In this post, I will tell you the story of this port.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a side-quest, I also wrote an article explaining why Windows 2 is kind of awesome. Make sure to check it out, too, if you need more Windows 2 screenshots in your life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A photograph of a dark grey computer with a CRT monitor - an Apricot PC - running Windows 2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please note that most of the images in this post were taken from a real green CRT, and thus their quality might vary. You can click the image to load it in full size.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you own an Apricot PC, or want to try the port in an emulator, check out the project on sr.ht. You need an Apricot PC, PC/Xi or Xen with at least 512 kB of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A few words about the Apricot PC/Xi&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want a personal computer today, your general choice is between a "PC" and a "Mac". Back in the 1980s, you would have to choose between dozens or even hundreds of computer architectures, and "PC" was not necessarily the most popular choice for a computer. One of the most promising market contenders, Victor 9000, also known as Sirius 1, was released in 1981. It gained popularity in Europe, creating a niche market for "Sirius-compatible" computers. Two years later, the British company ACT released its Sirius-compatible Apricot PC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A photograph of the main board of Apricot PC/Xi, in the process of being washed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apricot PC is a delightful computer with a great design. Its heart is Intel 8086, the older sibling of the 8088 used in the IBM PC. It uses lovely 3.5" floppy disks; and it is the first Western computer to have a 3.5" drive - before Apple Macintosh. The screen is 9 inches, 800x400 pixels, with great image fidelity. The PC/Xi model comes with a 10 megabyte Winchester hard drive, British-made Rodime RO352, the first-ever 3.5" hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A photograph of the computer's display showing multiple images at once: photographs of computer chips, schematics, and oscilloscope charts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The computer is simple enough to be understood by one person in its entirety (over the course of many months of studying). There are schematics, technical manuals, BIOS reference manuals, and example code available for it, too. Its CPU is supported by Microsoft C, Turbo Pascal, and Open Watcom. It even runs MS-DOS (2.0 to 3.20), though, of course, it cannot run any IBM PC programs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lack of IBM PC-compatibility proved to be fatal for the Apricot. The entirety of its software catalogue is less than 300 megabytes. There is only one graphical game with a soundtrack for it, and it was made in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were, of course, productivity applications for the Apricot, including Microsoft Word for DOS. But among those, only two word processors had a graphical interface: GEM Write and Microsoft Write for Windows 1. Neither were popular; GEM drivers were lost and re-created by John Elliot in 2012 or so. Windows 1 was thought to be lost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hypothetically, it should be possible to port a 16-bit Windows to this computer. It would require creating &lt;code&gt;SYSTEM.DRV&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;DISPLAY.DRV&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;KEYBOARD.DRV&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;MOUSE.DRV&lt;/code&gt;, and ideally &lt;code&gt;COMM.DRV&lt;/code&gt; drivers. But that would be a lot of work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A screenshot of Windows 1 Notepad. I didn't have a Windows 1 Write screenshot at hand, but trust me, it looks almost the same.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where things get interesting. A port of Windows 1 for the Apricot PC (released by ACT in 1987, a year before Windows 2) was miraculously preserved and surfaced online not that long ago. By itself, Windows 1 is unremarkable, as it does not have much useful software. But its driver architecture is not too different from Windows 2, so I thought it might be just about possible to make Windows 2 for the Apricot. And if I could somehow boot Windows 2, I'd be able to run Word, Excel, and Adobe Illustrator on my Apricot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, it only took two and a half years to pull it off!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Porting Windows 2 on the Apricot&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Booting, fast and slow&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even today, software historians are still arguing whether Windows 2.0 deserves to be called a major Windows update. It added dozens of new kernel features, but it barely changed the driver architecture of the system. The mouse and the keyboard drivers for Windows 2 would work fine on Windows 1, and vice versa. The CGA and EGA video drivers from Windows 1 would allow Windows 2 to boot, but could not render the fonts correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A screenshot of Windows 2 for IBM PC with a broken video driver; all text on the screen is garbled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A natural thing to try would be installing Windows 2 with the Apricot drivers for Windows 1. Except that there are no driver files.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you install Windows 1 or 2 on your computer, the SETUP utility combines (links) the driver files with the kernel. It is called "fast boot" and is supposed to improve the boot times of the system. The result of the SETUP is two files, WIN100.BIN and WIN100.OVL. The BIN file is an EXE file in disguise, consisting of the Windows kernel and the system drivers. The OVL file has resources and code that the system uses only from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Windows 1 port of Apricot was only ever distributed with the "fast boot". The individual driver files were not distributed, so we cannot use them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The stub drivers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there are no drivers, we can make some! Microsoft has a Driver Development Kit for Windows, also known as Windows DDK. The DDK comes with the drivers for the IBM PC, meant to be used as a reference for other platforms. With the help of the DDK, I implemented a stub video driver, and somehow got a stub mouse and system drivers. This was enough to confirm that Windows 2, indeed, can start on the Apricot PC without any patches to the kernel. I had my doubts about that, because Windows 2 comes with EMS memory support, and it might have been using something IBM PC-specific to test for it. Thankfully not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A screenshot of Windows 2 booting in the text mode. The file manager application simply dumps the list of files on the screen, without drawing any windows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Trying to write a video driver&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now I could expand the drivers to support the Apricot PC. Keyboard, mouse, and even system drivers are small and simple. The real beast of a driver is DISPLAY.DRV, as it has to implement a large subset of the Windows graphical subsystem. With the reference display drivers, this should not be a problem, as long as the video card supports a graphical mode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the Apricot PC doesn't have a real graphical mode. It has a 50x25 "graphics screen" with a fake 16x16 font. This is a big problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A page of the Apricot technical reference explaining the organisation of the Video RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reference video driver from Microsoft makes many bold assumptions about the way video RAM is organised. With the display initialisation routines corrected, the image produced by the reference driver is still undecipherable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A screenshot of the MAME emulator, running Windows 2 on the Apricot. There are no windows, only stripes of black.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Writing a driver for such a video card is significantly more painful than designing a VGA-compatible video card for the Apricot. Maybe I return to the Apricot display driver project one day (for the Windows 3.0 port), but for now, I have given up on it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Lose the battle, win the war: re-linking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originally, I entertained the idea of unlinking the drivers from the WIN100.BIN/OVL files and reusing them, but rejected it. Not only is it difficult to do, but it is also useless, because the Windows 1 video driver would not display the fonts on the screen under Windows 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But when I hit the roadblock with writing the driver from scratch, I got an idea: what if I use a driver from Windows 1 with fonts from Windows 1? Apparently, this trick works! And so, I decided to abandon the video driver writing if I could somehow extract a video driver from the WIN100.BIN/OVL, because I would not need to reverse-engineer it to patch in the font support; it could work out of the box. But how?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The driver files in WIN100 are not "simply concatenated together": some parts from DISPLAY.DRV ends up in WIN100.BIN, and some in WIN100.OVL. Looking closely at those parts, I realised that the part in WIN100.OVL is identical to the Hercules driver. This gave me an idea: I could get a Hercules video driver; then I could extract CODE and DATA segments along with the Entry Table from the WIN100.BIN, and patch them into the Hercules driver. Unfortunately, not a single NE file format tool supported this use-case. I ended up writing my own tool NExus-relink to assist in this process; the tool is still incomplete, but it gave me enough leverage to finish the job manually.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the video driver, I used a "combine" tool I made for NExus, and then manually patched in the offsets and lengths in the NE header (one for the entry table, two for the segments). Incredibly, this was enough to make Windows 2 happy about the display:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A screenshot of Windows 2 running in the MAME emulator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The same trick worked for the keyboard driver, but the mouse driver gave me a headache. I knew that when the mouse is not found, Windows doesn't display it on the screen, so I kept iterating on the driver, going deeper and deeper. The mouse driver has a relocation table of the OS Fixup type, and there are very few things written about it, so I wasn't sure if the driver was loading correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I confirmed that the interrupt handler of the driver works, and was about to check the kernel source of the corresponding event handler when I discovered that, in fact, the mouse was working fine. It's just that the cursor wasn't displayed on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Windows 1/2, the cursor is handled by the video driver to allow hardware acceleration and "hide cursor before taking a screenshot or drawing a bitmap". So, why is the video driver not drawing the cursor?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Windows DDK documentation has an answer: the mouse cursor drawing routines in the video driver are called by a timer routine, from the SYSTEM.DRV. I told about this to my fiancée, Atsuko, and she said: "Oh, you didn't notice the cursor wasn't blinking?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turns out, the timer routines in the SYSTEM.DRV were broken. The SYSTEM.DRV from Windows 1.0 cannot be used with Windows 2, so I implemented the Apricot PC &lt;code&gt;SYSTEM.DRV&lt;/code&gt; using Windows DDK as a reference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this driver complete, I had Windows 2 working on my Apricot PC/Xi.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Windows 2 for the Apricot PC: a tour&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome, welcome, let me show you around!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am greeted with the AUG logo when I power up my Apricot. I use the AUG BIOS because it supports the upgraded CPU, NEC V30, much better than the original one. Note that my machine has 896 kB of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The PC/Xi comes with a single 720 kB floppy drive and a 10 MB hard drive. I have MS-DOS 3.20 installed on the hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have created a file called `win.bat` that simply starts the kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome to Windows 2. I have GW Basic, Turbo Pascal, Windows 1, Windows 2, Word and Excel installed on the hard drive, and I still have almost 2 megabytes free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PC Paintbrush is one of the few programs that work on both Windows 1 and Windows 2. But it is more stable when running on top of Windows 2. Note that this is not Microsoft Paint **yet**: Microsoft would license this product only for its Windows 3.0 release.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have to remind you that the screen is monochrome. Pixel dithering works really well on a 100 PPI 800x400 display, creating shades of grey from pixel patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The screen is 4:3, so the pixels are not square. I have to pre-process raster images so they would look right on the Apricot's screen. Vector images are fine, though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default shell for Windows 2 is a bit too minimalistic to my taste. WANG's ClearView for Windows 2 brings a familiar to Windows 3 users PROGMAN-like experience to the Apricot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Windows 1 came with tiling windows; Windows 2 uses overlapping windows that quickly become a disorganised mess. ClearView's window manager can arrange the windows for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Windows 2 control panel looks a bit funny in monochrome, but it is a powerful reminder that Windows supports 24-bit colour, which is important for printing and publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A side note: Apricot's keyboard had an LED in the logo before ThinkPad did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The MicroScreen and re-programmable keys are fully supported by the Windows keyboard driver. There is no ALT key, so "Close" is as close as we can get to pressing ALT+f4. Note that there is a hotkey for starting the XENTEL telephone accessory. The XENTEL button is somewhat similar to a Copilot button, except it can actually be useful in some situations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft Word for Windows. Word for DOS, a completely different program, was first released back in 1983. Word for Windows had its first release in late 1989 due to a non-competition agreement with Apple. The success of Word for Windows made Microsoft abandon Word for DOS and Word for Mac; all the new versions of Word were based on this Word.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Word for Windows is surprisingly powerful for a brand-new product. There is a spellchecker, a page layout editor, and even support for macros. I have deleted the macros to save space on the hard drive, so the README file shows "Error!" where the macros were. The files created by Word for Windows 1.0 can be opened by modern office suites if you save as RTF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft Excel is a real must-have. There is no other spreadsheet as powerful as Excel on the Apricot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Excel for Windows from 1988 looks almost exactly like Excel for Windows from 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My previous trip to Japan was planned between Google Docs and Excel for Windows 2 (I had to convert the file back and forth). I needed a few GB of RAM for Google Docs, and only a few hundred kilobytes for Excel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Excel Help is a hidden gem. It is a hypertext application that feels a lot like a web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I used the Help application to see how to create a stonks chart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creating a stonks chart is surprisingly easy. There are 44 chart types, more than many modern programs offer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Until yesterday, Apricot PC had five graphical games: Chess, Where Is The Owl, Windows 1 Reversi, Windows 1 Minesweeper, and Windows 1 Risk. Now there are many more, including a solitaire and a Taipei mahjongg.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's it! There are many Windows 2 programs I have yet to try on the Apricot, but my quest for running modern-ish Word and Excel for Windows is finally over.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Thank you for reading! If you have any questions or comments, please let me know. You can leave a comment in the Mastodon thread about this article.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;My fiancée not only helped with beta-testing, she even designed a RAM expansion board for the Apricot PC/Xi that was necessary to run Windows on it. Love~&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;This project could not exist without advice from Michal Necasek of os2museum and David Simunič of krnl386 regarding drivers for ancient Windows version.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46403915</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 18:22:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rainbow Six Siege hacked as players get billions of credits and random bans</title><link>https://www.shanethegamer.com/esports-news/rainbow-six-siege-hacked-global-server-outage/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e5ff45575e6e7597"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rainbow Six Siege is currently facing a major crisis, with mounting evidence pointing to a large scale hack or exploit, even as Ubisoft continues to describe the situation as a server incident. The disruption has now escalated into full service outages across all platforms, according to Ubisoft’s own service status page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Players across PC and console are being urged by the community to stay offline, as reports continue to surface of accounts receiving billions of in game credits, rare and developer only skins, and experiencing random bans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;BREAKING: Ubisoft Rainbow Six Siege servers have been breached.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Players are reporting massive amounts of R6 Credits, Renown, Alpha Packs, and exclusive items unexpectedly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Numerous accounts even Ubisoft, including streamers’ and possibly official ones, have received random or… pic.twitter.com/9hGNbBCMAm&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;— Pirat_Nation 🔴 (@Pirat_Nation) December 27, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Ubisoft Confirms Widespread Outages Across All Platforms&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The official service status page for Rainbow Six Siege now shows critical issues across every major platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On PC, PS4, PS5, Xbox One, and Xbox Series X|S, core services including authentication, in game store access, and matchmaking are all listed as being in outage, while overall connectivity is marked as degraded. Ubisoft states that issues are being investigated, but has not provided a timeline for recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scale of the outages has further fuelled claims that this is far more serious than routine server instability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Ubisoft’s Statement Draws Heavy Criticism&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earlier, the official Rainbow Six account acknowledged that it was aware of an incident affecting the game and said teams were working on a resolution. No mention was made of a security breach, hack, or exploit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We’re aware of an incident currently affecting Rainbow Six Siege. Our teams are working on a resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We will share further updates once available.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;— Rainbow Six Siege X (@Rainbow6Game) December 27, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That wording has been met with heavy backlash from players, many of whom believe Ubisoft is attempting to downplay the severity of the situation. Community responses have accused the publisher of calling it a server issue while core systems appear compromised.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some players also questioned why the game remained online for hours while accounts were being altered in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Players Report Billions of Credits, Dev Skins, and Ban Chaos&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the incident unfolded, players reported logging in to find their accounts flooded with billions of R6 Credits and Renown, thousands of Alpha Packs, and access to exclusive cosmetics such as developer skins and Glaciers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Why is nobody talking about what is happening on Siege right now? Everyone that logs in gets 2 Billion R6 credits, Renown, Developer Skins and Glaciers 😭 pic.twitter.com/9SBiLdrirm&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;— Terd (@Terdsta) December 27, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were also widespread claims that the in game ban feed had been taken over, displaying arbitrary messages. Thousands of accounts were reportedly banned and unbanned at random, including those belonging to streamers and high profile players.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rainbow Six is fucked pic.twitter.com/OZpDXzttOZ&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;— Pirat_Nation 🔴 (@Pirat_Nation) December 27, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prominent Siege creator KingGeorge described the situation as completely broken, warning players not to log in and strongly advising against spending any currency, as it could lead to bans or rollbacks once Ubisoft regains control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Btw as a side note I would not login right now, definitely don’t spend any credits or renown could lead to a ban.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;— KingGeorge (@KingGeorge) December 27, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Community Expects Rollbacks, Fears Punishment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With authentication and account systems affected, many players now expect Ubisoft to roll accounts back to a previous state. However, fears remain that innocent players could still face penalties, especially those who unknowingly spent credits thinking the issue was a visual glitch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Others argue that banning a significant portion of the active player base would be disastrous, adding further pressure on Ubisoft to handle the aftermath carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lack of clear communication has only intensified frustration, with players demanding transparency about what actually happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Players Should Do Right Now&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Until Ubisoft confirms the issue is fully resolved and explains the cause, players are strongly advised to stay offline, avoid logging in, and do not spend any credits or Renown if access is restored.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Rainbow Six Siege’s core services offline worldwide and player accounts potentially compromised, this incident could have lasting implications for the game if not handled properly. Ubisoft is expected to provide further updates as its investigation continues.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46404597</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 19:45:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How we lost communication to entertainment</title><link>https://ploum.net/2025-12-15-communication-entertainment.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6d901f930c208a99"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How We Lost Communication to Entertainment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by Ploum on 2025-12-15&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;All our communication channels are morphed into content distribution networks. We are more and more entertained but less and less connected.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I did a controversial blog post about Pixelfed hurting the Fediverse. I defended the theory that, in a communication network, you hurt the trust in the whole network if you create clients that arbitrarily drop messages, something that Pixelfed is doing deliberately. It gathered a lot of reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I originally wrote this post, nearly one year ago, I thought that either I was missing something or Dansup, Pixelfed’s creator, was missing it. We could not both be right. But as the reactions piled in on the Fediverse, I realised that such irreconcilable opinions do not arise only from ignorance or oversight. It usually means that both parties have vastly different assumptions about the world. They don’t live in the same world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Two incompatible universes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started to see a pattern in the two kinds of reactions to my blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were people like me, often above 40, who like sending emails and browsing old-fashioned websites. We think of ActivityPub as a "communication protocol" between humans. As such, anything that implies losing messages without feedback is the worst thing that could happen. Not losing messages is the top priority of a communication protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then there are people like Dansup, who believe that ActivityPub is a content consumption protocol. It’s there for entertainment. You create as many accounts as the kinds of media you want to consume. Dansup himself is communicating through a Mastodon account, not a Pixelfed one. Many Pixelfed users also have a Mastodon account, and they never questioned that. They actually want multiple accounts for different use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the Fediverse threads, nearly all the people defending the Pixelfed philosophy posted from Mastodon accounts. They usually boasted about having both a Mastodon and a Pixelfed account.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A multiplicity of accounts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To me, the very goal of interoperability is not to force you into creating multiple accounts. Big Monopolies have managed to convince people that they need one account on each platform. This was done, on purpose, for purely unethical reasons in order to keep users captive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That brainwash/marketing is so deeply entrenched that most people cannot see an alternative anymore. It looks like a natural law: you need an account on a platform to communicate with someone on that platform. That also explains why most politicians want to "regulate" Facebook or X. They think it is impossible not to be on those platforms. They believe those platforms are "public spaces" while they truly are "private spaces trying to destroy all other public spaces in order to get a monopoly."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People flock to the Fediverse with this philosophy of "one platform, one account", which makes no sense if you truly want to create a federated communication protocol like email or XMPP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Manuel Moreale cracked it for me: the Fediverse is not a communication network. ActivityPub is not a communication protocol. The spec says it: ActivityPub is a protocol to build a "social platform" whose goal is "to deliver content."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;The ActivityPub protocol is a decentralised social networking protocol based upon the ActivityStreams 2.0 data format. It provides a client to server API for creating, updating and deleting content, as well as a federated server-to-server API for delivering notifications and content. (official W3C definition of ActivityPub)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;No more communication&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But aren’t social networks also communication networks? That’s what I thought. That’s how they historically were marketed. That’s what we all believed during the "Arab Spring."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But that was a lie. Communication networks are not profitable. Social networks are entertainment platforms, media consumption protocols. Historically, they disguised themselves as communication platforms to attract users and keep them captive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The point was never to avoid missing a message sent from a fellow human being. The point was always to fill your time with "content."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We dreamed of decentralised social networks as "email 2.0." They truly are "television 2.0."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They are entertainment platforms that delegate media creation to the users themselves the same way Uber replaced taxis by having people drive others in their own car.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what was created as "ride-sharing" was in fact a way to 1) destroy competition and 2) make a shittier service while people producing the work were paid less and lost labour rights. It was never about the social!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The lost messages&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My own interpretation is that social media users don’t mind losing messages because they were raised on algorithmic platforms that did that all the time. They don’t see the point in trusting a platform because they never experienced a trusted means of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that I write it, it may also explain why instant messaging became the dominant communication medium: because if you don’t receive an immediate answer, you don’t even trust the recipient to have received your messages. In fact, even if the message was received, you don’t even trust the recipient's attention span to remember the message.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiple studies have confirmed that we don’t remember the vast majority of what we see while doomscrolling. While the "view" was registered to increase statistics, we don’t have the slightest memory of most of that content, even after only a few seconds. It thus makes sense not to consider social media as a means of communication at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s no need for a reliable communication protocol if we assume that human brains are not reliable enough to handle asynchronous messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not Dansup who is missing something. It is me who is unadapted to the current society. I understand now that Pixelfed was only following some design decisions and protocol abuses fathered by Mastodon. Pixelfed was my own "gotcha" moment because I never understood Instagram in the first place, and, in my eyes, Pixelfed was no better. But if you take that route, Mastodon is no better than Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many reactions pointed, justly, that other Fediverse tools such as PeerTube, WriteFreely, or Mobilizon were just not displaying messages at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I didn’t consider it a big problem because they never pretended to do it in the first place. Nobody uses those tools to follow others. There’s no expectation. Those platforms are "publish only." But this is still a big flaw in the Fediverse! Someone could, using autocompletion, send a message pinging your PeerTube address and you will never see it. Try autocomplete "@ploum" from your Mastodon account and guess which suggestion is the only one that will send me a valid notification!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a more positive note, I should give credit to Dansup for announcing that Pixelfed will soon allow people to optionally "not drop" text messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How we lost email&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I cling to asynchronous reliable communications, but those are disappearing. I use email a lot because I see it as a true means of communication: reliable, asynchronous, decentralised, standardised, manageable offline with my own tools. But many people, even barely younger than me, tell me that email is "too formal" or "for old people" or "even worse than social network feeds."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And they are probably right. I like it because I’ve learned to use it. I apply a strong inbox 0 methodology. If I don’t reply or act on your email, it is because I decided not to. I’m actively keeping my inbox clean by sharing only disposable email addresses that I disable once they start to be spammed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But for most people, their email inbox is simply one more feed full of bad advertising. They have 4 or 5 digit unread count. They scroll through their inbox like they do through their social media feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Boringness of communications&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The main problem with reliable communication protocols? It is a mostly solved problem. Build simple websites, read RSS feeds, write emails. Use IRC and XMPP if you truly want real-time communication. Those are working and working great.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And because of that, they are boring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Communications protocols are boring. They don’t give you that well-studied random hit of dopamine. They don’t make you addicted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They don’t make you addicted which means they are not hugely profitable and thus are not advertised. They are not new. They are not as shiny as a new app or a new random chatbot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem with communication protocols was never the protocol part. It’s the communication part. A few sad humans never wanted to communicate in the first place and managed to become billionaires by convincing the rest of mankind that being entertained is better than communicating with other humans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;As long as I’m not alone&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe that a communication network must reach a critical mass to be really useful. People stay on Facebook to "stay in touch with the majority." I don’t believe that lie anymore. I’m falling back to good old mailing lists. I’m reading the Web and Gemini while offline through Offpunk. I also handle my emails asynchronously while offline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Offpunk, an offline-first command-line browser (offpunk.net)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There Is No Content on Gemini (ploum.net)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I may be part of an endangered species.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter. I made peace with the fact that I will never get in touch with everyone. As long as there are people posting on their gemlogs or blogs with RSS feeds, as long as there are people willing to read my emails without automatically summarising them, there will be a place for those who want to simply communicate. A protected reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are welcome to join!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Illustration of a message board piled with messages by David Revoy (CC By 4.0)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Illustration of animal meeting at an intersection with messages by David Revoy (CC By 4.0)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m Ploum, a writer and an engineer. I like to explore how technology impacts society. You can subscribe by email or by rss. I value privacy and never share your adress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I write science-fiction novels in French. For Bikepunk, my new post-apocalyptic-cyclist book, my publisher is looking for contacts in other countries to distribute it in languages other than French. If you can help, contact me!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46404848</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 20:15:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Public Domain Day 2026</title><link>https://web.law.duke.edu/cspd/publicdomainday/2026/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="aaf801d9dcba12b7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Public Domain Day 2026&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;January 1, 2026 is Public Domain Day: Works from 1930 are open to all, as are sound recordings from 1925!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By Jennifer Jenkins and James Boyle[1]&lt;lb/&gt; CC BY 4.0&lt;lb/&gt; Please note that this site is only about US law; the copyright terms in other countries are different.[2]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On January 1, 2026, thousands of copyrighted works from 1930 enter the US public domain, along with sound recordings from 1925. They will be free for all to copy, share, and build upon.[3] The literary highlights range from William Faulkner’s As I Lay Dying to Agatha Christie’s The Murder at the Vicarage and the first four Nancy Drew novels. From cartoons and comic strips, the characters Betty Boop, Pluto (originally named Rover), and Blondie and Dagwood made their first appearances. Films from the year featured Marlene Dietrich, Greta Garbo, the Marx Brothers, and John Wayne in his first leading role. Among the public domain compositions are I Got Rhythm, Georgia on My Mind, and Dream a Little Dream of Me. We are also celebrating paintings from Piet Mondrian and Paul Klee. Below you can find lists of some of the most notable books, characters, comics, and cartoons, films, songs, sound recordings, and art entering the public domain.[4] After each of them, we have provided an analysis of their significance. At the end of the article, we explain:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why all of this matters&lt;lb/&gt; How do copyright and trademark law apply to characters?&lt;lb/&gt; What is the impact of the long copyright term?&lt;lb/&gt; What are the basic rules for determining whether something is public domain?&lt;lb/&gt; Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;BOOKS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;William Faulkner, As I Lay Dying&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dashiell Hammett, The Maltese Falcon (the full book version)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Agatha Christie, The Murder at the Vicarage (the first novel featuring Miss Marple)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Carolyn Keene (pseudonym for Mildred Benson), the first four Nancy Drew books, beginning with The Secret of the Old Clock&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Watty Piper (pen name of Arnold Munk), The Little Engine That Could (the popular illustrated version, with drawings by Lois Lenski)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;William H. Elson, Elson Basic Readers (the first appearances of Dick and Jane)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Noël Coward, Private Lives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;T.S. Eliot, Ash Wednesday&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Evelyn Waugh, Vile Bodies&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;John Dos Passos, The 42nd Parallel&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Edna Ferber, Cimarron&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dorothy L. Sayers, Strong Poison&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;J. B. Priestley, Angel Pavement&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Olaf Stapledon, Last and First Men&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sigmund Freud, Civilization and Its Discontents (in the original German, Das Unbehagen in der Kultur)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Elizabeth Coatsworth (author) and Lynd Ward (illustrator), The Cat Who Went to Heaven&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Arthur Ransome, Swallows and Amazons&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;W. Somerset Maugham, Cakes and Ale&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bertrand Russell, The Conquest of Happiness&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is just a small selection from the thousands of books and plays entering the public domain in 2026. The famous works include modernist masterpieces, detective stories, a science-fiction classic, an early self-help book, and a seminal work on psychoanalysis. All of them and thousands more will be copyright-free in the US. The newly public domain corpus also includes a wealth of children’s and young adult fiction—the first four Nancy Drew books, the introduction of the characters Dick and Jane, a Newbery Award winner about the life of The Buddha, and the popular illustrated version of The Little Engine That Could.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Works from 1930 are not only enriching the public domain; they also illustrate its value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I have an idea that the only thing which makes it possible to regard this world we live in without disgust is the beauty which now and then men create out of the chaos. The pictures they paint, the music they compose, the books they write, and the lives they lead. Of all these the richest in beauty is the beautiful life. That is the perfect work of art.” –W. Somerset Maugham&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is a quote from W. Somerset Maugham, whose novel Cakes and Ale is entering the public domain in 2026. But artists don’t merely create “beauty…out of the chaos,” though our current moment has lots of the latter. They create beauty by drawing on our shared culture. Look at Maugham’s title: “Cakes and Ale.” Maugham himself was referring to a classic public domain work, in this case Shakespeare’s Twelfth Night. “Dost thou think, because thou art virtuous, there shall be no more cakes and ale?” says Sir Toby Belch reprovingly to his pompous Puritan steward Malvolio, who is always eager to judge the behavior of others. Maugham reuses the line precisely to make the same point about puritanical moralizing and, in the case of his novel, artistic hypocrisy. The narrator is disgusted by the snobbery and judgmental attitudes of his contemporaries towards Rosie Driffield, a former barmaid who became the wife of a famous fictional novelist. Rosie came from a working-class background and was forthright, without pretension, and sexually free. She is now decried for those qualities, but the narrator finds her far more impressive than the bourgeois scolds who disdain her. The title reaches back 330 years to show that one of our greatest playwrights was mocking faux puritanism in exactly the same way. Maugham's point is that the human race relives those moments and emotions in every era; the desire to moralize is always with us. Now his work is in the public domain and we, too, can reuse his insights and artistry to create new art.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The same point holds true for many of the other works entering the public domain this year. The title of Faulkner’s As I Lay Dying came from Homer’s Odyssey. The public domain contains far more than works with expired copyrights—names, titles, and very short phrases are not copyrightable standing alone and are therefore public domain in the US; one does not have to wait for the expiration of the copyright term. But when works enter the public domain, the artistic freedom granted over them is far greater. Plot, characters, images, vignettes; all can now be mined for future inspiration. And that, too, was true in the past just as it is now. The tale of the tenacious little engine that pulls the train over the mountain had been circulating in various forms before the Watty Piper version, or the predecessor it credits.[5] To tell new stories, we draw from older ones. One work of art inspires another – that is how the public domain feeds creativity. Why care about the public domain? That is one reason why.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;CHARACTERS, COMICS, CARTOONS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Betty Boop from Fleischer Studios' Dizzy Dishes and other cartoons&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rover (later renamed Pluto) from Disney's The Chain Gang (as an unnamed bloodhound) and The Picnic (as Rover)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Blondie and Dagwood from the Blondie comic strips by Chic Young&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Flip the Frog from Fiddlesticks and other cartoons, by Ub Iwerks after he left Disney&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Nine new Mickey Mouse cartoons, the initial week of Mickey Mouse comic strips, and ten new Silly Symphonies cartoons from Disney&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Betty Boop was introduced in the Fleischer Studios’ wonderful cartoon Dizzy Dishes, set in a restaurant full of anthropomorphic animals. She is instantly recognizable, with the familiar flapper girl appearance, pouting lips, enormous doe eyes, tiny button nose, and kiss-curls. She even sings her high-pitched “Boop Oop A Doop” tagline—but in a characteristic Fleischer touch of surrealism she has elongated dog ears (similar in shape to her later hoop earrings) and facial expressions that morph between human and animalistic. Betty’s boyfriend-to-be is a dog-chef called Bimbo, who serenades her on a duck that transforms into a guitar, while the restaurant clientele and staff include a fantastical menagerie of animals. The vibe is decidedly trippy: duck-guitars, lovestruck dog-chefs, dancing flapper cats, and needy gorillas. Betty is remarkably sexy. But, because she was designed as a girlfriend for Bimbo, she also has dog ears. The dissonance fits the setting. By contrast, Disney’s character Rover, later renamed Pluto, inhabits a world in The Picnic that is both cuter and more normal—Rover licks Mickey with unbridled enthusiasm, chases rabbits, and provides Mickey and Minnie with comedic canine companionship.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The contrast between the Fleischer and Disney aesthetics is fascinating. Max Fleischer once said, “If it can be done in real life, it isn’t animation.” Dizzy Dishes certainly does not disappoint. As described by the late Charles Silver, who ran MoMA’s Film Study Center, “Disney was based in Los Angeles and reflected the ‘wholesome’ mid-American values of Uncle Walt’s Kansas City roots. Fleischer’s New York product was more sophisticated and cosmopolitan…Broadly speaking, there was an innocence in Disney’s view of the world, while Fleischer projected an underlying kinkiness.” Our colleague Casey Herbert, who teaches cartoon history at Duke, put it this way: “Max and Dave Fleischer’s characters were drawn from the urban environment they knew so well. Vaudeville, dance-halls, diners, drinking and drugs were routinely part of the hallucinogenic mayhem…On the other hand, Walt, his brother Roy, and best friend Ub Iwerks, the core of the early Disney enterprises, all had roots in rural middle America. With upbeat music and clever solutions, mechanical and animal troubles of all sorts were resolved with a simple, can-do attitude that Mickey and his pals exude.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As more of Disney’s and Fleischer’s classic works enter the public domain, it is worth reflecting on how deeply their styles are embedded in the DNA of today’s animation. Now, entering 2026, we look back and think it inevitable that one genre of cartoons will be cutesy and folksy, with slapstick humor and an upbeat vibe, while another will use the unparalleled artistic freedom afforded by the cartoon medium to explore a distinctly more surreal worldview, sensual and trippy, with wild nightlife and mind-bending transformations. Looking back to 1930, we can find the progenitors of both, and see how the traditions began to diverge. Indeed, it is striking how “edgily modern” some of the Fleischer cartoons feel. To look into each year’s newly public domain crop is to open a time-capsule that offers fresh insights about our culture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As with Mickey Mouse, Popeye, and Winnie-the-Pooh, it is the original 1930 iterations of Betty Boop and Rover/Pluto that are entering the public domain. Newer, different versions of the characters are still copyrighted, and trademark rights still cover the character names and designs when they are used on merchandise as brand signifiers. The rules are complex and explored in more detail here, with their application to Betty Boop discussed here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the other highlights from 1930 are additional Mickey Mouse comic strips and cartoons, in which the famous mouse continues to develop, and the comic strip Blondie, featuring early versions of Blondie and Dagwood. In 1930 they are not yet married, and Dagwood has not yet discovered his signature sandwich.[6] Blondie’s maiden name is Boopadoop—similar to Betty Boop’s scat-singing catchphrase, which in turn echoed the phrase associated with the singer and actress Helen Kane and has been traced back to the African-American jazz performer “Baby” Esther Lee Jones. (Kane actually sued the Fleischers for appropriating the phrase, along with her persona and singing style. In response, the Fleischers claimed that Kane had copied those attributes from Esther Jones. The judge ruled against Kane. Based on the reports we can find, the accuracy of the specific claims and counterclaims is unclear, but accounts of Boop's creation indicate that the character was based at least partly on Kane.)[7]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;FILMS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All Quiet on the Western Front, directed by Lewis Milestone (winner of the Academy Award for Best Picture)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;King of Jazz, directed by John Murray Anderson (musical revue featuring Paul Whiteman and Bing Crosby’s first feature-film appearance)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cimarron, directed by Wesley Ruggles (winner of the Academy Award for Best Picture, registered for copyright in 1930)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Animal Crackers, directed by Victor Heerman (starring the Marx Brothers)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Soup to Nuts, directed by Benjamin Stoloff (written by Rube Goldberg, featuring later members of The Three Stooges)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Morocco, directed by Josef von Sternberg (starring Gary Cooper, Marlene Dietrich, and Adolphe Menjou)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Blue Angel (Der blaue Engel), directed by Josef von Sternberg (starring Marlene Dietrich)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anna Christie, directed by Clarence Brown (Greta Garbo’s first talkie)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hell's Angels, directed by Howard Hughes (Jean Harlow’s film debut)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Big Trail, directed by Raoul Walsh (John Wayne’s first leading role)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Big House, directed by George Hill&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Murder!, directed by Alfred Hitchcock&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;L'Âge d'Or, directed by Luis Buñuel, written by Buñuel and Salvador Dalí&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Free and Easy, directed by Edward Sedgwick (Buster Keaton’s first speaking role)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Divorcee, directed by Robert Z. Leonard&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Whoopee!, directed by Thornton Freeland&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;War films, musicals, thrillers, Westerns, comedies, surrealist satires—this year’s newly public domain films run the gamut. They feature familiar actors: Marlene Dietrich, Greta Garbo, John Wayne, the Marx Brothers, and the film debut of Moe Howard and Larry Fine, who would later be long-running members of The Three Stooges. There are also familiar names among the directors and writers: Alfred Hitchcock, Howard Hughes, and even Rube Goldberg and Salvador Dalí.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These films predated the enactment of the 1934-1968 “Hays Code” that censored profanity, criminal activity, “indecent” dance costumes, and sexual content such as “excessive and lustful kissing, lustful embraces, suggestive postures and gestures.” In Morocco, Marlene Dietrich, handsomely dressed in a top hat and tails, famously kisses another woman. King of Jazz features the sequence “I Like to Do Things For You,” described on Wikipedia as “humorously sadomasochistic.” Pre-Code Betty Boop was overtly seductive. As critic Gabrielle Bellot wrote: “On the one hand, Betty Boop was a creation of the heterosexual male gaze, with an endless parade of lecherous male characters trying to see under her skirt, yet on the other hand she wore power like a light shawl, her image an in-your-face depiction of unashamed sexuality.”[8] Post-Code Betty Boop covered her shoulders and garter. As with Maugham’s Rosie from Cakes and Ale, frank female sexuality was not to be tolerated. Malvolio would have liked the Hays Code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the scenes from these films are eerily resonant today. In King of Jazz, a man gets drunk and stammers: “You know what’s the matter with this country? It’s a tariff! That’s who!”, referring to the 1930 Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act that deepened the Great Depression. Today, there is a lot of debate about whether the public knows enough about the importance of the rule of law and the protections of due process. At the end of Animal Crackers, Groucho and Chico Marx (as Captain Spaulding and Ravelli) have this exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Groucho: “We go to court and get a writ of habeas corpus.”&lt;lb/&gt; Chico: “You gonna get rid of what?”&lt;lb/&gt; Groucho: “Haven’t you ever heard of habeas corpus?”&lt;lb/&gt; Chico: “No, but I’ve heard of ‘Habie’s Irish Rose’.”&lt;lb/&gt; Groucho sighs in exasperation and walks away&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Faulkner, the author whose novel begins this year’s list of books, wrote: “The past is never dead. It’s not even past.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cimarron is featured even though it was released in 1931 because it was copyrighted in 1930 and the earlier date controls (date discrepancies are resolved “in favor of the public”). Please note that only the original films from 1930 are public domain; later versions might have newly added material that is still copyrighted. If a film has been restored or reconstructed, only original and creative additions are eligible for copyright; if a restoration faithfully mimics the preexisting film, it does not contain newly copyrightable material. Putting skill, labor, and money into a project is not enough to qualify it for copyright, and the Supreme Court has made clear that “the sine qua non of copyright is originality.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What about the music in the films? We are in the era when “talkies” – movies with sound – were new. As with other works, the statutory copyright terms for this music began either upon “publication” or copyright registration. If musical works were previously unpublished or unregistered and first appeared in a film from 1930, the general rule is that the music was published along with the film and is also public domain in 2026. (The same is true of the "sounds accompanying a motion picture," discussed below.) In other circumstances, however, a film and its underlying music may have different copyright terms. If a song was copyrighted separately before the film, for example, the song would have entered the public domain earlier than the film, after its own 95-year term. Conversely, if the copyright in the song was renewed while the copyright in the film was not, the song remained copyrighted after the film went into the public domain. This happened with It’s A Wonderful Life (1946)—the movie’s copyright was not renewed but the soundtrack’s copyright was, so the movie was public domain while the soundtrack and underlying short story were not. But if musical works made their first appearance in a film and the film rights were renewed, then the prevailing view is that the movie and music enter the public domain at the same time.[9]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;MUSICAL COMPOSITIONS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Four Songs - I Got Rhythm, I've Got a Crush on You, But Not for Me, and Embraceable You - with lyrics by Ira Gershwin, music by George Gershwin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Georgia on My Mind, lyrics by Stuart Gorrell, music by Hoagy Carmichael&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dream a Little Dream of Me, lyrics by Gus Kahn, music by Fabian Andre and Wilbur Schwandt&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Livin' in the Sunlight, Lovin' in the Moonlight, lyrics by Al Lewis, music by Al Sherman&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;On the Sunny Side of the Street, lyrics by Dorothy Fields, music by Jimmy McHugh&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It Happened in Monterey, lyrics by Billy Rose, music by Mabel Wayne&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Body and Soul, lyrics by Edward Heyman, Robert Sour, Frank Eyton, music by Johnny Green&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Just a Gigolo (the first English translation), original German lyrics by Julius Brammer, English translation by Irving Caesar, music by Leonello Casucci&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You're Driving Me Crazy, lyrics and music by Walter Donaldson&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Beyond the Blue Horizon, lyrics by Leo Robin, music by Richard A. Whiting and W. Franke Harling (possible inspiration for the Star Trek theme song)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Royal Welch Fusiliers, by John Philip Sousa&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1930 brought us enduring jazz standards and popular songs. From George and Ira Gershwin came I Got Rhythm, the source of the foundational jazz chord progression known as the “rhythm changes,” and But Not for Me, memorably featured in the film When Harry Met Sally (RIP Rob Reiner). You might still find yourself humming the classics Georgia on My Mind and Dream a Little Dream of Me today. Just A Gigolo offered an early, melancholy take on the proverbial player who’s “gonna play, play, play.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only the musical compositions—the music and lyrics that you might see on a piece of sheet music—are entering the public domain, not the recordings of those songs, which are covered by a separate copyright with a different term of protection. The lyrics and music to Georgia on My Mind and Livin’ in the Sunlight, Lovin’ in the Moonlight were published in 1930 and will be free for anyone to copy, perform, record, adapt, or interpolate into their own song.[10] But the later recordings by Ray Charles and by Tiny Tim are still copyrighted. (Readers may remember the Tiny Tim recording from the first episode of SpongeBob SquarePants—that episode had to be omitted from the first season DVD because the rights were not cleared with Tiny Tim’s estate.) Sound recording rights are more limited than composition rights, however. You can legally imitate a sound recording – should you be able to channel Tiny Tim’s signature falsetto – even if your imitation sounds exactly the same, you just cannot copy from the actual recording.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Calculating the copyright term for these early songs can be tricky. Under the law at the time, the copyright clock only started ticking when songs were published in sheet music form, not merely released as recordings. Even though Mood Indigo came out in 1930, the sheet music was not published until 1931, so it will not be in the public domain until 2027. If works were registered for copyright and published in different years, the earlier date controls. So copyright lapses over Dream a Little Dream of Me in 2026 because its copyright was registered in 1930, even though it was not published until 1931.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;SOUND RECORDINGS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Nobody Knows the Trouble I've Seen, recorded by Marian Anderson&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Yes Sir, That's My Baby, recorded by Gene Austin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sweet Georgia Brown, recorded by Ben Bernie and His Hotel Roosevelt Orchestra&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You've Been A Good Old Wagon, recorded by Bessie Smith&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The St. Louis Blues, recorded by Bessie Smith, featuring Louis Armstrong&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fascinating Rhythm, recorded by the Paul Whiteman Orchestra&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I'll See You in My Dreams, recorded by Isham Jones, with Ray Miller’s Orchestra&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Everybody Loves My Baby (but My Baby Don't Love Nobody but Me), recorded by Clarence Williams’ Blue Five&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If I Lose, Let me Lose (Mama Don't Mind), recorded by Louis Armstrong, Fletcher Henderson, and Maggie Jones&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A Cup of Coffee, A Sandwich and You, recorded by the Carleton Terrace Orchestra&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Manhattan, recorded by The Knickerbockers (Ben Selvin and his Orchestra)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the 2018 Music Modernization Act, recordings from 1925 will be open for legal reuse after the conclusion of a 100-year term. There are some incredible performances: the civil rights icon Marian Anderson singing Nobody Knows the Trouble I’ve Seen in her haunting contralto, and The St. Louis Blues recorded by Bessie Smith and Louis Armstrong. Only the 1925 recordings made by these artists are entering the public domain, not their later recordings. To listen to old recordings, you can go to the Library of Congress National Jukebox.[11]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sound recordings within a movie are treated differently from separate sound recordings because copyright law’s definition of “sound recording” specifically excludes “sounds accompanying a motion picture.” So the 1930 recordings as they appeared in the film King of Jazz have the same copyright term as the movie and are public domain in 2026, while regular sound recordings from 1930 that were independent of motion pictures have the 100-year term and their copyrights won’t expire until 2031.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;ART&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Piet Mondrian, Composition with Red, Blue, and Yellow&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Abel Lafleur, the Jules Rimet Cup (the original trophy of the FIFA World Cup, also known as the Victory Trophy or Coupe du Monde)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Edward Steichen, Fashion for Vogue, October 27, 1930&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Paul Klee, Tierfreundschaft (Animal Friendship)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;José Clemente Orozco, Prometheus&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sophie Taeuber-Arp, Composition of Circles and Overlapping Angles&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Theo Van Doesburg, Simultaneous Counter-Composition&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Copyright will also expire in 2026 over works of art that were published or registered in 1930, reflecting artistic movements ranging from Art Deco to Constructivism and Neoplasticism. In the traumatic years of World War I, Paul Klee wrote that “the more horrifying this world becomes, the more art becomes abstract.” Artists such as Klee, Mondrian, Taeuber-Arp, and van Doesburg abstracted the world around them: stylizing, simplifying, flattening, and deconstructing. But the artists on our list also include José Clemente Orozco, whose intensely realistic Prometheus was described by Jackson Pollock as “the greatest painting in North America,” and Edward Steichen, who went on to revolutionize minimalism in commercial fashion photography.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Determining the copyright status of older artworks is challenging. They are only public domain in 2026 if they were “published” as defined by copyright law in 1930, and it is often unclear when exactly publication occurred.[12] The rules are murky and “published” is a legal term of art that was not well-defined. Generally the law looks at whether the art was genuinely released to the public by being exhibited without restrictions on copying, circulated in a magazine or catalogue with authorization, or offered for sale to the public. If it was created but remained only in the artist’s studio or shown only to a limited group, this did not count. But artistic records from almost 100 years ago are difficult to find. Our tireless research assistant Jason Rosenberg spent months contacting experts and combing through exhibition catalogues, museum archives, journals, catalogue raisonnés, provenance indexes, auction records, and biographies to confirm whether the highlighted works were published in 1930.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are other legal wrinkles too. Works by US artists had to comply with copyright “formalities,” including initial publication with a copyright notice and renewal after 28 years, to enjoy the full 95-year term. This is why American Gothic – which is from 1930 – is not on our list; it was by an American artist, Grant Wood, and entered the public domain in 1958 when its copyright was not renewed. Foreign authors such as Mondrian and Klee are treated differently—because of a 1996 provision that restored copyright over certain foreign works, they are eligible for the full term without notice or renewal. For such authors, the question is whether their works were actually “published” in 1930.[13]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may see reports that the Chrysler building is entering the public domain in 2026 because it was constructed in 1930. The building was reportedly scrubbed from the 2023 Spider-Man 2 video game because of a copyright claim. However, there is no legal basis for such a claim. US copyright law only covers buildings created on or after December 1, 1990, when protection was first extended to architectural works. And even with newer copyrighted buildings, the law allows “pictorial representations of the work, if the building in which the work is embodied is located in or ordinarily visible from a public place.” So if the Spider-Man story is true, it would be an example of copyright overreach or overly cautious avoidance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a short video celebrating the works entering the public domain in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep reading to learn more about the public domain! You can use the links below to jump to the answers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why celebrate the public domain?&lt;lb/&gt; How do copyright and trademark law apply to characters?&lt;lb/&gt; What is the impact of the long copyright term?&lt;lb/&gt; What are the basic rules for determining whether something is public domain?&lt;lb/&gt; Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;WHY CELEBRATE THE PUBLIC DOMAIN&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When works go into the public domain, they can legally be shared, without permission or fee. Community theaters can screen the films. Youth orchestras can perform the music publicly, without paying licensing fees. Online repositories such as the Internet Archive, HathiTrust, Google Books, and the New York Public Library can make works fully available online. This helps enable both access to and preservation of cultural materials that might otherwise be lost to history. 1930 was a long time ago and the vast majority of works from that year are not commercially available. You couldn’t buy them, or even find them, if you wanted. When they enter the public domain in 2026, anyone can rescue them from obscurity and make them available, where we can all discover, enjoy, and breathe new life into them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The public domain is also a wellspring for creativity. You could think of it as the yin to copyright’s yang. Copyright law gives authors important rights that encourage creativity and distribution—this is a very good thing. But the United States Constitution requires that those rights last only for a “limited time,” so that when they expire, works go into the public domain, where future authors can legally build on the past—reimagining the books, making them into films, adapting the songs and movies. That’s a good thing too! It is part of copyright’s ecosystem. The point of copyright is to promote creativity, and the public domain plays a central role in doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court explained: “The copyright term is limited so that the public will not be permanently deprived of the fruits of an artist’s labors.” To quote Justice Joseph Story, this benefits the public by “admitting the people at large, after a short interval, to the full possession and enjoyment of all writings . . . without restraint.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How does the public domain feed creativity? Here are just a few current illustrations. In 2025 you may have enjoyed Guillermo del Toro’s Frankenstein, derived from Mary Shelley’s novel, or Wicked: For Good, derived from L. Frank Baum’s The Wonderful Wizard of Oz. Perhaps you are looking forward to Christopher Nolan’s forthcoming epic IMAX version of The Odyssey, Wuthering Heights starring Margot Robbie as Catherine Earnshaw, or Lear Rex, a new version of King Lear starring Al Pacino as Lear. The Great Gatsby entered the public domain in 2021 and has already spawned a number of creative reworkings. 2025 saw others join them. We had The Gatsby Gambit, The Great Mann, Local Heavens, and Mrs. Wilson's Affair: A Great Gatsby Retelling. Clearly, this is a public domain work on which today's novelists have been feasting. Shakespeare, Dickens, and Austen continue to spawn adaptations too, including a reimagining of Hamlet in present-day London, A Far Better Thing (A Tale of Two Cities with fairy changelings), and The Season of Dragons (Pride and Prejudice and dragons). We haven't yet read it, but very much hope it contains the line, "It is a truth universally acknowledged, that a single dragon in possession of a good hoard of treasure, must be in want of a wife."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The works we are celebrating from 1930 also illustrate how the public domain nurtures creativity. Once again, a fine exemplar is Disney, whose beloved works, from Snow White and Cinderella to The Jungle Book and Sleeping Beauty, have consistently built upon the public domain. That was as true in 1930 as it is today. The Mickey Mouse cartoons from 1930 made ingenious reuse of public domain music. Here are some of the public domain songs from these works: Morning, Night and Noon in Vienna by Franz von Suppé (1844), the William Tell Overture by Gioachino Rossini (1829), Orphée aux Enfers by Jacques Offenbach (1858), A Hunting We Will Go by Thomas Arne (1777), Oh Susanna and Old Folks at Home/Swanee River by Stephen Foster (1848, 1851), The Farmer in the Dell (1820s) and Pop Goes the Weasel (1850s) (traditionals), and a tune known as the Snake Charmer Song (1840s). All of these compositions date from before 1880, when the maximum copyright term was 42 years, and could be freely used in 1930 animations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes people worry that entry into the public domain could mean the desecration of a beloved character or plot. Yes, inevitably there will be those who capitalize on public domain status to make deliberately shocking content—the slasher movie based on Winnie the Pooh comes to mind, or the low-budget horror films featuring Mickey Mouse. Works like that may even generate outrage—that is their whole marketing plan! But will they be remembered? We have always been able to make slasher or porn versions of Shakespeare, yet I am guessing that the Shakespearean adaptations you remember are Rosencrantz and Guildenstern Are Dead (from Hamlet, RIP Tom Stoppard), West Side Story (from Romeo and Juliet), Forbidden Planet (from The Tempest), or 10 Things I Hate About You (from The Taming of the Shrew). From the serious to the whimsical, these are public domain reuses with more enduring appeal. Far from dimming the luster of the original works, they have allowed their legacy to live on. The best reason not to care about the merely shocking use of public domain works, without an underlying artistic point, is that they tend not to stand the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This point is true far beyond Shakespeare. Think of all the other films, cartoons, books, plays, musicals, video games, songs, and other works based on Greek mythology, on Mary Shelley’s Frankenstein, or on the works of Austen and Dickens. The Odyssey inspired not only the upcoming Christopher Nolan epic and the title of As I Lay Dying, but also centuries of other remakes—The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, Ulysses, and the Coen brothers’ O Brother Where Art Thou, to name just a few.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that the public domain extends beyond works whose copyrights have expired. Some material is born in the public domain. Ideas, facts, and raw data can never be copyrighted. The public domain also includes official works of the US government such as legislation, legal opinions, and even NASA images. The images from the James Webb telescope, the NASA collections NASA on The Commons (flickr) and NASA image and video library, the famous “Earthrise” photograph taken by astronaut William Anders, and the Farm Security Administration - Office of War Information Photograph Collection (a pictorial record of American life from 1935-1944 that includes Dorothea Lange's powerful photograph "Migrant Mother," one of the enduring images of the Great Depression) are all copyright-free. Another category of public domain material consists of works that creators choose to dedicate to the public domain, and many have done so using Creative Commons’ CC0 tool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;HOW DO COPYRIGHT AND TRADEMARK LAW APPLY TO CHARACTERS?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Mickey Mouse 1.0 went into the public domain in 2024, he joined a host of other public domain characters—Winnie-the-Pooh, Sherlock Holmes, Snow White, Cinderella, Dracula, Frankenstein's Monster, Robin Hood, Santa Claus, and the Wonderful Wizard of Oz characters, to name a few. This year, we get the first versions of Betty Boop and Pluto (originally named Rover) and new iterations of Mickey and Minnie Mouse. Looking ahead, an exciting new cast of characters will become public domain in the coming years: the initial appearance of Goofy in 2028 (originally named Dippy Dawg), Donald Duck in 2030, Superman in 2034, Batman in 2035, Tom and Jerry and Bugs Bunny in 2036, and Wonder Woman in 2037.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Long-running characters such as Betty Boop and Mickey Mouse are subject to both expired and enduring rights. This creates a fascinating checkerboard of material that is free and still owned. The overall result is a layered mosaic of public domain and copyrighted character attributes. Here is a summary, with the legal rules spelled out in more detail afterward and applied to Betty Boop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beginning with Mickey Mouse as a concrete example, dozens of iterations of the mouse fall into each of the categories above. In the top left quadrant, we will have 24 Mickey cartoons (from 1928-1930) and 6 comic strips (1930) that have entered the public domain due to copyright expiration after the full term. At the top right, there are also non-renewed cartoons and over a thousand additional comic strips just from 1930-1935 that appear to be public domain due to non-renewal. And in the bottom row, there are decades of still-copyrighted works, as well as continuing trademark rights for the use of Mickey’s image on various Disney products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The non-renewed works in the top right quadrant present an additional legal twist. The only aspects that became public domain upon non-renewal were their new features, not material derived from earlier works that remained in-copyright. The chronology of owned and free in such works is inverted. The new is free; the old may be subject to copyright.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is how this nuance plays out in one Mickey story without a renewed copyright—the 1934 tale of Rumplewatt the Giant. This story introduces a gnome village from which the titular giant steals a golden goose. After Mickey defeats the giant, the butterfly who initially flew him to the castle morphs into Princess Minnie. As a reward for his valiance, she agrees to marry Mickey. So far as we can tell, these elements were newly introduced in the 1934 comic. If this is correct, they are in the public domain due to non-renewal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, Rumplewatt the Giant derived many of its elements from the still-copyrighted cartoon Giantland (1933). These include a sequence where Mickey hides in a sugar-cube jar and ends up in the giant’s coffee cup, and a bit where Mickey uses pepper to make the giant sneeze. Assuming these were original to Giantland, they are still copyrighted. Even though they reappear in the non-renewed comic, they are not in the public domain because they originated in a work that is still under copyright. Finally, both works share basic “ideas” that are uncopyrightable and were always in the public domain—these include the generic “hero fights a giant and defeats him” plot line.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;BETTY BOOP&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Betty Boop provides another illustration. As Betty Boop 1.0 enters the public domain, this is an opportunity to celebrate and appreciate Max and Dave Fleischers’ unparalleled artistry and pioneering animation. While Fleischer Studios may not be as well-known to the general public as Disney, perhaps they should be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We know that Boop’s initial appearances from 1930 are public domain in 2026. There are also dozens of post-1930 Betty Boop cartoons that have long been public domain due to non-renewal. And there are many still-copyrighted works featuring Boop, plus trademark rights over her name and depiction for certain products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleischer Studios has posted a statement called “Fact Check 2026: Is Betty Boop in the Public Domain?". It begins with "this year Betty Boop appeared on a number of [public domain] lists, claiming that she will enter the public domain on January 1, 2026, which is actually not true" and elaborates:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the copyright in the ‘Dizzy Dishes’ cartoon may fall into the public domain in 2026, this does not affect Fleischer Studios’ copyright in the fully developed BETTY BOOP character Fleischer Studios created in subsequent cartoons and other uses and continues to use today. Fleischer Studios’ copyright in that character will therefore remain in force for some years to come, as will Fleischer Studios’ copyrights in the many subsequently revised and modern versions of the BETTY BOOP character and related elements. Equally important, the BETTY BOOP name and various related character designs are well-known and valuable Fleischer Studios trademarks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is interesting because while Fleischer Studios does own continuing trademark rights over Betty Boop (discussed below), its claim to copyright over the fully developed character is less clear. In fact, in 2011, an appeals court definitively held that Fleischer did not own the copyright in the Boop character.[14] The original Fleischer Studios had gone out of business and sold off its rights in the 1940s. The current Fleischer Studios, “a distinct and separate entity,” had later tried to buy back those rights. The only issue before the court was whether Fleischer owned the familiar Boop character. The court ruled that, because “the chain of title is broken,” it did not. (Beside the text you can see, from the court exhibits, two versions of Boop that Fleischer did not then own. As you can see, they are more “modern” than the 1930 Boop with her subtle dog ears.) Perhaps Fleischer has since reacquired some of those rights, or perhaps they only have the rights over newly added features from the “subsequent cartoons and other uses” they mention. In the latter case, those rights would be narrow and would not extend to the underlying Boop character at issue in the 2011 decision. One thing is clear: regardless of who owns the later versions of the character, the original Betty Boop character from 1930 is in the public domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your head is spinning from all the complexities involved here, congratulations! You are in good company. This is another reason why copyright expiration is so important: It brings clarity. There can be multiple separate copyrights implicated in a single creative work – over characters, audiovisual content, music, and so on. During a copyright term that lasts almost 100 years, those multiple rights may have changed hands many times and may no longer be owned by a single entity, or indeed by any entity we can identify. It can be incredibly difficult to figure out who owns what. When entire works become public domain, they are free for reuse without having to untangle this web of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thankfully, now that Betty Boop 1.0 is public domain, the ownership and chain of title questions are immaterial. She, at least, is copyright-free. That brings us to another set of questions: What features of the newer, copyrighted Boop characters are still subject to exclusive ownership, and what is free to the public? Expanding on the checkerboard above, here are more specifics about the legal rules, and how they apply to Betty Boop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;EXPIRED AND SUBSISTING COPYRIGHTS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We begin with the left column on the checkboard above. When the copyright expires over a creative work, the characters within that work enter the public domain, and you can use them in new works without permission or fee. What if those characters also appear in more recent works that remain copyrighted?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, under US copyright law, anyone is free to use characters as they appeared in public domain works. If those characters recur in later works that are still under copyright, the rights only extend to the newly added material in those works, not the underlying material from the public domain works—that content remains freely available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, with newer versions of characters, copyright only extends to those new features that qualify for such protection. The features must be “original, creative expression,” meaning that they were independently created (as opposed to copied from somewhere else) and possess at least a modicum of creativity. Mere “ideas” such as generic character traits are not copyrightable. Nor are “merely trivial” or “minuscule” variations added to the original characters. It is not enough for the new material to be different; it has to meet copyright’s threshold requirements for protectability. In addition, using commonplace elements that have become standard or indispensable (copyright law calls these “scènes à faire”) is not infringement.[15] Finally, if your use qualifies as “fair use,” for example if you make a scathing parody that significantly transforms the original work, the copyright owner has no right to stop you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From what we have said so far, you can see that even when a work is still under copyright, the rightsholder’s control is not absolute. Here is a serendipitous example. In Nichols v. Universal (1930), the author of the play Abie’s Irish Rose (mentioned above as part of the Marx Brothers’ pun) sued the producers of a popular movie for copyright infringement, claiming appropriation of her characters and plot. The judge rejected this claim, invoking as an example Shakespeare’s Sir Toby Belch from Twelfth Night, the source of W. Somerset Maugham’s Cakes and Ale title highlighted earlier. The judge wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If Twelfth Night were copyrighted, it is quite possible that a second comer might so closely imitate Sir Toby Belch or Malvolio as to infringe, but it would not be enough that for one of his characters he cast a riotous knight who kept wassail to the discomfort of the household, or a vain and foppish steward who became amorous of his mistress. These would be no more than Shakespeare’s “ideas” in the play, as little capable of monopoly as Einstein’s Doctrine of Relativity, or Darwin’s theory of the Origin of Species.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applying this to Abie’s Irish Rose, the judge explained why copying two lovers from the play would not be infringement: “The lovers are so faintly indicated as to be no more than stage properties. They are loving and fertile; that is really all that can be said of them, and anyone else is quite within his rights if he puts loving and fertile lovers in a play of his own, wherever he gets the cue.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How do these legal rules apply to Betty Boop? BOOP! the Musical was made when the character was still under copyright. Permission needed to be obtained. What if you wanted to make your own different Betty Boop musical in 2026, now that Boop 1.0 is in the public domain?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of Boop’s features from the 1930 cartoons are public domain in 2026. In her first appearance in Dizzy Dishes, she has the familiar flapper girl appearance and dance moves, and sings variations of “Boop Oop a Doop” to the besotted Bimbo character.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That Betty Boop is in the public domain, along with the lyrics, plot, and incredible animation. So are the Boops from other 1930 cartoons (to the left, Barnacle Bill and Mysterious Mose). However, those are not the only parts of the character in the public domain. Some of her features were not copyrightable from the beginning, because they were copied from elsewhere. Her general appearance and “Boop Oop A Doop” catchphrase were inspired by the Jazz Age flapper girl archetype, as embodied by celebrities such as Helen Kane.[16] It was the way those came together into a captivating new character that was copyrighted and is now entering the public domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is how Betty Boop developed over time, from Fleischer Studios' "Becoming Betty Boop" website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What features of newer Betty Boops are copyrightable? While copyright still covers the overall post-1930 depictions of Boop, it does not extend to unoriginal, “merely trivial,” or stereotypical modifications of Boop 1.0, such as replacing the dog ears with human ones, dressing her in standard attire for a cabaret performer or homemaker, adding a Rosie the Riveter bandana, or modulating her voice to reflect newer singing styles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We went through this same process two years ago with Mickey Mouse. Mickey 1.0 did not have red shorts or speak in a high-pitched voice; those traits were added in later, still-copyrighted works. When the original Mickey became public domain, we were asked by many reporters whether creators could color his shorts red or have him talk in a falsetto. Are those variations, standing alone, copyrightable? Does choosing a single, bright, primary color for an article of clothing, or giving an animated mouse a squeaky voice (given that mice actually squeak), meet the copyrightability threshold? We would say no, but reasonable people could disagree on exactly where the line is to be drawn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let us be clear: None of this detracts from the astounding creativity in the Fleischer cartoons—they are some of the most innovative cartoons we have ever seen! The later works contain a wealth of copyright-eligible material such as plot lines, dialogue, and new characters. But with any creative work – as the quote about Twelfth Night demonstrates – there are also uncopyrightable building blocks that remain free for future creators. The challenge is to separate the copyrightable wheat from the uncopyrightable chaff.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;NON-RENEWED COPYRIGHTS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We now turn to the top right quadrant in the checkerboard—the plot thickens when we add works that are also in the public domain due to non-renewal. Under early copyright law, copyrights lapsed after 28 years if they were not renewed. Dozens of post-1930 Betty Boop cartoons, including Ker-Choo (1932) and Poor Cinderella (1934), did not have renewals.[17] The newly added material in these animations is also in the public domain. As mentioned earlier, however, the material derived from still-copyrighted Boop animations is not.[18]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To sum up the copyright story so far: in 2026, the underlying Betty Boop character goes into the public domain. She is joined there by the attributes, plot lines, and dialogue that were first introduced in those later cartoons without renewed copyrights, as well as the uncopyrightable attributes of her later instantiations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;WHAT IF THE CHARACTER IS NO LONGER COPYRIGHTED, BUT ITS NAME OR IMAGE IS STILL SUBJECT TO TRADEMARK RIGHTS?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We finish with the bottom right quadrant: trademarks. You may encounter claims that even though Betty Boop 1.0 is copyright-free in 2026, you still cannot use the character in new creative works because it is trademarked by Fleischer Studios. But this is not what the law actually says. While Fleischer’s trademark rights over Betty Boop are unaffected by her entry into the copyright public domain, those rights are limited. Trademark law only prohibits the use of a trademarked character if doing so “is likely to cause confusion, or to cause mistake, or to deceive” consumers about the source or sponsorship of a new product.[19] Here is a brief summary of the relevant law.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trademark rights are designed to prevent consumer confusion in the marketplace. They are not supposed to interfere with artistic expression that doesn’t create such confusion. Trademark law does not prevent you from using a public domain character’s name or image in a new creative work so long as consumers are not likely to be misled into thinking that your work is produced or sponsored by the trademark holder. In addition, the law has special rules that allow creators to use other people’s trademarks in artistic works without liability.[20]&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trademarks do not override copyright law.The Supreme Court has made clear that trademark rights cannot be used to block the freedoms that the expiration of copyright allows, such as using a public domain character in a book or movie.[21]&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;→ Therefore, trademark rights do not prevent you from using the 1930 Betty Boop character in a new creative work unless consumers will be confused into thinking it is a Fleischer-sponsored product.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is the précis; here is the expanded version for those who are interested. Copyrights and trademarks are different. Copyrights cover creative works and prevent people from copying and adapting them without permission, with the goal of providing economic incentives to create and distribute cultural material. The US Constitution requires that these rights expire after a “limited time,” so that the public and future creators can have unfettered access to creative works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trademarks cover words, logos, images, and other signifiers that serve as brands identifying the source of a product. The goal is to minimize consumer confusion in the marketplace. Nike can prevent other producers of athletic apparel from putting “Nike” or a swoosh on their merchandise so that when purchasers see those indicators, they know they are getting a Nike product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike copyrights, trademarks do not automatically expire. They can last as long as a mark is still being “used in commerce.” While trademarks can outlast copyrights, however, the rights themselves are more circumscribed. It is only trademark infringement if an unauthorized use is likely to create consumer confusion about a product’s source or sponsorship. Non-confusing uses are not prohibited, and there are a variety of legal safeguards for uses of trademarks in connection with expressive works such as films, books, and songs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes copyrights and trademarks overlap. A character such as Betty Boop might be covered both by copyright law (as a creative work) and trademark law (as an indicator of product-source). What happens when the copyright expires and the trademark is ongoing? In a unanimous opinion, the Supreme Court made clear that trademarks cannot be used to make an end run around copyright law because this would “create a species of mutant copyright law that limits the public’s federal right to copy and to use expired copyrights.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We have been careful to caution against misuse or overextension of trademark and related protections into areas traditionally occupied by . . . copyright.” Dastar v. Twentieth Century Fox (Supreme Court 2003)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In other words, trademark rights cannot be used to block the freedoms that the expiration of copyright allows, such as using a public domain character in a new creative work. Along the same lines, the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals explained that when a work enters the public domain “[w]e all own it now,” and trademark law “cannot be used to circumvent copyright law. If material covered by copyright law has passed into the public domain, it cannot then be protected by the Lanham Act [the federal trademark statute] without rendering the Copyright Act a nullity.”[22]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Therefore, you can use a character’s name or image in a new creative work so long as consumers do not think that your work is produced or sponsored by the trademark holder. Those who tell you otherwise are mistaken.[23] One way to help dispel potential confusion is to make clear the actual source of the work – you or your company – on the title screen or cover, along with a prominent disclaimer indicating that your work is not produced, sponsored, endorsed, licensed, or approved by the trademark owner.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleischer owns trademark rights to the words “Betty Boop” and “Boop” for products such as live musical theater performances and clothing. It also has trademarks over Betty Boop designs such as the one depicted here for a range of merchandise including jewelry, wallets, back packs, drinking glasses, plastic water bottles, clothing, and dolls. (As noted by the Ninth Circuit appeals court in the case rejecting Fleischer’s copyright claim, it turns out that Boop merchandise is extremely popular, even appearing in the most surprising locations: “This merchandise has reached such a high level of popularity that even drug dealers have been known to use it. See United States v. Lakoskey, 462 F.3d 965, 971 (8th Cir. 2006) (‘A search warrant was issued, and the package was opened pursuant to that warrant on January 26, 2004. The package contained a large ceramic Betty Boop doll, with four concealed, separately wrapped plastic bundles of high-purity-level methamphetamine inside’).”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleischer’s trademark rights are for uses of “Betty Boop,” “Boop,” and her image, but only in connection with particular specified products. Fleischer does not own the simple word “Boop,” unconnected to Betty. Other companies have federally registered “Boop” as a trademark for coffee mugs and pet stores. Trademarks do not convey ownership of a word. “Popeye” the sailor cartoons coexist happily with the unconnected “Popeyes” chicken and biscuits. Dove soap does not infringe Dove chocolate. Delta faucets and Delta airlines legally use the same brand name for different goods and services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result of all of these points is that Fleischer Studios cannot use trademark law to interfere with the production of a new creative work featuring the Betty Boop 1.0 character when it is clear that the new work is not a Fleischer-sponsored production.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here it is important to distinguish between different uses of the Boop character. Certainly, there would be a risk of consumer confusion if you use Betty Boop as a brand identifier on the kind of merchandise Fleischer sells—jewelry, back packs, water bottles, dolls. Trademark law does protect Fleischer against that risk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contrast these uses with simply putting the Boop character in a new artistic work. This is exactly what copyright expiration is intended to allow. Were trademark law to prevent this, then trademark rights would be leveraged to obtain the effective equivalent of a perpetual copyright—precisely what the Supreme Court said we cannot do. You can also use the trademarked terms “Betty Boop” or “Boop” in connection with the new work featuring that character. As one court explained:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“When a public domain work is copied, along with its title, there is little likelihood of confusion when even the most minimal steps are taken to distinguish the publisher of the original from that of the copy. The public is receiving just what it believes it is receiving—the work with which the title has become associated. The public is not only unharmed, it is unconfused.”[24]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If courts have delineated the line between copyright and trademark, why is there so little clarity in this area? Sadly, companies sometimes claim to have more expansive rights than they actually do, capitalizing on fear, uncertainty, and doubt to collect royalties and licensing fees to which they are not legally entitled. This is deeply regrettable. It interferes with the rights of everyone from the small community theater trying to screen a public domain movie, and being told they still have to pay licensing fees, to new creators trying to make a new work from a public domain character but facing baseless threats that they are infringing. In the process, it fundamentally misstates the law in a way that confuses the public.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When such overbroad claims have actually gone to court, they have been dismissed, sometimes harshly. In 2023 we covered the Sherlock Holmes saga. The ingenious detective and his faithful sidekick Dr. Watson had been in the public domain for a long time. But that did not stop Conan Doyle Estate Ltd. from demanding licensing fees. Most people simply paid up. But when Leslie Klinger, a lawyer and Sherlock Holmes scholar, fought back, a court decisively confirmed that all of the elements in the out-of-copyright Sherlock Holmes stories are “free for public use.” The estate appealed, in a move that the Seventh Circuit Court of Appeals described as bordering on the “frivolous” and “quixotic.” The appeals court affirmed Klinger’s right to use the Holmes and Watson characters and awarded him attorney’s fees. Judge Richard Posner called out the estate’s “unlawful business strategy”:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Doyle estate’s business strategy is plain: charge a modest license fee for which there is no legal basis, in the hope that the “rational” writer or publisher asked for the fee will pay it rather than incur a greater cost, in legal expenses, in challenging the legality of the demand…only Klinger (so far as we know) resisted. In effect he was a private attorney general, combating a disreputable business practice — a form of extortion…It’s time the estate, in its own self-interest, changed its business model. Klinger v. Conan Doyle Estate (7th Cir. 2014).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let us hope that 2026 does not see more of this type of disreputable legal overreach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;WHAT IS THE IMPACT OF THE LONG COPYRIGHT TERM?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For copyrighted culture, the public domain arrives only after a long wait. Works from 1930 were first set to go into the public domain after a 56-year term in 1986, but a term extension pushed that date to 2006. They were then supposed to go into the public domain in 2006, after being copyrighted for 75 years. But before this could happen, Congress hit a 20-year pause button and extended their copyright term to 95 years. Now the wait is over.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The works featured above are famous; that is why we included them. Their copyright holders benefitted from 20 more years of copyright because the works were still earning royalties. But they are just the tip of the iceberg. When Congress extended the copyright term for these works, it also did so for all of the works whose commercial viability had long lapsed. For the vast majority—probably 99%—of works from 1930, no copyright holder financially benefited from continued copyright. Yet they remained off limits, for no good reason.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Congressional Research Service report indicated that only around 2% of copyrights between 55 and 75 years old retain commercial value. After 75 years, that percentage is even lower. Most older works are “orphan works,” where the copyright owner cannot be found at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is why a former head of our Copyright Office concluded that adding an extra 20 years to the US copyright term was a “big mistake.” Indeed, there is a consensus among policymakers, economists, and academics that lengthy copyright extensions impose costs that far outweigh their benefits. Why? The benefits are minuscule—economists (including five Nobel laureates) have shown that term extension does not spur additional creativity. At the same time, it causes enormous harm, locking away millions of older works that are no longer generating any revenue for the copyright holders. Films have disintegrated because preservationists can’t digitize them. The works of historians and journalists are incomplete. Artists find their cultural heritage off limits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The public domain enables the rediscovery and reuse of works that might otherwise be forgotten. Empirical studies have shown that public domain books are less expensive, available in more editions and formats, and more likely to be in print—see here, here, and here. The works highlighted above are just a tiny snapshot of what will be copyright-free. Many more are waiting to be found and appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the arrival of works into the public domain is cause for celebration, the length of the copyright term means that even though works from 1930 are legally available, this does always not mean they are actually available. Many films from the era have been lost forever. Noteworthy lost or mostly lost films from 1930 include the sound version of John Ford’s Men Without Women and The Gorilla.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact that works from 1930 are legally available also does not mean that rights holders won't continue to claim copyright over them. The previous section mentioned what an appeals judge called the "disreputable business practice" of charging "license fee[s] for which there is no legal basis." Yet rights holders continue to claim copyright over public domain properties. Lloyd Entertainment has told small community theaters that, unless the pay licensing fees, they cannot screen Safety Last! – a silent film that went into the public domain in 2019 – even when the theaters are using their own music and thought they were playing public domain prints. Lloyd claims that no public domain versions of the film exist because all available copies have been restored. Not all restorations have new copyrights, however. As mentioned earlier, if a film has been restored, only original and creative additions are eligible for copyright. If the restoration faithfully mimics the preexisting film, it does not contain newly copyrightable material and can be screened just like the public domain version. Many restorations contain new copyrightable material, but is it possible that every surviving print of Lloyd's movies is both restored, and sufficiently creatively changed to acquire a new copyright? The fact that this is in doubt underscores the problem with the long copyright term: after nearly a century, works may be legally available, but it is difficult to find original versions. Harold Lloyd was brilliant and the rights holders to his films enjoyed 95 years of copyright exclusivity. But when that term expires, theaters should be able to screen the films—this is exactly what the public domain is supposed to allow. It is disappointing to know that rights holders are targeting people who are merely trying to show films to fans, out of love and respect for the art.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To take a similar example, the owners of the rights to Charlie Chaplin’s films have been sending aggressive letters to small theaters telling them that they cannot screen Chaplin films that are legally in the public domain. The letters contain assertions about US copyright law that are, to use the technical term, bogus. To be sure, Chaplin was a genius and his successors have legitimate rights over his still-copyrighted films. But they do not have the right to squelch activities that are entirely legal. As Judge Posner commented earlier, falsely claiming an entitlement to licensing fees over public domain works can be "a form of extortion."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Chaplin Office nevertheless claims that the 1925 film The Gold Rush cannot be screened because the copyright in the underlying screenplay does not expire until 70 years after Chaplin’s death, or the end of 2047, because Chaplin was British and his copyright was restored under special rules for works by foreign authors. (They focus on the screenplay because the film entered the public domain in 1953 due to non-renewal of its copyright.) Even if this copyright restoration met the law's requirements (it does not appear to) there is a more basic mistake in their calculation: they cite to the wrong provision of US copyright law, §303, for the life + 70 term, ignoring that it is only for works that were “created but not published or copyrighted before January 1, 1978.” The Copyright Office records show that the screenplay was copyrighted in 1925, and for such works the law states that the copyright lasts for “the remainder of the term of copyright that the work would have otherwise been granted in the United States,” which is 95 years under §304 of the Copyright Act, making the work public domain in 2021. Case closed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;WHAT ARE THE BASIC RULES FOR DETERMINING WHETHER SOMETHING IS PUBLIC DOMAIN?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How long does copyright last in the United States? The 1998 Copyright Term Extension Act gave works published or registered before 1978 a 95-year term, expiring on January 1 after the conclusion of the 95th year. Doing the math, you add 96 years to the publication date. Works from 1930 were copyrighted for 95 years—through 2025—and are in the public domain January 1, 2026. This year's featured works are in the public domain because of either a 1930 registration or publication with a 1930 copyright notice. We were also able to track down the renewal data indicating that they are still in-copyright through the end of 2025 and entering the public domain in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Works published before 1978 had to meet certain requirements to be eligible for the full 95-year term—they had to be published with a copyright notice, and works from before 1964 also had to have their copyrights renewed after an initial 28-year term. Works published from 1978 through 3/1/1989 without a notice had to register their copyrights within five years to fix the lack of copyright notice. This means that many works published after 1930 might technically be in the public domain. However, as a practical matter, users sometimes have to assume they’re still copyrighted (or risk a lawsuit) because the relevant copyright information is difficult to find. We do not have clear and comprehensive records of copyright ownership and older records can be fragmentary, confused, or lost. In addition, as mentioned earlier, the concept of "publication" is important and has a special meaning under copyright law. It refers to when the work was sold or distributed to the general public with the authority of the copyright owner. Determining whether and when publication occurred can be complicated and vary depending on the kind of work—with music from before 1978, for example, the distribution of recordings of a song did not publish the song.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For pre-1978 works that were never published or registered, the term is different: life-plus-70 years for works by natural persons, and 120 years from creation for works of corporate authorship. In this category, works created by people who died in 1955 are in the public domain in 2026. Newer works created since 1978 are also treated differently from those published before 1978. Works by natural persons from 1978 forward have a life-plus-70 term, while works of corporate authorship are copyrighted for 95 years after publication. This is the copyright term for works created today, and there are no longer notice or renewal requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What about foreign works? Some countries have a life-plus-50 term and many others, including EU countries, have a life-plus-70-year term, even for the older works that have the 95-year term in the US. This means that works might be copyrighted in one country and copyright-free in another. For example, W. Somerset Maugham’s Cakes and Ale enters the US public domain in 2026 but is still copyrighted elsewhere until 2036, because the author died in 1965. In life-plus-70 jurisdictions, works from authors who died in 1955 are public domain this year, so they are celebrating a different set of works on Public Domain Day. How do you know which law applies to you? As a general matter, courts have said that users are governed by the law in the jurisdiction where they are using the creative work. But this inquiry can be more complicated and depend on the circumstances surrounding the use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the US, many foreign works from 1930 are copyrighted until 2026 because of a provision that, in 1996, restored copyright over certain foreign works that had fallen into the US public domain because of non-compliance with notice or renewal requirements. This restored term applies to many of the foreign works we are highlighting. You can learn more about how this functions from the Copyright Office's circular Copyright Restoration Under the URAA. If the owners of copyright in foreign works filed a Notice of Intent to Enforce their restored copyright you can find that information here. You can also find copyright restoration records through the Copyright Office’s search portal here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rumor Alert! You may see inaccurate claims online that all works by non-US authors such as Charlie Chaplin, Alfred Hitchcock, or Hergé are not entering the US public domain because they are subject to a life + 70 copyright term. This is not true. The 1996 provision that restored US copyright over qualifying foreign works is clear that their copyrights last for “the remainder of the term of copyright that the work would have otherwise been granted in the United States.” For foreign works that were published or copyrighted in 1930 – such as the ones we highlight – this term is 95 years, and they enter the public domain in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the copyright term for sound recordings? The Music Modernization Act’s “Classics Protection and Access Act” established a timeline for old recordings to enter the public domain. Recordings first published between 1923–1946 are public domain in January 2024–2047 (the year after a 100-year term). Then there is a ten-year pause from 2048–2058. After that, recordings first published between 1947–1956 are public domain in January 2058–2067, after a 110-year term. The term for all remaining recordings first fixed from 1957 until February 15, 1972 ends on February 15, 2067. Note that the term of protection for sound recordings in other countries is different from the one in the US: in the EU it is 70 years, and elsewhere it is 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This year’s entrants into the public domain are a wonderful group—enthralling, and deeply entertaining. Whatever your artistic interest, they have some delicious “cakes and ale” for you. Malvolio would disapprove. But they also offer us something deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Language and art were once domains that humans thought solely our own. Generative AI has forced us to re-articulate our conception of art and the creative process; to focus on the subjective experience behind the work, not just the pretty patterns manifested within it. In that context, it is fascinating to reflect on these works from 1930. What leaps out at you is the humanity behind them—the wit, the stylistic innovation, the stories being told in the shadow of World War I and in the midst of the Great Depression.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These authors were producing meaning from lived experience, not just replicating patterns. Their artistic output is not merely a snapshot of our culture at a moment in time or an entertaining postcard from the past. It is a record of the lives they lived, the emotions they felt, and the art they made as a result of it. It gives new meaning to the Somerset Maugham quote with which we began this essay, speaking of the beauty that artists sometimes create out of chaos. “The pictures they paint, the music they compose, the books they write, and the lives they lead. Of all these the richest in beauty is the beautiful life. That is the perfect work of art.” In the age of AI, those words seem to offer us a luminous insight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Want to learn more about the public domain? Here is the legal background on how we got our current copyright terms (including summaries of court cases), why the public domain matters, and answers to Frequently Asked Questions. You can also read James Boyle’s book The Public Domain: Enclosing the Commons of the Mind (Yale University Press, 2008)—naturally, you can read the full text of The Public Domain online at no cost and you are free to copy and redistribute it for non-commercial purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More information on the copyright term can be found on this excellent chart on Copyright Term and the Public Domain in the United States. For additional guidance from the Copyright Office, see its circulars on Duration of Copyright, How to Investigate the Copyright Status of a Work, and Copyright Restoration Under the URAA. For a detailed guide to identifying public domain material, you can purchase Stephen Fishman’s The Public Domain: How to Find &amp;amp; Use Copyright-Free Writings, Music, Art &amp;amp; More. You can also read “In Ambiguous Battle: The Promise (and Pathos) of Public Domain Day,” an article by Center Director Jennifer Jenkins revealing the promise and the limits of various attempts to reverse the erosion of the public domain, referring to a previous Public Domain Day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[1] Jennifer Jenkins is the Director of the Center for the Study of the Public Domain and Clinical Professor of Law at Duke Law School. James Boyle is the William Neal Reynolds Professor of Law at Duke Law School and Faculty Co-Director of the Center.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[2] Our featured works are only entering the public domain under US copyright law. The copyright term for older works is different in other countries. In the EU, works from authors who died in 1955 are going into the public domain in 2026 after a life-plus-70 year term. As a general matter, under the principle of lex loci delicti, users are governed by the law in the jurisdiction where they are using the creative work. See Itar-Tass Russian News Agency v. Russian Kurier, Inc. (2d Cir. 1998). But this inquiry can be complicated and fact-specific, and governing law will depend on the circumstances of the use in question.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[3] Even though a work is still in-copyright, you may legally use it in certain ways if your activity qualifies for copyright’s “fair use” exception.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[4] To find more material from 1930, you can visit the Catalogue of Copyright Entries. In the US, only the author’s works from 1930 and earlier are in the public domain, not all of the other work published by that author. With regard to newly copyright-free works, only the original versions published in 1930 are entering the US public domain. Later versions of them—adaptations, movies, or translations—may still be copyrighted. However the later copyright only covers newly added creative material. The original content from the 1930 work remains free. As you look through these works from 1930, please note that they offer a temporal cross section of our cultural past, capturing the era in its complexity. Unfortunately many of the works from 1930 contain racist and sexist stereotypes and demeaning language. When such works enter the public domain, anyone is free to critique and remake them, even if doing so goes beyond what would be allowed under copyright’s fair use doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[5] Arnold Munk credited a book called “The Pony Engine” (1916) but later faced an unsuccessful claim that he took the story from Frances Ford who had written a similar story in 1910. For fascinating research into the stories that led up to Munk’s version, see Roy Plotnick, “In Search of Watty Piper: The History of the ‘Little Engine’ Story,” New Review of Children’s Literature and Librarianship, 18:11-26 (2012).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[6] We found "King Features Weekly" copyright renewals from 1935 that may cover the first appearance of Dagwood’s sandwich.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[7] Peter Benjaminson, The Life and Times of Betty Boop: The 100-Year History of an Animated Icon (Rowman &amp;amp; Littlefield Publishers, 2023), p17: “Early one morning in 1930, Dave Fleischer told animator Grim Natwick to design a girl dog who would costar with Bimbo in a cartoon to be titled ‘Dizzy Dishes.’ Natwick was told that the new character, as yet unnamed, would be singing a ‘boop-oop-a-doop’ song similar to those sung by Helen Kane. Fleischer also handed Natwick a picture of Kane.” The lyrics from the song that Boop sings in Dizzy Dishes are from “I Have to Have You,” performed by Helen Kane in a film the year before. Animation Resources recounts similar origins in this biography of Grim Natwick.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[8] You can find Bellot’s quote and a more in-depth analysis of the Betty Boop character before and after the Hays Code in Emily Wishingrad, “The Evolution of Betty Boop”, Smithsonian Magazine (March 9, 2022). Bellot further explained that "[Betty Boop] was a stereotype, yet she also defied stereotypes of what female cartoon characters could do onscreen. In The Life and Times of Betty Boop, Peter Benjaminson writes: “Betty is the only classic female comic character who isn’t someone’s wife, girlfriend, or regular employee. Unlike Olive Oyl, Blondie, and other cartoon women, Betty’s not defined by her relationship to a male character…She’s her own woman, known for herself, and not just because she belongs to some man.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[9] Here is additional information on the question of when musical compositions were “published” under early copyright law. We know that they were published when copies of sheet music were sold, and were not published if they were merely distributed as sound recordings. But what if the music first appeared in a movie? While courts have offered inconsistent interpretations of the law, the leading copyright treatise explains that the “general rule” is that publication of a movie also publishes the previously unpublished works incorporated within the movie, such as music and screenplays. 1 Nimmer on Copyright § 4.12. Cases following this rule include Shoptalk, Ltd. v. Concorde-New Horizons Corp. (2d Cir. 1999), Batjac Prods. Inc. v. GoodTimes Home Video Corp (9th Cir. 1998) and Maljack Prods. Inc. v. UAV Corp. (C.D. Cal. 1997). The logic is that publication of the film necessarily entails publication of its constituent parts. See Classic Film Museum, Inc. v. Warner Bros., Inc. (D.Me.1978) (“It is impossible to cleave the story, screenplay and musical score of a motion picture film from the film itself”; holding that non-renewal of the original 1937 film A Star Is Born “dedicated the film in its entirety [including the script and musical score] to the public use”). If the film’s owners complied with the legal requirements for the full 95-year copyright term, the owners of the underlying material in the film received that protection as well. When the term expires, the motion picture and its component parts become public domain, allowing use of the composite film.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Copyright Office agrees with this interpretation. In a 1975 review of the 1909 Copyright Act, which governed works from 1930, it explained: “On the basis of a thorough legal review and analysis of the status of motion picture soundtracks under the copyright statute, the Copyright Office has concluded that under the prevailing judicial view, copyright in a motion picture extends to an integrated sound track and its copyrightable component parts.” 37 C.F.R. § 202.15 (1975). Accordingly, under the 1909 Act, “[t]he U.S. Copyright Office considers a motion picture to be a unitary work in which the component parts are integral to the work as a whole.” Copyright Office Compendium § 2122.6(C). This remains true under today’s copyright law: “Where music is first published in a motion picture soundtrack, the motion picture is considered a copy of the musical work.” Copyright Office Compendium § 802.4(C).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are cases that departed from this general rule, but they did so in a different context. See Richlin v. Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Pictures, Inc. (9th Cir. 2008); TCA TV Corp. v. McCollum (2d Cir. 2016). These decisions did not afford the works embodied in a film the full copyright term, so that the composite entered the public domain after 95 years. Instead, they did the opposite, and said that the owners of such underlying works forfeited their copyrights because they could not benefit from the film owners’ compliance with copyright formalities. Criticizing this “harsh construction” of the law, Professor Nimmer invokes a scenario relevant to this discussion: “the fact that a songwriter may separately register her work for protection does not prove that her failure to separately register the work forfeits all protection in it—the possibility remains that she could rely on the registration of the work in which the song appears to vindicate her rights in that song.” After these rights expire, both the film and song go into the public domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The popular songs in King of Jazz were copyrighted separately from the film and either entered the public domain before 2026, as with My Bridal Veil (1920), Rhapsody in Blue (1924), Mississippi Mud (1927), and The Bluebirds and the Blackbirds Got Together (1929), or are from 1930 and are becoming public domain along with the film—these include A Bench in the Park, The Song of the Dawn, Happy Feet, I Like to Do Things for You, It Happened in Monterey, Ragamuffin Romeo, and Music Has Charms (all from 1930).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[10] Note that US copyright law allows you to cover a song without permission while it is still copyrighted under the “compulsory license” in §115, so long as you do not “change the basic melody or fundamental character” of the original song and pay a pre-set royalty rate. When a song is in the public domain you can make covers without complying with this provision, and you can also make other adaptations, performances, and interpolations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[11] The Music Modernization Act sets a timeline for older recordings to enter the public domain, and also has provisions allowing people to legally make noncommercial uses of still-copyrighted recordings that are no longer being commercially exploited. Older recordings contain a wealth of history; not just music but spoken word, radio broadcasts, oral histories. A lot of this material has faded into obscurity and is of interest primarily to scholars and hobbyists. But, like old films, old audio lives on a fragile substrate—many vintage formats deteriorate over time, to the point where they literally disintegrate, or it is impossible to play them again. Congress therefore included carveouts in the law to try and ensure that this history can be digitized and preserved for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[12] For never-published, never-registered works, the term is life + 70 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[13] Special thanks to the FIFA World Cup Museum and to Michael Schmalholz, Team Leader Heritage, for providing records on the Lafleur sculpture. Thanks also to the Internet Archive for the Wayback Machine, which helped preserve many records that we otherwise might not have been able to find.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[14] In the 2011 case Fleischer Studios v. A.V.E.L.A., the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals held that Fleischer Studios was not the owner of the copyright to the Betty Boop character. The original Fleischer Studios sold those rights away and was dissolved in the 1940s. The rights in the Betty Boop character were carved out from the rights in the cartoons and the separate sets of rights were eventually transferred to different companies. Later the Fleischer heirs formed a new Fleischer Studios – “a distinct and separate entity from the now defunct Original Fleischer which first owned Betty Boop” – and tried to buy back the copyright to the Betty Boop character. There was a complicated chain of title: “Original Fleischer transferred its rights to Paramount Pictures, Inc. (Paramount) in 1941; Paramount transferred those rights to UM &amp;amp; M TV Corp. (UM &amp;amp; M) in 1955; in 1958, UM &amp;amp; M transferred these rights to National Telefilm Associates, Inc. (NTA), which became Republic Pictures in 1986; and finally, Republic Pictures transferred the exclusive copyright to Fleischer in 1997.” The problem? There is a broken link in the chain: “it is clear that Paramount did not transfer the copyright to the Betty Boop character to UM &amp;amp; M.” Because the copyright was kept by Paramount, rather than transferred to UM &amp;amp; M, UM &amp;amp; M could not transfer it down the line to Fleischer. Something could have happened since this 2011 decision – for example, Fleischer could have regained rights directly from Paramount – but we cannot find anything in the legal filings or Copyright Office records and do not know who now owns the rights at issue in A.V.E.L.A. If Fleischer owns copyrights in later cartoons, this would only confer rights over character features that were not derived from the iterations it does not own. Suffice it to say that the scope of their copyright claims is unclear, and any copyright actions against others would necessarily be limited to uses that infringe on what they actually own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[15] To quote the Copyright Office primer on derivative works: “[I]t is not possible to extend the length of protection for a copyrighted work by creating a derivative work…the copyright in the derivative work will not extend to the public domain material, and the use of the public domain material in a derivative work will not prevent anyone else from using the same public domain work for another derivative work.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[16] See the Copyright Office Compendium. Regarding generic character traits, courts have held that being “nice,” having a “cocky attitude,” and being “young, attractive, and sarcastic” are not independently copyrightable character traits. See Shame on You Prods. v. Banks (C.D. Cal. 2015, aff’d 9th Cir. 2017); Campbell v. Walt Disney Co. (N.D. Cal. 2010); Gable v. Nat’l Broad. Co. (C.D. Cal. 2010).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[17] To look for renewals, we consulted both the Catalog of Copyright Entries and Virtual Card Catalog for renewal records and did not find any.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[18] See Stewart v. Abend (1990).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[19] 15 U.S.C. §§1114, 1125(a). A small subset of superbrands with “famous” marks gets extra protection against “dilution” that impairs the distinctiveness or harms the reputation of the famous mark, even when there is no consumer confusion. This protection is limited to “famous” marks, as defined by trademark law. Fame has a specialized meaning here: only trademarks that are widely recognized by the general public as a brand signifier qualify. It is not enough that a character is famous in the general sense of the word. Instead, its depiction would need to function like the Nike Swoosh in designating product source. Importantly, even for trademarks that qualify, anti-dilution protection is subject to statutory First-Amendment exceptions that allow for the kinds of expressive uses discussed in this section. See 15 U.S.C. §1125(c)(3). For instance, even though “Barbie” is a famous mark that qualifies for anti-dilution protection, the statutory exceptions in §1125(c)(3) have allowed artists to use the “Barbie” trademark for artistic commentary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[20] Trademark law has a number of speech-protecting limitations that safeguard artistic uses. These apply whether or not the trademark is also the subject of an expired copyright. One defense allows “nominative use” of a trademark as a point of reference – for example, using “Betty Boop” accurately to refer to the character in your work. Another comes from a case called Rogers v. Grimaldi, which privileged the use of trademarks in titles of expressive works when the term has some artistic relevance to the new work and does not explicitly mislead as to the source of the work. A 2023 Supreme Court decision let the Rogers test stand for these kinds of uses, see Jack Daniel's Properties, Inc. v. VIP Products LLC (2023), so long as the unauthorized use is not as a brand signifier. These doctrines are why Mattel loses in court when it sues people for using the word “Barbie” and the doll’s trademarked appearance in expressive works. See Mattel, Inc. v. Walking Mountain Productions (9th Cir. 2003); Mattel, Inc. v. MCA Records, Inc. (9th Cir. 2002). While a disclaimer is not required to benefit from these limitations, it can nevertheless be useful to make abundantly clear that you are not providing an official Fleischer Studios production.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[21] Dastar v. Twentieth Century Fox (2003) (“We have been careful to caution against misuse or overextension of trademark and related protections into areas traditionally occupied by . . . copyright”). This case dealt with an attempt to make an attribution-like claim under the federal trademark statute over public domain works, but the larger policy underlying the decision is that trademark law cannot be used to circumvent copyright expiration. Dastar had repackaged parts of a public domain documentary, removing the original credits and presenting it as a Dastar production. Twentieth Century Fox owned the copyrights to the documentary before they expired and claimed that Dastar violated trademark law by passing off Fox’s work as its own and failing to attribute it to Fox. The Supreme Court rejected this claim.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[22] Comedy III v. New Line (9th Cir. 2000). Nonetheless, people sometimes still try to use trademark law to interfere with legal reuses of public domain material, leading to unnecessary litigation and chilling effects. Zorro Productions, Inc. and Edgar Rice Burroughs, Inc. did this with the Zorro works and the Tarzan and John Carter works. Zorro lost in court—because the Zorro story was in the public domain, a new “Queen of Swords” TV series about Zorro’s sword-wielding daughter could proceed. See Sony v. Fireworks (C.D. Cal. 2001) (the case also included unsuccessful copyright claims). Burroughs was able to extract a joint licensing deal from the publisher of new “Lord of the Jungle” and “Warlord of Mars” comic books; even the threat of lawsuits can chill creative reuse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[23] The leading treatise on trademark law explains: “The expiration of copyright on a copyrighted work, such as a motion picture containing a cartoon character, should place limits on the scope of trademark rights in the character. Under the view that upon expiration of copyright the public should have free use of the work, copyright policy requires that anyone should be able to reproduce, display and perform the out-of-copyright motion picture so long as there is no confusion as to the source, sponsorship or affiliation of the seller of the reproduced film,” and “a court should not permit trademark in an image to serve the same function as did the lapsed copyright to exclude others from reproducing and distributing the out-of-copyright work, such as a film . . . a balancing of the rights of trademark and of the 'public domain' status of out-of-copyright works is needed. A similar balancing is made when constitutional free speech policies are balanced against the prevention of consumer confusion.” J. Thomas McCarthy, McCarthy on Trademarks and Unfair Competition, § 6.30.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[24] Maljack Prods. v. Goodtimes Home Video Corp. (9th Cir. 1996), quoting Leslie A. Kurtz, "Protection for Titles of Literary Works in the Public Domain", 37 Rutgers L. Rev. 53, 77 (1984). See also Walt Disney Productions v. Souvaine Selective Pictures, Inc. (S.D.N.Y. 1951, aff'd 2d Cir. 1951) (Disney could not prevent another film producer from using the title “Alice in Wonderland” because “the book ‘Alice in Wonderland’ is no longer subject to copyright and is as much in the public domain as are Shakespeare’s plays. Anyone has a legal right to make a picture based on Lewis Carroll’s book and entitled ‘Alice in Wonderland’”).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Written by Jennifer Jenkins and James Boyle. Special thanks to Researcher Sterling Dudley for researching works from 1930 and creating images and video content, to Jason Rosenberg for researching the provenance of artworks from 1930, and to web developers Michael Wright and Isaiah Cooper for building this site.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Public Domain Day 2026 by Jennifer Jenkins and James Boyle is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This website is not official legal advice. Instead, it is a summary of United States law relevant to the public domain and a guide to some of the works entering the public domain in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46405866</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 22:15:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Liberating Bluetooth on the ESP32</title><link>https://exquisite.tube/w/mEzF442Q4hUXnhQ8HmfZuq</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf6f84981497afad"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems JavaScript is either blocked or disabled in your web browser. We totally get that. However, this page will not work without it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are concerned about the security and privacy (or lack thereof) of JavaScript web applications, you might want to review the source code of the instance you are trying to access, or look for security audits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are sorry but it seems that PeerTube is not compatible with your web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please try with the latest version of Mozilla Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you think this is a mistake, please report it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46406098</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 22:37:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Functional programming and reliability: ADTs, safety, critical infrastructure</title><link>https://blog.rastrian.dev/post/why-reliability-demands-functional-programming-adts-safety-and-critical-infrastructure</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="99767a096f092704"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why Reliability Demands Functional Programming: ADTs, Safety, and Critical Infrastructure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In banking, telecom, and payments, reliability is not a nice to have. It is table stakes. The most reliable systems I have worked on reduce entire classes of bugs before the code even runs. Functional programming and Algebraic Data Types (ADTs) let you push correctness into the type system, so illegal states cannot be constructed in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What you will learn&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How invalid states show up in real systems and why they cause costly incidents&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How ADTs encode business rules so the compiler enforces them&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How pattern matching and exhaustiveness checks turn refactors into safe edits&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Practical modeling patterns for banking and telecom domains in TypeScript and OCaml&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A migration playbook that juniors and mid-levels can apply today&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Functional programming&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Algebraic data type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tagged union or sum type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Product type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pattern matching&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Immutable object&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pure function&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;High availability&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;1) Reliability starts at the type system&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most production incidents are not due to complex algorithms. They are due to the code entering a state that should never have been possible. If you have been on call, you have seen variants of these:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Magic strings: &lt;code&gt;"paypal"&lt;/code&gt;sneaks into a system that only supports&lt;code&gt;Cash&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Card&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Pix&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Nulls: a function expects an email and receives &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;in a path you forgot to guard&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Conflicting booleans: an account is both &lt;code&gt;isActive = true&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;isSuspended = true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Incomplete lifecycles: a transaction is marked &lt;code&gt;Pending&lt;/code&gt;and then jumps to&lt;code&gt;Reversed&lt;/code&gt;without an associated&lt;code&gt;Settled&lt;/code&gt;record&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Functional programming helps by modeling the domain with types that make invalid states unrepresentable. Pure functions and immutability keep behavior predictable and testable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;2) ADTs in practice: sums and products&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Product types combine fields, think "and". Sum types choose one of several cases, think "or". Together they model your domain rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Product type example&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type user = {
  id    : int;
  name  : string;
  email : string option;  (* Some "[email protected]" or None *)
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type User = Readonly&amp;lt;{
  id: number;
  name: string;
  email?: string; // we will improve this with Option next
}&amp;gt;;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Sum type example&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type payment =
  | Cash
  | Card of string   (* last 4 digits *)
  | Pix  of string
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript discriminated union
type Payment =
  | { kind: "cash" }
  | { kind: "card"; last4: string }
  | { kind: "pix"; key: string };
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this shape, &lt;code&gt;"paypal"&lt;/code&gt; cannot exist as a &lt;code&gt;Payment&lt;/code&gt;. The compiler refuses the value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3) Pattern matching and exhaustiveness&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you pattern match on a sum type, the compiler can force you to handle every variant. If you later add a new case, every non exhaustive match becomes a compilation error or warning. This is how refactors become safe by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
let describe_payment = function
  | Cash -&amp;gt; "Paid in cash"
  | Card last4 -&amp;gt; "Card ••••" ^ last4
  | Pix key -&amp;gt; "Pix " ^ key
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
const assertNever = (x: never): never =&amp;gt; { throw new Error(`Unhandled variant: ${JSON.stringify(x)}`) }

function describePayment(p: Payment): string {
  switch (p.kind) {
    case "cash":  return "Paid in cash"
    case "card":  return `Card ••••${p.last4}`
    case "pix":   return `Pix ${p.key}`
    default:      return assertNever(p)
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a new &lt;code&gt;Crypto&lt;/code&gt; method and both code bases will point out every place you must update.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;4) Failure scenarios and their type driven fixes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;4.1 Banking example: double settlement and reconciliation drift&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incident story&lt;lb/&gt; A payout worker retries on network timeouts and calls &lt;code&gt;settle()&lt;/code&gt; twice. The table allows &lt;code&gt;pending = false&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;settled = true&lt;/code&gt; twice with the same ledger id. Reconciliation finds duplicates and accounting needs a manual fix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why it happened&lt;lb/&gt; State is spread across booleans and strings. The database does not express the lifecycle. The application code does, but only by convention and tests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix with ADTs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type failure_reason =
  | InsufficientFunds
  | ComplianceHold
  | NetworkError of string

type txn_state =
  | Pending
  | Settled  of string       (* ledger_id *)
  | Failed   of failure_reason
  | Reversed of string       (* original_ledger_id *)

type txn = {
  id           : string;
  amount_cents : int;
  state        : txn_state;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type FailureReason =
  | { kind: "insufficientFunds" }
  | { kind: "complianceHold" }
  | { kind: "networkError"; message: string }

type TxnState =
  | { kind: "pending" }
  | { kind: "settled"; ledgerId: string }
  | { kind: "failed"; reason: FailureReason }
  | { kind: "reversed"; originalLedgerId: string }

type Txn = Readonly&amp;lt;{
  id: string
  amountCents: number
  state: TxnState
}&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transitions become total functions. You can return a &lt;code&gt;Result&lt;/code&gt; when a transition is not allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type 'a result = Ok of 'a | Error of string

let settle (t: txn) (ledger_id: string) : txn result =
  match t.state with
  | Pending -&amp;gt; Ok { t with state = Settled ledger_id }
  | Settled _ -&amp;gt; Error "already settled"
  | Failed _ -&amp;gt; Error "cannot settle a failed transaction"
  | Reversed _ -&amp;gt; Error "cannot settle a reversed transaction"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;  = { _tag: "Ok"; value: T }
type Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Err"; error: E }
type Result&amp;lt;T, E&amp;gt; = Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; | Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt;
const Ok = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Result&amp;lt;T, never&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Ok", value })
const Err = &amp;lt;E&amp;gt;(error: E): Result&amp;lt;never, E&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Err", error })

function settle(t: Txn, ledgerId: string): Result&amp;lt;Txn, string&amp;gt; {
  switch (t.state.kind) {
    case "pending":  return Ok({ ...t, state: { kind: "settled", ledgerId } })
    case "settled":  return Err("already settled")
    case "failed":   return Err("cannot settle a failed transaction")
    case "reversed": return Err("cannot settle a reversed transaction")
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now the illegal transitions are blocked by construction. Test coverage still matters, but the shape of the model prevents a class of bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Refactor safety&lt;lb/&gt; When product adds &lt;code&gt;Chargeback&lt;/code&gt;, the compiler highlights every match that ignores it. You cannot ship with a half handled lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;type TxnState =
  | { kind: "pending" }
  | { kind: "settled"; ledgerId: string }
  | { kind: "failed"; reason: FailureReason }
  | { kind: "reversed"; originalLedgerId: string }
  | { kind: "chargeback"; networkRef: string } // new
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; on &lt;code&gt;TxnState&lt;/code&gt; now requires a &lt;code&gt;chargeback&lt;/code&gt; branch. This is free guidance from the compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;4.2 Telecom example: ghost billing and incomplete sessions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incident story&lt;lb/&gt; The call detail record pipeline generates billing events whenever it sees a &lt;code&gt;Connected&lt;/code&gt; event. Under jitter and retries, some sessions never receive &lt;code&gt;Completed&lt;/code&gt;. The billing system charges based on the wrong boundary and customers complain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why it happened&lt;lb/&gt; The call lifecycle is implicit across many services. A connected session with no end was still billable because there was no type that separated non billable states from billable ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix with ADTs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type drop_reason = Network | Busy | Timeout

type call =
  | Dialing   of int                   (* at_ms *)
  | Connected of int                   (* started_ms *)
  | Dropped   of drop_reason * int     (* reason, at_ms *)
  | Completed of int * int             (* started_ms, ended_ms *)

let billable_seconds = function
  | Completed (start_ms, end_ms) -&amp;gt; max 0 (end_ms - start_ms) / 1000
  | _ -&amp;gt; 0
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type DropReason = "network" | "busy" | "timeout"

type Call =
  | { kind: "dialing";   atMs: number }
  | { kind: "connected"; startedMs: number }
  | { kind: "dropped";   reason: DropReason; atMs: number }
  | { kind: "completed"; startedMs: number; endedMs: number }

const billableSeconds = (c: Call): number =&amp;gt; {
  switch (c.kind) {
    case "completed": return Math.max(0, (c.endedMs - c.startedMs) / 1000)
    default:          return 0
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now a connected but never completed call cannot produce a billable duration. The shape forbids the bug.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;4.3 Config parsing example: hidden NaN and partial failures&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incident story&lt;lb/&gt; A cache TTL is stored in an environment variable. Someone sets &lt;code&gt;CACHE_TTL_SECS=30s&lt;/code&gt;. In JavaScript, &lt;code&gt;Number("30s")&lt;/code&gt; yields &lt;code&gt;NaN&lt;/code&gt; and your code treats it as zero, disabling caching in production.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix with Result types&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type 'a result = Ok of 'a | Error of string

let parse_int (s: string) : int result =
  try Ok (int_of_string s) with _ -&amp;gt; Error "invalid int"

let load_ttl () : int option =
  match Sys.getenv_opt "CACHE_TTL_SECS" with
  | None -&amp;gt; None
  | Some s -&amp;gt;
    match parse_int s with
    | Ok n -&amp;gt; Some n
    | Error _ -&amp;gt; None  (* or propagate the error *)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
const parseIntR = (s: string): Result&amp;lt;number, "invalid-int"&amp;gt; =&amp;gt;
  /^-?\d+$/.test(s) ? Ok(Number(s)) : Err("invalid-int")

function loadTtl(): Option&amp;lt;number&amp;gt; {
  const raw = process.env.CACHE_TTL_SECS
  if (!raw) return None
  const parsed = parseIntR(raw)
  return parsed._tag === "Ok" ? Some(parsed.value) : None
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ambiguity disappears. The code must handle absence and parse errors explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;5) Options and Results as first class tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do not use &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; to mean "maybe". Do not throw exceptions for expected errors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Option or Maybe&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type user = { id: int; email: string option }

let send_mail (u: user) =
  match u.email with
  | Some e -&amp;gt; (* send e *) ()
  | None   -&amp;gt; ()
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type None = { _tag: "None" }
type Some&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Some"; value: T }
type Option&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; = None | Some&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;
const None: None = { _tag: "None" }
const Some = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Option&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Some", value })

const map = &amp;lt;A, B&amp;gt;(o: Option&amp;lt;A&amp;gt;, f: (a: A) =&amp;gt; B): Option&amp;lt;B&amp;gt; =&amp;gt;
  o._tag === "Some" ? Some(f(o.value)) : None
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Result or Either&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
let result_map f = function
  | Ok x -&amp;gt; Ok (f x)
  | Error e -&amp;gt; Error e
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;  = { _tag: "Ok"; value: T }
type Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Err"; error: E }
type Result&amp;lt;T, E&amp;gt; = Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; | Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt;
const Ok  = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Result&amp;lt;T, never&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Ok", value })
const Err = &amp;lt;E&amp;gt;(error: E): Result&amp;lt;never, E&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Err", error })
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These types make the happy path and the error path equally explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;6) Immutability and why it simplifies reasoning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mutable shared state is a common source of heisenbugs under concurrency. Prefer immutable data and pure functions. When you need to update, create a new value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
let set_email (u: user) (e: string option) : user =
  { u with email = e }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type User = Readonly&amp;lt;{ id: number; name: string; email: Option&amp;lt;string&amp;gt; }&amp;gt;

const setEmail = (u: User, email: Option&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;): User =&amp;gt;
  ({ ...u, email })
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your tests become simple. Given the same inputs, the function returns the same output.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;7) Smart constructors and newtypes to protect units and invariants&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Numbers are not self describing. Create types that carry meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
module Cents : sig
  type t
  val make : int -&amp;gt; t            (* reject negatives *)
  val add  : t -&amp;gt; t -&amp;gt; t
end = struct
  type t = Cents of int
  let make x = if x &amp;lt; 0 then invalid_arg "negative cents" else Cents x
  let add (Cents a) (Cents b) = Cents (a + b)
end
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type Brand&amp;lt;K, T&amp;gt; = K &amp;amp; { __brand: T }

type Cents = Brand&amp;lt;number, "Cents"&amp;gt;
const Cents = (n: number): Cents =&amp;gt; {
  if (!Number.isInteger(n) || n &amp;lt; 0) throw new Error("invalid cents")
  return n as Cents
}

type Millis = Brand&amp;lt;number, "Millis"&amp;gt;
const Millis = (n: number): Millis =&amp;gt; n as Millis

const price: Cents = Cents(500)
// const wrong: Cents = Millis(500)  // type error
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You stop mixing milliseconds with seconds or dollars with cents by accident.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;8) Pure core, effectful shell&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep the domain logic pure and push IO to the edges. This makes unit tests cheap and fast.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml, pure core *)
let authorize_payment (amount: Cents.t) (balance: Cents.t) : bool =
  amount &amp;lt;= balance  (* assume a comparison helper inside the module *)

(* impure shell *)
let run () =
  let amount = Cents.make 500 in
  let balance = Cents.make 1200 in
  if authorize_payment amount balance then
    (* call database and payment gateway here *) ()
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript, pure core
const authorizePayment = (amount: Cents, balance: Cents): boolean =&amp;gt; {
  return (amount as unknown as number) &amp;lt;= (balance as unknown as number)
}

// effectful shell
async function run() {
  const amount = Cents(500)
  const balance = Cents(1200)
  if (authorizePayment(amount, balance)) {
    // perform DB writes or API calls here
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;9) Migration playbook&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start small and make continuous progress. Here is a practical order for a team new to these ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replace pairs of booleans with a sum type&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Before: &lt;code&gt;{ isActive: boolean; isSuspended: boolean }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;After: &lt;code&gt;type AccountState = { kind: "active" } | { kind: "suspended" } | { kind: "closed" }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Before: &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replace string enums with discriminated unions&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Avoid free form strings like &lt;code&gt;"pending" | "settled" | "failed" | string&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Avoid free form strings like &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replace nullable fields with Option&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;OCaml &lt;code&gt;string option&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;TypeScript &lt;code&gt;Option&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;or a stricter domain specific union&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OCaml &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replace thrown control flow with Result&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Reserve exceptions for truly unexpected situations&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Introduce newtypes or branded types for units and ids&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Prevent mixing &lt;code&gt;Millis&lt;/code&gt;with&lt;code&gt;Seconds&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Cents&lt;/code&gt;with&lt;code&gt;Dollars&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Prevent mixing &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Enforce exhaustiveness&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;OCaml already warns&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;TypeScript: discriminated unions, &lt;code&gt;assertNever&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;strictNullChecks&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;noImplicitReturns&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Add guard rails in CI&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Treat TypeScript non exhaustive switches and OCaml warnings as errors&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smells to look for&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multiple booleans that can be true at the same time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Strings that travel far before being validated&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Functions that sometimes return a value and sometimes throw&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Types that carry numbers without units&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;10) Performance and ergonomics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pattern matching compiles to simple branches. Discriminated unions in TypeScript are just plain objects. The main cost you will feel is validation at the boundaries in smart constructors. This is a trade worth making. The compiler then protects the interior of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reliability is designed. With Algebraic Data Types, pattern matching, Option and Result, immutability, and smart constructors, you encode domain rules directly in your types. Illegal states cannot compile. This is why industries that cannot afford failure, such as banking and telecom, gravitate to functional ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you work on code that touches money, minutes, or public availability, adopt these patterns now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Model workflows with sum types, not conflicting flags&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use Option and Result instead of nullable and throwable APIs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Keep a pure core with effects at the edges&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Brand units and identifiers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enforce exhaustiveness during code review and in CI&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your on call shifts will be quieter, and your users will notice the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Further reading&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Functional programming&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Algebraic data type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tagged union or sum type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Product type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pattern matching&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Immutable object&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pure function&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;High availability&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Appendix: paste ready helpers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript Option and Result
export type None = { _tag: "None" }
export type Some&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Some"; value: T }
export type Option&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; = None | Some&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;
export const None: None = { _tag: "None" }
export const Some = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Option&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Some", value })

export type Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;  = { _tag: "Ok"; value: T }
export type Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Err"; error: E }
export type Result&amp;lt;T, E&amp;gt; = Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; | Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt;
export const Ok  = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Result&amp;lt;T, never&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Ok", value })
export const Err = &amp;lt;E&amp;gt;(error: E): Result&amp;lt;never, E&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Err", error })

export const assertNever = (x: never): never =&amp;gt; { throw new Error(`Unhandled variant: ${JSON.stringify(x)}`) }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml Option and Result helpers *)
let option_map f = function
  | None -&amp;gt; None
  | Some x -&amp;gt; Some (f x)

let option_value ~default = function
  | None -&amp;gt; default
  | Some x -&amp;gt; x

let result_map f = function
  | Ok x -&amp;gt; Ok (f x)
  | Error e -&amp;gt; Error e
&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46406901</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 00:05:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Replacing JavaScript with Just HTML</title><link>https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/27/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e52da19219ff136"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can also use other input types:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;label for="quantity"&amp;gt;Quantity&amp;lt;/label&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that, at the time of this writing, Firefox was limited to only textual-based input types, so no &lt;code&gt;date&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;time&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;range&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;color&lt;/code&gt; for now... :-(&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also note that, at the time of this writing, there are limitations on mobile, and accessibility concerns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;popover&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;popovertarget&lt;/code&gt; attributes can replace the traditional JS-driven modal/popover/overlay:&lt;lb/&gt;CodePen: Modal / Popover&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An &lt;code&gt;auto&lt;/code&gt; popover (default) can be "light dismissed" (clicking outside of it or hitting the &lt;code&gt;esc&lt;/code&gt; key). Opening an &lt;code&gt;auto&lt;/code&gt; automatically closes any other &lt;code&gt;auto&lt;/code&gt; popovers that were open. Clicking the &lt;code&gt;button&lt;/code&gt; a second time will close the one it opened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button popovertarget="pop-auto"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;hint&lt;/code&gt; popover can also be "light dismissed". It does not close other &lt;code&gt;hint&lt;/code&gt; popovers when opened. Clicking the &lt;code&gt;button&lt;/code&gt; a second time will close the one it opened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button popovertarget="pop-hint"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that, at the time of this writing, Firefox and all iOS varieties do not support &lt;code&gt;hint&lt;/code&gt; popovers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;manual&lt;/code&gt; popover can not be "light dismissed". It does not close other &lt;code&gt;manual&lt;/code&gt; popovers when opened. Clicking the &lt;code&gt;button&lt;/code&gt; a second time will close the one it opened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button popovertarget="pop-manual"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Learn more about the opening and closing dialogs and popovers in the previously-published âControlling dialogs and popovers with the Invoker Commands API".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;popover&lt;/code&gt; page&lt;p&gt;The above Modal / Popover functionality can also be used to create an offscreen navigation that requires no JS:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CodePen: Offscreen Content&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button popovertarget="menu"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;#menu {&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;I use a &lt;code&gt;nav&lt;/code&gt; element to give it semantic value, but you can use any HTML element (&lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;section&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;aside&lt;/code&gt;, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;popover&lt;/code&gt; defaults to &lt;code&gt;position: fixed&lt;/code&gt; per the User Agent Stylesheet, and is simply pushed off screen when closed, and pulled back onscreen when it is open. Note that &lt;code&gt;margin: 0&lt;/code&gt; is required if you want to override the User Agent center-alignment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clicking outside of the above menu closes it. You can force the panel to stay open, requiring a manual/explicit close, by using &lt;code&gt;popover="manual"&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can also add a &lt;code&gt;backdrop&lt;/code&gt; pseudo element and style it as you wish:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;#menu::backdrop {&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;While we all love the power and flexibility JS provides, we should also respect it, and our users, by limiting its use to what it needs to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is so much more that has changed in recent years, including a ton of options that CSS now covers. If you are now hungry for more, have a look at [my longer article that covers those as well](https://aarontgrogg.com/blog/2023/05/31/replace-js-with-no-js-or-lo-js-options/.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy reducing!&lt;lb/&gt;Atg&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Web Developer / Performance Optimization Specialist&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blog: aarontgrogg.com&lt;lb/&gt;BlueSky: aarontgrogg.bsky.social&lt;lb/&gt;Mastodon: mastodon.social/@aarontgrogg&lt;lb/&gt;LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/aarontgrogg&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46407337</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 01:07:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fathers’ choices may be packaged and passed down in sperm RNA</title><link>https://www.quantamagazine.org/how-dads-fitness-may-be-packaged-and-passed-down-in-sperm-rna-20251222/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f66c934f689e0b5b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How Dad’s Fitness May Be Packaged and Passed Down in Sperm RNA&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The standard sperm-meets-egg story posits that sperm cells are hardly more than bundles of shrink-wrapped DNA with tails. Their mission is simple: Deliver a father’s genes into a mother’s egg for sexual reproduction. Just about all other aspects of a developing embryo, including its cellular and environmental components, have nothing to do with dad. Those all come from mom.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But nearly two decades of studies from multiple independent labs threaten to rewrite that story. They suggest that dad’s gametes shuttle more than DNA: Within a sperm’s minuscule head are stowaway molecules, which enter the egg and convey information about the father’s fitness, such as diet, exercise habits and stress levels, to his offspring. These non-DNA transfers may influence genomic activity that boots up during and after fertilization, exerting some control over the embryo’s development and influencing the adult they will become.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The findings, so far largely described in mouse models, could end up changing the way we think about heredity. They suggest “that what we do in this life affects the next generation,” said Qi Chen, a reproductive and developmental biologist at the University of Utah Medical School who is among the pioneers of this research. In other words: What a father eats, drinks, inhales, is stressed by or otherwise experiences in the weeks and months before he conceives a child might be encoded in molecules, packaged into his sperm cells and transmitted to his future kid. The researchers have largely zeroed in on RNA molecules, those short-lived copies of DNA that reflect genetic activity at a given time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a tantalizing notion. But the mechanistic details — how experience is encoded, how it’s transferred from sperm to egg, and whether and how it affects a developing embryo — are not easy to unpack, especially given the challenges of conducting research in human subjects. For this reason, and because of the potentially textbook-rewriting implications of the findings, researchers, including those spearheading the work, are cautious about overselling their results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s still very hand-wavy,” said the epigeneticist Colin Conine of the University of Pennsylvania Perelman School of Medicine and Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, who has been trying to uncover the mechanics of how sperm RNA can contribute nongenetic information to progeny. Some elements of the story are clear, he said: Researchers have significant evidence that the environment can regulate sperm RNAs, that these molecules transmit traits to offspring and that they can regulate embryonic development after fertilization. “We just don’t have really any understanding of how RNAs can do this, and that’s the hand-wavy part,” Conine said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But evidence keeps piling up. Most recently, in November 2025, a comprehensive paper published in Cell Metabolism traced the downstream molecular effects of a father mouse’s exercise regimen on sperm microRNAs that target genes “critical for mitochondrial function and metabolic control” in a developing embryo. The researchers found many of those same RNAs overexpressed in the sperm of well-exercised human men.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This study shows that paternal exercise can confer benefits — enhanced endurance and metabolic health — to offspring,” said Chen, who was not involved in the study. “It’s a powerful reminder that many sperm-mediated epigenetic effects are deeply adaptive in nature.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The possibility that a previously undocumented avenue of inheritance is at play is too important to ignore. That’s why the researchers are now hunkering down in their labs to trace out the molecular processes that would have to operate for a father’s here-and-now experience to be transferred as developmental instructions to his partner’s egg.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Epigenetic Avenues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In most animals, a sperm cell is tiny compared to an egg cell. In humans, an egg contains 10 million times the volume of a sperm and contributes most cellular components — nutrition, cytoplasm, mitochondria and other organelles, the molecular machinery to make proteins, and more — to a zygote (a newly fertilized egg that hasn’t started dividing). Plus, a mother provides the environment within which an embryo and then fetus develops and grows. As a result, the effect of a mother’s health on her children has long been scrutinized, including at the molecular level. But over the past 15 years or so, the evidence for some kind of non-DNA inheritance of paternal experience has also been strengthening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“There are many different labs that have done diet and stress studies, and typically the readouts of those in the next generation are either metabolism or behavioral changes,” Conine said. Feed a male mouse a high-fat or low-protein diet, or take him away from his mom when he is young, and his offspring will inherit traits, such as changes in mitochondrial function, related to those environmental conditions. These traits aren’t necessarily detrimental. For instance, mouse fathers exposed to nicotine sire male pups with livers that are good at disarming not just nicotine but cocaine and other toxins as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a survival logic here, said Oliver Rando, an epigeneticist at the University of Massachusetts Chan Medical School who led the nicotine study. It’s reasonable to expect that offspring will experience an environmental context similar to that of their parents. Biologically priming them for those conditions could therefore help them survive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“You might think of this as a way to tell your kids something useful for them so that they can be better at dealing with the world they inherit,” said Rando, a father of two boys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But logic does not make the story true. That’s why Chen, Rando, Conine and other researchers have been working to uncover the mechanistic components of dad-based epigenetic heredity to add to what is already known about these processes in mothers. “Epigenetics” refers to heredity processes that do not change the DNA sequences of genes, but rather involve when and to what degree genes are expressed and made into functional proteins. Epigeneticists focus on the molecular biology that unfolds around genomic and chromosomal frameworks that can switch genes on and off in response to internal and external cues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This kind of differential gene expression is central to some of biology’s greatest wonders — for example, the fact that all cells in the human body have the same DNA, and yet brain cells differ dramatically from liver, skin and blood cells. Some cues that trigger changes in gene expression are programmed into DNA, while others come from the environment — for example, a dearth of calories or nutrients due to food deprivation, or rising cortisol levels due to stressors such as the absence of parental care. These conditions affect the kinds of metabolites and other molecules circulating in our bodies, which influences what kinds of reactions and genomic processes cells can carry out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some molecules involved in epigenetic processes, such as methyl or acetyl groups, interface directly with DNA or bind to proteins attached to DNA. These actions loosen up or batten down portions of the genome and are akin to opening or closing doors to specific genes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RNA molecules — flexible, ephemeral versions of DNA sequences — can also intervene in gene expression. But because they are relatively short-lived, sometimes surviving mere minutes or hours before degrading, they have been overlooked as epigenetic regulators. Since the 1990s, their roles have been clarified, as has their longevity: Certain RNAs can survive for weeks or longer. Some RNAs (such as long noncoding RNAs, or lncRNAs) regulate gene expression by modifying DNA or its proteins. Others, known as microRNAs, alter or repress other RNAs, including those that would otherwise be translated into proteins; this discovery was awarded the 2024 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could sperm carry RNA or other molecules that then participate in epigenetic processes in the embryo? It seemed plausible to some researchers, but it would take a whole lot of experimental work to put the pieces together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Package of RNA&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are three core questions that biologists need to resolve to confirm that sperm cells transmit epigenetic inheritance. The first is how a father’s body physically encodes lived experience, such as stress, diet, exercise or nicotine use, in the form of molecules — for example, as RNAs circulating in blood that reflect gene expression in tissues. The next centers on how molecularly encoded experience could make its way into sperm cells. The third traces how those signals in sperm could become epigenetic vectors during and after fertilization to specify observable traits, known as phenotypes, in offspring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a series of studies beginning in 2012, Qi Chen started answering all three questions. In what he describes as one of the most serendipitous discoveries of his career, his team at the Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing used sequencing techniques to inventory the short RNA molecules present in mice sperm cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They were shocked to see a subset of the RNAs drastically increasing in concentration as sperm cells matured, and then crowding into the sperm heads with DNA. This same class of RNAs was abundant in the blood serum of various vertebrates, ranging from fish to humans, they found. All of this pointed to the possibility that information-carrying molecules were being transferred into the reproductive cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It got even more interesting when Chen, who moved to the U.S. academic circuit in 2015, and his team collected sperm RNAs from male mice fed different diets. The RNA assemblages in mice reared on high-fat foods differed dramatically from those in mice that were fed normal diets. And when the researchers injected the RNAs from the sperm of the fat-eating mice into a zygote, some of the male offspring showed metabolic issues associated with a high-fat diet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The experiments hinted at a seemingly heretical possibility, Chen said: that “certain acquired traits during paternal exposure can be ‘memorized’ in the sperm and inherited by the offspring.” After characterizing a pathway that regulates sperm RNAs, in 2019 Chen dubbed this channel of heredity the “sperm RNA code,” which he suggested “programs the metabolic health of offspring.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He wasn’t the only one to become fixated on this idea. Around the same time, in an article published in Developmental Cell in 2018, Rando’s team reported the use of biochemical techniques to characterize where and when RNAs are packaged into sperm cells and how those RNAs might change during this process. They were trying to answer the question: “What tissue could be responsible for choosing what to tell sperm to tell kids?” he said. One logical place to start looking was the epididymis. Within this tubular organ attached to the back of the testicle, sperm cells undergo a maturation process, taking about one to two weeks in most mammalian species, before they become ready for fertilization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rando’s data showed that sperm cells gain almost all their small RNAs when they are in the epididymis. Using techniques for tracking specific RNA molecules, the scientists observed RNAs getting packaged into virus-size capsules, called epididymosomes, which shuttled the molecules into sperm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This shows how small RNAs can get trafficked between the body’s nonreproductive cells, like those in the epididymis, and germline cells,” such as sperm, Rando said. “The epididymis has been emerging as a key location for paternal effects. Certainly the epididymis has to be taken seriously as a potential sensor of the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Molecular Snapshot&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By “sensor of the world,” Rando is referring to the first stage of a presumed paternal-effects mechanism — when a male’s body translates a lived condition, such as a high-fat diet, rigorous exercise or toxin exposure, into molecular signals. The epididymis then provides a route for the second step, packaging those signals for the next generation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is also where investigations by Isabelle Mansuy come in. At the University of Zurich and the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology Zurich, she studies the molecular and cellular mechanisms of epigenetic inheritance in mammals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;© Philippe Rossier / Ringier Media Switzerland&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In one line of her research, she focuses on processes that transmit the molecular effects of traumatic stress to subsequent generations by focusing on extracellular vesicles (EVs) that circulate in blood. Shed by almost every type of cell in the body, including in the epididymis (the epididymosomes are EVs), they carry a diversity of molecular cargo, such as RNAs, proteins, lipids and metabolites. Because EVs circulate in blood just about anywhere in the body and can cross cell membranes, they provide a potential means to transfer molecules and the biological cues they carry between bodily tissues and reproductive cells. Notably, RNAs tend to survive longer when packaged in EVs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mansuy creates trauma in mice by subjecting the animals to conditions such as restraint or maternal separation when they are young. Then she searches for molecular changes in reproductive cells that could cause similar consequences of trauma to manifest in the children or even grandchildren of the animals who directly endure it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She’s shown that traumatic stress alters metabolic pathways, especially those that involve lipids, in exposed male mice and their offspring. She has also found a similar metabolic profile in humans who experienced high stress in childhood. In mice, some of the metabolic changes remained discernible through five generations — a rare data-backed finding for epigenetic inheritance cascading through generations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dennis Kunkel Microscopy/Science Source&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In March 2025, in a preprint uploaded to biorxiv.org, Mansuy and colleagues reported that EVs in mice can transport certain RNAs, metabolites and lipids linked to early-life stress from circulating blood to sperm, with consequences for offspring. The offspring produced by these sperm cells had stress-related metabolic dysfunction as adults and bore the stress signatures in their own sperm RNA. “These changes imply a mechanistic link between sperm RNA modifications and phenotypic features in the offspring,” Mansuy’s team concluded in their paper, which has not yet been peer-reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Phenotypic Translation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps the trickiest step to understand is how sperm-borne molecules could influence an adult’s observable traits. In one form of experiment, researchers extract all the sperm RNA from mice that have been raised under stressful or health-altering conditions. Those isolated RNAs are then injected into a zygote. Pups that emerge usually “get the dad’s phenotypes,” Conine said, suggesting that the RNAs alone confer traits from dad to offspring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But how? During early development, epigenetic processes reign. As one fertilized cell divides into two, and those cells divide again, and so on, one set of DNA instructions is dynamically and repeatedly reprogrammed. The growing body specializes into different cell types and is sculpted into a sequence of increasingly complex forms. It’s possible, then, that early epigenetic alterations to the genome could have significant downstream effects on an adult.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Research out of Conine’s lab, published in 2024, showed that sperm microRNAs alter gene expression in mouse embryos. Experiments like these, he said, support the idea that offspring can inherit paternal traits via the transfer of non-DNA molecular stowaways in sperm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The recent Cell Metabolism paper took this idea a step further by tracing a mechanism by which this can happen. A team of more than two dozen Chinese researchers focused on the epigenetic transmission of exercise benefits, homing in on a set of microRNAs that reprogram gene expression in the early embryo. These changes ultimately result in skeletal muscle adaptations in adult offspring that enhance exercise endurance. The researchers found that well-exercised mice had more of these microRNAs in their sperm than sedentary mice did. When these microRNAs were transferred into zygotes, the adults they grew into were more physically fit, with more mitochondria in skeletal muscle and higher endurance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But how did the molecules generate the exercise-positive phenotype? In experiments, the researchers found that the microRNAs suppressed a particular protein, which had the effect of boosting genes related to mitochondrial activity and metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intriguingly, the sperm of physically trained male humans also hosted higher levels of many of the same microRNAs than those of untrained cohorts. “This cross-species conservation suggests a potential role for these sperm mi[cro]RNAs in intergenerational exercise adaptations in humans,” the researchers wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The First Draft&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The notion that a father’s lived experience can become recorded by his body, transmitted to his gametes and relayed to his offspring is no longer as outlandish as it once seemed. Many researchers in the field are willing to float speculative visions of what could be going on, even as they acknowledge that gaps remain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Our hypothesis is that the epididymis ‘sees’ the world and alters the small RNAs it produces in response,” Rando said. “These RNAs are then delivered to the zygote upon fertilization and control early gene regulation and development to shape offspring health and disease.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conine speculates that once certain RNAs make their way into the egg, they trigger “a cascade of changes in developmental gene expression that then leads to these phenotypes” of the father showing up in the next generation. Remarkably, this unfolds even though the sheer volume of the sperm’s contents is so much less than an egg’s contents, including the relative amounts of RNA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full picture of how paternal experience and behavior might epigenetically influence offspring is not nearly in hand. Researchers are currently piecing the story together, one experiment at a time, rather than proving out every step sequentially in the same set of organisms. One of the gaps is in the characterization of what RNA and perhaps other epigenetic factors do in the zygote to modify genomic activity as it unfolds during development, Mansuy said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We are still blind men describing for the first time different parts of the same elephant,” Chen said. “The underlying mechanism is almost certainly an orchestra of a sperm RNA code and factors beyond that.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confirming the findings in humans would take enormous effort, but it would be key to turning these findings in mice into “informed medical advice,” Chen said. This would require well-controlled experiments following multiple generations, tracking diet, exercise, aging and environmental exposures, while also using advanced tools to decode sperm-packaged molecules — and then looking for strong correlations between the molecular and phenotypic data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even amid the uncertainties, researchers are cautiously moving forward as they learn to believe the results of their own experiments. If they’re right, they will have discovered a new fact of life, Rando said. When he thinks about his two boys, he wonders what he might have done differently when he was younger, before they were born, that might have tweaked his RNA profile in ways that would affect them today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We don’t know enough yet to develop guidance like that,” Rando said. “Maybe we will get there.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46407502</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 01:33:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dialtone – AOL 3.0 Server</title><link>https://dialtone.live/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46408192</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 03:40:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Calendar</title><link>https://neatnik.net/calendar/?year=2026</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5ff9519dbc2b8b32"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👋 Hello! If you print this page, you’ll get a nifty calendar that displays all of the year’s dates on a single page. It will automatically fit on a single sheet of paper of any size. For best results, adjust your print settings to landscape orientation and disable the header and footer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take in the year all at once. Fold it up and carry it with you. Jot down your notes on it. Plan things out and observe the passage of time. Above all else, be kind to others.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking for 2026? Here you go!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Jan&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Feb&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Mar&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Apr&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;May&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Jun&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Jul&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Aug&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Sep&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Oct&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Nov&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Dec&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 F&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 M&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 F&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 M&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 F&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 M&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 F&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 M&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46408613</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 05:02:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Growing up in “404 Not Found”: China's nuclear city in the Gobi Desert</title><link>https://substack.com/inbox/post/182743659</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46408988</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 06:43:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hungry Fat Cells Could Someday Starve Cancer to Death</title><link>https://www.ucsf.edu/news/2025/01/429411/how-hungry-fat-cells-could-someday-starve-cancer-death</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3348413b9eaeeb1b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Liposuction and plastic surgery aren’t often mentioned in the same breath as cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But they are the inspiration for a new approach to treating cancer that uses engineered fat cells to deprive tumors of nutrition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers at UC San Francisco used the gene editing technology CRISPR to turn ordinary white fat cells into “beige” fat cells, which voraciously consume calories to make heat. The work is funded by the National Institute of Health (NIH).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, they implanted them near tumors the way plastic surgeons inject fat from one part of the body to plump up another. The fat cells scarfed up all the nutrients, starving most of the tumor cells to death. The approach even worked when the fat cells were implanted in mice far from the sites of their tumors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The approach's reliance on a common procedure could speed its use as a new form of cellular therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We already routinely remove fat cells with liposuction and put them back via plastic surgery,” said Nadav Ahituv, PhD, director of the UCSF Institute for Human Genetics and professor in the Department of Bioengineering and Therapeutic Sciences. He is the senior author of the paper, which appears Feb. 4 in Nature Biotechnology. “These fat cells can be easily manipulated in the lab and safely placed back into the body, making them an attractive platform for cellular therapy, including for cancer.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; Cold therapy sparks a new idea&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ahituv and his post-doc at the time, Hai Nguyen, PhD, were aware of studies that showed exposure to cold could suppress cancer in mice. One experiment even showed it could help a patient with non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Scientists concluded that the cancer cells were starving because the cold was activating brown fat cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But cold therapy isn’t a viable option for cancer patients with fragile health. So, Ahituv and Nguyen turned to the idea of using beige fat, wagering that they could engineer it to burn enough calories, even in the absence of cold, to deprive tumors of the fuel they needed to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nguyen, who is the first author of the paper, used CRISPR to activate genes that are dormant in white fat cells but are active in brown fat cells, in the hopes of finding the ones that would transform the white fat cells into the hungriest of beige fat cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A gene called UCP1 rose to the top. Nguyen grew UCP1 beige fat cells and cancer cells in a “trans-well” petri dish. The cancer cells were on the bottom and the fat cells were above them in separate compartments that kept the cells apart but forced them to share nutrients. The results were shocking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In our very first trans-well experiment, very few cancer cells survived. We thought we had messed something up – we were sure it was a mistake,” Ahituv recalled. “So, we repeated it multiple times, and we kept seeing the same effect.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The beige fat cells held sway over two different types of breast cancer cells, as well as colon, pancreatic and prostate cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No fat cells: Actively-multiplying cancer cells (pink) are seen in a mouse predisposed to develop breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fat cells are added: When fat cells were implanted in the breast, far fewer cancer cells were able to multiply.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Cancer is no match for hungry fat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the researchers still didn’t know if the beige fat cells would work in a more realistic context. So, they turned to fat organoids, which are coherent clumps of cells grown in a dish, to see if they could beat tumor cells when they were implanted next to tumors in mice. The approach worked against breast cancer, as well as pancreatic and prostate cancer cells. The cancer cells starved as the fat cells gobbled up all the available nutrients.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once implanted into mice that were genetically predisposed to develop cancer, the beige fat cells were so powerful that they suppressed pancreatic and breast tumors. Beige fat even worked when it was implanted far away from the breast cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To see how the fat cells would work in human tissue, Ahituv and Nguyen teamed up with Jennifer Rosenbluth, MD, PhD, a breast cancer specialist at UCSF. Rosenbluth had amassed a library of breast cancer tissue from mastectomies containing both fat cells and cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Because the breast has a lot of fat, we could get fat from the same patient, modify the fat and grow it in a single trans-well experiment with that patient’s own breast cancer cells,” Ahituv said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These same-patient beige fat cells outcompeted breast cancer cells in petri dishes – and when they were implanted together in mouse models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Knowing that cancers have preferred diets, the researchers engineered fat just to eat certain nutrients. Certain forms of pancreatic cancer, for example, rely on uridine when glucose is scarce. So, they programmed the fat cells to eat just uridine, and they easily outcompeted the pancreatic cancer cells. This suggested that fat could be adapted to any cancer’s dietary preferences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A new approach to living cell therapy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fat cells have many advantages when it comes to living cell therapies, according to Ahituv. They are easy to obtain from patients. They grow well in the laboratory and can be engineered to express different genes and take on different biological roles. And they behave well once they are put back into the body, not straying from the location where they’re implanted and playing nice with the immune system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a conclusion supported by decades of plastic surgery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“With fat cells, there’s less interaction with the environment, so there’s very little worry of the cells leaking out into the body, where they might cause problems,” Ahituv said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fat cells can also be programmed to emit signals or carry out more complicated tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And their ability to defeat cancer even when they are not right next to tumors could prove invaluable for treating hard-to-reach cancers like glioblastoma, which affects the brain, as well as many other diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We think these cells could also be designed to sense glucose in the bloodstream and release insulin, for diabetes, or suck up iron in diseases where there’s excessive iron like hemochromatosis,” Ahituv said. “The sky’s the limit for these fat cells.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;A pioneering scientist is lost too soon&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The discovery of how hungry fat cells could suppress cancer began in 2021, when Hai Nguyen, PhD, joined Ahituv’s lab. Nguyen had years of experience working with fat cells in the laboratory. But he wasn’t aware of their cancer-fighting potential until an experiment pitting engineered beige fat cells against cancer cells tipped them off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazed at how the beige fat was able to starve the tumors, they tested the engineered cells against all sorts of cancers in the lab. The project grew to include other scientists and cancer specialists at UCSF and across the country, offering a proof of principle that the approach could work against a wide range of cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nguyen moved to UT Austin to start his own lab in January 2024 but passed away suddenly in November before he could finish the final experiments. The paper, of which he is the first author, is dedicated to him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Hai was one of the most amazing post-docs I’ll ever have and a great friend,” Ahituv said. “We are heartbroken. He has left us with this incredible gift of a technology that could truly change lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;A pioneering scientist is lost&lt;lb/&gt; too soon&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The discovery of how hungry fat cells could suppress cancer began in 2021, when Hai Nguyen, PhD, joined Ahituv’s lab. Nguyen had years of experience working with fat cells in the laboratory. But he wasn’t aware of their cancer-fighting potential until an experiment pitting engineered beige fat cells against cancer cells tipped them off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazed at how the beige fat was able to starve the tumors, they tested the engineered cells against all sorts of cancers in the lab. The project grew to include other scientists and cancer specialists at UCSF and across the country, offering a proof of principle that the approach could work against a wide range of cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nguyen moved to UT Austin to start his own lab in January 2024 but passed away suddenly in November before he could finish the final experiments. The paper, of which he is the first author, is dedicated to him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Hai was one of the most amazing post-docs I’ll ever have and a great friend,” Ahituv said. “We are heartbroken. He has left us with this incredible gift of a technology that could truly change lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; Authors: In addition to Ahituv, Nguyen, and Rosenbluth, other UCSF authors include Kelly An, Yusuke Ito, Bhushan N. Kharbikar, PhD, Rory Sheng, Breanna Paredes, MS, Elizabeth Murray, Kimberly Pham, Michael Bruck, Xujia Zhou, MS, PhD, Cassidy Biellak, Aki Ushiki, PhD, Mai Nobuhara, MS, Daniel A. Bernards, PhD, Mark Jesus M. Magbanua, PhD, Laura A. Huppert, MD, Heinz Hammerlindl, PhD, Laura Esserman, MD, MBA, Tejal A. Desai, PhD, and Sook Wah Yee, MPharm. For all authors see the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Funding: The work was funded in part by the UCSF Sandler Program for Breakthrough Biomedical Research, the UCSF Living Therapeutics Initiative, the National Institutes of Health (1R01DK124769, 1R01CA283826) and the California Institute for Regenerative Medicine. Ahituv is a cofounder and on the scientific advisory board of Regel Therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disclosures: Ahituv receives funding from BioMarin Pharmaceutical Incorporate. Ahituv has filed a patent application covering embodiments and concepts disclosed in the manuscript. For all funding and disclosures see the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46409928</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 10:04:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Last Year on My Mac: Look Back in Disbelief</title><link>https://eclecticlight.co/2025/12/28/last-year-on-my-mac-look-back-in-disbelief/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="26bce657dc5791ff"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If someone had told me 12 months ago what was going to happen this past year, I wouldn’t have believed them. Skipping swiftly past all the political, economic and social turmoil, I come to the interface changes brought in macOS Tahoe with Liquid Glass. After three months of strong feedback during beta-testing, I was disappointed when Tahoe was released on 15 September to see how little had been addressed. When 26.1 followed on 3 November it had only regressed, and 26.2 has done nothing. Here I summarise my opinions on where Tahoe’s overhaul has gone wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;What goes round&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Almost all the content displayed in windows is best suited to rectangular views. Images, video, webpages and other text crave areas bounded by right angles. Gentle rounding on the corners, as in Sequoia, is fine, but the significantly increased radius enforced in Tahoe is a misfit. This either leads to cropping of contents, or reduction in size of the view and wasted space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cropping is misleading, as seen in this enlarged view of a thumbnail image in the Finder’s Gallery view, compared to the larger version shown below. The thumbnail misrepresents what’s in the original.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among Apple’s claims for this new look is greater consistency. But two windows in the same app, both created using SwiftUI, can’t even share a common radius, as shown below in Providable running in macOS 26.2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Out of control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tahoe has also increased the size of its controls, without using that to improve their clarity. The best way to see that is in my Mallyshag demo app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This looks good in Sequoia above, but becomes a mess in Tahoe (below) because of its changed control dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those three buttons are significantly wider, so now overlap one another and are wider than the text box below. The user sees no benefit to this, though, as the text within the controls is identical.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Iconoclasm&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;App icons need to be both distinguishable and readily recalled. The first ensures that we can tell one from another, and relies on all the visual cues we can muster, including colours, form and content. Tahoe enforces a rule that everything in the icon must be fitted inside its uniform square with rounded corners, so restricting cues to colours and contents. As a result, the icons of many bundled and other Apple apps have become harder to distinguish in a crowded Dock. Some, including Apple’s Developer app and the App Store, are indistinguishable, while others have degenerated into vague blotches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Above are most of the apps bundled in Sequoia, and below are those in Tahoe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Whiteout&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In real life, whiteouts are dangerous because they’re so disorienting. There’s no horizon, no features in the landscape, and no clues to navigation. We see and work best in visual environments that are rich in colour and tonal contrasts. Tahoe has continued a trend for Light Mode to be bleached-out white, and Dark Mode to be a moonless night. Seeing where controls, views and contents start and end is difficult, and leaves them suspended in the whiteout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In light mode, with default transparency, tool icons and text are clearly distinguished tonally, as are some controls including buttons and checkboxes. However, text entry fields are indistinguishable from the background, and there’s a general lack of demarcation, particularly between controls and the list view below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Wet-on-wet&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This technique is used in watercolours to merge layers of colour diffusely, and the best description of some of the results of transparency in Liquid Glass. My examples speak for themselves, and are drawn first from Apple’s own design for System Settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transparency of the Search box at the top of the sidebar on the left renders it incomprehensible when it’s underlaid by scrolled navigational content.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although the view title Keyboard remains readable, bleed-through of underlying colours is confusing, distracting and aesthetically upsetting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My next examples show the same window in Providable with a selected list row being scrolled up behind what used to be a window title bar.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the window in focus, the selection colour overwhelms the traffic light controls and window title, which should read Drop Files. This also draws attention to the limited width necessary to accommodate rectangular content in a window with excessively rounded corners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Out of focus the selected row is less overwhelming, but traffic lights and title have dissipated in grey blur.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m sure that, in the right place and time, transparency effects of Liquid Glass can be visually pleasing. Not only is this the wrong time and place, but those with visual impairment can no longer remove or even reduce these effects, as the Reduce Transparency control in Accessibility settings no longer reduces transparency in any useful way. That was one of the regressions in 26.1 that hasn’t been addressed in 26.2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Summary&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;macOS Tahoe’s visual interface:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fits largely rectangular contents into windows with excessively rounded corners.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enlarges controls without any functional benefit.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Results in app icons being more uniform, thus less distinguishable and memorable.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fails to distinguish tools, controls and other interface elements using differences in tone, so making them harder to use.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Makes a mess where transparent layers are superimposed, and won’t reduce transparency when that’s needed to render its interface more accessible.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe this is because I’m getting older, but that gives me the benefit of having experienced Apple’s older interfaces, with their exceptional quality and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That was little more than a decade ago, in 2014. Not that I want to turn the clock back, but it would be really helpful if I could read clearly what’s on my display once again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46409969</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 10:12:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Building a macOS app to know when my Mac is thermal throttling</title><link>https://stanislas.blog/2025/12/macos-thermal-throttling-app/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="25dc742d3b2ac9ec"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Building a macOS app to know when my Mac is thermal throttling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head class="block cursor-pointer bg-neutral-100 py-1 ps-5 text-lg font-semibold text-neutral-800 dark:bg-neutral-700 dark:text-neutral-100 lg:hidden"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the story about how I built MacThrottle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been very happy with my M2 MacBook Air for the past few years. However, when using an external display, especially a very demanding one like a 4K 120Hz display, I’ve noticed it started struggling more. Since it lacks fans, you can’t hear it struggling, but you can feel it as everything becomes very slow or unresponsive: that’s when thermal throttling kicks in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know it’s thermal throttling because I can see in iStat Menus that my CPU usage is 100% while the power usage in watts goes down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s even more obvious with MX Power Gadget: You can see the power usage and frequency of the performance core dropping, as usage keeps being 100%:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve also hit thermal throttling with my work MacBook Pro. It’s the 14" M4 Max variant, which is the worst variant because the thermal envelope of the 14" is too small for the max output for the M4 max. On my previous 14" M1 Pro MacBook Pro, I’ve never even heard the fans in 3 years…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That being said, I still love Apple Silicon for the performance and power usage, it’s still a dramatic improvement over the Intel days. 🫶&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway, I wanted to know: is there a way to tell if the Apple Silicon SoC is thermal throttling, that is not based on heuristics like in my screenshot?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Getting the thermal state programmatically #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was a wilder ride than I expected. It’s possible to know programmatically if the Mac is throttled, because macOS exposes this in various but inconsistent ways.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The approach that Apple recommends is to use &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo.thermalState&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;Foundation&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ swift -e 'import Foundation; print(["nominal", "fair", "serious", "critical"][ProcessInfo.processInfo.thermalState.rawValue])'
nominal
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sounds good, right? However, I knew that another tool could provide this information, though it needed root: &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ sudo powermetrics -s thermal

Password:
Machine model: Mac14,2
OS version: 25B78
Boot arguments:
Boot time: Sun Nov 23 10:19:29 2025



*** Sampled system activity (Wed Dec 17 09:48:34 2025 +0100) (5001.07ms elapsed) ***



**** Thermal pressure ****

Current pressure level: Nominal


*** Sampled system activity (Wed Dec 17 09:48:39 2025 +0100) (5001.25ms elapsed) ***



**** Thermal pressure ****

Current pressure level: Nominal
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(yes the output has that many newlines)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both report the pressure level to be “nominal”, they must be the same…right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After running a few stress tests &lt;code&gt;stress-ng --cpu 0 -t 600&lt;/code&gt;, I started to see the two values diverge!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For some reason, the granularity is different between &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo.thermalState&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt;. They have a different amount of possible states and they don’t line up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is my empirical experience:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo.thermalState&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;nominal&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;nominal&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;fair&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;moderate&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;fair&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;heavy&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I never managed to hit these states, so I don’t know if they match, but they’re technically defined:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo.thermalState&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;serious&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;trapping&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;critical&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sleeping&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In practice, when my Mac starts getting hot, from the &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt; perspective it goes into &lt;code&gt;moderate&lt;/code&gt;, and when it starts throttling, it goes into &lt;code&gt;heavy&lt;/code&gt;. The problem is that with &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo&lt;/code&gt;, both are covered by the &lt;code&gt;fair&lt;/code&gt; state, so it’s not really useful to know when the Mac is actually throttling. ☹️&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought maybe this was an iOS vs macOS thing? But Apple references it in the macOS docs as well. Maybe it was more consistent on Intel Macs?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon this article from Dave MacLachlan, a Googler working on Apple stuff, from 2020. I learned that there are other CLI tools to get thermal data, but they don’t seem to work on my Apple Silicon MacBook:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜ sudo thermal levels
Thermal levels are unsupported on this machine.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜ sudo pmset -g thermlog
Note: No thermal warning level has been recorded
Note: No performance warning level has been recorded
Note: No CPU power status has been recorded
^C
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the most interesting thing I learned is that the data &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt; shows is actually coming from &lt;code&gt;thermald&lt;/code&gt;. And &lt;code&gt;thermald&lt;/code&gt; writes the current thermal pressure to the Darwin notification system (&lt;code&gt;notifyd&lt;/code&gt;)!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜ notifyutil -g com.apple.system.thermalpressurelevel

com.apple.system.thermalpressurelevel 0
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The various levels are defined in &lt;code&gt;OSThermalNotification.h&lt;/code&gt; according to the article. Indeed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ xcrun --sdk macosx --show-sdk-path
/Applications/Xcode.app/Contents/Developer/Platforms/MacOSX.platform/Developer/SDKs/MacOSX26.2.sdk
➜  ~ SDK="$(xcrun --sdk macosx --show-sdk-path)"
➜  ~ find "$SDK/usr/include" -name 'OSThermalNotification.h'
/Applications/Xcode.app/Contents/Developer/Platforms/MacOSX.platform/Developer/SDKs/MacOSX26.2.sdk/usr/include/libkern/OSThermalNotification.h
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ head -n 52 "/Applications/Xcode.app/Contents/Developer/Platforms/MacOSX.platform/Developer/SDKs/MacOSX26.2.sdk/usr/include/libkern/OSThermalNotification.h"
/*
 * Copyright (c) 2007 Apple Inc. All rights reserved.
 *
 * @APPLE_LICENSE_HEADER_START@
 *
 * This file contains Original Code and/or Modifications of Original Code
 * as defined in and that are subject to the Apple Public Source License
 * Version 2.0 (the 'License'). You may not use this file except in
 * compliance with the License. Please obtain a copy of the License at
 * http://www.opensource.apple.com/apsl/ and read it before using this
 * file.
 *
 * The Original Code and all software distributed under the License are
 * distributed on an 'AS IS' basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER
 * EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, AND APPLE HEREBY DISCLAIMS ALL SUCH WARRANTIES,
 * INCLUDING WITHOUT LIMITATION, ANY WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
 * FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE, QUIET ENJOYMENT OR NON-INFRINGEMENT.
 * Please see the License for the specific language governing rights and
 * limitations under the License.
 *
 * @APPLE_LICENSE_HEADER_END@
 */

#ifndef _OSTHERMALNOTIFICATION_H_
#define _OSTHERMALNOTIFICATION_H_

#include &amp;lt;_bounds.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;sys/cdefs.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;Availability.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;TargetConditionals.h&amp;gt;

_LIBC_SINGLE_BY_DEFAULT()

/*
**  OSThermalNotification.h
**
**  Notification mechanism to alert registered tasks when device thermal conditions
**  reach certain thresholds. Notifications are triggered in both directions
**  so clients can manage their memory usage more and less aggressively.
**
*/

__BEGIN_DECLS

/* Define pressure levels usable by OSThermalPressureLevel */
typedef enum {
#if TARGET_OS_OSX || TARGET_OS_MACCATALYST
        kOSThermalPressureLevelNominal = 0,
        kOSThermalPressureLevelModerate,
        kOSThermalPressureLevelHeavy,
        kOSThermalPressureLevelTrapping,
        kOSThermalPressureLevelSleeping
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The funny thing is that &lt;code&gt;OSThermalNotification.h&lt;/code&gt; is barely referenced anywhere, there is only 3 pages of google results. It seems to be used in Bazel for example. That post was a big help.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s great about this approach is that it doesn’t require root! I can subscribe to the notification system for the &lt;code&gt;com.apple.system.thermalpressurelevel&lt;/code&gt; event to get the (good) thermal state!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a snippet to get it in Swift:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import Foundation

@_silgen_name("notify_register_check")
private func notify_register_check(
  _ name: UnsafePointer&amp;lt;CChar&amp;gt;, _ token: UnsafeMutablePointer&amp;lt;Int32&amp;gt;
) -&amp;gt; UInt32
@_silgen_name("notify_get_state")
private func notify_get_state(_ token: Int32, _ state: UnsafeMutablePointer&amp;lt;UInt64&amp;gt;) -&amp;gt; UInt32
@_silgen_name("notify_cancel")
private func notify_cancel(_ token: Int32) -&amp;gt; UInt32

let notifyOK: UInt32 = 0
let name = "com.apple.system.thermalpressurelevel"

var token: Int32 = 0
let reg = name.withCString { notify_register_check($0, &amp;amp;token) }
guard reg == notifyOK else { fatalError("notify_register_check failed: \(reg)") }
defer { _ = notify_cancel(token) }

var state: UInt64 = 0
let got = notify_get_state(token, &amp;amp;state)
guard got == notifyOK else { fatalError("notify_get_state failed: \(got)") }

let label =
  switch state {
  case 0: "nominal"
  case 1: "moderate"
  case 2: "heavy"
  case 3: "trapping"
  case 4: "sleeping"
  default: "unknown(\(state))"
  }

print("\(state) \(label)")
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prints:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ swift thermal.swift
0 nominal
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that I had a useful value to work with, it was time to build the app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building MacThrottle #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Armed with Opus 4.5, I set out to build a little menu bar app where I could see, at a glance, if my Apple Silicon die was trying to save itself from crossing 110°C. I called it MacThrottle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I built a simple SwiftUI app for the menu bar that shows me the status in a superbly original thermometer icon. The thermometer is filled depending on the thermal state, and its color changes from green to red. I have like 20 menu bar icons and they’re all monochromatic, so the color in the thermometer is very subtle to keep things consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The app is a simple SwiftUI app. Apple provides a scene called MenuBarExtra to render a menu bar control. It was simpler than I expected! To make it a pure menu bar app with no dock icon, you just need to set &lt;code&gt;LSUIElement&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;Info.plist&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;First approach: root helper for &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt; #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I explained the various approaches to get the thermal pressure level in the previous section. But when I was building the app, I discovered later on that &lt;code&gt;thermald&lt;/code&gt; was publishing the thermal state to &lt;code&gt;notifyd&lt;/code&gt;. So at first, I thought I had to use &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt; to get useful thermal state changes. Since that unfortunately requires root access, the app needed root access too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To reduce the scope of what runs as root, I did not run the app itself as root. Instead, the app does not work by default, but it gives you the option to install a helper. It does this through an AppleScript &lt;code&gt;with administrator privileges&lt;/code&gt; to prompt for access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The helper is just a bash script ran as a launchd daemon:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ cat /Library/LaunchDaemons/com.macthrottle.thermal-monitor.plist
&amp;lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE plist PUBLIC "-//Apple//DTD PLIST 1.0//EN" "http://www.apple.com/DTDs/PropertyList-1.0.dtd"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;plist version="1.0"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;dict&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;key&amp;gt;Label&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;string&amp;gt;com.macthrottle.thermal-monitor&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;key&amp;gt;ProgramArguments&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;array&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;string&amp;gt;/usr/local/bin/mac-throttle-thermal-monitor&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/array&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;key&amp;gt;RunAtLoad&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;true/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;key&amp;gt;KeepAlive&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;true/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dict&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/plist&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ cat /usr/local/bin/mac-throttle-thermal-monitor
#!/bin/bash
OUTPUT_FILE="/tmp/mac-throttle-thermal-state"

while true; do
    THERMAL_OUTPUT=$(powermetrics -s thermal -n 1 -i 1 2&amp;gt;/dev/null | grep -i "Current pressure level")

    if echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "sleeping"; then
        PRESSURE="sleeping"
    elif echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "trapping"; then
        PRESSURE="trapping"
    elif echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "heavy"; then
        PRESSURE="heavy"
    elif echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "moderate"; then
        PRESSURE="moderate"
    elif echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "nominal"; then
        PRESSURE="nominal"
    else
        PRESSURE="unknown"
    fi

    echo "{\"pressure\":\"$PRESSURE\",\"timestamp\":$(date +%s)}" &amp;gt; "$OUTPUT_FILE"
    chmod 644 "$OUTPUT_FILE"
    sleep 10
done
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bash script writes the thermal state to a file every few seconds and the app reads it every few seconds!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Using the &lt;code&gt;thermald&lt;/code&gt; IPC notifications #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once I discovered I could use the notification system without elevated privileges, I replaced the helper by code in the app the read the value from the notification system directly. Much simpler 🎉&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Temperature and fans #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wanted to show the temperature and fan speed (when supported) in a little graph in the menu bar app. This would allow me to correlate the thermal state with increased temperature, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, there are multiple APIs to read the temperature. First, I started using an undocumented API from IOKit, but I realised I was getting ~80ºC max, while iStat Menus or MX Power Gadget would show &amp;gt;100ºC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stats, the open source alternative to iStat Menus, helped me use the SMC instead and get the correct values. But the SMC is a much more unstable API because each SoC has different keys to access the temperature data:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;private let m1Keys = ["Tp01", "Tp05", "Tp09", "Tp0D", "Tp0H", "Tp0L", "Tp0P", "Tp0X", "Tp0b"]
private let m2Keys = ["Tp01", "Tp05", "Tp09", "Tp0D", "Tp0X", "Tp0b", "Tp0f", "Tp0j"]
private let m3Keys = ["Tf04", "Tf09", "Tf0A", "Tf0B", "Tf0D", "Tf0E", "Tf44", "Tf49", "Tf4A", "Tf4B"]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though the M3 keys seem to work on my M4 Max work MacBook Pro…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I ended up using SMC first to get the accurate temperature and fall back to IOKit if SMC doesn’t work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Graph in the menu bar #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the graph, I wanted a compact visualization that would show me the thermal history at a glance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The graph packs three layers of information:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Colored background segments for each thermal state (green for nominal, yellow for moderate, orange for heavy, red for critical)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A solid line for CPU temperature with a dynamic Y-axis that adjusts to actual values&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A dashed cyan line for fan speed percentage (on Macs that have fans)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I didn’t want to spend too much time making a super fancy graph system. Since it polls every two seconds, the graph gets very busy after a while. So I decided to keep it down to 10 minutes, since the thermal state history is mostly interesting short-term.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also added hover tooltips using &lt;code&gt;onContinuousHover&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the system was under load, I noticed the graph hovering was not very smooth on my 120Hz display. I found out I can add &lt;code&gt;.drawingGroup&lt;/code&gt; to my SwiftUI canvas to use GPU rendering!. Indeed, I added it, and it was smooth again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Adding macOS notifications #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also added notifications so I get alerted when the state changes, in case I miss the menu bar icon. It can alert on specific state transitions, and optionally on recovery. This is useful to know when it’s time to kill a VS Code instance or a Docker container!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s true that I usually already notice when the Mac is getting slow, but sometimes the Mac gets slow when it’s swapping heavily. At least now I know when it’s just too hot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Launching the app at Login #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, I want the app to start automatically now, since it works so well!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I expected that I would need to write &lt;code&gt;.plist&lt;/code&gt; again, but no, it’s extremely easy to prompt the user to add a “login item” as macOS calls it, using &lt;code&gt;SMAppService&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;SMAppService.mainApp.register()    // enable auto-start
SMAppService.mainApp.unregister()  // disable auto-start
SMAppService.mainApp.status == .enabled  // check current state
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to use it #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since I don’t have an Apple Developer account, I can’t notarize the app, so installing it from the releases is going to require a few extra clicks in &lt;code&gt;Privacy and Security&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And for Macs that disallow it entirely, building from source with Xcode is the only way. I added instructions in the README.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hope this is useful to someone else!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46410402</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 11:51:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Langfuse (YC W23) Is Hiring in Berlin, Germany</title><link>https://langfuse.com/careers</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a8cdb519cd720a6d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Building Langfuse&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Join the team building the leading open-source LLM engineering platform&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;View Open Positions →&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While LLMs improve a lot, we don’t see enough applications in production. Building these applications requires a new workflow of continuous monitoring and evaluation that we enable with Langfuse (learn more about our mission).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are seeing strong traction (see metrics below), thus it is the right time to grow the team to build out our backend systems, product, and how we communicate with developers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are backed by Lightspeed, General Catalyst, Y Combinator, and angels. We are growing fast (see metrics below) and work with some of the best AI teams such as Samsara, Twilio, Khan Academy, and Rocket Money.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If complex technical problems &amp;amp; great developer experiences excite you, we’d love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Marc, Clemens, Max and the Langfuse team&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Team&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Marc Klingen, @marcklingen, GitHub, Linkedin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Max Deichmann, @maxdeichmann, GitHub, Linkedin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clemens Rawert, @rawert, GitHub, Linkedin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Marlies Mayerhofer, @marliessophie, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hassieb Pakzad, @hassiebpakzad, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Steffen Schmitz, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Jannik Maierhöfer, @jmaierhoefer, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Felix Krauth, @felixkrrr, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Akio Nuernberger, @AkioNuernberger, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Nimar Blume, @nimarblu, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Michael Froehlich, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Valeriy Meleshkin, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lotte Verheyden, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Leonard Wolters, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Curious to build with us?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are excited about delivering exceptional open-source developer experiences alongside an insanely motivated team that ships, reach out!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Read our Handbook&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We publicly document our core principles and processes at Langfuse to align as a team, maintain transparency with our community, and help you determine if you’d enjoy working here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Main Chapters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;More Links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The handbook contains many more resources that define how we do things. These might be interesting to you:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Open Source&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Almost everything we do is public. Get a glimpse of our work here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Videos/Podcasts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you prefer watching videos or listening to podcasts to get an impression, here are some suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Public Metrics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Langfuse is the most widely adopted LLM Engineering platform with 19,719 GitHub stars, 23.1M+ SDK installs per month, and 6M+ Docker pulls. Trusted by 19 of the Fortune 50 and 63 of the Fortune 500 companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Work with us&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Curious to build with us?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are excited about delivering exceptional open-source developer experiences alongside an insanely motivated team that ships, reach out!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46410449</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 12:00:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'PromptQuest' is the worst game of 2025 (trying to make chatbots work)</title><link>https://www.theregister.com/2025/12/26/ai_is_like_adventure_games/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b72019fa8f83db75"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;'PromptQuest' is the worst game of 2025. You play it when trying to make chatbots work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Everything you hated about text adventure games is now being sold as a productivity tool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Opinion When Microsoft recently decided to open source the seminal text adventure game Zork, I contemplated revisiting it during the festive season... until I realized I've spent much of 2025 experiencing the worst of such games when using AI chatbots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adventure games like Zork and its many imitators invited players to explore a virtual world, often a Tolkien-esque cave, that existed only as words.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"You enter a dark room. A Goblin pulls a rusty knife from its belt and prepares to attack!" was a typical moment in such games. Players, usually armed with imagined medieval weapons, might respond "Hit Goblin" in the expectation that phrase would see them draw a sword to smite the monster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the game might respond to "Hit Goblin" by informing players "You punch the Goblin."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Goblin would dodge the punch and stab the player with the rusty knife.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Game over... until the player tried "Hit Goblin with sword" or "Stab Goblin" or whatever other syntax the game required, assuming they didn't just give up out of frustration at having to guess the correct verb/noun combination.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adventure games were big in the 1980s, a time when computers were flaky and unpredictable, and AI was an imagined technology. Games that required obscure syntax were mostly tolerable and generally excused.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm less tolerant of AI making me learn its language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, I recently prompted Microsoft's Copilot chatbot to scour data available online and convert some elements of it into a downloadable spreadsheet. The bot accepted that request and produced a Python script that it claimed will write a spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In other AI experiments, I have found that the same prompt produces different results on different days. One prompt I use to check I haven't left any terrible typos in stories produces responses in a different format every time I use it. Microsoft has also, in its wisdom, decided to offer different versions of Copilot in Office and in its desktop app. Each produces different results from the same prompt and the same source material.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using AI has therefore become a non-stop experiment in "Hit/Kill/Stab/Smite Goblin."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Microsoft research shows chatbots seeping into everyday life&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;US teens not only love AI, but also let it rot their brains&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Brits believe the bots even though study finds they're often talking nonsense&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Now you can share your AI delusions with Group ChatGPT&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And when Copilot starts using a new model, which it does without any change to its UI, prompts that worked reliably in the past produce different results, meaning I need to relearn what works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My point here is not that chatbots do dumb things and make mistakes. It's that working with this tech feels like groping through a cave in the dark – a horrible game I call "PromptQuest" – while being told this is improving my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After Copilot gave me a Python script instead of a spreadsheet, I played a long session of PromptQuest during which Microsoft's AI responded to many different prompts by repeatedly telling me it was ready to make a spreadsheet, would make it available to download, and had completed the job to my satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It never delivered the spreadsheet, and my frustration grew to the point at which I instructed Copilot to produce a progress bar so I could see it work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can see the results above. Ironically, I think it looks a lot like the output of a text adventure game. ®&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46411040</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 13:42:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Designing Predictable LLM-Verifier Systems for Formal Method Guarantee</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02080</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e89c2c0b05c79c88"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Artificial Intelligence&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 30 Nov 2025 (v1), last revised 16 Dec 2025 (this version, v2)]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:The 4/$δ$ Bound: Designing Predictable LLM-Verifier Systems for Formal Method Guarantee&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:The integration of Formal Verification tools with Large Language Models (LLMs) offers a path to scale software verification beyond manual workflows. However, current methods remain unreliable: without a solid theoretical footing, the refinement process acts as a black box that may oscillate, loop, or diverge. This work bridges this critical gap by developing an LLM-Verifier Convergence Theorem, providing the first formal framework with provable guarantees for termination in multi-stage verification pipelines. We model the interaction not as a generic loop, but as a sequential absorbing Markov Chain comprising four essential engineering stages: \texttt{CodeGen}, \texttt{Compilation}, \texttt{InvariantSynth}, and \texttt{SMTSolving}. We prove that for any non-zero stage success probability ($\delta &amp;gt; 0$), the system reaches the \texttt{Verified} state almost surely. Furthermore, because of the sequential nature of the pipeline, we derive a precise latency bound of $\mathbb{E}[n] \leq 4/\delta$. We stress-tested this prediction in an extensive empirical campaign comprising over 90,000 trials. The results match the theory with striking consistency: every run reached verification, and the empirical convergence factor clustered tightly around $C_f\approx 1.0$, confirming that the $4/\delta$ bound accurately mirrors system behavior rather than serving as a loose buffer. Based on this data, we identify three distinct operating zones -- marginal, practical, and high-performance -- and propose a dynamic calibration strategy to handle parameter drift in real-world environments. Together, these contributions replace heuristic guesswork with a rigorous architectural foundation, enabling predictable resource planning and performance budgeting for safety-critical software.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Submission history&lt;/head&gt;From: Pierre Dantas [view email]&lt;p&gt;[v1] Sun, 30 Nov 2025 22:19:09 UTC (459 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v2] Tue, 16 Dec 2025 22:28:30 UTC (491 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Current browse context: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;cs.AI&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46411539</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 15:02:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Scientists discover beer bottle in the Mariana Trench (2024)</title><link>https://www.unilad.com/news/scientist-beer-bottle-deepest-point-ocean-mariana-trench-667878-20240213</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="375f94ff76befc7d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;News Film and TV Music Tech Features Celebrity Politics Weird Community&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46412210</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 16:29:12 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>