<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 23:09:06 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Meta projected 10% of 2024 revenue came from scams</title><link>https://sherwood.news/tech/meta-projected-10-of-2024-revenue-came-from-scams-and-banned-goods-reuters/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="65c4990d8c33f59a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Meta projected 10% of 2024 revenue came from scams and banned goods, Reuters reports&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta has been making billions of dollars per year from scam ads and sales of banned goods, according internal Meta documents seen by Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new report quantifies the scale of fraud taking place on Meta’s platforms, and how much the company profited from them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Per the report, Meta internal projections from late last year said that 10% of the company’s total 2024 revenue would come from scammy ads and sales of banned goods — which works out to $16 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Discussions within Meta acknowledged the steep fines likely to be levied against the company for not stopping the fraudulent behavior on its platforms, and the company prioritized enforcement in regions where the penalties would be steepest, the reporting found. The cost of lost revenue from clamping down on the scams was weighed against the cost of fines from regulators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The documents reportedly show that Meta did aim to significantly reduce the fraudulent behavior, but cuts to its moderation team left the vast majority of user-reported violations to be ignored or rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta spokesperson Andy Stone told Reuters the documents were a “selective view” of internal enforcement:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“We aggressively fight fraud and scams because people on our platforms don’t want this content, legitimate advertisers don’t want it, and we don’t want it either.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Per the report, Meta internal projections from late last year said that 10% of the company’s total 2024 revenue would come from scammy ads and sales of banned goods — which works out to $16 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Discussions within Meta acknowledged the steep fines likely to be levied against the company for not stopping the fraudulent behavior on its platforms, and the company prioritized enforcement in regions where the penalties would be steepest, the reporting found. The cost of lost revenue from clamping down on the scams was weighed against the cost of fines from regulators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The documents reportedly show that Meta did aim to significantly reduce the fraudulent behavior, but cuts to its moderation team left the vast majority of user-reported violations to be ignored or rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta spokesperson Andy Stone told Reuters the documents were a “selective view” of internal enforcement:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“We aggressively fight fraud and scams because people on our platforms don’t want this content, legitimate advertisers don’t want it, and we don’t want it either.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45845772</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 12:39:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>We chose OCaml to write Stategraph</title><link>https://stategraph.dev/blog/why-we-chose-ocaml</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e1d8bb0b2f1cafc4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why we chose OCaml to write Stategraph&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're building infrastructure that manages other people's infrastructure. State corruption can't be "rare." It has to be impossible. That's why we chose OCaml.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stategraph stores Terraform state as a dependency graph in PostgreSQL with resource-level locking. The challenge isn't building a database-backed state store. The challenge is ensuring that concurrent operations can never corrupt state, even with concurrent operations/users, that database schema changes break the build instead of production, and that JSON transformations are correct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We chose OCaml because its type system catches entire categories of bugs at compile time that would require extensive testing and still slip through in other languages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Type-safe data structures&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's a scenario every infrastructure engineer has seen. Two Terraform operations run concurrently and both read a resource in an &lt;code&gt;active&lt;/code&gt; state. One updates it while the other destroys it. Without proper coordination, you risk marking the resource as &lt;code&gt;destroyed&lt;/code&gt; in state while it's still being modified in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most systems handle this defensively with locks and runtime validation, but race conditions are hard to test and the resulting state corruption usually appears in production, not CI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stategraph tackles this in two ways. Immutability and database-level locking prevent concurrent writes from corrupting state, while OCaml's type system makes the underlying data structures themselves safer by construction. Resources, outputs, and instances are all defined as strongly-typed records, so you can't access a field that doesn't exist or mix up field types. The compiler enforces correctness before anything runs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you try to access &lt;code&gt;state.versions&lt;/code&gt; (typo) instead of &lt;code&gt;state.version&lt;/code&gt;, you get a compiler error. If you try to assign a string to &lt;code&gt;serial&lt;/code&gt;, you get a compiler error. If you forget to handle &lt;code&gt;None&lt;/code&gt; in the outputs field, you get a compiler error with exhaustiveness checking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This extends throughout the codebase. Every Terraform resource type, every state transition, and every database record is strongly typed. The compiler catches entire categories of bugs at compile time, like accessing non-existent fields, missing null checks, or database schema mismatches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The database schema drift problem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You're iterating on your database schema by renaming a column, changing a type, or adding a constraint. In most languages, you update the schema, deploy the migration, and hope you caught all the queries that reference the old structure. You didn't because a query somewhere references the old column name. It works in dev with the old schema but crashes in staging with the new schema.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stategraph uses typed SQL where every query declares explicit types for its parameters and return values. When you change a query's type signature, every call site in the codebase must be updated to match, and the compiler enforces this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This query expects specific types. The &lt;code&gt;state_id&lt;/code&gt; must be a UUID, &lt;code&gt;mode&lt;/code&gt; must be text, and &lt;code&gt;module_&lt;/code&gt; is optional text. The return value is typed as &lt;code&gt;bigint&lt;/code&gt;. If you try to pass a string where a UUID is expected, you get a compiler error. If you forget to handle the optional return value, you get a compiler error.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you update a query to match a new schema, the type system ensures every place that calls that query gets updated too. You can't deploy code where query definitions and their usage are out of sync.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;JSON transformations that can't lose data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stategraph ingests Terraform state as JSON, normalizes it into a graph, stores it in PostgreSQL, and reconstructs it back to JSON when Terraform requests it. Every transformation is a place where data can get lost or corrupted, whether from a field you forgot to serialize, a nested structure you flattened incorrectly, or a type that doesn't round-trip.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Testing can catch some of this, and round-trip tests help, but you're fundamentally relying on test coverage. Missed cases show up when someone's Terraform state comes back missing a field.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OCaml has a feature called PPX (preprocessor extensions) that generates serialization code automatically. You define the type, and the serializer is generated from the type definition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you add a field, the serializer is regenerated. When you change a type, the serializer is regenerated. If you forget to handle a case, the exhaustiveness checker catches it at compile time. You don't write serialization tests because the type system guarantees serialization is correct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is how Stategraph handles Terraform's resource types. Every AWS resource, every GCP resource, every Azure resource is an OCaml type with automatic JSON serialization. We don't write serialization code. We don't test round-trips manually. The type system handles it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Race conditions prevented by default&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Terraform operations are inherently concurrent. Multiple users apply changes, CI pipelines run in parallel, and drift detection scans resources continuously. Coordinating all of this without data races requires careful mutex management and defensive programming, and it's easy to get wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OCaml provides immutability by default, so you can't accidentally share mutable state between concurrent operations because there is no mutable state by default. When you want to modify something, you create a new version explicitly. This eliminates entire categories of race conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One operation can't corrupt another operation's view of state because state is immutable by default. When combined with PostgreSQL's row-level locking at the database layer, concurrent operations compose correctly without manual mutex management or defensive copying.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Error handling with discipline&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Type safety is only half of what makes Stategraph robust. The other half is discipline in how we use those types.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We encode errors as variants and exhaustively match every case. We never use a catch-all "else" clause that matches everything. When we add a new error to the system, the compiler tells us every place we aren't handling it. This is how robust systems are built. Systems can fail in far more ways than they succeed, and the compiler ensures we handle all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This discipline extends throughout the codebase. Every error case is explicit. Every state transition is enumerated. Every optional value is handled. The type system gives us the tools, but discipline is what turns those tools into reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The difference in practice&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The same categories of bugs. Different places to catch them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Production systems that can't afford bugs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn't academic type theory. Production systems use OCaml for exactly this reason.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Terrateam, we process thousands of concurrent Terraform operations daily, managing infrastructure for hundreds of organizations where a state corruption bug would cascade across every customer. We're built on OCaml, and the type system catches bugs at compile time that would be production incidents in other languages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jane Street trades billions daily on OCaml infrastructure. Their trading systems handle concurrent market data and execute trades with zero tolerance for race conditions or undefined behavior. They chose OCaml because correctness isn't optional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Pattern Recognition&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Systems that absolutely cannot fail choose languages where certain failures are impossible, not just unlikely. Testing finds bugs, but types prevent entire categories of bugs from existing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;But who knows OCaml?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the most common objection, and OCaml developers are rare. This is true.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But here's what we've found. Engineers who understand distributed systems, type systems, and correctness learn OCaml quickly. The learning curve from Rust, Haskell, or even TypeScript with advanced types is gentler than you'd expect because the concepts transfer even if the syntax is unfamiliar.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More importantly, OCaml codebases are stable. We're not debugging race conditions or chasing down production crashes from schema drift. We're not writing extensive test suites for serialization edge cases. We're building features while the type system handles the category of bugs that would otherwise consume engineering time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you encode correctness in types, maintenance gets easier instead of harder. New engineers spend less time understanding implicit invariants and more time writing code the compiler verifies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Correctness as a feature&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're building Stategraph to manage Terraform state for infrastructure that runs production applications. State corruption has to be impossible instead of unlikely. Invalid state transitions need to be prevented by the compiler instead of caught by tests. Schema drift needs to break the build instead of production.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's what OCaml gives us. It provides a type system that makes entire categories of bugs impossible instead of just unlikely. The compiler proves properties about our code that testing can only approximate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OCaml's compile-time guarantees are why we use it to build Stategraph.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45845958</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 13:10:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenMW 0.50.0 Released – open-source Morrowind reimplementation</title><link>https://openmw.org/2025/openmw-0-50-0-released/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45846090</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 13:25:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I'm making a small RPG and I need feeback regarding performance</title><link>https://jslegenddev.substack.com/p/im-making-a-small-rpg-and-i-need</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45846360</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 13:52:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I Love OCaml</title><link>https://mccd.space/posts/ocaml-the-worlds-best/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e7b610ff8bbeacc1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pub rsa4096 2023-09-22 [SC]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;uid Marc Coquand &amp;lt;marc@mccd.space&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every morning, I wake up and ask myself: why isn’t OCaml more popular? I mean, the language is not perfect, but the more I use it the more I feel like this old language had it all figured out, somehow. I mean, not in the literal sense: you write &lt;code&gt;String.of_X&lt;/code&gt;
instead of &lt;code&gt;String.from_X&lt;/code&gt; because the language has French
origins. But it is perfect in the sense that it has everything that is
important to me, except popular adoption. OCaml has its quirks, its old
age, but at the same time there is so much I appreciate about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have some experience building amateur and professional software, in many different languages, and as a result I have collected a list of characteristics that I’ve come to appreciate over time. I think my journey into programming is different from many. I learned and adored functional programming before working in the industry, and while not my very first language, Haskell was important to me early on. Functional programming has allowed me to break big, complex problems down into subproblems that I know how to solve. It has made me a better thinker. Add to that the static guarantees of Haskell, which makes the mental overhead much lower than for other languages, and I am also more productive. Most importantly, with Haskell, I can focus more on the fun parts of programming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, Haskell’s issues lie in its immense complexity and slow compile times. I did say that Haskell lowers the mental overhead of programming, but that’s only if you use a small subset of the language. However because much of the community is very maximalist, introducing a lot of complexity into the code becomes inevitable. Much of the code you interact with is too “smart”, and becomes very hard to grok. Its runtime is also very complex, and there’s always the chance of running into notorious “space leaks”, that are extremely hard to debug.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At some point, I started exploring a language that is probably the polar opposite to Haskell: Go. With Go, I learned to appreciate simplicity and low-levels of abstractions, a good set of tooling, fast performance and fast compilation speed. I also started to appreciate good documentation that is easily available offline. The culture around Go also places a lot of value on simple solutions, which made interacting with the ecosystem easier. I can jump into any code base and understand what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over time, I also grew to hate the issues that come with the language being so conservative: it is verbose in its error handling yet manages to be fragile. At the same time, it doesn’t have explicit null checks. These factors combined makes Go quite unpleasant and easy to write buggy code in. I also found myself missing a REPL or fast way of interacting with the program. The language is “predictably disappointing”, which I guess is a good thing. However, the solutions to those disappointments have been around before the language was even created and I am just left feeling that these solutions could have been implemented, and the compiler would not be much more complex as a result. It just genuinely felt like the Go language designers didn’t want to engage with any of the ideas coming from functional programming. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From these experiences, a list of features I consider to be “good” features in a general programming language started to emerge:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then, enter OCaml. This language just checks so many boxes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m left feeling that the authors of OCaml have good taste. It is an old language, and there are a few features that could probably be left out like the OOP-related features, and some libraries in the ecosystem over-complicate things like in Haskell. But overall, it’s just damn good. There are a lot of other features I appreciate about OCaml that I didn’t share. But to summarize why I love it: the right balance between simple and expressive, good documentation and good tooling.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45846517</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 14:05:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Denmark's government aims to ban access to social media for children under 15</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/denmark-social-media-ban-children-7862d2a8cc590b4969c8931a01adc7f4</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3597dbb934a4cfc9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Denmark’s government aims to ban access to social media for children under 15&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Denmark’s government aims to ban access to social media for children under 15&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Denmark’s government on Friday announced an agreement to ban access to social media for anyone under 15, ratcheting up pressure on Big Tech platforms as concerns grow that kids are getting too swept up in a digitized world of harmful content and commercial interests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The move would give some parents — after a specific assessment — the right to let their children access social media from age 13. It wasn’t immediately clear how such a ban would be enforced: Many tech platforms already restrict pre-teens from signing up. Officials and experts say such restrictions don’t always work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Such a measure would be among the most sweeping steps yet by a European Union government to limit use of social media among teens and younger children, which has drawn concerns in many parts of an increasingly online world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking to The Associated Press, Caroline Stage, Denmark’s minister for digital affairs, said 94% of Danish children under age 13 have profiles on at least one social media platform, and more than half of those under 10 do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The amount of time they spend online — the amount of violence, self-harm that they are exposed to online — is simply too great a risk for our children,” she said, while praising tech giants as “the greatest companies that we have. They have an absurd amount of money available, but they’re simply not willing to invest in the safety of our children, invest in the safety of all of us.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;No rush to legislation, no loopholes for tech giants&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stage said a ban won’t take effect immediately. Allied lawmakers on the issue from across the political spectrum who make up a majority in parliament will likely take months to pass relevant legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I can assure you that Denmark will hurry, but we won’t do it too quickly because we need to make sure that the regulation is right and that there is no loopholes for the tech giants to go through,” Stage said. Her ministry said pressure from tech giants’ business models was “too massive.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It follows a move in December in Australia, where parliament enacted the world’s first ban on social media for children — setting the minimum age at 16.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That made platforms including TikTok, Facebook, Snapchat, Reddit, X and Instagram subject to fines of up to 50 million Australian dollars ($33 million) for systemic failures to prevent children younger than 16 from holding accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Officials in Denmark didn’t say how such a ban would be enforced in a world where millions of children have easy access to screens. But Stage noted that Denmark has a national electronic ID system — nearly all Danish citizens over age 13 have such an ID — and plans to set up an age-verification app. Several other EU countries are testing such apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We cannot force the tech giants to use our app, but what we can do is force the tech giants to make proper age verification, and if they don’t, we will be able to enforce through the EU commission and make sure that they will be fined up to 6% of their global income.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Aiming to shield kids from harmful content online&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many governments have been grappling with ways of limiting harmful fallout from online technologies, without overly squelching their promise. Stage said Denmark’s legislative push was “not about excluding children from everything digital” — but keeping them away from harmful content.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;China — which manufacturers many of the world’s digital devices — has set limits on online game time and smart-phone time for kids.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prosecutors in Paris this week announced an investigation into allegations that TikTok allows content promoting suicide and that its algorithms may encourage vulnerable young people to take their own lives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Children and young people have their sleep disrupted, lose their peace and concentration, and experience increasing pressure from digital relationships where adults are not always present,” the Danish ministry said. “This is a development that no parent, teacher or educator can stop alone.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EU’s Digital Services Act, which took effect two years ago, forbids children younger than 13 to hold accounts on social media like TikTok and Instagram, video sharing platforms like YouTube and Twitch, and sites like Reddit and Discord, as well as AI companions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many social media platforms have for years banned anyone 13 or under from signing up for their services. TikTok users can verify their ages by submitting a selfie that will be analyzed to estimate their age. Meta Platforms, parent of Instagram and Facebook, says it uses a similar system for video selfies and AI to help figure out a user’s age.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TikTok said in an email that it recognizes the importance of Denmark’s initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At TikTok, we have steadfastly created a robust trust and safety track record, with more than 50 preset safety features for teen accounts, as well as age appropriate experiences and tools for guardians such as Family Pairing,” a tool allowing parents, guardians, and teens to customize safety settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We look forward to working constructively on solutions that apply consistently across the industry,” it added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta didn’t respond immediately to requests for comment from the AP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We’ve given the tech giants so many chances to stand up and to do something about what is happening on their platforms. They haven’t done it,” said Stage, the Danish minister. “So now we will take over the steering wheel and make sure that our children’s futures are safe.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AP Business Writer Kelvin Chan contributed to this report.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45848083</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 16:28:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Toxic Salton Sea dust triggers changes in lung microbiome after just one week</title><link>https://phys.org/news/2025-10-toxic-salton-sea-triggers-lung.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="fc1c63126c290be5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Toxic Salton Sea dust triggers changes in lung microbiome after just one week&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Lisa Lock&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;scientific editor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Robert Egan&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;associate editor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dust from California's drying Salton Sea doesn't just smell bad. Scientists from UC Riverside found that breathing the dust can quickly re-shape the microscopic world inside the lungs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Genetic or bacterial diseases have previously been shown to have an effect on lung microbes. However, this discovery marks the first time scientists have observed such changes from environmental exposure rather than a disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Published in the journal mSphere, the study shows that inhalation of airborne dust collected close to the shallow, landlocked lake alters both the microbial landscape and immune responses in mice that were otherwise healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Even Salton Sea dust filtered to remove live bacteria or fungi is altering what microbes survive in the lungs," said Mia Maltz, UCR mycologist and lead study author. "It is causing deep changes to our internal environment."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scientists have studied the gut microbiome extensively, linking it to digestion, immunity, and even mental state. In contrast, the lung microbiome remains less well understood, though it's increasingly seen as important to overall health.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Our lab studies discovered that the dust generated at the Salton Sea can have significant health effects especially in the lung, and it is likely a major factor in the high incidence of asthma in the nearby communities," said David Lo, a UCR distinguished professor of biomedical sciences and study author.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The researchers collaborated on the design of an exposure chamber that mimicked real-world air conditions. The team collected dust samples both closer to and farther from the Salton Sea, then exposed mice to the aerosolized particles during a series of one-week trials.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were some clues about ill effects even before deeper analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Salton Sea residents have ongoing suspicions that the environment is linked to respiratory illness, and our lab has definitely felt the effects of the heat, dustiness, and pungent air while out there on field work," said Talyssa Topacio, UCR graduate student and co-first author of the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The dust also just doesn't smell good," said Emma Aronson, UCR environmental microbiologist and study author. "When we were processing it in the lab, it could be stinky."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the bacterial species that proliferated among mice exposed to the sea dust were Pseudomonas and Staphylococcus, both linked to respiratory inflammation. The most affected samples were rich in bacteria that produce LPS, a molecular residue on their outer membranes known to trigger immune responses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We think microbial products like LPS are part of what's causing the inflammation," Maltz said. "It's like breathing in a chemical fingerprint of dead bacteria."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some dust samples were especially potent. In one case, up to 60% of lung immune cells contained markers of neutrophil activation, showing aggressive inflammation. In mice breathing filtered air, levels of neutrophils were only 10% to 15%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aronson said the findings challenge longstanding assumptions in pulmonary science. "We've seen these kinds of microbial shifts in people with cystic fibrosis or infections," she said. "But these mice had no pre-existing conditions. This was a clean slate, and it still happened."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the Salton Sea lakebed continues to dry, more of its toxic sediment becomes airborne. The research group is examining whether similar microbial shifts occur in local children.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Breathing in the dust over time may have chronic impacts in the lung, and these studies on the potential for altering the lung microbiome are an important first step in identifying factors that could lead to asthma and other chronic diseases," Lo said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The research also raises broader questions. If dust can alter lung microbes, what about smoke, exhaust, or vaping aerosols? The researchers plan to test whether other exposures cause similar disruptions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This study relied on a method Maltz developed over four years to isolate microbial DNA from host tissue, enabling a more detailed look at the lung microbiome than ever before. The next step is to determine whether protective species are being lost, and how long any noticeable changes to the microbiome persist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We've only just begun to understand how dust exposure changes the lung microbiome," Maltz said. "We don't yet know how long the changes last, or whether they're reversible. That's another big question."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More information: Mia R. Maltz et al, Lung microbiomes' variable responses to dust exposure in mouse models of asthma, mSphere (2025). DOI: 10.1128/msphere.00209-25. journals.asm.org/doi/10.1128/msphere.00209-25&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Provided by University of California - Riverside&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45848341</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 16:52:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Angel Investors, a Field Guide</title><link>https://www.jeanyang.com/posts/angel-investors-a-field-guide/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b194193319d635e0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Angel Investors, A Field Guide&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been lucky to work with some of the best angel investors in the business.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I started Akita, my angel investors were my mentor Jason Hong, superangel Elad Gil, #ANGELS co-founder Jana Messerschmidt, Eventbrite co-founders Kevin and Julia Hartz, Stanford professor Dan Boneh, and NBA player Kevin Durant. I became a more well-prepared and well-connected founder thanks to my angel investors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I first became a founder, I had little idea how much working with the right angel investors could help. This post is everything I would tell a first-time founder (who is headed down the VC-funded) route about working angels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Akita’s fundraising story&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first check into my company was a SAFE from Jason Hong, a fellow CMU professor who has been an incredible mentor, both when I was in academia and after I became a founder. At the time, I had only been out of a PhD with a real job for two years and did not have the savings to bootstrap for long, so Jason’s investment was substantial. Jason’s uncapped SAFE gave me the runway to not worry about raising immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sooner than I expected, I raised a seed round co-led by Martin Casado at a16z and Mike Vernal at Sequoia. Once the round came together, there was only room for a small number of checks. Martin and Mike both advised strategic angels instead of friends and family to fill out the round, so that’s what we did. They put together a short list of angel investors who had been helpful to their companies and introduced me. We ultimately brought on Elad Gil, Jana Messerschmidt, Kevin and Julia Hartz, and Dan Boneh.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was at dinner with my a16z investor Martin Casado when I told him I wanted investment from Kevin Durant. It was fall 2018, KD was playing for the Warriors, and he had won Finals MVP earlier that year. I was a KD fan and had heard he did tech investing. Martin said, “How sure are you that you want him?” He sent one text to someone who happened to be walking into KD’s house at that very moment. KD said congratulations and the following week I had Thirty-Five Ventures on my cap table.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;My personal experience with angel investors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2017-2018, the first year of my company, Julia Hartz was running EventBrite so I worked with Kevin. This was before Kevin started his VC firm A*. During this time, he was spending a lot of time with founders and entrepreneurial folks. Kevin had incredible stories from his experience with Xoom and Eventbrite and I loved learning from him. One conversation that stuck with me: I was telling Kevin how my two lead investors had both interviewed a key product hire for the company. One was positive and one was in the middle. Kevin said to always be “strong yes” or “strong no” if I could help it. I still hire according to this philosophy today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jana Messerschmidt was probably my angel investor who was the most generous with her time and introductions. Jana was transitioning from doing angel investing to being a venture capital investor, having just started a job at Lightspeed. As a former exec at Twitter and Netflix, she had a fantastic network and especially in developer experience. Jana introduced me to developer experience executives, founders who had been good at developer experience, and ex-founders who gave great founder advice. Jana gave me great advice about how to leverage my investors: for instance, she told me to make a spreadsheet of customers I wanted warm introductions to and send it around. Jana telling me about how Crashlytics engineered themselves to go viral and introducing me to Jeff Seibert had a huge influence on how I think about developer products.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elad was elusive but the angel who was most consistently influential and supportive during my entire five-year run at Akita. We had a fifteen-minute call almost every quarter, sometimes at an unpredictable time, but always full of great guidance. When I was pivoting the company in 2020, saying that my original space was not working, Elad reminded me it was working for other people, just not Akita, but that’s okay. When I was gearing up for what I knew would be a tough fundraise in 2023, Elad went to work, making introductions to several promising potential investors. Elad has somehow seen every single startup situation and knows so many different founders that he had something concise and on-point to say in every single situation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Figuring out when and how to bring on angel investors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can either think of angel investors as the first checks in, or filling out a round. In my case, I had both: Jason Hong’s check gave me runway as I figured out my fundraise. I met my strategic angels once I decided on my investors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having good angels early on can help you get advice and introductions early on. That said, a lot of folks in the ecosystem will pay it forward and help you even if they are not involved as angel investors. My earliest angel investor Jason Hong was definitely helpful to me early on with advice, book recommendations, and stories from when he started Wombat Security. I also learned a lot from other ex-founders who were generous enough to give me 30-60 minutes of their time. I also cashed in pretty much every favor from friends and family to meet potential investors and to get feedback on the early product. Most of these people weren’t investors!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strategic angels. Strategic angels are who I filled my seed round out with after securing institutional VC investment. These are folks who you add to the cap table for complementary reasons to your institutional investors. Some strategic angels invest full-time; others are operators in a similar space to you. Some folks will bring on strategic angels for social proof. When it looked like the seed round was just going to be Martin from a16z, we had started throwing around names of angels that would be good for filling out the round. After we split the round with Sequoia, Martin told me the split alone was enough proof. We were able to then choose angels completely based on gaps in our networks and expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vanity angels. There’s a difference between a strategic angel and a vanity angel, a celebrity who invests in companies. These angel investors are less likely to be active in working with companies than institutional investors or strategic angels. They often have more name recognition to friends and family and junior hires. A lot of celebrities coinvest with major venture capital firms and many have their own family offices or investment staff. For instance, in working with Kevin Durant interfaced with his investment organization Thirty-Five Ventures, which was more extensive than I had initially expected. Folks will generally work in organizations like that if they have investing ambitions of their own and they were more helpful than I expected in offering introductions. I like the advice to have no more than one on your cap table.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Friends and family. Outside of my mentor Jason Hong, there is one kind of investor missing from my cap table: friends and family. My decision not to take friends or family investors for Akita came out of a personal hesitation to mix friendship with business. There was also little room left in the round by the time it got split between two institutional investors. In some of my tougher moments of Akita, the folks who ended up being the most motivated to help were the friends who had offered to invest, but who I didn’t end up working with as investors. In my own experience on the other side as an investor, the situation where I was probably the most helpful was one with a good personal friend, but it was also a situation where I would have probably given the same support regardless of the investing relationship. For me, jury’s still out about friends and family investors, if you’re also taking VC funding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Leveraging your angel investors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I first started working with Kevin Hartz, he said an investor relationship was like a gumball machine, except with help. You ask for help and you get help.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The best advice I have about working with your angel investors: get to know them. One to two times early on is enough to build a relationship. If they’re helpful, even 15-30 minutes once a quarter or half can go a long way. The more they know about where we are, the more they can help. Plus, these folks were way more experienced than I was with startups. Even offhand stories from their own startup experiences, or those of companies they worked with, were incredibly educational to me. The more they know about who you are, what you’re doing, and what you need, the more they can help. And the more you know about how they can help, the more you can lean on them for help.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The easiest way to keep in touch and stay top-of-mind for your investors: send monthly investor updates. The updates provide context to investors that help them help you: what stage the company is at, what the next big milestones are. At the end of each update, I would always put three to five specific requests for the investors, from helping with introductions to helping with hiring to helping amplify a launch. Upon the recommendation of one of my investors, I also put thank-yous to investors who helped the previous month. The combination of asks and shoutouts consistently got me helpful responses from my investors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s also one more important thing to understand about angel investors: angels can help in ways that institutional investors cannot. There’s one major reason underlying this: if a VC investor is doing their job well, they will make sure to keep investing in your company until they have a good amount of ownership. This means it is against their incentives to introduce you to other investors or do anything else that interferes with their ability to buy more shares in your company for a good price. Angel investors, on the other hand, are generally not jockeying for a large portion of your next round and everybody knows it. This allows them to play a much bigger role in helping you fundraise, from introducing you to other VCs to talking up your company to generate more interest across different VCs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;My perspective from the other side&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a whole spectrum of how investors and companies work together and everybody will tell you something different, so I’ll end with telling you about my specific take on angel investing, in case that helps founders who are trying to learn how to think about the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I angel invest primarily through my scouting relationship with the VC firm Andreesson Horowitz. They give me a budget for investing in each fund and I get a fraction of the carry. The goal is to invest in companies I’m excited about, that also fit the profile of high-growth companies a16z would be excited about. I started scouting for three reasons. First, it gives me more skin in the game to keep up with not only my space but adjacent spaces. Second, I’m happy to pay it forward if I can be helpful. Finally, startups have an unmatchable energy and great founders are fun to be around.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My criteria for companies I decide to work with: I’m excited about what they do and believe I can help. Angel investing is a hobby for me, so it’s really about where I get energy and what I want to be thinking about in my limited free time. I discovered I am almost exclusively interested in infra companies where the team is building a product in a B2B SaaS domain I’m familiar with. I particularly like product-led growth and I love developer tools. As for the specific companies, I need to first and foremost understand and believe in the problem they’re solving: it’s usually a problem space I’ve looked at myself, am interested in looking at, or have personally experienced. Then everything else I care about is fairly standard: how well is the team executing; do they have the differentiation necessary to take them all the way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Parting words&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’ve read all the way to the end of this post, you probably know way more than I did when I started Akita and brought on my angel investors. But I also recognize that I was extremely lucky and would like to help you create your own luck.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So if you’re going the VC-funded route, cap space will be limited, signalling matters a lot, and your network can go a long way in helping you signal. Choose your angels well and they can help you a lot! 😇&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With thanks to Umesh Khanna, whose Forward Deployed Angels series got me thinking about the importance of demystifying the angel/founder relationship. Thanks Umesh for kicking off the series by featuring TLDC and me!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45848468</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 17:03:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Myna: Monospace typeface designed for symbol-heavy programming languages</title><link>https://github.com/sayyadirfanali/Myna</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf9b609b0166edfd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you ever feel like your font treats symbols as second-class glyphs? Are you frustrated that &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; looks nothing like an arrow, and &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; seem ever mismatched?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Want to experience the beauty of ligatures without losing the simplicity of ASCII?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Myna (Gracula religiosa 🐦⬛) is a monospace font which aims to bring harmony to your editor by treating symbols as first-class glyphs alongside alphanumeric characters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Myna was borne out of a need to scratch a persistent typographical itch. While I've tried many otherwise well-crafted monospace fonts, I always found myself wanting to tweak a glyph here or adjust a shape there. After developing Myna and using it almost exclusively in my professional and personal work, I'm sharing it as a small contribution to the wonderful community of monospace typography enthusiasts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are a few of its attractive features that might make it your next favourite monospace font:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Symbol-First Design: clear emphasis on ASCII symbols which are ubiquitous in programming languages&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Near-Perfect Alignment: multi-character symbols like &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;=~&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;::&lt;/code&gt;align seamlessly&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Balanced Weight: symbols have just the right visual weight against your code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Minimalist Forms: geometric shapes for quotes and commas&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clear Distinction: no more confusing &lt;code&gt;1 l I |&lt;/code&gt;or&lt;code&gt;0 O o&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Language-Aware Design: clean sigils for Perl + elegant operators for Haskell + clear symbols for C&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NB: Myna is designed to be a simple font. The current release is a single weight without ligatures, though future updates may expand its features if demand arises. It does work out nicely with synthesised bold generated by fontconfig and pango on Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please click on the image to view it in full in a new tab.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Language&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Light&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Dark&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Perl&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Haskell&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;C&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bash&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Clojure&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Erlang&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;OCaml&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Rust&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;LaTeX&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;HTML&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SQL&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/sayyadirfanali/Myna.git
cd Myna
cp Myna.otf ~/.local/share/fonts/
fc-cache -v&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/sayyadirfanali/Myna.git
cd Myna
cp Myna.otf ~/Library/Fonts/&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Download the release&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Right-click &lt;code&gt;Myna.otf&lt;/code&gt;and select "Install for all users"&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SIL Open Font License, Version 1.1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Myna started out as Hera which was a customised version of Source Code Pro but now has come a long way after stealing many beautiful designs from Fira Mono, Inconsolata, Plex Mono, Office Code Pro, Anonymous Pro. Detailed credits could be found in the Hera repository.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Code banner and illustrations were produced using ImageMagick and Ray.so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Myna is designed to be used universally in every kind of terminal and editor. I've tried to include a reasonable subset of non-ASCII glyphs (mostly geometrical and mathematical characters). However, I'm considering expanding it based on community interest and would welcome contributions in these areas:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bug Reports: spacing and kerning issues, rendering problems, unavailable/incorrect glyphs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Feature Requests: suggest new glyphs or features via GitHub Issues&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please feel free to open issues and also contact me at irfan@irfanali.org.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45849342</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 18:27:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruby Solved My Problem</title><link>https://newsletter.masilotti.com/p/ruby-already-solved-my-problem</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e6c285f6ce2a7b9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Ruby already solved my problem 😅&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;One great question in office hours led me to delete a whole class.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yesterday I hosted November’s Hotwire Native Office Hours.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every month I host an hour long Zoom session for developers to directly ask me questions. The topics range greatly: some folks are just getting started and others are asking very specific, advanced questions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This month we covered everything from registering bridge components to native vs. web-based tabs to authenticating Apple Watch apps! It’s really fun to see what folks are working on in the Hotwire Native space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During the session I shared some code I wrote to figure out what version a Hotwire Native app is running. The app sends the version in the user agent (e.g. &lt;code&gt;v1.2.3&lt;/code&gt;) and then I parse it with the following Ruby class on the server:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;class AppVersion
  include Comparable

  attr_reader :major, :minor, :patch

  def initialize(version_string)
    parts = version_string.to_s.split(”.”).map(&amp;amp;:to_i)
    @major, @minor, @patch = parts[0] || 0, parts[1] || 0, parts[2] || 0
  end

  def &amp;lt;=&amp;gt;(other)
    [major, minor, patch] &amp;lt;=&amp;gt; [other.major, other.minor, other.patch]
  end

  def to_s
    “#{major}.#{minor}.#{patch}”
  end
end&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it works great! I use this throughout my apps to feature flag code based on which version the app is running.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But someone brought up something even better: &lt;code&gt;Gem::Version&lt;/code&gt;. This class accomplishes the same goal: “process string versions into comparable values”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;irb(main)&amp;gt; Gem::Version.new("1.2.3") &amp;gt; Gem::Version.new("1.2.2")
=&amp;gt; true

irb(main)&amp;gt; Gem::Version.new("2.0") &amp;gt; Gem::Version.new("1.2.2")
=&amp;gt; true&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It can even compare prerelease versions, like alphas or betas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;irb(main)&amp;gt; Gem::Version.new("2.0.b1") &amp;gt; Gem::Version.new("1.9")
=&amp;gt; true
irb(main)&amp;gt; Gem::Version.new("2.0") &amp;gt; Gem::Version.new("2.0.b1")
=&amp;gt; true&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The big advantage this class has over my implementation is that it’s built into Ruby!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not even a Rails dependency but part of the standard Ruby library. Internally, this class is used to compare version numbers when parsing your &lt;code&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt;. Check out the documentation, I picked up a few things on semantic versioning when reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve already replaced my &lt;code&gt;AppVersion&lt;/code&gt; class with &lt;code&gt;Gem::Version&lt;/code&gt;. But it makes me wonder what other Ruby/Rails features I don’t know about and am implementing on my own!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The power of community, no matter how small&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I never would have learned about &lt;code&gt;Gem::Version&lt;/code&gt; if it wasn’t for someone bringing it up during office hours. I’d still be using my custom (and most likely buggy!) &lt;code&gt;AppVersion&lt;/code&gt; implementation… like a chump. 😅&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But seriously, this is why I love connecting with folks in the Ruby/Rails community. Every time I go to an event, host a workshop, give a talk… I learn something new. Sometimes it’s small things like &lt;code&gt;Gem::Version&lt;/code&gt;. Other times it completely changes my career, like the first time I heard about Hotwire Native.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve taken this to heart and recently started organizing monthly Coffee and Code coworking sessions in my city, Portland, OR. Every month I post up at a local coffee shop with my laptop and invite all of the Portland Ruby Brigade to join.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This month we had five people! It’s no corporate-sponsored-meetup but it sure is something. And the connections that folks are making during these casual events are real. I’ve already seen folks exchange emails for potential future contract gigs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s the first step you can take today to build some community in your local area? Even if it is just finally inviting that connection-to-be for a beverage… I say go for it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to join next month’s office hours then consider becoming a paid subscriber of my newsletter. I hope to see you there! 👋&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45849528</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 18:45:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>James Watson has died</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/07/science/james-watson-dead.html</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45850069</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 19:30:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Three Emojis, a daily word puzzle for language learners</title><link>https://threeemojis.com/en-US/play/hex/en-US/2025-11-07</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="495f7def6e586e83"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;🏅🤝👑 Three Emojis November 7, 2025 Loading game data...&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45850125</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 19:36:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Should facial analysis help determine whom companies hire?</title><link>https://www.economist.com/business/2025/11/06/should-facial-analysis-help-determine-whom-companies-hire</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45850171</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 19:40:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How did I get here?</title><link>https://how-did-i-get-here.net/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b798a1154e30abef"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This part of the page is still loading while I wait for the above traceroute to load.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Behind the Scenes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To reach this website, your computer sent some packets across the Internet. If we’re curious what that path was, we can run a tool to generate a traceroute — a rough list of every server your packets touched to reach their destination. To build this website (source code on GitHub), I wrote my own traceroute program called ktr (also open source) that can stream results in real time while concurrently looking up interesting information about each hop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How does ktr work? Let’s start with a simplified explanation of Internet routing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting with the source device, each computer that handles a packet has to choose the best device to forward it to — I will explain how these routing decisions are made in a bit. Assuming everything works correctly, the packet will eventually reach a router that knows how to send it directly to its destination.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My traceroute implementation uses a protocol called ICMP. ICMP was designed specifically for sending diagnostic information around the Internet, and, helpfully, almost every Internet-connected device speaks it. Interestingly, ICMP packets have a “TTL” (time to live) field. This isn’t actually a “time” as implied by a name — it’s a countdown! Every time a router forwards an ICMP packet along, it’s supposed to decrement the TTL number. When the TTL hits zero, the router should stop forwarding it along and instead send an error message to the packet’s source IP saying that the packet has reached its maximum number of hops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can take advantage of this TTL feature! To do a traceroute, we can send a bunch of ICMP packets with increasingly large TTLs. The first packet with a TTL of 1 will error on the first device it reaches, and so on, until we hopefully get an error back from every routing device that touched the packet. These error packets include diagnostic information like the IP address of the device that sent the error, allowing us to trace your packets’ rough path across the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Frontend Fun&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This page will work perfectly fine with JavaScript disabled. From the browser’s perspective, this website just loaded slowly. From your perspective, a traceroute magically loaded in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you loaded this website, my program received a HTTP request coming from your IP address. It immediately started running a traceroute to your IP. Then, the server started responding to the HTTP request: it sent the beginning of this web page, and then it left the connection open. As ktr, my traceroute program, gave the server updates on your traceroute, it rendered the relevant HTML and sent it to your computer. When the traceroute finished, the server generated all the text and sent the rest of the website along the line before closing out the connection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that the traceroute progressively loads in lines above the bottom line. Web pages can only load forward. Since I didn’t want to use any JavaScript, I did the hackiest thing possible: every time I update the traceroute display, I embed a CSS block that hides the previous iteration! Since browsers render CSS as the page is loading, this made it look like the traceroute was being edited over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Front to Back, Back to Front&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My claim that this website’s traceroute was the path your packets took to reach my server was a bit of a white lie. To calculate that, I would’ve had to be able to run a traceroute to my server from your computer. Instead, I ran the traceroute from my server to your computer and just reversed it. That’s also why the traceroute at the top seemingly loads in reverse order.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does running a “reverse traceroute” sacrifice accuracy? A little, actually.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I said when describing Internet routing, each device a packet traverses makes a decision about where to send the packet next until it reaches its final destination. If you send a packet in the other direction, the devices might make different routing decisions… and if one device makes one different decision, the rest of the path will certainly be different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This reverse traceroute is still helpful. The paths will be roughly the same, likely differing only in terms of which specific routers see your packet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;So, What Are All Those Networks?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This site began with talk about the “networks” you traversed to reach my server. What, concretely, are these networks?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each network, also called an autonomous system (AS), is a collection of routers and servers that are privately connected to each other and generally owned by the same company. The owners of these autonomous systems decide the shape of the Internet by choosing which other autonomous systems to connect to. Internet traffic travels across autonomous systems that have “peering arrangements” with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Internet is often described as an open, almost anarchistic network connecting computers, some owned by people like you and me, and some owned by companies. In reality, the Internet is a network of corporation-owned networks, access and control to which is governed by financial transactions and dripping with bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want your own autonomous system, you can apply for an autonomous system number (ASN) with one of the five regional Internet registries (RIRs) that govern the Internet’s numbers. Be warned, they probably won’t listen to you if you aren’t backed by a company or you don’t have enough points of presence on the Internet. Just like we use IP addresses to identify—&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wait, what exactly do IP addresses identify? Uh… let’s say they represent devices with Internet access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;… Just like we use IP addresses to identify devices with Internet access, we use ASNs to identify the networks of the Internet. Those are the numbers like “AS24940” in the traceroute from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Notes on WHOIS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I wrote a cool traceroute program myself is so I could pull information on which autonomous systems own the IPs along your traceroute. A couple of organizations try to keep track of which ASes contain which IP addresses. Many of them let you perform ASN lookups using the WHOIS protocol, so I wrote a small client to parse the responses from some servers I arbitrarily selected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I then used this cool database called PeeringDB to figure out the companies behind the ASNs; PeeringDB has information on about 1/3rd of all autonomous systems. I used all of this information, alongside a couple hundred lines of if statements, to generate the text about network traversal for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WHOIS is actually an... interesting protocol to make a parser for. It turns out that the WHOIS protocol specification doesn't actually specify much. It specifies that you should make a TCP connection to the WHOIS server, send whatever you want to look up, and the server will send back some info and then terminate the connection. That’s all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yet, a lot of WHOIS servers will respond with structured-seeming information:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It turns out this structure is made up by the WHOIS server administrator and there just happen to be some shared conventions between servers. Even with the level of structure, the fields you want often show up with different names (origin? originas?) or even under multiple places at once.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My “parser” ended up as less of a parser and more as a lightweight simulator of how I, a human, might read through WHOIS results to find the ASN I need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;BGP&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you send a packet across the Internet, routers sitting at the borders where these networks connect decide which network to send your packet to next, until it reaches the network that contains the destination device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These border routers talk to each other about which networks they’re able to connect to using a protocol called Border Gateway Protocol (BGP).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BGP is the protocol that gives the Internet its shape, and you can’t directly speak it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;History Time&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1969, the same year Neil Armstrong landed on the moon, a message was (partially) sent on a prototype of the ARPANET. Over the next 20 years, this “network of interconnected computers” thing got pretty popular and everyone wanted on the train. Various universities, government agencies, and a couple random companies started making networks of their computers left and right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A couple of these organizations started connecting their networks together so they could share data more easily. The Internet as we know it didn’t exist yet, but these network interconnections were getting out of hand and there wasn’t a great standard for coordinating them. In 1989, engineers at Cisco and IBM published RFC 1105, describing the first ever version of BGP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the next couple of years, interconnected-network people got really busy as “the Internet” rapidly became a thing. Just one year after the BGP v1 RFC, Cisco went public and brought a lot of money into the networking industry, the term “IANA” was first used to refer to the random guy and his college department that were keeping track of numbers on the Internet, ARPANET shut down for good, and BGP v2 was released.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1994, as the Internet-is-a-thing-now whirlwind was just beginning to calm, the final major version of BGP, v4, was specified in RFC 1654. It was revised twice (in 1995 and 2006) and got some patches, but BGP v4 is still the protocol we use for choosing routes across the interconnected networks that make up the modern Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How Does This BGP Thing Work?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Routers at the borders between autonomous systems (“border gateways”) keep a list of every BGP route they know about, called a routing table. Each BGP route specifies the path of ASNs that could be followed to reach an autonomous system that controls a certain collection of IP addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These routes across the Internet are formed by peering relationships between autonomous systems. When the border gateways of two autonomous systems peer, they are typically agreeing to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Allow traffic to travel between the two routers, meaning BGP routes can go directly between the two ASNs.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Keep each other up to date about the BGP routes they know about.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example time! Router A of AS0001 is physically connected with Router B of AS0002 and they want to peer with each other. They send BGP messages to each other to establish a BGP session. Router A now knows that it should go through Router B for any BGP route that starts with AS0002, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BGP peers share the routes they know about with each other in a process called route advertisement. In our above example, when Router A connects to Router B, it would tell Router B “hey, here are all the routes I know about, you can go through my ASN (and by extension, me) to reach all of them.” Router B adds all of those routes through Router A — so, starting with AS0001 — to its routing table. Whenever another one of Router A’s peers advertises a new route, Router A will advertise those forward to Router B.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AS0001 probably directly controls some IP addresses itself. Router A would advertise those to Router B as well. Router B would then, in turn, advertise those direct routes forward, telling its peers that AS0002 → AS0001 is a valid route to reach those IPs. Through this process of forwarding route advertisements to peers, BGP routes are propagated across the entire network of autonomous systems such that any border gateway hopefully knows one or multiple AS paths to reach any IP on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To route a packet to a certain IP, a border gateway first searches its routing table for every route that would bring it to an AS that controls that IP. The router then picks the “best” route by various heuristics that include looking for the shortest path and weighing hardcoded preferences for or against certain autonomous systems. Finally, it routes the packet to the first AS in that path by sending it to that AS’s gateway router which it is peered with. That router, in turn, looks at its own routing table and makes its own decision about where to send the packet next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Recap&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When you loaded this website, it used my custom traceroute program to run a traceroute to your public IP (20.55.15.2), stream that over HTTP, and then render a textual explanation of the traceroute.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A traceroute depicts the path of routers traversed between two devices on the Internet. My particular implementation works by sending ICMP packets with increasing TTL fields.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;These routers are in networks called autonomous systems. Routers on the edges of these ASes peer with each other using BGP. Border routers use BGP to share their routing tables with each other, and then use this knowledge to make routing decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;BGP peering sessions are created according to (often private) arrangements between the owners of autonomous systems. Since traffic can only pass between peered networks, these arrangements are the sole governor of reachability on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Epilogue&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was frustrated with the state of understanding on the structure of the Internet and sought to write a comprehensive, interactive article covering its history and politics through the lens of protocols. However, I got caught up in a lot of complexity in life and, facing tight deadlines, didn't have the time to reach the lofty goals I had set for myself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to the encouragement of my friends at Hack Club, I made the best out of what I had. “Better to ship a tiny raft than never ship that cruise yacht!” If nothing else, I got to make use of the sick ass traceroute program that powers the shiniest part of this site :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hope this serves as another fun, informative, and well-crafted thing on the web that can last, be shared around, and inspire people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With love,&lt;lb/&gt;Lexi&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Other Stuff&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some things to check out:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Proudly open source:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45850382</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 20:01:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple is crossing a Steve Jobs red line</title><link>https://kensegall.com/2025/11/07/apple-is-crossing-a-steve-jobs-red-line/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e1c4f16f912121e9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Apple is crossing a Steve Jobs red line&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can fault Tim Cook for a number of things. Number one on the list, of course, is that he is not Steve Jobs. The nerve of that man!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What made Steve an effective and visionary leader was that his values were so crystal clear. He inspired Apple’s troops to excel in innovation, design and simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But he was also passionate about something that seems almost “old school”—the customer experience. Creating the best experience would lure new customers and build brand loyalty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is how Steve laid out his plan to us at the ad agency when he returned to a nearly bankrupt Apple in the late 1990s. The customer experience was all-important.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From that point on, Steve would go on to spend lavishly on things that improved the experience, and he would reject—often brutally—any idea that diluted or harmed the experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That was Steve’s red line. Cross it if you dare.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And what is the status of that distinct red line today? Sadly, it’s getting a bit blurry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recent reports say that we will soon be seeing ads in Apple Maps. Just as we saw ads appear in the App Store in 2015 and get amped up in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ll go out on a limb and say that uninvited advertising is not normally equated with a better customer experience. Why would Apple do such a thing?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shocker—it’s about money. One can only imagine how eyes lit up in the Apple boardroom as they celebrated a new revenue stream.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Who knows how, or even if, these ads register with Apple users as they become more visible. After all, ads are all around us today, everywhere we go. Still, many will shake their heads in disappointment that Apple—one of the richest companies on earth—is selling a piece of its soul for a bit of easy money.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What would Steve Jobs do?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I usually dodge that question on the grounds that it’s pure speculation. However, in this case, it is not speculation at all. I was in the room when Steve was presented with an eerily similar “opportunity.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some time ago (1999-ish), agency chief Lee Clow and I were invited to a hastily scheduled meeting with Steve and his top lieutenants. The topic was building advertising into the Mac system software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At that time, customers paid $125 for the annual upgrade to the Mac OS. It was proposed that Apple offer two flavors—an ad-free version for $125 and a free version subsidized by ads. Something for everyone! Free choice!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A number of ways to integrate ads were discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One was to show a cool video from a respected company (such as Nike) every time the Mac starts up. Another was to place ads in the OS contextually. For example, an “out of ink” notification might contain an ad for an ink supplier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After spirited debate, there was no immediate decision. But days later, Steve told me he had killed the idea. His bottom line was that it degraded the pure, elegant, clean interface that Mac users love.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It didn’t matter that customers would be free to choose a version with or without ads. He didn’t want any user to see the OS polluted in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He was protecting Apple’s crown jewels. He wouldn’t sacrifice the purity of the Mac experience to make a few extra bucks. He avoided the slippery slope by refusing to step onto it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All hail the red line!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, fast-forward to the present. Apple’s evolution tells us that red lines do not magically live forever. They exist only as long as company leaders want them to exist. Without proper maintenance, they begin to disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whatever his reason, Tim Cook is not as protective of the user experience as his predecessor was. If we were to ask Tim why it’s okay to bring ads into Apple products now, but wasn’t okay during Steve’s reign, the best (only?) answer would probably be, “Today’s Apple is very different from Steve’s Apple.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quite true. And that is exactly the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45850430</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 20:05:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ribir: Non-intrusive GUI framework for Rust/WASM</title><link>https://github.com/RibirX/Ribir</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f0af00b0dad9a36"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use Rust to build multi-platform applications from a single codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ribir is a Rust GUI framework that helps you build beautiful and native multi-platform applications from a single codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experience a novel approach to UI development that's directly based on your data structure APIs. Any data mutation will trigger a precise UI update. Your focus should be on designing your data structure and its APIs. Then, you can describe your data's UI without intruding on its logic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A simple example of a counter:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To use Ribir without DSL:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;use ribir::prelude::*;
fn main() {
  App::run_with_data(
    || Stateful::new(0),
    move |cnt: &amp;amp;'static Stateful&amp;lt;i32&amp;gt;| {
      let c_cnt = cnt.clone_writer();
      let mut btn = Button::declarer();
      btn
        .on_tap(move |_| *c_cnt.write() += 1)
        .with_h_align(HAlign::Center)
        .with_v_align(VAlign::Center);
      btn.finish().with_child(pipe!($read(cnt).to_string()))
    });
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More Examples&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Declarative language It doesn't introduce a completely new language. Instead, it provides a set of Rust macros for easier interaction. You can choose to use it or not.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Widgets compose system has four kinds of widgets to support you can implement your widget in different ways: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;function widget and &lt;code&gt;Compose&lt;/code&gt;, from other widgets composition.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Render&lt;/code&gt;, implement your layout and paint anything you want.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;ComposeChild&lt;/code&gt;, control the compose logic between parent and child widgets and specify the template of child widgets.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;function widget and &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Non-intrusive state converts your data to a listenable state and updates the view according to the change of the state.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Layout system learning and inspired by Flutter Sublinear layout, but not the same.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Event system is a composition event system, that supports event bubbling and capture. Allow to compose with any widget, and exists only if you use it.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Theme System: Supports using different themes for various parts of the sub-tree and enables theme modifications at runtime.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Painter converts the view to 2D paths.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GPU render is a backend of the Painter, do path tessellation so that you can easily render the triangles in any GPU render engine. A wgpu implementation is provided as the default GPU render engine. Tessellation base on [lyon].&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text support basic text typography and IME input, in a usable but rough stage.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Widgets library provides 20+ basic widgets, but all are in a rough stage, and the API is not stable yet.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Platform&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Support situation&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Linux&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Windows&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;macOS&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;iOS&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;🚧 Not yet&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Android&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;🚧 Not yet&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Web&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ribir is actively being developed and tested on desktop platforms, with both desktop and web platforms integrated into our CI/CD pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the framework can compile and run on mobile platforms, we haven't fully tested or adapted the user interface for them yet. We plan to focus on mobile support once the core framework is stable and a production-ready widget library is released.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you like Ribir, give our repo a ⭐ STAR ⬆️ and WATCH 👀 our repository to stay updated with the latest developments!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every encouragement and feedback can support us to go further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are grateful to the community for contributing bug fixes and improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;😎 New to Ribir?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start learning about the framework by helping us improve our documentation. Feel free to open a new "Documentation" issue. We are also very welcome:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Point out to us where our document has misunderstandings&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pull requests which improve test coverage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add undocumented code (e.g. built-in widget)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Report typo&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information please read：&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;🤔 Confused about something?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Feel free to go to Discussions and open a new "Q&amp;amp;A" to get help from contributors. Often questions lead to improvements to the ergonomics of the framework, better documentation, and even new features!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;😱 Found a bug?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please report all bugs! We are happy to help support developers fix the bugs they find if they are interested and have the time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project exists thanks to all the people who contributed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also found inspiration from the following frameworks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ribir is MIT-licensed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45850671</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 20:26:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>VLC's Jean-Baptiste Kempf Receives the European SFS Award 2025</title><link>https://fsfe.org/news/2025/news-20251107-01.en.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b6d75310e006ab2c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Jean-Baptiste Kempf receives the European SFS Award 2025 at SFSCON&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FSFE and LUGBZ have recognized VLC president and core developer with this European award for his long-term dedication to the project. What began as a student initiative has, through his continuous effort, evolved into one of the most widely used media players, with billion of users worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE), together with the Linux User Group Bolzano‑Bozen (LUGBZ), is proud to recognize Jean-Baptiste Kempf with the European SFS Award 2025, in recognition of his outstanding and lasting contributions to the Free Software movement and his long-term dedication to the VLC project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Born as a student project in 1996, this software has evolved into an essential, all-in-one media player that plays almost anything effortlessly. Originally a simple network streaming client, it has grown into a powerful universal media player that continues to evolve and impress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“For many people running non-free operating systems, it was the very first Free Software they ever installed. For many people running Free Software, it saved them from installing and booting into a proprietary operating system”, declared Matthias Kirschner, president of the FSFE during the Award ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jean-Baptiste Kempf joined the project as a student, and when it faced the risk of dying after the graduation of its original developers, he took the reins. With the help of other core developers, he transformed it into the indispensable media player we rely on today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the years, Kempf has become not only the president of the VideoLAN non-profit but also one of the lead developers of VLC Media Player and the founder of VideoLabs. “It’s small, fast, friendly, and seems to "understand everything you throw at it. I have always thought of it as "the program that eats everything", said Raphael Barbieri, a member of LUGBZ, during the winner’s announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;"I am extremely honoured to receive the European SFS Award. The Free Software multimedia community is quite niche and unknown, but we work hard so that video content can be free, can be played and processed. The work done around the VideoLAN community has been tremendous, despite its little resources. I want to thank the whole VideoLAN and FFmpeg teams, who spend their time on those projects, often with little recognition", declares Jean-Baptiste Kemp.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The European SFS Award&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The European SFS Award recognizes individuals whose work has made a significant and sustained difference in advancing Free Software across Europe. Since 2023 it is presented jointly by LUGBZ and the FSFE and honours those whose efforts strengthen software freedom, community building, and the ethical foundations of technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In previous years, the award was given to Frank Karlitschek (2023) for his leadership with Nextcloud, and posthumously to Bram Moolenaar (2024) for creating the Vim editor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2025 Laudatio&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raphael: There’s a program most of us have used - on laptops, phones, tablets or desktops computers. It might have run on screens in supermarkets or shops. It’s small, fast, friendly, and seems to "understand everything you throw at it". I have always thought of it as "the program that eats everything."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias: This amazing software did not come from a giant technology company with a huge budget. It began more than twenty years ago - as a modest experiment by a few students at an engineering school. They wanted to solve a problem they identified. Nothing fancy - just a student project to tinker, experiment, share, and have fun. No one knew that those first lines of code written for “network 2000” would one day reach billions of users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raphael: Like many student projects, it almost faded away when graduation came and the contributors had other priorities. But one young engineer, who had joined the group in 2000, refused to let it die. He reorganised the code, inspired new contributors, and slowly turned a university experiment into a world-class piece of software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias: He built a healthy community fostering the software. Hundreds of volunteers joined. They contributed by programming, testing, auditing, helping others, with translations, improving the design, or promoting the software. Thereby the community grew and people started using the software on every platform – GNU/Linux and other Unix like operating systems, Windows, Android, or MacOS and iOS. For many people running non-free operating systems, it was the very first Free Software they ever installed. For many people running Free Software, it saved them from installing and booting into a proprietary operating system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raphael: With this success our winner was offered tempting deals - big money, advertising, corporate buyouts. Every time, he gently said no. Because it was not about maximising profit. It was about maximising freedom for computer users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias: To protect that freedom, he later founded a non-profit organisation - so the software would always belong to its community. He also founded a company to support the technical side - keeping development professional while staying true to the values of software freedom. Under his leadership, the initiative has reached billions of downloads, maintained and added amazing features - all without losing its soul.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raphael: And there’s another thing this community is famous for - its sense of humour. Their symbol? A bright orange-and-white traffic cone. Legend has it that the original students used to collect these cones after late nights out. When it came time to pick a logo, they chose it proudly - a playful symbol of creativity, chaos, and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias: Nowadays, that little cone has become an icon you find on a huge amount of computers worldwide. At conferences their contributors wear the cones on their heads with pride as a clear sign of who they are and what they stand for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raphael: And the person behind it? He’s not just a brilliant engineer. He’s a leader, a mentor, and a true advocate for software freedom. In 2018, his contributions were honoured with the title of Chevalier de l’Ordre National du Mérite - the first Free Software developer ever to receive that distinction. Yes - a real knight of software freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias: His “Holy Grail” was not fame or fortune - it’s freedom: the freedom for billions of people to watch, listen, and share multimedia files without restrictions or surveillance. He has shown the world that integrity, community, and a bit of humour can change how we experience digital media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raphael: Today, we celebrate someone who has made it possible for all of us to enjoy open, universal access to media - and who continues to prove that Free Software is powerful, beautiful, and fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias: It is our great pleasure to present the European SFS Award 2025 to the president of the VideoLAN non-profit, one of the lead developers of VLC media player, the founder of VideoLabs, the bearer of the traffic cone, and a true knight of Free Software....&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matthias &amp;amp; Raphael: Jean-Baptiste Kempf!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45850751</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 20:31:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>YouTube Removes Windows 11 Bypass Tutorials, Claims 'Risk of Physical Harm'</title><link>https://news.itsfoss.com/youtube-removes-windows-11-bypass-tutorials/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b1c7b814f997e5f3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are no strangers to Big Tech platforms occasionally reprimanding us for posting Linux and homelab content. YouTube and Facebook have done it. The pattern is familiar. Content gets flagged or removed. Platforms offer little explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And when that happens, there is rarely any recourse for creators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, a popular tech YouTuber, CyberCPU Tech, has faced the same treatment. This time, their entire channel was at risk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;YouTube's High-Handedness on Display&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, Rich had posted a video on installing Windows 11 25H2 with a local account. YouTube removed it, saying that it was "encouraging dangerous or illegal activities that risk serious physical harm or death."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Days later, Rich posted another video showing how to bypass Windows 11's hardware requirements to install the OS on unsupported systems. YouTube took that down too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both videos received community guidelines strikes. Rich appealed both immediately. The first appeal was denied in 45 minutes. The second in just five.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rich initially suspected overzealous AI moderation was behind the takedowns. Later, he wondered if Microsoft was somehow involved. Without clear answers from YouTube, it was all guesswork.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then came the twist. YouTube eventually restored both videos. The platform claimed its "initial actions" (could be either the first takedown or appeal denial, or both) were not the result of automation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, if you have an all-organic, nature-given brain inside your head (yes, I am not counting the cyberware-equipped peeps in the house). Then you can easily see the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If humans reviewed these videos, how did YouTube conclude that these Windows tutorials posed "risk of death"?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This incident highlights how automated moderation systems struggle to distinguish legitimate content from harmful material. These systems lack context. Big Tech companies pour billions into AI. Yet their moderation tools flag harmless tutorials as life-threatening content. Another recent instance is the removal of Enderman's personal channel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, actual spam slips through unnoticed. What these platforms need is human oversight. Automation can assist but cannot replace human judgment in complex cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Suggested Reads 📖&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- Even the biggest players in the Linux world don't care about desktop Linux users. We do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- We don't put informational content behind paywall. Your support keeps it open for everyone. Think of it like 'pay it forward'.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- Don't like ads? With the Plus membership, you get an ad-free reading experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- When millions of AI-generated content is being published daily, you read and learn from real human Linux users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- It costs just $2 a month, less than the cost of your favorite burger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Become a Plus Member today and join over 300 people in supporting our work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45850963</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 20:50:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI is Dunning-Kruger as a service</title><link>https://christianheilmann.com/2025/10/30/ai-is-dunning-kruger-as-a-service/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="db41731da96946bc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;AI is Dunning-Kruger as a service&lt;/head&gt;Thursday, October 30th, 2025 at 8:52 pm&lt;p&gt;On January 6th, 1995 two bank robbers in Pittsburgh confused law enforcement by not making any attempts to conceal their faces but instead brazenly looking at security cameras as if they were invisible. The reason is that they actually thought they were.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clifton Earl Johnson had convinced his fellow in crime, McArthur Wheeler that covering their faces in lime juice would make them invisible to cameras. Much like lime juice can be “invisible ink” until you heat the paper. As a test, Johnson had taken a polaroid of Wheeler that showed his face smudged. That a camera fault might be the cause, or doing a second test didn’t get to their mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This baffling over-confidence in their flawed approach inspired two psychologist, Justin Kruger and David Dunning to see if there is a common bias in people when it comes to assessing their skills and their actual performance in doing them. They found out that there is such a thing and it is now known as the Dunning-Kruger Effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;A cognitive bias, where people with little expertise or ability assume they have superior expertise or ability. This overestimation occurs as a result of the fact that they don’t have enough knowledge to know they don’t have enough knowledge.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;One could say that the Dunning-Kruger effect is the opposite of Impostor Syndrome. Instead of people not being able to interiorise their obvious successes, people declare themselves as great and experts at things they have no or just a rudimentary clue about.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years we’ve been on a constant path to make this the standard mindset in the technology world. It started with a demand for everything to be released incredibly fast and to be a huge success in numbers from day one. Anything not growing exponentially is not a success.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fakers instead of makers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Fake it till you make it” is given as advice devoid of any irony. Instead, deception and inflation of numbers is seen as a smart move until you have the resources and knowledge to properly do the task. KPIs and OKRs are meant not to reflect delivery goals but aspirations. When you’re not gunning for a promotion every half year you’re not seen as a go-getter or having a growth mindset. In other words, we encourage bragadocious behaviour and language. Some of the things you hear from heads of states and other politicians in interviews sound like Muhammad Ali at press conferences before a fight in the 60s or old school rappers in the 70s and 80s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;AI bots excel at faking knowledge&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;But even worse, any interaction I have with AI chatbots gives me the same vibes. They give utter nonsense answers with high confidence and wrap errors in sycophantic language making me feel good for pointing out that they wasted my time. A correct answer is a lot less important than a good sounding one, a positive one or one that makes me interact more with the system. Time in product is the goal, not helping me find the right answer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GenAI makes you a genius without any effort&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The siren song of generative AI to turn anyone into an artist, wordsmith, composer or videographer by using “intelligent” tools is a push into Dunning Kruger territory. Vibe coding or vibe anything really focuses not on the craft, but the result. We’re not meant to create by learning the ropes and understanding the art. We’re much too clever and busy for that. Give it a prompt and create a product, an app or an agent that does your bidding. We’re continuously reminded that we all are capable of genius – if only we let the machines do the boring work for us. Our egos are fed, we are barraged by digital cheerleaders and confidence tricksters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Stop wasting time learning the craft&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adding human effort into things, really creating and writing yourself is taunted as wasting your time and not embracing change and progress. But the cost is that we forget about the craft and we lose the joy of creating. Creativity of any kind is messy and fraught with error and drawbacks. But all of these make us human and who we are. As Leonard Cohen put it: “There is a crack in everything, that’s how the light gets in”. Sure, you might not be good at painting, composing, writing or shooting movies. But a terrible, human effort still is worth so much more than asking the machine to build you a boring solution focused on crowd pleasing more than being a thing in itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am not happy about this, and I don’t see it as progress. If anything, it is deception and watering down craft and art. Politics have become an attack on intelligence, decency and research in favour of fairy tales of going back to “great values” of “the past when things were better”. Social media has become devoid of the social part and is a numbers game and addiction machine. But you know what? I don’t care. I keep doing what I do. I write down things I consider important at that time. I paint things although I suck at it. I publish on the web and my own blog because nobody stops me. Sure, I feel like a fraud when people applaud what I do more often that not. And yet – the joy of creation is something we should never give up on. Do you feel like what you do isn’t good enough or worth while? It is, and even if what you did isn’t amazing quality, you’ve created it and it is yours. And maybe, just maybe you are not the best judge to assess the quality of what you did anyways. One person’s disappointment may well be a joy to others. Keep creating and keep striving to improve and if others impressed you, tell them about it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45851483</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 21:44:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Becoming a Compiler Engineer</title><link>https://rona.substack.com/p/becoming-a-compiler-engineer</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45851495</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 21:45:03 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>