<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 16:12:02 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>iPhone dumbphone</title><link>https://stopa.io/post/297</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2286191ddb2639d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I used Apple Configurator to turn my iPhone into a dumb phone. I can only access the apps and websites I want to use, and it’s feeling great!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compared to when I started I’m saving about 2 hours of screen time a day. If I kept this up for a month I promised to write a post about this setup. It’s now two months so here’s my post. What follows is a backstory, observations, and a how-to-guide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get straight to the how-to-guide, click here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s common to rack up 4 hours or more of screen time a day on your phone. Here’s one way to see the cost of that: every 20 years, you lose 5 years of your waking time looking at your phone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what had me dreaming about the 2000s and old Nokia phones. But I couldn’t just go back to Nokia. My iPhone gave me Google Maps, Spotify, Uber and Waymo, Kindle and Audible, ChatGPT and Claude, Whatsapp, Wallet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s real utility to iPhones. If only access to utilities didn’t mean I’d also have access to social media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I often regretted my time on Twitter and Instagram. It would interrupt my flow states at work and detract from quality time with the people I loved. Even alone time suffered: instead of solitude I found myself checking for notifications. [1]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried and failed to fix this problem three times. Let me enumerate:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried self-control but I found myself outmatched. On the surface the solution feels simple: why not just stop using distracting apps? For me using self-control here was like a hunter-gatherer using a club in open battle with a nuclear society. Social media companies spent centuries of human effort figuring out ways to get me to check my phone. If I wanted to win, I would need to use guerrilla methods.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried Screen Time but it was too easy to ignore. Apple comes with Screen Time. You can set limits, but I found them useless. Once a limit runs out all you need to unlock your distracting app is to press a button. Do this a few times and you no longer notice the button.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried switching phones, but couldn’t let go of the long-tail of iPhone apps. There are lots of interesting dumb phones out there. There’s some with e-ink screens that are really cool. But they only have a few apps. There was always some app that I missed. Even with recent Android-based dumbphones, there were still apps that were only available on the iPhone (I am looking at you Things 3).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If only I could keep my iPhone, but choose just the apps and the websites that I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s where I discovered Apple Configurator. Apple Configurator lets organizations deploy specific restrictions onto iPhones. This is what lets Apple Stores restrict the iPhones on display, so you can’t change their wallpaper to something humorous.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Configurator is meant for businesses, but nothing stops us from using it personally. And it’s free too!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I found three advantages to using Configurator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first is that there is real friction to making changes. In order to adjust restrictions, you have to physically connect your iPhone to your laptop and open up a kludgy piece of software. This is cumbersome enough that if you have enough willpower to go through with it, you’ll be level-headed enough to not want too. [2]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second is that you can actually disable the App Store! This is a marvelous win. Having an App Store in your home screen is like being dieter with a pastry shop in your kitchen. It’s not a good idea. So no more App Store. And combine that with content filters for websites, and you can really lock down your phone. When you are at your weakest, there’s effectively no way to hack around the restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the final win, it’s still an iPhone. This means you can make a dumbphone that fits your needs exactly. There are some apps that sound distracting on the surface, that I just needed plain and simple. For example, my startup uses Discord to talk to users; I want to have it. I want the GitHub app. I want Things3 and Waymo. I want to access specific websites. I can set it all up so my phone is exactly the utility I need it to be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re getting excited, let me prepare you with two cons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first is that you have to factory reset your iPhone. You can only set up Apple Configurator with a completely reset phone. This means the initial setup is annoying and will take you a few hours. But perhaps this a good thing too. If you go through this trouble, you’ll be even more motivated to stick with your choices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second is that getting the right setup takes a few weeks, and you may need to rely on others. When you start out you may forget an app or two (or a lot more). For example, I went to my gym the day after I set my restrictions, only to remember that they have a special iPhone to check in. You’ll have lots of little frictions like this. As you do, you’ll improve your configuration so this happens less. It’ll get better but there will still be a long-tail. Maybe you’re at a restaurant and they need you to open a website for example. You may end up having to bug some people around you for their phone. It can be annoying but I haven’t found this to be too troublesome.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, it’s 2 months in. Here’s my experience so far:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It feels great. My phone feels like a utility. I think this is the same kind of change in feeling I would have had if I shifted from eating junk food to healthy food. My phone used to have this gravity: like invariably my attention would shift towards it. Now it just feels like a very useful rock.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I found ChatGPT and Claude critically useful. Whenever I need some information, I can just ask my LLM, and it can give me a distraction free summary. It helps the long-tail of weird situations too: for example if someone asks me to take a look at a website, I can ask my LLM to scrape it and summarize the details for me. It’s pretty hard to get distracted this way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And in the the last 2 months I have not felt the desire to remove the restrictions. This wasn’t the case with any previous setup I tried. I think it’s because the friction feels just right. I feel like I can control exactly how my phone should work; there’s just a day or two delay. The delay keeps me level-headed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So far the only real unsolved issue I have are related to “semi-important” apps. Consider email. I still need to have access to email, and I want to have notifications enabled so I don’t miss something truly important. But 90% of the emails I get aren’t important.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am not sure what the solution is to these kind of apps. Maybe I can find a special mail app, that only shows you important emails. If I had something like this I think I would just be over the moon with this setup. [3]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I used to spend about 4 hours a day on my phone. I’m now down to about 2 hours a day. Looking at the stats, it’s 1 hour of reasonably productive apps, mixed with communication apps (my family lives in a different country, so I make long calls). Overall I don’t regret this time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to do this yourself, it’s going to take a 2-hour initial commitment, and about 2 weeks of tweaks to get everything set up just right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the first 2 hours, you will factory reset your phone, and set up Apple Configurator. As those two weeks progress, you’ll tweak your restrictions so you have just the apps and the websites you actually need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, let’s get into those first 2 hours!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time to reset your iPhone. Go to Settings → General → Transfer or Reset iPhone → Erase all content and settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the first, and the scariest step. Do it, and you are on the journey 🫡&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now head on over to the Apple and install Apple Configurator. Open the app and click ‘Get Started’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can then prepare your device for configurator. Connect your iPhone to your laptop. You should see it show up in Configurator. Once you do, Right click and click “Prepare”:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Select “Manual Configuration”, with “Supervise devices” like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can skip “Sign in to Apple School Manager or Apple Business Manager”. Just press Next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now enter an “Organization”. Since this is just for yourself, you are an organization of one : ). I use my name:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In “Configure iOS Setup Assistant”, select “Don’t show any of these steps”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click “Prepare”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aand you’re ready to go!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your phone is now ready for Configurator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before we start adding restrictions, let’s set your phone up. Go through Apple’s setup, and make sure you do not restore your iPhone from an iCloud backup. This will undo the supervision stuff we just did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you set things up, go ahead and install all the apps that you’ll need. As a way to jog your memory, here are the apps that I ended up installing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;## Reading/Learning

- Audible
- Kindle

## Convenience

- Doordash
- Uber
- Lyft
- Waymo
- Turo

## Health

- (Your Gym App)
- Whoop

## Auth

- LastPass
- Authenticator

## Communication

- Messenger
- WhatsApp
- Signal
- Slack
- Discord

## AI

- ChatGPT
- Claude

## Google

- Gmail
- Google Calendar
- Google Maps
- Google Photos

## Dev

- Expo Go
- GitHub
- TestFlight

## Home

- Ring

## Music

- Spotify

## Producitvity

- Things&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now it’s time to set up your restrictions! You’ll create a new Configurator ‘Profile’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click ‘File’ → ‘New Profile’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll make three changes&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under ‘General’: For ‘Security’ and ‘Automatically Remove Profile’, set ‘Never’:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Head on over to ‘Content Filter’, and click ‘Configure’. For ‘Filter Type’, select “Specific Websites only”:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enter some of the sites you want to use. To jog your memory, here are some sites I added:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;## Google Auth

- https://accounts.google.com

## Docs

- https://dropbox.com

## Modern databases with real-time sync

- https://instantdb.com&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;‘Restrictions’ are where we will disable the App Store. Click on ‘Restrictions’ → ‘Configure’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep everything as it is, just uncheck ‘Allow Installing Apps’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With that, save your profile. Once we install this profile on your phone…you’re done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So let’s install this profile to your iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right click your phone on Configurator, hit ‘Add’ → ‘Profiles’, pick your profile, and you’re ready to go!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you load your phone, you should no longer see an App Store!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After a while you may realize you need to install some new apps. When you want to do that, connect your phone, ‘Right click’ → ‘Remove’ → ‘Profile’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you remove your profile, you’re back to a restrictionless world. Make all the changes you need, and then add it back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And with that, you have an iPhone dumbphone! I hope it’s as useful for you as it has been for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you follow the instructions and have any issues or changes to make, please send me an email.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Ilia Parunashvili for trying the original instructions I wrote out and providing screenshots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Alex Kotliarskyi, Alex Reichert, Daniel Woelfel, Jacky Wang, Nicole Garcia Fischer, for reviewing drafts of this essay.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45171200</guid></item><item><title>Microsoft doubles down on small modular reactors and fusion energy</title><link>https://www.techradar.com/pro/microsoft-joins-world-nuclear-association-as-it-doubles-down-on-small-modular-reactors-and-fusion-energy</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2614f17bdaa4a59e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Microsoft joins World Nuclear Association as it doubles down on small modular reactors and fusion energy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nuclear energy is stepping into big tech’s future electricity strategies&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Microsoft is chasing carbon-free energy while data demand keeps rising&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The World Nuclear Association gains unprecedented visibility through Microsoft’s membership&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Small modular reactors are being framed as digital infrastructure’s next foundation&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft has officially joined the World Nuclear Association (WNA), making it the first global technology company of its scale to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The announcement comes at a time when the nuclear industry is attempting to position itself as a necessary partner for both climate targets and the electricity needs of a rapidly expanding digital economy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Microsoft, the move signals a deeper commitment to technologies like small modular reactors and fusion energy as part of its long-term carbon-free ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Balancing climate goals with electricity demand&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Electricity consumption tied to data centers is expected to grow sharply in the next decade, putting pressure on utilities and energy-intensive industries alike.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft’s decision to align with the World Nuclear Association reflects this trend, as while the company already invests heavily in renewable power sources, nuclear energy offers continuous, high-capacity output that wind and solar cannot always provide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The WNA describes Microsoft’s membership as a "game-changing moment," but such claims will likely face scrutiny given the slow pace of nuclear deployment globally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Microsoft's membership with the Association is a game-changing moment for our industry," said World Nuclear Association Director General Sama Bilbao y León.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sign up to the TechRadar Pro newsletter to get all the top news, opinion, features and guidance your business needs to succeed!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"When one of the world's most innovative technology companies recognizes nuclear energy as essential to its carbon-negative future, it sends a powerful signal to markets, policymakers, and industry leaders worldwide. This partnership will accelerate nuclear deployment at the scale needed to meet both climate goals and the growth in energy demand from data centers."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft has already signed long-term agreements designed to secure reliable energy supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the most notable is a 20-year power purchase agreement with Constellation Energy, intended to restart the Crane Clean Energy Center, the former Three Mile Island Unit 1 facility in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition, the company struck one of the earliest commercial deals with fusion energy company Helion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As part of its World Nuclear Association membership, Microsoft is expected to work on areas like advanced nuclear technologies, regulatory efficiency, and supply chain resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Small modular reactors and next-generation systems, including potential fusion breakthroughs, are central to this collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Advocates argue that streamlined licensing and stronger global supply chains are critical if nuclear power is to play a larger role in meeting energy demand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, the challenges of cost, construction delays, and political opposition remain major barriers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft’s Energy Technology team, led by Dr. Melissa Lott, will take a leading role in shaping how the company participates in the Association’s initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the World Nuclear Association, securing a member like Microsoft brings both visibility and legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Microsoft, it offers a chance to hedge its energy bets in an uncertain market, but whether this partnership proves transformative depends on the ability of nuclear technologies to deliver results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Nuclear energy isn't just part of the technology sector’s energy strategy, it's essential to it," said León. "Microsoft joining the Association allows greater collaboration between one of the major energy users and the nuclear industry to address the regulatory, technical, and financial challenges to accelerate nuclear deployment. The global nuclear industry isn’t just generating electricity, it’s energizing technology."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;You might also like&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check out our pick of the best secure routers on offer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We've rounded up the best portable monitors available now&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sharing might be caring, but businesses are moving towards private servers&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Efosa has been writing about technology for over 7 years, initially driven by curiosity but now fueled by a strong passion for the field. He holds both a Master's and a PhD in sciences, which provided him with a solid foundation in analytical thinking. Efosa developed a keen interest in technology policy, specifically exploring the intersection of privacy, security, and politics. His research delves into how technological advancements influence regulatory frameworks and societal norms, particularly concerning data protection and cybersecurity. Upon joining TechRadar Pro, in addition to privacy and technology policy, he is also focused on B2B security products. Efosa can be contacted at this email: udinmwenefosa@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must confirm your public display name before commenting&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please logout and then login again, you will then be prompted to enter your display name.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45172609</guid></item><item><title>The elegance of movement in Silksong</title><link>https://theahura.substack.com/p/the-elegance-of-movement-in-silksong</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45174037</guid></item><item><title>Alterego: Thought to Text</title><link>https://www.alterego.io/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a5dbce4d1d28fbc5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Interact at the speed of thought&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Introducing Alterego, the first near-telepathic interface, designed to make technology as intuitive as using your inner voice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Alterego is a breakthrough technology that connects you with AI through a minimal, non-invasive device. Using Silent Sense, it understands what you intend to say without speaking, allowing you to extend your thinking without the need to type, tap, or talk out loud.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most intuitive interface&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From normal speech to silent communication that feels like telepathy, Alterego adapts to however you choose to interact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Designed to fade away&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stay completely hands-free and screen-free while accessing AI, sending messages, and getting information on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your thoughts stay private&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alterego only responds to intentional, silent speech. Your private thoughts stay private, and you direct every interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weâre building the next chapter of human-computer interaction. Sign up to track our progress and be first to know when Alterego becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45174125</guid></item><item><title>Liquid Glass in the Browser: Refraction with CSS and SVG</title><link>https://kube.io/blog/liquid-glass-css-svg/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="1ca61b6b4b7dc14b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Articles /&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Liquid Glass in the Browser: Refraction with CSS and SVG&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;#Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple introduced the Liquid Glass effect during WWDC 2025 in June—a stunning UI effect that makes interface elements appear to be made of curved, refractive glass. This article is a hands‑on exploration of how to recreate a similar effect on the web using CSS, SVG displacement maps, and physics-based refraction calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of chasing pixel‑perfect parity, we’ll approximate Liquid Glass, recreating the core refraction and a specular highlight, as a focused proof‑of‑concept you can extend.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We'll build up the effect from first principles, starting with how light bends when passing through different materials.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chrome‑only demo&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The interactive demo at the end currently works in Chrome only (due to SVG filters as backdrop‑filter).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can still read the article and interact with the inline simulations in other browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;#Understanding Refraction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Refraction is what happens when light changes direction as it passes from one material to another (like from air into glass). This bending occurs because light travels at different speeds through different materials.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The relationship between the incoming and outgoing light angles is described by Snell–Descartes law:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the above interactive diagram, you can see that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When , the light ray passes straight through without bending.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When , the ray bends toward the normal (the imaginary line perpendicular to the surface).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When , the ray bends away from the normal, and depending on the angle of incidence, it may bend so much that it reflects back into the original medium instead of passing through.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This is called Total Internal Reflection&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When incident ray is orthogonal to the surface, it passes straight through regardless of refractive indices.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Limitations in this project&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To keep things focused we avoid complex branches of behavior by constraining the scenario:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ambient medium has (air).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Use materials with , and prefer (glass).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Only one refraction event (ignore any later exit / second refraction).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Incident rays are always orthogonal to the background plane (no perspective).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Objects are 2D shapes parallel to the background (no perspective).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;No gap between objects and background plane (only one refraction).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Circle shapes only in this article:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Extending to other shapes requires preliminary calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Circles let us form rounded rectangles by stretching the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under these assumptions every ray we manipulate has a well-defined refracted direction via Snell's Law, and we simplify a lot our calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;#Creating the Glass Surface&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To create our glass effect, we need to define the shape of our virtual glass surface. Think of this like describing the cross-section of a lens or curved glass panel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Surface Function&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our glass surface is described by a mathematical function that defines how thick the glass is at any point from its edge to the end of the bezel. This surface function takes a value between (at the outer edge) and (end of bezel, start of flat surface) and returns the height of the glass at that point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the height we can calculate the angle of incidence, which is the angle between the incoming ray and the normal to the surface at that point. The normal is simply the derivative of the height function at that point, rotated by degrees:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Equations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For this article, we will use four different height functions to demonstrate the effect of the surface shape on the refraction:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simple circular arc → a spherical dome. Easier than the squircle, but the transition to the flat interior is harsher, producing sharper refraction edges—more noticeable when the shape is stretched away from a true circle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Uses the Squircle Apple favors: a softer flat→curve transition that keeps refraction gradients smooth even when stretched into rectangles—no harsh interior edges. It also makes the bezel appear optically thinner than its physical size because the flatter outer zones bend light less.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The concave surface is the complement of the convex function, creating a bowl-like depression. This surface causes light rays to diverge outward, displacing them beyond the glass boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We could make the surface function more complex by adding more parameters, but these four already give a good idea of how the surface shape affects the refraction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Simulation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now let's see these surface functions in action through interactive ray tracing simulations. The following visualization demonstrates how light rays behave differently as they pass through each surface type, helping us understand the practical implications of our mathematical choices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the simulation, we can see that concave surfaces push rays outside the glass; convex surfaces keep them inside.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We want to avoid outside displacement because it requires sampling background beyond the object. Apple’s Liquid Glass appears to favor convex profiles (except for the Switch component, covered later).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The background arrow indicates displacement—how far a ray lands compared to where it would have landed without glass. Color encodes magnitude (longer → more purple).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take a look at symmetry: rays at the same distance from the border share the same displacement magnitude on each side. Compute once, reuse around the bezel/object.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;#Displacement Vector Field&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that calculated the displacement at a distance from border, let's calculate the displacement vector field for the entire glass surface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vector field describes at every position on the glass surface how much the light ray is displaced from its original position, and in which direction. In a circle, this displacement is always orthogonal to the border.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Pre-calculating the displacement magnitude&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because we saw that this displacement magnitude is symmetric around the bezel, we can pre-calculate it for a range of distances from the border, on a single radius.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This allows us to calculate everything in two dimensions once (x and z axis), on one "half-slice" of the object, and we will the rotate these pre-calculated displacements around the z-axis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The actual number of samples we need to do on a radius is of 127 ray simulations, and is determined by the constraints of the SVG Displacement Map resolution. (See next section.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Normalizing vectors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the above diagram, the arrows are all scaled down for visibility, so they do not overlap. This is normalization, and is also useful from a technical standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To use these vectors in a displacement map, we need to normalize them. Normalization means scaling the vectors so that their maximum magnitude is , which allows us to represent them in a fixed range.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So we calculate the maximum displacement magnitude in our pre-calculated array:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And we divide each vector's magnitude by this maximum:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We store &lt;code&gt;maximumDisplacement&lt;/code&gt; as we will need it to re-scale the displacement map back to the actual magnitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;#SVG Displacement Map&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we need to translate our mathematical refraction calculations into something the browser can actually render. We'll use SVG displacement maps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A displacement map is simply an image where each pixel's color tells the browser how far it should find the actual pixel value from its current position.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SVG's &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feDisplacementMap /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; encodes these pixels in a 32 bit RGBA image, where each channel represents a different axis of displacement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's up to the user to define which channel corresponds to which axis, but it is important to understand the constraint: Because each channel is 8 bits, the displacement is limited to a range of -128 to 127 pixels in each direction. (256 values possible in total). 128 is the neutral value, meaning no displacement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SVG filters can only use images as displacement maps, so we need to convert our displacement vector field into an image format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feDisplacementMap /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; uses the red channel for the X axis and the green channel for the Y axis. The blue and alpha channels are ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Scale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Red (X) and Green (Y) channels are 8‑bit values (0–255). Interpreted without any extra scaling, they map linearly to a normalized displacement in [−1, 1], with 128 as the neutral value (no displacement):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;scale&lt;/code&gt; attribute of &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feDisplacementMap /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; multiplies this normalized amount:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because our vectors are normalized using the maximum possible displacement (in pixels) as the unit, we can reuse that maximum directly as the filter’s &lt;code&gt;scale&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also animate &lt;code&gt;scale&lt;/code&gt; to fade the effect in/out—no need to recompute the map (useful for artistic control even if not physically exact).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Vector to Red-Green values&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To convert our displacement vector field into a displacement map, we need to convert each vector into a color value. The red channel will represent the X component of the vector, and the green channel will represent the Y component.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We currently have polar coordinates (angle and magnitude) for each vector, so we need to convert them to Cartesian coordinates (X and Y) before mapping them to the red and green channels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because we normalised our vectors already, &lt;code&gt;magnitude&lt;/code&gt; here is between 0 and 1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From here, we just remap the values to the range of 0 to 255 for the red and green channels:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After converting every vector in the map to color value, we get an image that can be used as a displacement map in the SVG filter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Playground&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This playground applies the SVG displacement filter to a simple scene and lets you tweak surface shape, bezel width, glass thickness, and effect scale. Watch how these inputs change the refraction field, the generated displacement map, and the final rendering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Surface&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Controls&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Radius Simulation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Displacement Map&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Radius Displacements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Preview&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;#Specular Highlight&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final piece of our Liquid Glass effect is the specular highlight—those bright, shiny edges you see on real glass objects when light hits them at certain angles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The way Apple implements it seems to be a simple rim light effect, where the highlight appears around the edges of the glass object, and its intensity varies based on the angle of the surface normal relative to a fixed light direction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;#Combining Refraction and Specular Highlight&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the final SVG filter, we combine both the displacement map for refraction and the specular highlight effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both are loaded as separate &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feImage /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; elements, and then combined using &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feBlend /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to overlay the highlight on top of the refracted image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this part is actually the most "creative" part of the effect, and it's just by tweaking the number of filters, and their parameters, that you can get a variety of different looks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#SVG Filter as &lt;code&gt;backdrop-filter&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the part where cross-browser compatibility ends. Only Chrome currently supports using SVG filters as &lt;code&gt;backdrop-filter&lt;/code&gt;, which is essential for applying the Liquid Glass effect to UI components:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note: The backdrop-filter dimensions does not adjust automatically to the element size, so you need to ensure that your filter images fit the size of your elements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we have all the pieces in place, we can create components that use this effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;#Bringing It All Together: Real UI Components&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With our refraction math and displacement maps working, let's see how this translates to actual UI components you might use in an application.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chrome‑specific demo&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chrome allows using SVG filters as &lt;code&gt;backdrop-filter&lt;/code&gt;, which
isn’t part of the CSS spec.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Above, we used regular &lt;code&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; so it’s viewable in
Safari/Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next components use &lt;code&gt;backdrop-filter&lt;/code&gt;, so they’re
Chrome‑only.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal won't be to create real components for production, but just to get a taste of how the effect looks in different UI elements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Magnifying Glass&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This component actually uses two displacement maps: one for the refraction on the sides, and one for the zooming, which has a stronger refraction effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It also plays with shadows and scaling to create a more dynamic, interactive effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Liquid Glass—Precision Lens&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Drag the capsule to bend the page. This lens is a compact SVG displacement rig that refracts whatever sits beneath it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The field comes from a rounded bezel profile; pixels are pushed along its gradient, then topped with a subtle specular bloom for depth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sweep across strong edges—high contrast makes the bend snap.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Searchbox&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Switch&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This uses a lip bezel, which makes the surface convex on the outside and concave in the middle. This makes the center slider zoomed out, while the edges refract the inside.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Slider&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Slider allows you to see the current level through the glass, while the sides refract the background. It uses a convex bezel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;#Music Player&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This fake music player UI tries to mimic the look of Apple Music’s Liquid Glass panels, using a convex bezel and a subtle specular highlight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It relies on the iTunes Search API to fetch album art and song details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;#Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This prototype distills Apple’s Liquid Glass into real‑time refraction plus a simple highlight. It’s flexible, but still Chrome‑bound—only Chromium exposes SVG filters as &lt;code&gt;backdrop-filter&lt;/code&gt;. That said, it’s already viable inside Chromium‑based runtimes like Electron, elsewhere you could fake a softer fallback with layered blur.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Treat this strictly as experimental. Dynamic shape/size changes are currently costly because nearly every tweak (besides animating &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;filter /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; props, like &lt;code&gt;scale&lt;/code&gt;) forces a full displacement map rebuild.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code needs a cleanup pass and perf work before any possible open‑source release.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading my first post—I'd genuinely love any feedback, ideas, critiques, or suggestions. If it sparked a thought or you know someone who'd enjoy this kind of deep‑dive, feel free to pass it along.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45174297</guid></item><item><title>Strong Eventual Consistency – The Big Idea Behind CRDTs</title><link>https://lewiscampbell.tech/blog/250908.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="cf2e184ab08d0cf5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Strong Eventual Consistency - The Big Idea behind CRDTs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CRDTs. Data structures that can be replicated across multiple nodes, edited independently, merged back together, and it all just works. But collaborative document editing and multiplayer TODO lists are just the tip of the iceberg - I believe the big application is distributed databases, and for that we need to talk about consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CRDTs are a tool for Strong Eventual Consistency. Let's start with the definition of normal Eventual Consistency1:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Eventual Delivery&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;An update delivered to one node will eventually reaches all nodes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Eventual Convergence&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;If two nodes have seen all the same updates, they will eventually have the same state.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strong Eventual Consistency (SEC) replaces Eventual Convergence with Strong Convergence:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Strong Convergence&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;If two nodes have seen all the same updates, they will have the same state.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spot the difference! In SEC two replicas have the same state as soon as the updates are processed, not eventually. If multiple nodes are updated independently, there will be conflicts - this is inevitable. What SEC guarantees is that these conflicts are solved automatically and deterministically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This has massive implications. SEC means low latency, because nodes don't need to coordinate to handle reads and writes. It means incredible fault tolerance - every single node in the system bar one could simultaneously crash, and reads and writes could still happen normally. And it means nodes still function properly if they're offline or split from the network for arbitrary time periods.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strong Eventual Consistency is Eventual Consistency that works. If you're doing local first, or low latency geo-replicated systems - accept no substitute. This is the context I think we should see CRDTs in - building blocks of Strongly Eventually Consistent systems. CRDTs as application state as one thing, CRDTs as entire databases are quite another.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;All definitions here are adapted from Shapiro, Marc; Preguiça, Nuno; Baquero, Carlos; Zawirski, Marek (2011). "Conflict-Free Replicated Data Types". ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm available for hire.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45177518</guid></item><item><title>Mistral AI raises 1.7B€, enters strategic partnership with ASML</title><link>https://mistral.ai/news/mistral-ai-raises-1-7-b-to-accelerate-technological-progress-with-ai</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b8dee2d26b98879e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Mistral AI raises 1.7B€ to accelerate technological progress with AI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are announcing a Series C funding round of 1.7B€ at a 11.7B€ post-money valuation. This investment fuels our scientific research to keep pushing the frontier of AI to tackle the most critical and sophisticated technological challenges faced by strategic industries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Series C funding round is led by leading semiconductor equipment manufacturer, ASML Holding NV (ASML).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“ASML is proud to enter a strategic partnership with Mistral AI, and to be lead investor in this funding round. The collaboration between Mistral AI and ASML aims to generate clear benefits for ASML customers through innovative products and solutions enabled by AI, and will offer potential for joint research to address future opportunities.” said ASML CEO Christophe Fouquet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It includes participation from existing investors: DST Global, Andreessen Horowitz, Bpifrance, General Catalyst, Index Ventures, Lightspeed and NVIDIA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the last two years, we have advanced AI through cutting-edge research and strategic partnerships with corporate and industrial champions. We will continue to develop custom decentralized frontier AI solutions that solve the most complex engineering and industrial problems. It empowers enterprises, public sectors, and industries a competitive edge through state-of-the-art models, tailored solutions, and high-performance compute infrastructure. This funding round reaffirms the company’s independence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This investment brings together two technology leaders operating in the same value chain. We have the ambition to help ASML and its numerous partners solve current and future engineering challenges through AI, and ultimately to advance the full semiconductor and AI value chain”, said Mistral AI CEO Arthur Mensch.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45178041</guid></item><item><title>You too can run malware from NPM (I mean without consequences)</title><link>https://github.com/naugtur/running-qix-malware</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e5b5d354697d061b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Phishing NPM package authors continues, unsurprisingly. The stakes are not high enough to switch from phishing to anything more advanced (like https://xkcd.com/538/) but seeing article blurbs say "Supply chain Attack" next to "These packages generally receive 2-3 billion downloads per week." might finally be enough to make an impression, one hopes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is not a detailed analysis of the attack, there's plenty of that already. If you're looking for one, visit our friends at https://socket.dev/blog/npm-author-qix-compromised-in-major-supply-chain-attack&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, let's look at how you could have a compromised dependency like that get into your app and be stopped.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the compromised packages was &lt;code&gt;is-arrayish&lt;/code&gt; and I'll use that as an example going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So if an app uses &lt;code&gt;is-arrayish&lt;/code&gt; in the browser, it will override &lt;code&gt;fetch&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;XMLHttpRequest&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;window.ethereum.request&lt;/code&gt; and whenever it finds a transaction being sent, it'll replace the target address with one of the malware author's addresses that looks most alike.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I won't go into this either, but you can take a look at the summary of "donations" some other friends linked to here: https://intel.arkm.com/explorer/entity/61fbc095-f19b-479d-a037-5469aba332ab&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pretty low impact for an attack this big. Some of it seems to be people mocking the malware author with worthless transfers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Say we have an app. The app allows the user to send a meaningless transaction to themselves. Don't expect it to make sense. It also uses &lt;code&gt;is-arrayish&lt;/code&gt; because otherwise we'd have nothing to demo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const isArrayish = require("is-arrayish");

const button = document.createElement("button");
button.textContent = "Send ETH Transaction";
document.body.appendChild(button);

button.addEventListener("click", async () =&amp;gt; {
  const accounts = await window.ethereum.request({
    method: "eth_requestAccounts",
  });
  if (!isArrayish(accounts)) {
    throw new Error("Accounts response must be array-like");
  }
  const myAddr = accounts[0];

  const txHash = await window.ethereum.request({
    method: "eth_sendTransaction",
    params: [
      {
        value: "0x5af3107a4000",
        from: myAddr,
        to: myAddr,
      },
    ],
  });
  console.log("Transaction sent:", txHash);
});&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what it looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now after you update &lt;code&gt;is-arrayish&lt;/code&gt; to 0.3.3 and rebuild the project, you might notice a slight difference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your project was set up with LavaMoat, you'd be using a policy to decide which package is allowed access to what. More about policies in the guide&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With LavaMoat, all &lt;code&gt;is-arrayish&lt;/code&gt; can do is fail:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;TypeError: Cannot define property fetch, object is not extensible
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BTW, If the malware was written a little better to avoid detection and fail silently, the functionality of the app would be fully restored.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To protect the project, @lavamoat/webpack was used.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In short, what it does is: it puts modules from every dependency in a separate lexical global context that we call &lt;code&gt;Compartment&lt;/code&gt; and only allows access to globals that the policy lists. I also controls which packages can import which other packages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the project dependency gets updated to contain malicious code, the policy will not allow it to access any globals or imports it didn't use before.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read more in the official guide&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45179889</guid></item><item><title>DuckDB NPM packages 1.3.3 and 1.29.2 compromised with malware</title><link>https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb-node/security/advisories/GHSA-w62p-hx95-gf2c</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a90722870d337685"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;DuckDB NPM packages 1.3.3 and 1.29.2 compromised with malware&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Description&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The DuckDB distribution for Node.js on npm was compromised with malware (along with several other packages). An attacker published new versions of four of duckdb’s packages that included malicious code to interfere with cryptocoin transactions. The following packages and versions are affected:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;@duckdb/node-api@1.3.3&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;@duckdb/node-bindings@1.3.3&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;duckdb@1.3.3&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;@duckdb/duckdb-wasm@1.29.2&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note: The current release version of DuckDB is 1.3.2, with 1.4.0 expected to be released on Sept 10th, 2025 (tomorrow as of this writing). We do not plan to ever release a “legit” DuckDB 1.3.3. Users should double-check that they are not accidentally updating to those affected versions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have ourselves noticed this within four hours of it happening. Here’s our response:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;As an immediate response, we have deprecated the specific versions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We have reached out to npm support to delete the affected versions. They were so kind to do so.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We have also re-released the node packages with higher version numbers (1.3.4/1.30.0) as a further safeguard so the latest version of the package points to a safe version&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We apologize for this issue. We are reviewing our internal processes to ensure the safety of future releases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Postmortem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On September 8th (Monday), the DuckDB maintainers received the following message from "...@npmjs.help":&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the maintainers read through this text and found it somewhat reasonable. He followed the link (now defunct) to a website hosted under the domain &lt;code&gt;npmjs.help&lt;/code&gt;. This website contained a pixel-perfect copy of the npmjs.com website. He logged in using the &lt;code&gt;duckdb_admin&lt;/code&gt; user and password, followed by 2FA. Again, the user profile, settings etc. were a perfect copy of the npmjs.com website including all user data. As requested by the email, he then re-set the 2FA setup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the background, the copycat website forwarded all actions to the actual npm website, so the 2FA was actually updated there, too. But they also added a new API token, which they then used to publish the malicious package versions. In hindsight, the fact that his browser did not auto-complete the login should have been a red flag. It's painful to spell out, but we fell for a classic phishing attack.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We again apologize for this mishap. We are reviewing our internal processes to ensure the safety of future releases. It is fortunate that we noticed this within a few hours of it happening. The DuckDBLabs team was able to set up a call at 7AM to perform an immediate response. Fortunately we were not locked out of our NPM account, which also easily could have happened. We were able to rotate passwords, tokens and API keys immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45179939</guid></item><item><title>Hallucination Risk Calculator</title><link>https://github.com/leochlon/hallbayes</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="dd0e305a0bf2b6ae"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Post-hoc calibration without retraining for large language models. This toolkit turns a raw prompt into:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;a bounded hallucination risk using the Expectation-level Decompression Law (EDFL), and&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;a decision to ANSWER or REFUSE under a target SLA, with transparent math (nats).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It supports two deployment modes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Evidence-based: prompts include evidence/context; rolling priors are built by erasing that evidence.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Closed-book: prompts have no evidence; rolling priors are built by semantic masking of entities/numbers/titles.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All scoring relies only on the OpenAI Chat Completions API. No retraining required.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Install &amp;amp; Setup&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Core Mathematical Framework&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Understanding System Behavior&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Two Ways to Build Rolling Priors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;API Surface&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Calibration &amp;amp; Validation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Practical Considerations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Project Layout&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Deployment Options&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pip install --upgrade openai
export OPENAI_API_KEY=sk-...&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The module uses&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;openai&amp;gt;=1.0.0&lt;/code&gt;and the Chat Completions API (e.g.,&lt;code&gt;gpt-4o&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;gpt-4o-mini&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let the binary event &lt;lb/&gt; Build an ensemble of content-weakened prompts (the rolling priors) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information budget:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;math-renderer&gt;$$\bar{\Delta} = \tfrac{1}{m}\sum_k \mathrm{clip}_+(\log P(y) - \log S_k(y), B)$$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;(one-sided clipping; default&lt;math-renderer&gt;$B=12$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;nats to prevent outliers while maintaining conservative bounds).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior masses:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;math-renderer&gt;$q_k = S_k(\mathcal{A})$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;, with:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;math-renderer&gt;$\bar{q}=\tfrac{1}{m}\sum_k q_k$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;(average prior for EDFL bound)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;math-renderer&gt;$q_{\text{lo}}=\min_k q_k$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;(worst-case prior for SLA gating)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By EDFL, the achievable reliability is bounded by:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thus the hallucination risk (error) is bounded by &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For target hallucination rate &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Bits-to-Trust: &lt;math-renderer&gt;$\mathrm{B2T} = \mathrm{KL}(\mathrm{Ber}(1-h^*) | \mathrm{Ber}(q_{\text{lo}}))$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Information Sufficiency Ratio: &lt;math-renderer&gt;$\mathrm{ISR} = \bar{\Delta}/\mathrm{B2T}$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; ANSWER iff &lt;math-renderer&gt;$\mathrm{ISR}\ge 1$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;and&lt;math-renderer&gt;$\bar{\Delta} \ge \mathrm{B2T} + \text{margin}$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;(default&lt;code&gt;margin≈0.2&lt;/code&gt;nats)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why two priors? The gate uses worst-case&lt;/p&gt;&lt;math-renderer&gt;$q_{\text{lo}}$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;for strict SLA compliance. The RoH bound uses average&lt;math-renderer&gt;$\bar{q}$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;per EDFL theory. This dual approach ensures conservative safety while providing realistic risk bounds.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The toolkit exhibits different behaviors across query types, which is mathematically consistent with the framework:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Observation: May abstain despite apparent simplicity&lt;lb/&gt; Explanation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Models often attempt answers even with masked numbers (pattern recognition)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;This yields low information lift &lt;math-renderer&gt;$\bar{\Delta} \approx 0$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;between full prompt and skeletons&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Despite potentially low EDFL risk bound, worst-case prior gate triggers abstention (ISR &amp;lt; 1)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Observation: Generally answered with confidence&lt;lb/&gt; Explanation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Masking entities/dates substantially reduces answer propensity in skeletons&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Restoring these yields large &lt;math-renderer&gt;$\bar{\Delta}$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;that clears B2T threshold&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;System answers with tight EDFL risk bound&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is not a bug but a feature: The framework prioritizes safety through worst-case guarantees while providing realistic average-case bounds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Switch Event Measurement&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Use Correct/Incorrect instead of Answer/Refuse for factual QA&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Skeletons without key information rarely yield correct results → large &lt;math-renderer&gt;$\bar{\Delta}$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Enhance Skeleton Weakening&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Implement mask-aware decision head that refuses on redaction tokens&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Ensures skeletons have strictly lower "Answer" mass than full prompt&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Calibration Adjustments&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Relax &lt;math-renderer&gt;$h^*$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;slightly (e.g., 0.10 instead of 0.05) for higher answer rates&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Reduce margin for less conservative gating&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Increase sampling (&lt;math-renderer&gt;$n=7-10$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;) for stability&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Relax &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Provide Evidence&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Adding compact, relevant evidence increases &lt;math-renderer&gt;$\bar{\Delta}$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;while preserving bounds&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adding compact, relevant evidence increases &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Prompt contains a field like &lt;code&gt;Evidence:&lt;/code&gt;(or JSON keys)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Skeletons erase the evidence content but preserve structure and roles; then permute blocks deterministically (seeded)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Decision head: "Answer only if the provided evidence is sufficient; otherwise refuse."&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from scripts.hallucination_toolkit import OpenAIBackend, OpenAIItem, OpenAIPlanner

backend = OpenAIBackend(model="gpt-4o-mini")
prompt = (
    """Task: Answer strictly based on the evidence below.
Question: Who won the Nobel Prize in Physics in 2019?
Evidence:
- Nobel Prize press release (2019): James Peebles (1/2); Michel Mayor &amp;amp; Didier Queloz (1/2).
Constraints: If evidence is insufficient or conflicting, refuse.
"""
)
item = OpenAIItem(
    prompt=prompt, 
    n_samples=5, 
    m=6, 
    fields_to_erase=["Evidence"], 
    skeleton_policy="auto"
)
planner = OpenAIPlanner(backend, temperature=0.3)
metrics = planner.run(
    [item], 
    h_star=0.05, 
    isr_threshold=1.0, 
    margin_extra_bits=0.2, 
    B_clip=12.0, 
    clip_mode="one-sided"
)
for m in metrics: 
    print(f"Decision: {'ANSWER' if m.decision_answer else 'REFUSE'}")
    print(f"Rationale: {m.rationale}")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Prompt has no evidence&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Skeletons apply semantic masking of: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Multi-word proper nouns (e.g., "James Peebles" → "[…]")&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Years (e.g., "2019" → "[…]")&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Numbers (e.g., "3.14" → "[…]")&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Quoted spans (e.g., '"Nobel Prize"' → "[…]")&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Masking strengths: Progressive levels (0.25, 0.35, 0.5, 0.65, 0.8, 0.9) across skeleton ensemble&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mask-aware decision head refuses if redaction tokens appear or key slots look missing&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from scripts.hallucination_toolkit import OpenAIBackend, OpenAIItem, OpenAIPlanner

backend = OpenAIBackend(model="gpt-4o-mini")
item = OpenAIItem(
    prompt="Who won the 2019 Nobel Prize in Physics?",
    n_samples=7,  # More samples for stability
    m=6,          # Number of skeletons
    skeleton_policy="closed_book"
)
planner = OpenAIPlanner(backend, temperature=0.3, q_floor=None)
metrics = planner.run(
    [item], 
    h_star=0.05,           # Target max 5% hallucination
    isr_threshold=1.0,     # Standard ISR gate
    margin_extra_bits=0.2, # Safety margin in nats
    B_clip=12.0,          # Clipping bound
    clip_mode="one-sided" # Conservative clipping
)
for m in metrics: 
    print(f"Decision: {'ANSWER' if m.decision_answer else 'REFUSE'}")
    print(f"Δ̄={m.delta_bar:.4f}, B2T={m.b2t:.4f}, ISR={m.isr:.3f}")
    print(f"EDFL RoH bound={m.roh_bound:.3f}")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tuning knobs (closed-book):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;n_samples=5–7&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;temperature≈0.3&lt;/code&gt;stabilize priors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;q_floor&lt;/code&gt;(Laplace by default: $1/(n+2)$) prevents worst-case prior collapse to 0&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adjust masking strength levels if a task family remains too answerable under masking&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;OpenAIBackend(model, api_key=None)&lt;/code&gt;– wraps Chat Completions API&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;OpenAIItem(prompt, n_samples=5, m=6, fields_to_erase=None, skeleton_policy="auto")&lt;/code&gt;– one evaluation item&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;OpenAIPlanner(backend, temperature=0.5, q_floor=None)&lt;/code&gt;– runs evaluation:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;run(items, h_star, isr_threshold, margin_extra_bits, B_clip=12.0, clip_mode="one-sided") -&amp;gt; List[ItemMetrics]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;aggregate(items, metrics, alpha=0.05, h_star, ...) -&amp;gt; AggregateReport&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;make_sla_certificate(report, model_name)&lt;/code&gt;– creates formal SLA certificate&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;save_sla_certificate_json(cert, path)&lt;/code&gt;– exports certificate for audit&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;generate_answer_if_allowed(backend, item, metric)&lt;/code&gt;– only emits answer if decision was ANSWER&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every &lt;code&gt;ItemMetrics&lt;/code&gt; includes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;delta_bar&lt;/code&gt;: Information budget (nats)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;q_conservative&lt;/code&gt;: Worst-case prior&lt;math-renderer&gt;$q_{\text{lo}}$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;q_avg&lt;/code&gt;: Average prior&lt;math-renderer&gt;$\bar{q}$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;b2t&lt;/code&gt;: Bits-to-Trust requirement&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;isr&lt;/code&gt;: Information Sufficiency Ratio&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;roh_bound&lt;/code&gt;: EDFL hallucination risk bound&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;decision_answer&lt;/code&gt;: Boolean decision&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;rationale&lt;/code&gt;: Human-readable explanation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;meta&lt;/code&gt;: Dict with&lt;code&gt;q_list&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;S_list_y&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;P_y&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;closed_book&lt;/code&gt;, etc.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a labeled validation set:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sweep the margin parameter from 0 to 1 nats&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For each margin, compute: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Empirical hallucination rate among answered items&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Wilson upper bound at 95% confidence&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Select smallest margin where Wilson upper bound ≤ target &lt;math-renderer&gt;$h^*$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;(e.g., 5%)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Freeze policy: &lt;math-renderer&gt;$(h^*, \tau, \text{margin}, B, \text{clip_mode}, m, r, \text{skeleton_policy})$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The toolkit provides comprehensive metrics:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Answer/abstention rates&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Empirical hallucination rate + Wilson bound&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Distribution of per-item EDFL RoH bounds&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Worst-case and median risk bounds&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Complete audit trail&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default event is the decision &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Task Type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Recommended Event&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Rationale&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Factual QA&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Correct/Incorrect&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Directly measures hallucination&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Decision Support&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Answer/Refuse&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Measures confidence to respond&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Creative Writing&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Answer/Refuse&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Correctness often undefined&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For tasks where skeletons still trigger answers frequently (causing &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not a contradiction! The gate uses worst-case &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Solution: Increase &lt;code&gt;n_samples&lt;/code&gt;, lower decision temperature, ensure skeletons truly weaken the event&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cause: Clipping may be too aggressive&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Solution: Increase &lt;code&gt;B_clip&lt;/code&gt;(default 12) and use&lt;code&gt;clip_mode="one-sided"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cause: Pattern recognition allows answers even with masked numbers&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Solutions: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Switch to Correctness event&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Reduce masking strength for numbers on subset of skeletons&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Provide worked examples as evidence&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cause: All skeletons strongly refuse&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Solution: Apply prior floor (default Laplace: $1/(n+2)$) or use quantile prior&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Metric&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Typical Value&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Notes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Latency per item&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2-5 seconds&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 samples × 7 variants (1 full + 6 skeletons)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;API calls&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Can be parallelized&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Accuracy&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Wilson-bounded at 95%&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Empirically validated&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Cost&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~$0.01-0.03 per item&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Using gpt-4o-mini&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sampling parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Use &lt;math-renderer&gt;$n \ge 5$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;samples per variant&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Keep temperature &lt;math-renderer&gt;$\in [0.2, 0.5]$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;for decision head&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Lower temperature → more stable priors&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Skeleton ensemble:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Use &lt;math-renderer&gt;$m \ge 6$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;skeletons&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Ensure diversity in masking strengths&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Verify skeletons are meaningfully weaker&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clipping strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Always use one-sided clipping for conservative bounds&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Set &lt;math-renderer&gt;$B \ge 10$&lt;/math-renderer&gt;nats to avoid artificial ceilings&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Monitor clipping frequency in logs&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;.
├── app/                    # Application entry points
│   ├── web/web_app.py     # Streamlit UI
│   ├── cli/frontend.py    # Interactive CLI
│   ├── examples/          # Example scripts
│   └── launcher/entry.py  # Unified launcher
├── scripts/               # Core module
│   ├── hallucination_toolkit.py
│   └── build_offline_backend.sh
├── electron/              # Desktop wrapper
├── launch/                # Platform launchers
├── release/              # Packaged artifacts
├── bin/                  # Offline backend binary
├── requirements.txt
├── pyproject.toml
└── README.md
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from scripts.hallucination_toolkit import (
    OpenAIBackend, OpenAIItem, OpenAIPlanner,
    make_sla_certificate, save_sla_certificate_json
)

# Configure and run
backend = OpenAIBackend(model="gpt-4o-mini")
items = [OpenAIItem(prompt="...", n_samples=7, m=6)]
planner = OpenAIPlanner(backend, temperature=0.3)
metrics = planner.run(items, h_star=0.05)

# Generate SLA certificate
report = planner.aggregate(items, metrics)
cert = make_sla_certificate(report, model_name="GPT-4o-mini")
save_sla_certificate_json(cert, "sla.json")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;streamlit run app/web/web_app.py&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Windows: Double-click &lt;code&gt;launch/Launch App.bat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;macOS: Double-click &lt;code&gt;launch/Launch App.command&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux: Run &lt;code&gt;bash launch/launch.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First run creates &lt;code&gt;.venv&lt;/code&gt; and installs dependencies automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Development:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cd electron
npm install
npm run start&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build installers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm run build&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build single-file executable:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# macOS/Linux
bash scripts/build_offline_backend.sh

# Windows
scripts\build_offline_backend.bat&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creates &lt;code&gt;bin/hallucination-backend[.exe]&lt;/code&gt; with bundled Python, Streamlit, and dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from scripts.hallucination_toolkit import (
    OpenAIBackend, OpenAIItem, OpenAIPlanner,
    make_sla_certificate, save_sla_certificate_json,
    generate_answer_if_allowed
)

# Setup
backend = OpenAIBackend(model="gpt-4o-mini")

# Prepare items
items = [
    OpenAIItem(
        prompt="Who won the 2019 Nobel Prize in Physics?",
        n_samples=7,
        m=6,
        skeleton_policy="closed_book"
    ),
    OpenAIItem(
        prompt="If James has 5 apples and eats 3, how many remain?",
        n_samples=7,
        m=6,
        skeleton_policy="closed_book"
    )
]

# Run evaluation
planner = OpenAIPlanner(backend, temperature=0.3)
metrics = planner.run(
    items,
    h_star=0.05,           # Target 5% hallucination max
    isr_threshold=1.0,     # Standard threshold
    margin_extra_bits=0.2, # Safety margin
    B_clip=12.0,          # Clipping bound
    clip_mode="one-sided" # Conservative mode
)

# Generate report and certificate
report = planner.aggregate(items, metrics, alpha=0.05, h_star=0.05)
cert = make_sla_certificate(report, model_name="GPT-4o-mini")
save_sla_certificate_json(cert, "sla_certificate.json")

# Show results
for item, m in zip(items, metrics):
    print(f"\nPrompt: {item.prompt[:50]}...")
    print(f"Decision: {'ANSWER' if m.decision_answer else 'REFUSE'}")
    print(f"Risk bound: {m.roh_bound:.3f}")
    print(f"Rationale: {m.rationale}")
    
    # Generate answer if allowed
    if m.decision_answer:
        answer = generate_answer_if_allowed(backend, item, m)
        print(f"Answer: {answer}")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is licensed under the MIT License — see the LICENSE file for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developed by Hassana Labs (https://hassana.io).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This implementation follows the framework from the paper “Compression Failure in LLMs: Bayesian in Expectation, Not in Realization” (NeurIPS 2024 preprint) and related EDFL/ISR/B2T methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45180315</guid></item><item><title>Nango (YC W23) Is Hiring a Staff Back End Engineer (Remote)</title><link>https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/Nango/3467f495-c833-4dcc-b119-cf43b7b93f84</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e10fcdab2cdf53e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need to enable JavaScript to run this app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45180741</guid></item><item><title>Weaponizing Ads: How Google and Facebook Ads Are Used to Wage Propaganda Wars</title><link>https://medium.com/@eslam.elsewedy/weaponizing-ads-how-governments-use-google-ads-and-facebook-ads-to-wage-propaganda-wars-199c707704cc</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ffa493a89685dd50"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Weaponizing Ads: How Governments Use Google Ads and Facebook Ads to Wage Propaganda Wars&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In late 2024, the head of the UN’s Gaza aid agency made a disturbing discovery: when people searched for his organization on Google, the top result wasn’t the agency’s own site — it was a paid ad placed by the Israeli government. The ad mimicked a UN website but actually linked to an Israeli government page accusing the UN Relief and Works Agency (UNRWA) of supporting terroists (wired.com). “The spread of misinformation &amp;amp; disinformation continues to be used as a weapon in the war in Gaza,” UNRWA Commissioner-General Philippe Lazzarini warned, calling for investigations and stricter regulation of online propaganda (aljazeera.com). His alarm highlights a troubling new reality: digital advertising platforms have become battlefields for influence, where governments and political groups pay to sway public opinion in wars and crises.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traditional propaganda , think radio broadcasts, posters, state TV, has now gone high-tech. Platforms like Google Ads and Facebook (Meta) Ads allow paries to target specific audiences with tailored messages at massive scale. In theory, these companies have policies against hate speech or blatant lies. In practice, recent case studies show that sophisticated misinformation campaigns can exploit loopholes and lax enforcement, reaching millions of people with government-funded narratives. From the Israel–Palestine conflict to Russian and domestic political meddling, paid ads are being weaponized to promote war efforts, demonize opponents, and even undermine institutions like the UN. This article examines how it’s happening, why the platforms permit it, and what ethical and policy questions arise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Digital Propaganda via Paid Ads: A New Front in Information Warfare&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paid advertising on Google and Facebook has become a potent tool for political persuasion or manipulation. Unlike organic social media posts (which rely on shares or algorithms), ads can guarantee visibility: if you pay, you reach your target. And the targeting can be extremely granular. Google Ads lets advertisers bid on search keywords or place banner/video ads on websites and YouTube, often filtered by geography or audience interests. Facebook/Meta’s ad system enables micro-targeting by demographics, location, and user interests, while requiring a “paid for by” disclaimer on political ads for transparency. In theory, this gives legitimate political campaigns a way to reach supporters , but it equally gives propagandists a direct channel to the eyeballs of a chosen populace.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers note that this capacity can be abused by partisan or state actors to “manipulate or distract citizens with misinformation and government propaganda,” posing serious challenges to democracy (academic.oup.com). A notorious early example was Russia’s Internet Research Agency, which in 2016 created hundreds of fake Facebook accounts and purchased at least $100,000 worth of divisive ads to influence the U.S. election (abcnews.go.com). Many of those ads didn’t mention candidates directly; instead they amplified polarizing messages on issues like immigration and race to inflame social tensions. At the time, Facebook admitted that most of these propaganda ads “did not violate any company policies or laws,” underscoring how unprepared the platform’s rules were (abcnews.go.com). The incident sparked global awareness that paid media ads could be used as a propaganda weapon , and led to new transparency measures like Facebook’s Ads Library.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet, increased transparency hasn’t prevented the tactic from evolving. Recent conflicts show governments openly turning to ad campaigns as part of their information warfare strategy. Paid ads can be launched rapidly, scaled globally, and tailored to undermine an opponent or shape public perception of a war. Crucially, they also allow a state to influence foreign publics, beyond its own borders, often skirting the line of platform policies and international norms. The sections below explore a timely case study and the broader implications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Case Study: Israel’s Paid Propaganda Campaign in the Gaza War&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the clearest illustrations of war propaganda via paid ads is the Israeli government’s online advertising blitz during the 2023–2025 Gaza war. Israel has long engaged in hasbara (Hebrew for “explanation”), a term for state public relations efforts or propaganda (smex.org). But since the war in Gaza, Israel’s use of digital ads has intensified to unprecedented levels (smex.org).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Targeting the UN: Google Ads to Discredit Humanitarians&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In mid-January 2024, staff at UNRWA USA (a U.S.-based fundraising affiliate of the UN agency) noticed something strange: Google searches for “UNRWA” were yielding an ad that looked like it was from UNRWA, but actually led to an Israeli government site (wired.com). Upon investigation, they discovered a months-long Google Ads campaign by the Israeli Government Advertising Agency to discredit UNRWA (wired.com). The Israeli ads, which were clearly labeled as such in Google’s transparency data, appeared on searches for over 300 related keywords, from “UNRWA” to “Gaza aid”, effectively hijacking traffic from people seeking the UN agency (wired.com). The content of the ads and the landing pages was unmistakably propagandistic: the Israeli site alleged that UNRWA was “inseparable from Hamas” and even employed terrorists (wired.com). One ad bluntly asked, “Paychecks for terrorists or humanitarian aid?”, suggesting money given to UNRWA would fund armed militants (abc.net.au).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The aim of this campaign was clear: to cut off support and donations to the UN’s relief agency in Gaza. It came at a critical time, as UNRWA was providing life-saving food, water, and medical care to Palestinians under siege. UNRWA’s chief, Philippe Lazzarini, blasted Israel’s actions as a “deliberate disinformation campaign” to “dismantle the agency”, warning that smearing a humanitarian organization not only hurts its reputation but “puts the lives of our colleagues on the frontline at serious risk” (abc.net.au). In essence, Israeli authorities were using Google’s advertising system to undermine a UN institution in the middle of a humanitarian crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google’s response was relatively hands-off. When UNRWA representatives appealed to Google to stop what they saw as a dangerous misinformation campaign, the company did not immediately take down the ads (wired.com). A Google spokesperson defended that any government may run ads on Google as long as they adhere to our policies, and stated that Google enforces those rules “consistently and without bias” (wired.com). In other words, because the Israeli ads did not overtly violate Google’s ad policies, they were allowed to run. Notably, Google’s ad policies do prohibit misrepresentation, but they do not have a blanket ban on misinformation unless it relates to specific sensitive areas like election integrity (gomixte.com). As Wired reported, Google generally permits questionable claims in ads “unless it undermines participation or trust in an electoral process” (gomixte.com). This loophole meant that propaganda undermining a humanitarian agency , while arguably unethical , wasn’t against the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result: Israel’s anti-UNRWA ads often outcompeted the agency’s own Google ads. From May through July 2024, in head-to-head bidding, the Israeli ads won the top slot 44% of the time (versus UNRWA USA’s ads showing 34% of the time) (wired.com). UNRWA’s team had to spend tens of thousands of donor dollars trying to outbid Israel for visibility (wired.com). This “insidious” campaign, as UNRWA called it, exposed countless Americans and others to one-sided allegations just as they were searching for facts about Gaza relief (wired.com). “I want the public to know what’s happening,” said UNRWA USA director Mara Kronenfeld, “especially at a time when civilian lives are under attack in Gaza” (wired.com).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By late 2024, news investigations across the world had caught on. ABC News in Australia found that those same Israeli ads linking UNRWA to Hamas were appearing on major Australian news sites, served via Google’s display network (abc.net.au). The ads featured a masked militant wearing both the Hamas emblem and an UNRWA headband, visually equating the UN agency with a terror group (abc.net.au). Captions like “UNRWA has alternatives, it must be replaced” were shown next to news articles (abc.net.au). ABC confirmed at least eight such ad variants were targeted specifically at Australian audiences (in English) and noted the campaign ran in multiple languages including German, Italian, French, and Spanish (abc.net.au). This truly was a global propaganda ad campaign, orchestrated by a government via Google’s platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UNRWA officials, upon learning of the global ads, reiterated that these tactics were “a wider disinformation campaign” by Israel to cripple the agency (abc.net.au). Despite criticism from UN allies (Australia’s Foreign Minister called Israel’s actions “reprehensible” and urged them to stop undermining UNRWA (abc.net.au), the Israeli government showed no signs of relenting. It even escalated measures offline, banning UNRWA operations in Israel, as the online ad offensive continued (abc.net.au)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A coordinated ad push against the Hind Rajab Foundation (HRF)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alongside the UNRWA campaign, the Israeli Government Advertising Agency has also targeted the Hind Rajab Foundation (HRF), an EU-based human-rights nonprofit founded in 2024 to pursue accountability for alleged war crimes in Gaza and named in honor of five-year-old Hind Rajab, whose death became emblematic of the conflict (Hind Rajab Foundation). In Google’s Ads Transparency Center, the agency’s account shows creatives such as “Hind Rajab Foundation — HRF’s disturbing reality” that click through to a government microsite titled “Unmasking the Hind Rajab Foundation,” which portrays HRF as a pseudo-legal front with “extremist” ties (Ads Transparency Center, 2025; Government of Israel). Reporting on Israel’s recent $45 million placement with Google further notes that several ads explicitly link to this “Unmasking” report, indicating a coordinated effort to discredit HRF across search and display (Drop Site News). For context, HRF’s public materials frame the organization as a legal accountability initiative, while the story of Hind Rajab has gained global visibility through Kaouther Ben Hania’s Venice-premiering film The Voice of Hind Rajab, backed by high-profile producers including Brad Pitt, Joaquin Phoenix, Rooney Mara, and Jonathan Glazer, which has amplified awareness of the case well beyond activist circles (Reuters).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Flooding Social Media with War Narratives&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attack on UNRWA was just one facet of Israel’s broader digital PR war. Israeli agencies and allied groups pumped out hundreds of ads across Google/YouTube, Facebook/Instagram, and even children’s gaming apps to influence public opinion about the Gaza conflict. David Saranga, head of the Israeli Foreign Ministry’s digital bureau, confirmed that “the footage is part of a larger advocacy drive” in which the ministry spent $15 million on internet ads in just the first few weeks after October 7, 2023 (smex.org). Those ads often contained graphic and emotional imagery, for example, violent scenes and frightened Israeli families, even appearing as pop-ups in kids’ online games, where they left children “shocked and disturbed” (smex.org). Reuters journalists observed some of these graphic video ads playing in European video games used by children, raising serious questions about appropriateness and consent (business-humanrights.org).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Meta’s platforms (Facebook and Instagram), pro-Israel advertising also spiked dramatically. One effort led by a group calling itself “Facts for Peace” spent over $370,000 on Facebook/Instagram ads in a single month (November 2023) to push viral videos framing all support for Palestine as support for Hamas (business-humanrights.org). These ads, which amassed over 21 million views, were crafted to equate the Palestinian cause with barbaric violence. Despite the obviously misleading and inflammatory nature of such content, it spread widely: it was even promoted by right-wing influencers like Ben Shapiro and shared by official Israeli government social media (e.g. the Israeli embassy in Chile) (business-humanrights.org). Meta’s Ad Library showed 213 ads from Facts for Peace, of which only 3 were taken down for policy violations (business-humanrights.org). Meta told investigators that the campaign did not technically break their rules on transparency, since the ads carried a “Paid for by Facts for Peace” disclaimer and the page was authorized for political advertising. However, nowhere did the group disclose its true funding sources or organizers. (Journalists later linked it to a U.S. billionaire funding pro-Israel messaging (business-humanrights.org.) This case shows how easy it is for a new, opaque group to launch a massive political ad campaign and reach millions before anyone can fully scrutinize it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Israeli government entities themselves also ran extensive campaigns on social media. The Israeli Ministry of Foreign Affairs launched at least 75 distinct ads on YouTube alone in the first months of the war (smex.org). Some of these ads featured what observers called incitement to violence. In one video ad, a menacing message declared: “Israel will take every measure necessary to protect our citizens against these barbaric terrorists,” which borders on a call to collective violence (smex.org). YouTube’s political ads policy forbids content that “encourages others to commit violent acts,” yet this ad apparently slipped through (smex.org). On X (formerly Twitter), the Israeli government and military accounts also placed promoted posts with graphic images (e.g. charred buildings and victims), urging support for their military actions (smex.org). Such ads would seem to violate X’s pre-existing ban on state-affiliated media buying ads (a policy originally aimed at propaganda from outlets like Russia’s RT). Nonetheless, these promotions ran, and some critics questioned if Elon Musk’s open support for Israel influenced X’s lax enforcement (smex.org).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By early 2025, reports revealed that Israel had even formalized a multi-million dollar contract with Google to sustain its global propaganda offensive. According to investigative reporting by Drop Site News (and cited by outlets like TRT World), the Israeli Prime Minister’s Office signed a $45 million, six-month deal with Google in June 2025 to run a worldwide advertising blitz downplaying the humanitarian crisis in Gaza (trtworld.com). The campaign kicked off just after Israeli authorities imposed a siege cutting off food, fuel, and medicine to Gaza in March 2025, and as officials worried about “the public relations fallout”. Leaked documents described Google as a “key entity” in Netanyahu’s PR strategy (trtworld.com). Sure enough, soon after, YouTube and display ads proclaiming “there is food in Gaza. Any other claim is a lie” flooded the internet, with one such video, produced by Israel’s Foreign Ministry, racking up over 6 million views via paid promotion (trtworld.com). In effect, Google was being directly paid to broadcast the message that reports of starvation in Gaza were false, despite widespread documentation of severe hunger by the UN and NGOs. Israeli propaganda officials openly characterized these efforts as “hasbara” — literally “propaganda” — in internal communications (trtworld.com). Alongside Google, Israel spent another $3 million on ads on X (Twitter) and $2.1 million on other ad networks to bolster its narrative (trtworld.com).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The impact of Israel’s ad campaign is hard to quantify, but it undoubtedly reached broad swathes of the global public with the government’s perspective. By framing its military operations as justified self-defense and its critics (even humanitarian agencies) as terrorist sympathizers, Israel’s paid ads sought to shore up international support and neutralize opposition. Given that Israel’s security and billions in military aid depend on Western public opinion (smex.org), this digital influence strategy was a logical extension of the war itself. However, it came at the cost of injecting misinformation and extreme bias into the information ecosystem, potentially skewing public perceptions and policy debates. As we’ll see next, this case also exposes worrying gaps in platform policies and ethical oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Policy Gaps, Double Standards, and Ethical Dilemmas&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The use of paid ads for propaganda raises a blunt question: Are Google and Meta actually enforcing their own rules when it comes to wartime disinformation? The evidence from the above case suggests significant gaps and inconsistencies. Despite formal policies against harmful or misleading content, both companies’ systems enabled, and profited from, campaigns that arguably violate the spirit, if not the letter, of those rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Google’s laissez-faire approach to misinformation: Google’s advertising policies forbid certain categories of content (hate speech, explicit incitement to violence, etc.) and ban misrepresenting who you are. But they do not outright ban false or misleading claims in ads except in narrow contexts like election integrity or COVID-19 info (gomixte.com). This is why blatant propaganda, e.g. accusing a UN agency of abetting terror with scant evidence, can pass muster on Google Ads. Google relied on users or affected parties to report problematic ads, and stated it would “take swift action” if actual policy violations were found (wired.com). But in practice, Google did not pro-actively vet the truth of Israeli government claims. The company was, after all, in a business relationship with Israel (not to mention the formal $45M deal) and may have been reluctant to police a powerful client’s messaging beyond basic checks. This hands-off stance highlights a moral gray area: allowing a paying customer to spread potentially dangerous misinformation because it doesn’t fit neatly into a prohibited category. It suggests that platform policy enforcement can be very literal and reactive, leaving ethical judgment by the wayside.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Meta’s inconsistent enforcement and transparency issues: Facebook/Meta, on paper, has more expansive rules for political ads. They require identity verification for political advertisers and mandate a “Paid for by [Name]” disclosure on each ad. Certain types of violent or hateful content are disallowed even in ads. In the Israel–Gaza context, however, these rules were enforced unevenly. Meta’s own Ads Library data shows a bias: when ads violated policies (e.g. contained hate speech or graphic violence), pro-Palestinian ads were taken down faster and more frequently than pro-Israeli ads (smex.org). SMEX’s analysis of thousands of ads found that Israeli war-cheerleading ads often remained live longer despite breaking rules, whereas ads calling for Gaza humanitarian aid got removed with stricter urgency (smex.org). For example, the “Facts for Peace” videos that implied all Palestinian supporters endorse terror arguably constituted hateful generalization, yet most stayed up until their paid run ended. Meanwhile, at least one civil society test in late 2023 found that Facebook approved ads containing explicit hate speech calling for violence against Palestinians, indicating failures in the automated moderation system (business-humanrights.org). Meta responded that it prioritizes transparency — pointing to the existence of the Ad Library — but researchers found the library frustratingly opaque. Some ads that clearly ran were missing from public search, and crucial data like why an ad was removed or who exactly was targeted were absent (smex.org). Meta shut down useful tools like CrowdTangle (which helped monitor content virality) in 2024, hampering independent oversight (smex.org). All of this suggests that Meta’s professed neutrality masks a deeply flawed system, where enforcement can be influenced by political sensitivities or errors, and where the company’s profit motive in selling ads may conflict with taking decisive action against harmful content.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Double standards for different conflicts: A striking contrast can be seen in how platforms treated Russian state propaganda versus Israeli state propaganda. During Russia’s 2022 invasion of Ukraine, Western tech firms took an unusually hard line against Russia’s online influence operations. Meta banned Russian state media outlets from running ads or monetizing content on its platform and demoted their posts (smex.org). It also aggressively labeled or removed Russian disinformation about the war, under heavy pressure from governments and public opinion. Google similarly demonetized Russian state-affiliated channels (like RT) and limited their reach. These steps were lauded as Big Tech taking a stand against wartime disinformation. Yet, when it came to Israel, engaging in similar behavior, the response was far more lenient. No blanket bans or demonetization were applied to Israeli state entities pushing propaganda, even though some of their content arguably violated the same principles (for instance, denying documented human suffering in Gaza, or using dehumanizing language about “barbaric terrorists” broadly). Observers have pointed out this double standard, noting that platforms seemed willing to bend rules or look the other way for a U.S.-aligned government (smex.org). This inconsistency not only undermines the credibility of platform policies but also raises geopolitical questions: are ethical standards being applied universally, or only when convenient?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Violations of international norms: Beyond platform rules, there’s an argument that some of these ad campaigns tread on international ethical standards or even laws. For example, deliberately spreading false information to obstruct humanitarian aid (as Israel’s anti-UNRWA ads aimed to do) could be seen as running counter to International Humanitarian Law, which seeks to protect aid efforts and civilians during conflict. Incitement to violence against a population is outlawed under the Genocide Convention and other treaties — and while social media ads we’ve discussed stop short of explicit incitement, they foment hatred and misunderstanding that can fuel violence. The UN Secretary-General and other officials have repeatedly condemned the weaponization of disinformation in conflict settings, calling it “destructive” and urging tech companies to clamp down (wired.com) (aljazeera.com). Allowing a state to pay to propagate one-sided or false narratives undermining a UN agency could be seen as abetting an attack on that international institution’s integrity. These are largely uncharted waters, there’s no clear international law for “information warfare”, but the ethical condemnation is growing. As Lazzarini implored, such campaigns “should stop and be investigated”, and social media firms must do more to combat disinformation and hate speech in war (aljazeera.com).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All these issues point back to the central dilemma: What responsibility do the tech giants have when their advertising tools are used to spread propaganda or inflame conflicts? If they act as neutral carriers, they risk facilitating harm; if they intervene, they become arbiters of truth in explosive political situations. The next section looks at how Google, Meta, and others have responded, or failed to respond, and what more could be done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Responsibility of Tech Companies in Wartime Propaganda&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Major tech companies often insist they are platforms, not publishers, they provide the space, but aren’t responsible for every message that advertisers choose to push. However, the extreme examples we’ve explored put that claim to the test. When a company is paid millions to disseminate content that may be false or harmful, can it really wash its hands of accountability? Here are some considerations and responses from the companies and experts:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Official stances and defenses: Google’s official line, as noted, is that it applies its ad policies equally to all, including governments, and will remove ads that violate those policies (wired.com). Implicit in that statement is that Google does not see itself as the arbiter of factual truth in ads, unless a lie crosses certain predefined lines, Google will host it for a paying client. Meta, for its part, touts the transparency of its system. A Meta spokesperson, responding to concerns about the “Facts for Peace” campaign, emphasized that the ads were “clearly labeled with a ‘paid by’ disclaimer” and publicly archived in the Ads Library, implying that this level of transparency exceeds that of TV or print political ads (business-humanrights.org). Meta also points out that it has an Ad Standards enforcement team and that ads violating policies (when caught) are taken down and documented. In practice, as we saw, that enforcement can lag or falter — but the company’s message is that shining light on ads is the solution, rather than heavy-handed censorship.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Profit vs. principle: Critics argue that a big reason these platforms struggle to self-regulate is that they make money from every ad impression. When conflict-related content goes viral, ad spending surges. A joint analysis by CalMatters and The Markup found that after war broke out in Gaza on Oct 7, 2023, Meta saw a major increase in ad revenue related to the conflict (calmatters.org). In October 2023 alone, an estimated $3.1 million was spent on Facebook ads about the Israel–Gaza war, a huge spike compared to previous months (calmatters.org). This includes not just state propaganda but also ads for fundraising, merchandise, and advocacy around the crisis. The point is that war and political violence can become lucrative business for social media companies, something Meta’s own employees have acknowledged internally (Facebook famously admitted that outrage and misinformation drive engagement, which in turn drives ad revenue (calmatters.org). This profit motive can create a perverse disincentive to crack down on borderline content. While $3 million is a drop in the bucket of Meta’s $100+ billion annual revenue, it’s still revenue. And for Google, a $45 million contract from Israel’s government is significant. The companies risk accusations of “conflict profiteering” if they appear to take money to propagate one side’s propaganda. This has led to calls for them to refuse or refund ad buys that clearly aim to deceive or stoke conflict, though such moves remain rare.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Calls for stronger policies: Human rights organizations and digital rights groups are urging the platforms to develop special policies for ads in conflict zones or on politically sensitive issues. For instance, SMEX and others have suggested that in the context of an armed conflict, platforms should implement tailored rules to prevent the spread of hate speech and misinformation via ads, given the real-world stakes (smex.org). Concretely, this could mean temporarily banning state-run or state-funded advertising in active conflict situations, or at least subjecting them to human review and fact-checking. It could also mean disallowing ads that target foreign populations with war propaganda, treating it akin to foreign election interference. Another idea floated by experts is a “circuit breaker” approach: if a sudden war or crisis erupts, platforms might pause all political and issue-based ads in the affected regions until they can ramp up oversight. (Notably, Meta has recently decided to halt all political, electoral, and social issue ads in the entire EU starting in 2025, in response to new regulations (about.fb.com). This broad-brush ban is a compliance move for Europe, but it shows that turning off political ads is technically feasible when mandated.)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Transparency and researcher access: Many observers argue that if companies won’t ban propaganda ads outright, they should at least empower watchdogs to track and expose them. This means improving their ad transparency tools. Meta’s shutting down of CrowdTangle and the limitations of the Ads Library have drawn heavy criticism (smex.orgsmex.org). Experts like Sam Jeffers of Who Targets Me advocate for more robust disclosures — for example, revealing detailed targeting parameters of political ads (so we know who governments are trying to influence) and keeping archives of removed ads including why they were removed (business-humanrights.org) (smex.org). There are also calls for independent audits of platform algorithms and ad delivery, to see if certain viewpoints are getting amplified unfairly. Ultimately, greater transparency can help civil society and journalists “police” the propaganda if the platforms themselves are slow to do so.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Regulatory pressure and international standards: Governments and international bodies are starting to weigh in. The European Union’s Digital Services Act (DSA) and upcoming regulations on political advertising put legal requirements on big platforms to prevent misuse. For example, the DSA requires rapid removal of illegal content (which could include illegal hate speech or incitement in ads) and hefty fines for non-compliance. The EU is also pushing for strict transparency on political ads and even contemplating banning microtargeting for political messages. These rules, though EU-specific, often end up being adopted globally by platforms for simplicity’s sake. Outside of Europe, the lack of regulation has been evident, which is why UN officials like Lazzarini are directly calling for “more regulations for companies… to combat disinformation and hate speech” online (aljazeera.com). We may see moves in the UN or other international forums to establish norms against certain propaganda techniques. In the long run, if self-regulation fails, tech companies might face binding rules prohibiting them from accepting money for ads that undermine peace and truth, a challenging rule to draft, but an increasingly pertinent conversation.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The era of governments weaponizing Google and Facebook ads is upon us, raising thorny questions about truth, free speech, and corporate responsibility in the digital age. The case of Israel’s advertising blitz in the Gaza war demonstrates how easily paid platforms can be turned into tools of war propaganda, blasting millions with biased or false narratives at the click of a button. It also shows the real harms at stake: humanitarian aid blocked, democratic institutions undermined, and public discourse polluted. And Israel is not alone, from superpowers to militant groups, many actors have tested the boundaries of online ads to sway hearts and minds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the platforms, this is a moment of reckoning. Can Google and Meta continue to say “we’re just the middleman” while cashing checks for propaganda campaigns? Critics argue that neutrality is not neutral when it enables deception and violence. Yet, deciding where to draw the line is complex. Mistakes or overreach in moderation could themselves be seen as partisan interference. The tightrope between allowing robust political advocacy and preventing harmful propaganda is a difficult one to walk, especially under global scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is clear is that doing nothing is no longer tenable. Sunlight and accountability are the minimum: users deserve to know who is behind the political ads they see and to have confidence that egregious lies or incitements won’t be promoted by the world’s most powerful information platforms. Moving forward, it will likely require a mix of solutions , improved self-governance by tech firms, independent oversight, and smart regulation, to ensure that the tools of modern advertising are not abused to foment conflict or erode democracy. As the saying goes, “In war, truth is the first casualty.” In our digital world, we must decide how much we are willing to let paid algorithms hasten that casualty, or whether we can find ways to uphold truth even amid the fog of online war.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google involved in $45M deal with Netanyahu’s office to advertise Israeli hasbara — report — TRT World https://www.trtworld.com/world/article/538017f344e5&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Israel Is Buying Google Ads to Discredit the UN’s Top Gaza Aid Agency | WIRED https://www.wired.com/story/israel-unrwa-usa-hamas-google-search-ads/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UNRWA head accuses Israel of buying Google ads to block donations to agency | UNRWA News | Al Jazeera https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2024/8/31/unrwa-head-accuses-israel-of-buying-google-ads-to-block-donations-to-agency&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mass Political Information on Social Media: Facebook Ads … https://academic.oup.com/jeea/article/22/4/1678/7607367&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Facebook says it sold $100,000 in ads to fake Russian accounts during presidential election — ABC News https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/facebook-sold-100000-ads-fake-russian-accounts-presidential/story?id=49667831&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inside the Israeli occupation’s propaganda ad factory — SMEX https://smex.org/inside-the-israeli-occupations-propaganda-ad-factory/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google ads linking UNRWA with Hamas appearon Australian news websites as part of a global campaign — ABC News https://www.abc.net.au/news/2024-12-05/unrwa-hamas-google-ads-published-on-australian-news-sites/104685074&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How Google Ads Are Weaponized — Mixte Communications https://gomixte.com/blog/how-google-ads-are-weaponized/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Palestine/Israel: Viral campaign ads attacking proPalestine movement points to concerning gaps in Meta rules; incl. co. comment — Business &amp;amp; Human Rights Resource Centre https://www.business-humanrights.org/en/latest-news/palestineisrael-viral-campaign-ads-attacking-pro-palestine-movementpoints-to-concerning-gaps-in-meta-rules-incl-co-comment/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Transparency Fails: Meta’s Political Ad Policy During Israel’s War on Gaza — SMEX https://smex.org/when-transparency-fails-metas-political-ad-policy-during-israels-war-on-gaza/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How Meta brings in millions off political violence — CalMatters https://calmatters.org/economy/technology/2024/10/how-meta-brings-in-millions-off-political-violence/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ending Political, Electoral and Social Issue Advertising in the EU in … https://about.fb.com/news/2025/07/ending-political-electoral-and-social-issue-advertising-in-the-eu/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ads Transparency Center. (2025). Israeli Government Advertising Agency [Advertiser page]. Google. https://adstransparency.google.com/advertiser/AR00827556497616535553&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Drop Site News. (2025, June 18). Google’s $45 million contract with Netanyahu’s office to launder Gaza famine denial through ads. https://www.dropsitenews.com/p/google-youtube-netanyahu-israel-propaganda-gaza-famine&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reuters. (2025, September 4). Venice ovation fuels hopes for Gaza girl film to reach global audience. https://www.reuters.com/business/media-telecom/venice-ovation-fuels-hopes-gaza-girl-film-reach-global-audience-2025-09-04/&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45181094</guid></item><item><title>Google to Obey South Korean Order to Blur Satellite Images on Maps</title><link>https://www.barrons.com/news/google-to-obey-south-korean-order-to-blur-satellite-images-on-maps-653e934e</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="298e9ed01ca6598f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Google To Obey South Korean Order To Blur Satellite Images On Maps&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Google said on Tuesday that it would comply with the South Korean government's demand to blur sensitive satellite images on its mapping services, paving the way for the US tech giant to compete better with local navigation platforms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Barron's news department was not involved in the creation of the content above. This article was produced by AFP. For more information go to AFP.com.&lt;lb/&gt;© Agence France-Presse&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Continue reading this article with a Barron’s subscription&lt;/p&gt;SUBSCRIBE NOW&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45181626</guid></item><item><title>Apple highlights Brazilian study on domestic App Store performance</title><link>https://9to5mac.com/2025/09/04/apple-highlights-brazilian-study-on-domestic-app-store-performance/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a4ecbbba13961150"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the App Store faces increasing regulatory pressure in Brazil, a study highlighted by Apple today shows that iOS apps generated R$63.8 million ($11.7 million) in the country last year, with most of that revenue incurring no commission. Here are the details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A bit of background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like in many countries around the world, Apple has been fighting an uphill battle in Brazil, hoping to convince local regulators to keep the App Store model intact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In late 2022, MercadoLibre, Latin America’s biggest online marketplace, filed an antitrust complaint against Apple, accusing it of unfair practices related to the App Store.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since then, Apple has had its ups and downs in court, and it currently has until October to comply with orders that involve allowing sideloading on iOS and alternative payment methods beyond its own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As it stands right now, Apple and CADE (the country’s competition watchdog) are working together to iron out the details, as Apple still tries to reverse the situation. So far, Apple has managed to score a few postponements, but the deadline is reportedly currently set for October.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What today’s study says&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study highlighted by Apple today was conducted by Silvia Fagá de Almeida, an MBA professor at Fundação Getúlio Vargas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study concluded that the App Store generated R$63.8 billion ($11.7 billion) for Brazilian developers last year, with 90% of that revenue exempt from Apple’s commission.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It also noted that Brazilian developers saw a total of 570 million app downloads across the globe last year, and that 53% of that total came from users outside Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When it comes to commission fees, the study revealed that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“(…) most Brazilian developers who sell digital products and services are entitled to a reduced 15% commission on sales made through in-app purchases or paid downloads (for example, through the App Store Small Business Program and the Video Partner Program). The majority of Brazilian developers pay no commission to Apple, and among those who did pay a commission in 2024, 78% benefited from the reduced rate.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the study also breaks down the revenue facilitated by the App Store into categories (the numbers add up to 101% due to rounding adjustments):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;10% went to digital products and services&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;79% went to physical products and services&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;12% went to in-app advertising&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alongside the study, Apple also touted the fact that Brazilian users downloaded 1,5 billion apps last year, and that the country’s App Store had 25,5 million visits per week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple also pointed to its local initiatives for developers, including 10 Apple Developer Academy locations across Brazil, and success stories like Moises, the 2024 iPad App of the Year, as examples of domestic apps that achieved global growth. The company framed these as proof that the App Store should be seen as a launchpad rather than a walled garden.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find the full post (in Brazilian Portuguese) here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Accessory deals on Amazon&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apple AirTag 4 Pack, 19% off&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apple AirTag, 17% off&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Beats USB-C to USB-C Woven Short Cable, 19% off&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Wireless CarPlay adapter, $10 off&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links. More.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45182108</guid></item><item><title>U.S. Added 911,000 Fewer Jobs in Year Through March Than Reported Earlier</title><link>https://www.barrons.com/articles/jobs-report-revisions-bls-fed-3d88c77b?st=u8mw75</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45182111</guid></item><item><title>New Mexico is first state in US to offer universal child care</title><link>https://www.governor.state.nm.us/2025/09/08/new-mexico-is-first-state-in-nation-to-offer-universal-child-care/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="29aab1d30fac0dbe"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;PRESS RELEASES&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;New Mexico is first state in nation to offer universal child care&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SANTA FE — Governor Michelle Lujan Grisham and the New Mexico Early Childhood Education and Care Department announced a historic milestone on Monday: New Mexico will become the first state in the nation to guarantee no-cost universal child care starting Nov. 1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This groundbreaking new initiative will make child care available to all New Mexicans, regardless of income, by removing income eligibility requirements from the state’s child care assistance program and continuing the waiver of family copayments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Child care is essential to family stability, workforce participation, and New Mexico’s future prosperity,” said Lujan Grisham. “By investing in universal child care, we are giving families financial relief, supporting our economy, and ensuring that every child has the opportunity to grow and thrive.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This announcement fulfills the promise made by the governor and the New Mexico Legislature when they created the Early Childhood Education and Care Department in 2019. Since then, New Mexico has expanded access to no-cost child care to families with incomes at or below 400% of the federal poverty level, reducing financial strain on tens of thousands of families.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Monday’s announcement universal child care will be extended to every family in the state, regardless of income. This amounts to an average annual family savings of $12,000 per child.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“New Mexico is creating the conditions for better outcomes in health, learning, and well-being,” said Neal Halfon, professor of pediatrics, public health and public policy at the University of California, Los Angeles, and director of the Center for Healthier Children, Families, and Communities. “Its approach is rooted in data, driven by communities, and becoming a model for the nation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“By prioritizing public investments in early childhood educators, families, and children, New Mexico continues to lead the way in building a sustainable, affordable, and quality child care and early learning system that helps its communities and economy thrive,” said Michelle Kang, president and CEO of the National Association of the Education of Young Children (NAEYC). “Achieving universal child care will make a huge difference for the state’s children, families, businesses, and educators—and for all of us, by showing that it can be done.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Families who receive child care assistance report greater financial stability, more time to focus on their children, and the ability to choose higher-quality care settings. Now, every family in New Mexico will have the same opportunity. New Mexico is also taking decisive action to build the supply of infant and toddler care statewide:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Establishing a $12.7 million low-interest loan fund to construct, expand, and renovate child care facilities, with an additional $20 million requested in the Fiscal Year 2027 budget.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Targeting growth to focus on care for infants, toddlers, low-income families, and children with special needs.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Partnering with employers and school districts to expand child care options for working families.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Launching a statewide campaign to recruit licensed and registered home providers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;To support providers, reimbursement rates will rise to reflect the true cost of care.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programs that commit to paying entry-level staff a minimum of $18 per hour and offer 10 hours of care per day, five days a week, will receive an incentive rate. New Mexico estimates an additional 5,000 early childhood professionals are needed to fully achieve a universal system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Early childhood care and education is a public good,” said ECECD Sec. Elizabeth Groginsky. “By providing universal access and improving pay for our early childhood workforce, we are easing financial pressure on families, strengthening our economy, and helping every child learn in safe, nurturing environments. This is the kind of investment that builds equity today and prosperity for the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With universal child care, New Mexico is leading the nation by showing that what is best for children and families is also the smartest investment for long-term prosperity—building a stronger future for every community in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information about how families and providers can access universal child care benefits, visit and toolkit: ECECD Universal Child Care Resources Page.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45182372</guid></item><item><title>Claude can now create and edit files</title><link>https://www.anthropic.com/news/create-files</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="156a1e7a6ff712a3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Claude can now create and edit files&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude can now create and edit Excel spreadsheets, documents, PowerPoint slide decks, and PDFs directly in Claude.ai and the desktop app. This transforms how you work with Claude—instead of only receiving text responses or in-app artifacts, you can describe what you need, upload relevant data, and get ready-to-use files in return.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;File creation is now available as a preview for Max, Team, and Enterprise plan users. Pro users will get access in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What you can do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude creates actual files from your instructions—whether working from uploaded data, researching information, or building from scratch. Here are just a few examples:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Turn data into insights: Give Claude raw data and get back polished outputs with cleaned data, statistical analysis, charts, and written insights explaining what matters.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Build spreadsheets: Describe what you need—financial models with scenario analysis, project trackers with automated dashboards, or budget templates with variance calculations. Claude creates it with working formulas and multiple sheets.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cross-format work: Upload a PDF report and get PowerPoint slides. Share meeting notes and get a formatted document. Upload invoices and get organized spreadsheets with calculations. Claude handles the tedious work and presents information how you need it.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether you need a customer segmentation analysis, sales forecasting, or budget tracking, Claude handles the technical work and produces the files you need. File creation turns projects that normally require programming expertise, statistical knowledge, and hours of effort into minutes of conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How it works: Claude’s computer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past year we've seen Claude move from answering questions to completing entire projects, and now we're making that power more accessible. We've given Claude access to a private computer environment where it can write code and run programs to produce the files and analyses you need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This transforms Claude from an advisor into an active collaborator. You bring the context and strategy; Claude handles the technical implementation behind the scenes. This shows where we’re headed: making sophisticated multi-step work accessible through conversation. As these capabilities expand, the gap between idea and execution will keep shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Getting started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To start creating files:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enable "Upgraded file creation and analysis" under Settings &amp;gt; Features &amp;gt; Experimental&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Upload relevant files or describe what you need&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Guide Claude through the work via chat&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Download your completed files or save directly to Google Drive&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start with straightforward tasks like data cleaning or simple reports, then work up to complex projects like financial models once you're comfortable with how Claude handles files.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This feature gives Claude internet access to create and analyze files, which may put your data at risk. Monitor chats closely when using this feature. Learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45182381</guid></item><item><title>US HS students lose ground in math and reading, continuing yearslong decline</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/naep-reading-math-scores-12th-grade-c18d6e3fbc125f12948cc70cb85a520a</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45182657</guid></item><item><title>We All Dodged a Bullet</title><link>https://xeiaso.net/notes/2025/we-dodged-a-bullet/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="4e7e82b81462420f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Making sure you're not a bot! Loading... Please wait a moment while we ensure the security of your connection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45183029</guid></item><item><title>X open sourced their latest algorithm</title><link>https://github.com/twitter/the-algorithm</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="334a9371444e26e2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;X's Recommendation Algorithm is a set of services and jobs that are responsible for serving feeds of posts and other content across all X product surfaces (e.g. For You Timeline, Search, Explore, Notifications). For an introduction to how the algorithm works, please refer to our engineering blog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Product surfaces at X are built on a shared set of data, models, and software frameworks. The shared components included in this repository are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Component&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Data&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tweetypie&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Core service that handles the reading and writing of post data.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;unified-user-actions&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Real-time stream of user actions on X.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;user-signal-service&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Centralized platform to retrieve explicit (e.g. likes, replies) and implicit (e.g. profile visits, tweet clicks) user signals.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Model&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SimClusters&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Community detection and sparse embeddings into those communities.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;TwHIN&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Dense knowledge graph embeddings for Users and Posts.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;trust-and-safety-models&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Models for detecting NSFW or abusive content.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;real-graph&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Model to predict the likelihood of an X User interacting with another User.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tweepcred&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Page-Rank algorithm for calculating X User reputation.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;recos-injector&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Streaming event processor for building input streams for GraphJet based services.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;graph-feature-service&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Serves graph features for a directed pair of users (e.g. how many of User A's following liked posts from User B).&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;topic-social-proof&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Identifies topics related to individual posts.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;representation-scorer&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Compute scores between pairs of entities (Users, Posts, etc.) using embedding similarity.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Software framework&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;navi&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;High performance, machine learning model serving written in Rust.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;product-mixer&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Software framework for building feeds of content.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;timelines-aggregation-framework&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Framework for generating aggregate features in batch or real time.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;representation-manager&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Service to retrieve embeddings (i.e. SimClusers and TwHIN).&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;twml&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Legacy machine learning framework built on TensorFlow v1.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The product surfaces currently included in this repository are the For You Timeline and Recommended Notifications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The diagram below illustrates how major services and jobs interconnect to construct a For You Timeline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core components of the For You Timeline included in this repository are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Component&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Candidate Source&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;search-index&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Find and rank In-Network posts. ~50% of posts come from this candidate source.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tweet-mixer&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Coordination layer for fetching Out-of-Network tweet candidates from underlying compute services.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;user-tweet-entity-graph (UTEG)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Maintains an in memory User to Post interaction graph, and finds candidates based on traversals of this graph. This is built on the GraphJet framework. Several other GraphJet based features and candidate sources are located here.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;follow-recommendation-service (FRS)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Provides Users with recommendations for accounts to follow, and posts from those accounts.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ranking&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;light-ranker&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Light Ranker model used by search index (Earlybird) to rank posts.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;heavy-ranker&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Neural network for ranking candidate posts. One of the main signals used to select timeline posts post candidate sourcing.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Post mixing &amp;amp; filtering&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;home-mixer&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Main service used to construct and serve the Home Timeline. Built on product-mixer.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;visibility-filters&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Responsible for filtering X content to support legal compliance, improve product quality, increase user trust, protect revenue through the use of hard-filtering, visible product treatments, and coarse-grained downranking.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;timelineranker&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Legacy service which provides relevance-scored posts from the Earlybird Search Index and UTEG service.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core components of Recommended Notifications included in this repository are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Component&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Service&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;pushservice&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Main recommendation service at X used to surface recommendations to our users via notifications.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ranking&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;pushservice-light-ranker&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Light Ranker model used by pushservice to rank posts. Bridges candidate generation and heavy ranking by pre-selecting highly-relevant candidates from the initial huge candidate pool.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;pushservice-heavy-ranker&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Multi-task learning model to predict the probabilities that the target users will open and engage with the sent notifications.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We include Bazel BUILD files for most components, but not a top-level BUILD or WORKSPACE file. We plan to add a more complete build and test system in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We invite the community to submit GitHub issues and pull requests for suggestions on improving the recommendation algorithm. We are working on tools to manage these suggestions and sync changes to our internal repository. Any security concerns or issues should be routed to our official bug bounty program through HackerOne. We hope to benefit from the collective intelligence and expertise of the global community in helping us identify issues and suggest improvements, ultimately leading to a better X.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read our blog on the open source initiative here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45183039</guid></item></channel></rss>