<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 05:40:55 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Why are my headphones buzzing whenever I run my game?</title><link>https://alexene.dev/2025/12/03/Why-do-my-headphones-buzz-when-i-run-my-game.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f6e835137dac0b9f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why are my headphones buzzing whenever I run my game?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am working on an isometric game inspired from Gnomoria, RimWorld, Dwarf Fortress, etc. It uses my own simple engine (with rust and wgpu-rs). Whenever I started my game, my headphones were buzzing. I could play Fortnite, Overwatch or any other game and that doesn’t cause my headphones to buzz. It’s only my game.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it’s really annoying, as you might imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why can I play Overwatch and Fortnite fine, while my isometric game makes my headset buzz? I had a fairly decent CPU, a 3090RTX card, 32GB RAM and USB audio through a MODI 2 DAC. Nothing out of this world, but nothing too bad. One important detail here is that the power to the MODI device comes from an USB port in my computer. This was the first clue, I tried other ports with no change in results (headphones still buzzed).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially, I started to think it’s some sort of power-use related issue, because maybe my PSU was getting old, or had daemons in it. However, I still couldn’t explain why my tiny game was causing more chaos than say big games that send significantly more work at my PC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I noticed is that when it didn’t render anything, nothing buzzed (I run tests with rendering disabled). So that eliminated any sort of CPU work causing it. Let’s take a look at what the GPU does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The pipeline&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game has a simple graphics pipeline. I use WebGPU (more precisely wgpu-rs) and do some compute work to select visible entities, then use draw indirect to draw those entities. In the end, my render pipeline also outputs two things: the buffer that ends up on screen and a “picking texture”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A picking texture is a very simple idea. As the name says, it’s used to handle picking in the game, when you click somewhere on the screen (e.g. to select an unit), I use this texture to know what you clicked on. Instead of colors, every object instance writes their EntityID to this texture. Then, when you click the mouse, you check what id is in the pixel under the mouse position.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of a frame, I copy that picking texture back to RAM (from GPU memory), to check it against mouse positions in case of a click.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t ideal as transfers from GPU-&amp;gt;CPU memory take time, but it works and is way simpler to implement and debug than casting a ray through the scene:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;So why does rendering make my headphones buzz?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we have a picture of how the rendering in my game works, time to debug it. We know it’s something to do with the GPU work, but what can possibly cause this? As the trace above shows, my GPU is not under heavy load.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I was stuck and had no idea on what can be a likely issue, I proceeded to then disable parts of my rendering pipeline (first the compute, then the rendering, then transferring the picking texture). When I skipped downloading the picking texture the buzzing was fully gone. What was confusing in this process is that disabling parts of the pipeline, somehow made the buzzing a lower volume and less noticeable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be sure it was the picking texture download, I also issued the download every 250ms and noticed the noise is almost gone. Increasing the frequency on how often we download it to RAM, increased the buzzing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So at this point I had a likely source, but no idea why things would interfere in ways to what I assumed was the power to my MODI device. Through a bunch of discussion with other graphics engineers, someone suggested it may be due to the fact that I full on hit the GPU with tons of work, then pause the GPU to wait for that picking texture to transfer, then turn it back on 100% for the next frame.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That explanation is plausible and also likely as I further on proceeded to supply power to my MODI device from another source that’s not my PC and the buzzing was gone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we know this, all was left is to fix it. In hindsight, the solution is obvious. There’s no need to download the whole texture each frame, just the part of the picking texture that’s under the mouse. So I implemented that and it worked and buzzing is gone. As a bonus, now it’s also not visible at all on the GPU trace.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46135627</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:30:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MinIO is now in maintenance-mode</title><link>https://github.com/minio/minio/commit/27742d469462e1561c776f88ca7a1f26816d69e2</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="37a3c795b9d7e61e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;main&gt;
            &lt;turbo-frame&gt;
              &lt;div&gt;
                &lt;react-app&gt;
                  &lt;div&gt;
                    &lt;div&gt;
                      &lt;div&gt;
                        &lt;div&gt;
                          &lt;div&gt;
                            &lt;div&gt;
                              &lt;div&gt;
                                &lt;h2&gt;File tree&lt;/h2&gt;
                                &lt;div&gt;
                                  &lt;div&gt;
                                    &lt;div&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;Expand file tree&lt;/span&gt;
                                      &lt;button/&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;Collapse file tree&lt;/span&gt;
                                      &lt;h2&gt;1 file changed&lt;/h2&gt;
                                      &lt;p&gt;+14&lt;/p&gt;
                                      &lt;p&gt;-0&lt;/p&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;lines changed&lt;/span&gt;
                                    &lt;/div&gt;
                                  &lt;/div&gt;
                                &lt;/div&gt;
                              &lt;/div&gt;
                            &lt;/div&gt;
                          &lt;/div&gt;
                          &lt;div&gt;
                            &lt;div&gt;
                              &lt;div&gt;
                                &lt;div&gt;
                                  &lt;div&gt;
                                    &lt;div&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;Expand file tree&lt;/span&gt;
                                      &lt;button/&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;Collapse file tree&lt;/span&gt;
                                      &lt;h2&gt;1 file changed&lt;/h2&gt;
                                      &lt;p&gt;+14&lt;/p&gt;
                                      &lt;p&gt;-0&lt;/p&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;lines changed&lt;/span&gt;
                                    &lt;/div&gt;
                                  &lt;/div&gt;
                                  &lt;div&gt;
                                    &lt;div&gt;
                                      &lt;div&gt;
                                        &lt;table&gt;
                                          &lt;thead&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;th&gt;Original file line number&lt;/th&gt;
                                              &lt;th&gt;Diff line number&lt;/th&gt;
                                              &lt;th&gt;Diff line change&lt;/th&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                          &lt;/thead&gt;
                                          &lt;tbody&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;
                                                    &lt;span&gt;# &lt;span&gt;Maintenance Mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;**&lt;/span&gt;This project is currently under maintenance and is not accepting new changes.&lt;span&gt;**&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;4&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;5&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; The codebase is in a maintenance-only state&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;6&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; No new features, enhancements, or pull requests will be accepted&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;7&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; Critical security fixes may be evaluated on a case-by-case basis&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;8&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; Existing issues and pull requests will not be actively reviewed&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;9&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; Community support continues on a best-effort basis through &lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;Slack&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://slack.min.io&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;10&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;11&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;For enterprise support and actively maintained versions, please see &lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;MinIO AIStor&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://www.min.io/product/aistor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;12&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;13&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;
                                                    &lt;span&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;14&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;15&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;
                                                    &lt;span&gt;# &lt;span&gt;MinIO Quickstart Guide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;16&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;17&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;![&lt;/span&gt;Slack&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://slack.min.io/slack?type=svg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://slack.min.io&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;![&lt;/span&gt;Docker Pulls&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://img.shields.io/docker/pulls/minio/minio.svg?maxAge=604800&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://hub.docker.com/r/minio/minio/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;![&lt;/span&gt;license&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://img.shields.io/badge/license-AGPL%20V3-blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://github.com/minio/minio/blob/master/LICENSE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                          &lt;/tbody&gt;
                                        &lt;/table&gt;
                                      &lt;/div&gt;
                                    &lt;/div&gt;
                                  &lt;/div&gt;
                                &lt;/div&gt;
                                &lt;svg&gt;
                                  &lt;defs/&gt;
                                &lt;/svg&gt;
                              &lt;/div&gt;
                            &lt;/div&gt;
                          &lt;/div&gt;
                        &lt;/div&gt;
                      &lt;/div&gt;
                    &lt;/div&gt;
                  &lt;/div&gt;
                &lt;/react-app&gt;
              &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;/turbo-frame&gt;
          &lt;/main&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;svg/&gt;
        &lt;button&gt;
          &lt;svg/&gt;
        &lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;p&gt; You can’t perform that action at this time. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;template&gt;
        &lt;details&gt;
          &lt;details-dialog&gt;
            &lt;button&gt;
              &lt;svg/&gt;
            &lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;/details-dialog&gt;
        &lt;/details&gt;
      &lt;/template&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46136023</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 16:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>RCE Vulnerability in React and Next.js</title><link>https://github.com/vercel/next.js/security/advisories/GHSA-9qr9-h5gf-34mp</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9b77f64ed15ff8f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;RCE in React Server Components&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Package&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Affected versions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;=14.3.0-canary.77, &amp;gt;=15, &amp;gt;=16&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Patched versions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v16.0.7, v15.5.7, v15.4.8, v15.3.6, v15.2.6, v15.1.9, v15.0.5&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Description&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A vulnerability affects certain React packages1 for versions 19.0.0, 19.1.0, 19.1.1, and 19.2.0 and frameworks that use the affected packages, including Next.js 15.x and 16.x using the App Router. The issue is tracked upstream as CVE-2025-55182.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixed in:&lt;lb/&gt; React: 19.0.1, 19.1.2, 19.2.1&lt;lb/&gt; Next.js: 15.0.5, 15.1.9, 15.2.6, 15.3.6, 15.4.8, 15.5.7, 16.0.7&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vulnerability also affects experimental canary releases starting with 14.3.0-canary.77. Users on any of the 14.3 canary builds should either downgrade to a 14.x stable release or 14.3.0-canary.76.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All users of stable 15.x or 16.x Next.js versions should upgrade to a patched, stable version immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1 The affected React packages are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;react-server-dom-parcel&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;react-server-dom-turbopack&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;react-server-dom-webpack&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46136026</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 16:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>1D Conway's Life glider found, 3.7B cells long</title><link>https://conwaylife.com/forums/viewtopic.php?&amp;p=222136#p222136</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46137253</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 17:24:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Reverse engineering a $1B Legal AI tool exposed 100k+ confidential files</title><link>https://alexschapiro.com/security/vulnerability/2025/12/02/filevine-api-100k</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3555f7864f2737d5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How I Reverse Engineered a Billion-Dollar Legal AI Tool and Found 100k+ Confidential Files&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Zero authentication, full admin access, and a privacy nightmare for lawyers.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update: This post received a large amount of attention on Hacker News — see the discussion thread.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Timeline &amp;amp; Responsible Disclosure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initial Contact: Upon discovering this vulnerability on October 27, 2025, I immediately reached out to Filevine’s security team via email.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;November 4, 2025: Filevine’s security team thanked me for the writeup and confirmed they would review the vulnerability and fix it quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;November 20, 2025: I followed up to confirm the patch was in place from my end, and informed them of my intention to write a technical blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;November 21, 2025: Filevine confirmed the issue was resolved and thanked me for responsibly reporting it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Publication: December 3, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Filevine team was responsive, professional, and took the findings seriously throughout the disclosure process. They acknowledged the severity, worked to remediate the issues, allowed responsible disclosure, and maintained clear communication. This is another great example of how organizations should handle security disclosures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI legal-tech companies are exploding in value, and Filevine, now valued at over a billion dollars, is one of the fastest-growing platforms in the space. Law firms feed tools like this enormous amounts of highly confidential information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because I’d recently been working with Yale Law School on a related project, I decided to take a closer look at how Filevine handles data security. What I discovered should concern every legal professional using AI systems today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I first navigated to the site to see how it worked, it seemed that I needed to be part of a law firm to actually play around with the tooling, or request an official demo. However, I know that companies often have a demo environment that is open, so I used a technique called subdomain enumeration (which I had first heard about in Gal Nagli’s article last year) to see if there was a demo environment. I found something much more interesting instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I saw a subdomain called margolis.filevine.com. When I navigated to that site, I was greeted with a loading page that never resolved:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wanted to see what was actually loading, so I opened Chrome’s developer tools, but saw no Fetch/XHR requests (the request you often expect to see if a page is loading data). Then, I decided to dig through some of the Javascript files to see if I could figure out what was supposed to be happening. I saw a snippet in a JS file like &lt;code&gt;POST await fetch(${BOX_SERVICE}/recommend)&lt;/code&gt;. This piqued my interest – recommend what? And what is the BOX_SERVICE? That variable was not defined in the JS file the fetch would be called from, but (after looking through minified code, which SUCKS to do) I found it in another one: “dxxxxxx9.execute-api.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/prod”. Now I had a new endpoint to test, I just had to figure out the correct payload structure to it. After looking at more minified js to determine the correct structure for this endpoint, I was able to construct a working payload to /prod/recommend:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{"projectName":"Very sensitive Project"}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(the name could be anything of course). No authorization tokens needed, and I was greeted with the response:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At first I didn’t entirely understand the impact of what I saw. No matter the name of the project I passed in, I was recommended the same boxFolders and couldn’t seem to access any files. Then, not realizing I stumbled upon something massive, I turned my attention to the &lt;code&gt;boxToken&lt;/code&gt; in the response.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After reading some documentation on the Box Api, I realized this was a maximum access fully scoped admin token to the entire Box filesystem (like an internal shared Google Drive) of this law firm. This includes all confidential files, logs, user information, etc. Once I was able to prove this had an impact (by searching for “confidential” and getting nearly 100k results back)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I immediately stopped testing and responsibly disclosed this to Filevine. They responded quickly and professionally and remediated this issue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If someone had malicious intent, they would have been able to extract every single file used by Margolis lawyers – countless data protected by HIPAA and other legal standards, internal memos/payrolls, literally millions of the most sensitive documents this law firm has in their possession. Documents protected by court orders! This could have been a real nightmare for both the law firm and the clients whose data would have been exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To companies who feel pressure to rush into the AI craze in their industry – be careful! Always ensure the companies you are giving your most sensitive information to secure that data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46137514</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 17:44:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Launch HN: Phind 3 (YC S22) – Every answer is a mini-app</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46137548</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2c6a25dd25d976dd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hi HN,&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We are launching Phind 3 (https://www.phind.com), an AI answer engine that instantly builds a complete mini-app to answer and visualize your questions in an interactive way. A Phind mini-app appears as a beautiful, interactive webpage — with images, charts, diagrams, maps, and other widgets. Phind 3 doesn’t just present information more beautifully; interacting with these widgets dynamically updates the content on the page and enables new functionality that wasn’t possible before.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For example, asking Phind for “options for a one-bedroom apartment in the Lower East Side” (https://www.phind.com/search/find-me-options-for-a-72e019ce-...) gives an interactive apartment-finding experience with customizable filters and a map view. And asking for a “recipe for bone-in chicken thighs” gives you a customizable recipe where changing the seasoning, cooking method, and other parameters will update the recipe content itself in real-time (https://www.phind.com/search/make-me-an-recipe-for-7c30ea6c-...).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Unlike Phind 2 and ChatGPT apps, which use pre-built brittle widgets that can’t truly adapt to your task, Phind 3 is able to create tools and widgets for itself in real-time. We learned this lesson the hard way with our previous launch – the pre-built widgets made the answers much prettier, but they didn’t fundamentally enable new functionality. For example, asking for “Give me round-trip flight options from JFK to SEA on Delta from December 1st-5th in both miles and cash” (https://www.phind.com/search/give-me-round-trip-flight-c0ebe...) is not something that neither Phind 2 nor ChatGPT apps can handle, because its Expedia widget can only display cash fares and not those with points. We realized that Phind needs to be able to create and consume its own tools, with schema it designs, all in real time. Phind 3’s ability to design and create fully custom widgets in real-time means that it can answer these questions while these other tools can’t. Phind 3 now generates raw React code and is able to create any tool to harness its underlying AI answer, search, and code execution capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Building on our history of helping developers solve complex technical questions, Phind 3 is able to answer and visualize developers’ questions like never before. For example, asking to “visualize quicksort” (https://www.phind.com/search/make-me-a-beautiful-visualizati...) gives an interactive step-by-step walkthrough of how the algorithm works.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Phind 3 can help visualize and bring your ideas to life in seconds — you can ask it to “make me a 3D Minecraft simulation” (https://www.phind.com/search/make-me-a-3d-minecraft-fde7033f...) or “make me a 3D roller coaster simulation” (https://www.phind.com/search/make-me-a-3d-roller-472647fc-e4...).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our goal with Phind 3 is to usher in the era of on-demand software. You shouldn’t have to compromise by either settling for text-based AI conversations or using pre-built webpages that weren’t customized for you. With Phind 3, we create a “personal internet” for you with the visualization and interactivity of the internet combined with the customization possible with AI. We think that this current “chat” era of AI is akin to the era of text-only interfaces in computers. The Mac ushering in the GUI in 1984 didn’t just make computer outputs prettier — it ushered in a whole new era of interactivity and possibilities. We aim to do that now with AI.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On a technical level, we are particularly excited about:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;- Phind 3’s ability to create its own tools with its own custom schema and then consume them&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;- Significant improvements in agentic searching and a new deep research mode to surface hard-to-access information&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;- All-new custom Phind models that blend speed and quality. The new Phind Fast model is based on GLM-4.5-Air while the new Phind Large model is based on GLM 4.6. Both models are state-of-the-art when it comes to reliable code generation, producing over 70% fewer errors than GPT-5.1-Codex (high) on our internal mini-app generation benchmark. Furthermore, we trained custom Eagle3 heads for both Phind Fast and Phind Large for fast inference. Phind Fast runs at up to 300 tokens per second, and Phind Large runs at up to 200 tokens per second, making them the fastest Phind models ever.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While we have done Show HNs before for previous Phind versions, we’ve never actually done a proper Launch HN for Phind. As always, we can’t wait to hear your feedback! We are also hiring, so please don’t hesitate to reach out.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;– Michael&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46137548</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 17:47:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Micron Announces Exit from Crucial Consumer Business</title><link>https://investors.micron.com/news-releases/news-release-details/micron-announces-exit-crucial-consumer-business</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="c9a9907d4cbbb1ea"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BOISE, Idaho, Dec. 03, 2025 (GLOBE NEWSWIRE) -- Micron Technology, Inc. (Nasdaq: MU), a leader in innovative memory and storage solutions, today announced its decision to exit the Crucial consumer business, including the sale of Crucial consumer-branded products at key retailers, e-tailers and distributors worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Micron will continue Crucial consumer product shipments through the consumer channel until the end of fiscal Q2 (February 2026). The company will work closely with partners and customers through this transition and will provide continued warranty service and support for Crucial products. Micron will continue to support the sale of Micron-branded enterprise products to commercial channel customers globally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The AI-driven growth in the data center has led to a surge in demand for memory and storage. Micron has made the difficult decision to exit the Crucial consumer business in order to improve supply and support for our larger, strategic customers in faster-growing segments,” said Sumit Sadana, EVP and Chief Business Officer at Micron Technology. “Thanks to a passionate community of consumers, the Crucial brand has become synonymous with technical leadership, quality and reliability of leading-edge memory and storage products. We would like to thank our millions of customers, hundreds of partners and all of the Micron team members who have supported the Crucial journey for the last 29 years.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This decision reflects Micron’s commitment to its ongoing portfolio transformation and the resulting alignment of its business to secular, profitable growth vectors in memory and storage. By concentrating on core enterprise and commercial segments, Micron aims to improve long-term business performance and create value for strategic customers as well as stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Micron intends to reduce impact on team members due to this business decision through redeployment opportunities into existing open positions within the company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Micron Technology, Inc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Micron Technology, Inc. is an industry leader in innovative memory and storage solutions, transforming how the world uses information to enrich life for all. With a relentless focus on our customers, technology leadership, and manufacturing and operational excellence, Micron delivers a rich portfolio of high-performance DRAM, NAND, and NOR memory and storage products. Every day, the innovations that our people create fuel the data economy, enabling advances in artificial intelligence (AI) and compute-intensive applications that unleash opportunities — from the data center to the intelligent edge and across the client and mobile user experience. To learn more about Micron Technology, Inc. (Nasdaq: MU), visit micron.com.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Forward-Looking Statements&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This press release contains forward-looking statements, including statements regarding product supply and support, areas of growth and profitability, and workforce redeployment. These forward-looking statements are subject to a number of risks and uncertainties that could cause actual results to differ materially. Please refer to the documents Micron files with the Securities and Exchange Commission, specifically its most recent Form 10-K and Form 10-Q. These documents contain and identify important factors that could cause actual results to differ materially from those contained in these forward-looking statements. These certain factors can be found at https://investors.micron.com/risk-factor. Although Micron believes that the expectations reflected in the forward-looking statements are reasonable, Micron cannot guarantee future results, levels of activity, or achievements. Micron is under no duty to update any of the forward-looking statements after the date of this press release to conform these statements to actual results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;© 2025 Micron Technology, Inc. All rights reserved. Information, products, and/or specifications are subject to change without notice. Micron, the Micron logo, and all other Micron trademarks are the property of Micron Technology, Inc. All other trademarks are the property of their respective owners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Micron Media Relations Contact&lt;lb/&gt;Mark Plungy&lt;lb/&gt;+1 (408) 203-2910&lt;lb/&gt;corpcomms@micron.com &lt;lb/&gt;Micron Investor Relations Contact&lt;lb/&gt;Satya Kumar&lt;lb/&gt;+1 (408) 450-6199&lt;lb/&gt;satyakumar@micron.com &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46137783</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:04:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ghostty is now non-profit</title><link>https://mitchellh.com/writing/ghostty-non-profit</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="af5a505b2f305666"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Mitchell Hashimoto&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Ghostty Is Now Non-Profit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ghostty is now fiscally sponsored by Hack Club, a registered 501(c)(3) non-profit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fiscal sponsorship is a legal and financial arrangement in which a recognized non-profit extends its tax-exempt status to a project that aligns with its mission. This allows Ghostty to operate as a charitable initiative while Hack Club manages compliance, donations, accounting, and governance oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being non-profit clearly demonstrates our commitment to keeping Ghostty free and open source for everyone. It paves the way for a model for sustainable development beyond my personal involvement. And it also provides important legal protections and assurances to the people and communities that adopt and use Ghostty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why a Non-Profit?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of the project in 2023 and the private beta days of Ghostty, I've repeatedly expressed my intention that Ghostty legally become a non-profit. This intention stems from several core beliefs I have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, I want to lay bricks for a sustainable future for Ghostty that doesn't depend on my personal involvement technically or financially. Financially, I am still the largest donor to the project, and I intend to remain so, but a non-profit structure allows others to contribute financially without fear of misappropriation or misuse of funds (as protected by legal requirements and oversight from the fiscal sponsor).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, I want to squelch any possible concerns about a "rug pull". A non-profit structure provides enforceable assurances: the mission cannot be quietly changed, funds cannot be diverted to private benefit, and the project cannot be sold off or repurposed for commercial gain. The structure legally binds Ghostty to the public-benefit purpose it was created to serve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, despite being decades-old technology, terminals and terminal-related technologies remain foundational to modern computing and software infrastructure. They're often out of the limelight, but they're ever present on developer machines, embedded in IDEs, visible as read-only consoles for continuous integration and cloud services, and still one of the primary ways remote access is done on servers around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I believe infrastructure of this kind should be stewarded by a mission-driven, non-commercial entity that prioritizes public benefit over private profit. That structure increases trust, encourages adoption, and creates the conditions for Ghostty to grow into a widely used and impactful piece of open-source infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What This Means For Ghostty&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From a technical perspective, nothing changes for Ghostty. Our technical goals for the project remain the same, the license (MIT) remains the same, and we continue our work towards better Ghostty GUI releases and libghostty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Financially, Ghostty can now accept tax-deductible donations in the United States. This opens up new avenues for funding the project and sustaining development over the long term. Most immediately, I'm excited to begin compensating contributors, but I also intend to support upstream dependencies, fund community events, and pay for boring operational costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All our financial transactions will be transparent down to individual transactions for both inflows and outflows. You can view our public ledger at Ghostty's page on Hack Club Bank. At the time of writing, this is empty, but you'll soon see some initial funding from me and the beginning of paying for some of our operational costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All applicable names, marks, and intellectual property associated with Ghostty have been transferred to Hack Club and are now owned under the non-profit umbrella. Copyright continues to be held by individual contributors under the continued and existing license structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From a leadership perspective, I remain the project lead and final authority on all decisions, but as stated earlier, the creation of a non-profit structure lays the groundwork for an eventual future beyond this model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Important note: no funds will be sent to me (Mitchell Hashimoto) or used in any way that personally benefits me. Since I'm both the largest donor and lead of this project, this is a legally guaranteed protection. But also for altruistic reasons, all funds will be directed towards the needs of the project and its community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Supporting Hack Club&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As our fiscal sponsor, Hack Club provides essential services to Ghostty, including accounting, legal compliance, and governance oversight. To support this, 7% of all donations to Ghostty go to Hack Club to cover these costs in addition to supporting their broader mission of empowering young people around the world interested in technology and coding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the words of Zach Latta, Hack Club's founder and executive director this is a "good-for-good" trade. Instead of donor fees going to a for-profit management company or covering pure overhead of a single project, the fees go to another non-profit doing important work in the tech community and the overhead is amortized across many projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to the 7% fees, my family is personally donating $150,000 directly to the Hack Club project1 (not to Ghostty within it). Hack Club does amazing work and I would've supported them regardless of their fiscal sponsorship of Ghostty, but I wanted to pair these two things together to amplify the impact of both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Donate&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please consider donating to support Ghostty's continued development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I recognize that Ghostty is already in an abnormally fortunate position to have myself as a backer, but I do envision a future where Ghostty is more equally supported by a broader community. And with our new structure, you can be assured about the usage of your funds towards public-benefit goals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post isn't meant to directly be a fundraising pitch so it is purposely lacking critical details about our funding goals, budget, project goals, project metrics, etc. I'll work on those in the future. In the mean time, if you're interested in talking more about supporting Ghostty, please email me at m@mitchellh.com.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Support Ghostty&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your contribution helps sustain development and keeps Ghostty free and open source for everyone. Donations are tax-deductible in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use the EIN above and specify “Ghostty” as the recipient&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contact Paul at Hack Club&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reach out to Paul at Hack Club&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;7% of donations go to Hack Club to cover administrative costs and support their mission.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Thank You&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm thankful for Hack Club and their team for working with us to make this happen. I'm also thankful for the Ghostty community who has supported this project and has trusted me and continues to trust me to steward it responsibly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information about Ghostty's non-profit structure, see the dedicated page on Ghostty's website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We haven't finalized the transfer of the funds yet, but it is initiated and will be completed in the coming weeks. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46138238</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:40:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lie groups are crucial to some of the most fundamental theories in physics</title><link>https://www.quantamagazine.org/what-are-lie-groups-20251203/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e65190820f9d0f14"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;What Are Lie Groups?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In mathematics, ubiquitous objects called groups display nearly magical powers. Though they’re defined by just a few rules, groups help illuminate an astonishing range of mysteries. They can tell you which polynomial equations are solvable, for instance, or how atoms are arranged in a crystal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yet, among all the different kinds of groups, one type stands out. Identified in the early 1870s, Lie groups (pronounced “Lee”) are crucial to some of the most fundamental theories in physics, and they’ve made lasting contributions to number theory and chemistry. The key to their success is the way they blend group theory, geometry and linear algebra.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In general, a group is a set of elements paired with an operation (like addition or multiplication) that combines two of those elements to produce a third. Often, you can think of a group as the symmetries of a shape — the transformations that leave the shape unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider the symmetries of the equilateral triangle. They form a group of six elements, as shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mark Belan/Quanta Magazine&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Since a full rotation brings every point on the triangle back to where it started, mathematicians stop counting rotations past 360 degrees.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These symmetries are discrete: They form a set of distinct transformations that have to be applied in separate, unconnected steps. But you can also study continuous symmetries. It doesn’t matter, for instance, if you spin a Frisbee 1.5 degrees, or 15 degrees, or 150 degrees — you can rotate it by any real number, and it will appear the same. Unlike the triangle, it has infinitely many symmetries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These rotations form a group called SO(2). “If you have just a reflection, OK, you have it, and that’s good,” said Anton Alekseev, a mathematician at the University of Geneva. “But that’s just one operation.” This group, on the other hand, “is many, many operations in one package” — uncountably many.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each rotation of the Frisbee can be represented as a point in the coordinate plane. If you plot all possible rotations of the Frisbee in this way, you’ll end up with infinitely many points that together form a circle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This extra property is what makes SO(2) a Lie group — it can be visualized as a smooth, continuous shape called a manifold. Other Lie groups might look like the surface of a doughnut, or a high-dimensional sphere, or something even stranger: The group of all rotations of a ball in space, known to mathematicians as SO(3), is a six-dimensional tangle of spheres and circles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whatever the specifics, the smooth geometry of Lie groups is the secret ingredient that elevates their status among groups.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Off on a Tangent&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It took time for Marius Sophus Lie to make his way to mathematics. Growing up in Norway in the 1850s, he hoped to pursue a military career once he finished secondary school. Instead, forced to abandon his dream due to poor eyesight, he ended up in university, unsure of what to study. He took courses in astronomy and mechanics, and flirted briefly with physics, botany and zoology before finally being drawn to math — geometry in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the late 1860s, he continued his studies, first in Germany and then in France. He was in Paris in 1870 when the Franco-Prussian War broke out. He soon tried to leave the country, but his notes on geometry, written in German, were mistaken for encoded messages, and he was arrested, accused of being a spy. He was released from prison a month later and quickly returned to math.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In particular, he began working with groups. Forty years earlier, the mathematician Évariste Galois had used one class of groups to understand the solutions to polynomial equations. Lie now wanted to do the same thing for so-called differential equations, which are used to model how a physical system changes over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His vision for differential equations didn’t work out as he’d hoped. But he soon realized that the groups he was studying were interesting in their own right. And so the Lie group was born.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The manifold nature of Lie groups has been an enormous boon to mathematicians. When they sit down to understand a Lie group, they can use all the tools of geometry and calculus — something that’s not necessarily true for other kinds of groups. That’s because every manifold has a nice property: If you zoom in on a small enough region, its curves disappear, just as the spherical Earth appears flat to those of us walking on its surface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To see why this is useful for studying groups, let’s go back to SO(2). Remember that SO(2) consists of all the rotations of a Frisbee, and that those rotations can be represented as points on a circle. For now, let’s focus on a sliver of the circle corresponding to very small rotations — say, rotations of less than 1 degree.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here, the curve of SO(2) is barely perceptible. When a Frisbee rotates 1 degree or less, any given point on its rim follows a nearly linear path. That means mathematicians can approximate these rotations with a straight line that touches the circle at just one point — a tangent line. This tangent line is called the Lie algebra.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This feature is immensely useful. Math is a lot easier on a straight line than on a curve. And the Lie algebra contains elements of its own (often visualized as arrows called vectors) that mathematicians can use to simplify their calculations about the original group. “One of the easiest kinds of mathematics in the world is linear algebra, and the theory of Lie groups is designed in such a way that it just makes constant use of linear algebra,” said David Vogan of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Say you want to compare two different groups. Their respective Lie algebras simplify their key properties, Vogan said, making this task much more straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The interaction between these two structures,” Alessandra Iozzi, a mathematician at the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology Zurich, said of Lie groups and their algebras, “is something that has an absolutely enormous array of consequences.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Language of Nature&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The natural world is full of the kinds of continuous symmetries that Lie groups capture, making them indispensable in physics. Take gravity. The sun’s gravitational pull on the Earth depends only on the distance between them — it doesn’t matter which side of the sun the Earth is on, for instance. In the language of Lie groups, then, gravity is “symmetric under SO(3).” It remains unchanged when the system it’s acting on rotates in three-dimensional space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact, all the fundamental forces in physics — gravity, electromagnetism, and the forces that hold together atomic nuclei — are defined by Lie group symmetries. Using that definition, scientists can explain basic puzzles about matter, like why protons are always paired with neutrons, and why the energy of an atom comes in discrete quantities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1918, Emmy Noether stunned mathematicians and physicists by proving that Lie groups also underlie some of the most basic laws of conservation in physics. She showed that for any symmetry in a physical system that can be described by a Lie group, there is a corresponding conservation law. For instance, the fact that the laws of physics are the same today as they were yesterday and will be tomorrow — a symmetry known as time translation symmetry, represented by the Lie group consisting of the real numbers — implies that the universe’s energy must be conserved, and vice versa. “I think, even now, it’s a very surprising result,” Alekseev said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, Lie groups remain a vital tool for both mathematicians and physicists. “Definitions live in mathematics because they’re powerful. Because there are a lot of interesting examples and they give you a good way to think about something,” Vogan said. “Symmetry is everywhere, and that’s what this stuff is for.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46138632</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 19:12:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Everyone in Seattle hates AI</title><link>https://jonready.com/blog/posts/everyone-in-seattle-hates-ai.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="73395114bff6ccdd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I grabbed lunch with a former Microsoft coworker I've always admired—one of those engineers who can take any idea, even a mediocre one, and immediately find the gold in it. I wanted her take on Wanderfugl 🐦, the AI-powered map I've been building full-time. I expected encouragement. At worst, overly generous feedback because she knows what I've sacrificed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, she reacted to it with a level of negativity I'd never seen her direct at me before.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I finally got her to explain what was wrong, none of it had anything to do with what I built. She talked about Copilot 365. And Microsoft AI. And every miserable AI tool she's forced to use at work. My product barely featured. Her reaction wasn't about me at all. It was about her entire environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The AI Layoffs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Her PM had been laid off months earlier. The team asked why. Their director told them it was because the PM org "wasn't effective enough at using Copilot 365."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I nervously laughed. This director got up in a group meeting and said that someone lost their job over this?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After a pause I tried to share how much better I've been feeling—how AI tools helped me learn faster, how much they accelerated my work on Wanderfugl. I didn't fully grok how tone deaf I was being though. She's drowning in resentment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I left the lunch deflated and weirdly guilty, like building an AI product made me part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But then I realized this was bigger than one conversation. Every time I shared Wanderfugl with a Seattle engineer, I got the same reflexive, critical, negative response. This wasn't true in Bali, Tokyo, Paris, or San Francisco—people were curious, engaged, wanted to understand what I was building. But in Seattle? Instant hostility the moment they heard "AI."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The people at big tech in Seattle are not ok&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I joined Microsoft, there was still a sense of possibility. Satya was pushing "growth mindset" everywhere. Leaders talked about empowerment and breaking down silos. And even though there was always a gap between the slogans and reality, there was room to try things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I leaned into it. I pushed into areas nobody wanted to touch, like Windows update compression, because it lived awkwardly across three teams. Somehow, a 40% improvement made it out alive. Leadership backed it. The people trying to kill it shrank back into their fiefdoms. It felt like the culture wanted change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That world is gone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the layoff directive hit, every org braced for impact. Anything not strictly inside the org's charter was axed. I went from shipping a major improvement in Windows 11 to having zero projects overnight. I quit shortly after. In hindsight, getting laid off with severance might've been better than watching the culture collapse in slow motion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then came the AI panic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you could classify your project as "AI," you were safe and prestigious. If you couldn't, you were nobody. Overnight, most engineers got rebranded as "not AI talent." And then came the final insult: everyone was forced to use Microsoft's AI tools whether they worked or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Copilot for Word. Copilot for PowerPoint. Copilot for email. Copilot for code. Worse than the tools they replaced. Worse than competitors' tools. Sometimes worse than doing the work manually.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But you weren't allowed to fix them—that was the AI org's turf. You were supposed to use them, fail to see productivity gains, and keep quiet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, AI teams became a protected class. Everyone else saw comp stagnate, stock refreshers evaporate, and performance reviews tank. And if your team failed to meet expectations? Clearly you weren't "embracing AI."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bring up AI in a Seattle coffee shop now and people react like you're advocating asbestos.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon folks are slightly more insulated, but not by much. The old Seattle deal—Amazon treats you poorly but pays you more—only masks the rot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Self-Limiting Beliefs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This belief system—that AI is useless and that you're not good enough to work on it anyway—hurts three groups:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 1. The companies.&lt;lb/&gt; They've taught their best engineers that innovation isn't their job. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 2. The engineers.&lt;lb/&gt; They're stuck in resentment and self-doubt while their careers stall. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 3. Anyone trying to build anything new in Seattle.&lt;lb/&gt; Say "AI" and people treat you like a threat or an idiot. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; And the loop feeds itself:&lt;lb/&gt; Engineers don't try because they think they can't.&lt;lb/&gt; Companies don't empower them because they assume they shouldn't.&lt;lb/&gt; Bad products reinforce the belief that AI is doomed.&lt;lb/&gt; The spiral locks in. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My former coworker—the composite of three people for anonymity—now believes she's both unqualified for AI work and that AI isn't worth doing anyway. She's wrong on both counts, but the culture made sure she'd land there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seattle has talent as good as anywhere. But in San Francisco, people still believe they can change the world—so sometimes they actually do.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46138952</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 19:37:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: I built a dashboard to compare mortgage rates across 120 credit unions</title><link>https://finfam.app/blog/credit-union-mortgages</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3c94a31214402b4c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Buying a home or refinancing a mortgage is tough enough without confusing ads from banks and big lenders. Credit unions can offer competitive rates compared to big banks because theyâre member-owned, non-profit institutions. They focus on serving their members, not maximizing profits for shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But without big budgets and marketing departments, credit union rates arenât always easy to find or compare. Thatâs why we built a daily-updated comparison of mortgage rates from over 120 credit unions across the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Credit Union Mortgage Rates&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last updated: December 3, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;30-Year Fixed&lt;/head&gt;Updating...&lt;p&gt;Loading rate comparison table...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: These rates are informational and not a commitment to lend. FinFam has no institutional affiliation and does not receive any referral fees.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why build this dashboard?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we bought our home, the big bank Iâd been using for years tried to sell me on a mortgage with 7% APR. Turns out a local credit union was offering 5.5% for the exact same mortgage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What surprised me most wasnât that there were cheaper options, but that two mortgages can be exactly the same product, just with different packaging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the USA, the government buys almost all mortgages, requiring them to be standardized. So why the price difference? As explored in this Bloomberg Odd Lots episode about credit card rates, higher rates are mostly to pay for advertising and marketing. Big banks have marketing departments that non-profit credit unions donât have.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That âexclusiveâ inbox offer from Chase or Wells Fargo isnât generosity. Itâs a bet that you wonât shop around. My goal with this tool is simple: help people realize they have options and potentially save thousands of dollars a year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How the dashboard works&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Itâs a little involved! ð&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Rates are collected throughout the day from the websites of approximately 120 credit unions.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;National benchmarks come from the St. Louis Federal Reserve Bank, aka FRED: 30-Year Fixed benchmark (15Y). These update weekly.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Credit union eligibility data is manually curated from individual institution websites.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some rates (around a dozen) are hidden by default because theyâre statistical outliers: likely errors or ultra-specialized products. Toggle âShow outliersâ in the filters if you want to see them anyway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Found an error? Email blog@finfam.app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Next Steps: Make Decisions, Get Quotes&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our dashboard can only take you so far. Your actual rate depends on: credit score, down payment (20%+ is ideal), property type (primary residence gets best rates), and whether you pay points for a lower rate (always compare APR).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next step: Get quotes from multiple lenders by using the rate table above to contact institutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protip: Before submitting to any credit checks, protect your privacy with optoutprescreen.com, another free and regulated service I wish Iâd known about sooner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still not sure about buying or refinancing? Check out these interactive guides:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FinFam is built around collaborative financial planning, including community-authored, spreadsheet-powered guides, like those above. Read more in our docs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Questions or Feedback?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have questions about these rates or suggestions for improving this tool? Reach out to us at blog@finfam.app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Donât see your favorite CU here? As long as it has a website with a public rates page and clear eligibility requirements, weâd be happy to add it!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Disclaimers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;These rates are informational only and donât represent rate locks. Your actual rate will vary. Contact lenders with the links in the rate table to get your personalized quotes. FinFam has no institutional affiliation and receives no referral fees, nor provides any guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shoutout /r/dataisbeautiful for the encouragement. And big thanks to Asheesh Laroia for his guidance on the matter of mortgages. See his spreadsheet-friendly take on the data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46139761</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 20:35:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Checked-size array parameters in C</title><link>https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/1046840/3eb9029084cc9e1e/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="aa33f83beb8d96c8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Checked-size array parameters in C&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;[LWN subscriber-only content]&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;head&gt;Welcome to LWN.net&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The following subscription-only content has been made available to you by an LWN subscriber. Thousands of subscribers depend on LWN for the best news from the Linux and free software communities. If you enjoy this article, please consider subscribing to LWN. Thank you for visiting LWN.net!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are many possible programmer mistakes that are not caught by the minimal checks specified by the C language; among those is passing an array of the wrong size to a function. A recent attempt to add some safety around array parameters within the crypto layer involved the use of some clever tricks, but it turns out that clever tricks are unnecessary in this case. There is an obscure C feature that can cause this checking to happen, and it is already in use in a few places within the kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The discussion started when Ard Biesheuvel sought to improve the safety of the poetically named function xchacha20poly1305_encrypt():&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;void xchacha20poly1305_encrypt(u8 *dst, const u8 *src, const size_t src_len, const u8 *ad, const size_t ad_len, const u8 nonce[XCHACHA20POLY1305_NONCE_SIZE], const u8 key[CHACHA20POLY1305_KEY_SIZE]);&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A potential problem with this function is that it takes as parameters several pointers to arrays of type u8. As Biesheuvel pointed out, the size of the nonce and key arrays is not checked by the compiler, even though it is clearly specified in the function prototype. That makes it easy to, for example, give the parameters in the wrong order. The resulting vulnerabilities are generally not the outcome developers have in mind when they write cryptographic code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Biesheuvel suggested that it was possible to write the prototype this way instead (differences shown in bold):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;void xchacha20poly1305_encrypt(u8 *dst, const u8 *src, const size_t src_len, const u8 *ad, const size_t ad_len, const u8 (*nonce)[XCHACHA20POLY1305_NONCE_SIZE], const u8 (*key)[CHACHA20POLY1305_KEY_SIZE]);&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The types of the last two arguments have changed; there is a new level of pointer indirection, with the argument being a pointer to an array of a given size. Callers must change their calls by adding an additional &amp;amp; operator to obtain the desired pointer type, but the address that is passed is the same. In this case, though, the compiler will check the sizes of the array passed, and will now catch a reordering of the arguments to the function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Donenfeld was interested by the idea, but he knew of an arguably more straightforward way to address this problem. It seems that, buried deep within the C standard, is a strange usage of the static keyword, making it possible to write the prototype as:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;void xchacha20poly1305_encrypt(u8 *dst, const u8 *src, const size_t src_len, const u8 *ad, const size_t ad_len, const u8 nonce[static XCHACHA20POLY1305_NONCE_SIZE], const u8 key[static CHACHA20POLY1305_KEY_SIZE]);&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This, too, will cause the compiler to check the sizes of the arrays, and it does not require changes on the caller side. Unlike the pointer trick, which requires an exact match on the array size, use of static will only generate a warning if the passed-in array is too small. So it will not catch all mistakes, though it is sufficient to prevent memory-safety and swapped-argument problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Eric Biggers pointed out that GCC can often generate "array too small" warnings even without static, but that the kernel currently disables those warnings; that would suppress them when static is used as well. (The warning was disabled in 6.8 due to false positives.) But he thought that adding static was worthwhile to get the warnings in Clang — if Linus Torvalds would be willing to accept use of "&lt;quote&gt;this relatively obscure feature of C&lt;/quote&gt;". &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Torvalds, as it turns out, has no objection to this usage; he likes the feature, if not the way it was designed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;The main issue with the whole 'static' thing is just that the syntax is such a horrible hack, where people obviously picked an existing keyword that made absolutely no sense, but was also guaranteed to have no backwards compatibility issues.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He pointed out that there are a number of places in the kernel that are already using it; for a simple example, see getconsxy() in the virtual-terminal driver. He suggested perhaps hiding it with a macro like min_array_size() just to make the usage more obvious, but didn't seem convinced that it was necessary. Donenfeld followed up with a patch to that effect a few days later, but then pivoted to an at_least marker instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; A lot of work has gone into the kernel to make its use of C as safe as possible, but that does not mean that the low-hanging fruit has all been picked. The language has features, such as static when used to define formal array parameters, that can improve safety, but which are not generally known and not often used. In this particular case, though, it would not be surprising to see this "&lt;quote&gt;horrible hack&lt;/quote&gt;" come into wider use in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Index entries for this article&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kernel&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;C language safety&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kernel&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Releases/6.19&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Posted Dec 2, 2025 0:54 UTC (Tue) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] (6 responses) It's unfortunate that the kernel had to turn -Wstringop-overflow off; I hope that can be resolved eventually, and code using [n] can be safe again. [static n] is not as good as [n], among other reasons, because it doesn't guarantee that the function will not read beyond the first 'n' elements. GCC diagnoses if a function reads beyond that, but that's a GNU extension. [static n] as designed by the C Committee is bad, and should be avoided. Posted Dec 2, 2025 9:10 UTC (Tue) by danielthompson (subscriber, #97243) [Link] (4 responses) AFAICT the C standard defines static array indices as an single additional constraint on callers (e.g. there's nothing that [n] does that [static n] doesn't also do). Assuming that constraint is met then I don't see why [static n] is would be not as good as [n] when the function implementation does not honour its prototype. Posted Dec 2, 2025 9:47 UTC (Tue) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] (3 responses) Posted Dec 2, 2025 10:09 UTC (Tue) by excors (subscriber, #95769) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Dec 2, 2025 10:25 UTC (Tue) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] But yeah, I agree the diagnostics about array parameters need some improvements. On the other hand, -O2 is what most projects use. I personally build my projects in a loop with all different optimization levels, to maximize diagnostics. Posted Dec 2, 2025 15:28 UTC (Tue) by danielthompson (subscriber, #97243) [Link] From the point of view of the standard [static n] is essentially a hint to the optimizer that allows it to optimize the function more aggressively by imposing restrictions on the caller. Nothing to do with diagnostics, although without diagnostics then there is a risk that failing to meet the restrictions would go undiscovered. Given how similar they are, I'd assume the only reason [static n] would ever get "better" diagnostics might be because the false positive rate is lower: if the warnings can be switched independently then people who adopt the weird syntax for diagnostic reasons could simply switch back to [n] if there are false positive diagnostics. Posted Dec 2, 2025 12:32 UTC (Tue) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] However, it's worse than that. There's nothing that [static n] will enforce that wouldn't be enforced by [n]. Both GCC and Clang entirely ignore [static n] --as they should, it's pure crap-- regarding diagnostics of array bounds. I can only assume they were assuming [static n] would do something it doesn't do but didn't really test, because it's trivial to show that [static n] doesn't add any diagnostics. See &amp;lt;https://lwn.net/ml/all/ei7wbiu6m2lvso3gbc4ohvz3h575anjxqm...&amp;gt; Posted Dec 2, 2025 8:22 UTC (Tue) by taladar (subscriber, #68407) [Link] Posted Dec 2, 2025 13:24 UTC (Tue) by tdz (subscriber, #58733) [Link] (6 responses) "If the keyword static also appears within the [ and ] of the array type derivation, then for each call to This is essentially just an optimization hint. There is no requirement to do any bounds checking. When I tried a few years ago, clang did while gcc didn't warn about violations. Posted Dec 2, 2025 13:32 UTC (Tue) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] (2 responses) Posted Dec 2, 2025 16:27 UTC (Tue) by jrtc27 (subscriber, #107748) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Dec 2, 2025 21:32 UTC (Tue) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] That's what we call quality-of-implementation. It's not a bug, it's a feature. Quality compilers often diagnose things that the standard doesn't restrict. That's expected. You wouldn't want to use a compiler that diagnoses exactly what the standard requires and no more. &amp;gt; the C standard is very clear that array parameters are identical to pointer parameters, That's a bug in the standard. I hope it will be fixed in ISO C2y. Posted Dec 2, 2025 13:38 UTC (Tue) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] (2 responses) - It uses array notation for what is really a pointer. Posted Dec 2, 2025 21:10 UTC (Tue) by andy_shev (subscriber, #75870) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Dec 2, 2025 21:34 UTC (Tue) by alx.manpages (subscriber, #145117) [Link] Posted Dec 2, 2025 16:42 UTC (Tue) by jrtc27 (subscriber, #107748) [Link] (1 responses) Array parameter types are a particularly cursed corner of C. By the standard, they are confusing syntax for a pointer. But that means that you can legally assign to the array itself: If you want to stop that, like any other variable you want to prevent assignment to, you need to mark it const. But Other qualifiers work there too (e.g. restrict, which you do sometimes see in the real world). Posted Dec 2, 2025 19:06 UTC (Tue) by wahern (subscriber, #37304) [Link] Posted Dec 3, 2025 3:22 UTC (Wed) by zx2c4 (subscriber, #82519) [Link] (2 responses) Details are in the commit: https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/torvalds/... Posted Dec 3, 2025 17:04 UTC (Wed) by corbet (editor, #1) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Dec 3, 2025 17:46 UTC (Wed) by zx2c4 (subscriber, #82519) [Link] https://lore.kernel.org/all/20251123054819.2371989-4-Jaso... Posted Dec 4, 2025 2:14 UTC (Thu) by Xeyler (subscriber, #159814) [Link] &lt;head&gt;[static n] should be avoided if possible&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;[static n] should be avoided if possible&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head/&gt; It depends on what you call a guarantee. If you use appropriate compiler flags, you can get such guarantees &lt;head&gt;[static n] should be avoided if possible&lt;/head&gt;&lt;quote&gt; alx@devuan:~/tmp$ cat array-bounds.c void g(int a[43]); void f(int a[42]) { a[100] = 7; g(a); } alx@devuan:~/tmp$ gcc -Warray-parameter=2 -Werror=array-bounds=2 -Werror=stringop-overflow=4 -O2 -S array-bounds.c array-bounds.c: In function ‘f’: array-bounds.c:8:9: error: ‘g’ accessing 172 bytes in a region of size 168 [-Werror=stringop-overflow=] 8 | g(a); | ^~~~ array-bounds.c:8:9: note: referencing argument 1 of type ‘int[43]’ array-bounds.c:1:6: note: in a call to function ‘g’ 1 | void g(int a[43]); | ^ array-bounds.c:6:10: error: array subscript 100 is outside array bounds of ‘int[42]’ [-Werror=array-bounds=] 6 | a[100] = 7; | ~^~~~~ array-bounds.c:4:7: note: at offset 400 into object ‘a’ of size [0, 168] 4 | f(int a[42]) | ~~~~^~~~~ cc1: some warnings being treated as errors &lt;/quote&gt; The C standard claims [n] has no meaning at all, so it's easy for the C standard to also claim that [static n] has strictly stronger guarantees than [n]. However, the C standard doesn't acknowledge that existing quality compilers (i.e., GCC) assign [n] a stronger meaning than the C standard ackowledge. &lt;lb/&gt; About why [static n] would be worse than [n], there are a few reasons (plus the one mentioned above): &lt;head&gt;[static n] should be avoided if possible&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;[static n] should be avoided if possible&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; And GCC is indeed working on improving those diagnostics.&lt;head&gt;[static n] should be avoided if possible&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;[static n] is 100% useless (on top of being bad for safety)&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Waste of developer mental capacity&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Unfortunately compilers don't enforce [static N]&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; the function, the value of the corresponding actual argument shall provide access to the first element&lt;lb/&gt; of an array with at least as many elements as specified by the size expression"&lt;head/&gt; I don't know in the past, but in the present day, Clang is way behind GCC. GCC diagnoses both [n] and [static n] in exactly the same way, and [static n] is unnecessary. &lt;head&gt;GCC enforces both [n] and [static N]&lt;/head&gt;&lt;quote&gt; alx@devuan:~/tmp$ cat array-bounds.c void g(int a[43]); void f(int a[42]); void f(int a[42]) { a[100] = 7; g(a); } void gs(int a[static 43]); void fs(int a[static 42]); void fs(int a[static 42]) { a[101] = 8; gs(a); } int main(void) { int a[2]; f(a); fs(a); } alx@devuan:~/tmp$ gcc -S -O2 -Wall -Wextra array-bounds.c array-bounds.c: In function ‘f’: array-bounds.c:7:9: warning: ‘g’ accessing 172 bytes in a region of size 168 [-Wstringop-overflow=] 7 | g(a); | ^~~~ array-bounds.c:7:9: note: referencing argument 1 of type ‘int[43]’ array-bounds.c:1:6: note: in a call to function ‘g’ 1 | void g(int a[43]); | ^ array-bounds.c: In function ‘fs’: array-bounds.c:16:9: warning: ‘gs’ accessing 172 bytes in a region of size 168 [-Wstringop-overflow=] 16 | gs(a); | ^~~~~ array-bounds.c:16:9: note: referencing argument 1 of type ‘int[43]’ array-bounds.c:10:6: note: in a call to function ‘gs’ 10 | void gs(int a[static 43]); | ^~ array-bounds.c: In function ‘main’: array-bounds.c:24:9: warning: ‘f’ accessing 168 bytes in a region of size 8 [-Wstringop-overflow=] 24 | f(a); | ^~~~ array-bounds.c:24:9: note: referencing argument 1 of type ‘int[42]’ array-bounds.c:4:6: note: in a call to function ‘f’ 4 | void f(int a[42]) | ^ array-bounds.c:25:9: warning: ‘fs’ accessing 168 bytes in a region of size 8 [-Wstringop-overflow=] 25 | fs(a); | ^~~~~ array-bounds.c:25:9: note: referencing argument 1 of type ‘int[42]’ array-bounds.c:13:6: note: in a call to function ‘fs’ 13 | void fs(int a[static 42]) | ^~ array-bounds.c: In function ‘f’: array-bounds.c:6:10: warning: array subscript 100 is outside array bounds of ‘int[42]’ [-Warray-bounds=] 6 | a[100] = 7; | ~^~~~~ array-bounds.c:4:12: note: at offset 400 into object ‘a’ of size [0, 168] 4 | void f(int a[42]) | ~~~~^~~~~ array-bounds.c: In function ‘fs’: array-bounds.c:15:10: warning: array subscript 101 is outside array bounds of ‘int[42]’ [-Warray-bounds=] 15 | a[101] = 8; | ~^~~~~ array-bounds.c:13:13: note: at offset 404 into object ‘a’ of size [0, 168] 13 | void fs(int a[static 42]) | ~~~~^~~~~~~~~~~~ In function ‘f’, inlined from ‘main’ at array-bounds.c:24:2: array-bounds.c:6:16: warning: array subscript 100 is outside array bounds of ‘int[2]’ [-Warray-bounds=] 6 | a[100] = 7; | ~~~~~~~^~~ array-bounds.c: In function ‘main’: array-bounds.c:22:13: note: at offset 400 into object ‘a’ of size 8 22 | int a[2]; | ^ In function ‘fs’, inlined from ‘main’ at array-bounds.c:25:2: array-bounds.c:15:16: warning: array subscript 101 is outside array bounds of ‘int[2]’ [-Warray-bounds=] 15 | a[101] = 8; | ~~~~~~~^~~ array-bounds.c: In function ‘main’: array-bounds.c:22:13: note: at offset 404 into object ‘a’ of size 8 22 | int a[2]; | ^ alx@devuan:~/tmp$ clang -S -O2 -Weverything array-bounds.c array-bounds.c:25:2: warning: array argument is too small; contains 2 elements, callee requires at least 42 [-Warray-bounds] 25 | fs(a); | ^ ~ array-bounds.c:13:13: note: callee declares array parameter as static here 13 | void fs(int a[static 42]) | ^~~~~~~~~~~~ array-bounds.c:6:2: warning: unsafe buffer access [-Wunsafe-buffer-usage] 6 | a[100] = 7; | ^ array-bounds.c:15:2: warning: unsafe buffer access [-Wunsafe-buffer-usage] 15 | a[101] = 8; | ^ 3 warnings generated. &lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head&gt;GCC enforces both [n] and [static N]&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Quality of implementation &lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Re: [static 1] is a non-null pointer&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; - It would cause warnings in the function if it tries to access more than 1 element. (Except that these warnings are still under development, so this won't be triggered easily.)&lt;lb/&gt; - It's still a UB bomb, just like the attribute.&lt;head&gt;Re: [static 1] is a non-null pointer&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Re: [static 1] is a non-null pointer&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Weird corner of C&lt;/head&gt;&lt;code&gt;int get_second(int a[]) {
    a++;
    return *a;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;int const a[]&lt;/code&gt; makes the &lt;del&gt;array elements&lt;/del&gt; pointed-to objects const, not the pointer itself. The cursed solution that C came up with is putting the qualifiers inside the square brackets (where static can also go, as explained in the article), so you can write the following: &lt;code&gt;int get_second(int a[const]) {
    a++; // error: cannot assign to variable 'a' with const-qualified type 'int *const'
    return *a;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;head&gt;Weird corner of C&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;To editor: example using `at_least` needed&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head/&gt; Sorry, at_least was a late addition. Perhaps the best example is this whole series of changes posted by Eric Biggers. &lt;head&gt;To editor: example using `at_least` needed&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;To editor: example using `at_least` needed&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;bugged gcc&lt;/head&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46139782</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 20:37:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>8086 Microcode Browser</title><link>https://nand2mario.github.io/posts/2025/8086_microcode_browser/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f1bc214a171d033"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;8086 Microcode Browser&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since releasing 486Tang, I’ve been working on recreating the 8086 with a design that stays as faithful as possible to the original chip. That exploration naturally led me deep into the original 8086 microcode — extracted and disassembled by Andrew Jenner in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like all microcoded CPUs, the 8086 hides a lot of subtle behavior below the assembly layer. While studying it I kept extensive notes, and those eventually evolved into something more useful: an interactive browser for the entire 8086 microcode ROM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So here it is: the online 8086 microcode browser. Every 21-bit micro-instruction is decoded into readable fields. Hover over any field and you’ll get a tooltip explaining what it does. All jump targets are clickable — the 8086 μcode uses a surprising number of indirect jumps, calls, and short branches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One handy feature is Browse by Instruction. Click the button and you’ll get a list of ~300 documented 8086 instructions. Select any one, and the viewer jumps directly to its μcode entry point. Internally there are only about 60 unique μcode entry routines, and this feature makes navigating them effortless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;A few fun tidbits about 8086 μcode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Register IDs change meaning depending on context. For example,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;10100&lt;/code&gt;refers to SIGMA (the ALU result) when used as a source, but to tmpaL (the low 8 bits of a temporary ALU register) when used as a destination.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;N and R are the same physical register. Meanwhile, SI is called IJ internally — naming inside the chip is extremely inconsistent and reflects its evolutionary design process.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;IP (PC) does not point to the next instruction. It actually points to the next prefetch address. The μcode uses a dedicated micro-operation called CORR to rewind IP back to the true next-instruction boundary when handling branches and interrupts.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost all arithmetic instructions share the same 4 μinstructions (&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;008–00B&lt;/code&gt;). The heavy lifting is done by a single micro-operation named XI, which performs different arithmetic behaviors depending on opcode or ModRM bits. The amount of reuse here is elegant — and very 1978 Intel.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46140244</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 21:16:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Acme, a brief history of one of the protocols which has changed the Internet</title><link>https://blog.brocas.org/2025/12/01/ACME-a-brief-history-of-one-of-the-protocols-which-has-changed-the-Internet-Security/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6d19b1920b220c9d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ACME, a brief history of one of the protocols which has changed the Internet Security&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Preamble&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would like to share with you this article I wrote about the ACME protocol, which I “fell in love with” about ten years ago. It is for me a way to give back to this fantastic Free Software and Open Protocols developers community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This article is about the roots, the conception, the standardization, the relation with its ecosystem and the evolution challenges faced by the ACME protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To write this article, I had the privilege of interviewing several people who have been involved in the creation and the evolution of ACME: Aaron Gable, Sarah Gran, Jacob Hoffman-Andrews and J.C. Jones (more below).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you so much to all of you for your time and support! ð&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Internet and Network Protocols&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Open and Standardized Protocols at the Heart of the Internetâs Success&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During the 1990s, computing underwent a true revolution driven by the rise and global spread of the Internet. The Internet fulfilled the promise embodied in Sun Microsystemsâ slogan “The Network is the Computer”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By interconnecting individual computers, the Internet enabled its users to communicate without limits and without worrying about borders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This unrestricted interconnection emerged at a pivotal moment in modern history: the opposition between the West and the Eastern Bloc led by the USSR hadâalbeit temporarily, as we now knowâfaded away, China was becoming the worldâs factory, and the movement and collaboration between people were much freer and open than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Internet supported a kind of utopia of instant communication and sharing, previously unknown. This utopia was made possible by a set of open and standardized protocols. This was the key to enabling all kinds of different systems to cooperate and communicate seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were, of course, isolationist or monopolistic temptations from certain manufacturers or software editors. But open and standardized protocols ultimately prevailed, enabling unprecedented expansion. Built on top of IP, TCP, UDP, and DNS, among others, the HTTP and HTML duo would propel the Web as the Internetâs preferred communication platform for the next 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Limited Use of Encryption&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The success of this communication utopia was achieved without much concern for ensuring authentication, integrity, and confidentiality of exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2015, only ~40% of websites used encryption. The consequences of this negligence in addressing security risks were confirmed by Edward Snowdenâs revelations in 2013: our data was exposed to anyone who wanted and could intercept and collect it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Let’s Encrypt is coming&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Birth of an Automated and Free Certificate Authority&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When asked about the main obstacles to the widespread adoption of encryption, J.C. Jones, one of the architects of Letâs Encrypt and now one of its site reliability engineers after leading Firefoxâs cryptographic team, responds:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“More and more information was flowing across the Web, and most data being transferred did not have integrity or confidential protections from TLS. The biggest stumbling block to using TLS everywhere was obtaining and managing server-side certificates, and so: Letâs Encrypt” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Obtaining a certificate was the main obstacle, and this was the priority to address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This view was shared by a group of partners who, starting in 2013, pooled resources to establish Letâs Encrypt, an automated and free certificate authority. Sarah Gran, VP of Advancement at Letâs Encrypt, shares:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Early collaborators included people from Mozilla, Electronic Frontier Foundation, Akamai, Cisco, and the University of Michigan” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that’s how Let’s Encrypt was born.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the Web ecosystem, certificate authorities are organizations from which you can obtain a certificate for a domain after proving you control it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so, Let’s Encrypt is since 2015 a certificate authority that delivers for free (as in free beer) TLS Server certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the legal/administrative side, Let’s Encrypt certificate authority operates for the publicâs benefit and is a service provided by the Internet Security Research Group (ISRG), a California public benefit corporation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regarding Let’s Encrypt results ten years after its birth, they are really impressive (over 700M active certificates, over 60% of all the public TLS server certificates) and as Sarah Gran points out, so is the global HTTPS usage:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“When we started issuance, only about 39% of website visits were HTTPS. Today, itâs nearly 95% in the United States, and over 83% globally. We still have work to do, but we are proud of the progress weâve made over the last ten years” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s Encrypt delivers certificates in a automated manner using the ACME protocol which implies no manual action from the site owner nor the certificate authority. So, let’s speak now a little about the automation aspect!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Automation: The Core of the Operation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the mid-2020s perspective, the automation at the heart of Letâs Encrypt might seem obvious, but in the first half of the 2010s, it was far from the norm. The ecosystem of public certificate authorities issuing server certificates was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At first glance, automation appears to be there to help website managers reliably deploy the TLS protocol on their sites, but it was first and foremost an absolute prerequisite for the very viability of the Let’s Encrypt project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Aaron Gable, tech lead of Boulderâthe software at the core of Letâs Encryptâ, confirms:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Automation was always going to be critical to Letâs Encryptâs success. From the very beginning, we knew that there was no way we could scale manual validation on a non-profitâs budget” – Aaron Gable&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, it is worth noting that Letâs Encrypt has operated on an Internet scale from the start with a small team of about fifteen engineers, or even fewer at launch. For this team, automation was the only viable way to fulfill the immense mission they had set for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ACME&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Open and automated Protocol That Powers Letâs Encrypt&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we talk about automation in relation to Letâs Encrypt, we are talking about ACME (Automated Certificate Management Environment).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This protocol allows client software to prove to an ACME-compatible certificate authority that it controls the domain for which it is requesting a certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sarah Gran clarifies an important point:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“An important aspect of how Letâs Encrypt works is that we verify control over a domain, not ownership” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Control vs. ownership of a domainâa nuance everyone should keep in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This proof of control involves the client responding to a challenge issued by the ACME-compatible certificate authority. The challenge can be an HTTP, DNS, or TLS challenge, depending on the clientâs choice and certificate authority support. Completing the challenge requires the ACME client to place a value provided by the ACME serverâin a standardized HTTP path, a DNS zone, or a TLS response, respectively. All of these operations involve cryptography, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key point with ACME is that this entire dialogue between the client and the ACME server is executed without any human intervention, enabling the automatic issuance of certificates. Their deployment and integration into the web service can also generally be automated using scripts triggered after issuance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the Let’s Encrypt website, you can discover more information about how ACME works and get more detailled information about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Birth of ACME&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One might wonder whether ACME was part of Letâs Encryptâs design from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;J.C. Jones confirms:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“By late 2014, the idea of an HTTP REST API with “/challenge” and “/certificate” existed, but we hadnât defined much beyond that. We had a series of in-person meetings, in the Mozilla San Francisco office on Embarcadero and the EFF office in the Tenderloin through the spring of 2015 where we worked out the details” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ACME was indeed at the core of Letâs Encrypt from the start and underwent a refinement process to cover all use cases as thoroughly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To learn more about the roots of ACME and Let’s Encrypt, there is a very informative document to read: the Let’s Encrypt paper for ACM CCS 2019 in London. It mentions the previous work of two teams:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“A group led by Alex Halderman at the University of Michigan and Peter Eckersley at EFF was developing a protocol for automatically issuing and renewing certificates. Simultaneously, a team at Mozilla led by Josh Aas and Eric Rescorla was working on creating a free and automated certificate authority”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When these two teams discovered each other’s work, they joined forces. ACME and its implementation in Let’s Encrypt were the result of this joint effort supported by the initial partners mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Securing the Web or the Internet?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of use cases, one might wonder whether the Web was Letâs Encryptâs primary target, or if securing the Internet with its multiple protocols was also part of the objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sarah Gran provides an unambiguous first-level answer:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“From Day One, we have sought to get the web to 100% encryption” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But when asked about the various types of challenges in the protocol, J.C. Jones offers a nuance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“DNS, TLS-SNI, and HTTP were all in planning in spring 2015, but many of us were less confident in the procedure around the DNS validation. Which is ironic, as it turned out TLS-SNI had a vulnerability so we had to stop using it and our DNS validation was ultimately fine. In general, the collection of us were simply respectful of the great complexity within the DNS” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a perspective not often publicly expressed by engineers primarily from the Web: their lack of confidence in implementing a DNS challenge stemmed from their humility regarding the complexity of the DNS ecosystem and the level of expertise required to master it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The challenge was ultimately met, and this DNS challengeâthough not its primary purposeâenabled multiple protocols outside HTTP like SMTP to be secured by ACME.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Standardization and Open Source&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Developed in the Open&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ACME was documented openly from the start, and Certbot, the first open-source ACME client co-developed with the EFF, served as the client side reference implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, a standardization process through the IETF resulted in RFC 8555 in March, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the consequences developing an open and standardized protocol was the creation of a multitude of ACME clients covering a very wide range of use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;J.C. Jones confirms that this was the goal:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“This is what we foresaw, or at least hoped for. The initial client development often had conversations like, âoh, if someone wants that, then theyâll write their own client.â It was a key part of why the REST API needed to be an IETF standard, and was part of the argument at the IETF BoF that resulted in the formation of the ACME Working Group in Q3 2015” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Letâs Encrypt has also always provided constant support to developers by responding in its forum or on its GitHub issue tracker, and all this work has truly paid off. An interesting post has been recently written about support on the Let’s Encrypt blog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Standardization for what benefits?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other question that can be asked is whether or not the standardization process within the IETF has led to an improvement in the ACME protocol thanks to the cooperation that guides this process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jacob Hoffman-Andrews, one of the RFC 8555 authors working for EFF &amp;amp; Let’s Encrypt, confirms an initial benefit that the ACME protocol has been able to derive from its standardization process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“One of the big changes was from a validation-first flow to a certificate-request-first flow. In other words, earlier drafts had subscribers requesting validation for domain names and then requesting a certificate once those validations were successful. The final RFC has subscribers request a certificate, and then the CA tells the subscriber what validations are needed. This change originated from within the IETF discussion process, and was intended to make handling of wildcard certificates more natural.” – Jacob Hoffman-Andrews&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aside this first design improvement, Jacob details a second major improvement of the security of the protocol, improvement that also landed during the IETF standardization process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Another big change, also originated from within the IETF, was to make all requests authenticated, including GET requests. Since ACME is authenticated with signed POSTs, this necessitated the POST-as-GET concept thatâs in ACME today” – Jacob Hoffman-Andrews&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can see there how IETF iterations can challenge the security of a protocol and leads its development to innovative solutions to tackle the challenges it faces!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last, Jacob adds another information that illustrates the benefits of developing a protocol into the open: it allows the community to evaluate (and sometimes, fix) its security level due to the availability of all materials and often, of the reference implementation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Another very important evolution was the deprecation of the tls-sni-01 challenge method. This was found to be flawed by Frans Rosen, a security researcher. It was replaced with TLS-ALPN-01, developed at IETF with significant input from Google” – Jacob Hoffman-Andrews&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Letâs Encrypt, ACME, and the Public Certificate Authorities Ecosystem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2015, the arrival of Letâs Encrypt in the public certificate authorities ecosystem raised a number of questions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What level of cooperation or hostility? What impact on the viability of existing certificate authorities?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here again, the fact that Letâs Encrypt was based on an open protocol, immediately subject to an IETF standardization initiative, enabled collaboration and adoption by the most innovative certificate authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I spoke about the External Account Binding (EAB) option of the protocol with J.C. Jones. EAB is a way for an ACME client to authenticate to an ACME server using an identifier and a key value which are verifiable by the server in a repository it maintains. With EAB, an ACME server can filter who can uses its service which is useful for commercial certificate authorities for example; it is an alternative model to Let’s Encrypt one where anybody can ask for a certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the example of EAB, J.C. Jones confirms the collaboration with certificate authorities that happens during the IETF standardization process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“EAB was an early addition at the IETF ACME Working Group. Many in the room were worried that without a means to bind to a payment method, ACME would not get adoption. In fact, some of the counterarguments to forming ACME were blunted by EAB, as such a mechanism wasnât in the theoretically-competing, already-existent standard: SCEP. SCEP, it was argued, already handled ‘free’ certificate issuance, for private certificate authorities. Anything else needed a feasible path for usage payment.” – J.C. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond billing, the addition of EAB enabled also some commercial certificate authorities to integrate their existing domain control validation systems with ACME, allowing some of them to skip the challenge step of the ACME protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The IETF standardization process, based on an open process, created the necessary discussion space for cooperation among entities that did not necessarily share the same objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result, ten years after the introduction of ACME and the completion of its standardization process in 2019, is that ACME has become the primary means by which all public certificate authoritiesâboth free and commercialârely on for their transition to an automated future of issuing short-lived certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Effectively, until early this year, the maximum lifespan of a public TLS server certificate was set to 398 days by the CA/B Forum, the organization that set the rules for public certificate authorities. With the vote of the ballot SC081 at the CA/B Forum in April 2025, it has been decided that the certificate lifespan will decrease gradually starting March 2026 to reach 47 days in March 2029. The automation provided by ACME seems to be one of the main identified levers to help organizations to adapt to this drastic reduction in the lifespan of public TLS server certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Created at Let’s Encrypt, adopted everywhere&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is important to note that although ACME was developed by the team managing Let’s Encrypt, this protocol is now one of the main protocols for automated certificate acquisition adopted by all public certificate authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And outside the public certificate authorities ecosystem, I think it’s fair to say that this protocol is also becoming increasingly popular with technical architects in companies with private certificate authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This has been the case in my company for several years now, where we have deployed an ACME endpoint in front of our internal certificate authority. Among the benefits we have seen, we have been able to rely on the vast ACME clients ecosystem in order to provide an ACME client to each OS or middleware that powers our infrastructure. We can see there how certificate obtention agility powered by ACME helps organizations in their journey to global IT agility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Innovation and the adoption challenge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The ARI episode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We may fear that the development of a protocol supported primarily by a team as small as Let’s Encrypt’s will be fairly limited in terms of evolution and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the history of ACME shows that its evolution continues after its initial standardization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2025, we saw with the ARI (ACME Renewal Information – RFC 9773) extension that the ACME protocol continues to evolve. ARI is a way for a certificate authority to suggest a renewal period to its clients, often earlier than they would have determined themselves. This use case is particularly relevant when the certificate authority needs to mass-revoke certificates that, for example, did not comply with the rules the certificate authority must follow when issuing certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More specifically, J.C. Jones and Aaron Gable point two incidents that had to be handled by the Let’s Encrypt team and that were the start for the ARI initiative:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Explicitly, as remediation of https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1619179 and https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1715672 " J.C. Jones and Aaron Gabble&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Support to encourage adoption&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aaron Gable leads the effort of designing and implementing ARI. But even if a new extension to the protocol has been produced, it can only reach its potential users after ACME clients have implemented it into their code base. As previously said, the team and some community members invest a lot on providing support to the community. In the case of ARI, this support is oriented to the ACME clients developers in order to make these clients ARI aware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Providing an efficient support and effective resources to the client side ACME actors is a huge part of the challenge in order to keep ACME ecosystem healthy and agile.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As illustrates by Sarah Gran, another way to give momentum to a new feature is to lift certain restrictions on access to the certificate authority:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In order to encourage ARI adoption, weâve configured Letâs Encrypt to allow subscribers who renew via ARI to bypass our rate limits.” – Sarah Gran&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Client Side Update Challenge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But despite a good support work and incentive measures, Aaron Gable confirms ARI adoption is just at its start:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“There is still much progress to be made. Part of the appeal of the Automated Certificate Management Environment is that many users can set-and-forget their client and configuration. This means that most clients never receive software updates, and even client projects that have implemented ARI in their latest version still have massive install bases that arenât running that version. Weâve worked closely with many clients developers to implement ARI, and contributed implementations ourselves in several cases, but for widespread adoption the whole ecosystem will need to slowly turn over” – Aaron Gable&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This situation is really shared with a lot of client side softwares that “just work”(c) and it raises some concerns about how to make an ecosystem keeping track with innovation on its client side.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This challenge arises not only in terms of updating the client, but also in terms of updating the configuration. Many ACME clients rely on cron tasks. To have an efficient ARI setup, your task has to run ideally on a daily basis be able to ask the certification authority every day whether the certificate needs to be reissued. This is not the classic cron task setup. So, users have to modify this cron task frequency to reach the ARI goal of certificate reissuance led by certificate authority. Client side ACME setup evolution is a really challenging task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Evolution on server side ACME implementation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CA/B Forum has recently asked public certificate authorities to adopt Multi-Perspective Issuance Corroboration (MPIC) to guard against BGP attacks. We have asked Aaron Gable about the impacts that kind of measure have had on ACME server side implementation in the Let’s Encrypt infrastructure:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Weâve had to make few if any changes to our infrastructure to accommodate recent requirements changes such as MPIC and DNSSEC validation. We innovated MPIC (then called Remote Validation) along with a research team at Princeton, and implemented it in 2020. Our experience already running such a service helped inform the requirements as they were incorporated by the CA/B Forum.” – Aaron Gable&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lesson learnt here is that being at the edge of the innovation let you shape part of the future of your ecosystem and significantly lower the impact on your infrastructure of many regulatory measures that come into effect over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Future&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is really encouraging to see a lot of innovation in the ACME ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what evolutions can we expect to see in the future?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have asked the question to Aaron Gable who gave us two upcoming developments:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“Weâre currently working on standardizing profile selection for ACME, and our deployment of the early draft of this standard has already brought some much-needed flexibility to the WebPKI, enabling us to make changes to our certificate contents with minimal disruption.”&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“Iâm also excited about a potential future change which would introduce a ‘pubkey’ identifier type, along with a set of challenges that allow the client to demonstrate control over the corresponding keypair. This would fix the gap today that presenting a CSR does not actually prove possession of the key in that CSR.” – Araron Gable&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fastly has also recently contributed to ACME in order to improve the &lt;code&gt;dns-01&lt;/code&gt; challenge in a multi-cloud and multi-PKI environment. An IETF draft describing this &lt;code&gt;dns-account-01&lt;/code&gt; challenge is online. This is further proof that the public TLS ecosystem has truly embraced the ACME protocol as its primary automation tool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another recent development based on ACME has also shed new light on the potential of this protocol: since 2022, a draft is under progress at the IETF in order to write an ACME extension. The goal of this extension is to use ACME to obtain a certificate for a device in order to prove its identity. The challenge is based on device attestation and what’s new in this case is the arrival of a third party, the attestation server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is remarkable here is that we are no longer dealing with ACME’s initial use case, namely obtaining TLS server certificates: we can see in this IETF draft the potential of ACME as a challenge-based framework to obtain certificate in very different contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, we can venture to say that ACME’s future looks bright ð&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is heartening to see that, 30 years after the widespread adoption of the Internet, open and standardized protocols continue to revolutionize its use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ACME and its Let’s Encrypt implementation at scale have enabled the widespread adoption of HTTPS, thereby raising the level of security for billions of Internet users and also of private networks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having been able to do it inside a non profit organization, providing the Internet with an open and standardized protocol is a great success for all people believing in FreeSoftware and an Open Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a community, I really think we can thank these organizations, teams, and engineers who continue to uphold the promise of efficiency and Freedom brought about by cooperation around open protocols. They inspire new generations (and older ones I guess ð) demonstrating big things can still be achevied today in the open for the common good at the Internet scale!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would like to extend a special thank you to the members of the Let’s Encrypt team, J.C. Jones, Aaron Gable, Sarah Gran and Jacob Hoffman-Andrews, for the time and effort they dedicated to answering my questions. Without them, this article would not have been possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A big shout out also to Eric Leblond and Philippe Teuwen who carefully proofread some early drafts of the article and Philippe Bonnef and Thibault Meunier for proofreading some of the last drafts. They all gave me so valuable and insightful advices ð&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46141745</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 23:28:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zmx: Session Persistence for Terminal Processes</title><link>https://github.com/neurosnap/zmx</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="24ea9b180b8dab9d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;session persistence for terminal processes&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reason for this tool: You might not need &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Persist terminal shell sessions (pty processes)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ability to attach and detach from a shell session without killing it&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Native terminal scrollback&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multiple clients can connect to the same session&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Re-attaching to a session restores previous terminal state and output&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Works on mac and linux&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;This project does NOT provide windows, tabs, or splits&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Requires zig &lt;code&gt;v0.15&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clone the repo&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Run build cmd&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;zig build -Doptimize=ReleaseSafe --prefix ~/.local
# be sure to add ~/.local/bin to your PATH&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Important&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;ctrl+\&lt;/code&gt; to detach from the session.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Usage: zmx &amp;lt;command&amp;gt; [args]

Commands:
  [a]ttach &amp;lt;name&amp;gt; [command...]  Create or attach to a session
  [d]etach                      Detach all clients from current session  (ctrl+\ for current client)
  [l]ist                        List active sessions
  [k]ill &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;                 Kill a session and all attached clients
  [h]elp                        Show this help message
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;zmx attach dev              # start a shell session
zmx attach dev nvim .       # start nvim in a persistent session
zmx attach build make -j8   # run a build, reattach to check progress
zmx attach mux dvtm         # run a multiplexer inside zmx&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you attach to a zmx session, we don't provide any indication that you are inside &lt;code&gt;zmx&lt;/code&gt;. We do provide an environment variable &lt;code&gt;ZMX_SESSION&lt;/code&gt; which contains the session name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We recommend checking for that env var inside your prompt and displaying some indication there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;functions -c fish_prompt _original_fish_prompt 2&amp;gt;/dev/null

function fish_prompt --description 'Write out the prompt'
  if set -q ZMX_SESSION
    echo -n "[$ZMX_SESSION] "
  end
  _original_fish_prompt
end&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;todo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;todo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The entire argument for &lt;code&gt;zmx&lt;/code&gt; instead of something like &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; that has windows, panes, splits, etc. is that job should be handled by your os window manager.  By using something like &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; you now have redundent functionality in your dev stack: a window manager for your os and a window manager for your terminal.  Further, in order to use modern terminal features, your terminal emulator and &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; need to have support for them.  This holds back the terminal enthusiast community and feature development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, this tool specifically focuses on session persistence and defers window management to your os wm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;zmx&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; is a first-class citizen.  Instead of &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;ing into your remote system with a single terminal and &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; tmux panes, you open &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; terminals and run &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; for all of them.  This might sound tedious, but there are tools to make this a delightful workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, create an &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; config entry for your remote dev server:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Host = d.*
    HostName 192.168.1.xxx

    RemoteCommand zmx attach %k
    RequestTTY yes
    ControlPath ~/.ssh/cm-%r@%h:%p
    ControlMaster auto
    ControlPersist 10m&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now you can spawn as many terminal sessions as you'd like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ssh d.term
ssh d.irc
ssh d.pico
ssh d.dotfiles&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This will create or attach to each session and since we are using &lt;code&gt;ControlMaster&lt;/code&gt; the same &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; connection is reused for every call to &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; for near-instant connection times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now you can use the &lt;code&gt;autossh&lt;/code&gt; tool to make your ssh connections auto-reconnect.  For example, if you have a laptop and close/open your laptop lid it will automatically reconnect all your ssh connections:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;autossh -M 0 -q d.term&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or create an &lt;code&gt;alias&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;abbr&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;abbr -a ash "autossh -M 0 -q"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ash d.term
ash d.irc
ash d.pico
ash d.dotifles&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wow! Now you can setup all your os tiling windows how you like them for your project and have as many windows as you'd like, almost replicating exactly what &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; does but with native windows, tabs, splits, and scrollback!  It also has the added benefit of supporting all the terminal features your emulator supports, no longer restricted by what &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; supports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each session gets its own unix socket file. Right now, the default location is &lt;code&gt;/tmp/zmx&lt;/code&gt;. At the moment this is not configurable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We store global logs for cli commands in &lt;code&gt;/tmp/zmx/logs/zmx.log&lt;/code&gt;. We store session-specific logs in &lt;code&gt;/tmp/zmx/logs/{session_name}.log&lt;/code&gt;. These logs rotate to &lt;code&gt;.old&lt;/code&gt; after 5MB. At the moment this is not configurable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, nothing is configurable. We are evaluating what should be configurable and what should not. Every configuration option is a burden for us maintainers. For example, being able to change the default detach shortcut is difficult in a terminal environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Write programs that solve a well defined problem.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Write programs that behave the way most users expect them to behave.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Write programs that a single person can maintain.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Write programs that compose with other smol tools.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Write programs that can be finished.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;bug&lt;/code&gt;: unix socket files not always getting removed properly&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;bug&lt;/code&gt;: remove log files when closing session&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;bug&lt;/code&gt;: send resize event when a client first sends stdin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;feat&lt;/code&gt;: binary distribution (e.g.&lt;code&gt;aur&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;ppa&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;apk&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;brew&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The &lt;code&gt;daemon&lt;/code&gt;and client processes communicate via a unix socket&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Both &lt;code&gt;daemon&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;client&lt;/code&gt;loops leverage&lt;code&gt;poll()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Each session creates its own unix socket file &lt;code&gt;/tmp/zmx/*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We restore terminal state and output using &lt;code&gt;libghostty-vt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We use &lt;code&gt;libghostty-vt&lt;/code&gt; to restore the previous state of the terminal when a client re-attaches to a session.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How it works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;user creates session &lt;code&gt;zmx attach term&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;user interacts with terminal stdin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;stdin gets sent to pty via daemon&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;daemon sends pty output to client and &lt;code&gt;ghostty-vt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;ghostty-vt&lt;/code&gt;holds terminal state and scrollback&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;user disconnects&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;user re-attaches to session&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;ghostty-vt&lt;/code&gt;sends terminal snapshot to client stdout&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this way, &lt;code&gt;ghostty-vt&lt;/code&gt; doesn't sit in the middle of an active terminal session, it simply receives all the same data the client receives so it can re-hydrate clients that connect to the session.  This enables users to pick up where they left off as if they didn't disconnect from the terminal session at all.  It also has the added benefit of being very fast, the only thing sitting in-between you and your PTY is a unix socket.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below is a list of projects that inspired me to build this project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find the source code at this repo: https://github.com/shell-pool/shpool&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;shpool&lt;/code&gt; is a service that enables session persistence by allowing the creation of named shell sessions owned by &lt;code&gt;shpool&lt;/code&gt; so that the session is not lost if the connection drops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;shpool&lt;/code&gt; can be thought of as a lighter weight alternative to tmux or GNU screen. While tmux and screen take over the whole terminal and provide window splitting and tiling features, &lt;code&gt;shpool&lt;/code&gt; only provides persistent sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The biggest advantage of this approach is that &lt;code&gt;shpool&lt;/code&gt; does not break native scrollback or copy-paste.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find the source code at this repo: https://github.com/martanne/abduco&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;abduco provides session management i.e. it allows programs to be run independently from its controlling terminal. That is programs can be detached - run in the background - and then later reattached. Together with dvtm it provides a simpler and cleaner alternative to tmux or screen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46141893</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 23:46:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kea DHCP: Modern, open source DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 server</title><link>https://www.isc.org/kea/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ea1b597bc497298e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Kea 3.0, our first LTS version&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISC is excited to announce the release of Kea 3.0.0! This is a major release, and is the first Long-Term Support (LTS) version of Kea.&lt;/p&gt;Read&lt;p&gt;Modern, open source DHCPv4 &amp;amp; DHCPv6 server&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISC distributes TWO full-featured, open source, standards-based DHCP server distributions: Kea DHCP and ISC DHCP. Kea includes all the most-requested features, is far newer, and is designed for a more modern network environment. ISC announced the End of Life for the older ISC DHCP system in 2022. Users of ISC DHCP may find these resources helpful in migrating their DHCP server deployments to the Kea server.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modular Component Design, Extensible with Hooks Modules. The Kea distribution includes separate daemons for a DHCPv4 server, a DHCPv6 server, and a dynamic DNS (DDNS) module. Many optional features are enabled with dynamically-loaded “Hooks Modules,” which you need run only if you are using them. You can write your own hooks modules (in C++) or try some of the hooks we offer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On-line Re-configuration with REST API. Kea uses a JSON configuration file that can be modified remotely via &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; commands and reloaded without stopping and restarting the server, an operation that could take quite a while with ISC DHCP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Designed to Integrate with Your Existing Systems. Kea allows you to separate the data from the execution environment, enabling new deployment options. Your network data - leases, host reservation definitions, and most configuration data - can be located separately from the DHCP server itself, using a Kea “backend.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kea supports two database backends; MySQL and PostgreSQL. Besides the obvious benefits (you avoid JSON formatting errors, you can quickly and easily mine the data for other purposes) using a database backend enables multiple Kea servers to share the data. Potential benefits:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Web-based graphical dashboard. Kea now has a graphical dashboard for monitoring multiple Kea servers. This system, called Stork, uses agents deployed on the Kea servers to relay information to a centralized management platform, providing the administrator with an easy-to-use quick view of system status and activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Modern, higher performance implementation. Kea is multi-threaded, and when configured for efficient operation, it can be performant enough for a large-scale, short-lease duration environment, which is the most demanding scenario.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The core Kea daemons are open source, shared under MPL2.0 licensing. Kea is developed in the open on ISC’s GitLab; we welcome you to open issues and submit patches there. Kea runs on most Linux and Unix platforms, as well as MacOS. If you don’t want to build from our source distribution, we also provide a repository of pre-built packages for most popular operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contact ISC for Support&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your major design decisions are whether to deploy in pairs for High Availability and use the default csv file for host and lease data, or to install a separate database for a Kea data “backend.” Some of these decisions can limit your performance. See our Knowledgebase for advice on designing for optimal performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instructions are available for building and installing Kea from the source packages downloadable below. ISC provides pre-built packages for RHEL, Fedora, Ubuntu, and Debian. If you are using any Kea hook libraries, you will also need to install and configure those.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Kea Administrator Reference Manual (ARM) is the primary reference for Kea configuration. The extensive set of example configuration files in the project repo and our knowledgebase may help you get started. If you are migrating from an existing ISC DHCP deployment, try the Kea Migration Assistant (a special feature of the ISC DHCP distribution). This will enable you to save your current ISC DHCP server configuration as a Kea configuration file. It will still need some manual adjustment, but this tool should translate the bulk of your configuration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most users will benefit from joining the kea-users mailing list. Consider joining our Kea project GitLab to log issues, see what we’re working on, submit patches, and participate in development. Consider deploying Stork for a graphical management dashboard. If your DHCP is critical to your business, we recommend you subscribe for technical support from ISC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stork aggregates data about the health of the system hosting Kea, as well as the status and activity level of Kea itself. Parameters reported include memory, CPU utilization, software versions, and uptime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stork displays configured pools, with # of addresses provisioned and assigned and even tracks pool utilization across shared networks. Graphical elements highlight areas of high utilization to alert the operator to take actionHigh Availability pairs are monitored and their configured role and status are shown, making it easy to see which servers don’t have a backup established, and when a failover event has occurred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add, update and view DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 host reservations, using a graphical interface to select a host identifier, assign a hostname, reserve an IP address, associate a client class, and configure boot file information and DHCP options.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Service Options&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Gold support&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Silver support&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Bronze support&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Basic (no support)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Premium (no longer offered)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Critical issue response&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;30 minutes, 24x7&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1 hour, 24x7&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2 hours, business hours only*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;not included&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;not included&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Standard issue response&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4 business hours*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;8 business hours*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Next business day&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;community support via public mailing list&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;community support via public mailing list&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Early vulnerability notifications&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5 days&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5 days&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5 days&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3 days&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;not included&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Kea 3.0 hook libraries (RBAC and Configuration Backend are the only commercially-licensed ones)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Subscriber&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Subscriber&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Subscriber&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Subscriber&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;N/A&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Kea 2.6 and earlier hook libraries included&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Enterprise, Premium and Subscription&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;All - Enterprise, Premium and Subscription&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Premium and Subscription&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Premium and Subscription&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Premium&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Stork support&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Available&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Available&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Available&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Community support via user mailing list&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Community support via user mailing list&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Purchasing&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Quotation/Purchase order&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Quotation/Purchase order&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Quotation/Purchase order&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Quotation/Purchase order&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;no longer offered&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pricing based on deployment size and service level.&lt;/p&gt;Contact ISC for a quote&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;VERSION&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;STATUS&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;DOCUMENTATION&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;RELEASE DATE&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;EOL DATE&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;DOWNLOAD&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3.0.2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Current Stable - LTS&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Kea ARM ( HTML PDF )&lt;p&gt;Kea Messages ( HTML PDF )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Release Notes ( TXT )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;October 2025&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;June 2028&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="6"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2.6.4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Current Stable&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Kea ARM ( HTML PDF )&lt;p&gt;Kea Messages ( HTML PDF )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Release Notes ( TXT )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;July 2025&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;July 2026&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3.1.4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Development&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Kea ARM ( HTML PDF )&lt;p&gt;Kea Messages ( HTML PDF )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Release Notes ( TXT )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;November 2025&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;June 2026&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46142000</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 23:58:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Average DRAM price in USD over last 18 months</title><link>https://pcpartpicker.com/trends/price/memory/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46142100</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:08:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Euler Conjecture and CDC 6600</title><link>https://fortran-lang.discourse.group/t/euler-conjecture-and-cdc-6600/10501</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bec9d9882d3a9cda"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I don’t think this warning applies here because the array is small, but the danger of this approach in general is that the executable file must contain that compile-time computed data, which means that it takes time to load that memory from disk (SSD, etc.) into the process memory on startup. In contrast, if that memory is allocated at run time directly by the executable, and then filled by cpu instructions, then it can be some 10^3 to 10^5 times faster. You can also see the difference by looking at the size of the executable image (&lt;code&gt;ls -l a.out&lt;/code&gt;). With most modern compilers, you do not see the size of the declared array reflected in the executable size unless they are parameter arrays, arrays initialized at compile time, or arrays in common blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Also, if done at compile time, the whole array would need to be computed. That is 10^4 elements in this case (and integer overflows would be generated in doing so). The above run time code only computes 144 elements of the array before finding a solution and stopping.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A further question is where does that extra effort get charged? This extra effort is appropriate if the user is paying for that time (e.g. with money, or with elapsed time, or with total throughput through the machine), but not if that overhead is somehow not charged as user time (e.g. in a timeshare or batch environment with many other users). This is why the programmer sometimes writes code to minimize wall time and sometimes to minimize cpu time. Those two goals are not always exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In the original code, the posix &lt;code&gt;time&lt;/code&gt; command was used for the timings. That command returns three different time values for exactly this reason. If you alone own the machine you are running on, and you want to maximize throughput through that machine every 24 hour period, then it is the elapsed time that is critical. If you are one of many users sharing the machine, then it is the user time that you want to minimize, the system time is not charged to you because while your job is stalled waiting for the disk to respond, someone else’s job is swapped in and is being charged to execute its user time.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Here is the timing result of that last version of the code using gfortran -O3 with an Apple M2 cpu&lt;lb/&gt; on MacOS. It computes the &lt;code&gt;i**5&lt;/code&gt; values at run time, so the system time is minimal.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;i^5 =  61917364224
133 110 84 27 144

real    0m0.141s
user    0m0.139s
sys     0m0.002s
&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;One other comment about timings is that they are almost never really consistent from run to run. For small segments of code like this, one can do&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;$ time a.out; time a.out; time a.out
&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The first results are usually longer than the others, which are then usually more consistent if not identical at the millisecond level. But if timings are measured at the microsecond level, they would show variations too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46143618</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 03:50:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New homes in London were delayed by 'energy-hungry' data centres</title><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c0mpr1mvwj3o</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ff44ab375c942ffa"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;New homes delayed by 'energy-hungry' data centres&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The rapid growth of "energy-hungry" data centres is delaying new homes in London, just as its housing crisis is "at its worst", a new report has warned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data centres are giant warehouses full of powerful computers used to run digital services, such as streaming and artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, they require masses of electricity from the National Grid to keep running.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to the report from the London Assembly Planning and Regeneration Committee, some new housing developments in west London were temporarily delayed after the electricity grid reached full capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The committee's chair James Small-Edwards said energy capacity had become a "real constraint" on housing and economic growth in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2022, the General London Assembly (GLA) began to investigate delays to housing developments in the boroughs of Ealing, Hillingdon and Hounslow - after it received reports that completed projects were being told they would have to "wait until 2037" to get a connection to the electricity grid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were fears the boroughs may have to "pause new housing altogether" until the issue was resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the GLA found short-term fixes with the National Grid and energy regulator Ofgem to ensure the "worst-case scenario" did not happen - though several projects were still set back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The strains on parts of London's housing highlighted the need for "longer term planning" around grid capacity in the future, said the report.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It added that while data centres made up fewer than 10% of the UK's total electricity demand last year, that was expected to rise up by to 600% between 2025 and 2050.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It estimated the energy usage of one typical data centre was similar to that of roughly 100,000 households.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figures shared with BBC News in August showed an estimated 447 data centres currently in the UK, with that number set to rise by about 100 in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More than half of new data centres are planned in and around London.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Dakers, chief executive of industry body West London Business, told BBC News the area was proud to host "so much digital tech and investment", but that it came with challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"At the moment National Grid are looking to try and get 7 GW of additional power into west London by 2037," he said. "Our ask is that needs to happen faster... 12 years is just too far. The demand is here and now".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rhodri Williams, technical director of the Home Builders Federation, told BBC News it was "essential" the government made sure there was "adequate investment" into the supply network to support housing developments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among a list of recommendations, the committee suggested introducing a separate planning category for data centres, to ensure better energy coordination.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A government spokesperson told BBC News it was exploring "bespoke options", including through the AI Energy Council, to support data centres and the housing sector.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The report also called on Mayor of London Sir Sadiq Khan to include a dedicated data centre policy in the next London Plan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A spokesperson for the mayor told BBC News they are working to include "how to best address the need for data centres in London" in the next London Plan, and would "carefully consider" the recommendations of the report.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Under Sadiq, we have seen more new council home starts in London than at any time since the 1970s and, prior to the pandemic, more new homes completed in London than any time since the 1930s," they added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional reporting by Jess Warren.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sign up for our Tech Decoded newsletter to follow the world's top tech stories and trends. Outside the UK? Sign up here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46143622</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 03:51:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia Bans Roblox</title><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cn41q11gy58o</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b4260f7b21a18fda"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Russia bans Roblox over concerns about safety and extremist content&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russia has blocked access to popular gaming platform Roblox due to concerns over child safety and extremism, including the spread of LGBT-related content.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The country's media regulator said Roblox had become rife with "inappropriate content that can negatively impact the spiritual and moral development of children", according to local news outlets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The multiplayer online platform ranks among the world's most popular, but has been heavily criticised over its lack of features to protect children.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A spokesperson from Roblox said the company respects the laws where it operates, adding that the platform provides a "positive space" for learning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We have a deep commitment to safety and we have a robust set of proactive and preventative safety measures designed to catch and prevent harmful content on our platform," the spokesperson said in response to the BBC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian media reported that Roskomnadzor, the country's media regulator, blocked the US platform over concerns about terrorism-related content and information on LGBT issues, which are classified as extremist and banned in Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Such activity is often found in Roblox's servers, where scenarios simulating terrorist attacks, as well as gambling, have surfaced, the agency is quoted as saying.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Roblox, which ranks among Russia's most downloaded mobile games in recent years, allows players to create and share their own games - a model that has made regulation challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Roskomnadzor also flagged reports of sexual harassment of children and the sharing of intimate images on the platform. Other countries have raised similar issues, and the platform is already banned in certain countries, including Turkey, over concerns about child safety.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Roblox also came under scrutiny in Singapore in 2023 after the government there said a self-radicalised teenager had joined ISIS-themed servers on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last month, Texas Attorney General Ken Paxton sued the platform over "flagrantly ignoring" safety laws and "deceiving parents" about the dangers it posed to young people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This month, Roblox announced it would stop allowing children to chat with adult strangers, after longstanding criticism over the platform's networking feature.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46143841</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 04:34:14 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>