<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 16:46:41 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Transparent leadership beats servant leadership</title><link>https://entropicthoughts.com/transparent-leadership-beats-servant-leadership</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bce3d0111682d491"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Transparent Leadership Beats Servant Leadership&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;tl:dr: Parenting and leadership is similar. Teach a man to fish, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I spent a couple of years managing a team, and I entered that role – like many – without knowing anything about how to do it. I tried to figure out how to be a good manager, and doing so I ended up reading a lot about servant leadership. It never quite sat right with me, though. Servant leadership seems to me a lot like curling parenting: the leader/parent anticipate problems and sweep the way for their direct reports/children.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be clear, this probably feels very good (initially, anyway) for the direct reports/children. But the servant leader/curling parent quickly becomes an overworked single point of failure, and once they leave there is nobody else who knows how to handle the obstacles the leader moved out of the way for everyone. In the worst cases, they leave behind a group of people who have been completely isolated from the rest of the organisation, and has no idea what their purpose is and how to fit in with the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would like to invent my own buzzword: transparent leadership. In my book, a good leader&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;coaches people,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;connects people,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;teaches people methodical problem solving,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;explains values and principles embraced by the organisation to aid them in making aligned decisions on their own,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;creates direct links between supply and demand (instead of deliberately making themselves a middle man),&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;allows their direct reports career growth by gradually taking over leadership responsibilities,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;continuously trains their replacement, and&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;generally makes themselves redundant.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The middle manager that doesn’t perform any useful work is a fun stereotype, but I also think it’s a good target to aim for. The difference lies in what to do once one has rendered oneself redundant. A common response is to invent new work, ask for status reports, and add bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A better response is to go back to working on technical problems. This keeps the manager’s skills fresh and gets them more respect from their reports. The manager should turn into a high-powered spare worker, rather than a paper-shuffler.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46147540</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 13:40:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I have been writing a niche history blog for 15 years</title><link>https://resobscura.substack.com/p/why-i-have-been-writing-a-niche-history</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46151299</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 18:49:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>We gave 5 LLMs $100K to trade stocks for 8 months</title><link>https://www.aitradearena.com/research/we-ran-llms-for-8-months</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46154491</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 23:08:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trick users and bypass warnings – Modern SVG Clickjacking attacks</title><link>https://lyra.horse/blog/2025/12/svg-clickjacking/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="120802a0bcc92fb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;SVG Filters - Clickjacking 2.0&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clickjacking is a classic attack that consists of covering up an iframe of some other website in an attempt to trick the user into unintentionally interacting with it. It works great if you need to trick someone into pressing a button or two, but for anything more complicated it’s kind of unrealistic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve discovered a new technique that turns classic clickjacking on its head and enables the creation of complex interactive clickjacking attacks, as well as multiple forms of data exfiltration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I call this technique “SVG clickjacking”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Liquid SVGs&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The day Apple announced its new Liquid Glass redesign was pretty chaotic. You couldn’t go on social media without every other post being about the new design, whether it was critique over how inaccessible it seemed, or awe at how realistic the refraction effects were.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drowning in the flurry of posts, a thought came to mind - how hard would it be to re-create this effect? Could I do this, on the web, without resorting to canvas and shaders? I got to work, and about an hour later I had a pretty accurate CSS/SVG recreation of the effect1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;EMERGENCY!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Girls Rituals&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Won't Be The Last Time&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;acloudyskye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SOUND BANDIT FUCKING LIVES&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sound Bandit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Love &amp;amp; Ponystep&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vylet Pony&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I Love My Computer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ninajirachi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can drag around the effect with the bottom-right circle control thing in the demo above (chrome/firefox desktop, chrome mobile).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My little tech demo made quite a splash online, and even resulted in a news article with what is probably the wildest quote about me to date: “Samsung and others have nothing on her”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few days passed, and another thought came to mind - would this SVG effect work on top of an iframe?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like, surely not? The way the effect “refracts light”2 is way too complex to work on a cross-origin document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, to my surprise, it did.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reason this was so interesting to me is that my liquid glass effect uses the &lt;code&gt;feColorMatrix&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;feDisplacementMap&lt;/code&gt; SVG filters - changing the colors of pixels, and moving them, respectively. And I could do that on a cross-origin document?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This got me wondering - do any of the other filters work on iframes, and could we turn that into an attack somehow? It turns out that it’s all of them, and yes!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building blocks&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got to work, going through every &amp;lt;fe*&amp;gt; SVG element and figuring out which ones can be combined to build our own attack primitives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These filter elements take in one or more input images, apply operations to them, and output a new image. You can chain a bunch of them together within a single SVG filter, and refer to the output of any of the previous filter elements in the chain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at some of the more useful base elements we can play with:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feImage&amp;gt; - load an image file;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feFlood&amp;gt; - draw a rectangle;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feOffset&amp;gt; - move stuff around;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feDisplacementMap&amp;gt; - move pixels according to a map;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feGaussianBlur&amp;gt; - blur stuff;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feTile&amp;gt; - tiling and cropping utility;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feMorphology&amp;gt; - expand/grow light or dark areas;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feBlend&amp;gt; - blend two inputs according to the mode;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feComposite&amp;gt; - compositing utilities, can be used to apply an alpha matte, or do various arithmetics on one or two inputs;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&amp;lt;feColorMatrix&amp;gt; - apply a color matrix, this allows moving colors between channels and converting between alpha and luma mattes;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s quite a selection of utilities!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re a demoscener3 you’re probably feeling right at home. These are the fundamental building blocks for many kinds of computer graphics, and they can be combined into many useful primitives of our own. So let’s see some examples.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Fake captcha&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ll start off with an example of basic data exfiltration. Suppose you’re targeting an iframe that contains some sort of sensitive code. You could ask the user to retype it by itself, but that’d probably seem suspicious.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What we can do instead is make use of &lt;code&gt;feDisplacementMap&lt;/code&gt; to make the text seem like a captcha! This way, the user is far more likely to retype the code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is your secret code:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;6c79 7261 706f 6e79&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don't share it with anyone!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is your secret code:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;6c79 7261 706f 6e79&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don't share it with anyone!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(tapclick to edit if you're not a girl)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: Only the part inside the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;filter&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; block is relevant, the rest is just an example of using filters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add to this some color effects and random lines, and you’ve got a pretty convincing cap-tcha!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Out of all the attack primitives I’ll be sharing, this one is probably the least useful as sites rarely allow you to frame pages giving out magic secret codes. I wanted to show it though, as it’s a pretty simple introduction to the attack technique.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still, it could come in handy because often times you’re allowed to frame read-only API endpoints, so maybe there’s an attack there to discover.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Grey text hiding&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next example is for situations where you want to trick someone into, for example, interacting with a text input. Oftentimes the inputs have stuff like grey placeholder text in them, so showing the input box by itself won’t cut it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at our example target (try typing in the box).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this example we want to trick the user into setting an attacker-known password, so we want them to be able to see the text they’re entering, but not the grey placeholder text, nor the red “too short” text.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s start off by using &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt; with arithmetics to make the grey text disappear. The &lt;code&gt;arithmetic&lt;/code&gt; operation takes in two images, &lt;code&gt;i1&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;in=...&lt;/code&gt;) and &lt;code&gt;i2&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;in2=...&lt;/code&gt;), and lets us do per-pixel maths with &lt;code&gt;k1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;k2&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;k3&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;k4&lt;/code&gt; as the arguments according to this formula: 4.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tip! You can leave out the in/in2 parameters if you just want it to be the previous output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s getting there - by multiplying the brightness of the input we’ve made the grey text disappear, but now the black text looks a little suspicious and hard to read, especially on 1x scaling displays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We could play around with the arguments to find the perfect balance between hiding the grey text and showing the black one, but ideally we’d still have the black text look the way usually does, just without any grey text. Is that possible?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So here’s where a really cool technique comes into play - masking. We’re going to create a matte to “cut out” the black text and cover up everything else. It’s going to take us quite a few steps to get to the desired result, so lets go through it bit-by-bit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We start off by cropping the result of our black text filter with &lt;code&gt;feTile&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: Safari seems to be having some trouble with &lt;code&gt;feTile&lt;/code&gt;, so if the examples flicker or look blank, read this post in a browser such as Firefox or Chrome. If you're writing an attack for Safari, you can also achieve cropping by making a luma matte with &lt;code&gt;feFlood&lt;/code&gt; and then applying it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then we use &lt;code&gt;feMorphology&lt;/code&gt; to increase the thickness of the text.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now we have to increase the contrast of the mask. I’m going to do it by first using &lt;code&gt;feFlood&lt;/code&gt; to create a solid white image, which we can then &lt;code&gt;feBlend&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;difference&lt;/code&gt; to invert our mask. And then we can use &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt; to multiply5 the mask for better contrast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have a luma matte now! All that’s left is to convert it into an alpha matte with &lt;code&gt;feColorMatrix&lt;/code&gt;, apply it to the source image with &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt;, and make the background white with &lt;code&gt;feBlend&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looks pretty good, doesn’t it! If you empty out the box (try it!) you might notice some artifacts that give away what we’ve done, but apart from that it’s a pretty good way to sort of sculpt and form various inputs around a bit for an attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are all sorts of other effects you can add to make the input seem just right. Let’s combine everything together into a complete example of an attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set a new password&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can see how the textbox is entirely recontextualized now to fit a different design while still being fully functional.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Pixel reading&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;And now we come to what is most likely the most useful attack primitive - pixel reading. That’s right, you can use SVG filters to read color data off of images and perform all sorts of logic on them to create really advanced and convincing attacks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The catch is of course, that you’ll have to do everything within SVG filters - there is no way to get the data out6. Despite that, it is very powerful if you get creative with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a higher level, what this lets us do is make everything in a clickjacking attack responsive - fake buttons can have hover effects, pressing them can show fake dropdowns and dialogs, and we can even have fake form validation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s start off with a simple example - detecting if a pixel is pure black, and using it to turn another filter on or off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this target, we want to detect when the user clicks on the box to change its color, and use that to toggle a blur effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s start off by using two copies of the &lt;code&gt;feTile&lt;/code&gt; filter to first crop out the few pixels we’re interested in and then tile those pixels across the entire image.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The result is that we now have the entire screen filled with the color of the area we are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can turn this result into a binary on/off value by using &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt;’s arithmetic the same way as in the last section, but with a way larger &lt;code&gt;k2&lt;/code&gt; value. This makes it so that the output image is either completely black or completely white.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And just as before, this can be used as a mask. We once again convert it into an alpha matte, but this time apply it to the blur filter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So that’s how you can find out whether a pixel is black and use that to toggle a filter!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uh oh! It seems that somebody has changed the target to have a pride-themed button instead!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How can we adapt this technique to work with arbitrary colors and textures?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;--- very cool! click to change color&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The solution is pretty simple - we can simply use &lt;code&gt;feBlend&lt;/code&gt;’s difference combined with a &lt;code&gt;feColorMatrix&lt;/code&gt; to join the color channels to turn the image into a similar black/white matte as before. For textures we can use &lt;code&gt;feImage&lt;/code&gt;, and for non-exact colors we can use a bit of &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt;’s arithmetic to make the matching threshold more lenient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And that’s it, a simple example of how we can read a pixel value and use it to toggle a filter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Logic gates&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;But here’s the part where it gets fun! We can repeat the pixel-reading process to read out multiple pixels, and then run logic on them to program an attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By using &lt;code&gt;feBlend&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;feComposite&lt;/code&gt;, we can recreate all logic gates and make SVG filters functionally complete. This means that we can program anything we want, as long as it is not timing-based7 and doesn’t take up too many resources8.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Input: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; NOT: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feBlend mode=difference in2=white /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; AND: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feComposite operator=arithmetic k1=1 /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; OR: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feComposite operator=arithmetic k2=1 k3=1 /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; XOR: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;feBlend mode=difference in=a in2=b /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; NAND: &lt;code&gt;(AND + NOT)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; NOR: &lt;code&gt;(OR + NOT)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; XNOR: &lt;code&gt;(XOR + NOT)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These logic gates are what modern computers are made of. You could build a computer within an SVG filter if you wanted to. In fact, here’s a basic calculator I made:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SVG Adder&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a full adder circuit. This filter implements the logic gates for the output and for the carry bit using the logic gates described above. There are more efficient ways to implement an adder in SVG filters, but this is meant to serve as proof of the ability to implement arbitrary logic circuits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyways, for an attacker, what all of this means is that you can make a multi-step clickjacking attack with lots of conditions and interactivity. And you can run logic on data from cross-origin frames.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Securify&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this secure application!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hack confirmation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are you sure you'd like to get hacked?&lt;/p&gt;⌛&lt;p&gt;This is an example target where we want to trick the user into marking themselves as hacked, which requires a few steps:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Clicking a button to open a dialog&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Waiting for the dialog to load&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Clicking a checkbox within the dialog&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Clicking another button in the dialog&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Checking for the red text that appeared&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Securify&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this secure application!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hack confirmation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are you sure you'd like to get hacked?&lt;/p&gt;⌛&lt;p&gt;Win free iPod by following the steps below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A traditional clickjacking attack against this target would be difficult to pull off. You’d need to have the user click on multiple buttons in a row with no feedback in the UI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are some tricks you could do to make a traditional attack more convincing than what you see above, but it’s still gonna look sketch af. And the moment you throw something like a text input into the mix, it’s just not gonna work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyways, let’s build out a logic tree for a filter-based attack:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Is the dialog open? &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Is the red text present? &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Make the user press the button&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(Yes) Show the end screen&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(Yes) Is the dialog loaded? &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Show loading screen&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(Yes) Is the checkbox checked? &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Make the user check the checkbox&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(Yes) Make the user click the button&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(No) Is the red text present? &lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which can be expressed in logic gates9 as:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Inputs &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;D (dialog visible) = check for background dim&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;L (dialog loaded) = check for the button in dialog&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;C (checkbox checked) = check whether the button is blue or grey&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;R (red text visible) = &lt;code&gt;feMorphology&lt;/code&gt;and check for red pixels&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Outputs &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;(¬D) ∧ (¬R) =&amp;gt; button1.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;D ∧ (¬L) =&amp;gt; loading.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;D ∧ L ∧ (¬C) =&amp;gt; checkbox.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;D ∧ L ∧ C =&amp;gt; button2.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;(¬D) ∧ R =&amp;gt; end.png&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;And this is how we would implement it in SVG:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Securify&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this secure application!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hack confirmation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are you sure you'd like to get hacked?&lt;/p&gt;⌛&lt;p&gt;Play around with this and see just how much more convincing it is as an attack. And we could easily make it better by, for example, adding some extra logic to also add hover visuals to the buttons. The demo has debug visuals for the four inputs (D, L, C, R) in the bottom left as squares to make it easier to understand what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But yeah, that’s how you can make complex and long clickjacking attacks that have not been realistic with the traditional clickjacking methods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I kept this example here pretty short and simple, but real-world attacks can be a lot more involved and polished.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Docs bug&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve actually managed to pull off this attack against Google Docs!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the demo videos here (alt links: bsky, twitter).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What this attack does is:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Makes the user click on the “Generate Document” button&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Once pressed, detects the popup and shows a textbox for the user to type a “captcha” into &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;The textbox starts off with a gradient animation, which must be handled&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The textbox has focus states, which must also be present in the attack visuals, so they must be detected by the background color of the textbox&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The textbox has grey text for both a placeholder AND suggestions, which must be hidden with the technique discussed earlier&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Once the captcha is typed, makes the user seemingly click on a button (or press enter), which causes a suggested Docs item to be added into the textbox &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;This item must be detected by looking for its background color in the textbox&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Once the item is detected, the textbox must be hidden and another button must be shown instead &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Once that button is clicked, a loading screen appears, which must be detected&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;If the loading screen is present, or the dialog is not visible and the “Generate Document” button is not present, the attack is over and the final screen must be shown&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the past, individual parts of such an attack could’ve been pulled off through traditional clickjacking and some basic CSS, but the entire attack would’ve been way too long and complex to be realistic. With this new technique of running logic inside SVG filters, such attacks become realistic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Google VRP awarded me $3133.70 for the find. That was, of course, right before they introduced a novelty bonus for new vulnerability classes. Hmph!10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The QR attack&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something I see in online discussions often is the insistence on QR codes being dangerous. It kind of rubs me the wrong way because QR codes are not any more dangerous than links.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t usually comment on this too much because it’s best to avoid suspicious links, and the same goes for QR codes, but it does nag me to see people make QR codes out to be this evil thing that can somehow immediately hack you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I turns out though, that my SVG filters attack technique can be applied to QR codes as well!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The example from earlier in the blog with retyping a code becomes impractical once the user realizes they’re typing something they shouldn’t. We can’t stuff the data we exfiltrate into a link either, because an SVG filter cannot create a link.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But since an SVG filter can run logic and provide visual output, perhaps we could generate a QR code with a link instead?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Creating the QR&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating a QR code within an SVG filter is easier said than done however. We can shape binary data into the shape of a QR code by using &lt;code&gt;feDisplacementMap&lt;/code&gt;, but for a QR code to be scannable it also needs error correction data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QR codes use Reed-Solomon error correction, which is some fun math stuff that’s a bit more advanced than a simple checksum. It does math with polynomials and stuff and that is a bit annoying to reimplement in an SVG.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luckily for us, I’ve faced the same problem before! Back in 2021 I was the first person11 to make a QR code generator in Minecraft, so I’ve already figured out the things necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my build I pre-calculated some lookup tables for the error correction, and used those instead to make the build simpler - and we can do the same with the SVG filter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is already getting pretty long, so I’ll leave figuring out how this filter works as an exercise to the reader ;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a demo that displays a QR code telling you how many seconds you’ve been on this page for. It’s a bit fiddly, so if it doesn’t work make sure that you aren’t using any &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This demo &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Similarly, in a real attack, the scaling and color profile issues could be worked around using some JavaScript tricks or simply by implementing the filter a bit differently - this here is just a proof of concept that’s a bit rough around the edges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But yeah, that’s a QR code generator built inside an SVG filter!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Took me a while to make, but I didn’t want to write about it just being “theoretically possible”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Attack scenario&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;So the attack scenario with the QR code is that you’d read pixels from a frame, process them to extract the data you want, encode them into a URL that looks something like https://lyra.horse/?ref=c3VwZXIgc2VjcmV0IGluZm8 and render it as a QR code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, you prompt the user to scan the QR code for whatever reason (eg anti-bot check). To them, the URL will seem like just a normal URL with a tracking ID or something in it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once the user opens the URL, your server gets the request and receives the data from the URL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;And so on..&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are so many ways to make use of this technique I won’t have time to go over them all in this post. Some examples would be reading text by using the difference blend mode, or exfiltrating data by making the user click on certain parts of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You could even insert data from the outside to have a fake mouse cursor inside the SVG that shows the pointer cursor and reacts to fake buttons inside your SVG to make the exfiltration more realistic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or you could code up attacks with CSS and SVG where CSP doesn’t allow for any JS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyways, this post is long as is, so I’ll leave figuring out these techniques as homework.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Novel technique&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first time in my security research I’ve found a completely new technique!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I introduced it briefly at my BSides talk in September, and this post here is a more in-depth overview of the technique and how it can be used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can never know 100% for sure that a specific type of attack has never been found by anyone else, but my extensive search of existing security research has come up with nothing, so I suppose I can crown myself as the researcher who discovered it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s some previous research I’ve found:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;You click, I steal: analyzing and detecting click hijacking attacks in web pages,&lt;lb/&gt;On the fragility and limitations of current Browser-provided Clickjacking protection schemes&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;The papers mention SVG filters in clickjacking attacks, but only in the context of obscuring the underlying elements, not running logic.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Pixel Perfect Timing - Attacks with HTML5,&lt;lb/&gt;Security: SVG Filter Timing Attack&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Research on reading pixels through SVG filter timing attacks, which is a technique that is mitigated in modern browsers.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The Human Side Channel &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Some pretty cool clickjacking techniques, though no multi-step attacks or SVG logic.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;SVG is turing-complete-ish &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Another example of logic gates in SVG I found after writing my blog. It’s fun because it comes with reddit and hn threads - I particularly like the comment asking about whether this turing completeness is useful or just a fun fact, which got a reply confirming the latter. I like turning fun facts into vulnerabilities ^^.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Note that whether SVG filters are actually turing complete is questionable because filters are implemented in constant-time and can’t run in a loop. This doesn’t mean they can’t be turing complete, but it also doesn’t prove that they are.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t think me discovering this technique was just luck though. I have a history of seeing things such as CSS as programming languages to exploit and be creative with. It wasn’t a stretch for me to see SVG filters as a programming language either.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That, and my overlap between security research and creative projects - I often blur the lines between the two, which is what Antonymph was born out of.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any case, &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;afterword&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;whoa this post took such a long time for me to get done!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;i started work on it in july, and was expecting to release it alongside my CSS talk in september, but it has taken me so much longer than expected to actually finish this thing. i wanted to make sure it was a good in-depth post, rather than something i just get out as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;unlike my previous posts, i did unfortunately have to break my trend of using no images, since i needed a few data URIs within the SVG filters for demos. still, no images anywhere else in the post, no javascript, and just 42kB (gzip) of handcrafted html/css/svg.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;also, i usually hide a bunch of easter eggs in my post that link to stuff i’ve enjoyed recently, but i have a couple links i didn’t want to include without content warnings. finding responsibility is a pretty dark talk about the ethics of making sure your work won’t end up killing people, and youre the one ive always wanted is slightly nsfw doggyhell vent art.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;btw i’ll soon be giving talks at 39c3 and disobey 2026! the 39c3 one is titled “css clicker training” and will be about css crimes and making games in css. and the disobey one is the same talk as the bsides one about using css to hack stuff and get bug bounties, but i’ll make sure to throw some extra content in there to keep it fun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;see y’all around!!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: I you’re making content (articles, videos etc) based on this post, feel free to reach out to me to ask for questions or feedback.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discuss this post on: twitter, mastodon, lobsters&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I actually had after an hour was this, the Codepen link is an updated version that I added controls to later on. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a fancy way of saying it does a basic displacement of pixels. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;…or After Effects/Blender/Fusion etc user. Or anything else computer graphics. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;result = k1*i1*i2 + k2*i1 + k3*i2 + k4 in programmer language (I just couldn’t resist trying out the &amp;lt;math&amp;gt; tag for fun). ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The multiplication in this case is kind of the opposite of what you’d expect from the “multiply” blend mode - things will get lighter, not darker. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s not possible to get the pixel data out of a SVG filter as they’re implemented in constant-time. If you can find a way to retrieve the data then it’s a browser bug and you can most likely get bounty for it. Happy to collaborate if you’d like to turn such a finding into a working proof of concept for a report :). ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can actually pass the current time into an SVG filter, but we can’t do attacks such as “if a pixel changes, wait 1 second and then show a dialog” unless we can piggyback off an animation in the source frame. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since SVG filters are implemented in constant-time, they become pretty resource-intensive for complex filters on high-resolution targets. One optimization would be to have a full-resolution filter just for picking out the pixels, then a tiny-resolution backdrop-filter to run all the logic, and then another full-resolution filter to display the attack. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;¬ - NOT, ∧ - AND, ∨ - OR, ⊕ - XOR etc, see List of logic symbols. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is kind of similar to how I reported the Docs/YouTube/Slides chain right before they 5x’d the VRP rewards. I seem to have the worst luck with timing my reports… ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;I released my QR code generator in 2021, making it the earliest publicly released Minecraft QR code generator. I know, however, that DavidJR was independently working on a QR code generator at the same time as I was, eventually releasing it in 2023. Then there’s one from Sep 2024 by 37meliodas, and lastly there’s the probably most well-known one by mattbatwings from Dec 2024. The latter has an awesome video explaining everything in-depth, so I definitely recommend checking it out if you’re interested in Minecraft redstone. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46155085</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:03:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netflix’s AV1 Journey: From Android to TVs and Beyond</title><link>https://netflixtechblog.com/av1-now-powering-30-of-netflix-streaming-02f592242d80</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46155135</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:09:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>BMW PHEV: Safety fuse replacement is extremely expensive</title><link>https://evclinic.eu/2025/12/04/2021-phev-bmw-ibmucp-21f37e-post-crash-recovery-when-eu-engineering-becomes-a-synonym-for-unrepairable-generating-waste/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46155619</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 01:05:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UniFi 5G</title><link>https://blog.ui.com/article/introducing-unifi-5g</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e818a12e14516a1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UniFi 5G Max lineup was created with a clear goal in mind: deliver a sleek, versatile, and exceptionally powerful 5G internet experience that works effortlessly in any environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UniFi 5G Max lineup was created with a clear goal in mind: deliver a sleek, versatile, and exceptionally powerful 5G internet experience that works effortlessly in any environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UniFi 5G Max makes deployment easy, whether installed locally or at a remote site. Plug it into any PoE port and it instantly appears as a ready to use WAN interface, no matter whether plugged directly into your UniFi gateway or into your office switch. No new cable runs needed! It sits neatly on a desk, but you can reposition it for the best possible signal using the included wall or window mount.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 5G Max delivers downlink speeds up to 2 Gbps with ultra low latency that makes it reliable as a primary connection and seamless as a backup WAN. UniFi routing policies and SLAs let you choose exactly how and when 5G is used, and for which clients and VLANs. Easily set per-SIM usage limits to avoid overage costs with just a few clicks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For tougher environments or deployments with poor indoor cellular coverage, the outdoor model maintains the same high performance cellular connectivity with improved antenna performance in a durable IP67 rated enclosure. It is built for rooftop installs, off site locations, and mobile deployments where reliability is critical. Just like its indoor counterpart, you can also connect it via any PoE port, anywhere on your network, greatly simplifying cabling requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want everything UniFi in one device, the DreamRouter 5G Max combines 5G connectivity with WiFi 7, local storage, and full UniFi OS application support. Deploy it anywhere 5G is available and run an entire high-performance and scalable network stack instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every device in the UniFi 5G lineup supports both physical SIMs and eSIM, giving you the freedom to choose your carrier and switch whenever needed with zero friction. All are equipped with dual SIM slots, with one SIM replaceable by eSIM, and are fully unlocked: any major carrier, any type of deployment, with one piece of hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The UniFi 5G lineup brings sleek design, powerful performance, easy installation, and genuine WAN flexibility to every deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46157594</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 07:06:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kenyan court declares law banning seed sharing unconstitutional</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/kenya-seed-sharing-law-ruling-ad4df5a364299b3a9f8515c0f52d5f80</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d8e624ea1bbbd655"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Kenyan court declares law banning seed sharing unconstitutional&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;KISUMU, Kenya (AP) — A high court in Kenya on Thursday declared unconstitutional sections of a seed law that prevented farmers from sharing and selling indigenous seeds in what food campaigners have called a landmark win for food security.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Farmers in Kenya could face up to two years’ imprisonment and a fine of 1 million Kenya shillings ($7,700) for sharing seeds through their community seed banks, according to a seed law signed in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Justice Rhoda Rutto on Thursday said sections of the seed law that gave government officials powers to raid seed banks and seize seeds were also unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The law was introduced as a measure to curb growing sale of counterfeit seeds that were causing loses in the agricultural sector and gave sole seed trading rights to licensed companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The case had been filed by 15 smallholder farmers, who are members of community seed banks that have been in operation for years, preserving and sharing seeds among colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A farmer, Samuel Wathome, who was among the 15, said the old farming practices had been vindicated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“My grandmother saved seeds, and today the court has said I can do the same for my grandchildren without fear of the police or of prison,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elizabeth Atieno, a food campaigner at Greenpeace Africa, called the win a “victory for our culture, our resilience, and our future.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“By validating indigenous seeds, the court has struck a blow against the corporate capture of our food system. We can finally say that in Kenya, feeding your community with climate-resilient, locally adapted seeds is no longer a crime,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Food campaigners have in the past encouraged governments to work with farmers to preserve indigenous seeds as a way of ensuring food security by offering farmers more plant varieties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indigenous seeds are believed to be drought resistant and adaptable to the climate conditions of their native areas, and hence often outperform hybrid seeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kenya has a national seed bank based near the capital Nairobi where indigenous seeds are stored in cold rooms, but farmers say community seed banks are equally important for variety and proximity to the farmer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The country has faced challenges in the seed sector where counterfeit seeds were sold to farmers, leading to losses amounting to millions of shillings in a country that relies on rain-fed agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46158578</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 09:09:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sugars, Gum, Stardust Found in NASA's Asteroid Bennu Samples</title><link>https://www.nasa.gov/missions/osiris-rex/sugars-gum-stardust-found-in-nasas-asteroid-bennu-samples/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a654d1fe9bb70191"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The asteroid Bennu continues to provide new clues to scientists’ biggest questions about the formation of the early solar system and the origins of life. As part of the ongoing study of pristine samples delivered to Earth by NASA’s OSIRIS-REx (Origins, Spectral Interpretation, Resource Identification, and Security-Regolith Explorer) spacecraft, three new papers published Tuesday by the journals Nature Geosciences and Nature Astronomy present remarkable discoveries: sugars essential for biology, a gum-like substance not seen before in astromaterials, and an unexpectedly high abundance of dust produced by supernova explosions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sugars essential to life&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scientists led by Yoshihiro Furukawa of Tohoku University in Japan found sugars essential for biology on Earth in the Bennu samples, detailing their findings in the journal Nature Geoscience. The five-carbon sugar ribose and, for the first time in an extraterrestrial sample, six-carbon glucose were found. Although these sugars are not evidence of life, their detection, along with previous detections of amino acids, nucleobases, and carboxylic acids in Bennu samples, show building blocks of biological molecules were widespread throughout the solar system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For life on Earth, the sugars deoxyribose and ribose are key building blocks of DNA and RNA, respectively. DNA is the primary carrier of genetic information in cells. RNA performs numerous functions, and life as we know it could not exist without it. Ribose in RNA is used in the molecule’s sugar-phosphate “backbone” that connects a string of information-carrying nucleobases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“All five nucleobases used to construct both DNA and RNA, along with phosphates, have already been found in the Bennu samples brought to Earth by OSIRIS-REx,” said Furukawa. “The new discovery of ribose means that all of the components to form the molecule RNA are present in Bennu.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The discovery of ribose in asteroid samples is not a complete surprise. Ribose has previously been found in two meteorites recovered on Earth. What is important about the Bennu samples is that researchers did not find deoxyribose. If Bennu is any indication, this means ribose may have been more common than deoxyribose in environments of the early solar system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers think the presence of ribose and lack of deoxyribose supports the “RNA world” hypothesis, where the first forms of life relied on RNA as the primary molecule to store information and to drive chemical reactions necessary for survival.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Present day life is based on a complex system organized primarily by three types of functional biopolymers: DNA, RNA, and proteins,” explains Furukawa. “However, early life may have been simpler. RNA is the leading candidate for the first functional biopolymer because it can store genetic information and catalyze many biological reactions.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Bennu samples also contained one of the most common forms of “food” (or energy) used by life on Earth, the sugar glucose, which is the first evidence that an important energy source for life as we know it was also present in the early solar system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mysterious, ancient ‘gum’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A second paper, in the journal Nature Astronomy led by Scott Sandford at NASA’s Ames Research Center in California’s Silicon Valley and Zack Gainsforth of the University of California, Berkeley, reveals a gum-like material in the Bennu samples never seen before in space rocks – something that could have helped set the stage on Earth for the ingredients of life to emerge. The surprising substance was likely formed in the early days of the solar system, as Bennu’s young parent asteroid warmed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once soft and flexible, but since hardened, this ancient “space gum” consists of polymer-like materials extremely rich in nitrogen and oxygen. Such complex molecules could have provided some of the chemical precursors that helped trigger life on Earth, and finding them in the pristine samples from Bennu is important for scientists studying how life began and whether it exists beyond our planet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;On this primitive asteroid that formed in the early days of the solar system, we’re looking at events near the beginning of the beginning.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scott SandFord&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Astrophysicist, NASA's Ames Research Center&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bennu’s ancestral asteroid formed from materials in the solar nebula – the rotating cloud of gas and dust that gave rise to the solar system – and contained a variety of minerals and ices. As the asteroid began to warm, due to natural radiation, a compound called carbamate formed through a process involving ammonia and carbon dioxide. Carbamate is water soluble, but it survived long enough to polymerize, reacting with itself and other molecules to form larger and more complex chains impervious to water. This suggests that it formed before the parent body warmed enough to become a watery environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“With this strange substance, we’re looking at, quite possibly, one of the earliest alterations of materials that occurred in this rock,” said Sandford. “On this primitive asteroid that formed in the early days of the solar system, we’re looking at events near the beginning of the beginning.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using an infrared microscope, Sandford’s team selected unusual, carbon-rich grains containing abundant nitrogen and oxygen. They then began what Sandford calls “blacksmithing at the molecular level,” using the Molecular Foundry at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (Berkeley Lab) in Berkeley, California. Applying ultra-thin layers of platinum, they reinforced a particle, welded on a tungsten needle to lift the tiny grain, and shaved the fragment down using a focused beam of charged particles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the particle was a thousand times thinner than a human hair, they analyzed its composition via electron microscopy at the Molecular Foundry and X-ray spectroscopy at Berkeley Lab’s Advanced Light Source. The ALS’s high spatial resolution and sensitive X-ray beams enabled unprecedented chemical analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We knew we had something remarkable the instant the images started to appear on the monitor,” said Gainsforth. “It was like nothing we had ever seen, and for months we were consumed by data and theories as we attempted to understand just what it was and how it could have come into existence.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The team conducted a slew of experiments to examine the material’s characteristics. As the details emerged, the evidence suggested the strange substance had been deposited in layers on grains of ice and minerals present in the asteroid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was also flexible – a pliable material, similar to used gum or even a soft plastic. Indeed, during their work with the samples, researchers noticed the strange material was bendy and dimpled when pressure was applied. The stuff was translucent, and exposure to radiation made it brittle, like a lawn chair left too many seasons in the sun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Looking at its chemical makeup, we see the same kinds of chemical groups that occur in polyurethane on Earth,” said Sandford, “making this material from Bennu something akin to a ‘space plastic.’”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ancient asteroid stuff isn’t simply polyurethane, though, which is an orderly polymer. This one has more “random, hodgepodge connections and a composition of elements that differs from particle to particle,” said Sandford. But the comparison underscores the surprising nature of the organic material discovered in NASA’s asteroid samples, and the research team aims to study more of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By pursuing clues about what went on long ago, deep inside an asteroid, scientists can better understand the young solar system – revealing the precursors to and ingredients of life it already contained, and how far those raw materials may have been scattered, thanks to asteroids much like Bennu.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Abundant supernova dust&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another paper in the journal Nature Astronomy, led by Ann Nguyen of NASA’s Johnson Space Center in Houston, analyzed presolar grains – dust from stars predating our solar system – found in two different rock types in the Bennu samples to learn more about where its parent body formed and how it was altered by geologic processes. It is believed that presolar dust was generally well-mixed as our solar system formed. The samples had six-times the amount of supernova dust than any other studied astromaterial, suggesting the asteroid’s parent body formed in a region of the protoplanetary disk enriched in the dust of dying stars.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study also reveals that, while Bennu’s parent asteroid experienced extensive alteration by fluids, there are still pockets of less-altered materials within the samples that offer insights into its origin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“These fragments retain a higher abundance of organic matter and presolar silicate grains, which are known to be easily destroyed by aqueous alteration in asteroids,” said Nguyen. “Their preservation in the Bennu samples was a surprise and illustrates that some material escaped alteration in the parent body. Our study reveals the diversity of presolar materials that the parent accreted as it was forming.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA’s Goddard Space Flight Center provided overall mission management, systems engineering, and the safety and mission assurance for OSIRIS-REx. Dante Lauretta of the University of Arizona, Tucson, is the principal investigator. The university leads the science team and the mission’s science observation planning and data processing. Lockheed Martin Space in Littleton, Colorado, built the spacecraft and provided flight operations. Goddard and KinetX Aerospace were responsible for navigating the OSIRIS-REx spacecraft. Curation for OSIRIS-REx takes place at NASA’s Johnson Space Center in Houston. International partnerships on this mission include the OSIRIS-REx Laser Altimeter instrument from CSA (Canadian Space Agency) and asteroid sample science collaboration with JAXA’s (Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency’s) Hayabusa2 mission. OSIRIS-REx is the third mission in NASA’s New Frontiers Program, managed by NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, Alabama, for the agency’s Science Mission Directorate in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information on the OSIRIS-REx mission, visit:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.nasa.gov/osiris-rex&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Karen Fox / Molly Wasser&lt;lb/&gt;Headquarters, Washington&lt;lb/&gt;202-285-5155 / 240-419-1732&lt;lb/&gt;karen.c.fox@nasa.gov / molly.l.wasser@nasa.gov&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46160239</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 12:12:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netflix to Acquire Warner Bros</title><link>https://about.netflix.com/en/news/netflix-to-acquire-warner-bros</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7a920551567ba73c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Business&lt;/p&gt;05 December 2025&lt;p&gt;Transaction Unites Warner Bros.’ Iconic Franchises and Storied Libraries with Netflix’s Leading Entertainment Service, Creating an Extraordinary Offering for Consumers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netflix to Maintain Warner Bros.’ Current Operations&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Combination Will Offer More Choice and Greater Value for Consumers, Create More Opportunities for the Creative Community and Generate Shareholder Value&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acquisition Will Strengthen the Entertainment Industry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;HOLLYWOOD, Calif., Dec. 5, 2025 -- Today, Netflix, Inc. (the Company) and Warner Bros. Discovery, Inc. (WBD) announced they have entered into a definitive agreement under which Netflix will acquire Warner Bros., including its film and television studios, HBO Max and HBO.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cash and stock transaction is valued at $27.75 per WBD share (subject to a collar as detailed below), with a total enterprise value of approximately $82.7 billion (equity value of $72.0 billion). The transaction is expected to close after the previously announced separation of WBD’s Global Networks division, Discovery Global, into a new publicly-traded company, which is now expected to be completed in Q3 2026.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This acquisition brings together two pioneering entertainment businesses, combining Netflix’s innovation, global reach and best-in-class streaming service with Warner Bros.’ century-long legacy of world-class storytelling. Beloved franchises, shows and movies such as The Big Bang Theory, The Sopranos, Game of Thrones, The Wizard of Oz and the DC Universe will join Netflix’s extensive portfolio including Wednesday, Money Heist, Bridgerton, Adolescence and Extraction, creating an extraordinary entertainment offering for audiences worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Our mission has always been to entertain the world,” said Ted Sarandos, co-CEO of Netflix. “By combining Warner Bros.’ incredible library of shows and movies—from timeless classics like Casablanca and Citizen Kane to modern favorites like Harry Potter and Friends—with our culture-defining titles like Stranger Things, KPop Demon Hunters and Squid Game, we'll be able to do that even better. Together, we can give audiences more of what they love and help define the next century of storytelling.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“This acquisition will improve our offering and accelerate our business for decades to come,” continued Greg Peters, co-CEO of Netflix. “Warner Bros. has helped define entertainment for more than a century and continues to do so with phenomenal creative executives and production capabilities. With our global reach and proven business model, we can introduce a broader audience to the worlds they create—giving our members more options, attracting more fans to our best-in-class streaming service, strengthening the entire entertainment industry and creating more value for shareholders.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Today’s announcement combines two of the greatest storytelling companies in the world to bring to even more people the entertainment they love to watch the most,” said David Zaslav, President and CEO of Warner Bros. Discovery. “For more than a century, Warner Bros. has thrilled audiences, captured the world’s attention, and shaped our culture. By coming together with Netflix, we will ensure people everywhere will continue to enjoy the world’s most resonant stories for generations to come.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Combination Will Offer More Choice, More Opportunities, More Value&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Complementary strengths and assets: Warner Bros.’ studios are world-class, with Warner Bros. recognized as a leading supplier of television titles and filmed entertainment. HBO and HBO Max also provide a compelling, complementary offering for consumers. Netflix expects to maintain Warner Bros.’ current operations and build on its strengths, including theatrical releases for films.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;More choice and greater value for consumers: By adding the deep film and TV libraries and HBO and HBO Max programming, Netflix members will have even more high-quality titles from which to choose. This also allows Netflix to optimize its plans for consumers, enhancing viewing options and expanding access to content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;A stronger entertainment industry: This acquisition will enhance Netflix’s studio capabilities, allowing the Company to significantly expand U.S. production capacity and continue to grow investment in original content over the long term which will create jobs and strengthen the entertainment industry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;More opportunities for the creative community: By uniting Netflix’s member experience and global reach with Warner Bros.’ renowned franchises and extensive library, the Company will create greater value for talent—offering more opportunities to work with beloved intellectual property, tell new stories and connect with a wider audience than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;More value for shareholders: By offering members a wider selection of quality series and films, Netflix expects to attract and retain more members, drive more engagement and generate incremental revenue and operating income. The Company also expects to realize at least $2-3 billion of cost savings per year by the third year and expects the transaction to be accretive to GAAP earnings per share by year two.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transaction Details and Timing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the terms of the agreement, each WBD shareholder will receive $23.25 in cash and $4.501 in shares of Netflix common stock for each share of WBD common stock outstanding at the closing of the transaction. The transaction values Warner Bros. Discovery at $27.75 per share, implying a total equity value of approximately $72.0 billion and an enterprise value of approximately $82.7 billion&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In June 2025, WBD announced plans to separate its Streaming &amp;amp; Studios and Global Networks divisions into two separate publicly traded companies. This separation is now expected to be completed in Q3 2026, prior to the closing of this transaction. The newly separated publicly traded company holding the Global Networks division, Discovery Global, will include premier entertainment, sports and news television brands around the world including CNN, TNT Sports in the U.S., and Discovery, free-to-air channels across Europe, and digital products such as Discovery+ and Bleacher Report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The stock component is subject to a collar under which WBD shareholders will receive Netflix stock valued at $4.50 per share, provided the 15-day volume weighted average price (“VWAP”) of Netflix stock price (measured three trading days prior to closing) falls between $97.91 and $119.67. If the VWAP is below $97.91, WBD shareholders will receive 0.0460 Netflix shares for each WBD share. If the VWAP is above $119.67, WBD shareholders will receive 0.0376 Netflix shares for each WBD share.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transaction was unanimously approved by the Boards of Directors of both Netflix and WBD. In addition to the completion of the separation of Discovery Global (WBD’s Global Networks business), completion of the transaction is subject to required regulatory approvals, approval of WBD shareholders and other customary closing conditions. The transaction is expected to close in 12-18 months.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moelis &amp;amp; Company LLC is acting as Netflix’s financial advisor and Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp;amp; Flom LLP is serving as legal counsel. Wells Fargo is acting as an additional financial advisor and, along with BNP and HSBC, is providing committed debt financing related to the transaction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allen &amp;amp; Company, J.P. Morgan and Evercore are serving as financial advisors to Warner Bros. Discovery and Wachtell Lipton, Rosen &amp;amp; Katz and Debevoise &amp;amp; Plimpton LLP are serving as legal counsel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1 Reflects a 10% symmetrical collar.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Webcast&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netflix will conduct a conference call today at 5:00am PT/8:00am ET to discuss the contents of this release. A link to the live webcast of the conference call will be available at https://ir.netflix.net/.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contacts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netflix&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lowell Singer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;VP, Investor Relations&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(818) 434-2141&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emily Feingold&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;VP, Communications&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(323) 287-0756&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Warner Bros. Discovery&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Andrew Slabin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Investor Relations&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(212) 548-5544&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;andrew.slabin@wbd.com&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peter Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Investor Relations&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(212) 548-5907&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;peter.lee@wbd.com&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Robert Gibbs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Contact&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(347) 268-3017&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IMPORTANT INFORMATION AND WHERE TO FIND IT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In connection with the proposed transaction (the “Merger”) between Netflix, Inc. (“Netflix”) and Warner Bros. Discovery, Inc. (“WBD”), Netflix intends to file with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission (the “SEC”) a registration statement on Form S-4 (the “Registration Statement”), which will include a prospectus with respect to the shares of Netflix’s common stock to be issued in the Merger and a proxy statement for WBD’s stockholders (the “Proxy Statement/Prospectus”), and WBD intends to file with the SEC the proxy statement. The definitive proxy statement (if and when available) will be mailed to stockholders of WBD. WBD also intends to file a registration statement for a newly formed subsidiary (“Discovery Global”), which is contemplated to own certain assets and businesses of WBD not being acquired by Netflix in connection with the Merger. Each of Netflix and WBD may also file with or furnish to the SEC other relevant documents regarding the Merger. This communication is not a substitute for the Registration Statement, the Proxy Statement/Prospectus or any other document that Netflix or WBD may file with the SEC or mail to WBD’s stockholders in connection with the Merger.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;INVESTORS AND SECURITY HOLDERS OF NETFLIX AND WBD ARE URGED TO READ THE REGISTRATION STATEMENT AND THE PROXY STATEMENT/PROSPECTUS INCLUDED WITHIN THE REGISTRATION STATEMENT WHEN THEY BECOME AVAILABLE, AS WELL AS ANY OTHER RELEVANT DOCUMENTS FILED WITH THE SEC IN CONNECTION WITH THE MERGER OR INCORPORATED BY REFERENCE INTO THE REGISTRATION STATEMENT AND THE PROXY STATEMENT/PROSPECTUS (INCLUDING ANY AMENDMENTS OR SUPPLEMENTS THERETO), BECAUSE THEY WILL CONTAIN IMPORTANT INFORMATION REGARDING NETFLIX, WBD, THE MERGER AND RELATED MATTERS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The documents filed by Netflix with the SEC also may be obtained free of charge at Netflix’s website at https://ir.netflix.net/home/default.aspx. The documents filed by WBD with the SEC also may be obtained free of charge at WBD’s website at https://ir.wbd.com.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PARTICIPANTS IN THE SOLICITATION&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netflix, WBD and certain of their respective directors and executive officers may be deemed to be participants in the solicitation of proxies from the stockholders of WBD in connection with the Merger under the rules of the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information about the interests of the directors and executive officers of Netflix and WBD and other persons who may be deemed to be participants in the solicitation of stockholders of WBD in connection with the Merger and a description of their direct and indirect interests, by security holdings or otherwise, will be included in the Proxy Statement/Prospectus, which will be filed with the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information about WBD’s directors and executive officers is set forth in WBD’s proxy statement for its 2025 Annual Meeting of Stockholders on Schedule 14A filed with the SEC on April 23, 2025, WBD’s Annual Report on Form 10-K for the year ended December 31, 2024, and any subsequent filings with the SEC. Information about Netflix’s directors and executive officers is set forth in Netflix’s proxy statement for its 2025 Annual Meeting of Stockholders on Schedule 14A filed with the SEC on April 17, 2025, and any subsequent filings with the SEC. Additional information regarding the direct and indirect interests of those persons and other persons who may be deemed participants in the Merger may be obtained by reading the Proxy Statement/Prospectus regarding the Merger when it becomes available. Free copies of these documents may be obtained as described above.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NO OFFER OR SOLICITATION&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This communication is for informational purposes only and does not constitute, or form a part of, an offer to sell or the solicitation of an offer to buy any securities or a solicitation of any vote or approval, nor shall there be any sale of securities in any jurisdiction in which such offer, solicitation or sale would be unlawful prior to registration or qualification under the securities laws of any such jurisdiction. No offer of securities shall be made except by means of a prospectus meeting the requirements of Section 10 of the Securities Act of 1933, as amended, and otherwise in accordance with applicable law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAUTIONARY NOTE REGARDING FORWARD LOOKING STATEMENTS&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This document contains “forward-looking statements” within the meaning of the federal securities laws, including Section 27A of the U.S. Securities Act of 1933, as amended, and Section 21E of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, as amended. These forward-looking statements are based on Netflix’s and WBD’s current expectations, estimates and projections about the expected date of closing of the Merger and the potential benefits thereof, their respective businesses and industries, management’s beliefs and certain assumptions made by Netflix and WBD, all of which are subject to change. All forward-looking statements by their nature address matters that involve risks and uncertainties, many of which are beyond our control and are not guarantees of future results, such as statements about the consummation of the Merger and the anticipated benefits thereof. These and other forward-looking statements, including the failure to consummate the Merger or to make or take any filing or other action required to consummate the transaction on a timely matter or at all, are not guarantees of future results and are subject to risks, uncertainties and assumptions that could cause actual results to differ materially from those expressed in any forward-looking statements. Accordingly, there are or will be important factors that could cause actual results to differ materially from those indicated in such statements and, therefore, you should not place undue reliance on any such statements and caution must be exercised in relying on forward-looking statements. Important risk factors that may cause such a difference include, but are not limited to: (i) the completion of the Merger on anticipated terms and timing, including obtaining stockholder and regulatory approvals, completing the separation of WBD’s Global Networks business and Streaming and Studios business, anticipated tax treatment, unforeseen liabilities, future capital expenditures, revenues, expenses, earnings, synergies, economic performance, indebtedness, financial condition, losses, future prospects, business and management strategies, expansion and growth of WBD’s and Netflix’s businesses and other conditions to the completion of the Merger; (ii) failure to realize the anticipated benefits of the Merger, including as a result of delay in completing the transaction or integrating the businesses of Netflix and WBD; (iii) Netflix’s and WBD’s ability to implement their business strategies; (iv) consumer viewing trends; (v) potential litigation relating to the Merger that could be instituted against Netflix, WBD or their respective directors; (vi) the risk that disruptions from the Merger will harm Netflix’s or WBD’s business, including current plans and operations; (vii) the ability of Netflix or WBD to retain and hire key personnel; (viii) potential adverse reactions or changes to business relationships resulting from the announcement, pendency or completion of the Merger; (ix) uncertainty as to the long-term value of Netflix’s common stock; (x) legislative, regulatory and economic developments affecting Netflix’s and WBD’s businesses; (xi) general economic and market developments and conditions; (xii) the evolving legal, regulatory and tax regimes under which Netflix and WBD operate; (xiii) potential business uncertainty, including changes to existing business relationships, during the pendency of the Merger that could affect Netflix’s or WBD’s financial performance; (xiv) restrictions during the pendency of the Merger that may impact Netflix’s or WBD’s ability to pursue certain business opportunities or strategic transactions; and (xv) failure to receive the approval of the stockholders of WBD. These risks, as well as other risks associated with the Merger, will be more fully discussed in the Registration Statement and Proxy Statement/Prospectus to be filed with the SEC in connection with the Merger and the registration statement to be filed with the SEC in connection with the separation. While the list of factors presented here is, and the list of factors presented in the Registration Statement and Proxy Statement/Prospectus will be, considered representative, no such list should be considered to be a complete statement of all potential risks and uncertainties. Unlisted factors may present significant additional obstacles to the realization of forward-looking statements. Consequences of material differences in results as compared with those anticipated in the forward-looking statements could include, among other things, business disruption, operational problems, financial loss, legal liability to third parties and similar risks, any of which could have a material adverse effect on Netflix’s or WBD’s consolidated financial condition, results of operations or liquidity. The forward-looking statements included in this communication are made only as of the date hereof. Neither Netflix nor WBD assumes any obligation to publicly provide revisions or updates to any forward-looking statements, whether as a result of new information, future developments or otherwise, should circumstances change, except as otherwise required by securities and other applicable laws.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46160315</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 12:21:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Making RSS More Fun</title><link>https://matduggan.com/making-rss-more-fun/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2b4893113586319f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't like RSS readers. I know, this is blasphemous especially on a website where I'm actively encouraging you to subscribe through RSS. As someone writing stuff, RSS is great for me. I don't have to think about it, the requests are pretty light weight, I don't need to think about your personal data or what client you are using. So as a protocol RSS is great, no notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However as something I'm going to consume, it's frankly a giant chore. I feel pressured by RSS readers, where there is this endlessly growing backlog of things I haven't read. I rarely want to read all of a websites content from beginning to end, instead I like to jump between them. I also don't really care if the content is chronological, like an old post about something interesting isn't less compelling to me than a newer post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I want, as a user experience, is something akin to TikTok. The whole appeal of TikTok, for those who haven't wasted hours of their lives on it, is that I get served content based on an algorithm that determines what I might think is useful or fun. However what I would like is to go through content from random small websites. I want to sit somewhere and passively consume random small creators content, then upvote some of that content and the service should show that more often to other users. That's it. No advertising, no collecting tons of user data about me, just a very simple "I have 15 minutes to kill before the next meeting, show me some random stuff."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case the "algorithm" is pretty simple: if more people like a thing, more people see it. But with Google on its way to replacing search results with LLM generated content, I just wanted to have something that let me play around with the small web the way that I used to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There actually used to be a service like this called StumbleUpon which was more focused on pushing users towards popular sites. It has been taken down, presumably because there was no money in a browser plugin that sent users to other websites whose advertising you didn't control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;TL;DR&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can go download the Firefox extension now and try this out and skip the rest of this if you want. https://timewasterpro.xyz/ If you hate it or find problems, let me know on Mastodon. https://c.im/@matdevdug&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Functionality&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I wanted to do something pretty basic. You hit a button, get served a new website. If you like the website, upvote it, otherwise downvote it. If you think it has objectionable content then hit report. You have to make an account (because I couldn't think of another way to do it) and then if you submit links and other people like it, you climb a Leaderboard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the backend I want to (very slowly so I don't cost anyone a bunch of money) crawl a bunch of RSS feeds, stick the pages in a database and then serve them up to users. Then I want to track what sites get upvotes and return those more often to other users so that "high quality" content shows up more often. "High quality" would be defined by the community or just me if I'm the only user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's pretty basic stuff, most of it copied from tutorials scattered around the Internet. However I really want to drive home to users that this is not a Serious Thing. I'm not a company, this isn't a new social media network, there are no plans to "grow" this concept beyond the original idea unless people smarter than me ping with me ideas. So I found this amazing CSS library: https://sakofchit.github.io/system.css/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Apple's System OS design from the late-80s to the early 90s was one of my personal favorites and I think would send a strong signal to a user that this is not a professional, modern service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Great, the basic layout works. Let's move on!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Backend&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I ended up doing FastAPI because it's very easy to write. I didn't want to spend a ton of time writing the API because I doubt I nailed the API design on the first round. I use sqlalchemy for the database. The basic API layout is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;admin - mostly just generating read-only reports of like "how many websites are there"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;leaderboard - So this is my first attempt at trying to get users involved. Submit a website that other people like? Get points, climb leaderboard.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The source for the RSS feeds came from the (very cool) Kagi small web Github. https://github.com/kagisearch/smallweb. Basically I assume that websites that have submitted their RSS feeds here are cool with me (very rarely) checking for new posts and adding them to my database. If you want the same thing as this does, but as an iFrame, that's the Kagi small web service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scraping work is straightforward. We make a background worker, they grab 5 feeds every 600 seconds, they check for new content on each feed and then wait until the 600 seconds has elapsed to grab 5 more from the smallweb list of RSS feeds. Since we have a lot of feeds, this ends up look like we're checking for new content less than once a day which is the interval that I want.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then we write it out to a sqlite database and basically track "has this URL been reported", if so, put it into a review queue and then how many times this URL has been liked or disliked. I considered a "real" database but honestly sqlite is getting more and more scalable every day and its impossible to beat the immediate start up and functionality. Plus very easy to back up to encrypted object storage which is super nice for a hobby project where you might wipe the prod database at any moment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In terms of user onboarding I ended up doing the "make an account with an email, I send a link to verify the email". I actually hate this flow and I don't really want to know a users email. I never need to contact you and there's not a lot associated with your account, which makes this especially silly. I have a ton of email addresses and no real "purpose" in having them. I'd switch to Login with Apple, which is great from a security perspective but not everybody has an Apple ID.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also did a passkey version, which worked fine but the OSS passkey handling was pretty rough still and most people seem to be using a commercial service that handled the "do you have the passkey? Great, if not, fall back to email" flow. I don't really want to do a big commercial login service for a hobby application.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Auth is a JWT, which actually was a pain and I regret doing it. I don't know why I keep reaching for JWTs, they're a bad user experience and I should stop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Can I just have the source code?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm more than happy to release the source code once I feel like the product is in a somewhat stable shape. I'm still ripping down and rewriting relatively large chunks of it as I find weird behavior I don't like or just decide to do things a different way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the end it does seem to do whats on the label. We have over 600,000 individual pages indexed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;So how is it to use?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Honestly I've been pretty pleased. But there are some problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First I couldn't find a reliable way of switching the keyboard shortcuts to be Mac/Windows specific. I found some options for querying platform but they didn't seem to work, so I ended up just hardcoding them as Alt which is not great.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other issue is that when you are making an extension, you spend a long time working with these manifests.json. The specific part I really wasn't sure about was:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;"browser_specific_settings": {
    "gecko": {
      "id": "[email protected]",
      "strict_min_version": "80.0",
      "data_collection_permissions": {
        "required": ["authenticationInfo"]
      }
    }
  }&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm not entirely sure if that's all I'm doing? I think so from reading the docs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway I built this mostly for me. I have no idea if anybody else will enjoy it. But if you are bored I encourage you to give it a try. It should be pretty light weight and straight-forward if you crack open the extension and look at it. I'm not loading any analytics into the extension so basically until people complain about it, I don't really know if its going well or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Future stuff&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I need to sort stuff into categories so that you get more stuff in genres you like. I don't 100% know how to do that, maybe there is a way to scan a website to determine the "types" of content that is on there with machine learning? I'm still looking into it.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There's a lot of junk in there. I think if we reach a certain number of downvotes I might put it into a special "queue".&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I want to ensure new users see the "best stuff" early on but there isn't enough data to determine "best vs worst".&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I wish there were more independent photography and science websites. Also more crafts. That's not really a "future thing", just me putting a hope out into the universe. Non-technical beta testers get overwhelmed by technical content.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46160698</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 13:00:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Most technical problems are people problems</title><link>https://blog.joeschrag.com/2023/11/most-technical-problems-are-really.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2ed1d053672c65da"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I once worked at a company which had an enormous amount of technical debt - millions of lines of code, no unit tests, based on frameworks that were well over a decade out of date. On one specific project, we had a market need to get some Windows-only modules running on Linux, and rather than cross-compiling, another team had simply copied &amp;amp; pasted a few hundred thousand lines of code, swapping Windows-specific components for Linux-specific.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the non-technical reader, this is an enormous problem because now two versions of the code exist. So, all features &amp;amp; bug fixes must be solved in two separate codebases that will grow apart over time. When I heard about this, a young &amp;amp; naive version of me set out to fix the situation....&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;People Problems&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tech debt projects are always a hard sell to management, because even if everything goes flawlessly, the code just does roughly what it did before. This project was no exception, and the optics weren't great. I did as many engineers do and "ignored the politics", put my head down, and got it done. But, the project went long, and I lost a lot of clout in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I realized I was essentially trying to solve a people problem with a technical solution. Most of the developers at this company were happy doing the same thing today that they did yesterday...and five years ago. As Andrew Harmel-Law points out, code tends to follow the personalities of the people that wrote it. The code was calcified because the developers were also. Personality types who dislike change tend not to design their code with future change in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most technical problems are really people problems. Think about it. Why does technical debt exist? Because requirements weren't properly clarified before work began. Because a salesperson promised an unrealistic deadline to a customer. Because a developer chose an outdated technology because it was comfortable. Because management was too reactive and cancelled a project mid-flight. Because someone's ego wouldn't let them see a better way of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core issue with the project was that admitting the need for refactoring was also to admit that the way the company was building software was broken and that individual skillsets were sorely out of date. My small team was trying to fix one module of many, while other developers were writing code as they had been for decades. I had one developer openly tell me, "I don't want to learn anything new." I realized that you'll never clean up tech debt faster than others create it. It is like triage in an emergency room, you must stop the bleeding first, then you can fix whatever is broken.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;An Ideal World&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The project also disabused me of the engineer's ideal of a world in which engineering problems can be solved in a vacuum - staying out of "politics" and letting the work speak for itself - a world where deadlines don't exist...and let's be honest, neither do customers. This ideal world rarely exists. The vast majority of projects have non-technical stakeholders, and telling them "just trust me; we're working on it" doesn't cut it. I realized that the perception that your team is getting a lot done is just as important as getting a lot done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Non-technical people do not intuitively understand the level of effort required or the need for tech debt cleanup; it must be communicated effectively by engineering - in both initial estimates &amp;amp; project updates. Unless leadership has an engineering background, the value of the technical debt work likely needs to be quantified and shown as business value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Heads Up&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps these are the lessons that prep one for more senior positions. In my opinion, anyone above senior engineer level needs to know how to collaborate cross-functionally, regardless of whether they choose a technical or management track. Schools teach Computer Science, not navigating personalities, egos, and personal blindspots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have worked with some incredible engineers, better than myself - the type that have deep technical knowledge on just about any technology you bring up. When I was younger, I wanted to be that engineer - the "engineer's engineer". But I realize now, that is not my personality. I'm too ADD for that. :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For all of their (considerable) strengths, more often than not, those engineers shy away from the interpersonal. The tragedy is that they are incredibly productive ICs, but may fail with bigger initiatives because they are only one person - a single processor core can only go so fast. Perhaps equally valuable is the "heads up coder" - the person who is deeply technical, but also able to pick their head up &amp;amp; see project risks coming (technical &amp;amp; otherwise) and steer the team around them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46160773</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 13:07:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Pbnj – A minimal, self-hosted pastebin you can deploy in 60 seconds</title><link>https://pbnj.sh/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="aa4b2d5ddfbc6a08"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# API Reference

## Authentication

All write operations require a Bearer token:
```
Authorization: Bearer YOUR_AUTH_KEY
```

## Endpoints

### Create Paste

POST /api

#### JSON Request
```bash
curl &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 05_api.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 10 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# CLI Reference

## Installation

```bash
npm install -g @pbnjs/cli
```

## Configuration

Run the setup wizard:
```bash
pbnj --init
```

This creates ~/.pbnj with your configuration:
```
PBNJ_HOST=ht&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 04_cli.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 10 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Cost Breakdown

"This is deployed on Cloudflare, they might charge us eventually!"

Don't worry. Let's do the math.

## Cloudflare D1 Free Tier

- 500 MB storage
- 5 million reads/day
- 100,000 writ&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 03_cost.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 10 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Deployment Guide

## One-Click Deploy (Recommended)

Click the "Deploy to Cloudflare" button on the GitHub repo â that's it!

The deploy button automatically:
- Forks the repo to your GitHub account&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 02_deployment.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 10 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Welcome to pbnj

pbnj is a simple, minimal self-hosted pastebin solution.

## What is pbnj?

pbnj lets you share code snippets and text files with a simple URL.
No accounts, no bloat - just paste an&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 01_welcome.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 10 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Web Interface

pbnj includes a web interface for creating and managing pastes directly from your browser.

## Authentication

The web interface uses the same `AUTH_KEY` as the CLI and API. Authentic&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 07_web_interface.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 10 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Configuration

pbnj is configured through a single `pbnj.config.js` file in the project root.

## Default Configuration

```js
export default {
  name: 'pbnj',
  logo: '/logo.png',
  idStyle: 'sandw&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 06_configuration.md &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 10 hours ago &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46160824</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 13:13:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Influential study on glyphosate safety retracted 25 years after publication</title><link>https://www.lemonde.fr/en/environment/article/2025/12/03/influential-study-on-glyphosate-safety-retracted-25-years-after-publication_6748114_114.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="364059ff18954fcc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A quarter-century after its publication, one of the most influential research articles on the potential carcinogenicity of glyphosate has been retracted for "several critical issues that are considered to undermine the academic integrity of this article and its conclusions." In a retraction notice dated Friday, November 28, the journal Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology announced that the study, published in April 2000 and concluding the herbicide was safe, has been removed from its archives. The disavowal comes 25 years after publication and eight years after thousands of internal Monsanto documents were made public during US court proceedings (the "Monsanto Papers"), revealing that the actual authors of the article were not the listed scientists – Gary M. Williams (New York Medical College), Robert Kroes (Ritox, Utrecht University, Netherlands), and Ian C. Munro (Intertek Cantox, Canada) – but rather Monsanto employees.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Known as "ghostwriting," this practice is considered a form of scientific fraud. It involves companies paying researchers to sign their names to research articles they did not write. The motivation is clear: When a study supports the safety of a pesticide or drug, it appears far more credible if not authored by scientists employed by the company marketing the product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have 73.89% of this article left to read. The rest is for subscribers only.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46161125</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 13:39:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Emerge Career (YC S22) Is Hiring</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/emerge-career/jobs/qQhLEmC-founding-design-engineer</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d98101009444eae"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Who We Are:&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Emerge Career’s mission is to break the cycle of poverty and incarceration. We’re not just building software; we’re creating pathways to real second chances. Through an all-in-one platform deeply embedded within the criminal justice system, we recruit, train, and place justice-impacted individuals into life-changing careers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our vision is to become the country’s unified workforce development system, replacing disconnected brick-and-mortar job centers with one integrated, tech-powered solution that meets low-income individuals exactly where they are. Today, the federal government spends billions annually on education and training programs, yet only about 70% of participants graduate, just 38.6% secure training-related employment, and average first-year earnings hover around $34,708.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;By contrast, our seven-person team has already outperformed the job centers in two entire states (Vermont and South Dakota) in just the past year. With an 89% graduation rate and 92% of graduates securing training-related employment, our alumni aren’t just getting jobs—they’re launching new lives with average first-year earnings of $77,352. The results speak for themselves, and we’re just getting started.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Before Emerge, our founders Zo and Gabe co-founded Ameelio, an award-winning tech nonprofit that is dismantling the prison communication duopoly. Backed by tech luminaries like Reid Hoffman, Vinod Khosla, and Jack Dorsey, and by major criminal-justice philanthropies such as Arnold Ventures and the Mellon Foundation, Ameelio became a recognized leader in the space. Because of this experience both Zo and Gabe understood what it took to create change from within the system. After serving over 1M people impacted by incarceration, they witnessed firsthand the gap in second-chance opportunities and the chronic unemployment plaguing those impacted by the justice system. Emerge Career is committed to solving this issue.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our students are at the heart of our work. Their journeys have captured national attention on CBS, NBC, and in The Boston Globe, and our programs now serve entire states and cities. And we’re not doing it alone: our vision has attracted support from Alexis Ohanian (776), Michael Seibel, Y Combinator, the Opportunity Fund, and public figures like Diana Taurasi, Deandre Ayton, and Marshawn Lynch. All of us believe that, with the right mix of technology and hands-on practice, we can redefine workforce development and deliver true second chances at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why We Do This:&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Emerge Career was designed to tackle two systemic issues: recidivism, fueled by post-incarceration unemployment and poverty, and labor shortages in key industries. Over 60% of formerly incarcerated people remain unemployed a year after incarceration, seeking work but not finding it. The reality is shocking, workforce development programs are severely limited inside prison, with only one-third of incarcerated people ever participating. To worsen, the available prison jobs offer meager wages, often less than $1 per hour, and often do not equip individuals with the skills for long-term stable employment.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;About the Role&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We call this a Founding Design Engineer role—even three years in and with multiple contracts under our belt—for two reasons. First, you’ll be our very first engineer, joining our co-founder, who’s built the entire platform solo to date. Second, our growth is now outpacing our systems, and we can’t keep up on maintenance alone. We’re at a critical juncture: we can either hire someone to simply care for what exists, or we can bring on a talent who believes that, with the right blend of technology and hands-on practice, we can unify the workforce-development system and deliver second chances at true scale. We hope that can be you.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is not a traditional engineering job. You’ll do high-impact technical work, but just as often you’ll be on the phone with a student, writing documentation, debugging support issues, or figuring out how to turn a one-off solution into a repeatable system. You’ll ship features, talk to users, and fix what’s broken, whether that’s in the product or in the process. You’ll build things that matter, not just things that are asked for.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This role blends engineering, product, support, and program operations. We’re looking for someone who is energized by ownership, obsessed with user outcomes, and excited to work across domains to make things better. If you’re the kind of person who wants to be hands-on with everything—students, code, strategy, and execution—you’ll thrive here.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Who You Are:&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You love supporting other people’s growth. This role will feel like case work at times, and you’re drawn to that. You’ve dedicated your life volunteering, working in social impact, or finding ways to make the playing field more fair. You find joy in helping others rise. You don’t hesitate to call, text, or meet with a student who needs you. You show up consistently, personally, and with heart.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You believe everyone deserves a second chance. You treat everyone with dignity. You know how to meet people exactly where they are—with empathy and compassion—helping create a space where everyone feels seen and valued, regardless of their background..&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You identify yourself as a cracked engineer. You love finding a way or making one. You take extreme ownership of ideas, driving them to completion even when others need convincing. Every time you hit a wall, you think of three new ways to solve the issue.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You are tech-forward, but not tech-first. You look for ways to automate and scale, but you know not everything should be automated. You believe that with the right builder mindset, one coach can support hundreds of individuals—but you also understand that in a program like ours, many moments require a human touch. You know when to hand it to a system, and when to pick up the phone.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You are entrepreneurial. You’re scrappy, resourceful, autonomous, and low-maintenance. You know process matters—but at this stage, speed and iteration matter more. You’re comfortable building quickly and changing procedures often to get to the right solution. You roll up your sleeves and solve problems. No job is too small.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You play to win. You stay optimistic when things get tough and keep moving when others slow down. You’re not rattled by change or new ideas. You don’t need to agree with everything, but you bring a “yes, and” mindset that helps ideas grow instead of shutting them down.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You work hard. You show up early, stay late, and do what needs to get done—no ego, no excuses. You don’t wait around or ask for permission. This isn’t a 9-to-5. The team puts in 10+ hour days because we care about the mission and each other. If that sounds miserable, this isn’t for you. If it sounds exciting, you’ll fit right in.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You are a straight shooter. You don’t shy away from hard conversations—internally or externally. You bring clarity, care, and accountability to every interaction.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You love learning. You understand that recent advancements in AI have shifted the way we work and what it means to be a high performer. You tinker with new tools. You enjoy being an early adopter. You’re always rethinking and optimizing how you work so you can keep leveling up. Nobody needs to tell you to keep upping your game.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You have an eye for operational detail. This doesn’t mean you’re simply organized. At Emerge, operational excellence isn’t just about efficiency—it’s about protecting the real lives and futures of the people in our programs. You have an almost paranoid attention to detail, because you understand that even small oversights have real, human consequences.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You are a clear writer. This doesn’t mean you need to craft the next great novel, but you must communicate ideas simply and clearly. You value precision, clarity, and brevity. You understand that good writing reduces confusion, accelerates decisions, and ensures everyone stays aligned, especially in high-stakes environments like ours.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You are a strong prompter. You’ve seen firsthand how a few thoughtful prompts can transform messy tasks into scalable, repeatable AI workflows. You love tinkering with prompts, contexts, and configurations to get exactly the right outputs, and you take pride in turning cutting-edge AI into practical processes that anyone can use.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Requirements&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Willing to relocate and work in-person in New York City&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Experience taking a project from 0 to 1. You might have led a project, been a founder previously, built an impressive side project, or been one of the first 10 employees at an early stage startup&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You love working with React and Typescript&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Experience with Figma&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Experience collaborating with operations or support teams&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bonus Points&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Experience in ed-tech&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Experience with UX research&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;What you will be doing&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Coaching students. You’ll support students throughout their training journey—not just by building tools, but by directly engaging with them. This means texting, calling, and helping students one-on-one when needed. At the same time, you’ll take what you learn from those interactions and turn it into scalable systems and smart automations. You’ll be doing both engineering and non-engineering work to make sure students succeed and the product keeps improving.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Talking to students. Good founding engineers read feedback and iterate quickly. Great founding engineers have users they're friendly with, talk with them frequently, bounce ideas off them, and iterate with them when they ship new things.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Doing support. This is an engineering role with key program management responsibilities. You’ll work directly with students every day. That requires patience, empathy, and a willingness to meet people where they are. You’ll help investigate and resolve product issues, and you’ll take ownership of making the product better through what you learn.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Documenting your work and its impact. Our work is complex, spans months, and involves multiple teams. Clear documentation and communication are critical. You’ll be responsible for creating awareness when a change impacts operations, and for helping others understand how features affect different parts of training and service delivery. Precision matters.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Owning products and features end to end. You won’t just take tickets. You’ll originate ideas based on user conversations, your own instincts, and our larger strategy. You’ll test MVPs in production, iterate based on real feedback, and stay accountable to the long-term success of your work. We build in React and TypeScript. If you like shipping for the sake of it, this role isn’t for you. If you like shipping with purpose and ownership, you’ll love it here.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Implementing AI features and operational workflows. This is last for a reason. We don’t jump to automation. We do things manually first to fully understand the problem—then we build. If you care about applying AI meaningfully, not just for hype, this is the right place.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Benefits You’ll Receive: link&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Start Date: ASAP&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46161460</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 14:06:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Covid-19 mRNA Vaccination and 4-Year All-Cause Mortality</title><link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2842305</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46162262</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 15:07:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jolla Phone Pre-Order</title><link>https://commerce.jolla.com/products/jolla-phone-preorder</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f70dc9971d3f3de9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Jolla Phone Pre-order Voucher&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Jolla Phone Pre-order Voucher&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The independent European Do It Together (DIT) Linux phone, shaped by the people who use it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pre-Order Now for 99 €&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Full price: 499 € (incl. your local VAT). Normal price 599 € - 699 €.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Your 99 € is fully refundable and deducted from the full price later.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Markets: EU, UK, Norway and Switzerland&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Estimated delivery: by end of 1H/2026&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;387 sold of 2000&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This product will only be produced if at least 2000 units are supported by January 04, 2026 23:55 (Helsinki)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Calculating time remaining&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By reserving a device, you directly contribute bring the new Jolla Phone into reality. The product will be made once we reach 2,000 pre-orders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project goes ahead when we reach 2,000 pre-orders. If we don’t hit the goal, your payment is refunded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Priority Batch&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fully refundable&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Performance Meets Privacy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;5G with dual nano-SIM&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;12GB RAM and 256GB storage expandable up to 2TB&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sailfish OS 5&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Support for Android apps with Jolla AppSupport&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;User replaceable back cover with colour options&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;User replaceable battery&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Physical Privacy Switch&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Privacy by Design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No tracking, no calling home, no hidden analytics&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;User configurable physical Privacy Switch - turn off you microphone, bluetooth, Android apps, or whatever you wish&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Scandinavian styling in its pure form&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Honouring the original Jolla Phone form factor and design&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Replaceable back cover&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Available in three distinct colours inspired by Nordic nature&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Available in distinct user replaceable colours&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Snow White&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Kaamos Black&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Orange&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;An Independent Linux Phone&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A successor to the iconic original Jolla Phone from 2013, brought to 2026 with modern specs and honoring the Jolla heritage design. And faster, smoother, more capable than the current Jolla C2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A phone you can actually daily-drive. Still Private. Still Yours.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A True Alternative, Not a Fork of Big Tech&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Jolla Phone is not based on Big Tech technology. It is governed by European privacy thinking and a community-led model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Defined together with the Community&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past months, Sailfish OS community members voted on what the next Jolla device should be. The key characteristics, specifications and features of the device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on community voting and real user needs, this device has only one mission:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Put control back in your hands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;KEY BENEFITS OF PRE-ORDERING&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Special Edition Back Cover — Pre-order batch only&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Made as a thank-you to early supporters&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Directly contribute in making the product a reality&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Community Voice, Real Device: The questionnaire received overwhelming flow of input and this project captures that&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Now it is time to act! Your pre-order determines whether the project becomes reality&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Your phone, your apps, your control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run native Sailfish apps, Android apps with AppSupport, or go fully de-Googled whenever you wish – simply by shutting down the Android apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Still a real Linux phone&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not a walled garden. Not a pseudo-Linux. Actual Linux. Actual control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Privacy You Can Trust&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike mainstream phones, Sailfish OS is designed not to harvest your data. No trackers. No profiling. No data monetisation. Your phone should work for you, not exploit you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Built for Longevity&lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sailfish OS is proven to outlive mainstream support cycles. Long-term OS support, guaranteed for minimum 5 years. Incremental updates, and no forced obsolescence.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Your Phone Shouldn’t Spy on You&lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Mainstream phones send vast amounts of background data. A common Android phone sends megabytes of data per day to Google even if the device is not used at all.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sailfish OS stays silent unless you explicitly allow connections.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;This isn’t your regular smartphone project.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a community mission.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You voted on the device&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You guided its specs and definition&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You shaped the philosophy&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;And now you help bring it to life&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every pre-order makes production become a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;TECH SPECS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;SoC: High performant Mediatek 5G platform&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;RAM: 12GB&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Storage: 256GB + expandable with microSDXC&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cellular: 4G + 5G with dual nano-SIM and global roaming modem configuration&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Display: 6.36” ~390ppi FullHD AMOLED, aspect ratio 20:9, Gorilla Glass&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cameras: 50MP Wide + 13MP Ultrawide main cameras, front facing wide-lens selfie camera&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Battery: approx. 5,500mAh, user replaceable&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Connectivity: WiFi 6, BT 5.4, NFC&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dimensions: ~158 x 74 x 9mm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Other: Power key fingerprint reader, user changeable backcover, RGB indication LED, Privacy Switch&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Technical specification subject to final confirmation upon final payment and manufacturing. Minor alterations may apply.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;FAQ&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_Xg7HPj-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; Why a pre-order system? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because this is a community-funded device and we need committed pre-orders to turn the designs into a full product program and commit to order the first production batch. If we reach 2,000 units we start the full product program. If not, you get a full refund.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_7Rpcbi-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; Is the 99 € refundable? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes. Fully.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_mPxbE9-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; What is the normal price of the product, do I get discount participating to the pre-order? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final price of the product is not set yet but we estimate it to settle between 599€ - 699€ (incl. your local VAT). The final price depends on the confirmation of the final specification and the Bill-of-Materials, which happens on due course during the product program. Notably in particular memory component prices have had exceptionally high volatility during this year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By pre-ordering you confirm your special price of total 499€.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_VxbBNb-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; Can I cancel anytime? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_LBEdCJ-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; Is this phone real or just a concept? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is real. Definition and real electro-mechanical design is underway, based on the community voting. To turn the designs into a full product program and commit to order the first batch, we need in minimum 2,000 committed pre-orders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_wLPtcU-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; When will full specs be available? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the manufacturing pathway is confirmed at 2,000 pre-orders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_9fKqjL-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; Will there be accessories, like a spare battery and protective case? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, there will be. We’ll make those available on due course the project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_hYBf7e-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; When will the phone ship? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Estimated by end of 1H/2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_HXEkE6-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; Will the Jolla Phone work outside Europe, can I use it e.g. in the U.S.? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, we will design the cellular band configuration to enable global travelling as much as possible, including e.g. roaming in the U.S. carrier networks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head id="Summary-collapsible_row_WbwtM4-template--26992217882999__collapsible_content_VV7zwn"&gt; Can I buy the Jolla Phone if I’m outside Europe, can I use it e.g. in the U.S.? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The initial sales markets are EU, UK, Switzerland and Norway. Entering other markets, such as the U.S. and Canada are to be decided due course based on potential interest from the areas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We will design the cellular band configuration to enable potential future markets, including major U.S. carrier networks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;You may also like&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Jolla C2 protective sleeve&lt;/head&gt;Regular price 10,00 €Regular priceUnit price / per&lt;del class="price-item price-item--regular" rend="overstrike"/&gt;Sale price 10,00 €&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Jolla C2 screen protector&lt;/head&gt;Regular price 10,00 €Regular priceUnit price / per&lt;del class="price-item price-item--regular" rend="overstrike"/&gt;Sale price 10,00 €&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Sailfish OS subscription&lt;/head&gt;Regular price From 4,90 €Regular priceUnit price / per&lt;del class="price-item price-item--regular" rend="overstrike"/&gt;Sale price From 4,90 €&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46162368</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 15:15:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cloudflare outage on December 5, 2025</title><link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/5-december-2025-outage/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e418bb5fc591a8cb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On December 5, 2025, at 08:47 UTC (all times in this blog are UTC), a portion of Cloudflareâs network began experiencing significant failures. The incident was resolved at 09:12 (~25 minutes total impact), when all services were fully restored.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A subset of customers were impacted, accounting for approximately 28% of all HTTP traffic served by Cloudflare. Several factors needed to combine for an individual customer to be affected as described below.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The issue was not caused, directly or indirectly, by a cyber attack on Cloudflareâs systems or malicious activity of any kind. Instead, it was triggered by changes being made to our body parsing logic while attempting to detect and mitigate an industry-wide vulnerability disclosed this week in React Server Components.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Any outage of our systems is unacceptable, and we know we have let the Internet down again following the incident on November 18. We will be publishing details next week about the work we are doing to stop these types of incidents from occurring.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The graph below shows HTTP 500 errors served by our network during the incident timeframe (red line at the bottom), compared to unaffected total Cloudflare traffic (green line at the top).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare's Web Application Firewall (WAF) provides customers with protection against malicious payloads, allowing them to be detected and blocked. To do this, Cloudflareâs proxy buffers HTTP request body content in memory for analysis. Before today, the buffer size was set to 128KB.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As part of our ongoing work to protect customers using React against a critical vulnerability, CVE-2025-55182, we started rolling out an increase to our buffer size to 1MB, the default limit allowed by Next.js applications. We wanted to make sure as many customers as possible were protected.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This change was being rolled out using our gradual deployment system, and, as part of this rollout, we identified an increase in errors in one of our internal tools which we use to test and improve new WAF rules. As this was an internal tool, and the fix being rolled out was a security improvement, we decided to disable the tool for the time being as it was not required to serve or protect customer traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Disabling this was done using our global configuration system. This system does not use gradual rollouts but rather propagates changes within seconds to the entire network and is under review following the outage we recently experienced on November 18.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In our FL1 version of our proxy under certain circumstances, this latter change caused an error state that resulted in 500 HTTP error codes to be served from our network.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As soon as the change propagated to our network, code execution in our FL1 proxy reached a bug in our rules module which led to the following LUA exception:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;[lua] Failed to run module rulesets callback late_routing: /usr/local/nginx-fl/lua/modules/init.lua:314: attempt to index field 'execute' (a nil value)&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;resulting in HTTP code 500 errors being issued.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The issue was identified shortly after the change was applied, and was reverted at 09:12, after which all traffic was served correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Customers that have their web assets served by our older FL1 proxy AND had the Cloudflare Managed Ruleset deployed were impacted. All requests for websites in this state returned an HTTP 500 error, with the small exception of some test endpoints such as &lt;code&gt;/cdn-cgi/trace&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Customers that did not have the configuration above applied were not impacted. Customer traffic served by our China network was also not impacted.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cloudflareâs rulesets system consists of sets of rules which are evaluated for each request entering our system. A rule consists of a filter, which selects some traffic, and an action which applies an effect to that traffic. Typical actions are â&lt;code&gt;block&lt;/code&gt;â, â&lt;code&gt;log&lt;/code&gt;â, or â&lt;code&gt;skip&lt;/code&gt;â. Another type of action is â&lt;code&gt;execute&lt;/code&gt;â, which is used to trigger evaluation of another ruleset.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our internal logging system uses this feature to evaluate new rules before we make them available to the public. A top level ruleset will execute another ruleset containing test rules. It was these test rules that we were attempting to disable.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We have a killswitch subsystem as part of the rulesets system which is intended to allow a rule which is misbehaving to be disabled quickly. This killswitch system receives information from our global configuration system mentioned in the prior sections. We have used this killswitch system on a number of occasions in the past to mitigate incidents and have a well-defined Standard Operating Procedure, which was followed in this incident.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;However, we have never before applied a killswitch to a rule with an action of â&lt;code&gt;execute&lt;/code&gt;â. When the killswitch was applied, the code correctly skipped the evaluation of the execute action, and didnât evaluate the sub-ruleset pointed to by it. However, an error was then encountered while processing the overall results of evaluating the ruleset:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;if rule_result.action == "execute" then
  rule_result.execute.results = ruleset_results[tonumber(rule_result.execute.results_index)]
end&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This code expects that, if the ruleset has action=âexecuteâ, the ârule_result.executeâ object will exist. However, because the rule had been skipped, the rule_result.execute object did not exist, and Lua returned an error due to attempting to look up a value in a nil value.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is a straightforward error in the code, which had existed undetected for many years. This type of code error is prevented by languages with strong type systems. In our replacement for this code in our new FL2 proxy, which is written in Rust, the error did not occur.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What about the changes being made after the incident on November 18, 2025?&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We made an unrelated change that caused a similar, longer availability incident two weeks ago on November 18, 2025. In both cases, a deployment to help mitigate a security issue for our customers propagated to our entire network and led to errors for nearly all of our customer base.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We have spoken directly with hundreds of customers following that incident and shared our plans to make changes to prevent single updates from causing widespread impact like this. We believe these changes would have helped prevent the impact of todayâs incident but, unfortunately, we have not finished deploying them yet.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We know it is disappointing that this work has not been completed yet. It remains our first priority across the organization. In particular, the projects outlined below should help contain the impact of these kinds of changes:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Enhanced Rollouts &amp;amp; Versioning: Similar to how we slowly deploy software with strict health validation, data used for rapid threat response and general configuration needs to have the same safety and blast mitigation features. This includes health validation and quick rollback capabilities among other things.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Streamlined break glass capabilities: Ensure that critical operations can still be achieved in the face of additional types of failures. This applies to internal services as well as all standard methods of interaction with the Cloudflare control plane used by all Cloudflare customers.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;"Fail-Open" Error Handling: As part of the resilience effort, we are replacing the incorrectly applied hard-fail logic across all critical Cloudflare data-plane components. If a configuration file is corrupt or out-of-range (e.g., exceeding feature caps), the system will log the error and default to a known-good state or pass traffic without scoring, rather than dropping requests. Some services will likely give the customer the option to fail open or closed in certain scenarios. This will include drift-prevention capabilities to ensure this is enforced continuously.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Before the end of next week we will publish a detailed breakdown of all the resiliency projects underway, including the ones listed above. While that work is underway, we are locking down all changes to our network in order to ensure we have better mitigation and rollback systems before we begin again.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;These kinds of incidents, and how closely they are clustered together, are not acceptable for a network like ours. On behalf of the team at Cloudflare we want to apologize for the impact and pain this has caused again to our customers and the Internet as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Time (UTC)&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Status&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Description&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;08:47&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;INCIDENT start&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Configuration change deployed and propagated to the network&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;08:48&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Full impact&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Change fully propagated&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;08:50&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;INCIDENT declared&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Automated alerts&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;09:11&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Change reverted&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Configuration change reverted and propagation start&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;row&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;09:12&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;INCIDENT end&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;cell&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Revert fully propagated, all traffic restored&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46162656</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 15:35:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Framework Laptop 13 gets ARM processor with 12 cores via upgrade kit</title><link>https://www.notebookcheck.net/Framework-Laptop-13-gets-ARM-processor-with-12-cores-via-upgrade-kit.1177930.0.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f36d19f305b9d557"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Framework Laptop 13 gets ARM processor with 12 cores via upgrade kit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Qualcomm Snapdragon X Plus and Snapdragon X Elite have proven that ARM processors have earned a place in the laptop market, as devices like the Lenovo IdeaPad Slim 5 stand out with their long battery life and an affordable price point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MetaComputing is now offering an alternative to Intel, AMD and the Snapdragon X series. Specifically, the company has introduced a mainboard that can be installe in the Framework Laptop 13 or in a mini PC case. This mainboard is equipped with a CIX CP8180 ARM chipset, which is also found inside the Minisforum MS-R1. This processor has a total of eight ARM Cortex-A720 performance cores, the two fastest can hit boost clock speeds of up to 2.6 GHz. Moreover, there are four Cortex-A520 efficiency cores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additionally, there’s an ARM Immortalis-G720 GPU with ten cores and an AI accelerator with a performance of 30 TOPS. This chipset is likely slower than the Snapdragon X Elite or a current flagship smartphone chip, but it should still provide enough performance for many everyday tasks. Either way, this mainboard upgrade might only be interesting for developers for the most part, because early tests show that the SoC already draws about 16 watts at idle, which means battery life will likely be fairly short when combined with the 55Wh battery of the Framework Laptop 13.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Price and availability&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The MetaComputing ARM AI PC Kit is available now at the manufacturer’s official online shop. The base model with 16GB RAM, 1TB SSD and a mini PC case costs $549. The mainboard can be installed in a previously purchased Framework Laptop 13. Users who don’t own a Framework Laptop can order a bundle including the notebook for $999. MetaComputing charges an additional $100 for 32GB RAM. Shipping is free worldwide, but these list prices do not include import fees or taxes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Source(s)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MetaComputing (press release | product page)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46162872</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 15:49:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I'm Peter Roberts, immigration attorney who does work for YC and startups. AMA</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46163121</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b71490110132af37"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As usual, there are countless immigration topics and I'll be guided by whatever you're concerned with. Please remember that I can't provide legal advice on specific cases for obvious liability reasons because I won't have access to all the facts. Please stick to a factual discussion in your questions and comments and I'll do the same in my answers!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hi Peter, have you been seeing either a slowdown or increased denial rates to N-400 applications (5 year rule)? Just curious if it's more or less business as usual or if there is any impact on N-400 applications (we've heard of the neighborhood checks etc.) Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I work for an American company and I am based in Europe. I visit the US for work every now and then. I heard a lot of horror stories regarding border entries. If I am ever in a situation where the border police asks for access to my personal phone and pin code, what are my options? Can I refuse and what happens then?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could you please help with any insights about the social media vetting rules? This has been a blackbox to the visa applications - started with student visas, now being forced on work visas too from Dec 15th.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In your view, who are the winners and losers of the recent H1B changes? And any changes on your perspective for YC harboring international talent in SF Bay Area?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the end, the new requirements - really, just the $100K payment for now - are manageable/avoidable and absent this requirement, the rules and their application haven't really changed. The bigger change, which hasn't happened yet, is the across-the-board increase in prevailing wages. And this will have a profound effect on H-1B employment since the increases will be significant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My H-1B with my current employer expires on Jan 10, 2026 and can’t be extended because I don’t have an I-140. Another startup plans to file my O-1A at the end of December. Can I remain in the U.S. while the O-1A petition is pending?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have recently taken a job with an American based company and will need to complete a few weeks training in Miami. Based on the information they have given me I need a B1 visa and maybe an ESTA since I'm in the UK, and a C-1/D for moving through the US.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However they keep flip flopping between me needing a B1 and me just using my ESTA for the training, and their communication hasn't been the most straight forward. Which visa do I need to get to enter the US for the training?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether you present a B-1 visa or ESTA for admission, you will be seeking admission as a business visitor. Under these circumstances, my advice is almost always not to risk a denial of a B-1 visa application (which happens all the time) and to travel on ESTA. The only relative downside is that ESTA limits admission to 90 days. But of course run this all by the company's immigration counsel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hi Peter, thanks for doing the AMA! I have a Delaware registered LLC (10 years old), I managed to get even an EIN remotely. However, I can't open a bank account remotely and so I have just been paying the registered agent fees and Delaware gov taxes for the LLC all these years. I however, genuinely want to come to the states to open the bank account and actually expand my business into the US. The LLC hasn't really had any annual meetings/etc. but taxes are always paid on time. How do I use my LLC to apply for a B1/B2 to visit the US?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OR should I just close it and try the normal route? Thanks in advance!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My understanding of the B-1 visa is all you really need is a letter of employment. Might get tricky with you providing the letter of employment to yourself however.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46163121</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 16:04:20 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>