<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 17:10:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Grayskull: A tiny computer vision library in C for embedded systems, etc.</title><link>https://github.com/zserge/grayskull</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6e340ed9bad71609"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grayskull is a minimalist, dependency-free computer vision library designed for microcontrollers and other resource-constrained devices. It focuses on grayscale images and provides modern, practical algorithms that fit in a few kilobytes of code. Single-header design, integer-based operations, pure C99.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Image operations: copy, crop, resize (bilinear), downsample&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Filtering: blur, Sobel edges, thresholding (global, Otsu, adaptive)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Morphology: erosion, dilation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Geometry: connected components, perspective warp&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Features: FAST/ORB keypoints and descriptors (object tracking)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Local binary patterns: LBP cascades to detect faces, vehicles etc&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Utilities: PGM read/write&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As usual, no dependencies, no dynamic memory allocation, no C++, no surprises. Just a single header file under 1KLOC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check out the examples folder for more!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Online demo: try Grayskull in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include "grayskull.h"

struct gs_image img = gs_read_pgm("input.pgm");
struct gs_image blurred = gs_alloc(img.w, img.h);
struct gs_image binary = gs_alloc(img.w, img.h);

gs_blur(blurred, img, 2);
gs_threshold(binary, blurred, gs_otsu_theshold(blurred));

gs_write_pgm(binary, "output.pgm");
gs_free(img);
gs_free(blurred);
gs_free(binary);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;code&gt;gs_alloc&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;gs_free&lt;/code&gt; are optional helpers; you can allocate image pixel buffers any way you like.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct gs_image { unsigned w, h; uint8_t *data; };
struct gs_rect { unsigned x, y, w, h; }; // ROI
struct gs_point { unsigned x, y; }; // corners

uint8_t gs_get(struct gs_image img, unsigned x, unsigned y);
void gs_set(struct gs_image img, unsigned x, unsigned y, uint8_t value);
void gs_crop(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src, struct gs_rect roi);
void gs_copy(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);
void gs_resize(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);
void gs_downsample(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);

// Thresholding
void gs_histogram(struct gs_image img, unsigned hist[256]);
void gs_threshold(struct gs_image img, uint8_t threshold);
uint8_t gs_otsu_threshold(struct gs_image img);
void gs_adaptive_threshold(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src, unsigned radius, int c);

// Filters
void gs_blur(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src, unsigned radius);
void gs_erode(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);
void gs_dilate(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);
void gs_sobel(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src);

// Blobs (connected components) and contours
typedef uint16_t gs_label;
struct gs_blob { gs_label label; unsigned area; struct gs_rect box; struct gs_point centroid; };
struct gs_contour { struct gs_rect box; struct gs_point start; unsigned length; };
unsigned gs_blobs(struct gs_image img, gs_label *labels, struct gs_blob *blobs, unsigned nblobs);
void gs_blob_corners(struct gs_image img, gs_label *labels, struct gs_blob *b, struct gs_point c[4]);
void gs_perspective_correct(struct gs_image dst, struct gs_image src, struct gs_point c[4]);
void gs_trace_contour(struct gs_image img, struct gs_image visited, struct gs_contour *c);

// FAST/ORB
struct gs_keypoint { struct gs_point pt; unsigned response; float angle; uint32_t descriptor[8]; };
struct gs_match { unsigned idx1, idx2; unsigned distance; };
unsigned gs_fast(struct gs_image img, struct gs_image scoremap, struct gs_keypoint *kps, unsigned nkps, unsigned threshold);
float gs_compute_orientation(struct gs_image img, unsigned x, unsigned y, unsigned r);
void gs_brief_descriptor(struct gs_image img, struct gs_keypoint *kp);
unsigned gs_orb_extract(struct gs_image img, struct gs_keypoint *kps, unsigned nkps, unsigned threshold, uint8_t *scoremap_buffer);
unsigned gs_match_orb(const struct gs_keypoint *kps1, unsigned n1, const struct gs_keypoint *kps2, unsigned n2, struct gs_match *matches, unsigned max_matches, float max_distance);

// LBP cascades
struct gs_lbp_cascade { uint16_t window_w, window_h; uint16_t nfeatures, nweaks, nstages; const int8_t *features; /* [nfeatures * 4] */ const uint16_t *weak_feature_idx; const float *weak_left_val, *weak_right_val; const uint16_t *weak_subset_offset, *weak_num_subsets; const int32_t *subsets; const uint16_t *stage_weak_start, *stage_nweaks; const float *stage_threshold; };
void gs_integral(struct gs_image src, unsigned *ii);
unsigned gs_lbp_window(const struct gs_lbp_cascade *c, const unsigned *ii, unsigned iw, unsigned ih, int x, int y, float scale);
unsigned gs_lbp_detect(const struct gs_lbp_cascade *c, const unsigned *ii, unsigned iw, unsigned ih, struct gs_rect *rects, unsigned max_rects, float scale_factor, float min_scale, float max_scale, int step);

// Optional:
struct gs_image gs_alloc(unsigned w, unsigned h);
void gs_free(struct gs_image img);
struct gs_image gs_read_pgm(const char *path);
int gs_write_pgm(struct gs_image img, const char *path);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is licensed under the MIT License. Feel free to use in research, products, and your next embedded vision project!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45816673</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 22:35:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mr TIFF</title><link>https://inventingthefuture.ghost.io/mr-tiff/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6498b18bb326a2bd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For as long as I have published my books, one of my overarching goals was to give credit to those who actually invented the hardware and software that we use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have spent 10,000+ hours to create an accurate record of their work but I'm not complaining. The 'as-close-to-possible' truth of invention by individuals or teams meant identifying the work, educating myself, writing questions, and sending emails. And after that process, I set up a chat because it all gets down to talking to someone on the other side of the world, about something that happened 30 or 40 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the invention involves a team, I try to interview more than one person, so I can cross-check the facts. Not to call anyone out, it’s just that, given time, we all forget the facts. And everyone adds their personal take. It’s because of that, for example, that I know the English musician Peter Gabriel really did visit Apple's research labs as they tested the Apple Sound Chip, and gave the team his personal approval to use the song 'Red Rain' for the Macintosh II launch. Wil Oxford, Steve Perlman, Mike Potel, Mark Lentczner and Steve Milne told me so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I was wrapping up Version 2.3 of Inventing the Future, I spoke with Steve M and Mark about the AIFF (Audio Interchange File Format) audio standard that they built around the same time as their VIP visit. They did so as professional programmers, amateur musicians and electronic music experts. Milne and Lentczner knew users needed a standard file format to make their work lives easier and to fend off confusion in the nascent MIDI marketplace. But it didn't exist. So Steve and Mark consulted with users and manufacturers in the Apple cafeteria after hours. This work is interesting on its own but it also underpinned other research. The AIFF, Apple Sound Chip, and MIDI Manager work scaffolded QuickTime and its extensible video formats and programs in 1991. Senior engineer Toby Farrand told me:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio drove the development of QuickTime more than anything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So who or what drove the development of AIFF?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Steve and Mark referred me to the IFF (Interchange File Format (IFF) and the TIFF (Tag Image File Format) that were built before AIFF, in 1985 and 1986 respectively. These file formats were the benchmark for open media standards. My search pivoted, as it always does, to understand those inventions. I expected to be able to find the engineer or engineers names, track them down and interview them. It has worked around 100 times before.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jerry Morrison created IFF while working at Electronic Arts and then went to Apple, where he liaised with the AIFF team. I could easily background his work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I turned my attention to TIFF, built initially as an image standard for desktop publishing. TIFF was able to store monochrome, grayscale, and color images, alongside metadata such as size, compression algorithms, and color space information. In many ways, it was a lot like AIFF so I was keen to know more. But I couldn't find a TIFF creator. No matter how I enquired, Aldus created TIFF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be clear, while a search for AIFF will offer up a company (Apple) not a person, I was able to find Milne and Lentczner in part because of their unique names and because Apple publicised the AIFF work and those publications are archived.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All I had was Aldus, an American company that created desktop publishing with the help of Apple and Adobe. In fact, Paul Brainerd, the cofounder of Aldus coined the term 'desktop publishing' to quickly explain the technicality of what they were doing to potential investors. But Aldus and their seminal product, PageMaker, are long gone, and there were no breadcrumbs for TIFF's creation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, after a day-long trawl through MacWeek back issues, I found Steve Carlson. (below)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then I ran a similar length search through the Computer History Museum’s amazing Oral Histories transcriptions. Brainerd mentioned Carlson's name in an interview. (below)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it was too brief an explanation so I kept looking. Then the trail went cold.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that was because, folks had misspelt his name when quoting him and then that was copied into magazines, and reviews and so forth. Brainerd's CHM interview transcript was wrong. But I didn’t know that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I just kept looking for Steve Carlson.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I found other inventors because they had unique middle or last names or by random methods such as searching glider pilot licences in the Napa Valley after a tip from a former colleague that 'so and so' was a pilot in retirement. I had no tips, no links, nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why couldn’t I find Steve Carlson?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the while, the answer was right under my nose. I had downloaded the final Aldus TIFF specifications document, hoping to find the author’s name. However, the name is seemingly written in white text on white paper - making it invisible. What?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See below where I have highlighted the region with a blue block over the text.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a reason I can’t recall, I downloaded a plain text version and typed in Carlson to see if he was mentioned, but I must have paused at ‘Carls...' and the search functionality automatically filled in the rest. Suddenly I was staring at:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Author/Editor/Arbitrator: Steve Carlsen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;‘Carls-EN’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A quick trip to Google patents, and a search for Steve Carlsen, Stephen Carlsen. Bingo! Stephen E. Carlsen’s patents at Aldus (and Adobe) in Issaquah, WA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I checked the geography, as most folks of a certain age do not stray far from the addresses filed in their patents, and typed Stephen’s correctly spelled surname into the online US White Pages for Washington State. There was ‘a’ Stephen Carlsen listed in a retirement village in WA. His age matched, but there were no public facing email addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I searched bulletin boards on the topic of TIFF, as I had found a former Apple engineer that way. Don had picked an abbreviation of his initials and numbers to post on BBS in his college days and then carried that same combination into adulthood. Many of us did. I took a punt pasting his unique prefix into hotmail, gmail etc. and found Don and interviewed him, but - Stephen Carlsen did not show up in a BBS. So, no email to try.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My ‘last straw' method for finding someone is a stamped envelope. I wrote, printed and mailed a one-page letter to Stephen's listed address, and crossed my fingers. Four months later he popped up in my email.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was a surprise and a relief. We swapped a few emails, and he confirmed the TIFF catalyst story. For Stephen it was 'no big deal'. Once he had built the initial TIFF, Aldus needed to convince 3rd party developers and scanner manufacturers to agree to TIFF as a standard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We had to define and promote an industry standard for storing and processing scanned images, so that we wouldn't have to write import filters for every model of every scanner that would soon be entering the budding desktop scanner market."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stephen himself did much of the evangelizing as Paul Brainerd later pointed out:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“(Steve) developed the standard, and then we went out and promoted it in a series of meetings with specific companies - as well as some workshops we ran in Seattle and the Bay Area during the Seybold shows and the MacWorld shows.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I sent Stephen a draft of what I had written and he sent a prompt reply saying - ‘Looks good’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I followed up asking him how he ended up at a tiny startup in Seattle called Aldus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At that time, I was interviewing for a graphics position at Boeing Computer Services in Seattle, and noticed a small wanted ad that sounded really interesting, and seemed to be an excellent match for my background and interests. I interviewed with Paul and the 5-person mostly-ex-Atex engineering team, and I was hired.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Out of curiosity I put Stephen's email address, now that I knew it, into a Duck Duck search and found him helping people online with TIFF queries long after Aldus had been acquired by Adobe. He also contributed to a Google Group called tiffcentral.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having interviewed so many people across more than a decade, I’ve got pretty good at judging those who would like to talk or type, those who are verbose and those that are not. I knew Stephen had said what he was going to say. I added his pioneering work on TIFF to the AIFF story and moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two years had flown by when I received an email yesterday. His ex-wife Peggy found my paper letter and wrote to me. Stephen passed away earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you for your interest in and support of Stephen’s brilliant work creating TIFF. I’m not surprised Stephen didn’t finish corresponding with you, as he had begun to struggle with using his computer and phone. Some days were better than others for him, but he began to lose touch with people during those months you were reaching out to him. He was a humble man, and I guess never pushed to be recognized, although I believe those who worked with him knew the truth. His last week was in my home, where he was never left alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Peggy finished the email with, ‘I called him Mr TIFF up to his last moment.'&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 10,000+ hours of book research disappeared in an instant. As sad as it was, I could see clearly that all of my work was worth it. Every single second. Because of this email.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mr TIFF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last night, as everyone in my house went to sleep, I took a deep breath and edited the Wikipedia page for TIFF, the Tag Image File Format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It no longer reads ‘created by Aldus’, it reads ‘…created by Stephen Carlsen, an engineer at Aldus'&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Inventing the Future" here -&amp;gt; https://books.by/john-buck/inventing-the-future&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45816853</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 22:57:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UPS plane crashes near Louisville airport</title><link>https://avherald.com/h?article=52f5748f&amp;opt=0</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="52410b633192bbd9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Captain Crunch on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 16:54Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By LittleCupcakes on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 16:47Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By David Cornutt on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 16:38Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By DHE on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 16:34Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Kaj Jensen on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 16:34Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Afterburner119 on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 16:12Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Captain Crunch on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 16:02Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By MF on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 15:59Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Mark on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 15:39Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Anon on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 15:35Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Peter on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 15:24Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Strebav8or on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 15:13Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Captain Crunch on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 15:09Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Janaka Chandrasekera on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 14:50Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Captain Crunch on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 13:47Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Thomas on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 13:43Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Sam Coat on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 13:15Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By James on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 13:12Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By (anonymous) on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 13:06Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Dave on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 13:01Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Captain Crunch on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 12:38Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Delta 3 on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 12:34Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Martin on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 12:24Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By xicoff on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 12:15Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Rex on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 12:09Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Luap on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 12:06Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Rex on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 11:59Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Horstroad on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 11:56Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By Captain Crunch on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 11:17Z&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;By The Legacy on Wednesday, Nov 5th 2025 11:08Z&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45816963</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 23:10:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bluetui – A TUI for managing Bluetooth on Linux</title><link>https://github.com/pythops/bluetui</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e4d181ddbeaa2ea"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Linux based OS with bluez installed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might need to install nerdfonts for the icons to be displayed correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can download the pre-built binaries from the release page release page&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can install &lt;code&gt;bluetui&lt;/code&gt; from crates.io&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cargo install bluetui&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can install &lt;code&gt;bluetui&lt;/code&gt; from the extra repository:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pacman -S bluetui&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can install &lt;code&gt;bluetui&lt;/code&gt; from the lamdness Gentoo Overlay:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo eselect repository enable lamdness
sudo emaint -r lamdness sync
sudo emerge -av net-wireless/bluetui&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are a user of x-cmd, you can run:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;x install bluetui&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/pythops/bluetui
cd bluetui
cargo build --release&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This will produce an executable file at &lt;code&gt;target/release/bluetui&lt;/code&gt; that you can copy to a directory in your &lt;code&gt;$PATH&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Tab&lt;/code&gt;: Switch between different sections.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;j&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Down&lt;/code&gt; : Scroll down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Up&lt;/code&gt;: Scroll up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;s&lt;/code&gt;: Start/Stop scanning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt;: Show help.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;esc&lt;/code&gt;: Dismiss the help pop-up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ctrl+c&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;q&lt;/code&gt;: Quit the app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt;: Enable/Disable the pairing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;o&lt;/code&gt;: Power on/off the adapter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;d&lt;/code&gt;: Enable/Disable the discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;u&lt;/code&gt;: Unpair the device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Space or Enter&lt;/code&gt;: Connect/Disconnect the device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;t&lt;/code&gt;: Trust/Untrust the device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;e&lt;/code&gt;: Rename the device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Space or Enter&lt;/code&gt;: Pair the device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keybindings can be customized in the default config file location &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.config/bluetui/config.toml&lt;/code&gt; or from a custom path with &lt;code&gt;-c&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Possible values: "Legacy", "Start", "End", "Center", "SpaceAround", "SpaceBetween"
layout = "SpaceAround"

# Window width
# Possible values: "auto" or a positive integer
width = "auto"

toggle_scanning = "s"

[adapter]
toggle_pairing = "p"
toggle_power = "o"
toggle_discovery = "d"

[paired_device]
unpair = "u"
toggle_trust = "t"
rename = "e"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPLv3&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bluetui logo: Marco Bulgarelli&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45817114</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 23:29:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Microsoft SoftCard for the Apple II: Getting two processors to share memory</title><link>https://devblogs.microsoft.com/oldnewthing/20251104-00/?p=111758</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a2dfd9092d34a089"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Microsoft Z-80 SoftCard was a plug-in expansion card for the Apple II that added the ability to run CP/M software. According to Wikipedia, it was Microsoft’s first hardware product and in 1980 was the single largest revenue source for the company.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CP/M runs on an 8080 processor, but the Apple II has a 6502 processor. So how can you run CP/M on an Apple II? Answer: The card comes with its own 8080-compatible processor, the Zilog Z80, which was arguable better than the 8080 for a bunch of reasons given on its Wikipedia page.¹&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Great, you now have a processor. But what happens to the old 6502 processor? Ideally, you would just shut it off, but you can’t go cold turkey because some things still had to be handled by the 6502.² Nicole Branagan digs deeper into the story of how the two processors coexist. The idea is that the SoftCard tells the 6502 that it’s doing DMA, so the 6502 pauses and waits for the DMA to complete. However, you can’t leave the 6502 paused for too long or its internal registers degrade and lose their values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The solution is to take advantage of the Z80’s REFRESH line, which the processor uses to signal that it’s not accessing memory right now (because it’s decoding an instruction). This tells external memory refresh circuitry that it can run and keep the RAM values refreshed so that they don’t degrade and lose their values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the Apple II, memory refreshing is done by the video circuitry, so there is need for a dedicated REFRESH signal. The SoftCard uses this signal to allow the 6502 to execute a tiny little bit. (Presumably it is sitting in a spin loop waiting to be woken.) This keeps the 6502’s registers refreshed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the SoftCard needs the 6502 to do actual work, it can update some memory to tell the 6502, “Break out of your spin loop and do something for me, then let me know the answer and go back to the spin loop.” The Z80 then goes to sleep until it gets an answer from the 6502.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another wrinkle in the way that the 6502 and Z80 shared memory is in the memory map. Both the Z80 and 6502 consider the first 256 bytes of memory to be special and want to use it for different things. Furthermore, CP/M programs expect to be loaded at $0100, but the 6502 hard-codes its CPU stack to live in the range $0100–$01FF. There are other obstacles in the low part of the Apple II memory map: The Apple II system monitor uses $0200–$02FF as its keyboard input buffer, the bytes in the range $03F0–$03FF are used to hold interrupt vectors, and the text video frame buffer goes from $0400–$07FF. (There is a second text video frame buffer from $0800–$0BFF, but almost nobody uses it.) Other big obstacles are the memory range from $C000–$CFFF, which is used by peripheral devices, and the memory range from $D000–$FFFF, which holds the Apple II monitor ROM, but can be replaced by RAM if you have the Language Card (a 16KB memory expansion card), except that the last few bytes $FFFA–$FFFF are used by the CPU as interrupt vectors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The solution is to remap the memory by putting address translation circuitry on the SoftCard, so that when the Z80 asks for memory address $0000, say, it actually gets physical memory $1000. The remapping is carefully arranged so that all of the Apple II’s special reserved addresses get shuffled to the end of the Z80 memory map, and all of the Apple II’s normal RAM occupies contiguous address space in the Z80 memory map starting at $0000.³&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6502&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Physical&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Z80&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Special use&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$0000–$0FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;↘&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$1000–$1FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$0000–$0FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;normal RAM&lt;p&gt;(contiguous,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;up to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;installed RAM)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;normal RAM&lt;p&gt;(contiguous,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;up to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;installed RAM)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$1000–$1FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;↗&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$2000–$2FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$1000–$1FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$2000–$2FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$3000–$3FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$2000–$2FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$3000–$3FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$4000–$4FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$3000–$3FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$4000–$4FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$5000–$5FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$4000–$4FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$5000–$5FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$6000–$6FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$5000–$5FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$6000–$6FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$7000–$7FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$6000–$6FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$7000–$7FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$8000–$8FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$7000–$7FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$8000–$8FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$9000–$9FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$8000–$8FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$9000–$9FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$A000–$AFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$9000–$9FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$A000–$AFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$B000–$BFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$A000–$AFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$B000–$BFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$D000–$DFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$B000–$BFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;expansion RAM&lt;p&gt;(except for&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;last 6 bytes)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;I/O space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$C000–$CFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;↘&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$E000–$EFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$C000–$CFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;expansion RAM&lt;p&gt;(except for&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;last 6 bytes)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$D000–$DFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;↗&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$F000–$FFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$D000–$DFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="7"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$E000–$EFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$C000–$CFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$E000–$EFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;I/O space&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$F000–$FFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$0000–$0FFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$F000–$FFFF&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Special use&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The SoftCard manual contained lots of details on how to write code for it. For example, it included instructions on how to call into a 6502 subroutine from Z80 and had a chart showing how the memory was remapped for the Z80. It even included the Z80 processor reference manual, listing all the instructions. This will come in handy in a future story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;¹ I don’t know where the hyphen in Z-80 came from.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;² In many places, I/O was handled by timing loops, so if you wanted to access, say, the game paddles, you had to let the 6502 do the I/O with its precise software timing loops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;³ There were also two high resolution graphics frame buffers, one at $2000–$3FFF, and another at $4000–$5FFF. These were right in the middle of the Z80 memory map, but in practice it wasn’t a problem because CP/M was a text-mode operating system, so the programs you were running didn’t try to do graphics anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45818471</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 02:58:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hypothesis: Property-Based Testing for Python</title><link>https://hypothesis.readthedocs.io/en/latest/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a1031a81e5b71397"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Welcome to Hypothesis!¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hypothesis is the property-based testing library for Python. With Hypothesis, you write tests which should pass for all inputs in whatever range you describe, and let Hypothesis randomly choose which of those inputs to check - including edge cases you might not have thought about. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You should start with the tutorial, or alternatively the more condensed quickstart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tutorial¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An introduction to Hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New users should start here, or with the more condensed quickstart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How-to guides¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practical guides for applying Hypothesis in specific scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Explanations¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commentary oriented towards deepening your understanding of Hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;API Reference¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Technical API reference.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45818562</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 03:15:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I’m worried that they put co-pilot in Excel</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/5/brenda/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="4824a90a9dfb166d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I'm worried that they put co-pilot in Excel because Excel is the beast that drives our entire economy and do you know who has tamed that beast?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Brenda.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Who is Brenda?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;She is a mid-level employee in every finance department, in every business across this stupid nation and the Excel goddess herself descended from the heavens, kissed Brenda on her forehead and the sweat from Brenda's brow is what allows us to do capitalism. [...]&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;She's gonna birth that formula for a financial report and then she's gonna send that financial report to a higher up and he's gonna need to make a change to the report and normally he would have sent it back to Brenda but he's like oh I have AI and AI is probably like smarter than Brenda and then the AI is gonna fuck it up real bad and he won't be able to recognize it because he doesn't understand Excel because AI hallucinates.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You know who's not hallucinating?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Brenda.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;— Ada James, @belligerentbarbies on TikTok&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Recent articles&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A new SQL-powered permissions system in Datasette 1.0a20 - 4th November 2025&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;New prompt injection papers: Agents Rule of Two and The Attacker Moves Second - 2nd November 2025&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hacking the WiFi-enabled color screen GitHub Universe conference badge - 28th October 2025&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45820872</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 08:54:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Founder in Residence at Woz (San Francisco)</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45821921</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3ab8fb7857c0d6e6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Founder in Residence at Woz (San Francisco)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We’re opening one of the coolest jobs ever (only slightly biased).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At Woz, we’ve built the world's first AI App Factory, capable of building business quality mobile apps in just hours.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Now we’re handing over the keys to aspiring founders and challenging them to build real, revenue generating app businesses. Founders get full internal access to our platform, a salary, a dedicated marketing budget, and meaningful upside in any revenue they generate. This is a rare chance to operate like a founder inside a YC startup that recently raised a $6M seed round, surrounded by experienced engineers and builders in the heart of San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Who we’re looking for: - A technical builder who can ship, iterate and problem solve independently (experience with React Native and TypeScript is a plus) - Someone who has launched products, apps, or businesses before, or has a strong track record of building things on their own - Someone who understands go-to-market and growth, especially creative or viral marketing - Someone eager to learn, experiment, and build alongside our team in San Francisco (able to work in-person for at least the first three months)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Interested? Submit your info here. We’ll be in touch https://forms.gle/h8ZWjgRfQUpaTQf8A&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45821921</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 12:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The grim truth behind the Pied Piper (2020)</title><link>https://www.bbc.com/travel/article/20200902-the-grim-truth-behind-the-pied-piper</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf3fc84dbbe71458"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The grim truth behind the Pied Piper&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Writers like the Grimm Brothers and Robert Browning may have shaped the Pied Piper legend into art, but it turns out the story is likely based on an actual historical incident.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(This year, we published many inspiring and amazing stories that made us fall in love with the world – and this is one our favourites. Click here for the full list).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every working morning for the last 26 years, Michael Boyer has slipped into a pair of neon-bright, multi-coloured tights, tied on his lipstick-red cape, grabbed his flute and marched out into the medieval streets of Hamelin, a town of 60,000 residents in Lower Saxony, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“People sometimes mistake me for a superhero, court jester or Robin Hood,” he laughed. He’s also increasingly become an Instagram prop for tourists and, maybe in some woke eyes, a gender-fluid statement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But most people recognise him for what he is, the Pied Piper incarnate, appointed by Hamelin to impersonate its simultaneously favourite (at least commercially) and least favourite adopted son. Responsible for meeting and greeting visiting groups and dignitaries, he leads tours of the city and embodies the enduring hold of the legend that draws most travellers here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The tale in fact has survived for a very long time. Originating as medieval folklore, the story inspired a Goethe verse, Der Rattenfänger; a Grimm Brothers’ legend, The Children of Hamelin; and one of Robert Browning’s best-known poems, The Pied Piper of Hamelin. And although each writer tinkered with the story, the basics remained the same: the Piper was hired by Hamelin to rid the town of its plague of rats. Trailing after the hypnotic notes of the rat-catcher’s magical flute, the rodents politely filed through the city gates to their presumed doom.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They weren’t the only ones lured by his music, though. When the town refused to pay the Piper for his service, the saviour turned into a more satanic seducer and came for Hamelin’s children. Entranced by the notes of his flute, the transfixed boys and girls followed the Piper out of town and simply vanished.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the tale has endured, so has Hamelin itself, which still looks as though it belongs in a fairy tale. Boyer’s tour leads visitors past rows of half-timbered houses. There are 16th Century burgher manors encrusted with Gothic gables and scrollwork, and flamboyant wedding cake buildings offering prime examples of the local Weser-Renaissance architecture, all leering gargoyles and brightly coloured polychrome wood carvings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, all this is merely background for the town’s real cottage industry, which cashes in on all things Piper. The local restaurants plate a “rat tail” signature dish made from thinly sliced pork, and the bakeries do a brisk business in rodent-shaped breads and cakes. The Hameln Museum offers a sound and light Pied Piper re-enactment; local actors put on an open-air Pied Piper play during summer; and the souvenir shops hawk their own rat-inspired memorabilia. You can go home, if you wish, loaded down with Pied Piper T-shirts, fridge magnets, mugs and flutes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What could pass for mere comic relief, though, masks something deeper, and suggests why the legend lives on not only in Hamelin but in enduring folklore. On some level, the tale stokes a primal fear, with the Piper a version of a universal bogey man that continues to haunt us. Parents everywhere still fear the loss of their babies. Children, popping up on the nightly news, still go missing every day. And then we all ultimately vanish in something like an instant. The Piper, in the end, is one very grim reaper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if the tale evokes a universal fear, it still resonates most strongly in Hamelin – and the Piper’s tour suggests why. In fact, the real surprise of his tour isn’t so much the beautifully preserved townscape but the suggestion that the Pied Piper is much more than just a fairy tale. The Grimm Brothers and Browning may have shaped the legend into art, but the story, it turns out, is likely based on an actual historical incident.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;• The elusive hidden people of Iceland&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proof is etched on Hamelin’s face itself. An inscribed plaque on the stone facade of the so-called Pied Piper house, a half-timbered private residence dating to 1602 – similar to an even earlier one etched on the building’s window – bears explicit witness to the mystery. The inscription reads:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“A.D. 1284 – on the 26th of June – the day of St John and St Paul – 130 children – born in Hamelin – were led out of the town by a piper wearing multicoloured clothes. After passing the Calvary near the Koppenberg they disappeared forever.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The inscription isn’t the only clue. An entry in Hamelin’s town records, dating to 1384, laments that, “It is 100 years since our children left.” The stained-glass window in the town’s St Nicolai church, destroyed in the 17th Century but described in earlier accounts, reportedly illustrated the figure of the Pied Piper leading several ghostly white children. And the 15th Century Luneburg manuscript, an early German account of the event, along with five historical memory verses, some in Latin and others in Middle Low German, all refer to a similar story of 130 children or young people vanishing on the 26 June 1284, following a pied piper to a place called Calvary or Koppen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Pied Piper then, more than a fairy tale, becomes the emblem of a profound historical mystery. What happened to the missing children of Hamelin? Still the master seducer, the mesmerising rat-catcher is now leading a whole new trail of entranced followers – this time a conga line of historians each taking their own deep dive into the question of what exactly transpired in Hamelin on 26 June 1284.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The theories are legion, according to Wibke Reimer, project coordinator at the Hameln Museum who has been organising a special exhibit that focuses on the global reach of the Pied Piper legend. One of the leading current theories suggests the town’s youth were part of a migration of Germans to Eastern Europe fuelled by an economic depression.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In this scenario,” Reimer said, “the Pied Piper played the role of a so-called locator or recruiter. They were responsible for organising migrations to the east and were said to have worn colourful garments and played an instrument to attract the attention of possible settlers.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While some historians believe that the youth emigrated to Transylvania, the German linguist Jürgen Udolph’s theory is most accepted. “He suggests the regions around Berlin as the most probable location, in an area that’s now [eastern Germany],” Reimer said, “and he backs up his theory by place name evidence.” In fact, Udolph found that the family names common in Hamelin at the time show up with surprising frequency in the areas of Uckermark and Prignitz, near Berlin, that he locates as the centre of the migration. The theory is also reinforced by evidence that the region, newly liberated from the Danes, was ripe for German colonisation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More fanciful theories abound, too. Some historians suggest the legend reflects a 13th Century children’s crusade, part of the wave of medieval crusades aimed at winning back the Holy Land. And some argue the youth were lost to the Black Plague, though the dates don’t match up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More intriguing is a theory that points to the medieval phenomenon of “dancing mania”, driven by a succession of pandemics and natural disasters. Known as St Vitus’ Dance, the dancing plague is documented surfacing in continental Europe as early as the 11th Century. A form of mass hysteria, the dance could spread from individuals to large groups, all driven by an unshakeable compulsion to dance feverishly, sometimes for weeks, often leaping and singing and sometimes hallucinating to the point of exhaustion and occasionally death, like a top that can’t stop spinning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And, in fact, one 13th Century outbreak – a literal form of dance fever – occurred south of Hamelin, in the town of Erfurt, where a group of youths were documented as wildly gyrating as they travelled out of town, ending up 20km away in a neighbouring town. Some of the children, one chronicle suggests, expired shortly thereafter, having flat-out danced themselves to death, and those who survived were left with chronic tremors. Perhaps, some theorise, Hamelin witnessed a similar plague, dancing to the figurative tune of the Piper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But all these theories neglect one specific key to the Hamelin mystery. “They don’t explain the very particular date cited for the loss of the children, and the local sense of trauma,” Reimer noted. “Did something happen that officials had been covering up? Something so traumatic that it was transmitted orally for so long in the town’s collective memory, over decades and even centuries?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact, the date chronicled in all the local documentation pinpoint 26 June as the day the children disappeared. This day is also the date of pagan midsummer celebrations. The fact the documentation also emphasises that the youth followed the Piper to the Koppen, commonly translated as “hills”, suggest another link. “There were regions in Germany where midsummer was celebrated by lighting fires on the hills,” said Reimer. All that leads to one particularly macabre reading of the Pied Piper legend. Perhaps the Piper, emblematic of a pagan shaman, playing his flute, was leading the youth of Hamelin to their midsummer festivities when the local Christian faction, hoping to cement conversion of the region, waylaid and massacred the group. A less bloody theory: maybe the children were spirited away to local monasteries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the tale suggests a possible historical tragedy, though, it also offers an artistic redemption as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The Pied Piper story,” said Reimer, preparing for the debut of her exhibit on 26 June, “is to our knowledge known in at least 42 countries and 30 languages, maybe more. And it appears in international art, literature and music. The Pied Piper is a shared heritage of many people, and that cultural heritage connects people.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, then, the Piper didn’t just fracture a community. He also, in the end, brought a larger one together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Join more than three million BBC Travel fans by liking us on Facebook, or follow us on Twitter and Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you liked this story, sign up for the weekly bbc.com features newsletter called "The Essential List". A handpicked selection of stories from BBC Future, Culture, Worklife and Travel, delivered to your inbox every Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;{"image":{"pid":""}}&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45822071</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 12:21:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>iOS 26.2 to allow third-party app stores in Japan ahead of regulatory deadline</title><link>https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/05/ios-26-2-third-party-app-stores-japan/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bdcce95f1b2611c4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;iOS 26.2 to Allow Third-Party App Stores in Japan Ahead of Regulatory Deadline&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Apple on Tuesday released the first beta of iOS 26.2 to developers, and it appears that the software will allow users in Japan to install alternative app marketplaces on their devices when it is released to the public in December.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;According to a post shared on X by @Tzzlala, iPhones running the beta in Japan are able to install alternative app stores like AltStore PAL and Epic Games, and download apps from them, though Fortnite in-app purchases are currently region-blocked by Epic. &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Apple only lets iPhone and iPad users based in the EU to install apps using alternative app marketplaces in addition to the App Store. The ability was introduced in iOS 17.4 and iPadOS 18 in order to comply with the Digital Markets Act, and Apple does not currently allow it in any regions outside the 27-member bloc. However, that's set to change. &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;In June 2024, the Japanese parliament approved and enacted legislation that requires Apple to allow third-party app stores and payment providers on the iPhone. The law seeks to curb the dominance of major tech firms like Apple in the smartphone market.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;More recently, in August 2025, the Japan Fair Trade Commission established the Mobile Software Competition Act Guidelines. Under the new guidelines, platform operators like Apple and Google are banned from blocking or restricting the availability of alternative app stores and payment systems on their mobile operating systems. &lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The guidelines are set to come into effect by December 18, 2025, while Apple is expected to release iOS 26.2 in December, sometime between December 9 and December 16. Epic Games has already announced plans to bring Fortnite and its game store platform to iOS in Japan by late 2025. &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Popular Stories&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple is planning to launch at least 15 new products in 2026, according to Bloomberg's Mark Gurman. Gurman outlined what to expect from Apple in 2026 in the latest edition of his "Power On" newsletter. He said the company is heading "into one of its most pivotal years in recent memory," with the rollout of major new Apple Intelligence features, intense regulatory pressure on the App Store,...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;In his "Power On" newsletter, Bloomberg's Mark Gurman today provided an update on the status of Apple Intelligence and the plans for it in 2026. Apple is still planning to roll out its revamped version of Siri around March of next year. The release should be accompanied by the release of a new smart home display product with speaker-base and wall-mount options. A new Apple TV and HomePod...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;A new Apple TV and HomePod mini could launch as soon as this month, Bloomberg's Mark Gurman today suggested. In today's "Power On" newsletter, Gurman said that Apple retail stores are planning an overnight refresh on the evening of November 11, where changes will be made after closing, such as refreshing displays and placing new products for the following day. The timing of the overnight...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple today released iOS 26.1, the first major update to the iOS 26 operating system that came out in September, iOS 26.1 comes over a month after iOS 26 launched. iOS 26.1 is compatible with the iPhone 11 series and later, as well as the second-generation iPhone SE. The new software can be downloaded on eligible iPhones over-the-air by going to Settings &amp;gt; General &amp;gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;We're officially in the month of Black Friday, which will take place on Friday, November 28 in 2025. As always, this will be the best time of the year to shop for great deals, including popular Apple products like AirPods, iPad, Apple Watch, and more. In this article, the majority of the discounts will be found on Amazon. Note: MacRumors is an affiliate partner with some of these vendors. When ...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Following more than a month of beta testing, Apple released iOS 26.1 on Monday, November 3. The update includes a handful of new features and changes, including the ability to adjust the look of Liquid Glass and more. Below, we outline iOS 26.1's key new features. Liquid Glass Toggle iOS 26.1 lets you choose your preferred look for Liquid Glass. In the Settings app, under Display...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple is expected to launch a new foldable iPhone next year, based on multiple rumors and credible sources. The long-awaited device has been rumored for years now, but signs increasingly suggest that 2026 could indeed be the year that Apple releases its first foldable device. Below, we've collated an updated set of key details that have been leaked about Apple's foldable iPhone so far. Ove...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45822302</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 12:51:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NY smartphone ban has made lunch loud again</title><link>https://gothamist.com/news/ny-smartphone-ban-has-made-lunch-loud-again</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="366a9004b8c315ce"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These days, lunchtime at Benjamin N. Cardozo High School in Queens is a boisterous affair, a far cry from before the smartphone ban went into effect, when most students spent their spare time scrolling and teachers said you could hear a pin drop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This year's gotten way louder,” said Jimena Garcia, 15. “Sometimes I would take naps in the lunchroom, but now I can't because of the noise. But it's fun.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a recent fall afternoon, Garcia and her friends crowded around a lunch table in the large cafeteria playing Jenga, occasionally shrieking and gasping as the tower began to lean and fall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The faculty donated board games to help ease kids into the phone-free era. Student volunteers oversaw a table stacked with games: checkers, chess, Yahtzee, Scrabble, Clue, Life and Trivial Pursuit. For many of the kids, it was their first time playing the games, and they said they were enjoying it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“ I do like how this phone ban is allowing students to just connect with each other, make new friendships,” said 17-year-old Alyssa Ko, the school president. “Because some people use their phone to just hide away.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ban prohibits all internet-enabled devices throughout the school day, although there are exceptions for some students with disabilities, kids learning English who need translation apps, and in cases where a teacher says a device can be used for a lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Schools were given flexibility to choose their own storage plans, and Cardozo, which rolled out metal detectors this fall after a student was found with a gun, requires its 3,100 students to keep their phones in internet-blocking magnetic pouches. Other schools have installed storage lockers, or have kids keep their phones zipped up in backpacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As students adjust to lo-fi life, teachers seem pleased with the results. According to an October survey from the state teachers union, New York State United Teachers, 89% of school staff members said the new policies improved their schools' environments, and 76% said kids are more engaged in lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“When students put down their phones, they pick up books — and build friendships,” said NYSUT president Melinda Person.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The initial feedback reflects national trends. New York is one of 31 states, plus Washington, D.C. that have banned smartphones in schools, according to an EdWeek tracker. In a national survey from the University of Pennsylvania, teachers said banning phones helps kids focus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Teachers seem really happy with the changes that they're seeing in the classroom with the electronic device ban,” Cardozo principal Meagan Colby said. “They're telling us that there's a lot more student interaction, a lot more discussion among students, a lot better focus. Overall productivity in the classroom and engagement is higher.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Senior Raya Osagie, 16, said she has to “think more in class” because she used to Google answers or use artificial intelligence. “Now when we get computers, I actually have to [do] deep research instead of going straight to AI,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Students said they’ve also seen their classmates reading physical books more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the cafeteria, Ryan Tripathi, 16, was paging through “Lord of the Flies,” which he said is slow-going. “I'm just not used to reading,” he said. “I’m usually on my phone.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tripathi said it’s good that people are reading more and classroom discussions have become more lively. But he said he’s “not the biggest fan” of the smartphone ban. ”Sometimes you just want to go on your phone and you don't have the ability to do that anymore,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enakshi Barua, 14, said she’s also opposed to the ban, on principle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“ Students are distracted by the phones, but I also don’t believe they should take away our privileges," Barua said. "I feel like the trust isn’t there between the students and teachers. So I feel like that should be built instead of banning the phones.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Cardozo, a few kids break the rules, teachers said. Some either put “burner” phones in their pouches or bang them open. Shanna Burrows, who oversees restorative justice at the school, said staff members are collecting around 30 contraband phones a day. There’s a strike system with escalating punishments that include keeping phones for days, weeks or months, and meetings with parents. Under the state law, schools are not allowed to suspend students solely for smartphone-ban infractions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Students said they have found other ways to push boundaries, like passing old-fashioned notes. “ Especially when you're trying to talk but not have the teacher notice … it would just be [that] we’d send a text message or write on our notes app,” Ko said. “Passing notes is more common now.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ko said other analog activities have also made a comeback, including cards, hangman, tic-tac-toe and Polaroid cameras. “There are just a lot of memories that we make throughout high school that we want to capture,” she said. “I actually have a lot of Polaroids on my wall.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tiana Millen, assistant principal of climate and culture, said she’d also like to see another analog technology make a comeback: the clock.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“They don't know how to read the clocks," she said. "So I make jokes with them and say, ‘We're going to have classes just on how to read the clocks.’”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If they did, she said, they’d see they’re getting to class on time more than they used to; hallway traffic is moving better now that kids aren’t so focused on their phones.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45822539</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 13:20:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Radiant Computer</title><link>https://radiant.computer</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="899b796b21f8ecf7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radiant Computer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radiant's purpose is to explore what personal computing could be when designed from first principles.&lt;/p&gt;We believe the current trajectory of personal computing is leading us to a less free world, and that only a new computing movement rooted in human dignity, creation and autonomy can change its course.&lt;p&gt;Radiant is a computer reimagined from the ground up, a clean-slate design free from the historical baggage that plagues modern systems, and free from Big Tech's influence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's a computer designed to help you learn, create, play, and explore. It's a space to focus, free from distractions. A return to the simple joy of computing: just you and your ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computers today are designed around engagement and surveillance business models rather than user needs. App stores are filled with adware. Operating systems prioritize data collection over user agency. Social media algorithms optimize for addiction. Big Tech fundamentally reshaped computing from a tool for human empowerment into an attention extraction machine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radiant proposes an alternative vision for computing. It doesn't ship with a web browser; it has its own network reminiscent of the early Internet: no social media, no scripts, no trackers. It's a from-scratch system that doesn't retrace the footsteps of the contemporary OS. It's a new paradigm for personal computing that uses modern advances mindfully and deliberately. It's fully open, from hardware to software. It's an offline-first space, designed for focus and creation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Code is computing's native medium; the material you shape to build your own tools, stories, and spaces. Radiant is designed to make that accessible to everyone. It's a tool for personal computing where every application and every surface, exists as code you can read, edit, and extend. It's a system you can truly own. One that is designed to bring the joy of computing to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Writing software doesn't have to be daunting, but the platforms and tools we're stuck with make it so. Radiant aims to change that and truly empower users to create. Furthermore, advances in generative A.I. will make coding accessible to a much broader audience. One of our goals is to explore how an A.I.-native computer system can enhance the creative process, all while keeping data private.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radiant belongs to a more humane future: a personal computer that welcomes curiosity, invites experimentation, and keeps the power in your hands. This is personal computing for the next generation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Find out more about the Radiant system, or read our design principles and tenets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Radiant is an ongoing research project in personal computing. If this resonates with you, write us at 📧 letters@radiant.computer or follow us on 🦋 Bluesky @radiant.computer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can learn more about Radiant by browsing our log or notes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45822559</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 13:22:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Microsoft Can't Keep EU Data Safe from US Authorities</title><link>https://www.forbes.com/sites/emmawoollacott/2025/07/22/microsoft-cant-keep-eu-data-safe-from-us-authorities/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f1a0016b62c5443"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft has admitted that it can't protect EU data from U.S. snooping.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In sworn testimony before a French Senate inquiry into the role of public procurement in promoting digital sovereignty, Anton Carniaux, Microsoft France's director of public and legal affairs, was asked whether he could guarantee that French citizen data would never be transmitted to U.S. authorities without explicit French authorization. And, he replied, "No, I cannot guarantee it."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He said that the company resisted requests from the US authorities "when they are not well-founded", but that under the U.S. Cloud Act, U.S. companies can be forced to hand over data, regardless of where it is stored.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Carniaux did say that the situation had never arisen. However, the admission raises serious concerns around European data sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Microsoft has openly admitted what many have long known: under laws like the Cloud Act, US authorities can compel access to data held by American cloud providers, regardless of where that data physically resides. UK or EU servers make no difference when jurisdiction lies elsewhere, and local subsidiaries or ‘trusted’ partnerships don’t change that reality," commented Mark Boost, CEO of cloud provider Civo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This is more than a technicality. It is a real-world issue that can impact national security, personal privacy and business competitiveness."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The inquiry centers around Project Bleu - a partnership between Microsoft, Orange and Capgemini. There were concerns about the Health Data Hub medical research platform, which is hosted on Microsoft Azure. Senate members said they couldn't be sure that the two platforms were sufficiently separated, and that sensitive health data wouldn't be shared.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Carniaux's admission will increase concerns that the EU can't afford to be reliant on the big U.S. cloud providers such as Microsoft and AWS - even when they claim to be offering sovereign cloud services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The French Senate has set a precedent by demanding answers, and the UK and Europe have an opportunity to do the same," said Boost. "We’re already seeing a shift towards building homegrown solutions that support true data sovereignty rather than data residency."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, a recent European Parliament report found that U.S. firms account for 69% of the cloud infrastructure market share in Europe, while EU suppliers hold only 13%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45822902</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:00:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A P2P Vision for QUIC (2024)</title><link>https://seemann.io/posts/2024-10-26---p2p-quic/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="23b498505021acb9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;A p2p Vision for QUIC&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This article was co-authored by Christian Huitema. You can find his blog at privateoctopus.com.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the years, the IETF has standardized numerous protocols for establishing IP packet flows through NATs and firewalls, including STUN, ICE, and TURN.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is an inherently messy topic, and I can highly recommend reading Eric Rescorla’s blog post series about NATs (part 1, part 2, part 3). I won’t go into details about how exactly NATs work (again, read the ekr’s blog posts!), but in a nutshell, they rewrite the IP of packets passing through the NAT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(192.168.1.10) participant NAT as NAT&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(203.0.113.5) participant Server as Server&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(198.51.100.20) Client-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;NAT: Packet (Src: 192.168.1.10:1234) NAT-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Server: Packet (Src: 203.0.113.5:4321) Server--&amp;gt;&amp;gt;NAT: Response (Dst: 203.0.113.5:4321) NAT--&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Client: Response (Dst: 192.168.1.10:1234)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This allows multiple clients behind that NAT to share the same external IP address. Clients are able to reach any server on the internet, but it doesn’t allow nodes on the internet to reach the client, since the NAT won’t forward packets to the client, unless it determines that they belong to an existing flow. In that sense, the NAT acts as a firewall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although simple in theory, there are a lot of different ways to implement a NAT. For our purposes, the main difference lies in how the port numbers for the outgoing packets are allocated. Depending on the port allocation logic, it might or might not possible to establish a direct connection between two peers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem that p2p network engineers hope to solve is the following: How can two nodes that are both behind a NAT, respectively, connect to each other, no matter the kind of NAT?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this post, we explore how QUIC can be leveraged to provide a comprehensive solution for NAT traversal, encompassing everything from address discovery to UDP proxying, potentially simplifying and improving upon traditional p2p networking approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Traditional Way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Address Discovery using STUN&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Depending on the deployment scenario, a new node joining the network might or might not know its (public) IP address. Traditionally, applications use STUN (RFC 8489) to discover their public IP address. In a nutshell, a STUN client sends a “Binding Request” to a STUN server. The “Binding Response” of the server encodes the IP source address and the source port that the server observed on the client’s request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The client can infer from the responses to the STUN requests if it is located behind a NAT. The client might even compare responses from different STUN servers and attempt to infer the type of NAT, although this is notoriously difficult to get right. The IETF has pretty much given up on this approach (see section 2 of RFC 5389).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The STUN protocol can run over UDP, TCP, DTLS (RFC 7350) or TLS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Hole Punching Coordination using ICE&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we’ve seen above, once the NAT has seen the first packet to a remote server pass through, the NAT opens up the return path, allowing packets from the outside world to reach the node. The idea behind hole punching is to have both peers send packets simultaneously, each of them “punching” a hole in their respective firewall, establishing a direct flow of packets between the two nodes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The traditional hole punching process is specified by ICE RFC 8445. ICE starts with an address gathering phase, in which the two peers separately contact STUN servers to obtain lists of candidate IP addresses and ports. They may add to that list a set of TURN addresses (see next section, “relaying”).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the endpoints creates a list of available addresses, ordered by priority, and sends it to its peer. The peer compares that to its own list, establishes a list of “candidate pairs”, and sends it back. At that point, both endpoints have the same list of candidate pairs, and start the “connectivity” check. Each host will try to send a STUN binding request from its selected address to the paired address, and respond to STUN requests that it might receive from the peer. If at least one of these trials succeeds, the peers have established a new connection over this address pair. If several succeed, they keep the preferred pair.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Relaying using TURN&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, no matter how hard you try, there is a certain percentage of nodes for whom hole punching will never work. This is because their NAT behaves in an unpredictable way. While most NATs are well-behaved, some aren’t. This is one of the sad facts of life that network engineers have to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only solution for this problem is to employ the help of a third party, i.e. a server that is not located behind a NAT, and therefore can be reached by peers directly, without any hole punching. This server can then relay traffic between the two peers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, this comes at a cost. The path via the relay might be slower (in terms of latency and / or bandwidth) than a (hypothetical) direct path would have been. And relaying traffic is not for free for the operator of the relay: both processing resources as well as bandwidth cost money. However, we don’t really have a choice here, and despite these shortcomings, having a relayed connection might be preferable to having no connectivity at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The traditional solution relies on TURN servers, specified in RFC 5766 to provide these “last resort” connectivity. The node behind a NAT can ask the TURN server to open an UDP or TCP port. This “TURN Port” is usually specialized: the client specifies the address of the peer that will be able to send data to that port, or to which data will be sent. The corresponding IP address and port number will be sent to the peer, and will be the basis for some last resort “candidate pairs” used in the coordinated hole punching.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The previous section mentioned that in some cases more than one tried address pair will succeed. This is particularly true for the pairs that include a TURN provided address. This is why the trials will try to collect all the working pairs and pick the higher priority one. If both a “hole punching” and a “TURN” pair succeed, they will typically only retain the “hole punching” pair.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The QUIC Way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;QUIC Connection Migration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RFC 9000 defines how clients can migrate an existing QUIC connection to a different IP:port tuple. When we designed this mechanism, the primary use case we envisioned was solving the “parking lot problem”. Imagine you have a mobile phone, and you walk from your office (where the phone has WiFi) to the parking lot (with no / bad WiFi coverage). In this case, the client could detect that the WiFi connection is worsening, and migrate the connection to its cellular interface. Crucially, this would keep all connection state (e.g. open streams, datagram flows, etc.) intact, and would therefore be transparent to the application.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On detecting a network interface change, e.g. leaving the office, QUIC Path Migration works by first sending a so-called probing packet to the server. The purpose of this packet is to probe if the path actually works. The client includes a PATH_CHALLENGE frame in this packet, to which the server responds with a PATH_RESPONSE frame. This makes sure that the new path actually works (for example, that the path doesn’t block UDP packets), and supports QUIC (for example, allows packets that satisfy QUIC’s MTU requirements).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the wire, this path probing procedure looks pretty similar to a hole punch attempt. We just need a tiny modification to make this work in the p2p use case: If we could get the server to send probe packets as well, we could kill two birds with one stone: We’d punch a hole through the firewall, and at the same time verify connectivity on the path.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course this is not the only thing needed to achieve hole punching. Before the nodes can even send probe packets, we need to learn about the peer’s reflexive address, and be able to coordinate the timing. We’ll come to this in a bit, but first we’ll describe how we can replace STUN to discover our reflexive addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;QUIC Address Discovery&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Typically nodes use STUN to discover their reflexive addresses. In essence, STUN is a request-response protocol here, where the client requests the server to report the observed address of the request packet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In principle, we could achieve the same inside of a QUIC connection: The server could report the address of the client using, for example, a newly defined QUIC frame, and vice versa. This is exactly what the QUIC Address Discovery draft specifies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mechanism is really simple: every time a new path is established (incl. the path used for the handshake), endpoints inform each other of the observed address. This is a very efficient mechanism: Since the OBSERVED_ADDRESS frame is defined as a probing frame, it can be bundled with the PATH_CHALLENGE and PATH_RESPONSE frames used to probe a new path.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Performing address discovery over QUIC comes with multiple advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;QUIC packets are encrypted. An observer is not able to observe the exchange of OBSERVED_ADDRESS frames, nor interfere with this exchange (e.g. by tampering with the frame contents).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It doesn’t require running any additional services (i.e. a STUN server / client). It’s sufficient to enable the Address Discovery extension on a large enough number of nodes.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, in either case the client has to trust that the server is sending honest responses. A misbehaving server could respond with spoofed addresses, causing the “hole punching” packets to later be sent to these addresses. This is not hard to defend against: Clients can obtain some protection against such attacks by contacting several servers and comparing their responses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Hole Punching Coordination&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The node has now learned its reflexive addresses, and we know how to use QUIC’s connection migration mechanism to establish the NAT port mappings required to allow the establishment of a direct path. We now want to establish a connection to another node, behind its respective NAT.For the moment, we’ll assume that the two nodes are able to communicate via a (proxied) QUIC connection. We’ll see how this works in detail in the next section. The only thing that matters for now is that the nodes are able to communicate with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The NAT traversal draft defines how two nodes can negotiate hole punching attempts with each other. Out of convenience, the process is driven almost entirely by the client (i.e. the node that initiated the QUIC connection). This is not because the roles of the peers are fundamentally different (they are both peers in the same p2p network), but it leads to significant simplifications of the protocol. It also reduces the difference to RFC 9000, where connection migration can only be initiated by the client.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The server informs the clients about its reflexive address using ADD_ADDRESS frames. Multiple ADD_ADDRESS frames can be sent if the server has multiple reflexive addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ICE RFC goes into great detail on how to form candidate pairs from both nodes’ reflexive addresses, because both nodes need to agree on the ordering of the candidate pairs. Since the client is driving this process, we don’t need to specify any address matching logic that client and server would need to agree on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the client has formed address pairs (and once it feels like it’s the right time to start a hole punch attempt), it sends a PUNCH_ME_NOW frame to the server. The PUNCH_ME_NOW contains both the client’s and the server’s reflexive addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Immediately after sending the PUNCH_ME_NOW frame, the client starts path probing on the path formed by these two addresses. Equivalently, as soon as the server receives the PUNCH_ME_NOW frame, it starts path probing the path from its end. Timing is crucial here: As we’ve seen above, the path probing packets create the NAT binding required to allow the other side’s packets to make it through the NAT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both the client and the server will send PATH_CHALLENGE frames on a new path when sending or responding to &lt;code&gt;PUNCH_ME_NOW&lt;/code&gt;. They will need to allocate a yet unused Connection ID to the new path that they
are trying to establish. This implies that the number of parallel attempts is limited by the number of available Connection ID. This has both upsides and downside. On the one hand, having a limit reduces the amount of resource that a peer can be forced to consume, which makes the protocol more stable.
On the other hand, if the limits are reached, the next attempt will only be possible after one of the previous challenges has been abandoned, and the peer has provided a replacement Connection ID. This might be a slow process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether that process is too slow is debatable. Endpoints that plan to engage in p2p hole punching may be configured to provide a number of Connection IDs sufficient for most practical attempts. Also, the initial path will be available until the migration succeeds, which means the application endpoints do not need to wait the success of the negotiation to start exchanging data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adding new QUIC frames like &lt;code&gt;ADD_ADDRESS&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;PUNCH_ME_NOW&lt;/code&gt; is somewhat controversial. Misbehaving peers could send spoofed addresses in these frames, causing the peer to send hole punching packets to third parties. This is similar to the request forgery attacks described in the security section of RFC 9000, and calls at least for the same kind of defenses. This is something we will keep in mind when evolving the NAT traversal draft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Relaying UDP packets over HTTP&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RFC 9298 defines how UDP packets can be proxied in HTTP. The exchange starts a regular HTTP request: The client sends a so-called Extended CONNECT request to the proxy on a QUIC stream, instructing the proxy to open a UDP socket and proxy a flow of UDP packets to a target server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the proxy has accepted the proxying request, UDP packets are sent in HTTP Datagrams (RFC 9297), which themselves are a thin wrapper around QUIC DATAGRAM frames. QUIC Datagrams are a new QUIC frame defined in RFC 9221, which are sent in QUIC packets exchanged after completion of the QUIC handshake. They’re therefore encrypted the same way that any other data exchanged over the QUIC connection is. However, if a packet containing a DATAGRAM is lost, the DATAGRAM frame is not retransmitted. This makes DATAGRAMs suitable to proxy unreliable packets, such as UDP packets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiple UDP flows to different target servers can be proxied in the same QUIC connection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Proxying UDP packets is almost what we need to make relaying work in the p2p scenario, but not quite: While the client can reach any IP via the proxy, it’s still not possible for other nodes to communicate with the client (unless contacted first by the client).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there’s already a draft describing how to Proxy UDP Listeners in HTTP. The primary use case for this draft is running WebRTC over CONNECT-UDP. This is a very similar problem to the one we’re trying to solve: WebRTC peers actually use the ICE protocol to establish a direct connection, and for that they need to know their reflexive transport addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mechanism is pretty straight-forward: The proxy allocates a new IP:port for the client, and forwards all UDP packets on this socket to the client. Of course, it also has to include the 2-tuple that the packet originated from.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The simplificity of this approach is at the same time its biggest limitation: Since there are only 65535 port numbers (many of which are reserved), a proxy can only handle a limited number of clients at the same time. To be clear, this still allows tens of thousands of concurrent clients, and many deployment scenarios will never run into this limit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It might be possible to work around this limit in the future by using a similar approach as the QUIC-aware proxying draft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Preparing for Multipath&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The QUIC Working Group is finalizing the Multipath Extensions for QUIC. As the name suggests, this extensions allow multiple paths to be used simultaneously. For the p2p use case, this means that endpoints could keep the initial path available, even after a direct path was created by NAT traversal. These paths could either be used for load sharing or as a backup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get these benefits, we will need minor adaptations of the mechanism described here – effectively, managing connection IDs and path IDs in a multipath version of the &lt;code&gt;PUNCH_ME_NOW&lt;/code&gt; frame. We should work on that once the Multipath Extension for QUIC has made more progress in the IETF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Putting All the Pieces Together&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve explored all the components, let’s put them together and build a small p2p application running on top of QUIC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the node boots up, it first connects to a few hard-coded boot nodes. The majority of these nodes support the QUIC Address Discovery extension, so the node is able to learn that it’s behind a NAT, and what the NAT’s public addresses are.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It then connects to a relay and reserves an IP:port tuple with the relay. The node can now advertise this address to other peers in the network, for example by registering in some kind of peer directory, or by registering itself with the p2p network’s DHT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, other nodes can connect to the relay at this port, and have all their packets relayed. We’ve achieved the first goal: we have established connectivity. The relayed connections can immediately be used to exchange application data. Now the goal is to lighten the load on the relay server, and to obtain a direct (and potentially lower-latency, higher-throughput) to the peer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The nodes employ the mechanism described in the NAT traversal draft to punch holes through their respective NATs. This hole punching procedure might take a few attempts, depending on the number of candidate pairs (and if hole punching attempts are run in parallel), but should generally only take a few seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most importantly, this is entirely transparent to the application: The application can start to use the relayed connection, and use it all the while the QUIC stack tries to establish the direct path.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Where are we on this?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So far, there’s no implementation of this protocol in production, but a lot of the documents have made their way through the IETF process and have now become widely deployed RFCs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Specifically, the remaining pieces of the puzzle are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Proxy UDP Listeners in HTTP draft, which allows clients to reserve an IP:port tuple on a relay server.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The QUIC Address Discovery draft, which allows endpoints to learn about their public addresses. The current version of this draft is implemented by two different QUIC stacks: picoquic and a fork of quinn.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The NAT Traversal for QUIC draft, which defines how to coordinate hole punching attempts between peers.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The quic-go project and the QUIC Interop Runner are community-funded projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you find my work useful, please considering sponsoring:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45822982</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:06:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Removing XSLT for a more secure browser</title><link>https://developer.chrome.com/docs/web-platform/deprecating-xslt</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="be4a8c104cf770b8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Published: October 29, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chrome intends to deprecate and remove XSLT from the browser. This document details how you can migrate your code before the removal in late-2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chromium has officially deprecated XSLT, including the XSLTProcessor JavaScript API and the XML stylesheet processing instruction. We intend to remove support from version 155 (November 17, 2026). The Firefox and WebKit projects have also indicated plans to remove XSLT from their browser engines. This document provides some history and context, explains how we are removing XSLT to make Chrome safer, and provides a path for migrating before these features are removed from the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What is being removed?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two APIs in the browser that implement XSLT, and both are being removed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The XSLTProcessor class (for example, &lt;code&gt;new XSLTProcessor()&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The XSLT Processing Instruction (for example, &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?xml-stylesheet … ?&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Timeline For Chrome&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chrome has the following plan:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chrome 142 (Oct 28, 2025): Early warning console messages added to Chrome.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chrome 143 (Dec 2, 2025): Official deprecation of the API - deprecation warning messages begin to show in the console and in lighthouse.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chrome 148 (March 10, 2026 Canary): Canary, Dev, and Beta releases begin disabling XSLT by default, as an early-warning.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chrome 152 (Aug 25, 2026): Origin Trial (OT) and Enterprise Policy (EP) go live for testing. These allow sites and enterprises to continue using features past the removal date.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chrome 155 (Nov 17, 2026): XSLT stops functioning on Stable releases, for all users other than Origin Trial and Enterprise Policy participants.**&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chrome 164 (Aug 17, 2027): Origin Trial and Enterprise Policy stop functioning. XSLT is disabled for all users.**&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What is XSLT?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XSLT, or Extensible Stylesheet Language Transformations, is a language used to transform XML documents, commonly into other formats such as HTML. It uses an XSLT stylesheet file to define the rules for this conversion, and an XML file containing the data used as input.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In browsers, when an XML file is received that links to an XSLT stylesheet, the browser uses the rules in that stylesheet to rearrange, format, and convert the raw XML data into a structured page (often HTML) that can be rendered for the user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, an XSLT stylesheet could take the following XML input:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version="1.0"?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="demo.xsl" ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;page&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;message&amp;gt;
  Hello World.
 &amp;lt;/message&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/page&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and this XSL stylesheet:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;xsl:output method="html"/&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;xsl:template match="/page/message"&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Message: &amp;lt;xsl:value-of select="."/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/xsl:template&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/xsl:stylesheet&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and process them into this HTML for the browser to display: HTML&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Message: Hello World.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to the XSL processing instruction shown in the previous example, there's also the XSLTProcessor JavaScript API which can be used to process local XML documents with local XSLT stylesheets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;History of XSLT&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XSLT was recommended by the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) on November 16, 1999, as a language for transforming XML documents into other formats, most commonly HTML for display in web browsers. Before the official 1.0 recommendation, Microsoft took an early initiative by shipping a proprietary implementation based on a W3C working draft in Internet Explorer 5.0, released in March 1999. Following the official standard, Mozilla implemented native XSLT 1.0 support in Netscape 6 in late 2000. Other major browsers, including Safari, Opera, and later Chrome, also incorporated native XSLT 1.0 processors, making client-side XML-to-HTML transformations a viable web technology in the early 2000s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The XSLT language itself continued to evolve, with the release of XSLT 2.0 in 2007 and XSLT 3.0 in 2017, which introduced powerful features like regular expressions, improved data types, and the ability to process JSON. Browser support, however, stagnated. Today, all major web browser engines only provide native support for the original XSLT 1.0 from 1999. This lack of advancement, coupled with the rise of the use of JSON as a wire format, and JavaScript libraries and frameworks (like jQuery, React, and Vue.js) that offer more flexible and powerful DOM manipulation and templating, has led to a significant decline in the use of client-side XSLT. Its role within the web browser has been largely superseded by these JavaScript-based technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why does XSLT need to be removed?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The continued inclusion of XSLT 1.0 in web browsers presents a significant and unnecessary security risk. The underlying libraries that process these transformations, such as libxslt (used by Chromium browsers), are complex, aging C/C++ codebases. This type of code is notoriously susceptible to memory safety vulnerabilities like buffer overflows, which can lead to arbitrary code execution. For example, security audits and bug trackers have repeatedly identified high-severity vulnerabilities in these parsers (e.g., CVE-2025-7425 and CVE-2022-22834, both in libxslt). Because client-side XSLT is now a niche, rarely-used feature, these libraries receive far less maintenance and security scrutiny than core JavaScript engines, yet they represent a direct, potent attack surface for processing untrusted web content. Indeed, XSLT is the source of several recent high-profile security exploits that continue to put browser users at risk. The security risks of maintaining this brittle, legacy functionality far outweighs its limited modern utility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the original purpose of client-side XSLT—transforming data into renderable HTML—has been superseded by safer, more ergonomic, and better-maintained JavaScript APIs. Modern web development relies on things like the Fetch API to retrieve data (typically JSON) and the DOMParser API to safely parse XML or HTML strings into a DOM structure within the browser's secure JavaScript sandbox. Frameworks like React, Vue, and Svelte then manage the rendering of this data efficiently and securely. This modern toolchain is actively developed, benefits from the massive security investment in JavaScript engines, and is what virtually all web developers use today. Indeed, only about 0.02% of web page loads today actually use XSLT at all, with less than 0.001% using XSLT processing instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is not a Chrome or Chromium-only action: the other two major browser engines also support the removal of XSLT from the web platform: WebKit, Gecko.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For these reasons, deprecating and removing XSLT reduce the browser's attack surface for all users, simplify the web platform, and allow engineering resources to be focused on securing the technologies that actually power the modern web, with no practical loss of capability for developers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Improving XML parsing security&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similar to the severe security issues in libxslt, severe security issues were recently reported against libxml2 which is used in Chromium for parsing, serialization and testing the well-formedness of XML. To address future security issues with XML parsing In Chromium we plan to phase out the usage of libxml2 and replace XML parsing with a memory-safe XML parsing library written in Rust. Importantly, we won't be removing XML from the browser; only XSLT is being considered for removal here. We intend to ensure that replacing libxml2 is entirely transparent to web developers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to migrate&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are a few alternative paths for migration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;JSON&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For sites that are fully built on XML and XSL there is no one-size-fits all way to make the transition. Migration options include moving the XSLT processing pipeline to the server side and sending down the rendered HTML to the client, or migrating server-side XML API endpoints to JSON, and performing client-side rendering using JavaScript to transform JSON into HTML DOM and CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Client-side XSLT in JavaScript&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are a few client-side (JavaScript-based) XSLT libraries available, but the largest by far is produced by Saxonica (view the comprehensive documentation for Saxonica). The implementation goes well beyond the XSLT 1.0 implementation in web browsers, implementing full support for the latest v3.0 standard, and eventually the in-progress v4.0 standard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Polyfill&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a polyfill that attempts to allow existing code, which depends on web browsers' implementations of XSLT 1.0, to continue functioning, while not using native XSLT features from the browser. The polyfill is located on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The polyfill contains a functional WASM-based polyfilled replacement for the XSLTProcessor class, so existing JavaScript code can continue to work as-is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script src="xslt-polyfill.min.js"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
const xsltProcessor = new XSLTProcessor();
xsltProcessor.importStylesheet(xsltDoc);
const fragment = xsltProcessor.transformToFragment(xmlDoc, document);
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The polyfill also provides an automatic utility function for an easy way to replace XML documents that use XSLT processing instructions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For an original &lt;code&gt;demo.xml&lt;/code&gt; file like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version="1.0"?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="demo.xsl"?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ROOT&amp;gt;
...content...
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One line can be added to invoke the polyfill and transform the document with the referenced XSLT stylesheet:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version="1.0"?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="demo.xsl"?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;ROOT&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script src="xslt-polyfill.min.js"
   xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
...content...
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case, the new &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element loads the polyfill, which detects the
XML document type and the XSLT processing instruction and transparently loads
it, replacing the document.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Extension&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's also a Chrome extension that can be added to supported browsers, which will apply the same XSLT polyfill to all raw XML pages that contain XSLT processing instructions or calls to XSLTProcessor. This can be used for applications where the source XML or XSLT cannot be changed, to maintain functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In particular, when XSLT is disabled, Chrome now shows a warning banner that links directly to an extension search page, to help users locate an extension:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Specific use cases&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the discussion in HTML standards, several concrete use cases were identified. This section talks specifically about each of them, to recommend paths forward for developers publishing XML resources that use XSLT today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;RSS and Atom Feeds&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In many existing RSS or Atom feeds, XSLT is used to make raw XML feeds human-readable when viewed directly in a browser. The primary use case is that when a user accidentally clicks on a site's RSS feed link, rather than pasting that link into their RSS reader, they get a formatted HTML response that they can read, rather than the raw XML itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two paths forward for this use case. The "standard" HTML way to do this is to add &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;link rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to an
(HTML-based) site, rather than adding an explicit (user-visible) &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a
href="something.xml"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; that users might accidentally click. This solution allows
RSS readers to find the feed if a user pastes in just the website URL, but it
also allows human users to see the regular HTML content without getting confused
by a link to an XML resource. This also follows the normal web paradigm that
HTML is for humans and XML is for machines. Of course this doesn't solve the
case where a user just "has" an RSS link from somewhere, and they paste it into
their web browser (rather than their RSS reader).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When that solution isn't wanted, the polyfill offers another path. As mentioned previously, the RSS/Atom XML feed can be augmented with one line, &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script
src="xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;,
which will maintain the existing behavior of XSLT-based transformation to HTML.
That shouldn't affect RSS reader's ability to continue parsing the XML, since
the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is a direct child of the root element.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;API output for embedded devices&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some commercial embedded devices measure or otherwise generate XML data for consumption by users on the local network. Some of these devices do this by generating a single XML data feed that uses XSLT to transform it into a human-readable HTML format. That allows the API to be directly viewed in a browser without needing additional code on the device or in the browser.&lt;lb/&gt; Since this is a very application specific use case, the shape of the solution might vary. For applications where the source code of the embedded device can be updated, any of the options described previously (JSON, Polyfill) could work. In particular, however, many such devices are difficult or impossible to update, for various reasons. In that case, the extension is likely the best option, since it allows client browsers to continue to read the data in exactly the same way, without modifying the device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Lazy templating for web sites&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Web developers sometimes use XSLT on the client side to apply presentation markup to semantic markup, functioning as a lazy templating language that is separate from the JavaScript ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two solutions to this more general problem. For an existing site built in this way, the easiest solution is likely just to add the polyfill to maintain existing functionality. Or perhaps perform the XSLT transformation on the server side, and serve the resulting HTML to the client, rather than the raw XML. The more long-term solution for such properties would be to migrate to a more modern JavaScript or JSON-based framework.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you encounter a specific problem in Chrome related to this XSLT deprecation, report a bug here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45823059</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:14:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The shadows lurking in the equations</title><link>https://gods.art/articles/equation_shadows.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="370746cbee2f5ea1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For all the history of computational mathematical visualization, graphing equations has been done in binary mode - where graphs show only where an equation is EXACTLY equal. But when you only see in black-and-white, some things are invisible. For all this time, lurking beneath the error == 0 surface, mathematical shadows have been lurking in the equations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FuzzyGraph, on the other hand, visualizes equations in Non-Binary mode - showing not only where an equation are exactly equal, but also where the equation nearly equal and where the equation is far from equal (where the error is high). Sometimes, these high error areas form clear visual shadow-like features.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's look at some examples...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the "Slash Dot" Equation ( \( \frac{y}{x^2+y^2} = \frac{x+1}{x^2+y^2} \)) as both a conventional and fuzzy graph...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note the giant black hole that is present in the Fuzzy/Non-Binary graph, but invisible in conventional/Binary graphing. This "black hole" feature represents a region of high error in the equation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's look at another example: \(y = \frac{x}{x^2 + y^2} \) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice that the black hole eye-looking features are COMPLETELY INVISIBLE in the conventional/binary mode of graphing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get a better idea of what these black hole things are, let's look at a simpler example. First let's look at the opposite of a black hole - a simple star/particle example: \( x^2 + y^2 = 0 \). For this equation, there is only 1 solution: (0, 0). So if you graph this in a conventional graphing app, it will only show a single dot at (0, 0). But in FuzzyGraph, it looks like a fuzzy particle or something.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But now, let's invert this to get the "Black Hole Equation": \( \frac{1}{x^2+y^2} = 0 \)...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case, there is absolutely nothing to show on a conventional graph, as there are actual solutions to this equations. However, there is still a mathematical topography which can be visualized (as can be seen in the fuzzy graph).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not all of the Shadows are like black holes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this example, let's start by combining 2 lines together: \(y=x\) and \(y=-x\).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can visually add 2 equations together by refactoring them so they are both equal to 0, and then multiplying the two refactored equations together. \(y=x\) can be changed to \(y-x=0\), and \(y=-x\) can be refactored to \(y+x=0\).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can then combine 2 into a single equation these like this: \( (y-x) \times (y+x) = 0 \)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And now, let's invert one of the equations using division: \( \frac{x-y}{x+y} = 0 \)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So as you can see, the line that was inverted (under the division line) is now a Shadow Line. And this seems like a more "correct" way to visualize this than as the conventional graph shows it (which is indistinguishable from the simpler equation, \(y-x=0\)).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This equation works almost exactly as the previous. And like before, let's start with multiplication to combine 2 equations (in this case, a circle and a vertical line equation): \( x \times (x^2+y^2-1) = 0 \).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But now, let's invert the circle by using division, which makes the equation: \( \frac{x}{x^2+y^2-1} = 0 \).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that the Shadow Circle is invisible in the conventional graph. In fact, the conventional graph looks identical to a conventional graph of the \(x=0\) equation (as if the denominator was not there).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In all of these previous examples, the "shadows" have represented areas of high error. But in this last example, we'll see some hidden details that represent areas of low error - areas that are nearly solutions to the equation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider the equation, \( y=4 sin(x)+ sin(2.7y) \), as both a conventional graph and a fuzzy graph:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note the floating dots in the fuzzy graph version that are not there in the conventional/binary graph. These are like underwater islands - underwater mountains that are just below the surface of the water (or in this case, the \( error == 0 \) surface). These hidden islands represent area that are near-solutions to the equation (which are only visible in FuzzyGraph).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Their presense hints that we can tweak the equation slightly to cause them to burst above the surface of the water (which should also make them visible in conventional graphs).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So let's change the equation from: &lt;lb/&gt; \( y=4 sin(x)+ sin(2.7y) \) to: &lt;lb/&gt; \( y=4 sin(x)+ sin(2.8y) \)...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And as you can see, those previously-hidden islands are now visible in the conventional graph.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So Fuzzy/non-binary graphing can help us see features of the mathematical topography that are completely invisible with conventional/binary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Date published: 2025-11-05&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45823141</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:21:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Carice TC2 – A non-digital electric car</title><link>https://www.caricecars.com/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45823186</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:25:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ask HN: My family business runs on a 1993-era text-based-UI (TUI). Anybody else?</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45823234</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3ec6db1c2cb327ac"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Is anybody still using TUI applications for business?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My family company is a wholesale distribution firm (with lightweight manufacturing) and has been using the same TUI application (on prem unix box) since 1993. We use it for customer management, ordering, invoicing, kit management/build tickets, financials - everything. We've transitioned from green screen terminals to modern emulators, but the core system remains. I spent many summers running serial and ethernet cables.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I left the business years ago to become a full time software engineer, but I got my start as a script kiddie writing automations for this system with Microsoft Access, VBA, and SendKeys to automate data entry. Amazingly, they still have a Windows XP machine running many of those tasks I wrote back in 2004! It's brittle, but cumulatively has probably saved years of time. That XP machine could survive a nuclear winter lol.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I recently stepped back in to help my parents and spent a day converting many of those old scripts to a more modern system (with actual error-handling instead of strategic sleep()s and prayers) using Python and telnetlib3. I had a blast and still love this application. I can fly around in it. Training new people was always a pain, but for those that got it—they had super powers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This got me thinking: Are other companies still using this type of interface to drive their core operations? I’m reflecting on whether the only reason my family's business still uses this system is because of the efficiency hacks I put in place 20+ years ago. Without them, would they have been forced to switch to a modern cloud/GUI system? I’m not sure if I’m blinded by nostalgia or if this application is truly as wonderful as I remember it.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’d love to hear if and how these are still being utilized in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;P.S. The system we use was originally sold by ADP and has had different names (D2K, Prophet21). I believe Epicor owns it now (Activant before).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;P.P.S. Is anybody migrating their old TUI automation scripts to a more modern framework or creating new ones? I’m super curious to compare notes and see what other people are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45823234</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:29:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kosmos: An AI Scientist for Autonomous Discovery</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02824</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="347cd40b84d1c48e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Artificial Intelligence&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 4 Nov 2025]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:Kosmos: An AI Scientist for Autonomous Discovery&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:Data-driven scientific discovery requires iterative cycles of literature search, hypothesis generation, and data analysis. Substantial progress has been made towards AI agents that can automate scientific research, but all such agents remain limited in the number of actions they can take before losing coherence, thus limiting the depth of their findings. Here we present Kosmos, an AI scientist that automates data-driven discovery. Given an open-ended objective and a dataset, Kosmos runs for up to 12 hours performing cycles of parallel data analysis, literature search, and hypothesis generation before synthesizing discoveries into scientific reports. Unlike prior systems, Kosmos uses a structured world model to share information between a data analysis agent and a literature search agent. The world model enables Kosmos to coherently pursue the specified objective over 200 agent rollouts, collectively executing an average of 42,000 lines of code and reading 1,500 papers per run. Kosmos cites all statements in its reports with code or primary literature, ensuring its reasoning is traceable. Independent scientists found 79.4% of statements in Kosmos reports to be accurate, and collaborators reported that a single 20-cycle Kosmos run performed the equivalent of 6 months of their own research time on average. Furthermore, collaborators reported that the number of valuable scientific findings generated scales linearly with Kosmos cycles (tested up to 20 cycles). We highlight seven discoveries made by Kosmos that span metabolomics, materials science, neuroscience, and statistical genetics. Three discoveries independently reproduce findings from preprinted or unpublished manuscripts that were not accessed by Kosmos at runtime, while four make novel contributions to the scientific literature.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45823358</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:43:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruby and Its Neighbors: Smalltalk</title><link>https://noelrappin.com/blog/2025/11/ruby-and-its-neighbors-smalltalk/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="34329b3385e7083a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Ruby And Its Neighbors: Smalltalk&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last time, we talked about Perl as an influence on Ruby, this time, we’ll talk about the other major influence on Ruby: Smalltalk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk had a different kind of influence, since almost nothing of Smalltalk’s syntax made into Ruby. But many of the details of how objects work are directly inspired by Smalltalk, including the idea that every piece of data is part of the object system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also unlike Perl, I spent a good couple of years working in Smalltalk, and it is one of my favorite languages that I’ll never likely use in anger again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;(A Personal) History of Smalltalk&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk originated in the same Xerox PARC team that invented the windowed interface, ethernet, and the laser printer, and who knows what else, they may have invented ice cream and rainbows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a whole story about what project Smalltalk was invented to be a part of, and a whole alternate history of computing and how people interact with computers that we are going to largely ignore. (If you are interested, start by searching for “Alan Kay Dynabook”.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk went through a few different iterations in the 1970s, but the version that we know today is a direct descendent of Smalltalk-80, which was the first version released to the wider world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For most of the 80s and 90s, Smalltalk was something that doesn’t really exist today – a programming language and environment that companies paid money to use. Lots of money. The major player was ParcPlace, which was a spinoff of Xerox that provided Smalltalk tools. Their commercial product was originally called ObjectWorks, later changed to VisualWorks, and eventually sold off and presumably slowly losing customers after the late 90s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk was pretty big in the industry for a while. Most of the aviation industry ran on it in the 90s, the big payroll project that was the basis for Extreme Programming was a Smalltalk project, there was reasonably high demand for Smalltalk programmers through at least the mid 1990s. I taught an undergrad OO class in Smalltalk in 1997 and 1998 to students that wanted to be learning C++, and I remember telling them that Smalltalk programmers were paid more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I first encountered Smalltalk as a grad student in about 1993, where Georgia Tech used ObjectWorks to teach Smalltalk and Object-Oriented programming (there’s a whole other sidebar about how Object-Oriented languages came to prominence in the 90s, and the arguments over that but again, another day). ObjectWorks was pricey, and there was also a lower-cost vendor called Digitalk, and eventually I also used a product called Smalltalk Agents, which has apparently totally vanished from the entire internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1995, a bunch of the original Xerox Smalltalk team was together at Apple, and they decided to release an open-source Smalltalk VM. What they did was very interesting. They wrote a very, very small kernel in very vanilla C, and then 95% of the environment was then built in Smalltalk on top of that. Oh, and even the vanilla C was written in Smalltalk, they wrote a Smalltalk to C compiler. They called their new Smalltalk “Squeak”, which made a lot more sense when they all moved en masse to Disney.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact that Squeak was largely written in itself made it fairly easy to port to new systems, and it was quickly available on just about anything with a microchip.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure that I first saw Squeak at the OOPSLA conference in 1997. (Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages &amp;amp; Applications, since you asked) At this conference I somehow got to do a team-building exercise with Adelde Goldberg from the original Xerox PARC team, which is not relevant to anything but seemed very cool at the time. I was already using Smalltalk in my projects, but Squeak was immediately interesting and my extended research team started doing cool stuff. Like, what I’m pretty sure was the first Wiki tool outside the original C2 Wiki, was written in Squeak. (Apparently at least one is still running).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Smalltalk’s Environment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s important to understand that Smalltalk’s development is a different evolutionary tree from nearly every currently popular programming language, in that Smalltalk is in no way, shape, or form influenced by Unix or C. Perl, Ruby, Python, JavaScript, Swift, Kotlin and on and on, all come from a universe where they expect to run Unix libraries, and where C syntax is normal. The Unix philosophy of “small pieces, loosely joined” is not a part of Smalltalk’s DNA at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk is basically its own operating system, and the syntax is different from C-style languages in ways big and small. For example, the first element of an array is… 1. Which, when you think about how people count, actually makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s hard to separate Smalltalk the language from Smalltalk the environment, although I suppose technically you could have the language without the whole shebang (and I think there was a GNU Smalltalk that tried this), really the environment is part of the appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your main interfaces to the smalltalk system are a Workspace and a Browser. A workspace is analogous to REPL session, you can type in arbitrary Smalltalk code and have the system “do it” to execute the code, “print it” to execute the code and output the result. There are some other actions like “debug it” or “inspect it”, but that’s the basic idea. Unlike a Unix REPL, there’s no prompt, and you don’t automatically invoke code by hitting return, you have to select code and then invoke the menu item or the keyboard shortcut for the code you want to act on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Browser is where you write code. There a a few different versions in most Smalltalks, here’s the main one, this is from a modern Smalltalk called Cuis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the top, we have four window panes – left to right we have:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Categories – groups of classes that are related in some way. Cuis nicely puts each group in a pulldown list. Categories have no particular syntactic meaning, they are just there to make browsing easier.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Classes – one entry for each class in the currently selected category, at the bottom of this pane is a toggle for “class” vs. “instance” which determines what kinds of messages are shown in the next two panes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Protocols – a protocol is a user-defined group of messages. Smalltalk internally uses “message” rather than “method” because of how Alan Kay thinks about objects. Again, protocols are for the programmer, not the system.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Messages – each messages in the currently selected protocol is listed.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bottom pane is the code editor, and if a message is selected in the code pane, its code is displayed there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You probably have questions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does this mean that you can see the source code for the entire Smalltalk system?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, yes it does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;**Can you modify any code in the system? **&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, yes you can.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even, like, deep system code?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Isn’t that dangerous?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a Ruby developer, you should know that it’s only as dangerous as the developers who use it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How do you edit a message?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just display the existing message in the browser, edit the message and select “save”. The Smalltalk system will parse the code, stop if there are syntax errors, but if not, the updated method will be saved to the system. A side effect is you can’t save code that isn’t syntactically parsable, even as a draft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, but how do you create a message?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The “real” way is to select a protocol but not a message, and Smalltalk will put a template in the edit window. Write your message in the editor and save it. Alternately, you can just change the name of a message in the edit window, and a new method with that name will be created, without deleting the old message.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And how do you create a class?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you select a category and not a class, you’ll get this in the code editor pane:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Object subclass: #NameOfSubclass
	instanceVariableNames: ''
	classVariableNames: ''
	poolDictionaries: ''
	category: 'Kernel-Chronology'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thing to note is that this is not actually template, it’s actually code: a message, waiting for you to fill in the arguments, replacing &lt;code&gt;#NameOfSubclass&lt;/code&gt; and adding the instance variables and so on. You don’t save this, you “do it”, just like if you were in a workspace. The message call is evaluated, and Smalltalk creates a new class.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But wait, if all the code is in the image and isn’t in text files, how do people work together and share code?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t worry about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seriously, though, worry about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This has always been a problem. Smalltalk allows you to share “change sets”, effectively the code differences between one point and another. Classically, one person would export their change set, and other team members would import it. Different Smalltalks have built up more sophisticated tools over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Smalltalk’s Syntax&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk’s syntax is very simple, relative to Ruby and Perl.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wait a sec, I literally wrote this for a chapter in a book about Smalltalk literally 25 years ago, here’s a slight paraphrase:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every line of Smalltalk is evaluated the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Every variable is an object. There are no basic types that are not objects.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Every expression is a message being passed to an object, there is basically no expression syntax that is not a message.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;All messages return a value. (The return value is specified by&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;^&lt;/code&gt;, if the method does not specify a return value, it implicitly returns&lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt;, the instance that received the message.)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;There are three kinds of messages:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Unary messages like &lt;code&gt;3 negated&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Binary messages like &lt;code&gt;a + b&lt;/code&gt;, these actually are messages you can define, there is a small set of them, and they are special cases in the parser.&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Keyword messages such as &lt;code&gt;anArray at: 3 put: 7&lt;/code&gt;. This syntax got used by ObjectiveC and later Swift, so you may be familiar with it. It’s&lt;code&gt;receiver &amp;lt;messagepart&amp;gt;: &amp;lt;argument&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;where you can have multiple message parts. If you are referring to the message, typically you just say the message parts, so this message would be called&lt;code&gt;at:put:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unary messages like &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk does not have operator precedence. All code is evaluated strictly from left to right. Unary messages first, binary messages second, keyword messages last. Parenthesis can be used to force order of operations or to make things clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The assignment operator is&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;:=&lt;/code&gt;(Smalltalk uses&lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;for boolean equality), the right hand side is evaluated and the value is assigned to the result of the left hand side.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that’s basically it, with a couple of ways to create literals like strings, arrays, dictionaries, local variables, and blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, for 10 points and control of the board, what does this do?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;hypotenuse := 3 squared + 4 squared sqrt&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The unary messages are evaluated first:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;hypotenuse := 9 + 16 sqrt&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s still a unary message&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;hypotenuse := 9 + 4&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we can do the binary message:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;hypotenuse = 13&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get what you actually want, you need parentheses:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;hypotenuse := (3 squared + 4 squared) sqrt&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk does not have special syntax for loops, all loop behavior is defined by methods on &lt;code&gt;Array&lt;/code&gt; and the like, very similar to Ruby’s &lt;code&gt;Enumerable&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk does not have special syntax to create messages or classes. Message creation is managed by the editor (which internally calls a message that adds the new code), class creation is just another method – in Squeak, that method is &lt;code&gt;Object#subclass:instanceVariableNames:classVariableNames:poolDictionaries:category:&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk does not have special syntax for boolean logic, all logic behavior is defined by the classes &lt;code&gt;True&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;False&lt;/code&gt;. Ruby sort of does this, but Ruby does have &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; as special syntax. Smalltalk does not, you’d write a Smalltalk conditional as just another message:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(x &amp;gt; 10) ifTrue: [ x squared ] ifFalse: [ x sqrt ]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The square brackets are blocks, and behave very similar to Ruby blocks, except that you can treat them as just normal variables and normal arguments. You can even, as in this case, have multiple arguments that take blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The implementation if the method &lt;code&gt;ifTrue:ifFalse&lt;/code&gt; is simple. For the &lt;code&gt;True&lt;/code&gt; class, it just takes the true block and executes it by passing it the message &lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ifTrue: trueAlternativeBlock ifFalse: falseAlternativeBlock
	^trueAlternativeBlock value
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And for the false class, the exact opposite:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ifTrue: trueAlternativeBlock ifFalse: falseAlternativeBlock
	^falseAlternativeBlock value
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk doesn’t have a &lt;code&gt;case&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; statement, typically if you want behavior like that you’d define a dictionary of keys to blocks or you would use the object system and polymorphism and double dispatch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Smalltalk’s Object Model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a lot about Smalltalk’s object model that sound familiar to a Ruby developer:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There’s a base class called &lt;code&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt;that everything inherits from.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Instance variables are private. Getters and setters default to having the same name as the instance variable.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Method lookup happens at the point of the method call.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Classes are instances of the class &lt;code&gt;Class&lt;/code&gt;(sort of).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There’s a thing called a “Metaclass”&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There’s a method that’s the method of last resort – in Ruby, it’s &lt;code&gt;method_missing&lt;/code&gt;, but in Smalltalk it’s called&lt;code&gt;doesNotUnderstand&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are a couple of differences as well&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Smalltalk’s meta classes are structured differently, I explained this once and I’m not sure I ever want to explain it again.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Smalltalk doesn’t have multiple inheritance or mixins or modules or anything like that. Although there have been some attempts to add these features, the traditional Smalltalk way to do this is through delegation.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But overall, Smalltalk and Ruby are similar enough that a huge amount of Kent Beck’s Smalltalk Best Practice Patterns is applicable to Ruby as long as you translate the syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Happened?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike Perl, I actually did use Smallalk to build a few real applications that had real users. I miss it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I find that when I try to explain Smalltalk to people, it’s easy to explain the syntax and the object model. What’s hard to explain is how it is to work in a Smalltalk environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ve likely used powerful coding editors and terminals. Smalltalk is just different. You are in the running environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tests start instantly, and in general run very fast. There’s a dedicated test runner window. Some smalltalk integrate tests with the regular browser, so you can see test status from the code browsers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Debugging is amazing, you can investigate the state of any object in the system, you can change that state, you can easily execute arbitrary code. You can have a test halt on exception, update the code and re-run from the point failure. It’s hard to describe how fluid it is, especially since I’m no longer expert enough to do it fluently.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;While the editor doesn’t have all the niceties of the IDE’s you are used to, it’s very powerful in its own way. If you save code with a message name that does not appear in the image at all, Smalltalk will typically ask you if you want to define it right there. A lot of the things we ask a Language Server to do, Smalltalk just kind of does, because the image has access to everything.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the all-encompassing nature of the environment was also Smalltalk’s downfall. As more and more of the general computing environment became Unix and the “small pieces loosely joined” philosophy, Smalltalk got harder and harder to integrate. Smalltalk isn’t a scripting language, it was late to develop connectivity to external databases, its model of team interaction is fundamentally different from Unix source control. The image-based system has some drawbacks – you do get amazing access to the system, but it can be hard to tell where your code ends and the system begins. Code could depend on the state of the image in ways that were hard to replicate in deploys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Did Ruby Take From Smalltalk?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smalltalk’s legacy in Ruby is primarily the object model – the idea that everything is an object and everything is manageable via method calls, and that message calls are evaluated at the point of call, as late as possible. Ruby takes that idea and translates it into a syntax that is more familiar to programmers used to C/Perl/Java.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m not sure this is exactly on point as far as Smalltalk’s influence on Ruby, but my Ruby style has always been very aggressive about creating new classes and objects. I’m quite confident that a reason for that style is that I came from Smalltalk first and not Java, Smalltalk style is much more amenable to small classes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On my first largish Smalltalk project, users were simulating a chemical plant’s pipe system by placing tiles with pipes in them, and I frequently needed to do logic based on relative directions. I clearly remember creating a &lt;code&gt;Direction&lt;/code&gt; class with basically four live instances, &lt;code&gt;up&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;down&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;left&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;right&lt;/code&gt;, and just enough logic inside to say that &lt;code&gt;up.turn_left&lt;/code&gt; equals &lt;code&gt;left&lt;/code&gt;, but &lt;code&gt;down.turn_left&lt;/code&gt; equals &lt;code&gt;right&lt;/code&gt;. It was useful enough that I remember how much fun it was to build it even  now, nearly thirty years later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of all the other programming languages I’ve used, Ruby is the one that most clearly encourages that style of coding.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45823831</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 15:24:35 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>