<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 11:08:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Adaptive LLM routing under budget constraints</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21141</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="cc18340bf0f78482"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Machine Learning&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 28 Aug 2025]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:Adaptive LLM Routing under Budget Constraints&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:Large Language Models (LLMs) have revolutionized natural language processing, but their varying capabilities and costs pose challenges in practical applications. LLM routing addresses this by dynamically selecting the most suitable LLM for each query/task. Previous approaches treat this as a supervised learning problem, assuming complete knowledge of optimal query-LLM pairings. However, real-world scenarios lack such comprehensive mappings and face evolving user queries. We thus propose to study LLM routing as a contextual bandit problem, enabling adaptive decision-making using bandit feedback without requiring exhaustive inference across all LLMs for all queries (in contrast to supervised routing). To address this problem, we develop a shared embedding space for queries and LLMs, where query and LLM embeddings are aligned to reflect their affinity. This space is initially learned from offline human preference data and refined through online bandit feedback. We instantiate this idea through Preference-prior Informed Linucb fOr adaptive rouTing (PILOT), a novel extension of LinUCB. To handle diverse user budgets for model routing, we introduce an online cost policy modeled as a multi-choice knapsack problem, ensuring resource-efficient routing.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; IArxiv Recommender (What is IArxiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45094421</guid></item><item><title>One of Britain's largest stocks of second-hand books ever amassed</title><link>https://www.worldofinteriors.com/story/richard-axe-second-hand-books-yorkshire</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="fa91101555a054a1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of Britain’s largest stocks of second-hand books ever amassed can be found in the unlikeliest of locations: a vast former youth hostel in a pretty corner of the Yorkshire Dales. Meticulously sorted into subject areas, from naval history to 19th-century literature, architecture to zoology, over 150,000 volumes fill some 25 high-ceilinged rooms spread over four floors. To withstand the sheer weight of all those hardbacks, the building, which began life as a prep school in c1878, must surely be as strong as a Romanesque church.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Certainly the collection has been assembled with an almost religious zeal by sole trader Richard Axe, a spry 70-something who spoke to me from the Philippines, where he lives with his wife roughly half the year. Unlike the more commercially oriented of his peers, he has sold books primarily so that he could acquire more for himself. Of the Harrogate shop he owned prior to his move here he says: ‘Its main purpose was not to sell at all, but rather to buy and increase my buying profile.’ I had fondly imagined that Richard chose Aysgarth in order to lure customers from the nearby falls, a daytrippers’ magnet. But in fact, he says he’s never advertised, nor had more than four visitors per week, and all of them were by appointment. Yet very rarely did a week pass by without him shifting at least £1,000 worth of books.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So how did his business, which has been highly successful, operate? Most professionals in the field swim in the waters of either ‘good quality but relatively ordinary second-hand books’ or ‘very specialist, expensive antiquarian books’; Richard has ended up being a big fish in both streams. In his heyday, he would reckon to drive some 25,000 miles a year, attending auctions from Plymouth to Glasgow. There he’d bid for large lots, sometimes whole libraries, subsequently selling a handful of important titles to private customers and international dealers, while creaming off books for his own collection. Hence, in part, the appeal of North Yorkshire. Far from being ‘the back of beyond’, the A1, M1 and East Coast mainline railway offer superb connections. ‘I like the idea of being in the middle of the country.’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the eagle-eyed expert, the condition of a book is critical. Richard gives the example of Dickens – ‘incredibly popular in his own lifetime, and so a first edition in reasonably good nick might fetch £50. But a really fine copy could go for ten times that.’ As is the case with all antiques, the internet has had a polarising effect. In the past, you might have traipsed round bookshops for a lifetime not finding the missing piece in your authorial jigsaw, but often such editions previously thought rare can now be quite easily unearthed via online search engines, and so their value has slumped. ‘But what’s transpired is that things that are genuinely uncommon have shot up.’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The classic case is JK Rowling’s Harry Potter and the Philosopher’s Stone. Given that it was the first in the sequence, Bloomsbury, with no inkling of the monster the brand would become, published the smallest viable number of copies – 500 – in its first edition. It is thus truly rare, says Richard, much more so than a Jane Austen equivalent. As a consequence: ‘A fine copy is worth, certainly, £50,000.’ Similarly, photograph albums and manuscripts, by definition one-off items, have seen skyrocketing interest in cyberspace – and among a new, younger breed of collector to boot. Indeed, the most expensive item my interlocutor has ever sold was not a book at all, but a scrapbook owned by Cecil Beaton, which included the photographer’s own drawing of Mick Jagger, a personal friend, and sketches by Jean Cocteau.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Richard moved to his property in 2005, consolidating a warehouse, shop and large house in Harrogate, little structural work was required to the sturdily built edifice apart from new guttering, though he had to strip out rows of urinals and a few municipal-style kitchens. Inevitably, however, two men were employed full time for a year just building wooden shelves, which now stretch to a combined length of over a mile. The original plan was to carve out some domestic space in this behemoth of a building, but Richard states that mixing residence and business had potential VAT implications. And then there was the small issue of his ever-encroaching library… So he moved into the two-bedroom modern cottage previously inhabited by the youth-hostel manager. Presumably you had a no-book policy here, I ask Richard. ‘Well, if I did, it didn’t last,’ he replies ruefully. ‘Let’s just say it was restricted.’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Philosophical follies, such as doorknobs surreally attached to tree trunks, dot the unusual sculpture garden that Richard has proudly created out of a capacious paddock that’s part of the estate. In the middle of the pond sits an inaccessible table and chairs overhung with a metal fruit basket you also cannot reach. ‘It’s all about, you know, the unattainable.’ This modern take on the Tantalus myth strikes me as the perfect symbol for the avid collector, feverishly hunting down the final piece of a set, mourning the rarities that slipped through one’s fingers. The psychological make-up of the type emerged early on. Even as a Dulwich College scholarship boy, ‘I collected stamps rather more avidly than most.’ Later, at Bristol University, ‘I bought books initially to read, but the physical possession of having quite a lot, of having a substantial range of bookshelves, became important as a manifestation of knowledge and understanding and culture.’ Even now, he can find himself transfixed when, say, a history of signposts tumbles into his lap.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The physical demands of his job, combined with declining health, mean Richard ‘must face the facts of age’. With great reluctance, he is now selling his estate and collection, lock, stock and barrel, for around £1.5 million. His greatest fear is that the land, library and buildings get sold off bit by bit, ‘my life’s work just disappearing’. He is even prepared to play the role of éminence grise to the putative lucky buyer, sharing his contacts and experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what about the keepers? Surely, there are a few titles he’d like to hold on to? Well, there’s his extensive collection of antiquarian books on Yorkshire; those on another great love, football (‘though the Philippines is pretty much the only country in the world that doesn’t have an interest’); books on the fluctuatingly fashionable Ruskin, as well as 18th- and 19th-century folding maps that the chin-stroking aesthete might have consulted himself while hiking in the Lakes. Oh, and let’s not forget the collection of 1750s–1870s books in their original drab boards or cloth. ‘Cheaper to buy at the time, because they were unbound, they are now valuable because of their fragility.’ The bookseller’s eyes sparkle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To enquire about purchasing the property plus stock, ring Elaine Williams-Bird on 07798 818651 or email nellybirdpress@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45094692</guid></item><item><title>Implementing a Foil Sticker Effect</title><link>https://www.4rknova.com/blog/2025/08/30/foil-sticker</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7aab8b3d79ef373f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this post, I’ll walk you through how to create a custom shader in Three.js that simulates the look of a foil sticker, complete with angle-dependent iridescence and sparkling metallic flakes. The goal is to capture that premium, holographic effect you see on collectible stickers, trading cards, and high-end packaging, but to render it in real time directly in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Iridescence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever tilted a holographic sticker or watched sunlight catch on a soap bubble, you’ve seen iridescence in action. In the real world, this rainbow shimmer comes from thin-film interference. When light waves bounce between layers of a surface, some wavelengths are reinforced while others cancel out, causing colors to shift depending on your viewing angle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In real-time computer graphics, we don’t need to simulate the exact physics. Instead, we can approximate this by mapping view angle to hue, as the surface tilts relative to the camera, its color smoothly shifts through a spectrum. This gives that dynamic, “alive” quality you expect from foil stickers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Foil Flakes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alongside the shifting colors, there’s another key detail: foil flakes. Real metallic foils have tiny reflective particles embedded in them, creating hundreds of bright, sharp highlights that twinkle as you move. These aren’t smooth reflections but randomized sparkles, giving the surface its tactile, premium feel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To replicate this in a shader, we’ll introduce procedural noise to generate small random patches of brightness across the surface. When combined with lighting, they look like metallic specks catching the light. Together, angular hue shifts and flake sparkles create a convincing illusion of printed holographic foil without expensive rendering tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Implementation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This implementation simulates a peeling, iridescent sticker with foil flakes using Three.js. While I will borrow concepts such as metalness, roughness, and Fresnel from Physically Based Rendering (PBR), this shader is not physically based. The goal is to create a visually plausible, artistic effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below is a live demo of the shader, where you can modify its parameters and experiment with different configurations. Use your mouse to rotate the sticker around and see how the material reacts to the lighting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Vertex Shader&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vertex shader handles the peel geometry and passes useful information to the fragment shader.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Uniform / Varying&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Purpose&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uPeelAmount&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Overall peel strength (0 = flat, 1 = fully peeled).&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uPeelAngle&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Peel direction in degrees.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;vUv&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;vec2&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;UV coordinates for texture mapping.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;vWorldPos&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;vec3&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Vertex position in world space.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;vNormal&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;vec3&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Transformed normal for lighting.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;vAOIntensity&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Distance moved by vertex, used to darken lifted areas.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The shader goes through the following simple steps:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compute vector from hinge to current vertex.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Calculate the peel factor and angle.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Define the rotation axis and apply Rodrigues’ rotation formula to rotate the vertex around that axis.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apply the same rotation to the normal.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Calculate a fake ambient occlusion term.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the full vertex shader code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;uniform float uPeelAmount;  // Strength of peel (0.0 → no peel, 1.0 → full peel)
uniform float uPeelAngle;   // Peel angle in degrees (converted to radians in shader)
varying vec2  vUv;          // UV coordinates
varying vec3  vWorldPos;    // Vertex position in world space
varying vec3  vNormal;      // Transformed vertex normal
varying float vAOIntensity; // Ambient occlusion or peel intensity factor

void main() {
    vUv = vec2(uv.x, 1.0 - uv.y);
    vec3 pos = position;

    // Define hinge point for peel
    vec3 hinge = vec3(0.0, 0.0, 0.0);

    // Vector from hinge to current vertex
    vec3 toVertex = pos - hinge;

    // Peel factor calculation
    // Interpolates peel strength diagonally
    // (bottom-left → top-right)
    float peelFactor = (uv.x + uv.y) * 0.5;

    // Convert peel angle to radians
    // Final angle is scaled by peelAmount
    // and per-vertex peelFactor
    float radAngle = radians(uPeelAngle);
    float angle = radAngle * uPeelAmount * peelFactor;

    // Define rotation axis for peel
    // Diagonal axis pointing from top-left 
    // to bottom-right
    vec3 axis = normalize(vec3(-1.0, 1.0, 0.0));
    float cosA = cos(angle);
    float sinA = sin(angle);

    // Apply Rodrigues' rotation formula
    // Rotates the vertex around the diagonal axis
    vec3 rotated = toVertex * cosA +
                   cross(axis, toVertex) * sinA +
                   axis * dot(axis, toVertex) * (1.0 - cosA);

    // Update vertex position after rotation
    pos = hinge + rotated;

    // Rotate vertex normal the same way to
    // ensure lighting matches the peeled
    // geometry
    vec3 rotatedNormal = normal * cosA +
                         cross(axis, normal) * sinA +
                         axis * dot(axis, normal) * (1.0 - cosA);

    // Transform normal into view space
    vNormal = normalize(normalMatrix * rotatedNormal);

    // Transform vertex to world space
    vec4 worldPos = modelMatrix * vec4(pos, 1.0);
    vWorldPos = worldPos.xyz;

    // Ambient Occlusion term based on distance moved
    // from original vertex position
    vAOIntensity = length(toVertex - rotated);

    // Final projection
    gl_Position = projectionMatrix * viewMatrix * worldPos;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fragment Shader&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fragment shader handles all lighting, reflections, iridescence, and foil flakes. It layers procedural effects to create a rich, dynamic look.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Uniform&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Type&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Purpose&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sampler2D&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sticker albedo + alpha.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;envMap2D&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sampler2D&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Environment map for reflections.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uCameraPos&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;vec3&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Camera position for view vector.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uAlphaCutoff&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Discard pixels below this alpha.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uFlakesEnabled&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Toggle foil flakes.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uFlakeSize&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Size of flakes.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uFlakeReduction&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Randomness threshold for flakes.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uFlakeThreshold&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Brightness threshold to show flakes.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uFlakeBrightness&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Base brightness of flakes.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uMetalness&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;PBR-like metal reflectivity control.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uRoughness&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Controls reflection sharpness.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uEnvIntensity&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Scales environment contribution.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uMetalmask&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mask controlling metallic regions.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;uIridescence&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Strength of angle-dependent rainbow effect.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;uIriMin&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;uIriRange&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Range for simulated film thickness.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;uPeelAmount&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;uPeelAngle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;float&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Peel geometry info for shading.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is how this works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Alpha cutoff to discard transparent pixels early.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Back-face shading to render the rear surface as plain white or darkened, depending on peel.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Foil flakes are computed using procedural noise. Normals are perturbed slightly to create sparkle variation. The environment map is sampled to get an iridescent tint.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Iridescence (thin-film approximation) is calculated using sine-based waves to shift hue by view angle.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Environment reflections are modulated by Fresnel.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Final shading combines diffuse base, reflections, iridescence, and flakes.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the full vertex shader code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;precision highp float;

#define PI  3.14159265

varying vec2 vUv;
varying vec3 vNormal;
varying vec3 vWorldPos;
varying float vAOIntensity;

uniform sampler2D map;      // sticker albedo + alpha
uniform sampler2D envMap2D; // LDR equirectangular environment

uniform vec3  uCameraPos;
uniform float uAlphaCutoff;
uniform float uMaxMip;
uniform float uFlakesEnabled;
uniform float uFlakeSize;
uniform float uFlakeReduction;
uniform float uFlakeThreshold;
uniform float uFlakeBrightness;
uniform float uPeelAmount;
uniform float uPeelAngle;
uniform float uMetalness;
uniform float uRoughness;
uniform float uEnvIntensity;
uniform float uMetalmask;
uniform float uIridescence;
uniform float uIriMin;
uniform float uIriRange;

float hash(vec2 p) {
    return fract(sin(dot(p, vec2(127.1, 311.7))) * 43758.5453123);
}

// Map 3D dir to 2D equirect UV
vec2 dirToEquirectUv(vec3 dir) {
    dir = normalize(dir);
    float phi = atan(dir.z, dir.x);
    float theta = acos(clamp(dir.y, -1.0, 1.0));
    return vec2((phi + 3.14159265) / (2.0 * 3.14159265), theta / 3.14159265);
}

vec3 sampleEnvRough(vec3 R, float roughness) {
    vec2 uv = dirToEquirectUv(R);

    // Map roughness to LOD level
    float lod = roughness * uMaxMip;
    vec3 color = texture2DLodEXT(envMap2D, uv, lod).rgb;

    return color;
}

// Iridescence / thin-film color
vec3 iridescenceColor(float cosTheta) {
    float thickness = uIriMin + uIriRange * (1.0 - cosTheta);
    float phase = 6.28318 * thickness * 0.01; // scaled for visuals
    vec3 rainbow = 0.5 + 0.5 * vec3(sin(phase), sin(phase + 2.094), sin(phase + 4.188));
    return mix(vec3(1.0), rainbow, uIridescence);
}

// Convert RGB to perceived luminance (Rec.709)
float luminance(vec3 color) {
    return dot(color, vec3(0.2126, 0.7152, 0.0722));
}

void main() {

    vec4 base = texture2D(map, vUv);
    if(base.a &amp;lt; uAlphaCutoff)
        discard;

    if(!gl_FrontFacing) {
        float col = 1.0;
        if(uPeelAngle &amp;gt; 0.0) {
            col = mix(1.0, 0.2, vAOIntensity);
        }
        // Render back side as white
        gl_FragColor = vec4(vec3(col), base.a);
        return;
    }

    vec3 N = normalize(vNormal);
    vec3 V = normalize(uCameraPos - vWorldPos);
    vec3 R = reflect(-V, N);

    // Ambient occlusion / peel shadow
    float peelShadow = 0.0;

    if(uPeelAngle &amp;lt; 0.0) {
        peelShadow = smoothstep(0.0, 0.3, vAOIntensity);
        base.rgb *= mix(1.0, 0.3, peelShadow);
    }

    // Flakes
    float flakeIntensity = 0.0;
    vec3 flakeEnv = vec3(0.0);

    float brightness = luminance(base.rgb);

    if(uFlakesEnabled &amp;gt; 0.5) {
        // Procedural flake mask
        float flake = hash(floor(vUv * uFlakeSize));
        float flakeMask = smoothstep(uFlakeReduction, 1.0, flake);

        // Base brightness influence
        float flakeBoost = smoothstep(uFlakeThreshold, 1.0, brightness);

        // Perturbed flake normal
        float angleOffset = (hash(vec2(flake, flake + 3.0)) - 0.5) * 0.25;
        vec3 perturbedNormal = normalize(N + vec3(angleOffset, 0.0, angleOffset));

        // Reflection for sparkle
        vec3 PR = reflect(-V, perturbedNormal);

        // Dynamic flicker factor (only brightens, never darkens)
        float flakePhase = hash(floor(vUv * uFlakeSize) + floor(PR.xy * 15.0));
        float phaseMod = mix(1.0, 1.8, flakePhase);
        
        // Core sparkle factor (glimmer preserved)
        float flakeSpec = pow(clamp(dot(perturbedNormal, V) * 0.5 + 0.5, 0.0, 1.0), 8.0);
        flakeSpec = max(flakeSpec, 0.15); // always visible

        // Environment tint (never too dark, controlled by uniform)
        float flakeRough = clamp(uRoughness * 0.4, 0.0, 1.0);
        flakeEnv = sampleEnvRough(PR, flakeRough) * mix(0.9, 1.2, brightness);
        flakeEnv = max(flakeEnv, vec3(uFlakeBrightness));

        vec3 flakeIri = iridescenceColor(dot(perturbedNormal, V));
        flakeEnv *= mix(vec3(1.0), flakeIri, 0.9);

        // Final intensity
        flakeIntensity = flakeMask * flakeBoost * flakeSpec * phaseMod * 18.0;
        flakeIntensity = clamp(flakeIntensity, 0.0, 1.0);
    }

    // Final roughness modulation
    float finalRough = clamp(mix(uRoughness, 1.0, flakeIntensity), 0.0, 1.0);

    // Environment reflection
    vec3 env = sampleEnvRough(R, finalRough) * uEnvIntensity;

    // Blend in flake environment contribution
    env = mix(env, flakeEnv, clamp(flakeIntensity, 0.0, 1.0));

    // Fresnel term
    float cosTheta = clamp(dot(N, V), 0.0, 1.0);
    float F0 = mix(0.04, 1.0, uMetalness);
    float fres = F0 + (1.0 - F0) * pow(1.0 - cosTheta, 5.0);

    // Iridescence
    float metalicMask = mix(uMetalmask, 1.0, brightness);
    vec3 iriCol = iridescenceColor(cosTheta) * metalicMask;

    // Final color
    vec3 diffuse = base.rgb * (1.0 - uMetalness);
    vec3 spec = env * fres * iriCol * (1.0 - finalRough * 0.85);
    vec3 color = diffuse + spec;

    gl_FragColor = vec4(color, base.a);
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Licensing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code in this page is licensed under Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0). Feel free to share and adapt the code for non-commercial purposes with proper attribution. If you wish to use the code commercially, please contact me for a separate license agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45095460</guid></item><item><title>The future of 32-bit support in the kernel</title><link>https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/1035727/4837b0d3dccf1cbb/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="744b991fd8863dfd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The future of 32-bit support in the kernel&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;[LWN subscriber-only content]&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Nobody covers the Linux kernel like LWN; be in the know with a one-month trial subscription, no credit card needed.People naturally think about desktop machines first, he continued. If you were running Linux in the 1990s, you had a 32-bit, desktop system. Unix systems, though, moved to 64-bit platforms around 30 years ago, and the Linux desktop made that move about 20 years ago. Even phones and related devices have been 64-bit for the last decade. If those systems were all that Linux had to support, 32-bit support would have long since been removed from the kernel. He summarized the situation with this slide, showing how the non-embedded architectures have transitioned to either 64-bit or nonexistence over time:&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The world is not all desktops — or servers — though; embedded Linux exists as well. About 90% of those systems are running on Arm processors. The kernel has accumulated a lot of devicetree files describing those systems over the years; only in this last year has the number of devicetrees for armv8 (64-bit) systems exceeded the number for armv7 (32-bit) systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Arm processors with pre-armv7 architectures, there are only three for which it is still possible to buy hardware, but a number are still supported by the kernel community:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many other pre-armv7 CPUs are out of production, but the kernel still has support for them. Of those, he said, there are about ten that could be removed now. It would be nice to be able to say that support for the others will be removed after a fixed period, ten years perhaps, but hardware support does not work that way. Instead, one has to think in terms of half lives; every so often, it becomes possible to remove support for half of the platforms. It all depends on whether there are users for the processors in question.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The kernel is still adding support for some 32-bit boards, he said, but at least ten new 64-bit boards gain support for each 32-bit one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are a number of non-Arm 32-bit architectures that still have support in the kernel; these include arc, microblaze, nios2, openrisc, rv32, sparc/leon, and xtensa. All of them are being replaced by RISC-V processors in new products. RISC-V is what you use if you don't care about Arm compatibility, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Then, there is the dusty corner where nommu (processors without a memory-management unit) live; these include armv7-m, m68k, superh, and xtensa. Nobody is building anything with this kind of hardware now, and the only people who are working on them in any way are those who have to support existing systems. "&lt;quote&gt;Or to prove that it can be done&lt;/quote&gt;." &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are still some people who need to run 32-bit applications that cannot be updated; the solution he has been pushing people toward is to run a 32-bit user space on a 64-bit kernel. This is a good solution for memory-constrained systems; switching to 32-bit halves the memory usage of the system. Since, on most systems, almost all memory is used by user space, running a 64-bit kernel has a relatively small cost. Please, he asked, do not run 32-bit kernels on 64-bit processors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are some definite pain points that come with maintaining 32-bit support; most of the complaints, he said, come from developers in the memory-management subsystem. The biggest problem there is the need to support high memory; it is complex, and requires support throughout the kernel. High memory is needed when the kernel lacks the address space to map all of the installed physical memory; that tends to be at about 800MB on 32-bit systems. (See this article for more information about high memory).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Currently the kernel is able to support 32-bit systems with up to 16GB of installed memory. Such systems are exceedingly rare, though, and support for them will be going away soon. There are a few 4GB systems out there, including some Chromebooks. Systems with 2GB are a bit more common. Even these systems, he said, are "&lt;quote&gt;a bit silly&lt;/quote&gt;" since the memory costs more than the CPU does. There are some use cases for such systems, though. Most 32-bit systems now have less than 1GB of installed memory. The kernel, soon, will not try to support systems with more than 4GB. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are some ideas out there for how to support the larger-memory 32-bit systems without needing the high-memory abstraction. Linus Walleij is working on entirely separating the kernel and user-space address spaces, giving each 4GB to work with; this is a variant on the "4G/4G" approach that has occasionally been tried for many years. It is difficult to make such a system work efficiently, so this effort may never succeed, Bergmann said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another approach is the proposed "densemem" memory model, which does some fancy remapping to close holes in the physical address space. Densemem can support up to 2GB and is needed to replace the SPARSEMEM memory model, the removal of which which will eventually be necessary in any case. This work has to be completed before high memory can be removed; Bergmann said that he would be interested in hearing from potential users of the densemem approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One other possibility is to drop high memory, but allow the extra physical memory to be used as a zram swap device. That would not be as efficient as accessing the memory directly, but it is relatively simple and would make it possible to drop the complexity of high memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, there is the year-2038 problem, which he spent several years working on. The kernel-side work was finished in 2020; the musl C library was updated that same year, and the GNU C Library followed the year after. Some distributors have been faster than others to incorporate this work; Debian and Ubuntu have only become year-2038-safe this year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The year-2038 problem is not yet completely solved, though; there are a lot of packages that have unfixed bugs in this area. Anything using futex(), he said, has about a 50% chance of getting time handling right. The legacy 32-bit system calls, which are not year-2038 safe, are still enabled in the kernel, but they will go away at some point, exposing more bugs. There are languages, including Python and Rust, that have a lot of broken language bindings. Overall, he said, he does not expect any 32-bit desktop system to survive the year-2038 apocalypse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A related problem is big-endian support, which is also 32-bit only, and also obsolete. Its removal is blocked because IBM is still supporting big-endian mainframe and PowerPC systems; as long as that support continues, big-endian support will stay in the kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; A number of other types of support are under discussion. There were once 32-bit systems with more than eight CPUs, but nobody is using those machines anymore, so support could be removed. Support for armv4 processors, such as the DEC StrongARM CPU, should be removed. Support for early armv6 CPUs, including the omap2 and i.mx31, "&lt;quote&gt;complicates everything&lt;/quote&gt;"; he would like to remove it, even though there are still some Nokia 770 systems in the wild. The time is coming for the removal of all non-devicetree board files. Removal of support for Cortex M CPUs, which are nommu systems, is coming in a couple of years. Developers are eyeing i486 CPU support, but that will not come out yet. Bergmann has sent patches to remove support for KVM on 32-bit CPUs, but there is still "&lt;quote&gt;one PowerPC user&lt;/quote&gt;", so that support will be kept for now. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To summarize, he said, the kernel will have to retain support for armv7 systems for at least another ten years. Boards are still being produced with these CPUs, so even ten years may be optimistic for removal. Everything else, he said, will probably fade away sooner than that. The removal of high-memory support has been penciled in for sometime around 2027, and nommu support around 2028. There will, naturally, need to be more discussion before these removals can happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An audience member asked how developers know whether a processor is still in use or not; Bergmann acknowledged that it can be a hard question. For x86 support, he looked at a lot of old web pages to make a list of which systems existed, then showed that each of those systems was already broken in current kernels for other reasons; the lack of complaints showed that there were no users. For others, it is necessary to dig through the Git history, see what kinds of changes are being made, and ask the developers who have worked on the code; they are the ones who will know who is using that support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Another person asked about whether the kernel would support big-endian RISC-V systems. Bergmann answered that those systems are not supported now, and he hoped that it would stay that way. "&lt;quote&gt;With RISC-V, anybody can do anything, so they do, but it is not always a good idea&lt;/quote&gt;". The final question was about support for nommu esp32 CPUs; he answered that patches for those CPUs exist, but have not been sent upstream. Those processors are "&lt;quote&gt;a cool toy&lt;/quote&gt;", but he does not see any practical application for them. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The slides for this talk are available. The curious may also want to look at Bergmann's 2020 take on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; [Thanks to the Linux Foundation, LWN's travel sponsor, for supporting my travel to this event.]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Index entries for this article&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kernel&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Architectures&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Conference&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Open Source Summit Europe/2025&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Posted Sep 1, 2025 19:55 UTC (Mon) by jrtc27 (subscriber, #107748) [Link] (4 responses) I don't understand this point. 64-bit big-endian systems exist in the form of sparc64 and s390x (and powerpc64, though that's less of a thing given powerpc64le). Posted Sep 1, 2025 21:47 UTC (Mon) by mjw (subscriber, #16740) [Link] (3 responses) Posted Sep 1, 2025 22:27 UTC (Mon) by sam_c (subscriber, #139836) [Link] (1 responses) (Of course, BE isn't the future, I just don't think the platforms are all rotting near-universally as 32-bit ones are on average.) Posted Sep 2, 2025 8:07 UTC (Tue) by arnd (subscriber, #8866) [Link] For the moment, the problems are mainly in newly written code, where portability to both big-endian and 32-bit targets relies on someone actively testing those and submitting fixes. This is in contrast to nommu and highmem systems that no longer have the same level of commercial backing and are much further into the inevitable bitrot. [I believe the article citing "big-endian support, which is also 32-bit only" was a transcription error in an otherwise excellent report -- what I actually said is that the majority of big-endian (embedded) systems are 32-bit, while pointing to s390x/powerpc64 servers as the ones that keep them viable.] Posted Sep 2, 2025 7:05 UTC (Tue) by glaubitz (subscriber, #96452) [Link] Does IBM already know that s390x is supposed to be obsolete now? Posted Sep 1, 2025 19:58 UTC (Mon) by jrtc27 (subscriber, #107748) [Link] (2 responses) That's not really true. Halving is the limit of what you could hope to achieve, if every data type in your system was a machine word or pointer. But char, short, int and long long don't change, (u)intNN_t don't change, and float/double don't change, so depending on what data you're actually operating on you can see anywhere between almost no change (e.g. some purely computational workload on large amounts of raw data) and halving the memory usage. Posted Sep 1, 2025 20:24 UTC (Mon) by arnd (subscriber, #8866) [Link] (1 responses) I had expected to see a much smaller difference between the two environments like you describe, the numbers I saw for anything I tried were always roughly 100% overhead for the 64-bit code compared to armhf. I think this is a combination of multiple effects I measured in addition to the obvious sizeof(long) difference: arm64 has longer instruction words than armv7/thumb2, small malloc() calls are aligned to larger cache lines (128 vs 64 bytes), ELF sections have a larger default alignment (64K vs 4K), etc. For many real workloads, a larger portion of RAM if of course going to be filled with the same user data (text, video, sensor input, network packages, ...) so the difference becomes smaller; for the most memory constrained systems, 100% overhead is surprisingly good estimate that holds true for both kernel data and userland. Posted Sep 2, 2025 5:59 UTC (Tue) by jrtc27 (subscriber, #107748) [Link] Posted Sep 1, 2025 20:03 UTC (Mon) by jrtc27 (subscriber, #107748) [Link] (7 responses) Unfortunately people are building those systems and others are proposing supporting them[1]. It is a real shame this is the approach that's being taken rather than having dedicated byte-swapping load/store instructions to accelerate processing big-endian data structures like network packets, which is the main use case that I'm aware of, outside of being compatible with old software written for big-endian mainframes. [1] https://lore.kernel.org/all/20250822165248.289802-1-ben.d... Posted Sep 2, 2025 7:06 UTC (Tue) by glaubitz (subscriber, #96452) [Link] (6 responses) Why is this unfortunate? I don't understand. Is Linux supposed to run only on architectures that a small group of people likes? Posted Sep 2, 2025 7:55 UTC (Tue) by jrtc27 (subscriber, #107748) [Link] (5 responses) What I have a problem with is needless fragmentation and needless complexity within one specific architecture, in this case RISC-V. Sometimes the right design choice is to say no to options. Nobody was building big-endian RISC-V hardware, nobody was seriously writing big-endian RISC-V software and everything was just fine, but now everyone is expected to support yet another variant of RISC-V that doesn't really achieve anything except create a whole lot of work. It's not some new and interesting architecture that approaches things differently that happens to be big-endian, it is just RISC-V but with big-endian because nobody was willing to say no. Posted Sep 2, 2025 8:06 UTC (Tue) by glaubitz (subscriber, #96452) [Link] (4 responses) I wasn't actually looking at the username and only realized now it was you ;-). &amp;gt; What I have a problem with is needless fragmentation and needless complexity within one specific architecture, in this case RISC-V. I think this is a developer-centric perspective rather than a user-centric perspective. If there are legitimate use cases such as building open-source networking hardware based on RISC-V, then it should be legitimate to add big-endian support if someone is willing to maintain it. Posted Sep 2, 2025 8:43 UTC (Tue) by arnd (subscriber, #8866) [Link] (3 responses) Adding big-endian Armv8 support to Linux made sense in 2013 as users were still porting software from big-endian MIPS/Octeon or PowerPC/QorIQ systems, but it ended up being a mistake for the same reason that Jessica explained about RISC-V: it's an extra ABI that requires testing resources in order to keep running, for very little practical use. Now that all the Linux networking applications moved to arm64le, the only remaining use case for arm64be is to have an easily available platform find and fix endianness bugs, typically in a VM guest running on a LE host. This means we can't easily remove from the arm64 kernel, but it would still be a mistake to add it to riscv64 Linux. Posted Sep 2, 2025 9:01 UTC (Tue) by glaubitz (subscriber, #96452) [Link] (1 responses) How do you know that? Posted Sep 2, 2025 9:14 UTC (Tue) by arnd (subscriber, #8866) [Link] Additionally, all newer networking SoCs come with SystemReady certification these days, but SystemReady requires booting in little-endian UEFI mode rather than the traditional Linux boot interface that supports both big-endian and little-endian kernels. Posted Sep 2, 2025 10:19 UTC (Tue) by pabs (subscriber, #43278) [Link] Posted Sep 1, 2025 20:53 UTC (Mon) by ajb (subscriber, #9694) [Link] (6 responses) There are also going to be many products where it doesn't make much difference whether an ancient processor or an up to date riscv is used, and manufacturers are very likely to continue to choose ones where the licence fee is already paid off. Posted Sep 1, 2025 22:11 UTC (Mon) by smoogen (subscriber, #97) [Link] (4 responses) Posted Sep 2, 2025 1:44 UTC (Tue) by willy (subscriber, #9762) [Link] (2 responses) Posted Sep 2, 2025 4:56 UTC (Tue) by ajb (subscriber, #9694) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Sep 2, 2025 9:56 UTC (Tue) by hailfinger (subscriber, #76962) [Link] The three options for such vendors are: Posted Sep 2, 2025 7:30 UTC (Tue) by taladar (subscriber, #68407) [Link] Posted Sep 1, 2025 22:54 UTC (Mon) by iabervon (subscriber, #722) [Link] Posted Sep 2, 2025 0:42 UTC (Tue) by wileypob (subscriber, #139361) [Link] Posted Sep 2, 2025 2:44 UTC (Tue) by wtarreau (subscriber, #51152) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Sep 2, 2025 6:06 UTC (Tue) by jrtc27 (subscriber, #107748) [Link] Posted Sep 2, 2025 6:30 UTC (Tue) by andy_shev (subscriber, #75870) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Sep 2, 2025 7:33 UTC (Tue) by taladar (subscriber, #68407) [Link] Posted Sep 2, 2025 7:04 UTC (Tue) by glaubitz (subscriber, #96452) [Link] (1 responses) Neither M68k nor SuperH are nommu only. That statement is simply incorrect. And people are actually building new m68k-based hardware with the help of FPGAs. The retro community around the Amiga, Atari, Macintosh 68k as well as SuperH-based video game consoles such as the Sega Saturn and especially the Sega Dreamcast. Not sure why this article is so much focused on commercial applications. And I don't think big-endian targets are going to be obsolete any time soon unless someone convinces IBM to drop s390x. Posted Sep 2, 2025 10:52 UTC (Tue) by DrMcCoy (subscriber, #86699) [Link] They're not running Linux on these systems, though, are they? &lt;head&gt;64-bit big-endian&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;64-bit big-endian&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; The slides don't say that big-endian is 32-bit only, but "Equally obsolete as 32-bit".&lt;head&gt;64-bit big-endian&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;64-bit big-endian&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;64-bit big-endian&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Not all types are words / pointers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Not all types are words / pointers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Not all types are words / pointers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Big-endian RISC-V&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Big-endian RISC-V&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Big-endian RISC-V&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Big-endian RISC-V&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Big-endian RISC-V&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Big-endian RISC-V&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Big-endian RISC-V&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Big-endian RISC-V&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;longevity&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;longevity&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;longevity&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;longevity&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;longevity&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; 1. maintain an older kernel indefinitely (good luck with that, especially now that older upstream-unsupported kernels won't get CVEs allocated for security issues)&lt;lb/&gt; 2. work hard on keeping the affected chipses supported by the mainline kernel&lt;lb/&gt; 3. scrap their designs and start anew from another incopmatible design (not worth the effort)&lt;head&gt;longevity&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;longevity&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Embedded systems&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;MIPS ?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;MIPS ?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Industrial computers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Industrial computers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;M68k and SuperH are MMU ports!&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;M68k and SuperH are MMU ports!&lt;/head&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45095475</guid></item><item><title>Thoughts on (Amazonian) leadership</title><link>https://www.daemonology.net/blog/2025-09-01-Thoughts-on-Amazonian-Leadership.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d7850520cbaafdc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Thoughts on (Amazonian) Leadership&lt;/head&gt;Amazon's Leadership Principles are famous, not just within Amazon but also in the tech world at large. While they're frequently mocked — including by Amazonians — they're also generally sensible rules by which to run a company. I've been an Amazon customer for over 25 years and an AWS customer for almost 20 years, and also an AWS Hero for 6 years, and while I've never worked for Amazon I feel that I've seen behind the curtain enough to offer some commentary on a few of these principles.&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt; Customer Obsession: Leaders start with the customer and work backwards. They work vigorously to earn and keep customer trust. Although leaders pay attention to competitors, they obsess over customers. &lt;lb/&gt;Customer Obsession is great, but I often see Amazonians taking this too simplistically: "Start with the customer" doesn't have to mean "ask customers what they want and then give them faster horses". In the early days of AWS I saw a lot of what I call "cool engineering driven" products: When EC2 launched, it wasn't really clear what people would do with it, but it was very cool and it was clear that it could be a big deal in some form, sooner or later. Some time around 2012, the culture in AWS seemed to shift from "provide cool building blocks" to "build what customers are asking for" and in my view this was a step in the wrong direction (mind you, not nearly as much as the ca. 2020 shift to "build what analysts are asking for in quarterly earnings calls").&lt;p&gt;This tension of what customers are asking for vs what customers really need shows up in areas like resilience. Amazon's "Well-Architected Framework" strongly exhorts customers to avoid building production workloads in a single Availability Zone — but Amazon's cross-AZ bandwidth pricing is painful, and Amazon doesn't provide useful tools for building durable multi-AZ applications. Most customers are not going to implement Paxos, and very few customers — certainly not executives who are removed from actual development processes — are going to ask Amazon for Paxos-as-a-service; but if Amazonians sat down and asked themselves "what do customers need in order to design their applications well" they could probably come up with several services which Amazon already has internally. AWS should return to its roots and release important building blocks — the things customers will need, not necessarily what they're asking for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt; Ownership: Leaders are owners. They think long term and don't sacrifice long-term value for short-term results. They act on behalf of the entire company, beyond just their own team. They never say "that's not my job." &lt;lb/&gt;This principle is both too narrow, and not being fulfilled, in my view. It's not enough to simply act on behalf of the entire company: It's important to act on behalf of the entire technological ecosystem. Some Amazonians are great at this — I recently commited patches to FreeBSD's bhyve because an Amazonian was putting together a standard for interrupt handling in large VMs, and even though Amazon doesn't make any use of bhyve (at least, I don't think it does!) he understood the importance of getting standards widely accepted across the entire virtualization space rather than narrowly in the code Amazon relied upon. There's a saying in computer security, that anything which makes one of us less secure makes all of us less secure: Attackers will leverage an exploit against one system to allow them to attack another system. While the same does not directly apply in other fields, working with others to produce the best results for everyone will be much better in the long-term than focusing solely on what Amazon needs right now.&lt;p&gt;But in general Amazon doesn't even live up to its stated (narrow) promise of having leaders acting on behalf of the entire company — it's simply too siloed. Amazon is famously secretive, and this applies internally as well as externally: When AWS launches two similar services, it's often because two teams didn't know what each other was working on. How can leaders act across the entire company if nobody knows what's happening outside of their team? They can't; and if Amazon wants to allow its best people to be true Owners, Amazon needs to start breaking down walls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt; Bias for Action: Speed matters in business. Many decisions and actions are reversible and do not need extensive study. We value calculated risk taking. &lt;lb/&gt;Amazonians talk about "one-way doors" and "two-way doors", and it is quite true that many decisions are can be reversed... but that doesn't always mean that there is no cost associated with reversing a decision. There is a clear and widely recognized tension between "Bias for Action" and another principle, "Insist on the Highest Standards"; but there is also a tension between this and earning and keeping customer trust. When AWS ships a service which is half-baked, it diminishes customer trust in AWS as a whole; even if the problems in that service ultimately get corrected (either by fixing them or in some cases by simply getting rid of a service which should never have existed in the first place) the memory of a failed launch will live on in customers' minds for years to come.&lt;p&gt;During my seven-year tenure as FreeBSD Security Officer, people knew me as the guy sending out security advisories; but the most important thing I did was not to ship Security Advisories — that is, it was to stop the train and say "no, we are not going to send this out yet". I knew that for all the importance of getting patches into people's hands in a timely manner, it was even more important to establish trust: If I gave people a broken patch, even once, they would be much slower to install security updates in the future. My team became familiar with the phrase "convince me that this is correct", and I'd like to see more of that at senior levels of Amazon: Principal and Distinguished Engineers need to step in with a bias for inaction, and use the respect they have earned to stop projects which do not meet the highest standards before they undermine trust. Amazon's hiring process famously includes "bar raisers" who can veto hiring decisions; they should also have service bar raisers who can veto launches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45095545</guid></item><item><title>Amazon has mostly sat out the AI talent war</title><link>https://www.businessinsider.com/amazon-ai-talent-wars-internal-document-2025-8</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="cf8db5f163666cc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Amazon struggles to attract AI talent due to its pay model and perception of falling behind others.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Amazon's compensation model has long caused complaints from employees.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Competitors like Meta and OpenAI offer more attractive packages for AI engineers.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the AI talent war sweeps across Silicon Valley, Amazon has largely sat on the sidelines. A confidential internal document, and accounts from people familiar with the matter, reveal why.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company has flagged its unique pay structure, lagging AI reputation, and rigid return-to-office rules as major hurdles. Now, the tech giant is being pushed to rethink its recruiting strategy as it scrambles to compete for top talent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The document, from late last year, was written by the HR team covering Amazon's non-retail businesses, including Amazon Web Services, advertising, devices, entertainment, and the newly formed artificial general intelligence team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"GenAI hiring faces challenges like location, compensation, and Amazon's perceived lag in the space," the document noted. "Competitors often provide more comprehensive and aggressive packages." Business Insider obtained a copy of the document.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon's absence from recent splashy AI hires underscores those concerns. Meta has pulled in high-profile talent from ScaleAI, Apple, and OpenAI. Google and OpenAI continue to be top destinations for AI experts, while Microsoft has even drafted a wish list of Meta AI employees it hopes to recruit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon's spokesperson initially told BI that the company continues to "adapt our approach to remain highly competitive, maintaining flexibility in both our compensation packages and work arrangements to attract and retain the best AI talent in this dynamic market."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hours later, the spokesperson updated the statement, saying the premise of the story was "wrong," without providing any specifics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We continue to attract and retain some of the best people in the world and they're building and deploying GenAI applications at a rapid clip. Our compensation is competitive, but we also want missionaries who are passionate about inventing things that will make a meaningful difference for customers — for those kinds of people, there's no better place in the world to build."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Door desks and 'egalitarian' pay&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon is famously frugal. One of its origin stories recounts how the company bought cheap doors from Home Depot and hacked them together as office desks. This became guiding symbol of Amazon's cautious spending, with founder Jeff Bezos still using door desks today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This penny-pinching culture has smashed straight into an AI hiring battle that's being fueled by unprecedented spending, putting Amazon in a tricky situation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The internal document described compensation as one of the "hotly debated topics" among Amazon recruiters, citing the company's strict use of fixed salary bands for each role. Amazon's "egalitarian philosophy" on pay leaves its offers "below par" compared with top rivals, it added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The lack of salary range increases for several key job families over the past few years does not position Amazon as an employer of choice for top tech talent," the document warned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Amazon, missing out on top AI talent is a potential risk. The pool of top-tier AI researchers and engineers is limited, and without experts with deep knowhow, it's hard to compete at the frontier of the field. Indeed, Amazon has yet to find a blockbuster AI product like OpenAI's ChatGPT or Anthropic's Claude, although its Bedrock AI cloud service has made progress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon's pay structure has been a long-standing source of tension.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Several people who spoke to Business Insider cited the 2020 departure of Amazon robotics VP Brad Porter as evidence of the company's frugal approach hampering talent recruitment and retention. Porter left in part after Amazon refused to raise his pay band.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon's stock vesting schedule is also heavily backloaded, a structure that can be less attractive to new hires. The policy extends even to top executives, who generally receive no cash bonuses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;'Voting with their feet'&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to highlighting Amazon's "perceived lag in the AI space," the internal document said generative AI has further intensified the competition for specialized talent, particularly individuals with expertise in large language models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An August report from venture capital firm SignalFire shows Amazon is on the lower end of engineering retention, far below Meta, OpenAI, and Anthropic. Jarod Reyes, SignalFire's head of developer community, told Business Insider that Amazon rivals are making bigger strides in AI, across open models, foundational research, and developer tooling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Amazon hasn't clearly positioned itself as a leader in the generative AI wave," Reyes said. "Engineers are paying attention and they're voting with their feet."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some investors share that view. On Amazon's earnings call last month, Morgan Stanley analyst Brian Nowak pressed CEO Andy Jassy on Wall Street's "narrative right now that AWS is falling behind" in AI and fears of losing market share to rivals. Jassy's response fell flat, sending Amazon's stock lower during the call.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon intends to tackle these concerns. According to the document, the company will refine its "compensation and location strategy" and host more events designed to highlight its generative AI capabilities. It also intends to set up dedicated recruiting teams for generative AI within business units like AWS to boost efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;'Hubs' constrain talent&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another point of contention is Amazon's aggressive return-to-office mandate, which has already caused logistical issues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company's new "hub" policy — which requires employees to relocate to a central office or risk termination — has further limited its access to "high-demand talent like those with GenAI skills," according to the internal document.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Hubs constrain market availability," it stated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon is exploring ways to allow for more "location-flexible" roles, the document added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon's spokesperson told BI that the company is "always looking for ways to optimize our recruiting strategies and looking at alternate talent rich locations."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon hasn't been entirely on the sidelines. Last year, it brought on Adept CEO David Luan as part of a licensing deal with the AI startup. Luan now heads Amazon's AI agents lab. But the company has also seen departures, including senior AI leaders like chip designer Rami Sinno and VP Vasi Philomin, who worked on Bedrock.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One Amazon recruiter told Business Insider that a growing number of job candidates started declining offers last year because of the company's RTO policy. Even if a competitor pays less, people are open to taking the job if they can stay remote, this person said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We are losing out on talent," this person added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, Bloomberg reported recently that Oracle has hired away more than 600 Amazon employees in the past two years because Amazon's strict RTO policy has made poaching easier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Staying the course&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The internal Amazon document dates to late last year, leaving open the possibility that the company has since adjusted its compensation approach to make exceptions for top AI talent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, multiple people familiar with the situation told Business Insider there haven't been any formal updates to internal pay guidelines. One current Amazon manager said it remains almost impossible for the company to enact sweeping changes, given its long track record of sticking to the existing system. The people who spoke with Business Insider asked not to be identified discussing sensitive matters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Based on how we run our business and what we have achieved, there are more risks than potential benefits from changing an approach that has been so successful for our shareholders over the past several decades," Amazon wrote this year about executive compensation in its annual proxy statement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, the AI talent war may end up being an expensive and misguided strategy, stoked by hype and investor over-exuberance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the high-profile recruits Meta recently lured have already departed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a tip? Contact this reporter via email at ekim@businessinsider.com or Signal, Telegram, or WhatsApp at 650-942-3061. Use a personal email address, a nonwork WiFi network, and a nonwork device; here's our guide to sharing information securely.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45095603</guid></item><item><title>Patrick Winston: How to Speak (2018) [video]</title><link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Unzc731iCUY</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7055905545553646"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Press Copyright Contact us Creators Advertise Developers Terms Privacy Policy &amp;amp; Safety How YouTube works Test new features NFL Sunday Ticket © 2025 Google LLC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45095849</guid></item><item><title>The buyer-pull and seller-push theories of sales</title><link>https://howtogrow.substack.com/p/the-physics-of-sales</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45096254</guid></item><item><title>Raspberry Pi 5 support (OpenBSD)</title><link>https://marc.info/?l=openbsd-cvs&amp;m=175675287220070&amp;w=2</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e73f12d23de611fc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;quote&gt;[prev in list] [next in list] [prev in thread] [next in thread] List: openbsd-cvs Subject: CVS: cvs.openbsd.org: src From: Marcus Glocker &amp;lt;mglocker () cvs ! openbsd ! org&amp;gt; Date: 2025-09-01 18:56:04 Message-ID: dd1203a530237b22 () cvs ! openbsd ! org [Download RAW message or body] CVSROOT: /cvs Module name: src Changes by: mglocker@cvs.openbsd.org 2025/09/01 12:56:04 Modified files: distrib/arm64/iso: Makefile distrib/arm64/ramdisk: Makefile install.md list Log message: Add Raspberry Pi 5 Model B support for RAMDISK. Known issues: * Booting from PCIe storage HATs doesn't work because of missing U-Boot support. * WiFi on the Raspberry Pi 5 Model B "d0" boards doesn't work. * The active cooler (fan) doesn't work because of missing pwm/clock drivers (some work is in-progress). ok kettenis@, deraadt@ [prev in list] [next in list] [prev in thread] [next in thread] &lt;/quote&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Configure |
About |
News |
Add a list |
Sponsored by KoreLogic&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45096585</guid></item><item><title>Kazeta: An operating system that brings the console gaming experience of 90s</title><link>https://kazeta.org/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="859b1d2912326fbb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;An operating system that brings the console gaming experience of the '90s to modern PC hardware and games: insert cart, power on, play.&lt;/p&gt;Explore Kazeta&lt;p&gt;An operating system that brings the console gaming experience of the '90s to modern PC hardware and games: insert cart, power on, play.&lt;/p&gt;Explore Kazeta&lt;p&gt;Insert a game cart, press power, and you're gaming instantly. Relive that nostalgic golden age where nothing stood between you and the games you love.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transform your digital library into something tangible and permanent. Create physical game carts from your DRM-free titles and build a collection that you can play forever.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Say goodbye to the complexities of modern gaming and just play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Save data is captured automatically, so you never lose progress. When no cart is inserted, boot into a retro console inspired BIOS menu to manage your saves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Play almost any DRM-free game from platforms past or present.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bring back the family-friendly simplicity of gaming's distant past. Perfect for kids, parents, and grandparents who just want to play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Download Kazeta today and rediscover the joy of pure gaming.&lt;/p&gt;Download Now&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45098269</guid></item><item><title>Apple pulls iPhone torrent app from AltStore PAL in Europe</title><link>https://www.theverge.com/news/767344/apple-removes-itorrent-altstore-pal-ios-marketplace</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a484c98b531e11d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple has removed the iPhone torrenting client, iTorrent, from AltStore PAL’s alternative iOS marketplace in the EU, showing that it can still exert control over apps that aren’t listed on the official App Store. iTorrent developer Daniil Vinogradov told TorrentFreak that Apple has revoked his distribution rights to publish apps in any alternative iOS stores, but it seems the issue is related to government sanctions, rather than a block on torrenting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Apple pulls iPhone torrent app from AltStore PAL in Europe&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;iTorrent’s developer has been blocked from distributing apps on alternative iOS stores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;iTorrent’s developer has been blocked from distributing apps on alternative iOS stores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a statement to The Verge, Apple spokesperson Peter Ajemian said, “Notarization for this app was removed in order to comply with government sanctions-related rules in various jurisdictions. We have communicated this to the developer.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While Apple bans torrent apps on its own iOS store, the EU’s Digital Markets Act gave iPhone users within the bloc greater freedom to install apps from third-party app stores that the Cupertino company doesn’t directly manage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last month, Vinogradov said on iTorrent’s GitHub page that Apple “removed Alternative Distribution functionality from iTorrent’s Developer Portal without any warning.” Apple didn’t provide a reason for the removal, according Vinogradov, and distribution was revoked at the Apple Dev Account level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update, August 28th: Added a statement from Apple.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45098411</guid></item><item><title>FreeDroidWarn</title><link>https://github.com/woheller69/FreeDroidWarn</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a7a090d3f3147310"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This library shows an alert dialog with a deprecation warning informing that Google will require developer verification for Android apps outside the Play Store from 2026/2027 which the developer is not going to provide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Google has announced that, starting in 2026/2027, all apps on certified Android devices
will require the developer to submit personal identity details directly to Google.
Since the developers of this app do not agree to this requirement, this app will no longer 
work on certified Android devices after that time.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.androidauthority.com/android-developer-verification-requirements-3590911/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://developer.android.com/developer-verification&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add the JitPack repository to your root build.gradle at the end of repositories:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;allprojects {
  repositories {
    ...
    maven { url 'https://jitpack.io' }
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add the library dependency to your build.gradle file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;dependencies {
    implementation 'com.github.woheller69:FreeDroidWarn:V1.3'
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In onCreate of your app just add:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;     FreeDroidWarn.showWarningOnUpgrade(this, BuildConfig.VERSION_CODE);

&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This library is licensed under the GPLv3.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45098722</guid></item><item><title>WinBoat: Run Windows apps on Linux with seamless integration</title><link>https://github.com/TibixDev/winboat</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="39bff56e5f27b5dc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WinBoat is currently in beta, so expect to occasionally run into hiccups and bugs. You should be comfortable with some level of troubleshooting if you decide to try it, however we encourage you to give it a shot anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🎨 Elegant Interface: Sleek and intuitive interface that seamlessly integrates Windows into your Linux desktop environment, making it feel like a native experience&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📦 Automated Installs: Simple installation process through our interface - pick your preferences &amp;amp; specs and let us handle the rest&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🚀 Run Any App: If it runs on Windows, it can run on WinBoat. Enjoy the full range of Windows applications as native OS-level windows in your Linux environment&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🖥️ Full Windows Desktop: Access the complete Windows desktop experience when you need it, or run individual apps seamlessly integrated into your Linux workflow&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📁 Filesystem Integration: Your home directory is mounted in Windows, allowing easy file sharing between the two systems without any hassle&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;✨ And many more: Smartcard passthrough, resource monitoring, and more features being added regularly&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before running WinBoat, ensure your system meets the following requirements:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;RAM: At least 4 GB of RAM&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CPU: At least 2 CPU threads&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Storage: At least 32 GB free space in &lt;code&gt;/var&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Virtualization: KVM enabled in BIOS/UEFI&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Docker: Required for containerization&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Docker Compose v2: Required for compatibility with docker-compose.yml files&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Docker User Group: Add your user to the &lt;code&gt;docker&lt;/code&gt;group&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;FreeRDP: Required for remote desktop connection (Please make sure you have Version 3.x.x with sound support included)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Kernel Modules: &lt;code&gt;iptables&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;iptable_nat&lt;/code&gt;modules must be loaded&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can download the latest Linux builds under the Releases tab. We currently offer two variants:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AppImage: A popular &amp;amp; portable app format which should run fine on most distributions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unpacked: The raw unpacked files, simply run the executable (&lt;code&gt;linux-unpacked/winboat&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Podman is unsupported for now&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Docker Desktop is unsupported for now&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Distros that emulate Docker through a Podman socket are unsupported&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Any rootless containerization solution is currently unsupported&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For building you need to have NodeJS and Go installed on your system&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clone the repo (&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/TibixDev/WinBoat&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Install the dependencies (&lt;code&gt;npm i&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Build the app and the guest server using &lt;code&gt;npm run build:linux-gs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can now find the built app under &lt;code&gt;dist&lt;/code&gt;with an AppImage and an Unpacked variant&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make sure you meet the prerequisites&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Additionally, for development you need to have NodeJS and Go installed on your system&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clone the repo (&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/TibixDev/WinBoat&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Install the dependencies (&lt;code&gt;npm i&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Build the guest server (&lt;code&gt;npm run build-guest-server&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Run the app (&lt;code&gt;npm run dev&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contributions are welcome! Whether it's bug fixes, feature improvements, or documentation updates, we appreciate your help making WinBoat better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please note: We maintain a focus on technical contributions only. Pull requests containing political/sexual content, or other sensitive/controversial topics will not be accepted. Let's keep things focused on making great software! 🚀&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Feel free to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Report bugs and issues&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Submit feature requests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Contribute code improvements&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Help with documentation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Share feedback and suggestions&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check out our issues page to get started, or feel free to open a new issue if you've found something that needs attention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WinBoat is licensed under the MIT license&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These past few years some cool projects have surfaced with similar concepts, some of which we've also taken inspirations from.&lt;lb/&gt; They're awesome and you should check them out:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WinApps&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cassowary&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;dockur/windows (🌟 Also used in WinBoat)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🌐 Website: winboat.app&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🐦 Twitter/X: @winboat_app&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🦋 Bluesky: winboat.app&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🗨️ Discord: Join our community&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📧 Email: staff@winboat.app&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45099124</guid></item><item><title>Keyboards from my collection (2023)</title><link>https://aresluna.org/50-keyboards-from-my-collection/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7f544c11e59d1554"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marcin Wichary&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;12 February 2023 / 50 posts / 60 photos&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;50 keyboards from my collection&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is an archive of a Mastodon thread from 2023. You can still read the thread (and all the replies) at its original location, however the photo quality is much better on this page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To celebrate the Kickstarter for Shift Happens going well, I thought I would show you 50 keyboards from my collection of really strange/esoteric/meaningful keyboards that I gathered over the years. (It might be the worldâs strangest keyboard collection!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is technically a bit of a spoiler for the book, but a) a lot of them are not in the book, and b) the book comes out in half a year, and weâll all forget by then! &lt;lb/&gt;Letâs start!&lt;lb/&gt;Shift Happens on Kickstarter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Letâs start!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shift Happens on Kickstarter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1.&lt;lb/&gt;I have a SafeType, thanks to a friend who noticed one about to be thrown away. This is among the most notable and interesting âergonomicâ keyboards, complete with mirrors that help you orient yourself when youâre starting out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have a SafeType, thanks to a friend who noticed one about to be thrown away. This is among the most notable and interesting âergonomicâ keyboards, complete with mirrors that help you orient yourself when youâre starting out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2.&lt;lb/&gt;The Comfort System keyboard is another âergonomicâ device that is honestly pretty frightening to look at (explaining the challenge of making keyboards like these). You can reposition and reorient each of the three parts independently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Comfort System keyboard is another âergonomicâ device that is honestly pretty frightening to look at (explaining the challenge of making keyboards like these). You can reposition and reorient each of the three parts independently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3.&lt;lb/&gt;I love these DataDesk Little Fingers keyboards with smaller keys because you can see exactly when iMac was introduced and how the company tried to âredesignâÂ the keyboard to fit the new style.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love these DataDesk Little Fingers keyboards with smaller keys because you can see exactly when iMac was introduced and how the company tried to âredesignâÂ the keyboard to fit the new style.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4.&lt;lb/&gt;This is another Mac âalternate universeâ keyboard - an Adesso ergonomic keyboard that feels like âwhat if Apple Adjustable still existed when iMac came aroundâ?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is another Mac âalternate universeâ keyboard - an Adesso ergonomic keyboard that feels like âwhat if Apple Adjustable still existed when iMac came aroundâ?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;5.&lt;lb/&gt;This strange âmedicalâ keyboard is more mechanical than youâd expect! I wrote more about it here: A tale of three skeuomorphs. Cleaning required when flashing!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This strange âmedicalâ keyboard is more mechanical than youâd expect! I wrote more about it here: A tale of three skeuomorphs. Cleaning required when flashing!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;6.&lt;lb/&gt;Once youâre done with your shift (no pun intended) at the hospital, how about some Pizza? This is i-Opener, one of the many shortlived internet appliances, this one with a gimmick that keeps on gimmicking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once youâre done with your shift (no pun intended) at the hospital, how about some Pizza? This is i-Opener, one of the many shortlived internet appliances, this one with a gimmick that keeps on gimmicking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;7.&lt;lb/&gt;Speaking of spacebar-adjacent gimmicks, I am mildly obsessed with how beautiful is this first NeXT keyboard from 1987, with a bunch of cool subtle things including a Command *bar* underneath the spacebar. As a matter of fact, I just finished writing an essay on it today!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of spacebar-adjacent gimmicks, I am mildly obsessed with how beautiful is this first NeXT keyboard from 1987, with a bunch of cool subtle things including a Command *bar* underneath the spacebar. As a matter of fact, I just finished writing an essay on it today!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;8.&lt;lb/&gt;This is Olivetti Praxis 48: perhaps one of the most beautiful among the most beautiful typewriters, and strangely similar in palette to the above NeXT keyboard. You could turn on this (electric) typewriter just by pressing any key. Thatâs pretty wild.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is Olivetti Praxis 48: perhaps one of the most beautiful among the most beautiful typewriters, and strangely similar in palette to the above NeXT keyboard. You could turn on this (electric) typewriter just by pressing any key. Thatâs pretty wild.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;9.&lt;lb/&gt;This Olympia Reporter typewriter is not beautiful, but it has a lot of POWER THIS and POWER THAT keys that celebrate its marriage with electricity? Why is X and some other keys red? Those are the ones that auto repeat!â¨&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This Olympia Reporter typewriter is not beautiful, but it has a lot of POWER THIS and POWER THAT keys that celebrate its marriage with electricity? Why is X and some other keys red? Those are the ones that auto repeat!â¨&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10.&lt;lb/&gt;This is another typewriter, so proud of a functioning (erasing!) Backspace that it gives this a treatment I have never seen before or after.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is another typewriter, so proud of a functioning (erasing!) Backspace that it gives this a treatment I have never seen before or after.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;11.&lt;lb/&gt;This Turkish typewriter (another Olympia!) means so much to me â the small success of this article from 2015 was probably what was needed for me to start thinking about the book: What I learned about languages just by looking at a Turkish typewriter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This Turkish typewriter (another Olympia!) means so much to me â the small success of this article from 2015 was probably what was needed for me to start thinking about the book: What I learned about languages just by looking at a Turkish typewriter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;12.&lt;lb/&gt;This keypadâ¦ is so bad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This keypadâ¦ is so bad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;13.&lt;lb/&gt;This was meant to be mounted atop Commodore 64 (which I donât have), an interesting reversal from the early typewriters being nothing more than repurposed music keyboards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was meant to be mounted atop Commodore 64 (which I donât have), an interesting reversal from the early typewriters being nothing more than repurposed music keyboards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;14.&lt;lb/&gt;These two are taking this idea even further â mount these overlays on regular keyboards to turn them into new kinds of interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These two are taking this idea even further â mount these overlays on regular keyboards to turn them into new kinds of interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;15.&lt;lb/&gt;Thereâs also professional gaming. It was cheaper for me to buy QSENN keyboards and replicate what professional StarCraft gamers were doing in the 1990s, than to find a good existing photo of one of these keyboards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thereâs also professional gaming. It was cheaper for me to buy QSENN keyboards and replicate what professional StarCraft gamers were doing in the 1990s, than to find a good existing photo of one of these keyboards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;16.&lt;lb/&gt;And speaking of gaming â weâre all used to the thumb style of typing from the first photo that it was fun to discover the short moment where the gaming keyboards looked like the one in the second photo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And speaking of gaming â weâre all used to the thumb style of typing from the first photo that it was fun to discover the short moment where the gaming keyboards looked like the one in the second photo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;17.&lt;lb/&gt;And a bit earlier, some game consoles tried to reinvent themselves as home computers with keyboard accessories. This is among the strangest of them: a âkeyboardâ to add BASIC to the Atari 2600.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And a bit earlier, some game consoles tried to reinvent themselves as home computers with keyboard accessories. This is among the strangest of them: a âkeyboardâ to add BASIC to the Atari 2600.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;18.&lt;lb/&gt;I commissioned this âjoystickâ from @benjedwards and I am so happy with how it turned out. Itâs technically a joystick without a stick, but software turned it into a one-key keyboard. Itâs F11, currently mapped to muting/unmuting in Zoom. Itâs *incredibly* rewarding to press.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I commissioned this âjoystickâ from @benjedwards and I am so happy with how it turned out. Itâs technically a joystick without a stick, but software turned it into a one-key keyboard. Itâs F11, currently mapped to muting/unmuting in Zoom. Itâs *incredibly* rewarding to press.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;19.&lt;lb/&gt;Speaking of strange keyboards, this is my âspace cadetâ keyboard â a mini keyboard that outputs only spaces, and instead of legends, each key *feels* different. Wrote about it more here: Stop me if youâve seen this one before&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of strange keyboards, this is my âspace cadetâ keyboard â a mini keyboard that outputs only spaces, and instead of legends, each key *feels* different. Wrote about it more here: Stop me if youâve seen this one before&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;20.&lt;lb/&gt;And here is a keyboard I built and hid in my shoes, made for one very specific reason. Are you interested what it is? Check out the whole story here: To walk among keyboard magicians&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here is a keyboard I built and hid in my shoes, made for one very specific reason. Are you interested what it is? Check out the whole story here: To walk among keyboard magicians&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;21.&lt;lb/&gt;This is one of the most rare keyboards I have âÂ the strange abKey Evolution imported through a friend from Singapore â a keyboard that tried to reinvent perhaps one thing too many. Wrote more about it here: The worst keyboard ever made&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is one of the most rare keyboards I have âÂ the strange abKey Evolution imported through a friend from Singapore â a keyboard that tried to reinvent perhaps one thing too many. Wrote more about it here: The worst keyboard ever made&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;22.â¨&lt;lb/&gt;And this one from Commodore is not really that unique, except it has this fun property âÂ it reverses the usual beige colour scheme making the keys inside darker. Itâs kinda neat!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And this one from Commodore is not really that unique, except it has this fun property âÂ it reverses the usual beige colour scheme making the keys inside darker. Itâs kinda neat!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;23.&lt;lb/&gt;This is a really cheap Bulgarian keyboard with such a poor build quality it cannot be unseen! I wrote more about it here: The worst keyboard ever made&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a really cheap Bulgarian keyboard with such a poor build quality it cannot be unseen! I wrote more about it here: The worst keyboard ever made&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;24.&lt;lb/&gt;Oh, it gets worse. This calculator keyboard is so cheap itâs not a keyboard at all â just an exposed PCB with a pen to complete the circuit. More about it here: The worst keyboard ever made&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oh, it gets worse. This calculator keyboard is so cheap itâs not a keyboard at all â just an exposed PCB with a pen to complete the circuit. More about it here: The worst keyboard ever made&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;25.&lt;lb/&gt;And this is the opposite, an incredibly well-built IBM Model F banking typewriter with an enclosure made out of zinc. Hefty enough to stop a bank robbery? Perhaps. More here: To save a keyboard, pt. 2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And this is the opposite, an incredibly well-built IBM Model F banking typewriter with an enclosure made out of zinc. Hefty enough to stop a bank robbery? Perhaps. More here: To save a keyboard, pt. 2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Halfway through! I need a bit of a break. Is this interesting? Should I keep going!?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;26.&lt;lb/&gt;If your bank robbery goes poorly, you probably end up typing on this Swintec, transparent so that no contraband could be hidden inside. More about transparent tech for prisons in this Techmoan video: YouTube&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your bank robbery goes poorly, you probably end up typing on this Swintec, transparent so that no contraband could be hidden inside. More about transparent tech for prisons in this Techmoan video: YouTube&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;27.&lt;lb/&gt;This simple braille keyboard â Tellatouch â was gorgeous and important. Type a key on one side, and the right braille letter assembles itself on the other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This simple braille keyboard â Tellatouch â was gorgeous and important. Type a key on one side, and the right braille letter assembles itself on the other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;28.&lt;lb/&gt;This is a more modern version of an adjacent idea. Connect this device to a phone line, and you can speak even if you cannot talk. (Also, I just love any time a keyboard lands itself next to a segmented display.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a more modern version of an adjacent idea. Connect this device to a phone line, and you can speak even if you cannot talk. (Also, I just love any time a keyboard lands itself next to a segmented display.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;29.&lt;lb/&gt;The creators of this Seiko keyboard recognized a watch with a keyboard wouldnât make sense â so you could dock your watch and type this way. (I donât have the watch itself. Too expensive!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The creators of this Seiko keyboard recognized a watch with a keyboard wouldnât make sense â so you could dock your watch and type this way. (I donât have the watch itself. Too expensive!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;30.&lt;lb/&gt;Just kidding! Hereâs a keyboard on another Seiko watch. Itâs an index keyboard â you donât touch the keys directly, just move the cursor left and right like on Apple TV âÂ since the keys are smaller than 1mm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just kidding! Hereâs a keyboard on another Seiko watch. Itâs an index keyboard â you donât touch the keys directly, just move the cursor left and right like on Apple TV âÂ since the keys are smaller than 1mm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;31.&lt;lb/&gt;This TI calculator for school use has tiny keysâ¦ in between other keys. What a strange thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This TI calculator for school use has tiny keysâ¦ in between other keys. What a strange thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;32.&lt;lb/&gt;This calculator wentâ¦ a different way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This calculator wentâ¦ a different way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;33.&lt;lb/&gt;I love hybrid things and in-betweeners. This tiny Panasonic Toughbook asks a question: what if a BlackBerry keyboard, but twice the width?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love hybrid things and in-betweeners. This tiny Panasonic Toughbook asks a question: what if a BlackBerry keyboard, but twice the width?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;34.&lt;lb/&gt;This one, for TermiFlex, is a one-hand operation, inspired by phone keypads. There are three shifts under your long fingers!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one, for TermiFlex, is a one-hand operation, inspired by phone keypads. There are three shifts under your long fingers!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;35.&lt;lb/&gt;Speaking of complex shortcuts, look at this Apple keyboard with Avid software keycaps. The icon on Z is my favourite. I donât even wanna know what this function does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of complex shortcuts, look at this Apple keyboard with Avid software keycaps. The icon on Z is my favourite. I donât even wanna know what this function does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;36.&lt;lb/&gt;One among many foldable keyboards â this one for Palm devices (RIP).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One among many foldable keyboards â this one for Palm devices (RIP).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;37.&lt;lb/&gt;This Sony remote had a built-in keyboard for typing in MiniDisc titles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This Sony remote had a built-in keyboard for typing in MiniDisc titles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;38.&lt;lb/&gt;And *this* Sony keyboard had two numeric keypads going in two different directions! One for typical calculator use, and one inspired by mobile phones to allow to chat as easily for people who got used to chatting that way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And *this* Sony keyboard had two numeric keypads going in two different directions! One for typical calculator use, and one inspired by mobile phones to allow to chat as easily for people who got used to chatting that way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;39.&lt;lb/&gt;Very happy (and also maybe also a little concerned) to report I am in possession of the entire ProHance lineup of the strange pointing device/keyboard hybrids!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Very happy (and also maybe also a little concerned) to report I am in possession of the entire ProHance lineup of the strange pointing device/keyboard hybrids!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;40.&lt;lb/&gt;But itâs amazing how rarely the graphical user interfaces and keyboards intersect. This here â an old AT&amp;amp;T terminal keyboard â is an exception, providing dedicated keys for window management.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But itâs amazing how rarely the graphical user interfaces and keyboards intersect. This here â an old AT&amp;amp;T terminal keyboard â is an exception, providing dedicated keys for window management.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;41.&lt;lb/&gt;I had to get this keyboard for a now-obscure Harris word processor, just because LOOK AT THE SHAPE OF THIS ENTER KEY.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had to get this keyboard for a now-obscure Harris word processor, just because LOOK AT THE SHAPE OF THIS ENTER KEY.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;42.&lt;lb/&gt;I have seen so many keyboards, but only this one â from a strange titling device meant to be connected to your TV âÂ treats uppercase and lowercase exactly like all the other shifted and unshifted symbols. (With the exception of keyboards for kids, I assume!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have seen so many keyboards, but only this one â from a strange titling device meant to be connected to your TV âÂ treats uppercase and lowercase exactly like all the other shifted and unshifted symbols. (With the exception of keyboards for kids, I assume!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;43.&lt;lb/&gt;Back in the day, keyboards were so expensive that you often started on a âtrainingâ keyboard that came without the machine connected to it. Hereâs a training keyboard for a Linotype, which is itself a fascinating machine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back in the day, keyboards were so expensive that you often started on a âtrainingâ keyboard that came without the machine connected to it. Hereâs a training keyboard for a Linotype, which is itself a fascinating machine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;44.&lt;lb/&gt;Hereâs another one for the first popular line of desk calculators that predates a 10-key keypad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hereâs another one for the first popular line of desk calculators that predates a 10-key keypad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;45.&lt;lb/&gt;(I also have the actual calculator, called a Comptometer. Itâs beautiful, really fun to use, and honestly a work of art. A truly impressive machine from the bygone era. I bought it because I was so impressed reading what it can do.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(I also have the actual calculator, called a Comptometer. Itâs beautiful, really fun to use, and honestly a work of art. A truly impressive machine from the bygone era. I bought it because I was so impressed reading what it can do.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;46.&lt;lb/&gt;Hereâs another practice keyboard, with a record to play to teach you how to type!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hereâs another practice keyboard, with a record to play to teach you how to type!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;47.&lt;lb/&gt;And hereâs the most modern version of a practice keyboard I know of â itself a small computer. After that, the likes of Mavis Beacon took over teaching typing in software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And hereâs the most modern version of a practice keyboard I know of â itself a small computer. After that, the likes of Mavis Beacon took over teaching typing in software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;48.&lt;lb/&gt;Speaking of the 1980s, keyboards from failed computers often found a second life as Radio Shack components you could reuse in your DIY projects. Hereâs one from a home computer called Coleco Adam.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of the 1980s, keyboards from failed computers often found a second life as Radio Shack components you could reuse in your DIY projects. Hereâs one from a home computer called Coleco Adam.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;49.&lt;lb/&gt;While weâre speaking about failed computers, this is One Laptop Per Childâs interesting-looking keyboard. (I think OLPC is considered a failure? Iâm not 100% sure. This computer is not in the book, so I havenât researched that carefully.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While weâre speaking about failed computers, this is One Laptop Per Childâs interesting-looking keyboard. (I think OLPC is considered a failure? Iâm not 100% sure. This computer is not in the book, so I havenât researched that carefully.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;50. And here is Canon Cat, maybe my favourite failed machine of all time. Look at these Leap keys! Iâm somewhat in love with this machine.&lt;lb/&gt;Adult-onset felinophilia&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adult-onset felinophilia&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thatâs it! I hope you liked this sneak peek of my collectionâ if you did, consider backing the book since this is the level of quality Iâve been aiming at for the visual sideâ¦ there are a lot more photos like these, and of course a lot more great stories attached to them. &lt;lb/&gt;Shift Happens on Kickstarter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shift Happens on Kickstarter&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45099192</guid></item><item><title>Collecting All Causal Knowledge</title><link>https://causenet.org/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ef076201388bcbc9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Collecting All Causal Knowledge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CauseNet aims at creating a causal knowledge base that comprises all human causal knowledge and to separate it from mere causal beliefs, with the goal of enabling large-scale research into causal inference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;CauseNet: Towards a Causality Graph Extracted from the Web&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Causal knowledge is seen as one of the key ingredients to advance artificial intelligence. Yet, few knowledge bases comprise causal knowledge to date, possibly due to significant efforts required for validation. Notwithstanding this challenge, we compile CauseNet, a large-scale knowledge base of claimed causal relations between causal concepts. By extraction from different semi- and unstructured web sources, we collect more than 11 million causal relations with an estimated extraction precision of 83\% and construct the first large-scale and open-domain causality graph. We analyze the graph to gain insights about causal beliefs expressed on the web and we demonstrate its benefits in basic causal question answering. Future work may use the graph for causal reasoning, computational argumentation, multi-hop question answering, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Download&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We provide three versions of our causality graph CauseNet:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CauseNet-Full: The complete dataset&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CauseNet-Precision: A subset of CauseNet-Full with higher precision&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CauseNet-Sample: A small sample dataset for first explorations and experiments without provenance data&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Statistics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Relations&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Concepts&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;File Size&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CauseNet-Full&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11,609,890&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12,186,195&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1.8GB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CauseNet-Precision&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;199,806&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;80,223&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;135MB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CauseNet-Sample&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;264&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;524&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;54KB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Data Model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core of CauseNet consists of causal concepts which are connected by causal relations. Each causal relation has comprehensive provenance data on where and how it was extracted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Examples of Causal Relations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Causal relations are represented as shown in the following example. Provenance data is omitted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
    "causal_relation": {
        "cause": {
            "concept": "disease"
        },
        "effect": {
            "concept": "death"
        }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For CauseNet-Full and CauseNet-Precision, we include comprehensive provenance data. In the following, we give one example per source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For relations extracted from natural language sentences we provide:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;surface&lt;/code&gt;: the surface form of the sentence, i.e., the original string&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;path_pattern&lt;/code&gt;: the linguistic path pattern used for extraction&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;ClueWeb12 Sentences&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;clueweb12_page_id&lt;/code&gt;: page id as provided in the ClueWeb12 corpus&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;clueweb12_page_reference&lt;/code&gt;: page reference as provided in the ClueWeb12 corpus&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;clueweb12_page_timestamp&lt;/code&gt;: page access data as stated in the ClueWeb12 corpus&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
    "causal_relation":{
        "cause":{
            "concept":"smoking"
        },
        "effect":{
            "concept":"disability"
        }
    },
    "sources":[
        {
            "type":"clueweb12_sentence",
            "payload":{
                "clueweb12_page_id":"urn:uuid:4cbae00e-8c7f-44b1-9f02-d797f53d448a",
                "clueweb12_page_reference":"http://atlas.nrcan.gc.ca/site/english/maps/health/healthbehaviors/smoking",
                "clueweb12_page_timestamp":"2012-02-23T21:10:45Z",
                "sentence": "In Canada, smoking is the most important cause of preventable illness, disability and premature death.",
                "path_pattern":"[[cause]]/N\t-nsubj\tcause/NN\t+nmod:of\t[[effect]]/N"
            }
        }
    ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Wikipedia Sentences&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;wikipedia_page_id&lt;/code&gt;: the Wikipedia page id&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;wikipedia_page_title&lt;/code&gt;: the Wikipedia page title&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;wikipedia_revision_id&lt;/code&gt;: the Wikipedia revision id of the last edit&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;wikipedia_revision_timestamp&lt;/code&gt;: the timestamp of the Wikipedia revision id of the last edit&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;sentence_section_heading&lt;/code&gt;: the section heading where the sentence comes from&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;sentence_section_level&lt;/code&gt;: the level where the section heading comes from&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
    "causal_relation":{
        "cause":{
            "concept":"human_activity"
        },
        "effect":{
            "concept":"climate_change"
        }
    },
    "sources":[
        {
            "type":"wikipedia_sentence",
            "payload":{
                "wikipedia_page_id":"13109",
                "wikipedia_page_title":"Global warming controversy",
                "wikipedia_revision_id":"860220175",
                "wikipedia_revision_timestamp":"2018-09-19T04:52:18Z",
                "sentence_section_heading":"Global warming controversy",
                "sentence_section_level":"1",
                "sentence": "The controversy is, by now, political rather than scientific: there is a scientific consensus that climate change is happening and is caused by human activity.",
                "path_pattern":"[[cause]]/N\t-nmod:agent\tcaused/VBN\t+nsubjpass\t[[effect]]/N"
            }
        }
    ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Wikipedia Lists&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;list_toc_parent_title&lt;/code&gt;: The heading of the parent section the list appears in&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;list_toc_section_heading&lt;/code&gt;: The heading of the section the list appears in&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;list_toc_section_level&lt;/code&gt;: The nesting level of the section within the table of content (toc)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
    "causal_relation":{
        "cause":{
            "concept":"separation_from_parents"
        },
        "effect":{
            "concept":"stress_in_early_childhood"
        }
    },
    "sources":[
        {
            "type":"wikipedia_list",
            "payload":{
                "wikipedia_page_id":"33096801",
                "wikipedia_page_title":"Stress in early childhood",
                "wikipedia_revision_id":"859225864",
                "wikipedia_revision_timestamp":"2018-09-12T16:22:05Z",
                "list_toc_parent_title":"Stress in early childhood",
                "list_toc_section_heading":"Causes",
                "list_toc_section_level":"2"
            }
        }
    ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Wikipedia Infoboxes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;infobox_template&lt;/code&gt;: The Wikipedia template of the infobox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;infobox_title&lt;/code&gt;: The title of the Wikipedia infobox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;infobox_argument&lt;/code&gt;: The argument of the infobox (the key of the key-value pair)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
    "causal_relation":{
        "cause":{
            "concept":"alcohol"
        },
        "effect":{
            "concept":"cirrhosis"
        }
    },
    "sources":[
        {
            "type":"wikipedia_infobox",
            "payload":{
                "wikipedia_page_id":"21365918",
                "wikipedia_page_title":"Cirrhosis",
                "wikipedia_revision_id":"861860835",
                "wikipedia_revision_timestamp":"2018-09-30T15:40:21Z",
                "infobox_template":"Infobox medical condition (new)",
                "infobox_title":"Cirrhosis",
                "infobox_argument":"causes"
            }
        }
    ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Loading CauseNet into Neo4j&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We provide sample code to load CauseNet into the graph database Neo4j.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following figure shows an excerpt of CauseNet within Neo4j (showing a coronavirus causing the disease SARS):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Concept Spotting Datasets&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the construction of CauseNet, we employ a causal concept spotter as a causal concept can be composed of multiple words (e.g., “global warming”, “human activity”, or “lack of exercise”). We determine the exact start and end of a causal concept in a sentence with a sequence tagger. Our training and evaluation data is available as part of our concept spotting datasets: one for Wikipedia infoboxes, Wikipedia lists, and ClueWeb sentences. We split each dataset into 80% training, 10% development and 10% test set&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Paper&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CauseNet forms the basis for our CIKM 2020 paper CauseNet: Towards a Causality Graph Extracted from the Web. Please make sure to refer to it as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@inproceedings{heindorf2020causenet,
  author    = {Stefan Heindorf and
               Yan Scholten and
               Henning Wachsmuth and
               Axel-Cyrille Ngonga Ngomo and
               Martin Potthast},
  title     = {CauseNet: Towards a Causality Graph Extracted from the Web},
  booktitle = {{CIKM}},
  publisher = {{ACM}},
  year      = {2020}
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Contact&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For questions and feedback please contact:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stefan Heindorf, Paderborn University&lt;lb/&gt; Yan Scholten, Technical University of Munich&lt;lb/&gt; Henning Wachsmuth, Paderborn University&lt;lb/&gt; Axel-Cyrille Ngonga Ngomo, Paderborn University&lt;lb/&gt; Martin Potthast, Leipzig University&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Licenses&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code is licensed under a MIT license. The data is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45099418</guid></item><item><title>Next.js Is Infuriating</title><link>https://blog.meca.sh/3lxoty3shjc2z</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d05093007b4164b8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hey, it's finally happened. I've decided to write a blog post. And if you're reading this, I've also finished one. I have wanted to do this for a long time, but could never find the motivation to start. But you know what they say: anger is the best motivator. They do say that, right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Some context that's in the background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're going on a journey, you and I. But first, we need to set the scene. Imagine we're working for $COMPANY and one of our Next.js services did an oopsie. This being Next.js, we of course have no idea what actually happened since the default logging is only enabled during development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our quest is to go in and setup some production ready logging. It's not going to be easy, but then again, nothing ever is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Middleware? Middle of nowhere!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first step of our journey is the middleware. The documentation even states this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Middleware executes before routes are rendered. It's particularly useful for implementing custom server-side logic like authentication, logging, or handling redirects.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alright, looks simple enough. Time to pick a logging library. I went with pino since we have used it before. Anything is an upgrade over &lt;code&gt;console.log&lt;/code&gt; anyways. We'll get this done before lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's set up a basic middleware:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// middleware.ts
import { NextResponse, NextRequest } from "next/server";

export async function middleware(request: NextRequest) {
  return new NextResponse.next({
    request: request,
    headers: request.headers,
    // status: 200,
    // statusText: 'OK'
  });
}

export const config = {
  matcher: "/:path*",
};&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think we already have a problem here. You can pass a grand total of 4 parameters from your middleware. The only thing that actually affects the invoked route is the &lt;code&gt;headers&lt;/code&gt;. Let's not skip over the fact that you can't have multiple middlewares or chain them either. How do you fuck this up so bad? We've had middlewares since at least the early 2010s when Express came out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyways, we're smart and modern Node.js has some pretty nifty tools. Let's reach for &lt;code&gt;AsyncLocalStorage&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// app/logger.ts
import { AsyncLocalStorage } from "async_hooks";
import { Logger, pino } from "pino";

const loggerInstance = pino({
  // Whatever config we need
  level: process.env.LOG_LEVEL ?? "trace",
});

export const LoggerStorage = new AsyncLocalStorage&amp;lt;Logger&amp;gt;();

export function logger(): Logger | null {
  return LoggerStorage.getStore() ?? null;
}

export function requestLogger(): Logger {
  return loggerInstance.child({ requestId: crypto.randomUUID() });
}

// middleware.ts
export async function middleware(request: NextRequest) {
  LoggerStorage.enterWith(requestLogger());
  logger()?.debug({ url: request.url }, "Started processing request!");

  return NextResponse.next();
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whew, hard work done. Let's test it out. Visit localhost:3000 and we see this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{ requestId: 'ec7718fa-b1a2-473e-b2e2-8f51188efa8f' } { url: 'http://localhost:3000/' } 'Started processing request!'
 GET / 200 in 71ms
{ requestId: '09b526b1-68f4-4e90-971f-b0bc52ad167c' } { url: 'http://localhost:3000/next.svg' } 'Started processing request!'
{ requestId: '481dd2ff-e900-4985-ae15-0b0a1eb5923f' } { url: 'http://localhost:3000/vercel.svg' } 'Started processing request!'
{ requestId: 'e7b29301-171c-4c91-af25-771471502ee4' } { url: 'http://localhost:3000/file.svg' } 'Started processing request!'
{ requestId: '13766de3-dd00-42ce-808a-ac072dcfd4c6' } { url: 'http://localhost:3000/window.svg' } 'Started processing request!'
{ requestId: '317e054c-1a9a-4dd8-ba21-4c0201fbeada' } { url: 'http://localhost:3000/globe.svg' } 'Started processing request!'&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't know if you've ever used pino before, but this is wrong. Can you figure out why?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike Next.js I won't keep you waiting in limbo. This is the browser output. Why? Well, it's because the default Next.js middleware runtime is &lt;code&gt;edge&lt;/code&gt;. We can of course switch to the &lt;code&gt;nodejs&lt;/code&gt; runtime which should work. Except, of course, it might not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've tried it on a fresh Next.js project and it does work. But it didn't when I was trying it out on our actual project. I swear I'm not crazy. Anyways, this isn't the main issue. We're slowly getting there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Paging the local mental asylum&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Logging in the middleware is cool and all, but it's not where the bulk of the magic happens. For that, we need to log in pages and layouts. Let's try it out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// app/page.tsx
export default function Home() {
  logger()?.info("Logging from the page!");

  return &amp;lt;div&amp;gt;Real simple website!&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Refresh the page and we get this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;✓ Compiled / in 16ms
 GET / 200 in 142ms&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's it? That's it. Nothing. Nada. Zilch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For posterity's sake, this is what it's supposed to look like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;✓ Compiled / in 2.2s
[11:38:59.259] INFO (12599): Logging from the page!
    requestId: "2ddef9cf-6fee-4d1d-8b1e-6bb16a3e636b"
 GET / 200 in 2520ms&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ok,this is getting a bit long, so I'll get to the point. The &lt;code&gt;logger&lt;/code&gt; function returns &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;. Why? I'm not entirely sure, but it seems like rendering is not executed in the same async context as the middleware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's the solution then? You're not going to believe this. Remember how the only value you can pass from the middleware is &lt;code&gt;headers&lt;/code&gt;? Yeah. That's what we need to use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following is for people with strong stomachs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// app/log/serverLogger.ts
import { pino } from "pino";

export const loggerInstance = pino({
  // Whatever config we need
  level: process.env.LOG_LEVEL ?? "info",
});

// app/log/middleware.ts
// Yes, we need to split up the loggers ...
// Mostly the same as before
import { loggerInstance } from "./serverLogger";

export function requestLogger(requestId: string): Logger {
  return loggerInstance.child({ requestId });
}

// app/log/server.ts
import { headers } from "next/headers";
import { loggerInstance } from "./serverLogger";
import { Logger } from "pino";
import { NextRequest } from "next/server";

const REQUEST_ID_HEADER = "dominik-request-id";

export function requestHeaders(
  request: NextRequest,
  requestId: string,
): Headers {
  const head = new Headers(request.headers);
  head.set(REQUEST_ID_HEADER, requestId);
  return head;
}

// Yeah, this has to be async ...
export async function logger(): Promise&amp;lt;Logger&amp;gt; {
  const hdrs = await headers();
  const requestId = hdrs.get(REQUEST_ID_HEADER);

  return loggerInstance.child({ requestId });
}

// middleware.ts
import { logger, LoggerStorage, requestLogger } from "./app/log/middleware";
import { requestHeaders } from "./app/log/server";

export async function middleware(request: NextRequest) {
  const requestId = crypto.randomUUID();
  LoggerStorage.enterWith(requestLogger(requestId));

  logger()?.debug({ url: request.url }, "Started processing request!");

  return NextResponse.next({ headers: requestHeaders(request, requestId) });
}

// app/page.tsx
export default async function Home() {
  (await logger())?.info("Logging from the page!");

  // ...
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Isn't it beautiful? I especially appreciate how it's now possible to import the middleware logging code from the server. Which of course won't work. Or import the server logging code from the middleware. Which also won't work. Better not mess up. Also, we haven't even touched upon logging in client components, which despite the name also run on the server. Yeah, that's a third split.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Congratulations, you're being coddled. Please do not resist.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Listen. I wanted to apologize, because I've led you into this trap. You see, I have already fallen into it several times before. A middleware system can be pretty useful when designed correctly and I wanted you to see what it looks like when it's not. The reason for writing this blog post actually started here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think every one of us has reached a point in their lives where they've had enough. For me, it was right here. Fuck it, let's use a custom server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;A custom Next.js server allows you to programmatically start a server for custom patterns. The majority of the time, you will not need this approach. However, it's available if you need to eject.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's take a look at the example from the documentation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { createServer } from 'http'
import { parse } from 'url'
import next from 'next'
 
const port = parseInt(process.env.PORT || '3000', 10)
const dev = process.env.NODE_ENV !== 'production'
const app = next({ dev })
const handle = app.getRequestHandler()
 
app.prepare().then(() =&amp;gt; {
  createServer((req, res) =&amp;gt; {
    const parsedUrl = parse(req.url!, true)
    handle(req, res, parsedUrl)
  }).listen(port)
 
  console.log(
    `&amp;gt; Server listening at http://localhost:${port} as ${
      dev ? 'development' : process.env.NODE_ENV
    }`
  )
})&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that once again, &lt;code&gt;handle&lt;/code&gt; doesn't really take any parameters. Only the request URL and the raw request and response.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyways, we still have &lt;code&gt;AsyncLocalStorage&lt;/code&gt; so this doesn't concern us too much. Let's modify the example a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// app/logger.ts
// Reverted back to our AsyncLocalStorage variaton
import { pino, Logger } from "pino";
import { AsyncLocalStorage } from "async_hooks";

const loggerInstance = pino({
  // Whatever config we need
  level: process.env.LOG_LEVEL ?? "info",
});

export const LoggerStorage = new AsyncLocalStorage&amp;lt;Logger&amp;gt;();

export function logger(): Logger | null {
  return LoggerStorage.getStore() ?? null;
}

export function requestLogger(): Logger {
  return loggerInstance.child({ requestId: crypto.randomUUID() });
}

// server.ts
import { logger, LoggerStorage, requestLogger } from "./app/logger";

app.prepare().then(() =&amp;gt; {
  createServer(async (req, res) =&amp;gt; {
    // This is new
    LoggerStorage.enterWith(requestLogger());
    logger()?.info({}, "Logging from server!");

    const parsedUrl = parse(req.url!, true);
    await handle(req, res, parsedUrl);
  }).listen(port);
});

// middleware.ts
import { logger } from "./app/logger";

export async function middleware(request: NextRequest) {
  logger()?.info({}, "Logging from middleware!");
  return NextResponse.next();
}

// app/page.tsx
import { logger } from "./logger";

export default async function Home() {
  logger()?.info("Logging from the page!");
  
  // ...
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ok, let's test it out. Refresh the browser and ...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; Server listening at http://localhost:3000 as development
[12:29:52.183] INFO (19938): Logging from server!
    requestId: "2ffab9a2-7e15-4188-8959-a7822592108f"
 ✓ Compiled /middleware in 388ms (151 modules)
 ○ Compiling / ...
 ✓ Compiled / in 676ms (769 modules)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's it. Are you fucking kidding me right now? What the fuck?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, you might be thinking that this is just not how &lt;code&gt;AsyncLocalStorage&lt;/code&gt; works. And you might be right. But I would like to point out that &lt;code&gt;headers()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;cookies()&lt;/code&gt; use &lt;code&gt;AsyncLocalStorage&lt;/code&gt;. This is a power that the Next.js devs have that we don't.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell there are only two ways to pass information from a middleware to a page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Headers&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;NextResponse.redirect&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;NextResponse.rewrite&lt;/code&gt;to a route with extra params (eg. /[requestId]/page.tsx)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you might have noticed, neither of these are very pleasant to use in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are being coddled. The Next.js devs have a vision and it's either their way or the highway. Note that if it was just the middleware, I wouldn't be sitting here, wasting away my weekend, ranting about a React framework. Believe it or not, I've got better things to do. It's constant pain you encounter daily when working with Next.js.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Vercel can do better&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's infuriating about this example is that Vercel can very much do better. I don't want to sing too many praises at Svelte(Kit) because I have some misgivings about its recent direction, but it's so much better than Next.js. Let's look at their middleware docs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;handle - This function runs every time the SvelteKit server receives a request [...] This allows you to modify response headers or bodies, or bypass SvelteKit entirely (for implementing routes programmatically, for example).&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking good so far.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;locals - To add custom data to the request, which is passed to handlers in&lt;code&gt;+server.js&lt;/code&gt;and server&lt;code&gt;load&lt;/code&gt;functions, populate the&lt;code&gt;event.locals&lt;/code&gt;object, as shown below.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm crying tears of joy right now. You can also stuff real objects/classes in there. Like a logger for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;You can define multiple handle functions and execute them with sequence.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what real engineering looks like. SvelteKit is a Vercel product. How is the flagship offering worse than what is essentially a side project. What the hell?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Scientists discover a new super massive black hole at https://github.com/vercel/next.js/issues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't have anything else to add, but while I'm here I feel like I have to talk about the GitHub issue tracker. This is perhaps the crown jewel of the dumpster fire that is Next.js. It's a place where hopes and issues come to die. The mean response time for a bug report is never. I've made it a sport to search the issue tracker/discussion for problems I'm currently facing and bet on how many years it takes to even get a response from a Next.js dev.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You think I'm joking? There are hundreds of issues with as many 👍 emojis with no official response for years. And when you finally get a response, it's to tell you that what you're doing is wrong and a solution to your real problems is on the way. Then they proceed to keep the "solution" in canary for years on end.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I personally reported two issues a year ago. Keep in mind that to have a valid bug report, you need a reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, what do you get for taking the time to make a minimal reproduction? That's right. Complete silence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would have reported about a dozen other issues I have encountered, but after this experience I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Honestly, I don't even know if the issues are still valid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Have we learned anything?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't know. For me, personally, I don't want to use Next.js anymore. You might think that this is just a singular issue and I'm overreacting. But there's bugs and edge cases around every corner. How did they manage to make TypeScript compile slower than Rust? Why make a distinction between code running on client and server and then not give me any tools to take advantage of that? Why? Why? Why?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't think I quite have enough pull to move us out of Next.js land. But, I think I will voice my opinion if we end up writing another app. We'll see if the grass is any greener on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45099922</guid></item><item><title>Kapa.ai (YC S23) is hiring research and software engineers</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/kapa-ai/jobs</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bdc48a3b7f7b6dd6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fastest way to build AI assistants on technical content&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We make it easy for technical companies to build AI assistants. Companies like Docker, Grafana and Mixpanel deploy kapa in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We leverage companies existing technical knowledge sources including documentation, tutorials, forum posts, Slack channels, GitHub issues and many more to generate AI assistants that can handle complicated technical questions. More than 200 companies use kapa and we have answered more than 10 million questions to date.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45099939</guid></item><item><title>Run Erlang/Elixir on Microcontrollers and Embedded Linux</title><link>https://www.grisp.org/software</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3ddf79035115e1e6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GRiSP Software Stacks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Bring Erlang/Elixir all the way to the edge. Deterministic, fault-tolerant, and production-ready&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open-source on GitHub&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GRiSP Metal&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Erlang/Elixir on RTEMS. &lt;lb/&gt;Tiny BEAM for devices.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GRiSP Metal, formerly just GRiSP, boots straight into the Erlang/Elixir VM on RTEMS for deterministic, real‑time behavior with a minimal footprint. It runs on microcontrollers, and we've made the full stack fit in 16 MB of RAM, ideal when every byte and millisecond matter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Boots directly to the BEAM (Erlang/Elixir) on RTEMS&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MCU-class footprint (fits in 16 MB RAM)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Real-time scheduling with predictable I/O&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Direct, low-overhead access to hardware interfaces&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Supervision trees bring BEAM reliability to the edge&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GRiSP Alloy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Erlang/Elixir on Linux RT. &lt;lb/&gt;Buildroot edition.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GRiSP Alloy boots directly into the Erlang/Elixir VM atop a lean, Buildroot-based real-time Linux. Run multiple Erlang/Elixir VMs with distinct priorities and/or pinned to different cores, connected via efficient, secure distributed Erlang links.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Minimal Linux RT image (Buildroot) with BEAM-first boot path&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multiple BEAM instances with priority separation and core affinity&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Local, secure node-to-node links via distributed Erlang&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Full access to Linux drivers, filesystems, and networking&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fast boot, small attack surface, production-ready&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GRiSP Forge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Erlang/Elixir on Linux RT.&lt;lb/&gt;Yocto edition.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GRiSP Forge applies the same architecture as GRiSP Alloy to Yocto, for teams requiring long-term, customizable Linux stacks and BSP integration. Boots directly into the Erlang/Elixir VM with the same multi-VM model and secure local links via distributed Erlang.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Yocto-based builds with reproducible, customizable images&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multiple Erlang/Elixir VMs by design (priorities and/or core pinning)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Efficient, secure local links via distributed Erlang&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Industrial Linux ecosystem compatibility and tooling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Built for long lifecycles and enterprise requirements&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GRiSP-io: Manage Embedded Systems at Scale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GRiSP-io is our cloud and edge platform for deploying, monitoring, and managing distributed embedded systems built with GRiSP stacks. From remote updates to real-time system insights, it helps you stay in control—whether you're testing a prototype or scaling a fleet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Deploy and manage GRiSP-based devices remotely&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Monitor system performance and health in real-time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Perform over-the-air updates with confidence&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Integrate cloud and edge control into your workflows&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why Use GRiSP Software?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GRiSP brings the power of Erlang/Elixir to embedded systems, making development efficient, scalable, and fault-tolerant&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;For Developers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GRiSP enables developers to run Erlang and Elixir on bare metal or embedded Linux, reducing complexity with minimal overhead and real-time capabilities. With GRiSP stacks and GRiSP-io, they can build and deploy robust, distributed applications optimized for embedded environments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;For IoT &amp;amp; Industrial Systems&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From prototyping to production, GRiSP provides open-source tools that scale with project needs. Its real-time execution supports automation, robotics, and connected devices, while GRiSP-io enables remote management and monitoring of deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Manage Embedded Systems with GRiSP-io&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deploy, monitor, and control your connected devices from anywhere. GRiSP-io brings cloud and edge integration to embedded applications, simplifying system management at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45100499</guid></item><item><title>Unfortunately, the ICEBlock app is activism theater</title><link>https://micahflee.com/unfortunately-the-iceblock-app-is-activism-theater/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ac6a0190092354b9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Unfortunately, the ICEBlock app is activism theater&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this summer's HOPE conference, Joshua Aaron spoke about ICEBlock, his iPhone app that allows users to anonymously report ICE sightings within a 5 mile radius, and to get notifications when others report ICE sightings near them. You can see the full talk, and the lively/infuriating Q&amp;amp;A, here, starting at 6:12:10.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to repression from the highest levels of the Trump administration, his app has gone viral and garnered over a million downloads from the App Store. Karoline Leavitt called it "an incitement of further violence against our ICE officers." Tom Homan said, "DOJ needs to look at this and see if they're crossing that line." Kristi Noem called the app "obstruction of justice." Pam Bondi announced "we are looking at it, we are looking at him, and he better watch out, because that's not a protected speech." (Notifying people about ICE sightings is protected speech, no matter what the fascist Attorney General says.) Joshua and his family have been receiving threats.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But unfortunately, despite the app’s goal of protecting people from ICE, its viral success, and the state repression against it, ICEBlock has serious issues:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most importantly, it wasn’t developed with input from people who actually defend immigrants from deportation. As a result, it doesn’t provide people with what they need to stay safe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because ICE sightings in the app aren’t verified in any way, it's likely that most reports in the app aren't actually ICE, even if they’re posted by people who mean well – as I describe below, the vast majority of ICE reports are false positives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And judging by the App Store reviews, it’s clear that not everyone means well. One review says: “This is a great app for safety information. Unfortunately MAGA is now posting false information on there and making racist comments in the comment section.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joshua makes strong claims about the security and privacy of his app without backing any of them up with technical details. Many of his claims are false. He also chose to target only iOS, and not Android, because of a misunderstanding about how Android push notifications work. And even worse, during the Q&amp;amp;A, he made it clear that he didn't understand terms like “warrant canary,” "reverse engineering," or “security through obscurity,” which doesn't inspire confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Privacy promises without the evidence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I first heard about ICEBlock, I liked the idea, but I – and others in various group chats I'm part of – were skeptical.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joshua promises that ICE reports are "completely anonymous," that the app doesn't store any personal data, and that it's "impossible to trace reports back to individual users." These are bold claims that he hasn't backed up with evidence. Unlike reputable privacy tools, ICEBlock isn't open source (in the talk, he explicitly rejected the idea of open sourcing it or allowing the security community to help him improve it), and Joshua hasn't published a threat model or technical documentation explaining how his app keeps these promises.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My friend Cooper Quintin, a security researcher at EFF, was also skeptical of ICEBlock, and so he reverse engineered it, and spoke to 404 Media about his findings. He largely confirmed Joshua's claims:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is great, and it's the reason that (despite his hostility towards transparency) I really do think that Joshua means well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if we can trust that Joshua isn't collecting data himself, it's difficult to discern what Apple would be able to hand over if it got subpoenaed for data related to his app. The website simply says it's "completely anonymous," without any caveats.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But ignoring the lack of transparency, there's an even larger problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ICEBlock spreads unverified information, making it useless for defending immigrants&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Local immigrant defense groups around the country have been defending people from deportation for the last decade or more. In a training with NorCal Resist, I learned that when people post (and repost) unverified reports of ICE sightings on social media, it does more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Millions of people are living in a state of fear. From my experience working with NorCal Resist, most ICE sightings that people hear about aren't real, even when the person reporting it believes that they are. It's common for someone to see a bunch of dudes in uniforms, or sketchy looking vans, and assume it's ICE, when it's actually something else. If I had to guess, I'd say about 98% of reports are false positives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;False reports encourage panic, which doesn't help anyone. Meanwhile, what people actually need are legal observers – people to document the behavior of federal agents, and provide this evidence to their lawyers. They also need help with connecting families of kidnapped people with information and lawyers, and they need communities coming out to defend their neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I asked Joshua about this during the Q&amp;amp;A of his talk, he didn't answer the question. Here's my question and his non-answers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Specifically, I asked:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;With my local group, they put a whole lot of energy into verifying every single report before spreading information about it. My question is, how do you know that ICEBlock isn't just full of false positives? And have you done any user research, or worked with local immigration groups to figure out how reliable this is, how much it's actually helping people versus causing panic?&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In an attempt to answer the question about user research, Joshua said, "No, we do not do any user data or metrics." He misunderstood the question, apparently thinking that I meant collecting data from users rather than talking to humans who know more than he does and incorporating their feedback into the design of the app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He then explained what ICEBlock does to prevent malicious people from making false reports — including falsely claiming that it's "not possible" to make tons of simultaneous fake reports (more on this below).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ICEBlock doesn't verify anything, and instead only spreads unverified rumors. To be fair, verification is a very hard problem. In my local group, we have announcement-only Signal groups full of volunteers who physically verify every single ICE sighting that's reported to our rapid response hotline. The vast majority of reports are false positives. There might be several reports a day, but actual ICE or CBP activity is much more rare. I've personally gone to check out maybe 10 to 15 different ICE sightings, only one of which turned out to be actual immigration enforcement (though by the time I got to the location, ICE had already left the area). None of these false reports were malicious: they were simply scared people who saw a bunch of vehicles and people in uniforms and reported an ICE sighting, when it was actually something else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another person in the audience asked a similar question:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;I'm wondering, I think someone asked earlier, if in the design of ICEBlock, or even now, are you currently working with immigrant communities to figure out what resources they need?&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His answer was that ICEBlock has been translated into many different languages. And that the community organizers he's spoken with told him that ICEBlock doesn't meet their needs. So, he decided to not worry about their feedback and do his own thing instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to support people who are actually protecting immigrants from deportation, please donate to NorCal Resist or your local community rapid response networks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What's GPS spoofing?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Joshua explained the safeguards against abuse in the app, he claimed that it's "not possible" to make 100 fake reports in a single morning, in part because you can only make reports within a 5 mile radius of your location. But apparently, Joshua has never heard of GPS spoofing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even though I'm sitting at my house in California right now, here's a screenshot I just took of the ICEBlock app from the Eiffel Tower in Paris. While I won't go into details of the masterful hacking skills that this took, I'll give you a hint: it's the same technique kids use to cheat at Pokemon Go.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Make ICEBlock open source? "Absolutely not."&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Someone asked whether Joshua would be interested in collaborating with the hacker community on ICEBlock, so they could provide him with advice and help him with feature development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joshua rejected the idea, saying that he believes that he'd need to completely trust anyone he collaborated with. "Believe me when I say I would love help. I'm supporting over a million users myself. There's not some giant company behind this," he said. "But it's really really hard for me to put my trust in somebody, and share the source code, and share the access to this."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is, of course, not how secure software development works. The most widely trusted security and privacy tools that exist, like Signal and Tor, are open source, and they accept peer review and code contributions from the public.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thing that makes this perfectly reasonable and safe is code review. If Joshua published the ICEBlock source code, experts in the hacker community could add features or fix bugs for him, and make pull requests with their changes. He could then carefully review the changes before merging them into his codebase. He could reject whatever changes he wants. You don't actually need to trust – or even know the identity of – hackers who help you develop software. This is a solved a problem, and Joshua seems utterly unaware of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My friend Jen Helsby, the CTO of Freedom of the Press Foundation and a SecureDrop developer, explicitly asked if he would be open to making ICEBlock open source. Here's the clip:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jen asked:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;There's a lot of secure software, that probably people in this room work on, that is developed in the open, and that is used primarily by at-risk users, including things like Tor, Signal, SecureDrop. That's great, because it makes it easy for folks to contribute. Maybe you don't want that, I understand that can be hard. But it also makes it easier for people to audit and gain assurance that the app is doing what you claim without having to have, you know, EFF reverse engineer it. Would you be open to making the app open source?&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His answer: "Absolutely not."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why? "I don't want anybody from the government to have their hooks in how I'm doing what I'm doing. Once you go open source, everybody has access to it. So I'm just going to keep the codebase private at this time."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He also claimed that the government can't learn everything about how an app works by reverse engineering it, which isn't true.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I agree with Jen. His answers are very concerning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What's security through obscurity?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another person asked specifically how concealing the details of how the app works from the government is distinguishable from security through obscurity, Joshua agreed that security through obscurity is terrible... and denied that he's doing it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In case you're not aware of this term, the first sentence of the Wikipedia article on security through obscurity has a concise definition:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;In security engineering, security through obscurity is the practice of concealing the details or mechanisms of a system to enhance its security.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NIST's General Guide to Server Security lists "Open Design" as a core security principle, saying that, "System security should not depend on the secrecy of the implementation or its components."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minutes before this, Joshua had just finishing explaining that he definitely won't open source his app because, "I don't want anybody from the government to have their hooks in how I'm doing what I'm doing."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He's implying that his code includes some "secret sauce" that, if it were made public, would make the app less secure, so he can't risk letting anyone discover how it works. This is the definition of security through obscurity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My server is "HIGHLY secure," he says to a room full of hackers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Throughout the Q&amp;amp;A, Joshua kept referencing the security of his server. At one point, he even said that he built it himself and it's "HIGHLY secure." He also assured the audience, "Trust me when I tell you, I think about EVERYTHING to the Nth degree."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It took about 20 minutes of digging around to discover that the server that hosts the iceblock.app website is running on Linode and also hosts the websites of several of Joshua's other projects, going back decades. This includes a website for his IT consulting business, his band, etc. If any one of those old websites gets hacked, it's possible that the hacker could more easily access ICEBlock data that's stored on the same server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without providing more details, I also discovered that his server is running outdated software with known vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What's a warrant canary?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At one point, a lawyer asked some excellent legal questions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;I'm curious if ICEBlock either currently or has intentions to implement something like a warrant canary or other method. And more generally, whether you have received anything like search warrants, or All Writs Act requests, or anything else. Things like more intrusive means of obtaining information from ICEBlock. Things like requests for live interception, which would be authorized under a search warrant. And if you have a response plan in place already for those.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're not familiar with warrant canaries, these are basically public notices that say, "I've never been forced to give up user data." If the notice ever gets taken down, the public can infer that the service was in fact forced to hand over user data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joshua said, "No on the warrant canary, because it would probably require some sort of user data to do that." He seemed to think that a warrant canary would be a new feature in the app (that's uh, not what a warrant canary is), and he completely ignored the legal questions, instead opting to talk about why it's important to keep the app design simple.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the lawyer asked again what he would do if the government tried to compel him to spy on his users, Joshua simply said, "I'd just tell them to go fuck themselves." It's a good answer, but it's also naive. Government requests can include gag orders, preventing him from telling anyone that he has received them, and punishment for disobeying them can include threats of jail time. It's good to plan ahead. Luckily, he has EFF and ACLU offering him legal support, in case he ever actually has to face something like this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;It's not too late&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite everything, I do think that Joshua's heart is in the right place and that he genuinely wants to help people. He's sticking his neck out to fight fascism, and the far right is harassing him and his family for it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is why I, and several other hackers who attended his HOPE talk, spent so much time and energy (both during his talk and in the days after it) trying to encourage him to open things up so that ICEBlock, and its million-strong userbase, might yet become a helpful tool in defending immigrants against Trump's fascist plans. He has rejected our offers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's possible for him to turn things around, but sadly, I'm not holding my breath.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45101117</guid></item><item><title>Europol said ChatControl doesn't go far enough; they want to retain data forever</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/europe/comments/1n6cjw1/europol_said_chat_control_doesnt_go_far_enough/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45101127</guid></item></channel></rss>