<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 07:11:52 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Calculus for Mathematicians, Computer Scientists, and Physicists [pdf]</title><link>https://mathcs.holycross.edu/~ahwang/print/calc.pdf</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46024773</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 16:31:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Native Secure Enclave backed SSH keys on macOS</title><link>https://gist.github.com/arianvp/5f59f1783e3eaf1a2d4cd8e952bb4acf</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="26c8095d3de23971"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It turns out that MacOS Tahoe can generate and use secure-enclave backed SSH keys! This replaces projects like https://github.com/maxgoedjen/secretive&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a shared library &lt;code&gt;/usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib&lt;/code&gt; that traditionally has been used to add smartcard support
to ssh by implementing &lt;code&gt;PKCS11Provider&lt;/code&gt; interface. However since recently it also implements &lt;code&gt;SecurityKeyProivder&lt;/code&gt;
which supports loading keys directly from the secure enclave! &lt;code&gt;SecurityKeyProvider&lt;/code&gt; is what is normally used to talk to FIDO2 devices (e.g. &lt;code&gt;libfido2&lt;/code&gt; can be used to talk to your Yubikey). However you can now use it to talk to your Secure Enclave instead!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head class="px-3 py-2"&gt;recording.mov&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See &lt;code&gt;man sc_auth&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;man ssh-keychain&lt;/code&gt; for all the options&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To create a Secure Enclave backed key that requires biometrics, run the following command and press TouchID:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;% sc_auth create-ctk-identity -l ssh -k p-256-ne -t bio
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can confirm that the key was create with the &lt;code&gt;list-ctk-identities&lt;/code&gt; command:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;arian@Mac ssh-keychain % sc_auth  list-ctk-identities       
Key Type Public Key Hash                          Prot Label Common Name Email Address Valid To        Valid 
p-256-ne A71277F0BC5825A7B3576D014F31282A866EF3BC bio  ssh   ssh                       23.11.26, 17:09 YES
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It also supports listing the ssh key fingerprints instead:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;% sc_auth  list-ctk-identities -t ssh
Key Type Public Key Hash                                    Prot Label Common Name Email Address Valid To        Valid 
p-256-ne SHA256:vs4ByYo+T9M3V8iiDYONMSvx2k5Fj2ujVBWt1j6yzis bio  ssh   ssh                       23.11.26, 17:09 YES 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keys can be deleted with&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;% sc_auth delete-ctk-identity -h &amp;lt;Public Key Hash&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can "download" the public / private keypair from the secure enclave using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;% ssh-keygen -w /usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib -K -N ""
Enter PIN for authenticator: 
You may need to touch your authenticator to authorize key download.
Saved ECDSA-SK key to id_ecdsa_sk_rk
% cat id_ecdsa_sk_rk.pub 
sk-ecdsa-sha2-nistp256@openssh.com AAAAInNrLWVjZHNhLXNoYTItbmlzdHAyNTZAb3BlbnNzaC5jb20AAAAIbmlzdHAyNTYAAABBBKiHAiAZhcsZ95n85dkNGs9GnbDt0aNOia2gnuknYV2wKL3y0u+d3QrE9cFkmWXIymHZMglL+uJA+6mShY8SeykAAAAEc3NoOg== ssh:
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can just use the empty string for PIN. For some reason &lt;code&gt;openssh&lt;/code&gt; always asks for
it even if the authenticator in question does not use a PIN but a biometric.
Note that the "private" key here is just a reference to the FIDO credential. It does
not contain any secret key material. Hence I'm specifiyng &lt;code&gt;-N ""&lt;/code&gt; to skip an encryption
passphrase.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now if you copy this public key to your authorized keys file, it should work!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;% ssh-copy-id -i id_ecdsa_sk_rk localhost
% ssh -o SecurityKeyProvider=/usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib localhost
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of downloading the public/private keypair to a file you can also directly make the keys available to &lt;code&gt;ssh-agent&lt;/code&gt;. For this you can use the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;% ssh-add -K -S /usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib
Enter PIN for authenticator: 
Resident identity added: ECDSA-SK SHA256:vs4ByYo+T9M3V8iiDYONMSvx2k5Fj2ujVBWt1j6yzis
% ssh-add -L
sk-ecdsa-sha2-nistp256@openssh.com AAAAInNrLWVjZHNhLXNoYTItbmlzdHAyNTZAb3BlbnNzaC5jb20AAAAIbmlzdHAyNTYAAABBBKiHAiAZhcsZ95n85dkNGs9GnbDt0aNOia2gnuknYV2wKL3y0u+d3QrE9cFkmWXIymHZMglL+uJA+6mShY8SeykAAAAEc3NoOg== 
% ssh-copy-id localhost
% ssh -o SecurityKeyProvider=/usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib localhost
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;SecurityKeyProvider&lt;/code&gt; can be configured in &lt;code&gt;.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt; but I recommend setting
&lt;code&gt;export SSH_SK_PROVIDER=/usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;.zprofile&lt;/code&gt; instead as
that environment variable gets picked up by &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ssh-add&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ssh-keygen&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means you can just do:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ssh-add -K
ssh my-server
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ssh-keygen -K
ssh -i id_ecdsa_rk_sk my-server
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;to ssh into your server&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's also an exportable variant where the private key is encrypted using the secure enclave as opposed to generated on the secure enclave. This is might be considered less secure but is convenient for key backup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;% sc_auth create-ctk-identity -l ssh-exportable -k p-256 -t bio
% sc_auth list-ctk-identities
p-256    A581E5404ED157C4C73FFDBDFC1339E0D873FCAE bio  ssh-exportable ssh-exportable               23.11.26, 19:50 YES  
% sc_auth export-ctk-identity -h A581E5404ED157C4C73FFDBDFC1339E0D873FCAE -f ssh-exportable.pem
Enter a password which will be used to protect the exported items:
Verify password:
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can then re-import it on another device&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;% sc_auth import-ctk-identities -f ssh-exportable.pem.p12 -t bio
Enter PKCS12 file password:
&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46025721</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 17:55:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fran Sans – font inspired by San Francisco light rail displays</title><link>https://emilysneddon.com/fran-sans-essay</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="1e9811a28de60dc3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Published on 6TH NOVEMBER 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fran Sans is a display font in every sense of the term. It’s an interpretation of the destination displays found on some of the light rail vehicles that service the city of San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I say some because destination displays aren’t consistently used across the city’s transit system. In fact, SF has an unusually high number of independent public transit agencies. Unlike New York, Chicago or L.A., which each have one, maybe two, San Francisco and the greater Bay Area have over two dozen. Each agency, with its own models of buses and trains, use different destination displays, creating an eclectic patchwork of typography across the city.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among them, one display in particular has always stood out to me: the LCD panel displays inside Muni’s Breda Light Rail Vehicles. I remember first noticing them on a Saturday in October on the N-Judah, heading to the Outer Sunset for a shrimp hoagie. This context is important, as anyone who’s spent an October weekend in SF knows this is the optimal vibe to really take in the beauty of the city.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What caught my eye was how the displays look mechanical and yet distinctly personal. Constructed on a 3×5 grid, the characters are made up of geometric modules: squares, quarter-circles, and angled forms. Combined, these modules create imperfect, almost primitive letterforms, revealing a utility and charm that feels distinctly like the San Francisco I’ve come to know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This balance of utility and charm seems to show up everywhere in San Francisco and its history. The Golden Gate’s “International Orange” started as nothing more than a rust-proof primer, yet is now the city’s defining colour. The Painted Ladies became multicoloured icons after the 1960s Colourist movement covered decades of grey paint. Even the steepness of the streets was once an oversight in city planning but has since been romanticised in films and on postcards. So perhaps it is unsurprising that I would find this same utility and charm in a place as small and functional as a train sign.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To learn more about these displays, I visited the San Francisco Municipal Transportation Agency’s (SFMTA) Electronics Shop at Balboa Park. There, technician Armando Lumbad had set up one of the signs. They each feature one large LCD panel which displays the line name, and twenty-four smaller ones to display the destination. The loose spacing of the letters and fluorescent backlighting gives the sign a raw, analogue quality. Modern LED dot-matrix displays are far more efficient and flexible, but to me, they lack the awkwardness that makes these Breda signs so delightful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Armando showed me how the signs work. He handed me a printed matrix table listing every line and destination, each paired with a three-digit code. On route, train operators punch the code into a control panel at the back of the display, and the LCD blocks light on specific segments of the grid to build each letter. I picked code 119, and Armando entered it for me. A few seconds later the panels revealed my own stop: the N-Judah at Church &amp;amp; Duboce. There in the workshop, devoid of the context of the trains and the commute, the display looked almost monolithic, or sculptural, and I have since fantasised whether it would be possible to ship one of these home to Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking inside of the display, I found labels identifying the make and model. The signs were designed and manufactured by Trans-Lite, Inc., a company based in Milford, Connecticut that specialised in transport signage from 1959 until its acquisition by the Nordic firm Teknoware in 2012. After lots of amateur detective work, and with the help from an anonymous Reddit user in a Connecticut community group, I was connected with Gary Wallberg, Senior Engineer at Trans-Lite and the person responsible for the design of these very signs back in 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learning that the alphabet came from an engineer really explains its temperament and why I was drawn to it in the first place. The signs were designed for sufficiency: fixed segments, fixed grid, and no extras. Characters were created only as destinations required them, while other characters, like the Q, X, and much of the punctuation, were never programmed into the signs. In reducing everything to its bare essentials, somehow character emerged, and it’s what inspired me to design Fran Sans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I shared some initial drawings with Dave Foster of Foster Type who encouraged me to get the font software Glyphs and turn it into my first working font. From there, I broke down the anatomy of the letters into modules, then used them like Lego to build out a full set: uppercase A–Z, numerals, core punctuation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some glyphs remain unsolved in this first version, for example the standard @ symbol refuses to squeeze politely into the 3×5 logic. Lowercase remains a question for the future, and would likely mean reconsidering the grid. But, as with the displays themselves, I am judging Fran Sans as sufficient for now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Getting up close to these signs, you’ll notice Fran Sans’ gridlines are simplified even from its real‑life muse, but my hope is that its character remains. Specifically: the N and the zero, where the unusually thick diagonals close in on the counters; and the Z and 7, whose diagonals can feel uncomfortably thin. I’ve also noticed the centre of the M can scale strangely and read like an H at small sizes, but in fairness, this type was never designed for the kind of technical detail so many monospaced fonts aim for. Throughout the process I tried to protect these unorthodox moments, because to me, they determined the success of this interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fran Sans comes in three styles: Solid, Tile, and Panel, each building in visual complexity. The decision to include variations, particularly the Solid style, was inspired by my time working at Christopher Doyle &amp;amp; Co. There, we worked with Bell Shakespeare, Australia’s national theatre company dedicated to the works of William Shakespeare. The equity of the Bell Shakespeare brand lies in its typography, which is a beautiful custom typeface called Hotspur, designed and produced by none other than Dave Foster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Often, brand fonts are chosen or designed to convey a single feeling. Maybe it’s warmth and friendliness, or a sense of tech and innovation. But what I’ve always loved about the Bell typeface is how one weight could serve both Shakespeare’s comedies and tragedies, simply by shifting scale, spacing, or alignment. Hotspur has the gravity to carry the darkness of Titus Andronicus and the roundness to convey the humour of Much Ado About Nothing. And while Fran Sans Solid is technically no Hotspur, I wanted it to share that same versatility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further inspiration for Fran Sans came from the Letterform Archive, the world’s leading typography archive, based in San Francisco. Librarian and archivist Kate Long Stellar thoughtfully curated a research visit filled with modular typography spanning most of the past century. On the table were two pieces that had a significant impact on Fran Sans and are now personal must-sees at the archive. First, Joan Trochut’s Tipo Veloz “Fast Type” (1942) was created during the Second World War when resources were scarce. Tipo Veloz gave printers the ability to draw with type, rearranging modular pieces to form letters, ornaments and even illustrations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, Zuzana Licko’s process work for Lo-Res (1985), an Emigre typeface, opened new ways of thinking about how ideas move between the physical and the digital and then back again. Seeing how Lo-Res was documented through iterations and variations gave the typeface a depth and richness that changed my understanding of how fonts are built. At some point I want to explore physical applications for Fran Sans out of respect for its origins, since it is impossible to fully capture the display’s charm on screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back at the SFMTA, Armando told me the Breda vehicles are being replaced, and with them their destination displays will be swapped for newer LED dot-matrix units that are more efficient and easier to maintain. By the end of 2025 the signs that inspired Fran Sans will disappear from the city, taking with them a small but distinctive part of the city’s voice. That feels like a real loss. San Francisco is always reinventing itself, yet its charm lies in how much of its history still shows through. My hope is that Fran Sans can inspire a deeper appreciation for the imperfections that give our lives and our cities character. Life is so rich when ease and efficiency are not the measure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OUTSIDE MY LIFE,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;INSIDE THE DREAM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FALLING UP THE STAIRS,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;INTO THE STREET.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LET THE CABLE CAR&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CARRY ME.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;STRAIGHT OUT OF TOWN,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;INTO THE SEA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PAST THE DAHLIAS AND&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;THE SELF-DRIVING CARS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;THE CHURCH OF 8 WHEELS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;THE LOWER HAIGHT BARS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;THE PEAK HOUR SPRAWL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;THE KIDS IN THE PARK.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;THE SLANTING HOUSES.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;THE BAY AFTER DARK.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MY WINDOW, MY OWN&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SILVER SCREEN.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I FOLLOW WHERE THE&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FOG TAKES ME.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By MADDY CARRUCAN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46025942</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 18:20:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>µcad: New open source programming language that can generate 2D sketches and 3D</title><link>https://microcad.xyz/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="db25b240da5dd2dc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Alpha Release 0.2.14&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What a day! This morning we just wanted to push a release and ended up in struggling with Issue #289…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome to the website of µcad!&lt;lb/&gt;Microcad (or µcad) is a new open source programming language that can generate 2D sketches and 3D objects.&lt;lb/&gt;The project is still in its early stages, but µcad is becoming increasingly stable. New ideas are being added to the code every week.&lt;lb/&gt;In this blog, we want to keep you up to date on the latest developments at µcad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What a day! This morning we just wanted to push a release and ended up in struggling with Issue #289…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What at first may look like a minimalist Christmas decoration, is a Spirograph consisting of five parts that we successfully…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46027216</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 20:51:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Particle Life</title><link>https://sandbox-science.com/particle-life</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9329e31e48c192bf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Loading simulation...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CPU&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matrix Settings&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;World Settings&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Particle Number&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Color Number&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Depth Limit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Walls Settings :&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rectangle Size&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;x&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;y&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Physics Settings&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Repel Force&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Force Factor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Friction Factor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Randomizer Settings&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Min. Radius&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Max. Radius&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Graphics Settings&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;General Settings :&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Circle Shape&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Particle Size&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3D Settings :&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Depth Size&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Depth Opacity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Min. Opacity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Max. Opacity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Debug Tools&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Show Cells&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cell Group Size&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cell Size Factor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Save and Share&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brush Settings :&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radius&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intensity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Attract&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Repulse&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46027722</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 21:54:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iowa City made its buses free. Traffic cleared, and so did the air</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/18/climate/iowa-city-free-buses.html</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46027833</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 22:06:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A desktop app for isolated, parallel agentic development</title><link>https://github.com/coder/mux</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="79d4563a6c9ba2a8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A desktop application for parallel agentic development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Why parallelize?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some specific use cases we enable:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Contextual continuity between relevant changes: &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;e.g. create a workspace for &lt;code&gt;code-review&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;refactor&lt;/code&gt;, and&lt;code&gt;new-feature&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;e.g. create a workspace for &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GPT-5-Pro: use the slow but powerful GPT-5-Pro for complex issues &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Run in the background for hours on end&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The stream will automatically resume after restarts or intermittent connection issues. If the model completes early we will show an indicator.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A/B testing: run multiple workspaces in parallel on the same problem but different approaches, abandon the bad ones.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tangent exploration: launch tangents in &lt;code&gt;mux&lt;/code&gt;away from main work&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Isolated workspaces with central view on git divergence&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multi-model (&lt;code&gt;sonnet-4-*&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;grok-*&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;gpt-5-*&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;opus-4-*&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;VS Code Extension: Jump into mux workspaces directly from VS Code (docs)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Supporting UI and keybinds for efficiently managing a suite of agents&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rich markdown outputs (mermaid diagrams, LaTeX, etc.)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;mux has a custom agent loop but much of the core UX is inspired by Claude Code. You'll find familiar features like Plan/Exec mode, vim inputs, &lt;code&gt;/compact&lt;/code&gt; and new ones
like opportunistic compaction and mode prompts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Warning&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;mux is in a Preview state. You will encounter bugs and performance issues. It's still possible to be highly productive. We are using it almost exclusively for our own development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download pre-built binaries from the releases page for macOS and Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See the documentation for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See AGENTS.md for development setup and guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Copyright (C) 2025 Coder Technologies, Inc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU Affero General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation, version 3 of the License.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See LICENSE for details.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46027947</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 22:24:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: I wrote a minimal memory allocator in C</title><link>https://github.com/t9nzin/memory</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a397485a6eb7beb9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A memory allocator written from scratch using &lt;code&gt;sbrk&lt;/code&gt; for small allocations and &lt;code&gt;mmap&lt;/code&gt; for large allocations. It includes optimizations like block splitting to reduce fragmentation and coalescing to merge adjacent free blocks. Please note that this allocator is not thread-safe. Concurrent calls to malloc/free/realloc will cause undefined behavior. I've also written a blog post (~20 minute read) explaining step by step the process behind writing this memory allocator project, if that's of interest, you can read it here!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GCC compiler&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;POSIX-compliant system (Linux, macOS) because we're using &lt;code&gt;sbrk()&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;mmap()&lt;/code&gt;&amp;lt;- won't work on Windows&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;make           # build everything
make tests     # run tests
make bench     # run benchmark&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Build the static library:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;make lib&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Include the header in your C file:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;#include "allocator.h"&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Compile your program with the library:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;gcc -I./include examples/my_program.c -L./build -lallocator -o my_program&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Run the compiled program&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;./my_program&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;.
├── Makefile
├── README.md
├── examples
│   └── my_program.c        # an example program using implemented malloc()
├── include
│   └── allocator.h         # header file w/ function declarations
├── src
│   └── allocator.c         # allocator
└── tests
    ├── benchmark.c         # performance benchmarks
    ├── test_basic.c        # basic functionality tests
    └── test_edge_cases.c   # edge cases and stress tests 
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Not thread-safe (no mutex protection)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fyi: &lt;code&gt;sbrk&lt;/code&gt;is deprecated on macOS but still functional&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No defragmentation or compaction&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT License :D&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contributions are welcome. Please open an issue or submit a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I credit Dan Luu for his fantastic malloc() tutorial which I greatly enjoyed reading and served as a helpful reference for this project. If you would like to take a look at his tutorial (which I highly recommend), you can find it here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'd also like to thank Joshua Zhou and Abdul Fatir for reading over and giving me great feedback on the accompanying blog post for this project.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46027962</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 22:25:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Liva AI (YC S25) Is Hiring</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/liva-ai/jobs/fYP8QP8-growth-intern</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bb4e601ff5d377f7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Audio &amp;amp; Video Data&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About the role:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Liva AI (YC S25) is focused on collecting high-quality and proprietary voice and video data. We're actively hiring for a community growth intern. You’ll help us foster a community at Liva AI, with an emphasis on building large online communities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Job responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No need to send resume, just send me the server/subreddit/community you made with a brief description.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Liva's mission is to make AI look and sound truly human. The AI voices and faces today feel off, and lack the capability to reflect diverse people across different ethnicities, races, accents, and career professions. We’re fixing that by building the world’s richest library of human voice and video data, fueling the next generation of realistic AI.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46028046</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 22:36:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ego, empathy, and humility at work</title><link>https://matthogg.fyi/a-unified-theory-of-ego-empathy-and-humility-at-work/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="be635b5ba3068937"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;A Unified Theory Of Ego, Empathy, And Humility At Work&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our daily lives empathy and humility are obvious virtues we aspire to. They keep our egos in check. Less obvious is that they’re practical skills in the workplace, too. I think, for developers and technical leaders in particular, that the absence of ego is the best way to further our careers and do great work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the simplest of terms the ego is the characteristic of personhood that enables us to practice self-reflection, self-awareness, and accountability for the actions or decisions we take.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the ego also motivates us to reframe our perception of the world in whatever way keeps us centered in it. Each of us is perpetually driven to justify our place in the world. This constant self-justification is like an engine that idles for our entire lives, and it requires constant fine-tuning. When it runs amok this is what we call a “big” ego.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Breaking News! Developers Have Egos!&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m not thinking only of the 10x engineer stereotype, although I’ve worked with such folks in the past. Ego is more nuanced than that. Besides the most arrogant developer in the room throwing their weight around, our egos manifest in hundreds of ways that are much harder to detect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As developers we’re more susceptible to letting our egos run free. The nature of our work is so technical that to others it can seem obscure, arcane, or even magical. Sometimes we don’t do enough to actively dispel that notion—and just like that half the work of self-justification is already done for us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Very often it’s not intentional. The simplest example is the overuse of jargon and acronyms. We all do it, but as Jeremy Keith explains:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still, I get why initialisms run rampant in technical discussions. You can be sure that most discussions of particle physics would be incomprehensible to outsiders, not necessarily because of the concepts, but because of the terminology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simply mashing a few letters together can be empowering for ourselves while being exclusionary for others. It’s an artifact—albeit a small one—of our egos. We know what the technobabble means. Our justified place in the universe is maintained.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we express our egos more deliberately. Developers have a clear tendency towards gatekeeping. For most, it’s an honest mistake. There’s a fine line between holding others to a certain expectation versus actively keeping people on the outside. When we see ourselves doing this we can correct it easily enough.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sadly there are developers who seemingly like to gatekeep. They get to feel like wizards in their towers with their dusty books and potions. But, it’s actually self-limiting. Gatekeeping by definition means you’re fixed in place and never moving, standing guard for eternity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My point is our egos can “leak” in so many ways that it takes diligence to catch it let alone correct it. The following is a short, incomplete list of typical statements we as developers might say or hear at work. If you parse them more precisely each one is an attempt at self-justification:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;“That’s the way we’ve always done it.”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;“It’s not that complicated! You just…”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;“Yeah, I should be able to finish this in a day.”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;“This legacy codebase is an absolute disaster.”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;“Assign it to me. Nobody else will be able to fix it.”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;“You can’t be a senior dev. You don’t know anything about…”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;“Ugh, our morning standup is so useless.”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;“This feature is too important to assign to the junior dev.”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;“We should start using this new tool in our pipeline.”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;“We should never use that new tool in our pipeline.”&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Everything Is Bigger Than You&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ego is concerned with the self but very easily becomes something harmful in the absence of new information or context. Indeed, the ego nudges us to self-justify so much that one could argue it actively resists new information when left unchecked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may have read one of the example statements above with some familiarity and thought, “But what if I’m right?”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To which I’d say: OK, but should that be your default stance? Why might you feel the need to immediately start a conversation with a self-justification? There are ways to adjust our approach, make our points, and accept new information all at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any interaction—be it a meeting, Slack thread, or water cooler conversation—we must remember that the matter at hand is bigger than us in ways we don’t yet understand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a simple enough heuristic but we need the skills to gain that understanding. We need empathy and humility. Empathy is the ability to recognize and comprehend what someone else is thinking or feeling. Humility is a resistance to our “competitive reflexes” through the practice of emotional neutrality and vulnerability. Both serve to counteract the ego.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To make these concepts more actionable I find it simpler to define them in terms of the purposes they serve. Specifically…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Empathy is how we gather new information.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Humility is how we allow information to change our behavior.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;This framing also helps remind us what empathy and humility are not. It’s not about putting yourself in another’s shoes, as the saying goes. It’s not about being submissive or a pushover. It’s not about altruism or self-sacrifice. We can easily practice empathy and humility without it ever being at our own expense.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Pursuit Of Information&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t know about you but I go to work to solve problems, be creative, and build shit. I can’t think of a single instance where an unruly ego solved anything I’ve worked on. Ego just makes an existing challenge worse. Solutions require information I don’t have yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Empathy and humility are usually top of mind during situations of pain or distress, but they’re really aspects of emotional intelligence that should be activated at all times. Once you adjust your mindset to treat them as basic tools for the pursuit of information you’ll see opportunities to leverage them everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Developers can apply this mindset with almost anybody they come into contact with. Fellow developers, naturally. But also less technical teammates (e.g., QAs, designers, product owners, stakeholders) who have their own unique skills and context that our success depends on. And of course our users should be at the center of every problem we’re working to solve. Lastly, even executives and upper management have some insight to offer if you dare (but only up to a certain point).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;“Be Curious, Not Judgmental”&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve been waiting years for a chance to work Ted Lasso into one of my essays. Today’s the day, readers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The titular character is such an archetype for leadership that my jaw hit the floor when I first watched the show. The example Ted sets has spawned countless think pieces about leadership and management. Suffice it to say he exhibits all of my principles over the series’ 34 episodes. He’s empathy and humility sporting a mustache. He’s the absence of ego personified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend watching the show but to get a taste this 5 minute clip is worth your time. This is the famous “darts scene”…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s a common and derisive attitude that qualities like empathy or humility are signs of weakness. You have to get all up in your feelings. Ew! But they require enormous reserves of strength, patience, and determination. It’s those who follow their egos who are weak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Letting your ego take control is the easiest thing in the world. Just ask any toddler throwing a temper tantrum. Resisting those impulses and remaining calm, on the other hand, has been a virtue humanity has aspired to for thousands of years. As the Roman emperor and Stoic philosopher Marcus Aurelius wrote: “The nearer a man comes to a calm mind, the closer he is to strength.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;You’re Neither Ted Lasso Nor A Roman Emperor&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The practice of empathy, humility, and keeping your ego in check will test you daily. The feedback I’ve received the most from my coworkers is that I’m extraordinarily calm and even-keeled in any situation—even situations where I’d be right to freak out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is that just naturally my personality? Maybe in part, but remaining calm is a choice. I’m actively choosing to favor solutions over my own ego. To my colleagues past and present I confess to you now that any time you’ve seen me calm, cool, and collected I was very likely internally screaming.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If this sounds like a lot of work you might be wondering if it’s worth it. I think it is. At the very least your coworkers and colleagues will like you better. That’s no small thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In all seriousness, the positive feedback I get most about the developers I manage is when they’ve demonstrated empathy and humility while dialing back their egos. This is because they’re people we can work with—literally. Nobody wants to work with a narcissist or a rock star. Nobody is materially impressed by how many lines of code we wrote, or how fast we wrote it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When people want to work with us—or even look forward to it—that means we have trust and respect. We’ll be on proper footing for working effectively as a group to solve problems. For developers this looks like coaching a junior developer, hopping on a quick call to pair with somebody, or understanding the business value of the next backlog item. For leaders this looks like people who feel empowered to do their work, who can proactively identify issues, or who can rally and adapt when circumstances change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anybody can do this! I can’t think of any other career advice that’s as universal as empathy and humility. Everybody is capable of, at any point in their lives, small yet impactful improvements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So remember—watch your ego and look for opportunities to leverage empathy and humility in the pursuit of information so that you can solve problems together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my next essay on this subject I’ll get into the practical. What I like about this advice is that, while there’s much we can do, we don’t have to do it all to see some benefit. We can pick and choose and try something out. We can take your time and grow. Nobody’s perfect, not even Ted Lasso. Even if we take after a character like Roy Kent we can still call that a win. Just watch the show, OK?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our daily lives empathy and humility are obvious virtues we aspire to. They keep our egos in check. Less obvious is that they're practical skills in the workplace, too. I think, for developers and technical leaders in particular, that the absence of ego is the best way to further our careers and do great work.&lt;/p&gt;https://matthogg.fyi/a-unified-theory-of-ego-empathy-and-humility-at-work/&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46029534</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 02:01:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Passing the Torch – My Last Root DNSSEC KSK Ceremony as Crypto Officer 4</title><link>https://technotes.seastrom.com/2025/11/23/passing-the-torch.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e483d9919623d7d9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sun 23 November 2025&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;misc&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many years ago, when I was but an infant, the first computers were connected on the ARPANET - the seminal computer network that would eventually evolve to become the Internet. Computers at the time were large and expensive; indeed the first version of NCP - the predecessor of TCP/IP - only countenanced roughly 250 computers on the network.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The name (human friendly) to network address (computer friendly) mapping on this network was maintained via a "hosts file" - literally a flat file of ordered pairs, creating the connection between host (computer) name and address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So it continued as computers got less expensive and proliferated, the Network Effect caused more institutions to want to be connected to the ARPANET. TCP/IP was developed in response to this, with support for orders of magnitude more connected computers. Along the way, the military users of the network got carved off into its own network, and by the early 1980s we had the beginnings of the Internet, or a "catenet" as it was sometimes called at the time - a network of networks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clearly, as we went from "a couple hundred computers" to "capacity for billions", a centrally managed host file wasn't going to scale, and by the early 1980s development had started on a distributed database to replace the centrally managed file. The name for this distributed database was the Domain Name System, or DNS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's important to realize that at the time, access to the network of networks was still restricted to a chosen few - higher education, research institutions, military organizations and the military-industrial complex (ARPA, later DARPA, was, after all, an activity of the United States Department of Defense), and a few companies that were tightly associated with one or more of those constituencies. Broad public commercial access to the Internet was many years in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was in this environment that the DNS sprang forth. Academics, military researchers, university students - a pretty collegial environment. Not to mention paleo-cybersecurity practices - indeed the word "cybersecurity" may not have even been coined yet, though the notion of "computer security" dates back to the early 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've mentioned this brief "history of the early Internet" to preemptively answer the question which inevitably arises: why didn't DNS have better security built in? The answer is twofold: firstly it didn't have to based on the environment that it evolved in, and secondly, even if it had, the security practices would have been firmly rooted in 1980s best practices, which would certainly be inadequate by modern standards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Discovery of security flaws in 1990 led the IETF to begin development on Domain Name System Security Extensions (DNSSEC) in 1995. Early versions were difficult to deploy. Later versions improved somewhat. But inertia is a thing, the status quo tends to prevail, and there was very real concern that DNSSEC would be a net reliability minus (security vs. availability can be a tricky circle to square), concentrate power in undesirable ways, and result in other unforeseen negative effects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, as it so often does, it took a crisis to get the ball rolling for real. In 2008, Dan Kaminsky discovered a fundamental flaw in DNS, which simplified cache poisoning - essentially making it possible for an attacker to misdirect users to arbitrary web sites.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In less than two years, the DNS root would be cryptographically signed - allowing those who wished to sign their domains as well to create a cryptographic chain of trust authenticating their DNS lookups. This is non-repudiation, not non-disclosure - DNS queries and responses continued to happen in the clear. But this time, responses came back with a digital signature, courtesy of DNSSEC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;David Huberman at ICANN did a splendid slide deck explaining how it all works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trust in a system requires more than technical correctness. It involves trust in the execution of running the system itself. For that reason ICANN decided that it would build a framework to facilitate trust and transparency. Among other things it included:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Placing the cryptographic material in two highly secure sites, one near Washington DC and one in Los Angeles (geographic diversity)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Creating a multi-layered security regimen requiring several people to access the Key Management Facility&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Storing cryptographic material in offline HSMs which utilize Shamir's Secret Sharing to require a quorum of at least 3 out of 7 Crypto Officers to be present in order to "wake them up"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trusted Community Representatives with roles of Crypto Officer and Recovery Key Share Holder&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Highly scripted (and therefore auditable) ceremonies surrounding handling the cryptographc material&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Live streaming all events&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hosting External Witnesses from the community who have expressed interest in being present for a ceremony in person&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the call for volunteers to be Trusted Community Representatives came out, I was no stranger to community involvement, having served several years on the ARIN Advisory Council and done community work (and later Board work) for NANOG. I was employed by a Top Level Domain operator, and submitted my CV and expressed my interest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's how I found myself in Culpeper, Virginia in 2010 as Crypto Officer 4 at the first ceremony for signing the DNSSEC Root. I had no idea that I would still be doing it fifteen years later. I was the last of the original Crypto Officers for KMF-East, and the second last overall - outlasted only by Subramanian "SM" Moonesamy, who is Crypto Officer 7 for KMF-West.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's been an adventure. I've been a small participant in root key rolls, put in a B-roll appearance on BBC Horizon (S53E13), become friends with many of the people I served with, overseen ceremonies remotely during the COVID lockdown, and witnessed an amazing pivot by ICANN staff who managed to get new HSMs selected, tested, integrated, and deployed on only 8 months' notice, a feat which I remain in awe of.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was an early advocate for improving trust in our process by leveraging natural turnover and backfilling existing TCRs with people selected from a broader set of qualified individuals than just the fellowship of DNS protocol experts, operators, and developers. I'm grateful that our voices were heard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On November 13th 2025, I passed the torch to Lodrina Cherne who is now Crypto Officer 4 for KMF-East. Lodrina is a security researcher, an educator with an emphasis on digital forensics, and works in security engineering at a large cloud provider. I'm honored to have her as my successor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've had several people reach out to me to ask what prompted me to step back from the ICANN volunteer work. Those who were hoping for some kind of salacious dirt or scandal were sorely disappointed - quite the opposite, this is a huge success story and I'm pleased to have been able to do my small part. A direct cut and paste from Slack logs with one of them follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;What led you to step back from ICANN?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Several things:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It was understood to be a 5 year commitment. I've been doing it for more than 15.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It was broadly agreed among the cohort many years ago (over a decade ago) that more people from more diverse backgrounds than just DNS-old-boy-network (which was the original group of TCRs) was a Good Thing.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Many people cycled out earlier; I was happy to let the folks for whom travel was more odious go first. But it's only practical and only really good for the system to cycle out a single TCR per ceremony.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;COVID delayed this. Kaminsky's untimely death and subsequent replacement as a recovery key shareholder (RKSH) delayed this.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A further delay was the AEP Keyper HSM getting abruptly EOLed, and the transition to the Thales Luna HSMs. It went off without a hitch after being researched, developed, and executed in 8 months - a record which I stand in awe of and which is a true testament to the skill and commitment of the ICANN PTI team. ICANN expressed the desire for continuity among long-serving COs past that milestone; Frederico Neves (fellow original Crypto Officer) and I were willing to extend our stay for that.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So in short it was time to pass the torch. Everyone has been doing everything right. I remarked at the end of the Ceremony 59 that when we started doing this 15 years ago, success was not guaranteed; it took the Kaminsky bug to get us over the line to actually deploy it. Today, the major Unix DNS resolvers ship with DNSSEC validation enabled. All of the major public DNS resolvers (google, quad9, cloudflare) do DNSSEC validation. I thanked everyone who has been responsible for and put their personal credibility on the line for the security, integrity, and credibility of this process and stated that I was honored to have been able to play a small part in doing that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Epilogue:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I won't be participating in most East Coast ceremonies from here on out, but I don't rule out occasionally showing up as an external witness, particularly at KMF-West where I have never visited in person.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here scans of our ceremony scripts from both Ceremony 59 and the previous day's administrative ceremonies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Root DNSSEC KSK Administrative Ceremony 59 Backup HSM Acceptance Testing&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46029649</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 02:16:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ask HN: Hearing aid wearers, what's hot?</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46029699</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="16e2875fc8f6a6a6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;One of my Phonak Audeo 90’s (RIC) died the other day after 5 years and I’m shopping for new. What’s your go to hearing aid currently if you’ve upgraded recently or have been thinking of doing so?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Moderate loss, have worn them for many years, enjoy listening to music and nature, but also need help in meetings and noisy environments.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not worried about cost and wanting to get one more good deal out of work insurance before I retire.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46029699</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 02:25:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>We stopped roadmap work for a week and fixed 189 bugs</title><link>https://lalitm.com/fixits-are-good-for-the-soul/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3623d0560ff62cdd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;We stopped roadmap work for a week and fixed 189 bugs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s Friday at 4pm. I’ve just closed my 12th bug of the week. My brain is completely fried. And I’m staring at the bug leaderboard, genuinely sad that Monday means going back to regular work. Which is weird because I love regular work. But fixit weeks have a special place in my heart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s a fixit, you ask?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once a quarter, my org with ~45 software engineers stops all regular work for a week. That means no roadmap work, no design work, no meetings or standups.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, we fix the small things that have been annoying us and our users:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;an error message that’s been unclear for two years&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;a weird glitch when the user scrolls and zooms at the same time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;a test which runs slower than it should, slowing down CI for everyone&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The rules are simple: 1) no bug should take over 2 days and 2) all work should focus on either small end-user bugs/features or developer productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also have a “points system” for bugs and a leaderboard showing how many points people have. And there’s a promise of t-shirts for various achievements: first bug fix, most points, most annoying bug, etc. It’s a simple structure, but it works surprisingly well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What we achieved&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some stats from this fixit:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;189 bugs fixed&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;40 people participated&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;4 was the median number of bugs closed per person&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;12 was maximum number of bugs closed by one person&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bug Burndown Chart for the Q4'25 Fixit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some of the highlights (sadly many people in my org work in internal-facing things so I cannot share their work!):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I closed a feature request from 2021! It’s a classic fixit issue: a small improvement that never bubbled to the priority list. It took me one day to implement. One day for something that sat there for four years. And it’s going to provide a small but significant boost to every user’s experience of Perfetto.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;My colleague made this small change to improve team productivity. Just ~25 lines of code in a GitHub Action to avoid every UI developer taking two extra clicks to open the CI’s build. The response from the team speaks for itself:&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Such a simple change but the team loved it!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I also fixed this issue to provide a new “amalgamated” version of our SDK, allowing it to be easily integrated into projects. It’s one of those things that might be the difference between someone deciding to use us or not, but building it took just one hour of work (with liberal use of AI!).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The benefits of fixits&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;For the product: craftsmanship and care&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I care deeply about any product I work on. That means asking big questions like “what should we build?” and “how do we make this fast?” But it also means asking smaller questions: “is this error message actually helpful?” or “would I be frustrated using this?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A hallmark of any good product is attention to detail: a sense that someone has thought things through, and the pieces fit together to make a cohesive whole. And the opposite is true: a product with rough edges might be tolerated if there are no alternatives, but there will always be a sense of frustration and “I wish I could use something else”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixits are a great chance to work on exactly those details that separate good products from great ones. The small things your average user might not consciously notice, but absolutely will notice if they’re wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;For the individual: doing, not thinking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I sometimes miss the feeling I had earlier in my career when I got to just fix things. See something broken, fix it, ship it the same day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The more senior you get in a big company, the less you do that. Most of your time becomes thinking about what to build next, planning quarters ahead, navigating tradeoffs and getting alignment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixits give me that early-career feeling back. You see the bug, you fix it, you ship it, you close it, you move on. There’s something deeply satisfying about work where the question isn’t “what should we do?” but rather “can I make this better?” And you get to answer that question multiple times in a week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;For the team: morale and spirit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People sharing live updates in the Fixit chatroom&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having 40 people across two time zones all fixing bugs together adds a whole other dimension.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vibe of the office is different: normally we’re all heads-down on different projects, but during fixit the team spirit comes out strong. People share their bug fixes in chat rooms, post before-and-after screenshots and gather around monitors to demo a new feature or complain about a particularly nasty bug they’re wrestling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The daily update from Friday&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The leaderboard amplifies this energy. There’s a friendly sense of competition as people try and balance quick wins with meatier bugs they can share stories about.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s also a short update every morning about how the previous day went:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;total bugs fixed&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;how many people have fixed at least one bug&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;how many different products we’ve fixed things in&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;who’s currently at the top of the leaderboard&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of this creates real momentum, and people feel magnetically pulled into the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to run a fixit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve participated in 6 fixits over the years and I’ve learned a lot about what makes them successful. Here are a few things that matter more than you’d think.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Preparation is key&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of what makes a fixit work happens before the week even starts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All year round, we encourage everyone to tag bugs as “good fixit candidates” as they encounter them. Then the week before fixit, each subteam goes through these bugs and sizes them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;small (less than half a day)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;medium (less than a day)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;large (less than 2 days).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They assign points accordingly: 1, 2, or 4.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also create a shortlist of high-priority bugs we really want fixed. People start there and move to the full list once those are done. This pre-work is critical: it prevents wasting day one with people aimlessly searching for bugs to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The 2-day hard limit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In one of our early fixits, someone picked up what looked like a straightforward bug. It should have been a few hours, maybe half a day. But it turned into a rabbit hole. Dependencies on other systems, unexpected edge cases, code that hadn’t been touched in years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They spent the entire fixit week on it. And then the entire week after fixit trying to finish it. What started as a bug fix turned into a mini project. The work was valuable! But they missed the whole point of a fixit. No closing bugs throughout the week. No momentum. No dopamine hits from shipping fixes. Just one long slog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s why we have the 2-day hard limit now. If something is ballooning, cut your losses. File a proper bug, move it to the backlog, pick something else. The limit isn’t about the work being worthless - it’s about keeping fixit feeling like fixit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Number of people matters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We didn’t always do fixits with 40 people. Early on, this wasn’t an org-wide effort, just my subteam of 7 people. It worked okay: bugs got fixed and there was a sense of pride in making the product better. But it felt a bit hollow: in the bigger picture of our org, it didn’t feel like anyone else noticed or cared.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At ~40 people, it feels like a critical mass that changes things significantly. The magic number is probably somewhere between 7 and 40. And it probably varies based on the team. But whatever the number is, the collective energy matters. If you’re trying this with 5 people, it might still be worth doing, but it probably won’t feel the same.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Gamification&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The points and leaderboard are more than a gimmick, but they have to be handled carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What works for us:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Points are coarse, not precise: We deliberately use 1/2/4 points instead of trying to measure exact effort; the goal is “roughly right and fun”, not accurate performance evaluation.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Celebrate breadth, not just volume. We give t-shirts for things like “first bug fix”, “most annoying bug fixed”, not just “most points”. That keeps newer or less experienced engineers engaged.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Visibility over prizes. A shout-out in the daily update or an internal post often matters more than the actual t-shirt.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No attachment to perf reviews. This is important: fixit scores do not feed into performance reviews. The moment they do, people will start gaming it and the good vibe will die.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve had very little “gaming” in practice. Social norms do a good job of keeping people honest and 40 is still small enough that there’s a sense of “loyalty to the cause” from folks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The AI factor&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The big challenge with fixits is context switching. Constantly changing what you’re working on means constantly figuring out new parts of the codebase, thinking about new problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI tools have mitigated this in a big way. The code they write is less important than their ability to quickly search through relevant files and summarize what needs to change. They might be right or wrong, but having that starting point really reduces the cognitive load. And sometimes (rarely) they one-shot a fix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This docs change was a perfect example of the above: an update to our docs which catches out new contributors and AI was able to one-shot the fix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, in my record page change it was more useful for giving me prototypes of what the code should look like and I had to put in significant effort to correct the bad UX it generated and its tendency to “over-generate” code. Even so, it got me to the starting line much faster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Criticisms of fixits (and why I still like them anyway)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve definitely come across people who question whether fixits are actually a good idea. Some of the criticisms are fair but overall I still think it’s worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;“Isn’t this just admitting you ignore bugs the rest of the time?”&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To some extent, yes, this is an admission of the fact that “papercut” bugs are underweighted in importance, both by managers and engineers. It’s all too easy to tunnel on making sure a big project is successful and easier to ignore the small annoyances for users and the team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixits are a way of counterbalancing that somewhat and saying “actually those bugs matter too”. That’s not to say we don’t fix important bugs during regular work; we absolutely do. But fixits recognize that there should be a place for handling the “this is slightly annoying but never quite urgent enough” class of problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The whole reason we started fixits in the first place is that we observed these bugs never get actioned. Given this, I think carving out some explicit time for it is a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;“Isn’t it a waste to pause roadmap work for a whole week?”&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s definitely a tradeoff. 40 engineer-weeks is a lot of manpower and there’s an argument to be made it should be used for actually solving roadmap problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I think this underweights the importance of polish of products to users. We’ve consistently found that the product feels noticeably better afterward (including positive comments from users about things they notice!) and there’s a sense of pride in having a well-functioning product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A user’s response to my PR to improve the Perfetto UI “record” page&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, many of the team productivity fixes compound (faster tests, clearer errors, smoother workflows) so the benefits carry forward well beyond the week itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;This only works at big companies!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I agree that a full week might be too much for tiny teams or startups. But you can still borrow the idea in smaller chunks: a “fixit Friday” once a month, or a 2-day mini-fixit each quarter. The core idea is the same: protected, collective time to fix the stuff people complain about but no one schedules time to address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fixits are good for the soul&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The official justification for fixits is that they improve product quality and developer productivity. And of course they do this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the unofficial reason I love them is simpler: it just feels good to fix things. It takes me back to a simpler time, and putting thought and attention into building great products is a big part of my ethos for how software engineering should be done. I wouldn’t want to work like that all the time. But I also wouldn’t want to work somewhere that never makes time for it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46029772</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 02:36:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A free tool that stuns LLMs with thousands of invisible Unicode characters</title><link>https://gibberifier.com</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="26bd1c36eda432b6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Block AIs from reading your text with invisible Unicode characters while preserving meaning for humans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How it works: This tool inserts invisible zero-width Unicode characters between each character of your input text. The text will look the same but will be much longer and can help stop AI plagarism. It also helps to waste tokens, causing users to run into ratelimits faster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How to use: This tool works best when gibberifying the most important parts of an essay prompt, up to about 500 characters. This makes it harder for the AI to detect while still functioning well in Google Docs. Some AI models will crash or fail to process the gibberified text, while others will respond with confusion or simply ignore everything inside the gibberified text.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use cases: Anti-plagiarism, text obfuscation for LLM scrapers, or just for fun!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even just one word's worth of gibberified text is enough to block something like Flint AI from grading a session.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;🤖 Tested Against AI Models&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;🤖 ChatGPT&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Result: Doesn't understand gibberified text - responds with confusion or completely ignores the invisible characters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46029889</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 03:00:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Cloudflare outage was a good thing</title><link>https://gist.github.com/jbreckmckye/32587f2907e473dd06d68b0362fb0048</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="eb10b5770b2785f9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare, the CDN provider, suffered a massive outage today. Some of the world's most popular apps and web services were left inaccessible for serveral hours whilst the Cloudflare team scrambled to fix a whole swathe of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that might be a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proximate cause of the outage was pretty mundane: a bad config file triggered a latent bug in one of Cloudflare's services. The file was too large (details still hazy) and this led to a cascading failure across Cloudflare operations. Probably there is some useful post-morteming about canary releases and staged rollouts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the bigger problem, the ultimate cause, behind today's chaos is the creeping centralisation of the internet and a society that is sleepwalking into assuming the net is always on and always working.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's not just "trivial" stuff like Twitter and League of Legends that were affected, either. A friend of mine remarked caustically about his experience this morning&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I couldn't get air for my tyres at two garages because of cloudflare going down. Bloody love the lack of resilience that goes into the design when the machine says "cash only" and there's no cash slot. So flat tires for everyone! Brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are living in a society where every part of our lives is increasingly mediated through the internet: work, banking, retail, education, entertainment, dating, family, government ID and credit checks. And the internet is increasingly tied up in fewer and fewer points of failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's ironic because the internet was actually designed for decentralisation, a system that governments could use to coordinate their response in the event of nuclear war. But due to the economics of the internet, the challenges of things like bots and scrapers, more of more web services are holed up in citadels like AWS or behind content distribution networks like Cloudflare.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outages like today's are a good thing because they're a warning. They can force redundancy and resilience into systems. They can make the pillars of our society - governments, businesses, banks - provide reliable alternatives when things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Ideally ones that are completely offline)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can draw a parallel to how COVID-19 shook up global supply chains: the logic up until 2020 was that you wanted your system to be as lean and efficient as possible, even if it meant relying totally on international supplies or keeping as little spare inventory as possible. After 2020 businesses realised they needed to diversify and build slack in the system to tolerate shocks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the same way that growing one kind of banana, nearly resulted in bananas going extinct, we're drifing towards a society that can't survive without digital infrastructure; and a digital infrastructure that can't operate without two or three key players. One day there's going to be an outage, a bug, or cyberattack from a hostile state, that demonstrates how fragile that system is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Embrace outages, and build redundancy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46029908</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 03:04:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>RuBee</title><link>https://computer.rip/2025-11-22-RuBee.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e20d99aa1e6f77f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;RuBee&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have at least a few readers for which the sound of a man's voice saying "government cell phone detected" will elicit a palpable reaction. In Department of Energy facilities across the country, incidences of employees accidentally carrying phones into secure areas are reduced through a sort of automated nagging. A device at the door monitors for the presence of a tag; when the tag is detected it plays an audio clip. Because this is the government, the device in question is highly specialized, fantastically expensive, and says "government cell phone" even though most of the phones in question are personal devices. Look, they already did the recording, they're not changing it now!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the things that I love is weird little wireless networks. Long ago I wrote about ANT+, for example, a failed personal area network standard designed mostly around fitness applications. There's tons of these, and they have a lot of similarities---so it's fun to think about the protocols that went down a completely different path. It's even better, of course, if the protocol is obscure outside of an important niche. And a terrible website, too? What more could I ask for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The DoE's cell-phone nagging boxes, and an array of related but more critical applications, rely on an unusual personal area networking protocol called RuBee.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RuBee is a product of Visible Assets Inc., or VAI, founded in 2004 1 by John K. Stevens. Stevens seems a somewhat improbable founder, with a background in biophysics and eye health, but he's a repeat entrepreneur. He's particularly fond of companies called Visible: he founded Visible Assets after his successful tenure as CEO of Visible Genetics. Visible Genetics was an early innovator in DNA sequencing, and still provides a specialty laboratory service that sequences samples of HIV in order to detect vulnerabilities to antiretroviral medications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clinical trials in the early 2000s exposed Visible Genetics to one of the more frustrating parts of health care logistics: refrigeration. Samples being shipped to the lab and reagents shipped out to clinics were both temperature sensitive. Providers had to verify that these materials had stayed adequately cold throughout shipping and handling, otherwise laboratory results could be invalid or incorrect. Stevens became interested in technical solutions to these problems; he wanted some way to verify that samples were at acceptable temperatures both in storage and in transit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moreover, Stevens imagined that these sensors would be in continuous communication. There's a lot of overlap between this application and personal area networks (PANs), protocols like Bluetooth that provide low-power communications over short ranges. There is also clear overlap with RFID; you can buy RFID temperature sensors. VAI, though, coined the term visibility network to describe RuBee. That's visibility as in asset visibility: somewhat different from Bluetooth or RFID, RuBee as a protocol is explicitly designed for situations where you need to "keep tabs" on a number of different objects. Despite the overlap with other types of wireless communications, the set of requirements on a visibility network have lead RuBee down a very different technical path.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visibility networks have to be highly reliable. When you are trying to keep track of an asset, a failure to communicate with it represents a fundamental failure of the system. For visibility networks, the ability to actually convey a payload is secondary: the main function is just reliably detecting that endpoints exist. Visibility networks have this in common with RFID, and indeed, despite its similarities to technologies like BLE RuBee is positioned mostly as a competitor to technologies like UHF RFID.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are several differences between RuBee and RFID; for example, RuBee uses active (battery-powered) tags and the tags are generally powered by a complete 4-bit microcontroller. That doesn't necessarily sound like an advantage, though. While RuBee tags advertise a battery life of "5-25 years", the need for a battery seems mostly like a liability. The real feature is what active tags enable: RuBee operates in the low frequency (LF) band, typically at 131 kHz.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At that low frequency, the wavelength is very long, about 2.5 km. With such a long wavelength, RuBee communications all happen at much less than one wavelength in range. RF engineers refer to this as near-field operation, and it has some properties that are intriguingly different from more typical far-field RF communications. In the near-field, the magnetic field created by the antenna is more significant than the electrical field. RuBee devices are intentionally designed to emit very little electrical RF signal. Communications within a RuBee network are achieved through magnetic, not electrical fields. That's the core of RuBee's magic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The idea of magnetic coupling is not unique to RuBee. Speaking of the near-field, there's an obvious comparison to NFC which works much the same way. The main difference, besides the very different logical protocols, is that NFC operates at 13.56 MHz. At this higher frequency, the wavelength is only around 20 meters. The requirement that near-field devices be much closer than a full wavelength leads naturally to NFC's very short range, typically specified as 4 cm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At LF frequencies, RuBee can achieve magnetic coupling at ranges up to about 30 meters. That's a range comparable to, and often much better than, RFID inventory tracking technologies. Improved range isn't RuBee's only benefit over RFID. The properties of magnetic fields also make it a more robust protocol. RuBee promises significantly less vulnerability to shielding by metal or water than RFID.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two key scenarios where this comes up: the first is equipment stored in metal containers or on metal shelves, or equipment that is itself metallic. In that scenario, it's difficult to find a location for an RFID tag that won't suffer from shielding by the container. The case of water might seem less important, but keep in mind that people are made mostly of water. RFID reading is often unreliable for objects carried on a person, which are likely to be shielded from the reader by the water content of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These problems are not just theoretical. WalMart is a major adopter of RFID inventory technology, and in early rollouts struggled with low successful read rates. Metal, moisture (including damp cardboard boxes), antenna orientation, and multipath/interference effects could cause read failure rates as high as 33% when scanning a pallet of goods. Low read rates are mostly addressed by using RFID "portals" with multiple antennas. Eight antennas used as an array greatly increase read rate, but at a cost of over ten thousand dollars per portal system. Even so, WalMart seems to now target a success rate of only 95% during bulk scanning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;95% might sound pretty good, but there are a lot of visibility applications where a failure rate of even a couple percent is unacceptable. These mostly go by the euphemism "high value goods," which depending on your career trajectory you may have encountered in corporate expense and property policies. High-value goods tend to be items that are both attractive to theft and where theft has particularly severe consequences. Classically, firearms and explosives. Throw in classified material for good measure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wonder if Stevens was surprised by RuBee's market trajectory. He came out of the healthcare industry and, it seems, originally developed RuBee for cold chain visibility... but, at least in retrospect, it's quite obvious that its most compelling application is in the armory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because RuBee tags are small and largely immune to shielding by metals, you can embed them directly in the frames of firearms, or as an aftermarket modification you can mill out some space under the grip. RuBee tags in weapons will read reliably when they are stored in metal cases or on metal shelving, as is often the case. They will even read reliably when a weapon is carried holstered, close to a person's body.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since RuBee tags incorporate an active microcontroller, there are even more possibilities. Temperature logging is one thing, but firearm-embedded RuBee tags can incorporate an accelerometer (NIST-traceable, VAI likes to emphasize) and actually count the rounds fired.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sidebar time: there is a long history of political hazard around "smart guns." The term "smart gun" is mostly used more specifically for firearms that identify their user, for example by fingerprint authentication or detection of an RFID fob. The idea has become vague enough, though, that mention of a firearm with any type of RFID technology embedded would probably raise the specter of the smart gun to gun-rights advocates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further, devices embedded in firearms that count the number of rounds fired have been proposed for decades, if not a century, as a means of accountability. The holder of a weapon could, in theory, be required to positively account for every round fired. That could eliminate incidents of unreported use of force by police, for example. In practice I think this is less compelling than it sounds, simple counting of rounds leaves too many opportunities to fudge the numbers and conceal real-world use of a weapon as range training, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, the NRA has long been vehemently opposed to the incorporation of any sort of technology into weapons that could potentially be used as a means of state control or regulation. The concern isn't completely unfounded; the state of New Jersey did, for a time, have legislation that would have made user-identifying "smart guns" mandatory if they were commercially available. The result of the NRA's strident lobbying is that no such gun has ever become commercially available; "smart guns" have been such a political third rail that any firearms manufacturer that dared to introduce one would probably face a boycott by most gun stores. For better or worse, a result of the NRA's powerful political advocacy in this area is that the concept of embedding security or accountability technology into weapons has never been seriously pursued in the US. Even a tentative step in that direction can produce a huge volume of critical press for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I bring this up because I think it explains some of why VAI seems a bit vague and cagey about the round-counting capabilities of their tags. They position it as purely a maintenance feature, allowing the armorer to keep accurate tabs on the preventative maintenance schedule for each individual weapon (in armory environments, firearm users are often expected to report how many rounds they fired for maintenance tracking reasons). The resistance of RuBee tags to concealment is only positioned as a deterrent to theft, although the idea of RuBee-tagged firearms creates obvious potential for security screening. Probably the most profitable option for VAI would be to promote RuBee-tagged firearms as tool for enforcement of gun control laws, but this is a political impossibility and bringing it up at all could cause significant reputational harm, especially with the government as a key customer. The result is marketing copy that is a bit odd, giving a set of capabilities that imply an application that is never mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;VAI found an incredible niche with their arms-tracking application. Institutional users of firearms, like the military, police, and security forces, are relatively price-insensitive and may have strict accounting requirements. By the mid-'00s, VAI was into the long sales cycle of proposing the technology to the military. That wasn't entirely unsuccessful. RuBee shot-counting weapon inventory tags were selected by the Naval Surface Warfare Center in 2010 for installation on SCAR and M4 rifles. That contract had a five-year term, it's unclear to me if it was renewed. Military contracting opened quite a few doors to VAI, though, and created a commercial opportunity that they eagerly pursued.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps most importantly, weapons applications required an impressive round of safety and compatibility testing. RuBee tags have the fairly unique distinction of military approval for direct attachment to ordnance, something called "zero separation distance" as the tags do not require a minimum separation from high explosives. Central to that certification are findings of intrinsic safety of the tags (that they do not contain enough energy to trigger explosives) and that the magnetic fields involved cannot convey enough energy to heat anything to dangerous temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's not the only special certification that RuBee would acquire. The military has a lot of firearms, but military procurement is infamously slow and mercurial. Improved weapon accountability is, almost notoriously, not a priority for the US military which has often had stolen weapons go undetected until their later use in crime. The Navy's interest in RuBee does not seem to have translated to more widespread military applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then you have police departments, probably the largest institutional owners of firearms and a very lucrative market for technology vendors. But here we run into the political hazard: the firearms lobby is very influential on police departments, as are police unions which generally oppose technical accountability measures. Besides, most police departments are fairly cash-poor and are not likely to make a major investment in a firearms inventory system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That leaves us with institutional security forces. And there is one category of security force that are particularly well-funded, well-equipped, and beholden to highly R&amp;amp;D-driven, almost pedantic standards of performance: the protection forces of atomic energy facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protection forces at privately-operated atomic energy facilities, such as civilian nuclear power plants, are subject to licensing and scrutiny by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. Things step up further at the many facilities operated by the National Nuclear Security Administration (NNSA). Protection forces for NNSA facilities are trained at the Department of Energy's National Training Center, at the former Manzano Base here in Albuquerque. Concern over adequate physical protection of NNSA facilities has lead Sandia National Laboratories to become one of the premier centers for R&amp;amp;D in physical security. Teams of scientists and engineers have applied sometimes comical scientific rigor to "guns, gates, and guards," the traditional articulation of physical security in the nuclear world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That scope includes the evaluation of new technology for the management of protection forces, which is why Oak Ridge National Laboratory launched an evaluation program for the RuBee tagging of firearms in their armory. The white paper on this evaluation is curiously undated, but citations "retrieved 2008" lead me to assume that the evaluation happened right around the middle of the '00s. At the time, VAI seems to have been involved in some ultimately unsuccessful partnership with Oracle, leading to the branding of the RuBee system as Oracle Dot-Tag Server. The term "Dot-Tag" never occurs outside of very limited materials around the Oracle partnership, so I'm not sure if it was Oracle branding for RuBee or just some passing lark. In any case, Oracle's involvement seems to have mainly just been the use of the Oracle database for tracking inventory data---which was naturally replaced by PostgreSQL at Oak Ridge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Oak Ridge trial apparently went well enough, and around the same time, the Pantex Plant in Texas launched an evaluation of RuBee for tracking classified tools. Classified tools are a tricky category, as they're often metallic and often stored in metallic cases. During the trial period, Pantex tagged a set of sample classified tools with RuBee tags and then transported them around the property, testing the ability of the RuBee controllers to reliably detect them entering and exiting areas of buildings. Simultaneously, Pantex evaluated the use of RuBee tags to track containers of "chemical products" through the manufacturing lifecycle. Both seem to have produced positive results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are quite a few interesting and strange aspects of the RuBee system, a result of its purpose-built Visibility Network nature. A RuBee controller can have multiple antennas that it cycles through. RuBee tags remain in a deep-sleep mode for power savings until they detect a RuBee carrier during their periodic wake cycle. When a carrier is detected, they fully wake and listen for traffic. A RuBee controller can send an interrogate message and any number of tags can respond, with an interesting and novel collision detection algorithm used to ensure reliable reading of a large number of tags.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The actual RuBee protocol is quite simple, and can also be referred to as IEEE 1902.1 since the decision of VAI to put it through the standards process. Packets are small and contain basic addressing info, but they can also contain arbitrary payload in both directions, perfect for data loggers or sensors. RuBee tags are identified by something that VAI oddly refers to as an "IP address," causing some confusion over whether or not VAI uses IP over 1902.1. They don't, I am confident saying after reading a whole lot of documents. RuBee tags, as standard, have three different 4-byte addresses. VAI refers to these as "IP, subnet, and MAC," 2 but these names are more like analogies. Really, the "IP address" and "subnet" are both configurable arbitrary addresses, with the former intended for unicast traffic and the latter for broadcast. For example, you would likely give each asset a unique IP address, and use subnet addresses for categories or item types. The subnet address allows a controller to interrogate for every item within that category at once. The MAC address is a fixed, non-configurable address derived from the tag's serial number. They're all written in the formats we associate with IP networks, dotted-quad notation, as a matter of convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that's about it as far as the protocol specification, besides of course the physical details which are a 131,072 Hz carrier, 1024 Hz data clock, either ASK or BPSK modulation. The specification also describes an interesting mode called "clip," in which a set of multiple controllers interrogate in exact synchronization and all tags then reply in exact synchronization. Somewhat counter-intuitively, because of the ability of RuBee controllers to separate out multiple simultaneous tag transmissions using an anti-collision algorithm based on random phase shifts by each tag, this is ideal. It allows a room, say an armory, full of RuBee controllers to rapidly interrogate the entire contents of the room. I think this feature may have been added after the Oak Ridge trials...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RuBee is quite slow, typically 1,200 baud, so inventorying a large number of assets can take a while (Oak Ridge found that their system could only collect data on 2-7 tags per second per controller). But it's so robust that it an achieve a 100% read rate in some very challenging scenarios. Evaluation by the DoE and the military produced impressive results. You can read, for example, of a military experiment in which a RuBee antenna embedded in a roadway reliably identified rifles secured in steel containers in passing Humvees.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paradoxically, then, one of the benefits of RuBee in the military/defense context is that it is also difficult to receive. Here is RuBee's most interesting trick: somewhat oversimplified, the strength of an electrical radio signal goes as 1/r, while the strength of a magnetic field goes as 1/r^3. RuBee equipment is optimized, by antenna design, to produce a minimal electrical field. The result is that RuBee tags can very reliably be contacted at short range (say, around ten feet), but are virtually impossible to contact or even detect at ranges over a few hundred feet. To the security-conscious buyer, this is a huge feature. RuBee tags are highly resistant to communications or electronic intelligence collection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider the logical implications of tagging the military's rifles. With conventional RFID, range is limited by the size and sensitivity of the antenna. Particularly when tags are incidentally powered by a nearby reader, an adversary with good equipment can detect RFID tags at very long range. VAI heavily references a 2010 DEFCON presentation, for example, that demonstrated detection of RFID tags at a range of 80 miles. One imagines that opportunistic detection by satellite is feasible for a state intelligence agency. That means that your rifle asset tracking is also revealing the movements of soldiers in the field, or at least providing a way to detect their approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most RuBee tags have their transmit power reduced by configuration, so even the maximum 100' range of the protocol is not achievable. VAI suggests that typical RuBee tags cannot be detected by radio direction finding equipment at ranges beyond 20', and that this range can be made shorter by further reducing transmit power.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once again, we have caught the attention of the Department of Energy. Because of the short range of RuBee tags, they have generally been approved as not representing a COMSEC or TEMPEST hazard to secure facilities. And that brings us back to the very beginning: why does the DoE use a specialized, technically interesting, and largely unique radio protocol to fulfill such a basic function as nagging people that have their phones? Because RuBee's security properties have allowed it to be approved for use adjacent to and inside of secure facilities. A RuBee tag, it is thought, cannot be turned into a listening device because the intrinsic range limitation of magnetic coupling will make it impossible to communicate with the tag from outside of the building. It's a lot like how infrared microphones still see some use in secure facilities, but so much more interesting!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;VAI has built several different product lines around RuBee, with names like Armory 20/20 and Shot Counting Allegro 20/20 and Store 20/20. The founder started his career in eye health, remember. None of them are that interesting, though. They're all pretty basic CRUD applications built around polling multiple RuBee controllers for tags in their presence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then there's the "Alert 20/20 DoorGuard:" a metal pedestal with a RuBee controller and audio announcement module, perfect for detecting government cell phones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the strangest things about RuBee is that it's hard to tell if it's still a going concern. VAI's website has a press release section, where nothing has been posted since 2019. The whole website feels like it was last revised even longer ago. When RuBee was newer, back in the '00s, a lot of industry journals covered it with headlines like "the new RFID." I think VAI was optimistic that RuBee could displace all kinds of asset tracking applications, but despite some special certifications in other fields (e.g. approval to use RuBee controllers and tags around pacemakers in surgical suites), I don't think RuBee has found much success outside of military applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RuBee's resistance to shielding is impressive, but RFID read rates have improved considerably with new DSP techniques, antenna array designs, and the generally reduced cost of modern RFID equipment. RuBee's unique advantages, its security properties and resistance to even intentional exfiltration, are interesting but not worth much money to buyers other than the military.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So that's the fate of RuBee and VAI: defense contracting. As far as I can tell, RuBee and VAI are about as vital as they have ever been, but RuBee is now installed as just one part of general defense contracts around weapons systems, armory management, and process safety and security. IEEE standardization has opened the door to use of RuBee by federal contractors under license, and indeed, Lockheed Martin is repeatedly named as a licensee, as are firearms manufacturers with military contracts like Sig Sauer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Besides, RuBee continues to grow closer to the DoE. In 2021, VAI appointed Lisa Gordon-Hagerty to it board of directors. Gordon-Hagerty was undersecretary of Energy and had lead the NNSA until the year before. This year, the New Hampshire Small Business Development Center wrote a glowing profile of VAI. They described it as a 25-employee company with a goal of hitting $30 million in annual revenue in the next two years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite the outdated website, VAI claims over 1,200 RuBee sites in service. I wonder how many of those are Alert 20/20 DoorGuards? Still, I do believe there are military weapons inventory systems currently in use. RuBee probably has a bright future, as a niche technology for a niche industry. If nothing else, they have legacy installations and intellectual property to lean on. A spreadsheet of VAI-owned patents on RuBee, with nearly 200 rows, encourages would-be magnetically coupled visibility network inventors not to go it on their own. I just wish I could get my hands on a controller....&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I have found some conflicting information on the date, it could have been as early as 2002. 2004 is the year I have the most confidence in.↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The documentation is confusing enough about these details that I am actually unclear on whether the RuBee "MAC address" is 4 bytes or 6. Examples show 6 byte addresses, but the actual 1902.1 specification only seems to allow 4 byte addresses in headers. Honestly all of the RuBee documentation is a mess like this. I suspect that part of the problem is that VAI has actually changed parts of the protocol and not all of their products are IEEE 1902.1 compliant.↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46029932</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 03:08:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Build desktop applications using Go and Web Technologies</title><link>https://github.com/wailsapp/wails</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f72de05a9f79331d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Build desktop applications using Go &amp;amp; Web Technologies. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Introduction&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Features&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Getting Started&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sponsors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;FAQ&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Stargazers over time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Contributors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;License&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inspiration&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The traditional method of providing web interfaces to Go programs is via a built-in web server. Wails offers a different approach: it provides the ability to wrap both Go code and a web frontend into a single binary. Tools are provided to make this easy for you by handling project creation, compilation and bundling. All you have to do is get creative!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use standard Go for the backend&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use any frontend technology you are already familiar with to build your UI&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Quickly create rich frontends for your Go programs using pre-built templates&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Easily call Go methods from Javascript&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Auto-generated Typescript definitions for your Go structs and methods&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Native Dialogs &amp;amp; Menus&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Native Dark / Light mode support&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Supports modern translucency and "frosted window" effects&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unified eventing system between Go and Javascript&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Powerful cli tool to quickly generate and build your projects&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multiplatform&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Uses native rendering engines - no embedded browser!&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The project roadmap may be found here. Please consult it before creating an enhancement request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The installation instructions are on the official website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is supported by these kind people / companies:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Is this an alternative to Electron?&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Depends on your requirements. It's designed to make it easy for Go programmers to make lightweight desktop applications or add a frontend to their existing applications. Wails does offer native elements such as menus and dialogs, so it could be considered a lightweight electron alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Who is this project aimed at?&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Go programmers who want to bundle an HTML/JS/CSS frontend with their applications, without resorting to creating a server and opening a browser to view it.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;What's with the name?&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When I saw WebView, I thought "What I really want is tooling around building a WebView app, a bit like Rails is to Ruby". So initially it was a play on words (Webview on Rails). It just so happened to also be a homophone of the English name for the Country I am from. So it stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The contributors list is getting too big for the readme! All the amazing people who have contributed to this project have their own page here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project was mainly coded to the following albums:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Manic Street Preachers - Resistance Is Futile&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Manic Street Preachers - This Is My Truth, Tell Me Yours&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Midnight - Endless Summer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gary Newman - Savage (Songs from a Broken World)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Steve Vai - Passion &amp;amp; Warfare&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ben Howard - Every Kingdom&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ben Howard - Noonday Dream&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adwaith - Melyn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gwidaith Hen Fran - Cedors Hen Wrach&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metallica - Metallica&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bloc Party - Silent Alarm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Maxthor - Another World&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Alun Tan Lan - Y Distawrwydd&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46030414</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 04:33:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lambda Calculus – Animated Beta Reduction of Lambda Diagrams</title><link>https://cruzgodar.com/applets/lambda-calculus</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="962d55ae5cddd3a0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JavaScript is required to use this site and many others. Consider enabling it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46030613</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 05:17:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Feds Want to Make It Illegal to Even Possess an Anarchist Zine</title><link>https://theintercept.com/2025/11/23/prairieland-ice-antifa-zines-criminalize-protest-journalism/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="45a1911142235093"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Federal prosecutors have filed a new indictment in response to a July 4 noise demonstration outside the Prairieland ICE detention facility in Alvarado, Texas, during which a police officer was shot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are numerous problems with the indictment, but perhaps the most glaring is its inclusion of charges against a Dallas artist who wasn’t even at the protest. Daniel “Des” Sanchez is accused of transporting a box that contained “Antifa materials” after the incident, supposedly to conceal evidence against his wife, Maricela Rueda, who was there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the boxed materials aren’t Molotov cocktails, pipe bombs, or whatever MAGA officials claim “Antifa” uses to wage its imaginary war on America. As prosecutors laid out in the July criminal complaint that led to the indictment, they were zines and pamphlets. Some contain controversial ideas — one was titled “Insurrectionary Anarchy” — but they’re fully constitutionally protected free speech. The case demonstrates the administration’s intensifying efforts to criminalize left-wing activists after Donald Trump announced in September that he was designating “Antifa” as a “major terrorist organization” — a legal designation that doesn’t exist for domestic groups — following the killing of Charlie Kirk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sanchez was first indicted in October on charges of “corruptly concealing a document or record” as a standalone case, but the new indictment merges his charges with those against the other defendants, likely in hopes of burying the First Amendment problems with the case against him under prosecutors’ claims about the alleged shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s an escalation of a familiar tactic. In 2023, Georgia prosecutors listed “zine” distribution as part of the conspiracy charges against 61 Stop Cop City protesters in a sprawling RICO indictment that didn’t bother to explain how each individual defendant was involved in any actual crime. I wrote back then about my concern that this wasn’t just sloppy overreach, but also a blueprint for censorship. Those fears have now been validated by Sanchez’s prosecution solely for possessing similar literature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There have been other warnings that cops and prosecutors think they’ve found a constitutional loophole — if you can’t punish reporting it, punish transporting it. Los Angeles journalist Maya Lau is suing the LA County Sheriff’s Department for secretly investigating her for conspiracy, theft of government property, unlawful access of a computer, burglary, and receiving stolen property. According to her attorneys, her only offense was reporting on a list of deputies with histories of misconduct for the Los Angeles Times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s also reminiscent of the Biden administration’s case against right-wing outlet Project Veritas for possessing and transporting Ashley Biden’s diary, which the organization bought from a Florida woman later convicted of stealing and selling it. The Constitution protects the right to publish materials stolen by others — a right that would be meaningless if they couldn’t possess the materials in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite the collapses of the Cop City prosecution and the Lau investigation — and its own dismissal of the Project Veritas case — the Trump administration has followed those dangerous examples, characterizing lawful activism and ideologies as terrorist conspiracies (a strategy Trump allies also floated during this first term) to seize the power to prosecute pamphlet possession anytime they use the magic word “Antifa.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s a chilling combination for any journalist, activist, or individual who criticizes Trump. National security reporters have long dealt with the specter of prosecution under the archaic Espionage Act for merely obtaining government secrets from sources, particularly after the Biden administration extracted a guilty plea from WikiLeaks founder Julian Assange. But the rest of the press — and everyone else, for that matter — understood that merely possessing written materials, no matter what they said, is not a crime.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Guilt by Literature&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At what point does a literary collection or newspaper subscription become prosecutorial evidence under the Trump administration’s logic? Essentially, whenever it’s convenient. The vagueness is a feature, not a bug. When people don’t know which political materials might later be deemed evidence of criminality, the safest course is to avoid engaging with controversial ideas altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The slippery slope from anarchist zines to conventional journalism isn’t hypothetical, and we’re already sliding fast. Journalist Mario Guevara can tell you that from El Salvador, where he was deported in a clear case of retaliation for livestreaming a No Kings protest. So can Tufts doctoral student Rümeysa Öztürk, as she awaits deportation proceedings for co-writing an opinion piece critical of Israel’s wars that the administration considers evidence of support for terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At least two journalists lawfully in the U.S. — Ya’akub Ira Vijandre and Sami Hamdi — were nabbed by ICE just last month. The case against Vijandre is partially based on his criticism of prosecutorial overreach in the Holy Land Five case and his liking social media posts that quote Quranic verses, raising the question of how far away we are from someone being indicted for transporting a Quran or a news article critical of the war on terror.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sanchez’s case is prosecutorial overreach stacked on more prosecutorial overreach. The National Lawyers Guild criticized prosecutors’ tenuous dot-connecting to justify holding 18 defendants responsible for one gunshot wound. Some defendants were also charged with supporting terrorism due to their alleged association with “Antifa.” Anarchist zines were cited as evidence against them, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sanchez was charged following a search that ICE proclaimed on social media turned up “literal insurrectionist propaganda” he had allegedly transported from his home to an apartment, noting that “insurrectionary anarchism is regarded as the most serious form of domestic (non-jihadi) terrorist threat.” The tweet also said that Sanchez is a green card holder granted legal status through the Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals program.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The indictment claims Sanchez was transporting those materials to conceal them because they incriminated his wife. But how can possession of literature incriminate anyone, let alone someone who isn’t even accused of anything but being present when someone else allegedly fired a gun? Zines aren’t contraband; it’s not illegal to be an anarchist or read about anarchism. I don’t know why Sanchez allegedly moved the box of documents, but if it was because he (apparently correctly) feared prosecutors would try to use them against his wife, that’s a commentary on prosecutors’ lawlessness, not Sanchez’s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Violent rhetoric is subject to punishment only when it constitutes a “true threat” of imminent violence. Even then, the speaker is held responsible, not anyone merely in possession of their words.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Government prosecutors haven’t alleged the “Antifa materials” contained any “true threats,” or any other category of speech that falls outside the protection of the First Amendment. Nor did they allege that the materials were used to plan the alleged actions of protesters on July 4 (although they did allege that the materials were “anti-government” and “anti-Trump”).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even the aforementioned “Insurrectionary Anarchy: Organizing for Attack” zine, despite its hyperbolic title, reads like a think piece, not a how-to manual. It advocates for tactics like rent strikes and squatting, not shooting police officers. Critically, it has nothing to do with whether Sanchez’s wife committed crimes on July 4.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being guilty of possessing literature is a concept fundamentally incompatible with a free society. We don’t need a constitutional right to publish (or possess) only what the government likes, and the “anti-government” literature in Sanchez’s box of zines is exactly what the First Amendment protects. With history and leaders like Vladimir Putin and Viktor Orbán as a guide, we also know it’s highly unlikely that Trump’s censorship crusade will stop with a few radical pamphlets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Framers Loved Zines&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s an irony in a supposedly conservative administration treating anti-government pamphlets as evidence of criminality. Many of the publications the Constitution’s framers had in mind when they authored the First Amendment’s press freedom clause bore far more resemblance to Sanchez’s box of zines than to the output of today’s mainstream news media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Revolutionary-era America was awash in highly opinionated, politically radical literature. Thomas Paine’s “Common Sense” was designed to inspire revolution against the established government. Newspapers like the Boston Gazette printed inflammatory writings by Samuel Adams and others urging the colonies to prepare for war after the Coercive Acts. The Declaration of Independence itself recognized the right of the people to rise up. It did not assume the revolution of the time would be the last one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One might call it “literal insurrectionist propaganda” — and some of it was probably transported in boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The framers enshrined press freedom not because they imagined today’s professionally trained journalists maintaining careful neutrality. They protected it because they understood firsthand the need for journalists and writers who believed their government had become tyrannical to espouse revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For all their many faults, the framers were confident enough in their ideas that they were willing to let them be tested. If the government’s conduct didn’t call for radical opposition, then radical ideas wouldn’t catch on. It sure looks like the current administration doesn’t want to make that bet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IT’S EVEN WORSE THAN WE THOUGHT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What we’re seeing right now from Donald Trump is a full-on authoritarian takeover of the U.S. government.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is not hyperbole.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Court orders are being ignored. MAGA loyalists have been put in charge of the military and federal law enforcement agencies. The Department of Government Efficiency has stripped Congress of its power of the purse. News outlets that challenge Trump have been banished or put under investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet far too many are still covering Trump’s assault on democracy like politics as usual, with flattering headlines describing Trump as “unconventional,” “testing the boundaries,” and “aggressively flexing power.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Intercept has long covered authoritarian governments, billionaire oligarchs, and backsliding democracies around the world. We understand the challenge we face in Trump and the vital importance of press freedom in defending democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;We’re independent of corporate interests. Will you help us?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Latest Stories&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Nydia Velázquez Hears Calls for Generational Change, Setting Up a Fight on the Left in New York&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Democratic congresswoman was an early believer in Zohran Mamdani. His win showed her it was “the right time to pass the torch.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;AIPAC Donors Back Real Estate Tycoon Who Opposed Gaza Ceasefire for Deep-Blue Chicago Seat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Progressive Rep. Danny Davis rejected AIPAC cash at the end of his career. Now the Israel lobby is coming for his seat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chilling Dissent&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The FBI Wants AI Surveillance Drones With Facial Recognition&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An FBI procurement document requests information about AI surveillance on drones, raising concerns about a crackdown on free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46030750</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 05:46:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Git 3.0 will use main as the default branch</title><link>https://thoughtbot.com/blog/git-3-0-will-use-main-as-the-default-branch</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f6b4314f1da67723"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting with Git 3.0, developers will no longer have to configure the default branch for new repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Git 2.52, released this week, includes this small but meaningful line in the patch notes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Declare that “git init” that is not otherwise configured uses ‘main’ as the initial branch, not ‘master’, starting Git 3.0.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This change has been a long time coming. The Software Freedom Conservancy—the nonprofit home of the Git project—said in June 23, 2020 that Git would eventually update its default branch name. GitHub followed soon after, changing its default branch for new repositories to &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; on October 1, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Git 3.0 has no planned release date as of now, but current estimates put it near the end of 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other notable changes planned for 3.0 include:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changing the default hash function from SHA-1 to SHA-256, improving security.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changing the default storage format to better support macOS and Windows, and to improve performance.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;More formally integrating Rust into Git’s own build process&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46031025</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 06:37:20 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>