<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 23:34:25 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>FAWK: LLMs can write a language interpreter</title><link>https://martin.janiczek.cz/2025/11/21/fawk-llms-can-write-a-language-interpreter.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5ff690b5ea490edb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After reading the book The AWK Programming Language (recommended!), I was planning to try AWK out on this year’s Advent of Code. Having some time off from work this week, I tried to implement one of the problems in it to get some practice, set up my tooling, see how hard AWK would be, and… I found I’m FP-pilled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I knew I’m addicted to the combination of algebraic data types (tagged unions) and exhaustive pattern matching, but what got me this time was immutability, lexical scope and the basic human right of being allowed to return arrays from functions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 1 of the Advent of Code problem was easy enough, but for part 2 (basically a shortest path search with a twist, to not spoil too much), I found myself unable to switch from my usual functional BFS approach to something mutable, and ended up trying to implement my functional approach in AWK.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It got hairy very fast: I needed to implement:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;hashing of strings and 2D arrays (by piping to &lt;code&gt;md5sum&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;a global &lt;del rend="overstrike"&gt;set&lt;/del&gt;array of seen states&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;a way to serialize and deserialize a 2D array to/from a string&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;and a few associative arrays for retrieving this serialized array by its hash.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was very lost by the time I had all this; I spent hours just solving what felt like accidental complexity; things that I’d take for granted in more modern languages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, I know nobody said AWK is modern, or functional, or that it promises any convenience for anything other than one-liners and basic scripts that fit under a handful of lines. I don’t want to sound like I expect AWK to do any of this; I knew I was stretching the tool when going in. But I couldn’t shake the feeling that there’s a beautiful AWK-like language within reach, an iteration on the AWK design (the pattern-action way of thinking is beautiful) that also gives us a few of the things programming language designers have learnt over the 48 years since AWK was born.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Dreaming of functional AWK&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stopping my attempts to solve the AoC puzzle in pure AWK, I wondered: what am I missing here?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if AWK had first-class arrays?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BEGIN {
  # array literals
  normal   = [1, 2, 3]
  nested   = [[1,2], [3,4]]
  assoc    = ["foo" =&amp;gt; "bar", "baz" =&amp;gt; "quux"]
  multidim = [(1,"abc") =&amp;gt; 999]

  five = range(1,5)
  analyze(five)
  print five  # --&amp;gt; still [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]! was passed by value
}

function range(a,b) {
  r = []
  for (i = a; i &amp;lt;= b; i++) {
    r[length(r)] = i
  }
  return r  # arrays can be returned!
}

function analyze(arr) {
  arr[0] = 100
  print arr[0]  # --&amp;gt; 100, only within this function
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if AWK had first-class functions and lambdas?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BEGIN {
  # construct anonymous functions
  double = (x) =&amp;gt; { x * 2 }
  add = (a, b) =&amp;gt; { c = a + b; return c }

  # functions can be passed as values
  apply = (func, value) =&amp;gt; { func(value) }

  print apply(double,add(1,3))  # --&amp;gt; 8
  print apply(inc,5)  # --&amp;gt; 6
}

function inc(a) { return a + 1 }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if AWK had lexical scope instead of dynamic scope?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# No need for this hack anymore ↓     ↓
#function foo(a, b         ,local1, local2) {
function foo(a, b) {
  local1 = a + b
  local2 = a - b
  return local1 + local2
}

BEGIN {
  c = foo(1,2)
  print(local1)  # --&amp;gt; 0, the local1 from foo() didn't leak!
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if AWK had explicit globals, and everything else was local by default?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BEGIN { global count }
END {
  foo()
  print count  # --&amp;gt; 1
  print mylocal # --&amp;gt; 0, didn't leak
}
function foo() { count++; mylocal++ }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(This one, admittedly, might make programs a bit more verbose. I’m willing to pay that cost.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if AWK had pipelines? (OK, now I’m reaching for syntax sugar…)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BEGIN {
  result = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5] 
      |&amp;gt; filter((x) =&amp;gt; { x % 2 == 0 })
      |&amp;gt; map((x) =&amp;gt; { x * x })
      |&amp;gt; reduce((acc, x) =&amp;gt; { acc + x }, 0)

  print "Result:", result
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Making it happen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Janiczek/fawk&lt;/code&gt;on GitHub&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now for the crazy, LLM-related part of the post. I didn’t want to spend days implementing AWK from scratch or tweaking somebody else’s implementation. So I tried to use Cursor Agent for a larger task than I usually do (I tend to ask for very small targeted edits), and asked Sonnet 4.5 for a README with code examples, and then a full implementation in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it did it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note: I also asked for implementations in C, Haskell and Rust at the same time, not knowing if any of the four would succeed, and they all seem to have produced code that at least compiles/runs. I haven’t tried to test them or even run them though. The PRs are here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was very impressed—I still am! I expected the LLM to stumble and flail around and ultimately get nothing done, but it did what I asked it for (gave me an interpreter that could run those specific examples), and over the course of a few chat sessions, I guided it towards implementing more and more of “the rest of AWK”, together with an excessive amount of end-to-end tests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only time I could see it struggle was when I asked it to implement arbitrary precision floating point operations without using an external library like &lt;code&gt;mpmath&lt;/code&gt;. It attempted to use Taylor series, but couldn’t get it right for at
least a few minutes. I chickened out and told it to &lt;code&gt;uv add mpmath&lt;/code&gt; and simplify
the interpreter code. In a moment it was done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other things that I thought it would choke on, like &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; being both a
statement (with &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; redirection support) and an expression, or
multi-dimensional arrays, or multi-line records, these were all implemented
correctly. Updating the test suite to also check for backwards compatibility
with GAWK - not an issue. Lexical scoping
and tricky closure environment behaviour - handled that just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What now?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the cool kids say, I have to update my priors. The frontier of what the LLMs can do has moved since the last time I tried to vibe-code something. I didn’t expect to have a working interpreter the same day I dreamt of a new programming language. It now seems possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The downside of vibe coding the whole interpreter is that I have zero knowledge of the code. I only interacted with the agent by telling it to implement a thing and write tests for it, and I only really reviewed the tests. I reckon this would be an issue in the future when I want to manually make some change in the actual code, because I have no familiarity with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This also opened new questions for me wrt. my other projects where I’ve previously run out of steam, eg. trying to implement a Hindley-Milner type system for my dream forever-WIP programming language Cara. It seems I can now just ask the LLM to do it, and it will? But then, I don’t want to fall into the trap where I am no longer able to work on the codebase myself. I want to be familiar with and able to tinker on the code. I’d need to spend my time reviewing and reading code instead of writing everything myself. Perhaps that’s OK.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Performance of FAWK might be an issue as well, though right now it’s a non-goal, given my intended use case is throwaway scripts for Advent of Code, nothing user-facing. And who knows, based on what I’ve seen, maybe I can instruct it to rewrite it in Rust and have a decent chance of success?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For now, I’ll go dogfood my shiny new vibe-coded black box of a programming language on the Advent of Code problem (and as many of the 2025 puzzles as I can), and see what rough edges I can find. I expect them to be equal parts “not implemented yet” and “unexpected interactions of new PL features with the old ones”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re willing to jump through some Python project dependency hoops, you can try to use FAWK too at your own risk, at &lt;code&gt;Janiczek/fawk&lt;/code&gt; on
GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46003144</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 10:28:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Making a Small RPG</title><link>https://jslegenddev.substack.com/p/making-a-small-rpg</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46004293</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:23:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EXIF orientation info in PNGs isn't used for image-orientation: from-image</title><link>https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1627423</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="fb52bd5796b2ff66"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;EXIF orientation info in PNGs isn't used for image-orientation: from-image&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Categories&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;(Core :: Layout: Images, Video, and HTML Frames, defect, P3)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tracking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;()&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;People&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;(Reporter: e, Unassigned)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;References&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;(Blocks 2 open bugs)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Details&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;(Keywords: parity-chrome, parity-safari, webcompat:platform-bug)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;User Story&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;user-impact-score:40&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Reporter&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Description&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;5 years ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; Intel Mac OS X 10_15_4) AppleWebKit/605.1.15 (KHTML, like Gecko) Version/13.1 Safari/605.1.15&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Steps to reproduce:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go to https://ericportis.com/etc/PNG-EXIF-orientation/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actual results:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The JPEG and PNG are rotated differently, even though they both have the same EXIF info (Orientation: Rotate 90 CW), and are both set to &lt;code&gt;image-orientation: from-image;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expected results:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They should display the same.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Reporter&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Comment 1&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;5 years ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further findings: neither Safari, Chrome, or Firefox respects exiftool's default output, which appends EXIF to the end of a PNG. This is allowed by the spec, but seems to be incompatible with progressive rendering of partially-downloaded PNGs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Safari does respect EXIF orientation info that appears before the image data, but Firefox and Chrome do not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://bugs.webkit.org/show_bug.cgi?id=210021#c4&lt;lb/&gt; https://ericportis.com/etc/PNG-EXIF-orientation/shuffling-chunks/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Comment 2&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;5 years ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;heycam: Will this be covered by any of your follow-up work related to bug 1607667?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Comment 3&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;5 years ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Huh, I didn't even know that PNG supported orientation data. I found https://ftp-osl.osuosl.org/pub/libpng/documents/pngext-1.5.0.html#C.eXIf which defines the &lt;code&gt;eXif&lt;/code&gt; table.  The patches I'm working on don't add support for this, but it would not be too difficult to do so, at least if the table appears earlier than the image data.  (I don't think our current image loading flow would handle the image size changing as a result of the orientation data later on.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Comment 4&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;5 years ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because this bug's Severity has not been changed from the default since it was filed, and it's Priority is &lt;code&gt;P3&lt;/code&gt; (Backlog,) indicating it has been triaged, the bug's Severity is being updated to &lt;code&gt;S3&lt;/code&gt; (normal.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Updated&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;1 year ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Comment 5&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;1 year ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is spec'd in PNG-3 https://www.w3.org/TR/2024/CRD-png-3-20240718/#eXIf&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Updated&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;1 year ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Comment 6&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;11 months ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the expected waiting time for the issue to be resolved?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Updated&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;2 months ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;head&gt;Comment 7&lt;/head&gt;•&lt;p&gt;1 month ago &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Should be fixed by bug 1682759. If that is incorrect please re-open.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46004364</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:29:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>We should all be using dependency cooldowns</title><link>https://blog.yossarian.net/2025/11/21/We-should-all-be-using-dependency-cooldowns</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="af811b9b5ac90ef0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nov 21, 2025 Tags: oss, security&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Dependency cooldowns are a free, easy, and incredibly effective way to mitigate the large majority of open source supply chain attacks. More individual projects should apply cooldowns (via tools like Dependabot and Renovate) to their dependencies, and packaging ecosystems should invest in first-class support for cooldowns directly in their package managers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;âSupply chain securityâ is a serious problem. Itâs also seriously overhyped, in part because dozens of vendors have a vested financial interest in convincing your that their framing of the underlying problem1 is (1) correct, and (2) worth your money.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whatâs consternating about this is that most open source supply chain attacks have the same basic structure:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An attacker compromises a popular open source project, typically via a stolen credential or CI/CD vulnerabilty (such as âpwn requestsâ in GitHub Actions).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attacker introduces a malicious change to the project and uploads it somewhere that will have maximum effect (PyPI, npm, GitHub releases, &amp;amp;c., depending on the target).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, the clock has started, as the attacker has moved into the public.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users pick up the compromised version of the project via automatic dependency updates or a lack of dependency pinning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the aforementioned vendors are scanning public indices as well as customer repositories for signs of compromise, and provide alerts upstream (e.g. to PyPI).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably, vendors are incentivized to report quickly and loudly upstream, as this increases the perceived value of their services in a crowded field.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upstreams (PyPI, npm, &amp;amp;c.) remove or disable the compromised package version(s).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;End-user remediation begins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key thing to observe is that the gap between (1) and (2) can be very large2 (weeks or months), while the gap between (2) and (5) is typically very small: hours or days. This means that, once the attacker has moved into the actual exploitation phase, their window of opportunity to cause damage is pretty limited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can see this with numerous prominent supply chain attacks over the last 18 months3:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Attack&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Approx. Window of Opportunity&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;References&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;xz-utils&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;â 5 weeks4&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ultralytics (phase 1)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 hours&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ultralytics (phase 2)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 hour&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tj-actions&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 days&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;chalk&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&amp;lt; 12 hours&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Nx&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 hours&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;rspack&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 hour&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;num2words&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&amp;lt; 12 hours&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kong Ingress Controller&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;â 10 days&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;web3.js&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 hours&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Each of these attacks has significant downstream effect, of course, but only within their window of opportunity. Subsequent compromises from each, like Shai-Hulud, represent new windows of opportunity where the attackers regrouped and pivoted onto the next set of compromised credentials.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My takeaway from this: some windows of opportunity are bigger, but the majority of them are under a week long. Consequently, ordinary developers can avoid the bulk of these types of attacks by instituting cooldowns on their dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A âcooldownâ is exactly what it sounds like: a window of time between when a dependency is published and when itâs considered suitable for use. The dependency is public during this window, meaning that âsupply chain securityâ vendors can work their magic while the rest of us wait any problems out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love cooldowns for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Theyâre empirically effective, per above. They wonât stop all attackers, but they do stymie the majority of high-visibiity, mass-impact supply chain attacks that have become more common.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Theyâre incredibly easy to implement. Moreover, theyâre literally free to implement in most cases: most people can use Dependabotâs functionality, Renovateâs functionality, or the functionality build directly into their package manager5.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is how simple it is in Dependabot:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Rinse and repeat for other ecosystems as needed.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cooldowns enforce positive behavior from supply chain security vendors: vendors are still incentivized to discover and report attacks quickly, but are not as incentivized to emit volumes of blogspam about âcriticalâ attacks on largely underfunded open source ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the very small sample set above, 8/10 attacks had windows of opportunity of less than a week. Setting a cooldown of 7 days would have prevented the vast majority of these attacks from reaching end users (and causing knock-on attacks, which several of these were). Increasing the cooldown to 14 days would have prevented all but 1 of these attacks6.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cooldowns are, obviously, not a panacea: some attackers will evade detection, and delaying the inclusion of potentially malicious dependencies by a week (or two) does not fundamentally alter the fact that supply chain security is a social trust problem, not a purely technical one. Still, an 80-90% reduction in exposure through a technique that is free and easy seems hard to beat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Related to the above, itâs unfortunate that cooldowns arenât baked directly into more packaging ecosystems: Dependabot and Renovate are great, but even better would be if the package manager itself (as the source of ground truth) could enforce cooldowns directly (including of dependencies not introduced or bumped through automated flows).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem being, succinctly: modern software stacks are complex and opaque, with little to no difference in privilege between first-party code and third-party dependencies.Â ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In part because of the prevalence of long-lived, overscoped credentials. Long-lived credentials let attackers operate on their own (comfortable) timelines; this is why Trusted Publishing is such a useful (but not wholly sufficient) technique for reducing the attackerâs attack staging window.Â ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Filippo Valsorda has an excellent compilation of recent supply chain compromises here.Â ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The xz-utils attack is a significant outlier, both in its scope and the length of its window of opportunity. In this case, Iâve measured from the attackerâs first backdoored release (v5.6.0, 2024-02-24) to the time of rollback within Debian (2024-03-28).Â ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, pnpmâs &lt;code&gt;minimumReleaseAge&lt;/code&gt;.
           uv also has &lt;code&gt;exclude-newer&lt;/code&gt;, 
           although this specifies an absolute cutoff rather than a rolling cooldown.Â ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably, the only attack that would have stymied a 14-day cooldown is xz-utils, which is also the most technically, logistically, and socially advanced of all of the attacks.Â ↩&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46005111</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 14:50:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>XBMC 4.0 for the Original Xbox</title><link>https://www.xbox-scene.info/articles/announcing-xbmc-40-for-the-original-xbox-r64/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f9edd7dc8a4cddc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Major Modernization of the Killer App That Started It All&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A new version of Xbox Media Center (XBMC), version 4.0, has been released. This version marks a significant update to the long-standing media center platform for the Original Xbox. This marks the first major advancement to the software since 2016 and represents a renewed commitment to preserving, modernizing, and extending the capabilities of one of the most iconic console homebrew applications ever created.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XBMC has a long and influential history. In 2002, XboxMediaPlayer (XMP) was released and turned the console into a powerful multimedia device fit for the living room in an era when connecting a computer to a TV was quite novel. Later that same year, XMP merged with YAMP and became Xbox Media Player 2.0. A few years later, the software evolved into Xbox Media Center, or XBMC, which introduced a new interface, a plugin system powered by Python, and a robust skinning engine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XBMC eventually became so capable that it outgrew the Xbox entirely. By 2007, developers were working on PC ports and in 2010, the project split into two branches: one for general computers while the Xbox version became XBMC4Xbox, and each codebase was maintained from then on by separate teams. XBMC was later renamed to Kodi in 2014 and continues to be one of the most popular media center applications available. Even Plex traces its roots back to XBMC. Plex began as OSXBMC, a Mac port of XBMC in late 2007, before becoming its own project in 2008. This means the Original Xbox helped shape not one but two of the biggest media center apps used today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last official release of XBMC4Xbox arrived in February 2016 with version 3.5.3. Although the community never declared the project dead, meaningful updates became scarce. XBMC 4.0 continues that legacy by bringing a modern interface, updating it to be more inline with Kodi's modern codebase, and backporting features to the original 64MB RAM / Pentium-III hardware where it all began.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is distinct and separate from XBMC4Gamers, the games-focused variation of XBMC4Xbox (v3.5.3) by developer Rocky5.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Modern Interface Powered by Estuary&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the most notable advancements in XBMC 4.0 is the introduction of the Estuary user interface (skin).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Estuary, originally released in 2017 with Kodi v17 ("Krypton"), provides a clean and modern layout that improves navigation and readability over past skins. Bringing Estuary to the Xbox required extensive updates to the underlying GUI framework, including a port of the more contemporary GUIlib engine. This allows the platform to support modern skinning standards and makes future skin ports much more straightforward. After the initial work of porting GUIlib was done, porting Estuary to the Xbox was a relatively simple process of tweaking a handful of configuration files and adding contextual features specific to the Xbox. The result is a modern, intuitive front end that retains the performance and responsiveness required on legacy hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firing up an Xbox made in 2001 and being greeted by the same interface as what you'd find if you were to download Kodi today onto your PC feels like a bit of magic, and helps keep this beloved classic console relevant and useful well into the modern era.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Expanded Games Library Support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XBMC 4.0 introduces a fully realized games library system. This enhancement brings the same level of metadata support found in the Movies and Music sections to Xbox and emulated games. Titles can now display artwork, descriptions, and other metadata, transforming the games section into a polished and user-friendly library. XBMC’s longstanding support for trainers remains intact, giving users the option to apply gameplay modifications for compatible titles. Emulated game collections benefit as well, with the ability to browse ROM libraries and launch them directly in a user’s preferred emulator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Online Scrapers and Metadata Support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XBMC 4.0 restores full functionality to metadata scrapers for movies and television. This allows users to build rich media libraries complete with artwork, plot summaries, cast listings, and other information retrieved directly from online sources. XBMC 4.0 handles these tasks efficiently, even on the Xbox’s limited memory and processing power. Video playback continues to support 480p and 720p content, enabling the console to serve as a surprisingly capable media device for its age. Similar to Kodi, XBMC 4.0 supports filtering, building playlists, watch progress history for media, and intelligent handling of TV shows with seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aside from scrapers for multimedia, support for rich library capabilities for games has also been added. XBMC has always been a media-first app, and now users can enjoy the library experience that they've come to love for media now in the context of their games library (more info below).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Improved Task Scheduling and Multitasking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite the constraints of the Xbox’s single-threaded 733MHz CPU, XBMC 4.0 includes improvements to task scheduling that allow multiple activities to run concurrently. Background library updates, metadata scraping, and audio/video playback can occur while users navigate and use other parts of the interface. These optimizations help ensure a fluid experience without compromising performance. Much work has been done "under the hood" to keep XBMC on task and within memory budgets while achieving multi-tasking on a console that wasn't exactly designed with it in mind. Users who own RAM and/or CPU upgraded consoles can also take advantage of the extra overhead, as XBMC 4.0 makes use of the extra horsepower for an even smoother experience. Utilizing an SSD with higher UDMA speeds will also yield an improvement in overall responsiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Music Experience and Visualizers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Music playback has always been a strong element of XBMC, and version 4.0 maintains that focus. The Original Xbox is capable of high quality audio output, and XBMC continues to support lossless codecs such as FLAC. The release includes compatibility with various audio visualizers, including MilkDrop, which remains one of the most visually impressive and customizable audio visualization engines available. These features allow XBMC 4.0 to function not only as a media organizer, but also as an immersive audio display system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An online repository has been established and will be maintained moving forward where users can download legacy and newly-released add-ons as they become available. This repository is accessible without additional setup, right out of the box!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Add-ons and Python Support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XBMC 4.0 continues to offer an extendable architecture powered by Python-based add-ons. While the current release uses Python 2.7 for compatibility, work is underway to transition to Python 3.4.10 in the future, which may provide a path for backporting many newer Kodi add-ons. Even in its current state, XBMC 4.0 already supports a variety of community-developed add-ons that extend the system’s functionality, including tools for online video playback (i.e. YouTube), online weather services, and enhanced media organization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Updated Settings, Network Services, and System Tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The settings interface has been revised to provide more clarity and control. The update includes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Playback options, including episode progression, crossfade behavior, and subtitle handling&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Library management tools&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Network features, such as SMB, FTP, UPnP sharing, web server access, and Insignia-compatible DNS options&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Comprehensive interface customization options&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Multiple user profiles with individual library settings&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Advanced system controls for video calibration, display modes, input devices, and power management&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A robust System Information section for diagnostics, with info geared towards the Original Xbox&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A flexible File Manager with support for network protocols including FTP, SMB, WebDAV, and more&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users may also take advantage of an online add-ons repository, offering the same experience modern Kodi provides with being able to download add-ons to extend functionality of the app with things like online multimedia providers, weather, skins, visualizers, and more. Developers can submit new add-ons to the official repository via Github.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Continuing the Legacy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XBMC has been a staple of the Original Xbox's homebrew scene since its inception in the early 2000's. This new update is a revival of the platform that helped shape the landscape of home media software and helps revitalize a codebase that has been somewhat stagnant for many years. This release honors that heritage while modernizing the experience for a new generation of enthusiasts and preserving the functionality of the Original Xbox as a versatile and capable media center.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although the hardware is decades old, the renewed effort behind XBMC 4.0 demonstrates that the platform still has room to grow and tricks up its sleeve. With ongoing development and a codebase designed with modern Kodi compatibility in mind, XBMC 4.0 represents a significant step forward into the continued development on the Original Xbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The development team looks forward to continuing this work and expanding the possibilities of the Original Xbox for years to come. This version is the first of many to come, with lots of things cooking in the background. Keep an eye out for future releases by joining the Xbox-Scene Discord and turning on notifications in the xbmc-news channel or by periodically checking the project's Github page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Downloads&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XBMC 4.0 (and subsequent releases) builds along with source code are available via Github:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Main project page: Click Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: XBMC 4.0 is is in active development! This means updates will be released in a more frequent manner for the time being until things settle down. Check the nightly builds section on Github for the most up-to-date version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Contributions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XBMC is open source software and welcomes contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Coding: Developers can help XBMC by fixing a bug, adding new features, making our technology smaller and faster and making development easier for others. XBMC's codebase consists mainly of C++ with small parts written in a variety of coding languages. Our add-ons mainly consist of python and XML.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Helping users: Our support process relies on enthusiastic contributors like you to help others get the most out of XBMC. The #1 priority is always answering questions in our support forums. Everyday new people discover XBMC, and everyday they are virtually guaranteed to have questions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Localization: Translate XBMC, add-ons, skins etc. into your native language.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add-ons: Add-ons are what make XBMC the most extensible and customizable entertainment hub available. Get started building an add-on.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Support and Bug Reporting&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Need help?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support can be found in the XBMC -&amp;gt; General channel within the Xbox-Scene Discord server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Credits and Disclaimers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Nikola Antonić - Primary Developer, Project Lead&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;astarivi - Contributor (cURL, wolfSSL), Tester, Debugger&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;EqUiNoX - Contrubitor, Tester&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rocky5 - Contributor, Tester&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;.lavenderStarlight+ - Add-ons / Skins Development, Tester&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GoTeamScotch - Tester, Feedback&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Haguero - Tester, Feedback&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XBMC is GPLv2 licensed. You may use, distribute and copy it under the license terms. XBMC is licensed under the same terms as Kodi. For detailed information on the licensing, please refer to the Kodi license.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project, XBMC version 4.0 (and upcoming releases), is distinct from and is not affiliated with Team Kodi of The Kodi Foundation, or its members.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46005349</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 15:18:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Arduino published updated terms and conditions: no longer an open commons</title><link>https://www.molecularist.com/2025/11/did-qualcomm-kill-arduino-for-good.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b470b35817f47bba"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Six weeks ago, Qualcomm acquired Arduino. The maker community immediately worried that Qualcomm would kill the open-source ethos that made Arduino the lingua franca of hobby electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This week, Arduino published updated terms and conditions and a new privacy policy, clearly rewritten by Qualcomm’s lawyers. The changes confirm the community’s worst fears: Arduino is no longer an open commons. It’s becoming just another corporate platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what’s at stake, what Qualcomm got wrong, and what might still be salvaged, drawing from community discussions across maker forums and sites.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What changed?&lt;lb/&gt;The new terms read like standard corporate boilerplate: mandatory arbitration, data integration with Qualcomm’s global ecosystem, export controls, AI use restrictions. For any other SaaS platform, this would be unremarkable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Arduino isn’t SaaS. It’s the foundation of the maker ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most dangerous change is Arduino now explicitly states that using their platform grants you no patent licenses whatsoever. You can’t even argue one is implied.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means Qualcomm could potentially assert patents against your projects if you built them using Arduino tools, Arduino examples, or Arduino-compatible hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here’s the disconnect, baffling makers. Arduino’s IDE is licensed under AGPL. Their CLI is GPL v3. Both licenses explicitly require that you can reverse engineer the software. But the new Qualcomm terms explicitly forbid reverse engineering “the Platform.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s really going on?&lt;lb/&gt;The community is trying to figure out what is Qualcomm’s actual intent. Are these terms just bad lawyering with SaaS lawyers applying their standard template to cloud services, not realizing Arduino is different? Or is Qualcomm testing how much they can get away with before the community revolts? Or is this a first step toward locking down the ecosystem they just bought?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some people point out that “the Platform” might only mean Arduino’s cloud services (forums, Arduino Cloud, Project Hub) not the IDE and CLI that everyone actually uses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If that’s true, Qualcomm needs to say so, explicitly, and in plain language. Because library maintainers are likely wondering whether contributing to Arduino repos puts them at legal risk. And hardware makers are questioning whether “Arduino-compatible” is still safe to advertise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why Adafruit’s alarm matters&lt;lb/&gt;Adafruit has been vocal about the dangers of this acquisition. Some dismiss Adafruit’s criticism as self-serving. After all, they sell competing hardware and promote CircuitPython. But that misses who Adafruit is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adafruit has been the moral authority on open hardware for decades. They’ve made their living proving you can build a successful business on open principles. When they sound the alarm, it’s not about competition, it’s about principle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What they’re calling out isn’t that Qualcomm bought Arduino. It’s that Qualcomm’s lawyers fundamentally don’t understand what they bought. Arduino wasn’t valuable because it was just a microcontroller company. It was valuable because it was a commons. And you can’t apply enterprise legal frameworks to a commons without destroying it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adafruit gets this. They’ve built their entire business on this. That’s why their criticism carries weight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What Qualcomm doesn’t seem to understand&lt;lb/&gt;Qualcomm probably thought they were buying an IoT hardware company with a loyal user base. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They weren’t. They bought the IBM PC of the maker world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arduino’s value was never just the hardware. Their boards have been obsolete for years. Their value is the standard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Arduino IDE is the lingua franca of hobby electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Millions of makers learned on it, even if they moved to other hardware. ESP32, STM32, Teensy, Raspberry Pi Pico – none of them are Arduino hardware, but they all work with the Arduino IDE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thousands of libraries are “Arduino libraries.” Tutorials assume Arduino. University curricula teach Arduino. When you search “how to read a sensor,” the answer comes back in Arduino code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the ecosystem Qualcomm’s lawyers just dropped legal uncertainty onto.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If Qualcomm’s lawyers start asserting control over the IDE, CLI, or core libraries under restrictive terms, they will poison the entire maker ecosystem. Even people who never buy Arduino hardware are dependent on Arduino software infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualcomm didn’t just buy a company. They bought a commons. And now they inadvertently are taking steps that are destroying what made it valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What are makers supposed to do?&lt;lb/&gt;There has been some buzz of folks just leaving the Arduino environment behind. But Arduino IDE alternatives such as PlatformIO and VSCode are not in any way beginner friendly. If the Arduino IDE goes, then there’s a huge problem. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I remember when Hypercard ended. There were alternatives, but none so easy. I don’t think I really coded again for almost 20 years until I picked up the Arduino IDE (go figure).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If something happens to the Arduino IDE, even if its development stalls or becomes encumbered, there’s no replacement for that easy onboarding. We’d lose many promising new makers because the first step became too steep.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The institutional knowledge at risk&lt;lb/&gt;But leaving Arduino behind isn’t simple. The platform’s success depends on two decades of accumulated knowledge, such as countless Arduino tutorials on YouTube, blogs, and school curricula; open-source libraries that depend on Arduino compatibility; projects in production using Arduino tooling; and university programs built around Arduino as the teaching platform&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of these depend on Arduino remaining open and accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If Qualcomm decided to sunset the open Arduino IDE in favor of a locked-down “Arduino Pro” platform, or if they start asserting patent claims, or if uncertainty makes contributors abandon the ecosystem, all that knowledge becomes stranded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s like Wikipedia going behind a paywall. The value isn’t just the content, it is the trust that it remains accessible. Arduino’s value isn’t just the code, it’s the trust that the commons would stay open.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That trust is now gone. And once lost, it hard to get back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why this happened (but doesn’t excuse it)&lt;lb/&gt;Let’s be fair to Qualcomm, their lawyers were doing their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you acquire a company, you standardize the legal terms; add mandatory arbitration to limit class action exposure; integrate data systems for compliance and auditing; add export controls because you sell to defense contractors; prohibit reverse engineering because that’s in the template.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For most acquisitions, this is just good corporate hygiene. And Arduino, now part of a megacorp, faces higher liabilities than it did as an independent entity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But here’s what Qualcomm’s lawyers missed: Arduino isn’t a normal acquisition. The community isn’t a customer base, it’s a commons. And you can’t apply enterprise SaaS legal frameworks to a commons without destroying what made it valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is tone-deafness, not malice. But the outcome is the same. A community that trusted Arduino no longer does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understanding why this happened doesn’t excuse it, but it might suggest what needs to happen next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What should have happened and how to still save it&lt;lb/&gt;Qualcomm dropped legal boilerplate on the community with zero context and let people discover the contradictions themselves. That’s how you destroy trust overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualcomm should have announced the changes in advance. They should have given the community weeks, not hours, to understand what’s changing and why. They should have used plain-language explanations, not just legal documents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualcomm can fix things by explicitly carving out the open ecosystem. They should state clearly that the terms apply to Arduino Cloud services, and the IDE, CLI, and core libraries remain under their existing open source licenses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’d need concrete commitments, such as which repos stay open, which licenses won’t change, what’s protected from future acquisition decisions. Right now we have vague corporate-speak about “supporting the community.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, they could create some structural protection, as well, by putting IDE, CLI, and core libraries in a foundation that Qualcomm couldn’t unilaterally control (think the Linux Foundation model).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, Qualcomm might wish to establish some form of community governance with real representation and real power over the tools the community depends on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The acquisition is done. The legal integration is probably inevitable. But how it’s done determines whether Arduino survives as a commons or dies as just another Qualcomm subsidiary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s next?&lt;lb/&gt;Arduino may be the toolset that made hobby electronics accessible to millions. But that maker community built Arduino into what it became. Qualcomm’s acquisition has thrown that legacy into doubt. Whether through legal confusion, corporate tone-deafness, or deliberate strategy, the community’s trust is broken.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next few months will reveal whether this was a stumble or a strategy. If Qualcomm issues clarifications, moves repos to some sort of governance, and explicitly protects the open toolchain, then maybe this is salvageable. If they stay silent, or worse, if IDE development slows or license terms tighten further, then that’s a signal to find alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The question isn’t whether the open hobby electronics maker community survives. It’s whether Arduino does.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46005553</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 15:44:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Command Lines</title><link>https://www.wreflection.com/p/command-lines-ai-coding</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3751c158b81408fc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Command Lines&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;AI Coding's Control Spectrum&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the early 1950s, Grace Hopper coined the term “compiler” and built one of the first versions with her A-0 system1. The compilers that followed abstracted away machine code, letting programmers focus on higher-level logic instead of lower-level hardware details. Today, AI coding assistants2 are enabling a similar change, letting software engineers focus on higher-order work by generating code from natural language prompts3. Everyone from big tech to well-funded startups is competing to capture this shift. Yesterday Google announced Antigravity, their new AI coding assistant, and the day before, AWS announced the general availability of their AI coding tool, Kiro. Last week, Cursor, the standout startup in this space, raised $2.3B in their series-D round at a valuation of $29.3B.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two lines in Cursor’s press release stood out to me. The first:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We’ve also crossed $1B in annualized revenue, counting millions of developers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This disclosure means Anysphere Inc. (Cursor’s parent company) is the fastest company in history to reach $1B in annual recurring revenue (ARR). Yes, faster than OpenAI, and faster than Anthropic4.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Engineers are trying every new AI coding tool. As a result, the AI-coding tool market is growing exponentially (+5x in just over a year)5. But it’s still early. As I wrote in Why Some AI Wrappers Build Billion-dollar Businesses, companies spend several hundred billion dollars a year on software engineering, and AI has the potential to unlock productivity gains across that entire spend.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Software developers represent roughly 30% of the workforce at the world’s five largest market cap companies, all of which are technology firms as of October 2025. Development tools that boost productivity by even modest percentages unlock billions in value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my view, this nascent market is splitting based on three types of users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On one end is Handcrafted Coding. These are engineers who actively decline to use LLMs, either because of skepticism about quality or insistence on full control of every code. They argue that accepting AI suggestions creates technical debt you cannot see until it breaks in production. This segment continues to decline as the quality of AI coding models improves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The opposite end is Vibe Coding. These are typically non-engineers, who use AI to build concepts and prototypes. They prompt the model hoping for an end-to-end solution, accept the output with minimal review, and trust that it works. The user describes what they want and lets the model figure out the implementation details of how to build it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the middle sits Architect + AI Coding. The engineer uses the AI/LLM as a pair programmer exploring system designs, analyzing data models, and reviewing API details. When the work is something entirely new or something that needs careful handling, the human programmer still codes those pieces by hand. But for boilerplate code, package installations, generic User Interface (UI) components, and any kind of code that is typically found on the internet, they assign it to the model6. The engineer stays in command of what is important to them and delegates what is not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Market Split&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on the user types, I think, the AI coding market splits into two.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Hands-off: Non-engineers (product managers, designers, marketers, other internal employees) use these tools to vibe code early product concepts. They look to AI as the lead engineer to spin-up concepts/prototypes of apps, websites, and tools by simply prompting the AI to make something for them. Lovable, Vercel, Bolt, Figma Make, and Replit fit here7. Code from these users, as of now, are not typically pushed to prod.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Hands-on: Professional software engineers use these tools in their existing workflow to ship production code. They use AI as an assistant to write boilerplate code, refactor existing services, wire new features or UI screens, and triage bugs in codebases. Cursor, Claude Code, OpenAI Codex, Github Copilot, Cline, AWS Kiro play here. These products live where the work is done, and integrate into the engineer’s workflow. This is, at least as of now, the bigger market segment.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To see an evaluation of all the major AI coding tools currently in the market, checkout this breakdown by Peter Yang, who runs the newsletter Behind The Craft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That brings me to the second thing in Cursor’s press release that stood out to me:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our in-house models now generate more code than almost any other LLMs in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While I am not convinced about that claim8, what I am convinced about is that Cursor is still growing despite its previous reliance on foundation models. From Why Some AI Wrappers Build Billion-dollar Businesses again:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;But Cursor and other such tools depend almost entirely on accessing Anthropic, OpenAI and Gemini models, until&lt;/p&gt;&lt;del&gt;open-source&lt;/del&gt;open-weight and in-house models match or exceed frontier models in quality. Developer forums are filled with complaints about rate limits from paying subscribers. In my own projects, I exhausted my Claude credits in Cursor mid-project and despite preferring Cursor’s user interface and design, I migrated to Claude Code (and pay ten times more to avoid rate limits). The interface may be better, but model access proved decisive.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cursor’s new in-house model Composer-2, which just launched last month, is a good example of how this model versus application competition is evolving. Cursor claims (without any external benchmarks, I must say) that Composer-2 is almost as good as frontier models but 4x faster. It’s still early to say how true that is. Open-source models have not yet come close to the top spots in SWE-bench verified or in private evals9.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To me, model quality is the most decisive factor in these AI coding wars. And in my view, that’s why Claude Code has already overtaken Cursor, and OpenAI’s Codex is close behind, despite both having launched a year or so later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even though the newcomers Cursor, Claude Code, and OpenAI Codex are the talk of the (developer) town, incumbents such as Microsoft with Github Copilot, AWS with Kiro, and Google with Antigravity, can utilize their existing customer relationships, bundle their offerings with their existing suites, and/or provide their option as the default in their tech stack to compete. As an example, Cursor charges $20–$40 monthly per user for productive usage, while Google Antigravity launched free with generous limits for individual users. Github Copilot still leads this market, proving once again that enterprise bundling and distribution has structural advantages. This is the classic Microsoft Teams vs. Slack Dynamic10.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One way for startups to compete is by winning individual users who may use a coding tool with or without formal approval, and then be the tool’s advocate inside the organization. That organic interest and adoption eventually forces IT and security teams to officially review the tool and then eventually sanction its usage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet, even as these newer tools capture developer mindshare, the underlying developer tools market is changing. Both the IDEs developers choose and the resources &lt;del&gt;they&lt;/del&gt; we consult have changed dramatically. StackOverflow, once the default for programmers stuck on a programming issue, has seen its traffic and number of questions decline dramatically since ChatGPT’s launch, suggesting that AI is already replacing some traditional developer resources.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just as compilers freed programmers from writing assembly code, AI tools are freeing software engineers from the grunt work of writing boilerplate and routine code, and letting &lt;del&gt;them&lt;/del&gt; us focus on higher-order thinking. Eventually, one day, AI may get so good that it will generate applications on demand and create entire software ecosystems autonomously. Both hands-off and hands-on AI coding tools, as well as incumbents and newcomers, see themselves as the path to that fully autonomous software generation, even if they are taking different approaches. The ones who get there will be those who deliver the best model quality that ships code reliably, go deep enough to ship features that foundation models can’t care enough to replicate, and become sticky enough that users will not leave even when they can11. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed this post, please consider sharing it on Twitter/X or LinkedIn, and tag me when you do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hopper’s A-0 system and her definition of the term compiler is different from what we consider a compiler today, but it established the foundational concept.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the context of coding assistants, most products labeled as AI tools are powered by LLMs, and so I use AI and LLM interchangeably in this article despite the actual difference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A better comparison might be at the product level rather than company level. In that case, ChatGPT and Claude both reached $1B faster than Cursor did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would argue that the vast majority of productive code is hidden behind company firewalls. Current foundation models are trained on publicly available data on the internet, and do not have access to proprietary codebases. We are yet to see breakthrough solutions where a company augments their confidential private data to generate production-ready code using current LLMs. While Retrieval-Augmented Generation has shown some promise, it has not yet delivered transformative results. Companies such as Glean are actively working on this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Replit and Cognition probably appeal to both segments. To me, Replit leans hands-off with its rapid prototyping focus. Cognition’s agent-based approach, though hands-off, lets engineers still control the code directly, making it lean hands-on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was curious how Cursor knows how much code is generated by other LLMs outside Cursor? When I asked this on hackernews, swyx suggested that they “can pretty much triangulate across openrouter x feedback from the top 3 model labs to compare with internal usage and figure that out”. To me, triangulation makes sense for internal estimates. but for external publication, I’m surprised Cursor didn’t include “we estimate” or similar qualifying language. My understanding is that FTC policy requires substantiation before making definitive comparative claims (like more than, better than etc). All that to say, I’m not fully convinced about their claims.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SWE-bench is a benchmark for evaluating large language models (LLMs) on real world software engineering tasks and issues collected from GitHub. Performance against public benchmarks can be gamed by the model builders. Currently after any new model launch, we see people using the model in the wild and forming a consensus around how the model performs which is a better indicator than these benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft bundled Teams into Office 365 subscriptions at no extra cost, using its dominant enterprise distribution to surpass Slack’s paid standalone product within three years despite Slack’s earlier launch and product innovation. See https://venturebeat.com/ai/microsoft-teams-has-13-million-daily-active-users-beating-slack&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Natasha Malpani, Twitter/X, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46006004</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 16:33:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Wealthfolio 2.0- Open source investment tracker. Now Mobile and Docker</title><link>https://wealthfolio.app/?v=2.0</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="27ab40bb69b94b92"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Grow Wealth. Keep Control.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A beautiful, Private and Open-Source investment tracker that runs locally on all your devices.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;WHY CHOOSE WEALTHFOLIO?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A beautiful portfolio tracker that respects your privacy and your data&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Privacy-First Approach&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your data never leaves your device. As an open-source project, we prioritize security and transparency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Simple and Beautifully Crafted&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Powerful features wrapped in an elegant, easy-to-use interface. Simplicity meets sophistication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No Hidden Costs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Free to use with optional one-time payment. No subscriptions or recurring fees.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;THE ESSENTIALS YOU NEED TO TRACK YOUR WEALTH&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No More Messy Spreadsheets or Privacy Concerns - Just You and Your Secure, Personal Wealth Companion Application&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Accounts Aggregation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gather all your investment and savings accounts in one place. See everything at a glance, from stocks to savings! Import your CSV statements from your broker or bank.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Comprehensive View&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See all your accounts in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;CSV Import&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Easily import your CSV statements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Holdings Overview&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get a clear picture of what's in your portfolio. Stocks, ETFs, or Cryptocurrencies - know what you have and how it's performing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Portfolio Insights&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand your asset allocation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Performance Tracking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Monitor how your investments are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Performance Dashboard&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See how your investments stack up, all in one place. Compare your accounts side by side, check if you are beating the S&amp;amp;P 500, and track your favorite ETFs without the hassle. No fancy jargon - just clear, useful charts that help you understand how your money is really doing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Compare Your Accounts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See which accounts are doing best.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Beat the Market?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check how you stack up against some popular indexes and ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Income Tracking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Monitor dividends and interest income across your entire portfolio. Get a clear view of your passive income streams, helping you make informed decisions about your investments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Dividend Monitoring&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Track your dividend income.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Interest Income&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep an eye on interest earnings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Accounts Performance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Track your accounts' holdings and performance over time. See how a particular account is performing, and how it's changing over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Historical Data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;View past performance trends.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Account Analysis&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Analyze individual account performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Goals Tracking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set your savings targets clearly. Distribute your funds across these objectives, assigning a specific percentage to each. Keep an eye on your progress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Target Setting&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Define your financial goals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Progress Monitoring&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Track your progress towards goals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Contribution Rooms and Limit Tracking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stay on top of your contribution limits for tax-advantaged accounts like IRAs, 401(k)s, or TFSAs. Track your available contribution room and avoid over-contributing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Limit Awareness&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Know your contribution limits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Avoid Over-Contribution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prevent excess contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Extend Wealthfolio with Powerful Add-ons&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Investment Fees Tracker&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Track and analyze investment fees across your portfolio with detailed analytics and insights&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Goal Progress Tracker&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Track your investment progress towards target amounts with a visual representation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Stock Trading Tracker&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simple swing stock trading tracker with performance analytics and calendar views&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46006016</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 16:34:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>You can make PS2 games in JavaScript</title><link>https://jslegenddev.substack.com/p/you-can-now-make-ps2-games-in-javascript</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46006082</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 16:42:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pivot Robotics (YC W24) Is Hiring for an Industrial Automation Hardware Engineer</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/pivot-robotics/jobs/7xG9Dc6-mechanical-engineer-controls</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6e34f445ca77fde2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI for Robot Arms in Factories&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualifications&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pivot Robots (YC W24) is building the AI brain for robot arms for high-mix manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pivot Robots combines off-the-shelf robots and vision sensors with recent breakthroughs in foundation vision models to give industrial robot arms the power to adapt. Our first product directly addresses the dangerous and unpopular task of grinding metal parts. Currently, our software is being deployed on 10+ robots at a large cast iron foundry.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46006250</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Solving Fizz Buzz with Cosines</title><link>https://susam.net/fizz-buzz-with-cosines.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="12d2190568f48aac"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Solving Fizz Buzz with Cosines&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fizz Buzz is a counting game that has become oddly popular in the world of computer programming as a simple test of basic programming skills. The rules of the game are straightforward. Players say the numbers aloud in order beginning with one. Whenever a number is divisible by 3, they say 'Fizz' instead. If it is divisible by 5, they say 'Buzz'. If it is divisible by both 3 and 5, the player says both 'Fizz' and 'Buzz'. Here is a typical Python program that prints this sequence:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;for n in range(1, 101):
    if n % 15 == 0:
        print('FizzBuzz')
    elif n % 3 == 0:
        print('Fizz')
    elif n % 5 == 0:
        print('Buzz')
    else:
        print(n)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the output: fizz-buzz.txt. Can we make the program more complicated? Perhaps we can use trigonometric functions to encode all four cases in a single closed-form expression. That is what we are going to explore in this article. By the end, we will obtain a finite Fourier series that can take any integer \( n \) and select the text to be printed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Definitions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before going any further, we establish a precise mathematical definition for the Fizz Buzz sequence. We begin by introducing a few functions that will help us define the Fizz Buzz sequence later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Symbol Functions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We define a set of four functions \( \{ s_0, s_1, s_2, s_3 \} \) for integers \( n \) by: \begin{align*} s_0(n) &amp;amp;= n, \\ s_1(n) &amp;amp;= \mathtt{Fizz}, \\ s_2(n) &amp;amp;= \mathtt{Buzz}, \\ s_3(n) &amp;amp;= \mathtt{FizzBuzz}. \end{align*} We call these the symbol functions because they produce every term that appears in the Fizz Buzz sequence. The symbol function \( s_0 \) returns \( n \) itself. The functions \( s_1, \) \( s_2 \) and \( s_3 \) are constant functions that always return the literal words \( \mathtt{Fizz}, \) \( \mathtt{Buzz} \) and \( \mathtt{FizzBuzz} \) respectively, no matter what the value of \( n \) is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Fizz Buzz Sequence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we can define the Fizz Buzz sequence as the sequence \[ (s_{f(n)}(n))_{n = 1}^{\infty} \] where \[ f(n) = \begin{cases} 1 &amp;amp; \text{if } 3 \mid n \text{ and } 5 \nmid n, \\ 2 &amp;amp; \text{if } 3 \nmid n \text{ and } 5 \mid n, \\ 3 &amp;amp; \text{if } 3 \mid n \text{ and } 5 \mid n, \\ 0 &amp;amp; \text{otherwise}. \end{cases} \] The notation \( m \mid n \) means that the integer \( m \) divides the integer \( n, \) i.e. \( n \) is a multiple of \( m. \) Equivalently, there exists an integer \( c \) such that \( n = cm . \) Similarly, \( m \nmid n \) means that \( m \) does not divide \( n, \) i.e. \( n \) is not a multiple of \( m. \) With the above definitions in place, we can expand the first few terms of the sequence explicitly as follows: \begin{align*} (s_{f(n)}(n))_{n = 1}^{\infty} &amp;amp;= (s_{f(1)}(1), \; s_{f(2)}(2), \; s_{f(3)}(3), \; s_{f(4)}(4), \; s_{f(5)}(5), \; s_{f(6)}(6), \; s_{f(7)}(7), \; \dots) \\ &amp;amp;= (s_0(1), \; s_0(2), \; s_1(3), \; s_0(4), s_2(5), \; s_1(6), \; s_0(7), \; \dots) \\ &amp;amp;= (1, \; 2, \; \mathtt{Fizz}, \; 4, \; \mathtt{Buzz}, \; \mathtt{Fizz}, \; 7, \; \dots). \end{align*} Note how the function \( f(n) \) produces an index \( i \) which we then use to select the symbol function \( s_i(n) \) to produce the \( n \)th term of the sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Indicator Functions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the function \( f(n) \) from the previous section with its cases and conditions rearranged to make it easier to spot interesting patterns: \[ f(n) = \begin{cases} 0 &amp;amp; \text{if } 5 \nmid n \text{ and } 3 \nmid n, \\ 1 &amp;amp; \text{if } 5 \nmid n \text{ and } 3 \mid n, \\ 2 &amp;amp; \text{if } 5 \mid n \text{ and } 3 \nmid n, \\ 3 &amp;amp; \text{if } 5 \mid n \text{ and } 3 \mid n. \end{cases} \] This function helps us to select another function \( s_{f(n)}(n) \) which in turn determines the \( n \)th term of the Fizz Buzz sequence. Our goal now is to replace this piecewise formula with a single closed-form expression. To do so, we first define indicator functions \( I_m(n) \) as follows: \[ I_m(n) = \begin{cases} 1 &amp;amp; \text{if } m \mid n, \\ 0 &amp;amp; \text{if } m \nmid n. \end{cases} \] The formula for \( f(n) \) can now be written as: \[ f(n) = \begin{cases} 0 &amp;amp; \text{if } I_5(n) = 0 \text{ and } I_3(n) = 0, \\ 1 &amp;amp; \text{if } I_5(n) = 0 \text{ and } I_3(n) = 1, \\ 2 &amp;amp; \text{if } I_5(n) = 1 \text{ and } I_3(n) = 0, \\ 3 &amp;amp; \text{if } I_5(n) = 1 \text{ and } I_3(n) = 1. \end{cases} \] Do you see a pattern? Here is the same function written as a table:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;\( I_5(n) \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;\( I_3(n) \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;\( f(n) \)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 0 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 0 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 0 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 0 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 1 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 1 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 1 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 0 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 2 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 1 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 1 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;\( 3 \)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you see it now? If we treat the values in the first two columns as binary digits and the values in the third column as decimal numbers, then in each row the first two columns give the binary representation of the number in the third column. For example, \( 3_{10} = 11_2 \) and indeed in the last row of the table, we see the bits \( 1 \) and \( 1 \) in the first two columns and the number \( 3 \) in the last column. In other words, writing the binary digits \( I_5(n) \) and \( I_3(n) \) side by side gives us the binary representation of \( f(n). \) Therefore \[ f(n) = 2 \, I_5(n) + I_3(n). \] We can now write a small program to demonstrate this formula:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
 for n in range(1, 101):
    s = [n, 'Fizz', 'Buzz', 'FizzBuzz']
    i = (n % 3 == 0) + 2 * (n % 5 == 0)
    print(s[i])
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can make it even shorter at the cost of some clarity:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
 for n in range(1, 101):
    print([n, 'Fizz', 'Buzz', 'FizzBuzz'][(n % 3 == 0) + 2 * (n % 5 == 0)])
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What we have obtained so far is pretty good. While there is no universal definition of a closed-form expression, I think most people would agree that the indicator functions as defined above are simple enough to be permitted in a closed-form expression.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Complex Exponentials&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the previous section, we obtained the formula \[ f(n) = I_3(n) + 2 \, I_5(n) \] which we then used as an index to look up the text to be printed. We also argued that this is a pretty good closed-form expression already.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, in the interest of making things more complicated, we must ask ourselves: What if we are not allowed to use the indicator functions? What if we must adhere to the commonly accepted meaning of a closed-form expression which allows only finite combinations of basic operations such as addition, subtraction, multiplication, division, integer exponents and roots with integer index as well as functions such as exponentials, logarithms and trigonometric functions. It turns out that the above formula can be rewritten using only addition, multiplication, division and the cosine function. Let us begin the translation. Consider the sum \[ S_m(n) = \sum_{k = 0}^{m - 1} e^{2 \pi i k n / m}, \] where \( i \) is the imaginary unit and \( n \) and \( m \) are integers. This is a geometric series in the complex plane with ratio \( r = e^{2 \pi i n / m}. \) If \( n \) is a multiple of \( m , \) then \( n = cm \) for some integer \( c \) and we get \[ r = e^{2 \pi i n / m} = e^{2 \pi i c} = 1. \] Therefore, when \( n \) is a multiple of \( m, \) we get \[ S_m(n) = \sum_{k = 0}^{m - 1} e^{2 \pi i k n / m} = \sum_{k = 0}^{m - 1} 1^k = m. \] If \( n \) is not a multiple of \( m, \) then \( r \ne 1 \) and the geometric series becomes \[ S_m(n) = \frac{r^m - 1}{r - 1} = \frac{e^{2 \pi i n} - 1}{e^{2 \pi i n / m} - 1} = 0. \] Therefore, \[ S_m(n) = \begin{cases} m &amp;amp; \text{if } m \mid n, \\ 0 &amp;amp; \text{if } m \nmid n. \end{cases} \] Dividing both sides by \( m, \) we get \[ \frac{S_m(n)}{m} = \begin{cases} 1 &amp;amp; \text{if } m \mid n, \\ 0 &amp;amp; \text{if } m \nmid n. \end{cases} \] But the right-hand side is \( I_m(n). \) Therefore \[ I_m(n) = \frac{S_m(n)}{m} = \frac{1}{m} \sum_{k = 0}^{m - 1} e^{2 \pi i k n / m}. \]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Cosines&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We begin with Euler's formula \[ e^{i x} = \cos x + i \sin x \] where \( x \) is a real number. From this formula, we get \[ e^{i x} + e^{-i x} = 2 \cos x. \] Therefore \begin{align*} I_3(n) &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{3} \sum_{k = 0}^2 e^{2 \pi i k n / 3} \\ &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{3} \left( 1 + e^{2 \pi i n / 3} + e^{4 \pi i n / 3} \right) \\ &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{3} \left( 1 + e^{2 \pi i n / 3} + e^{-2 \pi i n / 3} \right) \\ &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{3} + \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right). \end{align*} The third equality above follows from the fact that \( e^{4 \pi i n / 3} = e^{6 \pi i n / 3} e^{-2 \pi i n / 3} = e^{2 \pi i n} e^{-2 \pi i n/3} = e^{-2 \pi i n / 3}. \)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The function above is defined for integer values of \( n \) but we can extend its formula to real \( x \) and plot it to observe its shape between integers. As expected, the function takes the value \( 1 \) whenever \( x \) is an integer multiple of \( 3 \) and \( 0 \) whenever \( x \) is an integer not divisible by \( 3. \)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, \begin{align*} I_5(n) &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{5} \sum_{k = 0}^4 e^{2 \pi i k n / 5} \\ &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{5} \left( 1 + e^{2 \pi i n / 5} + e^{4 \pi i n / 5} + e^{6 \pi i n / 5} + e^{8 \pi i n / 5} \right) \\ &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{5} \left( 1 + e^{2 \pi i n / 5} + e^{4 \pi i n / 5} + e^{-4 \pi i n / 5} + e^{-2 \pi i n / 5} \right) \\ &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{5} + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right) + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right). \end{align*} Extending this expression to real values of \( x \) allows us to plot its shape as well. Once again, the function takes the value \( 1 \) at integer multiples of \( 5 \) and \( 0 \) at integers not divisible by \( 5. \)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recall that we expressed \( f(n) \) as \[ f(n) = I_3(n) + 2 \, I_5(n). \] Substituting these trigonometric expressions yields \[ f(n) = \frac{1}{3} + \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right) + 2 \cdot \left( \frac{1}{5} + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right) + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right) \right). \] A straightforward simplification gives \[ f(n) = \frac{11}{15} + \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right) + \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right) + \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right). \] We can extend this expression to real \( x \) and plot it as well. The resulting curve takes the values \( 0, 1, 2 \) and \( 3 \) at integer points, as desired.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we can write our Python program as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
 from math import cos, pi
for n in range(1, 101):
    s = [n, 'Fizz', 'Buzz', 'FizzBuzz']
    i = round(11 / 15 + (2 / 3) * cos(2 * pi * n / 3)
                      + (4 / 5) * cos(2 * pi * n / 5)
                      + (4 / 5) * cos(4 * pi * n / 5))
    print(s[i])
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To summarise, we have defined the Fizz Buzz sequence as \[ (s_{f(n)}(n))_{n = 1}^{\infty} \] where \[ f(n) = \frac{11}{15} + \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right) + \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right) + \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right) \in \{ 0, 1, 2, 3 \} \] and \( s_0(n) = n, \) \( s_1(n) = \mathtt{Fizz}, \) \( s_2(n) = \mathtt{Buzz} \) and \( s_3(n) = \mathtt{FizzBuzz}. \) A Python program to print the Fizz Buzz sequence based on this definition was presented earlier. That program can be written more succinctly as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
 from math import cos, pi
for n in range(1, 101):
    print([n, 'Fizz', 'Buzz', 'FizzBuzz'][round(11 / 15 + (2 / 3) * cos(2 * pi * n / 3) + (4 / 5) * (cos(2 * pi * n / 5) + cos(4 * pi * n / 5)))])
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can also wrap this up nicely in a shell one-liner, in case you want to share it with your friends and family and surprise them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;python3 -c 'from math import cos, pi; [print([n, "Fizz", "Buzz", "FizzBuzz"][round(11/15 + (2/3) * cos(2*pi*n/3) + (4/5) * (cos(2*pi*n/5) + cos(4*pi*n/5)))]) for n in range(1, 101)]'&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The keen-eyed might notice that the expression we have obtained for \( f(n) \) is a finite Fourier series. This is not surprising, since the output of a Fizz Buzz program depends only on \( n \bmod 15. \) Any function on a finite cyclic group can be written exactly as a finite Fourier expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have taken a simple counting game and turned it into a trigonometric construction: a finite Fourier series with a constant term \( 11/15 \) and three cosine terms with coefficients \( 2/3, \) \( 4/5 \) and \( 4/5. \) None of this makes Fizz Buzz any easier, of course, but it does show that every \( \mathtt{Fizz} \) and \( \mathtt{Buzz} \) now owes its existence to a particular set of Fourier coefficients. We began with the modest goal of making this simple problem more complicated. I think it is safe to say that we did not fall short.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46006598</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:28:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Helping Valve to power up Steam devices</title><link>https://www.igalia.com/2025/11/helpingvalve.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="961b0d5348912672"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Helping Valve to Power Up Steam Devices&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last week, Valve stunned the computer gaming world by unveiling three new gaming devices at once: the Steam Frame, a wireless VR headset; the Steam Machine, a gaming console in the vein of a PlayStation or Xbox; and the Steam Controller, a handheld game controller. Successors to the highly successful Valve Index and Steam Deck, these devices are set to be released in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Igalia has long worked with Valve on SteamOS, which will power the Machine and Frame, and is excited to be contributing to these new devices, particularly the Frame. The Frame, unlike the Machine or Deck which have x86 CPUs, runs on an ARM-based CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under normal circumstances, this would mean that only games compiled to run on ARM chips could be played on the Frame. In order to get around this barrier, a translation layer called FEX is used to run applications compiled for x86 chips (which are used in nearly all gaming PCs) on ARM chips by translating the x86 machine code into ARM64 machine code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;âIf you love video games, like I do, working on FEX with Valve is a dream come true,â said Paulo Matos, an engineer with Igaliaâs Compilers Team. Even so, the challenges can be daunting, because making sure the translation is working often requires manual QA rather than automated testing. âYou have to start a game, sometimes the error shows up in the colors or sound, or how the game behaves when you break down the door in the second level. Just debugging this can take a while,â said Matos. âFor optimization work I did early last year, I used a game called Psychonauts to test it. I must have played the first 3 to 4 minutes of the game many, many times for debugging. Looking at my history, Steam tells me I played it for 29 hours, but it was always the first few minutes, nothing else.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond the CPU, the Qualcomm Adreno 750 GPU used in the Steam Frame introduced its own set of challenges when it came to running desktop games, and other complex workloads, on these devices. Doing so requires a rock-solid Vulkan driver that can ensure correctness, eliminating major rendering bugs, while maintaining high performance. This is a very difficult combination to achieve, and yet thatâs exactly what weâve done for Valve with Mesa3D Turnip, a FOSS Vulkan driver for Qualcomm Adreno GPUs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before we started our work, critical optimizations such as LRZ (which you can learn more about from our blog post here) or the autotuner (and its subsequent overhaul) werenât in place. Even worse, there wasnât support for the Adreno 700-series GPUs at all, which we eventually added along with support for tiled rendering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;âWe implemented many Vulkan extensions and reviewed numerous others,â said Danylo Piliaiev, an engineer on the Graphics Team. âOver the years, we ensured that D3D11, D3D12, and OpenGL games rendered correctly through DXVK, vkd3d-proton, and Zink, investigating many rendering issues along the way. We achieved higher correctness than the proprietary driver and, in many cases, Mesa3D Turnip is faster as well.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weâve worked with many wonderful people from Valve, Google, and other companies to iterate on the Vulkan driver over the years in order to introduce new features, bug fixes, performance improvements, as well as debugging workflows. Some of those people decided to join Igalia later on, such as our colleague and Graphics Team developer Emma Anholt. âIâve been working on Mesa for 22 years, and itâs great to have a home now where I can keep doing that work, across hardware projects, where the organization prioritizes the work experience of its developers and empowers them within the organization.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valveâs support in all this cannot be understated, either. Their choice to build their devices using open software like Mesa3D Turnip and FEX means theyâre committed to working on and supporting improvements and optimizations that become available to anyone who uses the same open-source projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;âWeâve received a lot of positive feedback about significantly improved performance and fewer rendering glitches from hobbyists who use these projects to run PC games on Android phones as a result of our work,â said Dhruv Mark Collins, another Graphics Team engineer working on Turnip. âAnd it goes both ways! Weâve caught a couple of nasty bugs because of that widespread testing, which really emphasizes why the FOSS model is beneficial for everyone involved.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An interesting area of graphics driver development is all the compiler work that is involved. Vulkan drivers such as Mesa3D Turnip need to process shader programs sent by the application to the GPU, and these programs govern how pixels in our screens are shaded or colored with geometry, textures, and lights while playing games. Job Noorman, an engineer from our Compilers Team, made significant contributions to the compiler used by Mesa3D Turnip. He also contributed to the Mesa3D NIR shader compiler, a common part that all Mesa drivers use, including RADV (most popularly used on the Steam Deck) or V3DV (used on Raspberry Pi boards).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As is normal for Igalia, while we focused on delivering results for our customer, we also made our work as widely useful as possible. For example: âWhile our target throughout our work has been the Snapdragon 8 Gen 3 thatâs in the Frame, much of our work extends back through years of Snapdragon hardware, and we regression test it to make sure it stays Vulkan conformant,â said Anholt. This means that Igaliaâs work for the Frame has consistently passed Vulkanâs Conformance Test Suite (CTS) of over 2.8 million tests, some of which Igalia is involved in creating.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our very own Vulkan CTS expert Ricardo GarcÃa says:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Igalia and other Valve contractors actively participate in several areas inside the Khronos Group, the organization maintaining and developing graphics API standards like Vulkan. We contribute specification fixes and feedback, and we are regularly involved in the development of many new Vulkan extensions. Some of these end up being critical for game developers, like mesh shading. Others ensure a smooth and efficient translation of other APIs like DirectX to Vulkan, or help take advantage of hardware features to ensure applications perform great across multiple platforms, both mobile like the Steam Frame or desktop like the Steam Machine. Having Vulkan CTS coverage for these new extensions is a critical step in the release process, helping make sure the specification is clear and drivers implement it correctly, and Igalia engineers have contributed millions of source code lines and tests since our collaboration with Valve started.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A huge challenge we faced in moving forward with development is ensuring that we didnât introduce regressions, small innocent-seeming changes can completely break rendering on games in a way that even CTS might not catch. What automated testing could be done was often quite constrained, but Igalians found ways to push through the barriers. âI made a continuous integration test to automatically run single-frame captures of a wide range of games spanning D3D11, D3D9, D3D8, Vulkan, and OpenGL APIs,â said Piliaiev, about the development covered in his recent XDC 2025 talk, âensuring that we donât have rendering or performance regressions.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, Igaliaâs work for Valve will continue to deliver benefits to the wider Linux Gaming ecosystem. For example, the Steam Frame, as a battery-powered VR headset, needs to deliver high performance within a limited power budget. A way to address this is to create a more efficient task scheduler, which is something Changwoo Min of Igaliaâs Kernel Team has been working on. As he says, âI have been developing a customized CPU scheduler for gaming, named LAVD: Latency-criticality Aware Virtual Deadline scheduler.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In general terms, a scheduler automatically identifies critical tasks and dynamically boosts their deadlines to improve responsiveness. Most task schedulers donât take energy consumption into account, but the Rust-based LAVD is different. âLAVD makes scheduling decisions considering each chipâs performance versus energy trade-offs. It measures and predicts the required computing power on the fly, then selects the best set of CPUs to meet that demand with minimal energy consumption,â said Min.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of our other kernel engineers, Melissa Wen, has been working on AMD kernel display drivers to maintain good color management and HDR support for SteamOS across AMD hardware families, both for the Steam Deck and the Steam Machine. This is especially important with newer display hardware in the Steam Machine, which features some notable differences in color capabilities, aiming for more powerful and efficient color management which necessitated driver work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¦and thatâs a wrap! We will continue our efforts toward improving future versions of SteamOS, and with a partner as strongly supportive as Valve, we expect to do more work to make Linux gaming even better. If any of that sounded interesting and youâd like to work with us to tackle tricky problems of your own, please get in touch!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46006616</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 17:29:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tuxedo Computers Cancels Snapdragon X1 Linux Laptop</title><link>https://www.tuxedocomputers.com/en/Discontinuation-of-ARM-notebooks-with-Snapdragon-X-Elite-SoC.tuxedo</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="600c35d002b48faf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We ship your order to almost all countries, in Europe mostly even free of charge! The respective shipping costs and the cost threshold above which we will cover the costs for you can be found here or for international shipping in the table below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are no shipping costs within Germany for goods worth €100 or more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No matter how many small articles you order, such as USB stick card reader, LAN adapters or fan articles, with us, you pay a maximum of 7.99 € shipping costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can check all occurring shipping costs or if we even deliver for free right before sending your order!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are the shipping costs as well as the amount threshold for your order. The threshold is referring to the total amount of your order, which enables free shipping.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For orders outside the EU there might be additional duties, taxes or charges needed to be paid by the customer. These don't have to be paid to the supplier, but to local authorities. Please check for any details with your local customs or tax authorities before ordering! But as a benefit you don't have to pay German taxes, this means you save up to 19%!&lt;lb/&gt; Due to the Brexit and the associated changes, there may be delays of several days in customs clearance on site for deliveries to the UK. This is not within our sphere of influence, so we ask for your understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Country&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Shipping Fee&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Free Shipping From&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Albania&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;99,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Andorra&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;59,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Belgium&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8,49 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bulgaria&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Denmark&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8,49 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Estonia&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Faroe Islands&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;129,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Finland&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;150 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;France&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;120 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Greece&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22,90 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;United Kingdom&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;120 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;199,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;India&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;199,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ireland&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;150 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Island&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;129,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Italy&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;120 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Japan&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;99,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Canada&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;99,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Croatia&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;34,90 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;500 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Latvia&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Lithuania&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Luxembourg&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8,49 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Macau&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;199,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Malta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;34,90 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;500 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Macedonia&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;59,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Moldova&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;199,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Monaco&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Montenegro&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;99,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Netherlands&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8,49 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Norway&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;150 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Austria&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8,49 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Poland&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Portugal&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;150 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Romania&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;San Marino&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;120 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sweden&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;150 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Switzerland&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;150 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Serbia&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;34,90 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;500 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Singapore&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;199,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Slovakia&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Slovenia&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Spain (without Canary Islands)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;150 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Czech Republic&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hungary&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15,99 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;160 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;USA including Hawaii&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;99,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;United Arabic Emirates&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;199,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Cyprus&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;34,90 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;500 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Qatar&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;199,00 EUR&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;-&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If not stated differently in the article's description, we deliver goods in:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For orders paid in advance, the delivery time starts with receipt of the payment. Please keep in mind that there is no delivery on Sundays or on holidays.&lt;lb/&gt; For goods delivered as download, there will be no shipping fees due.&lt;lb/&gt; Access data for downloads are sent out via e-mail 1-3 working days after contract formation. For orders with advanced payment, we will deliver after receiving the payment. You can download the item by using the link sent to you via e-mail.&lt;lb/&gt; Self-pick-up of orders is not possible, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46008156</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 19:46:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pixar: The Early Days A never-before-seen 1996 interview</title><link>https://stevejobsarchive.com/stories/pixar-early-days</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2501819f3360cdbd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Pixar: The Early Days&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A never-before-seen 1996 interview&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;November 18, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To mark Toy Story’s 30th anniversary, we’re sharing a never-before-seen interview with Steve from November 22, 1996—exactly one year after the film debuted in theaters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Toy Story was the world’s first entirely computer-animated feature-length film. An instant hit with audiences and critics, it also transformed Pixar, which went public the week after its premiere. Buoyed by Toy Story’s success, Pixar’s stock price closed at nearly double its initial offering, giving it a market valuation of approximately $1.5 billion and marking the largest IPO of 1995. The following year, Toy Story was nominated for three Academy Awards en route to winning a Special Achievement Oscar in March. In July, Pixar announced that it would close its television-commercial unit to focus primarily on feature films. By the time of the interview, the team had grown by 70 percent in less than a year; A Bug’s Life was in production; and behind the scenes, Steve was using his new leverage to renegotiate Pixar’s partnership with Disney.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this footage, Steve reveals the long game behind Pixar’s seeming overnight success. With striking clarity, he explains how its business model gives artists and engineers a stake in their creations, and he reflects on what Disney’s hard-won wisdom taught him about focus and discipline. He also talks about the challenge of leading a team so talented that it inverts the usual hierarchy, the incentives that inspire people to stay with the company, and the deeper purpose that unites them all: to tell stories that last and put something of enduring value into the culture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Pixar, Steve collaborated closely with president Ed Catmull and refined a management approach centered on creating the conditions for talent to thrive. When he returned to Apple a few weeks after this interview, his experience at Pixar shaped how he saw his role as CEO: building a company on timeless ideas made new through technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Stay Hungry, Stay Foolish&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Celebrating Steve’s timeless address&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46008769</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 20:45:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>We remain alive also in a dead internet</title><link>https://slavoj.substack.com/p/why-we-remain-alive-also-in-a-dead-954</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46008788</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 20:46:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The senior population is booming. Caregiving is struggling to keep up</title><link>https://www.cnbc.com/2025/11/21/senior-caregiving-labor.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2f2889550f9488f9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In November 2022, Beth Pinsker's 76-year-old mother began to get sick.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ann Pinsker, an otherwise healthy woman, had elected to have a spinal surgery to preserve her ability to walk after having back issues. What Ann and Beth had thought would be a straightforward recovery process instead yielded complications and infections, landing Ann in one assisted living facility after another as her daughter navigated her care.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eventually, by July of the following year, Ann died.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We thought she'd be back up to speed a few weeks after hospital stay, rehab, home, but she had complications, and it was all a lot harder than she thought," Beth Pinsker, a certified financial planner and financial planning columnist at MarketWatch who has written a book on caregiving, told CNBC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It wasn't Pinsker's first time navigating senior care. Five years before her mother's death, she took care of her father, and before that, her grandparents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But throughout each of those processes, Pinsker said she noticed a significant shift in the senior caregiving sector.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"From the level of care that my grandparents received to the level of care that my mom received, prices skyrocketed and services decreased," she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's evocative of a larger trend across the sector as the senior population in the U.S. booms and the labor force struggles to keep up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recent data from the U.S. Census Bureau found that the population of people ages 65 and older in the country grew from 12.4% in 2004 to 18% in 2024, and the number of older adults outnumbered children in 11 states — up from just three states in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along with that population change came other shifts, including increased demand for care for older people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics, the prices for senior care services are rising faster than the price of inflation. In September, the Consumer Price Index rose 3% annually, while prices for nursing homes and adult day services rose more than 4% over the same period.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the labor force hasn't necessarily kept up with the surge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The demand for home care workers is soaring as the gap widens, with a projected 4.6 million unfulfilled jobs by 2032, according to Harvard Public Health. And McKnight's Senior Living, a trade publication that caters to senior care businesses, found that the labor gap for long-term care is more severe than any other sector in health care, down more than 7% since 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;'A critical labor shortage'&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That shortage is primarily driven by a combination of low wages, poor job quality and difficulty climbing the ranks, according to experts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"This is coming for us, and we are going to have this create an enormous need for long-term care," Massachusetts Institute of Technology economist Jonathan Gruber told CNBC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gruber said the country is entering a period of "peak demand" for aging baby boomers, creating a situation where rising demand and pay do not sufficiently match up, leading to a "critical labor shortage."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On top of that, the jobs at nursing homes are often strenuous and vary in skills depending on the specific needs of each senior, he said, leading nursing assistants to be staffed in difficult jobs that often only pay slightly more than a retail job, despite requiring more training.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to the BLS' most recent wage data from May 2024, the average base salary for home health and personal care aides was $16.82 per hour, compared with $15.07 per hour for fast food and counter workers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"If we can create a better caring system with an entitlement to all care for those who need it, that will free millions of workers to make our economy grow, so this is a drag on economic growth," Gruber said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pinsker said she saw that shortage play out firsthand. At one of the assisted living facilities she toured for her mother, she noticed nurses wheeling residents into the dining hall for lunch at 10:30 a.m., an hour and a half before lunch would be served, because the home did not have enough caregivers to retrieve them at noon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"They were bringing them in one at a time, whoever was available, seating them in rows at their tables, and just leaving them there to sit and wait," Pinsker said. "This was their morning activity for these people in this nursing home. … They just don't have enough people to push them around. That's what a staffing shortage looks like in real time."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pinsker said her mother was placed in a nursing rehab facility, unable to walk or get out of bed, and that her facility had zero doctors on the premises. Most often, she said the facility was just staffed with business-level caretakers who change bedpans and clothing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"They don't have enough doctors and registered nurses and physical therapists and occupational therapists and people to come and check blood pressure and take blood samples and that sort of stuff," she said. "They're short on all ends of the staffing spectrum."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Filling the gap&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gruber said there are three directions he thinks the country could go in to solve the labor gap: Pay more for these jobs, allow more immigration to fill the jobs or set up better career ladders within the sector.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's not rocket science — you've either got to pay more, or you've got to let in way more people. … There are wonderful, caring people all over the world who would like to come care for our seniors at the wages we're willing to pay, and we just have to let them in," Gruber said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He's also part of an initiative in Massachusetts focused on making training more affordable for nurses to be able to climb the career ladder and pipelines to fill the shortages, which he said helps staff more people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Care.com CEO Brad Wilson, an overwhelming demand for senior care made it clear to the company that it needed to set up a separate category of job offerings. Care.com, which is most known for listing child care service jobs, met the demand and rolled out additional senior care options, as well as a tool for families trying to navigate what would work best for their situations and households.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wilson said the company sees senior care as a $200 billion to $300 billion per year category. Now, it's the company's fastest-growing segment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"We've heard from families that it's an enormous strain as they go through the senior care aspect of these things, because child care can be a little bit more planned, but sometimes your adult or senior care situation is sudden, and there's a lot to navigate," he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Care.com is also increasingly seeing demand rise for "house managers," Wilson said, who can help multiple people in a single household, as caregiving situations evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I can't underscore enough ... this is the most unforeseen part of the caregiving journey, and it's increasingly prevalent," he added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And as the senior population booms, so too does the so-called sandwich generation, whose members are taking care of both their aging parents and their young children. Wilson said his family is in the thick of navigating caring for older family members while also raising three children.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"By 2034, there will actually be more seniors in this country than children," Wilson said, citing Census Bureau statistics. "Senior care is in a crisis. It's actually the very much unseen part of the caregiving crisis today, and we're really trying to bring some visibility to it and share that we have solutions that can help people."&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46008983</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 21:05:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Untold History of Arduino</title><link>https://arduinohistory.github.io/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b774c8d9b3b21372"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;日本語 · italiano · Deutsch · Français&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hello. My name is Hernando Barragán.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through the years, and more recently due to the affairs between Arduino LLC and Arduino S.R.L., I have received a lot of questions from people about the history of Wiring and, of course, Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was also shown this US Federal Courts website, which presents documents citing my work to support the plaintiff’s claims which, in my opinion, contribute to the distortion of information surrounding my work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The history of Arduino has been told by many people, and no two stories match. I want to clarify some facts around the history of Arduino, with proper supported references and documents, to better communicate to people who are interested, about Arduino’s origin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As well, I will attempt to correct some things that have distorted my role or work by pointing out common mistakes, misleading information, and poor journalism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will go through a summary of the history first, then I will answer a series of questions that I have been often asked over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started Wiring in 2003 as my Master’s thesis project at the Interaction Design Institute Ivrea (IDII) in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The objective of the thesis was to make it easy for artists and designers to work with electronics, by abstracting away the often complicated details of electronics so they can focus on their own objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full thesis document can be downloaded here: http://people.interactionivrea.org/h.barragan/thesis/thesis_low_res.pdf&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Massimo Banzi and Casey Reas (known for his work on Processing) were supervisors for my thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The project received plenty of attention at IDII, and was used for several other projects from 2004, up until the closure of the school in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because of my thesis, I was proud to graduate with distinction; the only individual at IDII in 2004 to receive the distinction. I continued the development of Wiring while working at the Universidad de Los Andes in Colombia, where I began teaching as an instructor in Interaction Design.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What Wiring is, and why it was created can be extracted from the abstract section of my thesis document. Please keep in mind that it was 2003, and these premises are not to be taken lightly. You may have heard them before recited as proclamations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“… Current prototyping tools for electronics and programming are mostly targeted to engineering, robotics and technical audiences. They are hard to learn, and the programming languages are far from useful in contexts outside a specific technology …”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“… It can also be used to teach and learn computer programming and prototyping with electronics…”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Wiring builds on Processing…”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These were the key resulting elements of Wiring:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through the thesis document, it is possible to understand the design process I followed. Considerable research and references to prior work has served as a basis for my work. To quickly illustrate the process, a few key points are provided below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered where those commands come from?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Probably one of the most distinctive things, that is widely known and used today by Arduino users in their sketches, is the set of commands I created as the language definition for Wiring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pinMode()&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;digitalRead()&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;digitalWrite()&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;analogRead()&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;analogWrite()&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;delay()&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;millis()&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Abstracting the microcontroller pins as numbers was, without a doubt, a major decision, possible because the syntax was defined prior to implementation in any hardware platform. All the language command naming and syntax were the result of an exhaustive design process I conducted, which included user testing with students, observation, analysis, adjustment and iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I developed the hardware prototypes, the language also naturally developed. It wasn’t until after the final prototype had been made that the language became solid and refined.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are still curious about the design process, it is detailed in the thesis document, including earlier stages of command naming and syntax that were later discarded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From a designer’s point of view, this was probably the most difficult part to address. I asked for or bought evaluation boards from different microcontroller manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some key moments in the hardware design for Wiring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first prototype for Wiring used the Parallax Javelin Stamp microcontroller. It was a natural option since it was programmed in a subset of the Java language, which was already being used by Processing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Problem: as described in the thesis document on page 40, compiling, linking and uploading of user’s programs relied on Parallax’s proprietary tools. Since Wiring was planned as open source software, the Javelin Stamp was simply not a viable option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Photo of Javelin Stamp used for first prototype for Wiring hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the next prototypes, microcontrollers were chosen on a basis of availability of open source tools for compiling, linking and uploading the user’s code. This led to discarding the very popular Microchip PIC family of microcontrollers very early, because, at the time (circa 2003), Microchip did not have an open source toolchain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the second Wiring hardware prototype, the Atmel ARM-based AT91R40008 microcontroller was selected, which lead to excellent results. The first sketch examples were developed and command naming testing began. For example, &lt;code&gt;pinWrite()&lt;/code&gt; used to be the name of the now ubiquitous &lt;code&gt;digitalWrite()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Atmel R40008 served as a test bed for the digital input/output API and the serial communications API, during my evaluation of its capabilities. The Atmel R40008 was a very powerful microcontroller, but was far too complex for a hands-on approach because it was almost impossible to solder by hand onto a printed circuit board.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more information on this prototype, see page 42 in the thesis document.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Photo of Atmel AT91R40008 used for second Wiring hardware prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The previous prototype experiments led to the third prototype, where the microcontroller was downscaled to one still powerful, yet with the possibility of tinkering with it without the requirements of specialized equipment or on-board extra peripherals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I selected the Atmel ATmega128 microcontroller and bought an Atmel STK500 evaluation board with a special socket for the ATmega128.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Photo of Atmel STK500 with ATmega128 expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tests with the STK500 were immediately successful, so I bought a MAVRIC board from BDMICRO with the ATmega128 soldered. Brian Dean’s work on his MAVRIC boards were unparalleled at that time, and his work drove him to build a software tool to easily upload new programs to his board. It is still used today in the Arduino software, and is called “avrdude”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As traditional COM ports were disappearing from computers, I selected FTDI hardware for communication through a USB port on the host computer. FTDI provided drivers for Windows, Mac OS X and Linux which was required for the Wiring environment to work on all platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Photo of BDMICRO MAVRIC-II used for the third Wiring hardware prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Photo of an FTDI FT232BM evaluation board used in the third Wiring hardware prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FTDI evaluation board was interfaced with the MAVRIC board and tested with the third Wiring prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Testing with the BDMICRO MAVRIC-II board and FTDI-FT232BM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In early 2004, based on the prototype using the MAVRIC board (Prototype 3), I used Brian Dean’s and Pascal Stang’s schematic designs as a reference to create the first Wiring board design. It had the following features:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I used Eagle PCB from Cadsoft to design the schematic and printed circuit board.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wiring board printed circuit board layout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along with the third prototype, the final version of the API was tested and refined. More examples were added and I wrote the first LED blink example that is still used today as the first sketch that a user runs on an Arduino board to learn the environment. Even more examples were developed to support liquid crystal displays (LCDs), serial port communication, servo motors, etc. and even to interface Wiring with Processing via serial communication. Details can be found on page 50 in the thesis document.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In March 2004, 25 Wiring printed circuit boards were ordered and manufactured at SERP, and paid for by IDII.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hand-soldered these 25 boards and started to conduct usability tests with some of my classmates at IDII. It was an exciting time!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Photos of the first Wiring board&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After graduating from IDII in 2004, I moved back to Colombia, and began teaching as an instructor in Interaction Design at the Universidad de Los Andes. As I continued to develop Wiring, IDII decided to print and assemble a batch of 100 Wiring boards to teach physical computing at IDII in late 2004. Bill Verplank (a former IDII faculty member) asked Massimo Banzi to send 10 of the boards to me for use in my classes in Colombia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2004, Faculty member Yaniv Steiner, former student Giorgio Olivero, and information designer consultant Paolo Sancis started the Instant Soup Project, based on Wiring at IDII.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the autumn of 2004, Wiring was used to teach physical computing at IDII through a project called Strangely Familiar, consisting of 22 students, and 11 successful projects. Four faculty members ran the 4-week project:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It turned out to be a resounding success for both the students as well as the professors and teachers. Strangely Familiar demonstrated the potential of Wiring as an innovation platform for interaction design.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On December 16th, 2004, Bill Verplank sent an email to me saying:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;[The projects] were wonderful. Everyone had things working. Five of the projects had motors in them! The most advanced (from two MIT grads - architect and mathematician) allowed drawing a profile in Proce55ing and feeling it with a wheel/motor run by Wiring…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It is clear that one of the elements of success was [the] use of the Wiring board.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the brief for the course:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a booklet with the resulting projects:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tug Tug phones by Haiyan Zhang (with Aram Armstrong)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commitment Radio by David Chiu and Alexandra Deschamps-Sonsino&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speak Out by Tristam Sparks and Andreea Cherlaru (with Ana Camila Amorim)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Feel the Music I by James Tichenor and David A. Mellis&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Amazing All Band Radio by Oren Horev &amp;amp; Myriel Milicevic (with Marcos Weskamp)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In May 2005, I contracted Advanced Circuits in the USA to print the first 200 printed circuit boards outside of IDII, and assembled them in Colombia. I began selling and shipping boards to various schools and universities, and by the end of 2005, Wiring was being used around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Wiring’s Reach by 2005” graphic, provided by Collin Reisdorf&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When IDII manufactured the first set of Wiring boards, the cost was probably around USD$50 each. (I don’t know what the actual cost was, as I wasn’t involved in the process. However, I was selling the boards from Colombia for about USD$60.) This was a considerable drop in price from the boards that were currently available, but it was still a significant cost for most people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2005, Massimo Banzi, along with David Mellis (an IDII student at the time) and David Cuartielles, added support for the cheaper ATmega8 microcontroller to Wiring. Then they forked (or copied) the Wiring source code and started running it as a separate project, called Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There was no need to create a separate project, as I would have gladly helped them and developed support for the ATmega8 and any other microcontrollers. I had planned to do this all along.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had inadvertantly taken a photo of some notes about my plans for Wiring, in the photo of Karmen Franinovic (former IDII student from 2002 to 2004) testing a stretch sensor for a lamp in March 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wiring and Arduino shared many of the early development done by Nicholas Zambetti, a former IDII student in the same class as David Mellis. For a brief time, Nicholas had been considered a member of the Arduino Team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Around the same time, Gianluca Martino (he was a consultant at SERP, the printed circuit board factory at Ivrea where the first Wiring boards were made), joined the Arduino Team to help with manufacturing and hardware development. So, to reduce the cost of their boards, Gianluca, with some help from David Cuartielles, developed cheaper hardware by using the ATmega8.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apparently this is the first “Arduino” prototype - dubbed Wiring Lite. I think Massimo Banzi designed this one, but I’m unsure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arduino Extreme v2 - “Second production version of the Arduino USB boards. This has been properly engineered by Gianluca Martino.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tom Igoe (a faculty member at the ITP at NYU2) was invited by Massimo Banzi to IDII for a workshop and became part of the Arduino Team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To this day, I do not know exactly why the Arduino Team forked the code from Wiring. It was also puzzling why we didn’t work together. So, to answer the question, I was never asked to become a member of the Arduino Team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even though I was perplexed by the Arduino Team forking the code, I continued development on Wiring, and almost all of the improvements that had been made to Wiring, by me and plenty of contributors, were merged into the Arduino source code. I tried to ignore the fact that they were still taking my work and also wondered about the redundancy and waste of resources in duplicating efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the end of 2005, I started to work with Casey Reas on a chapter for the book “Processing: A Programming Handbook for Visual Artists and Designers.” The chapter presents a short history of electronics in the Arts. It includes examples for interfacing Processing with Wiring and Arduino. I presented those examples in both platforms and made sure the examples included worked for both Wiring and Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The book got a second edition in 2013 and the chapter was revised again by Casey and me, and the extension has been made available online since 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, each of them had experience with Wiring before creating Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Massimo Banzi taught with Wiring at IDII from 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Massimo Banzi teaching interaction design at IDII with Wiring boards in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;David Mellis was a student at IDII from 2004 to 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A blurry version of David Mellis learning physical computing with Wiring in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In January 2005, IDII hired David Cuartielles to develop a couple of plug-in boards for the Wiring board, for motor control and bluetooth connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two plug-in boards developed at IDII by David Cuartielles and his brother. Bluetooth shield on the left, and a motor controller shield on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I showed early versions of Wiring to Tom Igoe during a visit to ITP in New York in 2003. At the time, he had no experience with Atmel hardware, as Tom was using PIC microcontrollers at ITP as an alternative to the costly platforms like Parallax Basic Stamp or Basic X. One of Tom’s recommendations at this visit was: “well, do it for PIC, because this is what we use here.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Years later, in 2007, Tom Igoe released the first edition of the “Making Things Talk” book published by O’Reilly3, which presents the use of both Wiring and Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gianluca Martino originally worked for SERP (the factory that made the first 25 Wiring circuit boards) and later he founded Smart Projects SRL (April 1st, 2004). Smart Projects made the first batch of 100 Wiring boards for IDII to teach physical computing in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programma2003 was a Microchip PIC microcontroller board developed by Massimo Banzi in 2003. After using BasicX to teach Physical computing in the winter of 2002, Massimo decided to do a board using the PIC chip in 2003. The problem with the PIC microcontrollers was that there wasn’t an open source toolchain available at the time, to use a language like C to program them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programma2003 board designed by Massimo Banzi in 2003&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because of the lack of an open source toolchain, Massimo decided to use an environment called JAL (Just Another Language) to program the PIC microcontroller. JAL was created by Wouter van Ooijen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It consisted of the JAL compiler, linker, uploader, bootloader and examples for the PIC. However, the software would only run on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make JAL easier to use, Massimo used the base examples from JAL and simplified some of them for the distribution package for IDII.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, in 2003, most students at IDII used Mac computers. So I volunteered to help Massimo by making a small and simple environment for Mac OS X so students with a Mac could use it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my thesis document, I characterized Programma2003 as a non-viable model to follow, since other more comprehensive tools were already available in the market. The main problems were:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was impossible to know if it was powered or not (frustrating/dangerous in a learning environment) and an additional RS232 to USB expensive converter was required to connect it to a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a gesture to help Massimo’s Programma2003 project, I also wrote something I called Programma2003 Interface, which basically interfaced any serial communication between a microcontroller and a computer with the network. This expanded the prototyping toolbox at IDII. It allowed students to use software like Adobe Flash (formerly Macromedia) to communicate with a microcontroller.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reference to Wiring on the Arduino.cc website, although it has improved slightly over time, is misleading as it tries to attribute Wiring to Programma2003.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arduino.cc website version of Arduino’s History from https://www.arduino.cc/en/Main/Credits&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adding to the confusion is this Flickr photo album by Massimo Banzi:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mbanzi/albums/72157633136997919/with/8610131426/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is called “Teaching: IDII 2004 Strangely Familiar”. Strangely Familiar was taught with Wiring (see above). This photo album seems to associate the Programma2003 with the class, but it was, in fact, never used. It is odd that the Wiring boards are absent from the album, however one Wiring board picture does appear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is no secret that the acknowledgement of Wiring has been very limited in the past. Back in 2013, at Open Hardware Summit at MIT, during the panel “Implications of Open Source Business: Forking and Attribution”, David Mellis acknowledges, for the first time, that the Arduino Team hadn’t done a very good job acknowledging Wiring. Unfortunately, he didn’t go into details why they hadn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been quiet about everything that has happened with Arduino for a long time. But now that people are fraudulently saying that my work is their’s, I feel like I need to speak up about the past.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, in the ongoing case between Arduino LLC and Arduino S.R.L., there is a claim, by the Plaintiff, such that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;34. Banzi is the creator of the Programma2003 Development Platform, a precursor of the many ARDUINO-branded products. See: http://sourceforge.net/projects/programma2003/. Banzi was also the Master’s Thesis advisor of Hernando Barragan whose work would result in the Wiring Development Platform which inspired Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is what, in my opinion, is wrong with that claim:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further on:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;39. The Founders, assisted by Nicholas Zambetti, another student at IDII, undertook and developed a project in which they designed a platform and environment for microcontroller boards (“Boards”) to replace the Wiring Development Project. Banzi gave the project its name, the ARDUINO project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are the questions I’d ask “The Founders:”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know it might be done now and again, but, in my opinion, it is unethical and a bad example for academics to do something like this with the work of a student. Educators, more than anybody else, should avoid taking advantage of their student’s work. In a way, I still feel violated by “The Founders” for calling my work their’s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It may be legal to take an open source software and hardware project’s model, philosophy, discourse, and the thousands of hours of work by its author, exert a branding exercise on it, and release it to the world as something “new” or “inspired”, but… is it right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Someone once said:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“If we don’t make things ultra clear, people draw their own conclusions and they become facts even if we never said anything like that.”4&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems to me that this is universally true, and especially if you mislead people with only slight alterations of the truth, you can have control over their conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are a couple of mainstream examples of misleading information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;http://blog.experientia.com/uploads/2013/10/Interaction_Ivrea_arduino.pdf&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This diagram was produced to tell the story of the prototyping tools developed at IDII. It was beautifully done by Giorgio Olivero, using the content provided by the school in 2005, and released in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The projects presented in the red blobs, although they were made with Wiring, appear to be associated with Arduino at a time when Arduino didn’t even exist, nor was even close to being ready to do them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the authors of the projects inquired about the mistake, and why their projects were shifted to Arduino, but received no response.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that nothing was changed in this highly public document, I have to thank the support of the students who pointed it out and inquired about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another very public piece of media from 2010 was The Arduino Documentary (written and directed by Raúl Alaejos, Rodrigo Calvo).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one is very interesting, especially seeing it today in 2016. I think the idea of doing a documentary is very good, especially for a project with such a rich history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some parts that present some interesting contradictions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1:45 - “We wanted it to be open source so that everybody could come and help, and contribute.” It is suggested here that Wiring was closed source. Because part of Wiring was based on Processing, and Processing was GPL open source, as well as all the libraries, Wiring, and hence Arduino, had to be open source. It was not an option to have it be closed source. Also, the insinuation that they made the software easier is misleading, since nothing changed in the language, which is the essence of the project’s simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3:20 - David Cuartielles already knew about Wiring, as he was hired to design two plug-in boards for it by IDII in 2005 as pointed out earlier in this document. David Mellis learned physical computing using Wiring as a student at IDII in 2004. Interestingly, Gianluca came in as the person who was able to design the board itself (he wasn’t just a contractor for manufacturing); he was part of the “Arduino Team”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;8:53 - David Cuartielles is presenting at the Media Lab in Madrid, in July 2005: “Arduino is the last project, I finished it last week. I talked to Ivrea’s technical director and told him: Wouldn’t it be great if we can do something we offer for free? he says - For free? - Yeah!” David comes across here as the author of a project that he completed “last week”, and convincing the “technical director” at IDII to offer it for free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;18:56 - Massimo Banzi:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For us at the beginning it was a specific need: we knew the school was closing and we were afraid that lawyers would show up one day and say - Everything here goes into a box and gets forgotten about. - So we thought - OK, if we open everything about this, then we can survive the closing of the school - So that was the first step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one is very special. It misleadingly presents the fact of making Arduino open source as the consequence of the school closing. This poses a question: why would a bunch of lawyers “put in a box” a project based on other open source projects? It is almost puerile. The problem is, common people might think this is true, forming altruistic reasons for the team to make Arduino open source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There seems to be a trend in how the Arduino Team fails to recognize significant parties that contributed to their success.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In October 2013, Jan-Christoph Zoels (a former IDII faculty member) wrote to the IDII community mail list, a message presenting the article released at Core77 about the Intel-Arduino news on Wired UK:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A proud moment to see Intel referring to an Interaction Ivrea initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And a good investment too:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Arduino development was started and developed at Interaction Design Institute Ivrea with an original funding of circa 250.000€. Another good decision was to keep Arduino as open source at the end of Interaction Ivrea in 2005 before merging with Domus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To which Massimo Banzi responded:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I would like to point out that we never got any funding from Ivrea for Arduino (apart from buying 50 of them in the last year of the institute)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;250.000 EUR is ridiculous…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This article must be retracted now&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Sorry JC but you had nothing to do.with this…. You can’t possibly try to get credit for.something you hadn’t been involved with&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was nice, however, to get this a few days later in the same email thread:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this section, I just wanted to show a fraction of the many different articles (and other press) that have been written about Arduino, which include its history that is rarely told the same way twice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, please, read them at your leisure, and form your own opinions, and, definitely, ask questions!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is rare to see well researched journalism these days. The articles below are excellent examples of that postulate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a 2008 Wired interview, Banzi explains how he did Arduino in a weekend:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The two decided to design their own board and enlisted one of Banzi’s students—David Mellis—to write the programming language for it. In two days, Mellis banged out the code; three days more and the board was complete. They called it the Arduino, after a nearby pub, and it was an instant hit with the students.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This article has been written without any fact checking. It certainly doesn’t help that the interviewee isn’t telling them the right information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a 2011 IEEE Spectrum article, titled “The Making of Arduino”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, the history is taken verbatim from the interviewee. I was not contacted before the article was published, even though I was mentioned. And I doubt that anyone from IDII was contacted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just one of the many confusing parts of Arduino’s history is in this quote:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Since the purpose was to create a quick and easily accessible platform, they felt they’d be better off opening up the project to as many people as possible rather than keeping it closed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was never closed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A 2014 article from Circuits Today has a very confusing opening:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It was in the Interactive Design Institute [sic] that a hardware thesis was contributed for a wiring design by a Colombian student named Hernando Barragan. The title of the thesis was “Arduino–La rivoluzione dell’open hardware” (“Arduino – The Revolution of Open Hardware”). Yes, it sounded a little different from the usual thesis but none would have imagined that it would carve a niche in the field of electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A team of five developers worked on this thesis and when the new wiring platform was complete, they worked to make it much lighter, less expensive, and available to the open source community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The title of my thesis is obviously wrong. There weren’t five “developers” working on the thesis. And the code was always open source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, I wasn’t contacted for reference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a 2013 interview by Dale Dougherty with Massimo Banzi, once again the story changes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Wiring had an expensive board, about $100, because it used an expensive chip. I didn’t like that, and the student developer and I disagreed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this version of the story by Massimo Banzi, Arduino originated from Wiring, but it is implied that I was insistent on having an expensive board.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regarding the “disagreement”: I never had a discussion with Massimo Banzi about the board being too expensive. I wish that he and I would have had more discussions on such matters, as I had with other advisors and colleagues, as I find it very enriching. The closest thing to a disagreement took place after a successful thesis presentation event, where Massimo showed some odd behaviour towards me. Because he was my advisor, I was at a disadvantage, but I asked Massimo why he was behaving badly towards me, to which I received no answer. I felt threatened, and it was very awkward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His odd behaviour extended to those who collaborated with me on Wiring later on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I decided that we could make an open source version of Wiring, starting from scratch. I asked Gianluca Martino [now one of the five Arduino partners] to help me manufacture the first prototypes, the first boards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here, Massimo is again implying that Wiring wasn’t open source, which it was. And also that they would build the software from “scratch”, which they didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I understand how easy it is to engage people with good storytelling and compelling tales, but academics are expected to do their homework, and at least check the facts behind unsubstantiated statements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this book, Making Futures: Marginal Notes on Innovation, Design, and Democracy Hardcover – October 31, 2014 by Pelle Ehn (Editor), Elisabet M. Nilsson (Editor), Richard Topgaard (Editor):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chapter 8: How Deep is Your Love? On Open-Source Hardware (David Cuartielles)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In 2005, at the Interaction Design Institute Ivrea, we had the vision that making a small prototyping platform aimed at designers would help them getting a better understanding of technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;David Cuartielles’ version of Arduino’s history doesn’t even include Wiring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This book has been released chapter by chapter under Creative Commons: http://dspace.mah.se/handle/2043/17985&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wiring as predecessor to Arduino:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interview with Ben Fry and Casey Reas:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Safari Books Online, Casey Reas, Getting Started with Processing, Chapter One, Family Tree:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nicholas Zambetti Arduino Project Page:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Nicholas did a lot of work with both Wiring and Arduino)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wired Italy - What’s happening in Arduino?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;http://www.wired.it/gadget/computer/2015/02/12/arduino-nel-caos-situazione/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Repubblica Italy - Massimo Banzi: “The Reason of the War for Arduino”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Makezine - Massimo Banzi Fighting for Arduino&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;http://makezine.com/2015/03/19/massimo-banzi-fighting-for-arduino/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hackaday - Federico Musto of Arduino SRL discusses Arduino legal situation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;http://hackaday.com/2015/07/23/hackaday-interviews-federico-musto-of-arduino-srl/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hackaday - Federico Musto of Arduino SRL shows us new products and new directions&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Massimo going to Ted Talk – candid (2012-08-06)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tZxY8_CNiCw&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a candid view of Massimo just before performing at a TED Talk. You can make your own mind up about the majority of the video, however, the most interesting comment, in my opinion, is at the end, where he says:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;… Innovation without asking for permission. So, in a way, Open Source allows you to be innovative without asking for permission.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you for taking time to read this. I think it is very important, not just in the academic world, to properly acknowledge the origin of things. As I learned from fantastic educators, doing this properly not only enriches your work, but also positions it better to allow others to investigate and see where your ideas come from. Maybe they will find other alternatives or improve what was done and better position their own ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Personally, watching the outreach of what I created back in 2003 in so many different contexts, seeing those commands bringing to life people’s ideas and creations from all over the world, has brought me so many satisfactions, surprises, new questions, ideas, awareness and friendships. I am thankful for that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think it is important to know the past to avoid making the same mistakes in the future. Sometimes I wish I would have had a chance to talk about this differently, for a different motif. Instead, many times I have come across journalists and common people compromised in their independence. Either they had direct business with Arduino, or simply wanted to avoid upsetting Massimo Banzi. Or there are the close-minded individuals following a cause and refusing to see or hear anything different from what they believe. And then there are the individuals who are just part of the crowd that reproduce what they are told to reproduce. For those others, this document is an invitation to trust your curiosity, to question, to dig deeper in whatever interests you and is important to you as an individual or as a member of a community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ll see you soon,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hernando.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The notion of a “Sketch” within the context of writing programs comes from Processing and previously from Design by Numbers (DBN). It was extended by Wiring within the context of prototyping with electronics or “sketching” with hardware. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interactive Telecommunications Program at New York University ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Page 34, ISBN-13: 978-0596510510 ISBN-10: 0596510519, http://www.amazon.com/Making-Things-Talk-Practical-Connecting/dp/0596510519/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=Making+Things+Talk ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://groups.google.com/a/arduino.cc/d/msg/developers/HEKecd0qhS4/nADS2jW6DgAJ ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46009209</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 21:29:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>LAPD Helicopter Tracker with Real-Time Operating Costs</title><link>https://lapdhelicoptertracker.com/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46009591</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 22:11:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Is Matrix Multiplication Ugly?</title><link>https://mathenchant.wordpress.com/2025/11/21/is-matrix-multiplication-ugly/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b305911521a69631"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I was minding my own business, peacefully reading a well-written and informative article about artificial intelligence, when I was ambushed by a passage in the article that aroused my pique. That’s one of the pitfalls of knowing too much about a topic a journalist is discussing; journalists often make mistakes that most readers wouldn’t notice but that raise the hackles or at least the blood pressure of those in the know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The article in question appeared in The New Yorker. The author, Stephen Witt, was writing about the way that your typical Large Language Model, starting from a blank slate, or rather a slate full of random scribbles, is able to learn about the world, or rather the virtual world called the internet. Throughout the training process, billions of numbers called weights get repeatedly updated so as to steadily improve the model’s performance. Picture a tiny chip with electrons racing around in etched channels, and slowly zoom out: there are many such chips in each server node and many such nodes in each rack, with racks organized in rows, many rows per hall, many halls per building, many buildings per campus. It’s a sort of computer-age version of Borges’ Library of Babel. And the weight-update process that all these countless circuits are carrying out depends heavily on an operation known as matrix multiplication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Witt explained this clearly and accurately, right up to the point where his essay took a very odd turn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;HAMMERING NAILS&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what Witt went on to say about matrix multiplication:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“‘Beauty is the first test: there is no permanent place in the world for ugly mathematics,’ the mathematician G. H. Hardy wrote, in 1940. But matrix multiplication, to which our civilization is now devoting so many of its marginal resources, has all the elegance of a man hammering a nail into a board. It is possessed of neither beauty nor symmetry: in fact, in matrix multiplication, a times b is not the same as b times a.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last sentence struck me as a bizarre non sequitur, somewhat akin to saying “Number addition has neither beauty nor symmetry, because when you write two numbers backwards, their new sum isn’t just their original sum written backwards; for instance, 17 plus 34 is 51, but 71 plus 43 isn’t 15.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next day I sent the following letter to the magazine:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I appreciate Stephen Witt shining a spotlight on matrices, which deserve more attention today than ever before: they play important roles in ecology, economics, physics, and now artificial intelligence (“Information Overload”, November 3). But Witt errs in bringing Hardy’s famous quote (“there is no permanent place in the world for ugly mathematics”) into his story. Matrix algebra is the language of symmetry and transformation, and the fact that a followed by b differs from b followed by a is no surprise; to expect the two transformations to coincide is to seek symmetry in the wrong place — like judging a dog’s beauty by whether its tail resembles its head. With its two-thousand-year-old roots in China, matrix algebra has secured a permanent place in mathematics, and it passes the beauty test with flying colors. In fact, matrices are commonplace in number theory, the branch of pure mathematics Hardy loved most.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confining my reply to 150 words required some finesse. Notice for instance that the opening sentence does double duty: it leavens my many words of negative criticism with a few words of praise, and it stresses the importance of the topic, preëmptively1 rebutting editors who might be inclined to dismiss my correction as too arcane to merit publication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I haven’t heard back from the editors, and I don’t expect to. Regardless, Witt’s misunderstanding deserves a more thorough response than 150 words can provide. Let’s see what I can do with 1500 words and a few pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;THE GEOMETRY OF TRANSFORMATIONS&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a static object, matrices are “just” rectangular arrays of numbers, but that doesn’t capture what they’re really about. If I had to express the essence of matrices in a single word, that word would be “transformation”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One example of a transformation is the operation f that takes an image in the plane and flips it from left to right, as if in a vertical mirror.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Another example is the operation g that that takes an image in the plane and reflects it across a diagonal line that goes from lower left to upper right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;The key thing to notice here is that the effect of f followed by g is different from the effect of g followed by f. To see why, write a capital R on one side of a square piece of paper–preferably using a dark marker and/or translucent paper, so that you can still see the R even when the paper has been flipped over–and apply f followed by g; you’ll get the original R rotated by 90 degrees clockwise. But if instead, starting from that original R, you were to apply g followed by f, you’d get the original R rotated by 90 degrees counterclockwise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Same two operations, different outcomes! Symbolically we write g ◦ f ≠ f ◦ g, where g ◦ f means “First do f, then do g” and f ◦ g means “First do g, then f”.2 The symbol ◦ denotes the meta-operation (operation-on-operations) called composition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact that the order in which transformations are applied can affect the outcome shouldn’t surprise you. After all, when you’re composing a salad, if you forget to pour on salad dressing until after you’ve topped the base salad with grated cheese, your guests will have a different dining experience than if you’d remembered to pour on the dressing first. Likewise, when you’re composing a melody, a C-sharp followed by a D is different from a D followed by a C-sharp. And as long as mathematicians used the word “composition” rather than “multiplication”, nobody found it paradoxical that in many contexts, order matters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;THE ALGEBRA OF MATRICES&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we use the usual x, y coordinates in the plane, the geometric operation f can be understood as the numerical operation that sends the pair (x, y) to the pair (−x, y), which we can represented via the 2-by-2 array&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;where more generally the array&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;stands for the transformation that sends the pair (x, y) to the pair (ax+by, cx+dy). This kind of array is called a matrix, and when we want to compose two operations like f and g together, all we have to do is combine the associated matrices under the rule that says that the matrix&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;composed with the matrix&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;equals the matrix&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more about where this formula comes from, see my Mathematical Enchantments essay “What Is A Matrix?”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s nothing special about 2-by-2 matrices; you could compose two 3-by-3 matrices, or even two 1000-by-1000 matrices. Going in the other direction (smaller instead of bigger), if you look at 1-by-1 matrices, the composition of&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;is just&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;so ordinary number-multiplication arises as a special case of matrix composition; turning this around, we can see matrix-composition as a sort of generalized multiplication. So it was natural for mid-19th-century mathematicians to start using words like “multiply” and “product” instead of words like “compose” and “composition”, at roughly the same time they stopped talking about “substitutions” and “tableaux” and started to use the word “matrices”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In importing the centuries-old symbolism for number multiplication into the new science of linear algebra, the 19th century algebraists were saying “Matrices behave kind of like numbers,” with the proviso “except when they don’t”. Witt is right when he says that when A and B are matrices, A times B is not always equal to B times A. Where he’s wrong is in asserting that is a blemish on linear algebra. Many mathematicians regard linear algebra as one of the most elegant sub-disciplines of mathematics ever devised, and it often serves as a role model for the kind of sleekness that a new mathematical discipline should strive to achieve. If you dislike matrix multiplication because AB isn’t always equal to BA, it’s because you haven’t yet learned what matrix multiplication is good for in math, physics, and many other subjects. It’s ironic that Witt invokes the notion of symmetry to disparage matrix multiplication, since matrix theory and an allied discipline called group theory are the tools mathematicians use in fleshing out our intuitive ideas about symmetry that arise in art and science.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So how did an intelligent person like Witt go so far astray?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PROOFS VS CALCULATIONS&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m guessing that part of Witt’s confusion arises from the fact that actually multiplying matrices of numbers to get a matrix of bigger numbers can be very tedious, and tedium is psychologically adjacent to distaste and a perception of ugliness. But the tedium of matrix multiplication is tied up with its symmetry (whose existence Witt mistakenly denies). When you multiply two n-by-n matrices A and B in the straightforward way, you have to compute n2 numbers in the same unvarying fashion, and each of those n2 numbers is the sum of n terms, and each of those n terms is the product of an element of A and an element of B in a simple way. It’s only human to get bored and inattentive and then make mistakes because the process is so repetitive. We tend to think of symmetry and beauty as synonyms, but sometimes excessive symmetry breeds ennui; repetition in excess can be repellent. Picture the Library of Babel and the existential dread the image summons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;G. H. Hardy, whose famous remark Witt quotes, was in the business of proving theorems, and he favored conceptual proofs over calculational ones. If you showed him a proof of a theorem in which the linchpin of your argument was a 5-page verification that a certain matrix product had a particular value, he’d say you didn’t really understand your own theorem; he’d assert that you should find a more conceptual argument and then consign your brute-force proof to the trash. But Hardy’s aversion to brute force was specific to the domain of mathematical proof, which is far removed from math that calculates optimal pricing for annuities or computes the wind-shear on an airplane wing or fine-tunes the weights used by an AI. Furthermore, Hardy’s objection to your proof would focus on the length of the calculation, and not on whether the calculation involved matrices. If you showed him a proof that used 5 turgid pages of pre-19th-century calculation that never mentioned matrices once, he’d still say “Your proof is a piece of temporary mathematics; it convinces the reader that your theorem is true without truly explaining why the theorem is true.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you forced me at gunpoint to multiply two 5-by-5 matrices together, I’d be extremely unhappy, and not just because you were threatening my life; the task would be inherently unpleasant. But the same would be true if you asked me to add together a hundred random two-digit numbers. It’s not that matrix-multiplication or number-addition is ugly; it’s that such repetitive tasks are the diametrical opposite of the kind of conceptual thinking that Hardy loved and I love too. Any kind of mathematical content can be made stultifying when it’s stripped of its meaning and reduced to mindless toil. But that casts no shade on the underlying concepts. When we outsource number-addition or matrix-multiplication to a computer, we rightfully delegate the soul-crushing part of our labor to circuitry that has no soul. If we could peer into the innards of the circuits doing all those matrix multiplications, we would indeed see a nightmarish, Borgesian landscape, with billions of nails being hammered into billions of boards, over and over again. But please don’t confuse that labor with mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Join the discussion of this essay over at Hacker News!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This essay is related to chapter 10 (“Out of the Womb”) of a book I’m writing, tentatively called “What Can Numbers Be?: The Further, Stranger Adventures of Plus and Times”. If you think this sounds interesting and want to help me make the book better, check out http://jamespropp.org/readers.pdf. And as always, feel free to submit comments on this essay at the Mathematical Enchantments WordPress site!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ENDNOTES&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#1. Note the New Yorker-ish diaresis in “preëmptively”: as long as I’m being critical, I might as well be diacritical.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#2. I know this convention may seem backwards on first acquaintance, but this is how ◦ is defined. Blame the people who first started writing things like “log x” and “cos x“, with the x coming after the name of the operation. This led to the notation f(x) for the result of applying the function f to the number x. Then the symbol for the result of applying g to the result of applying f to x is g(f(x)); even though f is performed first, “f” appears to the right of “g“. From there, it became natural to write the function that sends x to g(f(x)) as “g ◦ f“.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46009660</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 22:17:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Personal blogs are back, should niche blogs be next?</title><link>https://disassociated.com/personal-blogs-back-niche-blogs-next/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3b8090076bc54a9f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Personal blogs are back, should niche blogs be next?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;20 November 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When it comes to blogging there are few rules. Write content that is somehow meaningful might be one of them though. I think it’s down to the individual to determine what constitutes meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the hey-day, the so-called golden age of blogging, there were plenty of people prepared to offer definitions of meaningful, and how to write accordingly. It was natural. The web was once awash with all sorts of blogs. Likewise people who wanted to show others how to blog “successfully”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, the definition of successful resided with the individual, but it was obvious this involved monetary return for some people. And why not. If you’re going to invest time and energy in creating a resource that is useful to other people, why shouldn’t you earn money, make a living even, from it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of these people blogging about blogging was Melbourne based Australian writer and author Darren Rowse, who launched his blogging resource Problogger in 2004. Without going into detail, because you can look it up for yourself, Rowse, as one of the earlier bloggers about blogging, did, and still does presumably, rather well for himself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rowse’s writing, and that of his contributors, attracted numerous readers keen to learn what they could about blogging, and the potential to make money from it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Problogger is what’s called a niche blog. As a blog about blogging, it has a reasonably singular focus. Some people considered this niche principle to be a core tenet of blogging. There was this idea, in the earlier days of blogging, which possibly still persists, that blogs would do better if they had a speciality. Not only were search engines said to be in favour the approach, but the author of a speciality, or niche blog, would generally be considered to be an expert, of some sort, in their field.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A master of one trade, rather than the proverbial jack of all trades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless, the world was once full of blogs on every topic imaginable. It was a great time to be alive. If you wanted to learn about something in particular, there was a blog for you. Some publications featured quality content, others required a little fact checking, while some were definitely to be taken with a pinch of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But niche blogging was never a format that suited everyone. There are people who did, still do, well, writing about a range, sometimes a wide range, of topics. Kottke is one of the better known blogs that does not have a specific speciality. Here, the publication itself is the speciality. To repeat what I wrote in the first sentence of this article: the rules of blogging are few.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the facets of blogging covered at Problogger, and numerous other similar websites, usually only applied to blogs of a commercial nature. That’s not to say one or two personal bloggers might have looked at the tips posted there for increasing their audience, or improving their writing though. But in my view, personal bloggers were not, are not, part of Problogger’s target audience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s been a long time since I last wrote about Problogger, let alone visited the website, maybe fifteen plus years, but a recent mention of it by Kev Quick, via ldstephens, caught my eye. But I don’t believe Rowse is being critical, in any way, of personal bloggers because they do not adhere to a niche or speciality publishing format. That’s not what Problogger, or Rowse, is about.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this started me thinking, and writing another of my long posts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In an age where social media, and influencers, have usurped blogs and their A-List authors, in the jostle for supremacy, it has to be wondered what role websites like Problogger still have. Only a handful of blogs generate liveable incomes today. Despite the doom and gloom though, the form has not completely died off. A backlash against social media, and a growing IndieWeb/SmallWeb community, has precipitated a revival in personal websites.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a largely non-commercial movement. Of course, there’s nothing wrong with personal websites. Many of us started out with them in the early days of the web. But the web was not only intended for personal journals. It was a vehicle for sharing all manner of information. The web could also empower individuals, and partnerships, to not only set up shop online, be that blogs, or quite literally shops, but potentially make a living at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But with the revival of personal blogs well underway, I think it’s time to bring niche blogs back into the fold. I’m talking about well written, quality, topic focused resources. This is material fast vanishing from the web, leaving ever diminishing options to source useful and accurate information. What are the alternatives? The misinformation morass that is social media? Being served AI generated summaries in response to search engine queries? A web choke full of AI slop?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, I’m not advocating for a return of niche blogs plastered with adverts, and popup boxes urging visitors to subscribe to say a newsletter, before they’ve even had a chance to blink at what they came to read.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m talking about work produced by independent writers, with an interest in their subject matter, who are not backed by large media organisations, or private equity. This is bringing back reliable sources of information, that also recompenses the content writers in some way. Hopefully we’ve learned a few lessons about monetisation since the earlier wave of niche blogging. We know it is possible to generate revenue without compromising the reader experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A resurgence in personal blogging is the first step in rebuilding a vibrant, thriving, web, of if you like, blogosphere. Now the focus needs to be on restoring the flow of accessible and trusted information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RELATED CONTENT&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;blogs, history, IndieWeb, self publishing, SmallWeb, technology, trends&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46009894</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 22:40:28 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>