<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 15:41:29 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Let's put Tailscale on a jailbroken Kindle</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/tailscale-jailbroken-kindle</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="77000a1e01fd3fdc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s a rite of passage to run Tailscale on weird devices.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So writes Mitanshu Sukhwani on his blog, detailing the steps for getting Tailscale onto a jailbroken Kindle. Getting there, and seeing a kindle entry with a satisfying green dot in your Tailscale admin console, takes some doing. But take the trip, and you’ll end up with an e-reader that can run some neat unofficial apps, and is more open to third-party and DRM-free ebooks. And with a Tailscale connection, it’s easier to connect to files and a command line on your underpowered little Linux slab.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“For me, it's the freedom of being able to do anything with the device I own,” Sukhwani writes by email. “What I can do with the freedom is a different story.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What is a jailbroken Kindle, exactly?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jailbreaking refers to removing the software restrictions on a device put there by its maker. Getting around these restrictions, typically by gaining “root” or administrative access, allows for accessing operating system internals, running unapproved software, and generally doing more things than a manufacturer intended. With the Kindle, you still get the standard Kindle reading experience, including Amazon's store and the ability to send the Kindle books from apps like Libby. You just add many more options, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The term gained purchase after the first iPhone’s debut in mid-2007; since then, nearly every device with a restricted environment has gained its own jailbreaking scene, including Kindles (debuting five months after the iPhone).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kindle jailbreaks come along every so often. Right now, an unlocking scheme based on Amazon’s own lockscreen ads, “AdBreak,” is available for all but the most up-to-date Kindles (earlier than firmware version 5.18.5.0.2). I know this because I wrote this paragraph and the next on my 11th-generation Kindle, using the open-source Textadept editor, a Bluetooth keyboard, and Tailscale to move this draft file around.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One paragraph doesn’t seem that impressive until you consider that on a standard Kindle, you cannot do any of that. Transferring files by SSH, or Taildrop, is certainly not allowed. And that’s in addition to other upgrades you can get by jailbreaking a Kindle, including the feature-rich, customizable e-reader KOReader, and lots of little apps available in repositories like KindleForge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your Kindle has been connected to Wi-Fi all this time (as of early December 2025), it may have automatically updated itself and no longer be ready for jailbreaking. If you think it still has a chance, immediately put it into airplane mode and follow along.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Obligatory notice here: You’re running a risk of bricking your device (having it become unresponsive and unrecoverable) and voiding your warranty when you do this. That having been noted, let's dig further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Tailscale adds to a jailbroken Kindle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailscale isn’t necessary on a jailbroken Kindle, but it really helps. Here are some of the ways Tailscale makes messing about with an opened-up Kindle more fun:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A persistent IP address (100.xx.yyy.zzz), just like any other Tailscale device, instead of having to remember yet another 192.168.random.number&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Easier SSH access with magicDNS: ssh root@kindle and you’re in&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Taildrop for sending files to whatever Kindle directory you want&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Setting up a self-hosted Calibre Web library with Tailscale, then securely grabbing books from it anywhere with KOReader.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key to the Kindle-plus-Tailscale experience is an easier way (SSH and Taildrop) to get epub, mobi, and other e-book and document formats into the /documents folder, ready for your KOReader sessions. Tailscale also helps with setting up some of the key jailbreak apps, saving you from plugging and unplugging the Kindle into a computer via USB cord (and then finding a second USB cord, because the first one never works, for some reason).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Getting your Kindle ready&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What follows is by no means a comprehensive guide to jailbreaking and accessing your Kindle. You will want to read the documentation for each tool and app closely. Pay particular attention to which Kindle you have, which version number of the Kindle firmware it’s running, and how much space you have left on that device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first step is to check your Kindle’s version number (Settings &amp;gt; Device info) and see if there is a jailbreak method available for it. The Kindle Modding Wiki is the jailbreaking community’s go-to resource. As of this writing, there is a “WinterBreak” process available for Kindles running firmware below 15.18.1, and AdBreak is available for firmwares from 15.18.1 through 5.18.5.0.1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your Kindle’s version number fits one of those ranges, put it in Airplane mode and move on. If not, you’re going to have to wait until the next jailbreak method comes along.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The actual jailbreaking part&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before you dive in, have a computer (PC, Mac, or Linux) and USB cable that works with your Kindle handy. Have your Kindle on reliable Wi-Fi, like your home network—but don’t take your Kindle off airplane mode if you’ve been keeping it that way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Follow these steps to jailbreak your Kindle. The techniques are different, but you may need to do some other tasks, like enable advertisements, or fill your Kindle with junk files to prevent automatic updates midway through the process.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Install a hotfix and disable over-the-air updates so that you can keep your Kindle on Wi-Fi and not have its jailbreak undone&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Install the Kindle Unified Application Launcher (KUAL) and MRPI (MobileRead Package Installer). KUAL is vital to installing most jailbroken apps, including Tailscale.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You will almost certainly want to install KOReader, too.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those bits above are standard jailbreaking procedures. If you want Tailscale on your Kindle, you’ll go a bit further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Adding Tailscale to a jailbroken Kindle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make sure you have KUAL and MRPI installed and working. Next up: install this “simple” version of USBNetworking for Kindle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before you go further, you’ll want to choose between Mitanshu’s “standard” Tailscale repository, or the fork of it that enables Taildrop. I recommend the Taildrop-enabled fork; if it goes wrong, or stops being updated, it’s fairly easy (relative to doing this kind of project) to wipe it and go back to Mitanshu’s “vanilla” version.Either way, you’ll want to get USB access to your Kindle for this next part. If you toggled on USBNetworking to try it out, toggle it off; you can’t get USB access while it’s running, as its name somewhat implies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Download the Tailscale/KUAL repository of your choice using git clone or download a ZIP from the Code button on GitHub&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Head to Tailscale’s page of static Linux binaries and grab the latest arm (not arm64) release&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Copy the tailscale and tailscaled binaries from the Tailscale download and place them into the /extensions/tailscale/bin directory of the KUAL/Kindle repository you’ll be copying over&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Head to your Tailscale admin console and generate an authentication key. Name it something like kindle; you’ll want to enable the “Reusable” and “Pre-approved” options. Copy the key that is generated.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Open the file extensions/tailscale/config/auth_key.txt for editing while it is on your (non-Kindle) computer. Paste in the key text you generated.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you’re using the variant with Taildrop, you can set a custom directory in which to deliver Taildrop files by editing extensions/tailscale/config/taildrop_dir.txt; setting /mnt/us/documents makes sense if you’re mostly sending yourself things to read in KOReader.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Head into the extensions folder on your computer and copy the tailscale folder you’ve set up into the extensions folder on your Kindle.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With all that done, open up KUAL on your Kindle. Go into USBNetLite and click USBNetwork Status to ensure it is enabled (tap the Toggle button if not). Go back (with the “/” button at the bottom), tap Tailscale, and first tap Start Tailscaled (note the “d” at the end). Wait about 10 seconds to give the Tailscaled daemon time to start, then tap Start Tailscale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If everything is settled, you should be able to see your Kindle as connected on your Tailscale admin console. Once you’ve finished smiling to yourself, click the three dots on the right-hand side of the Kindle row and select “Disable key expiry.” In most situations, you’re better off not having to patch a new key value into a Kindle text file every few months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Enjoy your (slightly) less wonky Kindle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Tailscale installed, it’s easier to get into your Kindle via SSH for file management and installing and configuring other apps. Getting a Bluetooth keyboard to work via the Kindle’s quirky command-line Bluetooth interface would not have been fun using a touchscreen keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because the Kindle is on your tailnet, it can access anything else you have hosted there. Kindles set up this way can use tools like the Shortcut Browser to become dashboards for Home Assistant, or access a self-hosted Calibre-Web e-book server (with some tweaking).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having Taildrop handy, and having it drop files directly into the documents folder, is probably my favorite upgrade. I was on my phone, at a train station, when I came across Annalee Newitz’s Automatic Noodle at Bookshop.org. I bought it on my phone and downloaded the DRM-free epub file. When I got home, I opened and unlocked my Kindle, sent the epub to the Kindle via Taildrop, then tapped Receive Taildrop Files in the Tailscale app inside KUAL. Epubs, PDFs, comic book archives, DjVu files—they’re all ready to be dropped in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’ve gotten Tailscale to run on weird (or just uncommon) devices, we’d more than love to hear about it. Let us know on Reddit, Discord, Bluesky, Mastodon, or LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46194337</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 16:34:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Launch HN: Nia (YC S25) – Give better context to coding agents</title><link>https://www.trynia.ai/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46194828</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 17:10:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jepsen: NATS 2.12.1</title><link>https://jepsen.io/analyses/nats-2.12.1</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2790905544351bb0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;1 Background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NATS is a popular streaming system. Producers publish messages to streams, and consumers subscribe to those streams, fetching messages from them. Regular NATS streams are allowed to drop messages. However, NATS has a subsystem called JetStream, which uses the Raft consensus algorithm to replicate data among nodes. JetStream promises âat least onceâ delivery: messages may be duplicated, but acknowledged messages1 should not be lost.2 Moreover, JetStream streams are totally ordered logs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JetStream is intended to âself-heal and always be availableâ. The documentation also states that âthe formal consistency model of NATS JetStream is Linearizableâ. At most one of these claims can be true: the CAP theorem tells us that Linearizable systems can not be totally available.3 In practice, they tend to be available so long as a majority of nodes are non-faulty and communicating. If, say, a single node loses network connectivity, operations must fail on that node. If three out of five nodes crash, all operations must fail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, a later section of the JetStream docs acknowledges this fact, saying that streams with three replicas can tolerate the loss of one server, and those with five can tolerate the simultaneous loss of two.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Replicas=5 - Can tolerate simultaneous loss of two servers servicing the stream. Mitigates risk at the expense of performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When does NATS guarantee a message will be durable? The JetStream developer docs say that once a JetStream clientâs &lt;code&gt;publish&lt;/code&gt; request is acknowledged by the server, that message has âbeen successfully persistedâ. The clustering configuration documentation says:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In order to ensure data consistency across complete restarts, a quorum of servers is required. A quorum is Â½ cluster size + 1. This is the minimum number of nodes to ensure at least one node has the most recent data and state after a catastrophic failure. So for a cluster size of 3, youâll need at least two JetStream enabled NATS servers available to store new messages. For a cluster size of 5, youâll need at least 3 NATS servers, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With these guarantees in mind, we set out to test NATS JetStream behavior under a variety of simulated faults.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;2 Test Design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We designed a test suite for NATS JetStream using the Jepsen testing library, using JNATS (the official Java client) at version 2.24.0. Most of our tests ran in Debian 12 containers under LXC; some tests ran in Antithesis, using the official NATS Docker images. In all our tests we created a single JetStream stream with a target replication factor of five. Per NATSâ recommendations, our clusters generally contained three or five nodes. We tested a variety of versions, but the bulk of this work focused on NATS 2.12.1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The test harness injected a variety of faults, including process pauses, crashes, network partitions, and packet loss, as well as single-bit errors and truncation of data files. We limited file corruption to a minority of nodes. We also simulated power failureâa crash with partial amnesiaâusing the LazyFS filesystem. LazyFS allows Jepsen to drop any writes which have not yet been flushed using a call to (e.g.) &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our tests did not measure Linearizability or Serializability. Instead we ran several producer processes, each bound to a single NATS client, which published globally unique values to a single JetStream stream. Each message included the process number and a sequence number within that process, so message &lt;code&gt;4-0&lt;/code&gt; denoted the first &lt;code&gt;publish&lt;/code&gt; attempted by process &lt;code&gt;4&lt;/code&gt;, message &lt;code&gt;4-1&lt;/code&gt; denoted the second, and so on. At the end of the test we ensured all nodes were running, resolved any network partitions or other faults, subscribed to the stream, and attempted to read all acknowledged messages from the the stream. Each reader called &lt;code&gt;fetch&lt;/code&gt; until it had observed (at least) the last acknowledged message published by each process, or timed out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We measured JetStreamâs at-least-once semantics based on the union of all published and read messages. We considered a message OK if it was attempted and read. Messages were lost if they were acknowledged as published, but never read by any process. We divided lost messages into three epochs, based on the first and last OK messages written by the same process.4 We called those lost before the first OK message the lost-prefix, those lost after all the last OK message the lost-postfix, and all others the lost-middle. This helped to distinguish between lagging readers and true data loss.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to verifying each acknowledged message was delivered to at least one consumer across all nodes, we also checked the set of messages read by all consumers connected to a specific node. We called it divergence, or split-brain, when an acknowledged message was missing from some nodes but not others.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;3 Results&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We begin with a belated note on total data loss in version 2.10.22, then continue with four findings related to data loss and replica divergence in version 2.12.1: two with file corruption, and two with power failures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3.1 Total Data Loss on Crash in 2.10.22 (#6888)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before discussing version 2.12.1, we present a long-overdue finding from earlier work. In versions 2.10.20 through 2.10.22 (released 2024-10-17), we found that process crashes alone could cause the total loss of a JetStream stream and all its associated data. Subscription requests would return &lt;code&gt;"No matching streams for subject"&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;getStreamNames()&lt;/code&gt; would return an empty list. These conditions would persist for hours: in this test run, we waited 10,000 seconds for the cluster to recover, but the stream never returned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jepsen reported this issue to NATS as #6888, but it appears that NATS had already identified several potential causes for this problem and resolved them. In #5946, a cluster-wide crash occurring shortly after a stream was created could cause the loss of the stream. A new leader would be elected with a snapshot which preceded the creation of the stream, and replicate that empty snapshot to followers, causing everyone to delete their copy of the stream. In #5700, tests running in Antithesis found that out-of-order delivery of snapshot messages could cause streams to be deleted and re-created as well. In #6061, process crashes could cause nodes to delete their local Raft state. All of these fixes were released as a part of 2.10.23, and we no longer observed the problem in that version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3.2 Lost Writes With &lt;code&gt;.blk&lt;/code&gt; File Corruption (#7549)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NATS has several checksum mechanisms meant to detect data corruption in on-disk files. However, we found that single-bit errors or truncation of JetStreamâs &lt;code&gt;.blk&lt;/code&gt; files could cause the cluster to lose large windows of writes. This occurred even when file corruption was limited to just one or two nodes out of five. For instance, file corruption in this test run caused NATS to lose 679,153 acknowledged writes out of 1,367,069 total, including 201,286 which were missing even though later values written by the same process were later read.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In some cases, file corruption caused the quiet loss of just a single message. In others, writes vanished in large blocks. Even worse, bitflips could cause split-brain, where different nodes returned different sets of messages. In this test, NATS acknowledged a total of 1,479,661 messages. However, single-bit errors in &lt;code&gt;.blk&lt;/code&gt; files on nodes &lt;code&gt;n1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;n3&lt;/code&gt; caused nodes &lt;code&gt;n1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;n3&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;n5&lt;/code&gt; to lose up to 78% of those acknowledged messages. Node &lt;code&gt;n1&lt;/code&gt; lost 852,413 messages, and nodes &lt;code&gt;n3&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;n5&lt;/code&gt; lost 1,167,167 messages, despite &lt;code&gt;n5&lt;/code&gt;âs data files remaining intact. Messages were lost in prefix, middle, and postfix: the stream, at least on those three nodes, resembled Swiss cheese.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NATS is investigating this issue (#7549).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3.3 Total Data Loss With Snapshot File Corruption (#7556)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we truncated or introduced single-bit errors into JetStreamâs snapshot files in &lt;code&gt;data/jetstream/$SYS/_js_/&lt;/code&gt;, we found that nodes would sometimes decide that a stream had been orphaned, and delete all its data files. This happened even when only a minority of nodes in the cluster experienced file corruption. The cluster would never recover quorum, and the stream remained unavailable for the remainder of the test.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this test run, we introduced single-bit errors into snapshots on nodes &lt;code&gt;n3&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;n5&lt;/code&gt;. During the final recovery period, node &lt;code&gt;n3&lt;/code&gt; became the metadata leader for the cluster and decided to clean up &lt;code&gt;jepsen-stream&lt;/code&gt;, which stored all the testâs messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;[1010859] 2025/11/15 20:27:02.947432 [INF]
Self is new JetStream cluster metadata leader
[1010859] 2025/11/15 20:27:14.996174 [WRN]
Detected orphaned stream 'jepsen &amp;gt;
jepsen-stream', will cleanup&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nodes &lt;code&gt;n3&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;n5&lt;/code&gt; then deleted all files in the stream directory. This might seem defensibleâafter all, some of &lt;code&gt;n3&lt;/code&gt;âs data files were corrupted. However, &lt;code&gt;n3&lt;/code&gt; managed to become the leader of the cluster despite its corrupt state! In general, leader-based consensus systems must be careful to ensure that any node which becomes a leader is aware of majority committed state. Becoming a leader, then opting to delete a stream full of committed data, is particularly troubling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although nodes &lt;code&gt;n1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;n2&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;n4&lt;/code&gt; retained their data files, &lt;code&gt;n1&lt;/code&gt; struggled to apply snapshots; &lt;code&gt;n4&lt;/code&gt; declared that &lt;code&gt;jepsen-stream&lt;/code&gt; had no quorum and stalled. Every attempt to subscribe to the stream threw &lt;code&gt;[SUB-90007] No matching streams for subject&lt;/code&gt;. Jepsen filed issue #7556 for this, and the NATS team is looking into it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3.4 Lazy &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;/code&gt; by Default (#7564)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NATS JetStream promises that once a &lt;code&gt;publish&lt;/code&gt; call has been acknowledged, it is âsuccessfully persistedâ. This is not exactly true. By default, NATS calls &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;/code&gt; to flush data to disk only once every two minutes, but acknowledges messages immediately. Consequently, recently acknowledged writes are generally not persisted, and could be lost to coordinated power failure, kernel crashes, etc. For instance, simulated power failures in this test run caused NATS to lose roughly thirty seconds of writes: 131,418 out of 930,005 messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because the default flush interval is quite large, even killing a single node at a time is sufficient to cause data loss, so long as nodes fail within a few seconds of each other. In this run, a series of single-node failures in the first two minutes of the test caused NATS to delete the entire stream, along with all of its messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are only two mentions of this behavior in the NATS documentation. The first is in the 2.10 release notes. The second, buried in the configuration docs, describes the &lt;code&gt;sync_interval&lt;/code&gt; option:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Change the default fsync/sync interval for page cache in the filestore. By default JetStream relies on stream replication in the cluster to guarantee data is available after an OS crash. If you run JetStream without replication or with a replication of just 2 you may want to shorten the fsync/sync interval. You can force an fsync after each messsage [sic] with&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;always&lt;/code&gt;, this will slow down the throughput to a few hundred msg/s.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consensus protocols often require that nodes sync to disk before acknowledging an operation. For example, the famous 2007 paper Paxos Made Live remarks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note that all writes have to be flushed to disk immediately before the system can proceed any further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Raft thesis on which NATS is based is clear that nodes must âflush [new log entries] to their disksâ before acknowledging. Section 11.7.3 discusses the possibility of instead writing data to disk asynchronously, and concludes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The trade-off is that data loss is possible in catastrophic events. For example, if a majority of the cluster were to restart simultaneously, the cluster would have potentially lost entries and would not be able to form a new view. Raft could be extended in similar ways to support disk-less operation, but we think the risk of availability or data loss usually outweighs the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For similar reasons, replicated systems like MongoDB, etcd, TigerBeetle, Zookeeper, Redpanda, and TiDB sync data to disk before acknowledging an operation as committed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, some systems do choose to &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;/code&gt; asynchronously. YugabyteDBâs default is to acknowledge un-fsynced writes. Liskov and Cowlingâs Viewstamped Replication Revisited assumes replicas are âhighly unlikely to fail at the same timeââbut acknowledges that if they were to fail simultaneously, state would be lost. Apache Kafka makes a similar choice, but claims that it is not vulnerable to coordinated failure because Kafka âdoesnât store unflushed data in its own memory, but in the page cacheâ. This offers resilience to the Kafka process itself crashing, but not power failure.5 Jepsen remains skeptical of this approach: as Alagappan et al. argue, extensive literature on correlated failures suggests we should continue to take this risk seriously. Heat waves, grid instability, fires, lightning, tornadoes, and floods are not necessarily constrained to a single availability zone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jepsen suggests that NATS change the default value for &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;always&lt;/code&gt;, rather than every two minutes. Alternatively, NATS documentation should prominently disclose that JetStream may lose data when nodes experience correlated power failure, or fail in rapid succession (#7564).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3.5 A Single OS Crash Can Cause Split-Brain (#7567)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In response to #7564, NATS engineers noted that most production deployments run with each node in a separate availability zone, which reduces the probability of correlated failure. This raises the question: how many power failures (or hardware faults, kernel crashes, etc.) are required to cause data loss? Perhaps surprisingly, in an asynchronous network the answer is âjust oneâ.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To understand why, consider that a system which remains partly available when a minority of nodes are unavailable must allow states in which a committed operation is presentâsolely in memoryâon a bare majority of nodes. For example, in a leader-follower protocol the leader of a three-node cluster may consider a write committed as soon as a single follower has responded: it has two acknowledgements, counting itself. Under normal operation there will usually be some window of committed operations in this state.6.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now imagine that one of those two nodes loses power and restarts. Because the write was stored only in memory, rather than on disk, the acknowledged write is no longer present on that node. There now exist two out of three nodes which do not have the write. Since the system is fault-tolerant, these two nodes must be able to form a quorum and continue processing requestsâcreating new states of the system in which the acknowledged write never happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strictly speaking, this fault requires nothing more than a single power failure (or HW fault, kernel crash, etc.) and an asynchronous networkâone which is allowed to deliver messages arbitrarily late. Whether it occurs in practice depends on the specific messages exchanged by the replication system, which node fails, how long it remains offline, the order of message delivery, and so on. However, one can reliably induce data loss by killing, pausing, or partitioning away a minority of nodes before and after a simulated OS crash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, process pauses and a single simulated power failure in this test run caused JetStream to lose acknowledged writes for windows roughly on par with &lt;code&gt;sync_interval&lt;/code&gt;. Stranger still, the cluster entered a persistent split-brain which continued after all nodes were restarted and the network healed. Consider these two plots of lost writes, based on final reads performed against nodes &lt;code&gt;n1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;n5&lt;/code&gt; respectively:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consumers talking to &lt;code&gt;n1&lt;/code&gt; failed to observe a short window of acknowledged messages written around 42 seconds into the test. Meanwhile, consumers talking to &lt;code&gt;n5&lt;/code&gt; would miss acknowledged messages written around 58 seconds. Both windows of write loss were on the order of our choice of &lt;code&gt;sync_interval = 10s&lt;/code&gt; for this run. In repeated testing, we found that any node in the cluster could lose committed writes, including the node which failed, those which received writes before the failure, and those which received writes afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact that a single power failure can cause data loss is not new. In 2023, RedPanda wrote a detailed blog post showing that Kafkaâs default lazy &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;/code&gt; could lead to data loss under exactly this scenario. However, it is especially concerning that this scenario led to persistent replica divergence, not just data loss! We filed #7567 for this issue, and the NATS team is investigating.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;â&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Summary&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Event Required&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Fixed in&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;#6888&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Stream deleted on crash in 2.10.22&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Crashes&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2.10.23&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;#7549&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Lost writes due to &lt;code&gt;.blk&lt;/code&gt; file corruption&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Minority truncation or bitflip&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unresolved&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;#7556&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Stream deleted due to snapshot file corruption&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Minority truncation or bitflip&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unresolved&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;#7564&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Write loss due to lazy &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;/code&gt; policy&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Coordinated OS crash&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Documented&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;#7567&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Write loss and split-brain&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Single OS crash and pause&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unresolved&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;4 Discussion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In NATS 2.10.22, process crashes could cause JetStream to forget a stream ever existed (#6888). This issue was identified independently by NATS and resolved in version 2.10.23, released on 2024-12-10. We did not observe data loss with simple network partitions, process pauses, or crashes in version 2.12.1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, we found that in NATS 2.12.1, file corruption and simulated OS crashes could both lead to data loss and persistent split-brain. Bitflips or truncation of either &lt;code&gt;.blk&lt;/code&gt; (#7549) or snapshot (#7556) files, even on a minority of nodes, could cause the loss of single messages, large windows of messages, or even cause some nodes to delete their stream data altogether. Messages could be missing on some nodes and present on others. NATS has multiple checksum mechanisms designed to limit the impact of file corruption; more thorough testing of these mechanisms seems warranted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, NATS only flushes data to disk every two minutes, but acknowledges operations immediately. This approach can lead to the loss of committed writes when several nodes experience a power failure, kernel crash, or hardware fault concurrentlyâor in rapid succession (#7564). In addition, a single OS crash combined with process crashes, pauses, or network partitions can cause the loss of acknowledged messages and persistent split-brain (#7567). We recommended NATS change the default value of &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;always&lt;/code&gt;, or clearly document these hazards. NATS has added new documentation to the JetStream Concepts page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This documentation also describes several goals for JetStream, including that â[t]he system must self-heal and always be available.â This is impossible: the CAP theorem states that Linearizable systems cannot be totally available in an asynchronous network. In our three and five-node clusters JetStream generally behaved like a typical Raft implementation. Operations proceeded on a majority of connected nodes but isolated nodes were unavailable, and if a majority failed, the system as a whole became unavailable. Jepsen suggests clarifying this part of the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As always, Jepsen takes an experimental approach to safety verification: we can prove the presence of bugs, but not their absence. While we make extensive efforts to find problems, we cannot prove correctness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;4.1 LazyFS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work demonstrates that systems which do not exhibit data loss under normal process crashes (e.g.Â &lt;code&gt;kill -9 &amp;lt;PID&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) may lose data or enter split-brain under simulated OS-level crashes. Our tests relied heavily on LazyFS, a project of INESC TEC at the University of Porto.7 After killing a process, we used LazyFS to simulate the effects of a power failure by dropping writes to the filesystem which had not yet been &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;/code&gt;ed to disk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While this work focused purely on the loss of unflushed writes, LazyFS can also simulate linear and non-linear torn writes: an anomaly where a storage device persists part, but not all, of written data thanks to (e.g.) IO cache reordering. Our 2024 paper When Amnesia Strikes discusses these faults in more detail, highlighting bugs in PostgreSQL, Redis, ZooKeeper, etcd, LevelDB, PebblesDB, and the Lightning Network.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;4.2 Future Work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We designed only a simple workload for NATS which checked for lost records either across all consumers, or across all consumers bound to a single node. We did not check whether single consumers could miss messages, or the order in which they were delivered. We did not check NATSâ claims of Linearizable writes or Serializable operations in general. We also did not evaluate JetStreamâs âexactly-once semanticsâ. All of these could prove fruitful avenues for further tests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In some tests, we added and removed nodes from the cluster. This work generated some preliminary results. However, the NATS documentation for membership changes was incorrect and incomplete: it gave the wrong command for removing peers, and there appears to be an undocumented but mandatory health check step for newly-added nodes. As of this writing, Jepsen is unsure how to safely add or remove nodes to a NATS cluster. Consequently, we leave membership changes for future research.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our thanks to INESC TEC and everyone on the LazyFS team, including Maria Ramos, JoÃ£o Azevedo, JosÃ© Pereira, TÃ¢nia Esteves, Ricardo Macedo, and JoÃ£o Paulo. Jepsen is also grateful to Silvia Botros, Kellan Elliott-McCrea, Carla Geisser, Coda Hale, and Marc Hedlund for their expertise regarding datacenter power failures, correlated kernel panics, disk faults, and other causes of OS-level crashes. Finally, our thanks to Irene Kannyo for her editorial support. This research was performed independently by Jepsen, without compensation, and conducted in accordance with the Jepsen ethics policy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Throughout this report we use âacknowledged messageâ to describe a message whose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;publish&lt;/code&gt;request was acknowledged successfully by some server. NATS also offers a separate notion of acknowledgement, which indicates when a message has been processed and need not be delivered again.â©ï¸&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;JetStream also promises âexactly once semanticsâ in some scenarios. We leave this for later research.â©ï¸&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The CAP theoremâs definition of âavailabilityâ requires that all operations on non-faulty nodes must succeed.â©ï¸&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is overly conservative: in a system with Linearizable writes, we should never observe a lost message which was acknowledged prior to the invocation of the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;publish&lt;/code&gt;call for an OK message, regardless of process. However, early testing with NATS suggested that it might be better to test a weaker property, and come to stronger conclusions about data loss.â©ï¸&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Redpanda argues that the situation is actually worse: a single power failure, combined with network partitions or process pauses, can cause Kafka to lose committed data.â©ï¸&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Some protocols, like Raft, consider an operation committed as soon as it is acknowledged by a majority of nodes. These systems offer lower latencies, but at any given time there are likely a few committed operations which are missing from a minority of nodes due to normal network latency. Other systems, like Kafka, require acknowledgement from all âonlineâ nodes before considering an operation committed. These systems offer worse latency in healthy clusters (since they must wait for the slowest node) but in exchange, committed operations can only be missing from some node when the fault detector decides that node is no longer online (e.g.Â due to elevated latency).â©ï¸&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Jepsen contributed some funds, testing, and integration assistance to LazyFS, but most credit belongs to the LazyFS team.â©ï¸&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46196105</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:51:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Has the cost of building software dropped 90%?</title><link>https://martinalderson.com/posts/has-the-cost-of-software-just-dropped-90-percent/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a35880536496fbfd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Has the cost of building software just dropped 90%?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've been building software professionally for nearly 20 years. I've been through a lot of changes - the 'birth' of SaaS, the mass shift towards mobile apps, the outrageous hype around blockchain, and the perennial promise that low-code would make developers obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The economics have changed dramatically now with agentic coding, and it is going to totally transform the software development industry (and the wider economy). 2026 is going to catch a lot of people off guard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my previous post I delved into why I think evals are missing some of the big leaps, but thinking this over since then (and recent experience) has made me confident we're in the early stages of a once-in-a-generation shift.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The cost of shipping&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started developing just around the time open source started to really explode - but it was clear this was one of the first big shifts in cost of building custom software. I can remember eye watering costs for SQL Server or Oracle - and as such started out really with MySQL, which did allow you to build custom networked applications without incurring five or six figures of annual database licensing costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since then we've had cloud (which I would debate is a cost saving at all, but let's be generous and assume it has some initial capex savings) and lately what I feel has been the era of complexity. Software engineering has got - in my opinion, often needlessly - complicated, with people rushing to very labour intensive patterns such as TDD, microservices, super complex React frontends and Kubernetes. I definitely don't think we've seen much of a cost decrease in the past few years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI Agents however in my mind massively reduce the labour cost of developing software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;So where do the 90% savings actually come from?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the start of 2025 I was incredibly sceptical of a lot of the AI coding tools - and a lot of them I still am. Many of the platforms felt like glorified low code tooling (Loveable, Bolt, etc), or VS Code forks with some semi-useful (but often annoying) autocomplete improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take an average project for an internal tool in a company. Let's assume the data modelling is already done to some degree, and you need to implement a web app to manage widgets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Previously, you'd have a small team of people working on setting up CI/CD, building out data access patterns and building out the core services. Then usually a whole load of CRUD-style pages and maybe some dashboards and graphs for the user to make. Finally you'd (hopefully) add some automated unit/integration/e2e tests to make sure it was fairly solid and ship it, maybe a month later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that's just the direct labour. Every person on the project adds coordination overhead. Standups, ticket management, code reviews, handoffs between frontend and backend, waiting for someone to unblock you. The actual coding is often a fraction of where the time goes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nearly all of this can be done in a few hours with an agentic coding CLI. I've had Claude Code write an entire unit/integration test suite in a few hours (300+ tests) for a fairly complex internal tool. This would take me, or many developers I know and respect, days to write by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The agentic coding tools have got extremely good at converting business logic specifications into pretty well written APIs and services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A project that would have taken a month now takes a week. The thinking time is roughly the same - the implementation time collapsed. And with smaller teams, you get the inverse of Brooks's Law: instead of communication overhead scaling with headcount, it disappears. A handful of people can suddenly achieve an order of magnitude more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Latent demand&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the face of it, this seems like incredibly bad news for the software development industry - but economics tells us otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jevons Paradox says that when something becomes cheaper to produce, we don't just do the same amount for less money. Take electric lighting for example; while sales of candles and gas lamps fell, overall far more artificial light was generated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we apply this to software engineering, think of supply and demand. There is so much latent demand for software. I'm sure every organisation has hundreds if not thousands of Excel sheets tracking important business processes that would be far better off as a SaaS app. Let's say they get a quote from an agency to build one into an app for $50k - only essential ones meet the grade. At $5k (for a decent developer + AI tooling) - suddenly there is far more demand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Domain knowledge is the only moat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So where does that leave us? Right now there is still enormous value in having a human 'babysit' the agent - checking its work, suggesting the approach and shortcutting bad approaches. Pure YOLO vibe coding ends up in a total mess very quickly, but with a human in the loop I think you can build incredibly good quality software, very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This then allows developers who really master this technology to be hugely effective at solving business problems. Their domain and industry knowledge becomes a huge lever - knowing the best architectural decisions for a project, knowing which framework to use and which libraries work best.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Layer on understanding of the business domain and it does genuinely feel like the mythical 10x engineer is here. Equally, the pairing of a business domain expert with a motivated developer and these tools becomes an incredibly powerful combination, and something I think we'll see becoming quite common - instead of a 'squad' of a business specialist and a set of developers, we'll see a far tighter pairing of a couple of people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This combination allows you to iterate incredibly quickly, and software becomes almost disposable - if the direction is bad, then throw it away and start again, using those learnings. This takes a fairly large mindset shift, but the hard work is the conceptual thinking, not the typing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don't get caught off guard&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The agents and models are still improving rapidly, which I don't think is really being captured in the benchmarks. Opus 4.5 seems to be able to follow long 10-20 minute sessions without going completely off piste. We're just starting to see the results of the hundreds of billions of dollars of capex that has gone into GB200 GPUs now, and I'm sure newer models will quickly make these look completely obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, I've spoken to so many software engineers that are really fighting this change. I've heard the same objections too many times - LLMs make too many mistakes, it can't understand &lt;code&gt;[framework]&lt;/code&gt;, or it doesn't really save any time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These assertions are rapidly becoming completely false, and remind me a lot of the desktop engineers who dismissed the iPhone in 2007. I think we all know how that turned out - networking got better, the phones got way faster and the mobile operating systems became very capable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Engineers need to really lean in to the change in my opinion. This won't change overnight - large corporates are still very much behind the curve in general, lost in a web of bureaucracy of vendor approvals and management structures that leave them incredibly vulnerable to smaller competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if you're working for a smaller company or team and have the power to use these tools, you should. Your job is going to change - but software has always changed. Just perhaps this time it's going to change faster than anyone anticipates. 2026 is coming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One objection I hear a lot is that LLMs are only good at greenfield projects. I'd push back hard on this. I've spent plenty of time trying to understand 3-year-old+ codebases where everyone who wrote it has left. Agents make this dramatically easier - explaining what the code does, finding the bug(s), suggesting the fix. I'd rather inherit a repo written with an agent and a good engineer in the loop than one written by a questionable quality contractor who left three years ago, with no tests, and a spaghetti mess of classes and methods.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46196228</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 19:00:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trials avoid high risk patients and underestimate drug harms</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w34534</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f9f935b219307f6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Trials Avoid High Risk Patients and Underestimate Drug Harms&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FDA does not formally regulate representativeness, but if trials under-enroll vulnerable patients, the resulting evidence may understate harm from drugs. We study the relationship between trial participation and the risk of drug-induced adverse events for cancer medications using data from the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results Program linked to Medicare claims. Initiating treatment with a cancer drug increases the risk of hospitalization due to serious adverse events (SAE) by 2 percentage points per month (a 250% increase). Heterogeneity in SAE treatment effects can be predicted by patient's comorbidities, frailty, and demographic characteristics. Patients at the 90th percentile of the risk distribution experience a 2.5 times greater increase in SAEs after treatment initiation compared to patients at the 10th percentile of the risk distribution yet are 4 times less likely to enroll in trials. The predicted SAE treatment effects for the drug's target population are 15% larger than the predicted SAE treatment effects for trial enrollees, corresponding to 1 additional induced SAE hospitalization for every 25 patients per year of treatment. We formalize conditions under which regulating representativeness of SAE risk will lead to more externally valid trials, and we discuss how our results could inform regulatory requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Copy CitationJason Abaluck, Leila Agha, and Sachin Shah, "Trials Avoid High Risk Patients and Underestimate Drug Harms," NBER Working Paper 34534 (2025), https://doi.org/10.3386/w34534.Download Citation&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46196308</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 19:07:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Icons in Menus Everywhere – Send Help</title><link>https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2025/icons-in-menus/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="422090131970f19e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Icons in Menus Everywhere — Send Help&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I complained about this on the socials, but I didn’t get it all out of my system. So now I write a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve never liked the philosophy of “put an icon in every menu item by default”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google Sheets, for example, does this. Go to “File” or “Edit” or “View” and you’ll see a menu with a list of options, every single one having an icon (same thing with the right-click context menu).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s extra noise to me. It’s not that I think menu items should never have icons. I think they can be incredibly useful (more on that below). It’s more that I don’t like the idea of “give each menu item an icon” being the default approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This posture lends itself to a practice where designers have an attitude of “I need an icon to fill up this space” instead of an attitude of “Does the addition of a icon here, and the cognitive load of parsing and understanding it, help or hurt how someone would use this menu system?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The former doesn’t require thinking. It’s just templating — they all have icons, so we need to put something there. The latter requires care and thoughtfulness for each use case and its context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To defend my point, one of the examples I always pointed to was macOS. For the longest time, Apple’s OS-level menus seemed to avoid this default approach of sticking icons in every menu item.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is, until macOS Tahoe shipped.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Menus in macOS Tahoe&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tahoe now has icons in menus everywhere. For example, here’s the Apple menu:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s look at others. As I’m writing this I have Safari open. Let’s look at the “Safari” menu:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hmm. Interesting. Ok so we’ve got an icon for like half the menu items. I wonder why some get icons and others don’t?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, the “Settings” menu item (third from the top) has an icon. But the other item in its grouping “Privacy Report” does not. I wonder why? Especially when Safari has an icon for Privacy report, like if you go to customize the toolbar you’ll see it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hmm. Who knows? Let’s keep going.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s look at the "File" menu in Safari:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some groupings have icons and get inset, while other groupings don’t have icons and don’t get inset. Interesting…again I wonder what the rationale is here? How do you choose? It’s not clear to me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s keep going. Let’s go to the "View" menu:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oh boy, now we’re really in it. Some of these menu items have the notion of a toggle (indicated by the checkmark) so now you’ve got all kinds of alignment things to deal with. The visual symbols are doubling-up when there’s a toggle and an icon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The “View” menu in Mail is a similar mix of:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text + toggles&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text + icons&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text + icons + toggles&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You know what would be a fun game? Get a bunch of people in a room, show them menus where the textual labels are gone, and see who can get the most right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In so many of these cases, I honestly can’t intuit why some menus have icons and others do not. What are so many of these icons affording me at the cost of extra visual and cognitive parsing? I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be fair, there are some menus where these visual symbols are incredibly useful. Take this menu from Finder:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The visual depiction of how those are going to align is actually incredibly useful because it’s way easier for my brain to parse the symbol and understand where the window is going to go than it is to read the text and imagine in my head what “Top Left” or “Bottom &amp;amp; Top” or “Quarters” will mean. But a visual symbol? I instantly get it!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those are good icons in menus. I like those.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Apple Abandons Its Own Guidance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I find really interesting about this change on Apple’s part is how it seemingly goes against their own previous human interface guidelines (as pointed out to me by Peter Gassner).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They have an entire section in their 2005 guidelines (and 1992 and 2020) titled “Using Symbols in Menus”:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See what it says?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are a few standard symbols you can use to indicate additional information in menus…Don’t use other, arbitrary symbols in menus, because they add visual clutter and may confuse people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confused people. That’s me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They even have an example of what not to do and guess what it looks like? A menu in macOS Tahoe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s pretty obvious how I feel. I’m tired of all this visual noise in my menus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And now that Apple has seemingly thrown in with the “stick an icon in every menu by default” crowd, it’s harder than ever for me to convince people otherwise. To persuade, “Hey, unless you can articulate a really good reason to add this, maybe our default posture should be no icons in menus?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I guess this is the world I live in now. Icons in menus. Icons in menus everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Send help.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46196688</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 19:44:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: I built a system for active note-taking in regular meetings like 1-1s</title><link>https://withdocket.com</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46198430</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 22:21:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kroger acknowledges that its bet on robotics went too far</title><link>https://www.grocerydive.com/news/kroger-ocado-close-automated-fulfillment-centers-robotics-grocery-ecommerce/805931/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="24a7c19bfeaa83a7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kroger’s announcement on Tuesday that it will shutter three of its robotic e-commerce fulfillment facilities represents a sharp turnabout for the grocery company, which until recently had expressed confidence in its ability to leverage automation to run a profitable online grocery business.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Less than a year ago, Kroger said it planned to expand the fleet of high-tech fulfillment centers it has been developing in partnership with U.K.-based warehouse automation company Ocado. And in mid-2024, Kroger revealed that it would install new technology from Ocado to improve the efficiency of the warehouses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Kroger launched its partnership with Ocado, the company “believed in the relentless drive to innovate way ahead of the market in order to delight our customers and advance our position as one of America’s leading e-commerce companies,” former Kroger CEO Rodney McMullen said in a video about improvements to its equipment that the automation company announced last year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, Kroger’s projected confidence came even as it was questioning whether the Ocado network was living up to expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kroger revealed in September 2023 that it had decided to pause development of the Ocado project as it waited to see if sites it had already started operating would meet performance benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a further sign that its strategy was faltering, Kroger announced last March it would close three spoke facilities that worked in tandem with several of its robotic centers, with a spokesperson noting that the facilities “did not meet the benchmarks we set for success.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By September 2025, it was clear that depending on automation as the foundation of a money-making grocery delivery business was probably not going to pan out for Kroger. Speaking during an earnings call, interim Kroger CEO Ron Sargent — who took over in March after McMullen’s sudden departure following an ethics probe — said the company would conduct a “full site-by-site analysis” of the Ocado network.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sargent also said Kroger would refocus its e-commerce efforts on its fleet of more than 2,700 grocery supermarkets because it believed that its stores gave it a way to “reach new customer segments and expand rapid delivery capabilities without significant capital investments.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kroger said on Tuesday that its decision to close the three robotic facilities, along with other adjustments to its e-commerce operations, would provide a $400 million boost as it looks to improve e-commerce profitability. But the course-correction will be expensive, forcing Kroger to incur charges of about $2.6 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ken Fenyo, a former Kroger executive who now advises retailers on technology as managing partner of Pine Street Advisors, said the changes Kroger is making reflect the broader reality that grocery e-commerce has not reached the levels the industry had predicted when the COVID-19 pandemic supercharged digital sales five years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fenyo added that Kroger’s decision to locate the Ocado centers outside of cities turned out to be a key flaw.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Ultimately those were hard places to make this model work,” said Fenyo. “You didn’t have enough people ordering, and you had a fair amount of distance to drive to get the orders to them. And so ultimately, these large centers were just not processing enough orders to pay for all that technology investment you had to make.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With its automated fulfillment network, Kroger bet that consumers would be willing to trade delivery speed for sensible prices on grocery orders. That model has been highly successful for Ocado in the U.K., but U.S. consumers have shown they value speed of delivery, with companies like Instacart and DoorDash expanding rapidly in recent years and rolling out services like 30-minute delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Acknowledging this reality, Kroger noted on Tuesday that it’s deepening partnerships with third-party delivery companies. The grocer also said it will pilot “capital-light, store-based automation in high-volume markets” — a seeming nod to the type of micro-fulfillment technology that grocers have tested in recent years, and that Amazon is currently piloting in a Whole Foods Market store in Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fenyo pointed out that micro-fulfillment technology has also run into significant headwinds, adding that he thinks that outside of areas with large numbers of shoppers and high online ordering volume, putting automated order-assembly systems in stores probably doesn’t justify the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kroger’s decision to reduce its commitment to automation also poses a significant setback to Ocado, which has positioned its relationship with Kroger as a key endorsement of its warehouse automation technology. Shares in the U.K.-based robotics company have fallen dramatically and are now back to their level 15 years ago, when the company went public.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46199411</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 23:53:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Manual: Spaces</title><link>https://type.today/en/journal/spaces</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d7a8147305c8adb9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Space (whitespace) is a whole group of glyphs, one of the most important and frequently-used. Any computer user knows space as the widest key on their keyboard, however the notion itself is much bigger and comprises multiple important typographic terms and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Space in general is a blank unprinted area, a counterform that separates letters, words, lines etc. In typography, there are several types of spaces: sinkage (space on a page above a textblock), indent (space before the paragraph), leading (vertical space), word spacing, and letter spacing. In this article, we will primarily focus on word spacing, i.e. the space as a glyph.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;European languages did not use word spacing for a long time, it was not until the 7th century that word spacing entered Latin script. In the age of metal type, the space was a material, tangible object — a piece of metal that left no print. In the pre-digital era, most text blocks were justified, which required several spaces of different width. Those types of spacing were defined by the notion of em (or point size), which is height of the piece of metal &lt;lb/&gt;Diagram of a cast metal sort, c is point size used for printing a character. For example, one em in a 12-point typeface is 12 points, whereas its en (half-em) spaces’ width is 6pt, third space (of an em) equals 4pt, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whitespace characters in Gauge. Widths and correlations between spaces differ depending on the typeface&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These types of spaces are still existent in the digital age, but they are mostly used by advanced typographers. Messengers, text editors, and other programs and applications most typically use only regular space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Word space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standard space, word space, space per se, is the symbol typed using the widest key on the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In metal type, the size of standard space varied depending on the typographic tradition, in most cases the space was rather wide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a standard word space, metal composition used an en space, half the height of the point size, or em-square (in Cyrillic typography), while Latin space was equal to the third of the em space. Alexandra Korolkova Living Typography (2012)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the early digitised fonts one often sees excessively wide spaces; probably, it was an attempt to imitate en space, or three-per-em space, which were used as the main spacing material in metal type. Such a space width can affect the typesetting rhythm and would seem redundant in modern typography.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wide spacing is both physiologically unnecessary and makes the whole typeset structure reticulate, aesthetically ruining the page’s layout. If for some reason you can’t stick to en space size in this particular line, it’s better to scale down spacing using three-per-em spaces (that equal to the third of an em), or spaces of 3, or even 2 points. M. I. Schelkunov History, Technique, Art of Printing (1926)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A wide word spacing seems weird to an eye of the modern reader, and it is way too visible in texts&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, word space width is specified by the typeface’s designer themselves, and it is one of the defining moments in designing a typeface, along with spacing, — texture and rhythm of the typeset are heavily dependent on word space width.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many modern typographers are seeking to subject the space width to certain rules. For example, some type designers claim that the space should be equal to the bounding box of lowercase letter i. However, this rule can’t be universal: specifically, it definitely won’t work for typefaces where letter i is of unconventional design and proportions. In super large point sizes, spacing and word spaces are often intentionally reduced, as in such cases even the bounding box of the i can be too wide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It used to be a rule of thumb for headline settings to leave a space between words that is just wide enough to fit in a lowercase i. For comfortable reading of long lines, the space between words should be much wider. Erik Spiekermann Stop stealing sheep &amp;amp; find out how type works (1993)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Depending on whether your typeface is serif or sans serif, it makes sense to take, or not to take, in consideration sidebearings of the glyph. It can be very different depending on style, too: with wide and light weights, there will be more unprinted area than with narrow and heavy weights, and this also applies to the space width.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is no question but that wordspaces may not be too large, or that the line must appear to be an even, well-balanced whole. What applies to letterspaces also applies to wordspaces: they too are a function of the counters of the individual letters: the smaller these are, the smaller the wordspaces; the larger the counters, the larger the wordspaces. Jost Hochuli Detail in Typography (2008)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blank space between words should be such as to ensure that words are visibly separated from each other — if spacing is wider, there will be holes between words, if smaller, it will be difficult to tell one word from another. You can’t measure space with a ruler, as everything depends on specific design or typeface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Word spaces as set in Kazimir Text. The space width is good: words are separated from one another, the hierarchy of white space is maintained If you increase word spacing, word spaces would conflict with leading, which makes it hard to navigate through the text If you decrease the width of word space, it will affect legibility, as the words will blend together&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using double spaces is a technique inherited from the age of typewriters. It is strongly advisable to check a document for double spaces and replace those by single spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the recommendations learned by the educated typist are still now acquired habits wrongly used in digital documents; for instance, the use of three spaces after a period or two after the comma. There was just one space width available in the typewriter, so words and sentences were separated by the same distance. The double space was used to differentiate sentences and improve the readability of the text. María Ramos Silva Type design for typewriters: Olivetti (2015)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional spacing after a period is a questionable method in terms of readability. It can be assumed that in the age of typewriters additional space could have better separated sentences from one another in the context of monowidth typeface, yet monowidth period and space already form a larger gap than any space within the sentence. Since typewriters, typesetting tools have significantly improved over time, and today nobody will typeset in a monowidth typeface, unless it is absolutely necessary. So, currently, the use of double spaces is considered mauvais ton, i.e. bad manners, regardless of typeface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;American lawyer Matthew Butterick wrote a book on typography for lawyers, writers, and anyone who works with text. In the US, it is still very common among the older generation to use double spaces, so Matthew dedicated two entire chapters of his Practical Typography to this issue. Butterick tried to convince his audience by imaginary dialogues:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“If you approve of smaller word spaces in some situations, why do you insist on only one space between sentences, where a larger gap might be useful?” Because you’re already getting a larger gap. A sentence-ending word space typically appears next to a period. A period is mostly white space. So visually, the space at the end of a sentence already appears larger than a single word space. No need to add another. Matthew Butterick Butterick’s Practical Typography (2013)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Non-breaking Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Non-breaking space is a space character that prevents an automatic line break at its position. For instance, in Russian and a number of other Central and Eastern European languages, non-breaking space serves to stick together a preposition and a word next to it, numbers and units of measurements, name and surname, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Non-breaking space is supported by almost any text editing program, graphic design software, or browser, along with a standard space, so one shouldn’t forget to utilise it according to the typesetting rules of any given language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Russian language, non-breaking space shall connect the dash and its previous word (except for direct speech), prepositions with following words, initials with surname, abbreviations (such as i.e.), numero sign with numbers, numbers and units of measurements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In English it is considered good manners to stick together not prepositions, but pronouns and articles with the following word. However, this rule is often neglected, especially when it comes to newspapers and magazines.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professional typesetting software have spaces of non-standard widths. In InDesign, all additional spaces — em space, en space, thin space, etc. — are non-breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Additional spaces&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standard space is used everywhere; it is supported by any word, text, or code processing app. Non-breaking space is supported almost anywhere as well. However, computer typesetting still possesses a number of spaces dating back to metal type, allowing for finer adjustment of white space if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If a font supports additional spaces, those can be fetched via glyphs palette or using clipboard. Most graphic software do not support those spaces; for example, Adobe Illustrator 2020 includes only four additional spaces: em space, en space, thin space, and hair space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And there is a reason for that: neither Illustrator, nor Photoshop were designed for advanced typesetting and laying out books. However, in InDesign you can easily set any kind of space, and a skilled typographer will use those.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Em Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A space equal to the height of the em square (point size.) In early serifs, the metal face of the capital М tended to be square — probably, thus the English name. Metal type often used em space as paragraph indent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;En Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Half of the width of an em. Russian-language metal type composition considered it the main type of space, even though in word spacing, especially if the text is aligned to the left or right, it is excessively wide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Three-per-em Space, Third Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One third of an em space. Historically considered as the main space in Western European typography.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first obligation of a good typesetter is to achieve a compact line image, something best accomplished by using three-to-em or three-space word spacing. In former times even roman was set much tighter than we do it today; the specimen sheet that contains the original of Garamond’s roman of 1592, printed in 14-point, shows a word spacing in all lines of 2 points only, which is one-seventh of an em! This means that we cannot call three-to-em word spacing particularly tight. Jan Tschichold The Form Of The Book (1975)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Quarter Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One fourth of an em space. Some authors believe quarter space to be the primary word space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a normal text face in a normal text size, a typical value for the word space is a quarter of an em, which can be written M/4. (A quarter of an em is typically about the same as, or slightly more than, the set-width of the letter t.) Robert Bringhurst The Elements of Typographic Style (1992)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Thin Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;⅕ of an em space. It is common that thin space equals about half the standard one, which is why thin space is used where standard word space would be too wide. For example, thin space is often utilised for spacing a dash in cases where standard space is too wide. Thin space is also used for spacing initials, from each other and from the surname:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standard space in Spectral is too wide to be used for spacing initials and dashes Thin spaces look more neat, better connecting initials with a surname and two parts of a sentence with each other&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;French typographic tradition prescribes the use of either thin or hair spaces to space any two-part symbols: exclamation mark, question mark, semicolon, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless of the language, such glyphs as question mark and exclamation mark typically are very visible in lowercase, but they can get lost in an all-caps typeset — in this case, one should finely space them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sixth Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sixth space is used when the thin space is too large.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Hair Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The narrowest of spaces. In metal type, it was equal to 1/10 of an em space, in the digital age it is mostly 1/ 24 of an em. It might be useful if a certain typeface’s punctuation marks have too tight sidebearings, but a thin space would be too wide. For example, you can use hair space to space dashes instead of thin one — everything depends on the sidebearings and the design of the particular typeface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You should keep in mind that after you change font, selected space glyphs will remain, but their width can change, — and this will affect the texture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Isn’t it ridiculous when a punctuation mark, relating to the entire preceding phrase, is tied to one last word of the said phrase? And, vice versa, how unfortunately it looks when there is a large gap between this mark and the previous word. As a matter of fact, it is about time type foundry workers started thinking about it and cast the punctuation mark with an extra sidebearing on its left. However, typefounders are not always, or rather rarely, that forethoughtful, and also they are used to cast all letters without generous sidebearings. During punching of matrices, the beauty of spacing punctuation marks is also barely remembered. Therefore, it is your burden and responsibility to fix this &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Spacing in justified texts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full justification — that is, alignment of text to its both margins, — is still commonly used in books and magazines. When the text is justified, the width of word spaces is not constant, it is changing to distribute words to the entire width of the line. In this situation, the uniformity of spacing could be even more important than the very width of these spaces: evenly large spaces in the entire page are better than large spaces in only one line. That is why, no matter how optimised the typeface’s word spacing in terms of its width is, it will not be enough for typesetting a justified text. While in metal type all spaces were set manually, and a typesetter knew what space they should add for even typesetting, nowadays it’s a computer that defines the length of spaces for justified texts. The algorithm divides the remaining space into equal parts and adds them to regular spaces. In doing so, the algorithm ignores letters, syntax, and punctuation, which is why when typesetting justified texts one should always double-check and adjust spacing manually.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Indesign, it is possible to set minimum and maximum word spacing width for fully justified text typesetting: the width of standard space is used as a basis 100 %, maximum is normally about 120 %, minimum is about 80 %.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the text is justified, a reasonable minimum word space is a fifth of an em (M/5), and M/4 is a good average to aim for. A reasonable maximum in justified text is M/2. If it can be held to M/3, so much the better. But for loosely fitted faces, or text set in a small size, M/3 is often a better average to aim for, and a better minimum is M/4. In a line of widely letterspaced capitals, a word space of M/2 or more may be required. Robert Bringhurst The Elements of Typographic Style (1992)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Robert Bringhurst recommends choosing appropriate spaces based on an em. However, space is a relative value, so in justified texts you should consider not the width of some abstract em, but rather the width of space in particular font.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The optimal word space width in justified texts is ephemeral and changes depending on typeface, point size, line width, line spacing, and many other factors. That is why in Indesign you can’t set maximum and minimum values once and for all cases — you will have to choose the best possible options manually.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In setting justified texts, standard word space width becomes a fluctuating value. The fixed width space and all additional spaces with constant width can help better control the setting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The more even are the gaps between words, the better &amp;lt;…&amp;gt;. In no case shall you allow a considerable disparity in space widths, while an insignificant difference won’t ruin the beauty of typesetting. Pyotr Kolomnin A Concise Account of Typography (1899)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Figure Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure space, or numeric space, is used for typesetting tables and sheets. If a typeface is fitted with tabular figures, its figure space will be equal to the width of tabular figures. Figure space is a non-breaking one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Normally, figure space is significantly wider than standard space, it will be helpful when you need to even a large amount of multi-digit numbers&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Punctuation Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In most cases, the width of this space is equal to the glyph width of a period or a colon. May be of use in making up numbers in tables where digits are defined by a spacing element instead of period or colon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Narrow No-break Space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A thin space that prevents an automatic line break. The name of this symbol in Unicode causes additional confusion: Narrow in this case is the same thing as Thin, and Narrow Space has the same width as Thin Space does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In some applications, such as InDesign, the simple regular thin space is non-breaking by default and is called with Thin Space. In other cases it’s a separate symbol, for example, the Web uses Narrow No-break Space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Spaces in layout&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The distribution of white space in text setting is a highly important factor, responsible for the neat design and the content’s clear structure. Many designers keep in mind correlation between point size, line width, and margins, but some tend to forget that word spacing is an equivalent factor of these relations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Body text font, designed for smaller sizes, would require smaller spacing and word spaces if used to set a large headline. The point size gets more important in determining spacing and white unprinted area in general, than whether it is a text typeface or a display one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is also necessary to consider spacing when you’re dealing with particular elements of the text. For instance, small-caps or all-caps fragments quite often should be additionally spaced. Manual spacing is sometimes necessary in bold or italic styles, or even if no additional styles are applied at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Small-caps spacing in Charter is too tight by default, more white space is needed In William, small caps are taken care of, this generous spacing doesn’t require additional adjustment A text set in a quality typeface sometimes needs manual adjustment: standard word space in Guyot is clearly not enough for the of ‘i’ combination&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;White spaces in software&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most typically, in non-professional software and web services there are only standard and non-breaking spaces available. You might be able to set additional symbols using clipboard almost anywhere where Unicode is supported. That said, you have to check everytime: for example, at the time of writing this piece, Facebook allows for inserting additional symbols in its input field, but automatically replaces them while posting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of the Web, additional spaces are available as HTML special characters: if you use them, your source code might become a bit cluttered, but that would allow you to control the placing of each non-standard space. Please note that different browsers might render spacing differently, and not so long ago some of them even ignored additional spaces, replacing them by regular ones. You should check on the correct display of additional spaces where you use it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two industry standards for text formatting and typesetting, InDesign and Quark Xpress, support all kinds of spaces. Today, type designers usually include at least thin and hair spaces. Their width might vary from one typeface to another — but the typographer, at least, has more control over the word spacing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In InDesign, an additional space not included in the typeface would still be visible, but its width would be defined by the software with no regard to what kind of typeface it is. For example, hair space in 24pt size will be 1pt — both in a display face with tight spacing and in a text face with loose spacing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spaces calculated this way are not always suitable for your task. Depending on the typeface, the additional space width suggested by InDesign can be insufficient or excessive. And if you export the text with such spaces from InDesign to Figma, their width will most likely change — every software may have its own algorithms for calculating these values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be vigilant and trust your eye: it is not mathematical values that matter, but a convincing, reasonable relationship between the black and the white.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These dashes are spaced by hair spaces provided by the typeface These dashes are spaced by hair spaces provided by the typeface The typefaces above have no hair space, therefore its width is set automatically With x-height and spacing that Arno Pro and RIA Text have, the InDesign’s hair space is good enough. Whereas in IBM Plex we perhaps should put thin space instead of a hair one&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whitespace characters are among the most important typographic elements. Alongside sidebearings, they define text rhythm and organise blocks of information. Disregard for white spaces can ruin relations between them: line and word spacing, word spacing and column-gap. In such case the reader wouldn’t be able to easily track the line and would have to put additional &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Summary table&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Non-breaking space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;MacOS: Alt + Space&lt;p&gt;Windows: Alt+0160&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unicode: U00A0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;HTML:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → Nonbreaking Space or Alt + Cmnd + X&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;in case you need a space of non-changing width, in a justified text layout:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Type → Insert White Space → Nonbreaking Space (Fixed Width)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Thin space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U2009&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;ThinSpace;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → Thin Space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shift + Alt + Cmnd + M&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Thin non-breaking space (for Web)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U202F&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;#8239;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Em space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U2003&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;emsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → Em Space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;En space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U2002&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;ensp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → En Space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Third space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U2004&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;emsp13;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → Third Space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Quarter space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U2005&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;emsp14;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → Quarter Space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sixth space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U2006&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;#8198;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → Sixth Space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hair space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U200A&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;hairsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → Hair Space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Figure space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U2007&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;numsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → Figure Space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Punctuation space&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unicode: U2008&lt;p&gt;HTML: &amp;amp;puncsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indesign: Type → Insert White Space → Punctuation Space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;References&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;In English&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kirill Belyayev, Whitespaces and zero width characters with buttons for copying to clipboard, short mnemonics and usage comments &lt;lb/&gt; Robert Bringhurst, The Elements of Typographic Style &lt;lb/&gt; Matthew Butterick, Butterick’s Practical Typography &lt;lb/&gt; Jost Hochuli, Detail in Typography &lt;lb/&gt; Yves Peters, Adventures in Space (fontshop.com) &lt;lb/&gt; María Ramos Silva, Type design for typewriters: Olivetti &lt;lb/&gt; Erik Spiekermann, Stop stealing sheep &amp;amp; find out how type works &lt;lb/&gt; Jan Tschichold, The Form Of The Book &lt;lb/&gt; Martin Wichary, Space Yourself (smashingmagazine.com) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;In Russian&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pyotr Kolomnin, A Concise Account of Typography &lt;lb/&gt; Alexandra Korolkova, Living Typography &lt;lb/&gt; M. I. Schelkunov, History, Technique, Art of Printing &lt;lb/&gt; Alexei Yozhikov, (Nearly) Everything You Need To Know About Whitespace (habr.com) &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46199530</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:07:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The universal weight subspace hypothesis</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05117</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3c1d2c0bdef3808e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Machine Learning&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 4 Dec 2025 (v1), last revised 6 Dec 2025 (this version, v2)]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:The Universal Weight Subspace Hypothesis&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:We show that deep neural networks trained across diverse tasks exhibit remarkably similar low-dimensional parametric subspaces. We provide the first large-scale empirical evidence that demonstrates that neural networks systematically converge to shared spectral subspaces regardless of initialization, task, or domain. Through mode-wise spectral analysis of over 1100 models - including 500 Mistral-7B LoRAs, 500 Vision Transformers, and 50 LLaMA-8B models - we identify universal subspaces capturing majority variance in just a few principal directions. By applying spectral decomposition techniques to the weight matrices of various architectures trained on a wide range of tasks and datasets, we identify sparse, joint subspaces that are consistently exploited, within shared architectures across diverse tasks and datasets. Our findings offer new insights into the intrinsic organization of information within deep networks and raise important questions about the possibility of discovering these universal subspaces without the need for extensive data and computational resources. Furthermore, this inherent structure has significant implications for model reusability, multi-task learning, model merging, and the development of training and inference-efficient algorithms, potentially reducing the carbon footprint of large-scale neural models.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Submission history&lt;/head&gt;From: Prakhar Kaushik [view email]&lt;p&gt;[v1] Thu, 4 Dec 2025 18:59:58 UTC (14,316 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v2] Sat, 6 Dec 2025 04:42:07 UTC (14,321 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Current browse context: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;cs.LG&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; IArxiv Recommender (What is IArxiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46199623</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:16:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>30 Year Anniversary of WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness</title><link>https://www.jorsys.org/archive/december_2025.html#newsitem_2025-12-09T07:42:19Z</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="be435c9aabb33e50"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has now been 30 years since WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness was released. After the great response to Warcraft: Orcs and Humans, released in November 1994, Blizzard began working on Warcraft II: Tides of Darkness. Development stared in the first months of 1995, and the game was released in North America and Australia on December 9, 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While WarCraft: Orcs and Humans had laid the foundations of the series — arguably even for the RTS genre at a whole — it was really WarCraft II that took things to new heights. More units could be selected at once, the player could right-click to issue commands, naval and aerial combat was introduced, and buildings and units could be upgraded. The graphics were more vivid and visually appealing, and features like the Fog of War was introduced, where you could only see in the vicinity of your own units — unlike in the first game, where you could indefinitely see any area you had previously visited, you now had to continuously scout the map.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many things still resembled the first game. The two factions — the Humans and the Orcs — were balanced through their similarites. For every unit and building of one faction, the other had one that was functionally equivalent, and so the sides largely mirrored each other. The only real differences lay in the spells available to their higher-level units. In that regard, the clear winners were the Orcs, who had a tremendous advantage thanks to the incredibly powerful and unbalanced Bloodlust spell of the Ogre-Magi.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is quite impressive that Blizzard managed to release a title of such quality in such a short span of time, especially considering that the overall design and gameplay evolved during development. Originally, Blizzard’s concept blended modern and fantasy elements, such as fighter pilots being ambushed by a fire-breathing dragon. In the Alpha version (it is still probably floating around somewhere on the Internet) which was given to magazines for review shortly before the game's release, players could, for example mine rocks, which acted as an additional required resource.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Several versions and bundles of WarCraft II were released over the years:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness, originally written for DOS, though it had a Windows launch screen and ran well under Windows 95. A Macintosh version was also released. The DOS version supported multiplayer games via null modem cable, modem, or IPX, while Mac players could also play via TCP/IP or AppleTalk.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: Beyond the Dark Portal, the expansion, released in April 1996.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft: Battle Chest, released in 1996, was a bundle which included WarCraft: Orcs and Humans, WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness, and WarCraft II: Beyond the Dark Portal.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: The Dark Saga, released in 1997, was a port for the Sega Saturn and PlayStation consoles by Electronic Arts, including the campaigns from both Tides of Darkness and Beyond the Dark Portal.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: Battle.net Edition, released in 1999, ported the game's code to Microsoft Windows, fixed some minor bugs, and enabled multiplayer support via Blizzard's online service, Battle.net.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II Battle Chest, released in 1999, included the Battle.net Edition and its official strategy guide.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WarCraft II: Remastered, released in November 2024, is modern remaster of Tides of Darkness and Beyond the Dark Portal, with improved graphics and updated controls.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WarCraft II: Tides of Darkness received enthusiastic reviews, elevating Blizzard to the top ranks alongside Westwood Studios, id Software, and LucasArts. The rivalry between Blizzard's series and Westwood Studios' Command and Conquer series helped fuel the RTS boom of the late 1990s. PC Gamer US named WarCraft II the best game of 1995, calling it an "easy" choice and writing that "Warcraft II stand[s] out — way out — as the most impressive, most entertaining, game of 1995". The editors also awarded it Best Multi-Player Game of 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WarCraft II was notable for the large number of third-party utilities created for it. Quickly, Daniel Lemberg reverse-engineered and published the map file (*.pud) format and wrote the first third-party map editor, War2xEd, which could do multiple things that the bundled map editor could not, such as editing unit attributes. Blizzard apparently began using War2xEd internally, and it influenced their decision to later ship a feature-rich map editor with StarCraft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, Alexander Cech and Daniel Lemberg reverse-engineered the game data format, the WAR archives. Alexander Cech went on to make a hugely important tool called Wardraft, which allowed users to browse and modify the contents of the WAR archives. This enabled extensive game modifications, known as "Total Conversions". Many such projects gained popularity and remained in development for a long time, notable examples being DeathCraft: Twilight of Demons, War of the Ring, Editor's Total Conversion, Funcraft and Rituals of Rebirth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of these utilities and conversions have long since faded into obscurity, but their legacy lives on. They impacted Blizzard's desicion to bundle ever more powerful editors and trigger systems into StarCraft and later WarCraft III, which in turn later spawned entire games such as Dota (which began as a WarCraft III map). Hopefully, someday (soon?) we can host some of the Total Conversions here at Jorvik Systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a personal anecdote, I vividly remember two defining moments related to the game. I was young when it came out, and my dad's friend had pirated it; somehow the game ended up on our computer. I was too young to speak English at the time, and the interface was confusing to me, so a relative helped me understand the basics — how to make peons construct buildings, how to control units, and how to navigate around the map. I hadn't played computer games much before then, but from that moment on, I was arguably obsessed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A second strong memory came a few months later, at my friend Erik's house, on his Intel 486 PC. He was experimenting with the WarCraft II map editor, which I hadn't known existed, and I was blown away. I simply could not believe that Blizzard would ship such a tool with the game; to me, it meant that people could essentially create their own games by designing entirely new scenarios. It is quite possible that my fascination with modding was born in that very moment. We probably went outside to play shortly afterward, which I found incredibly lame — we had at our disposal the most powerful tool I could imagine, so why were we not inside using it?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46202921</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 09:13:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Joy of Playing Grandia, on Sega Saturn</title><link>https://www.segasaturnshiro.com/2025/11/27/the-joy-of-playing-grandia-on-sega-saturn/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b78dd71e0a31439d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Renaissance Period&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are living through a Saturn renaissance. Buckets of titles previously locked away in Japan are seeing new audiences, thanks to the herculean efforts of small but dedicated teams of enthusiast translators, removing the veil of Japanese illiteracy from before our tired eyes. Interestingly, the majority of efforts are being directed at the games with the biggest scripts, and no other genre was as impacted by the language barrier as the text-heavy, story-driven RPG. Over a dozen quality titles are now playable in English. The Saturn is, once again, ascendant…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Ain’t life Grand?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enter Grandia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What hasn’t been said about Grandia? In the run-up to its late 1997 release, the game enjoyed significant worldwide coverage in the gaming press, not least because some positioned it as the anti-FF7 title. Hot on the heels of the remaster of Lunar: Silver Star Story and hailing from respected software house Game Arts, featuring state of the art fully 3D environments, a score by notable composer Noriyuki Iwadare, sound effects produced by Skywalker Sound… Grandia was indeed shaping up to be one of the premier JRPG experiences of the 5th generation. There was serious talk of bringing the game out West — Working Designs was touted as the favoured house to do the honors, owing to their strong partnership with Game Arts, but the game’s massive script would have meant a late 1998 release by even the speediest conversion standards of the time. By then, the Western Saturn retail market had collapsed, and despite a shrinking but fervently dedicated base of Saturn fans holding on to hope of seeing the title cross the ocean, the game wound up locked away in Japan, forever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;NEVER say Forever&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Game Arts subsequently ported Grandia to the PlayStation, dropping it in Japan in the summer of 1999. Sony speedily localized the game for Western release later that same year… but we aren’t going to focus too much on the PlayStation version here because, at the time of writing, PlayStation discs don’t boot on your SEGA Saturn. It’s the Saturn game that we are concerned with. For us Saturn stalwarts, we had to wait to the mid-2020s for an intrepid team led by TrekkiesUnite113 to transplant the PlayStation’s English script into the Saturn code. By then, the game was decades old, not to mention re-released and ‘re-mastered’ on modern platforms. So, why translate Grandia for the Saturn, when multiple other English options exist?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because Grandia is Best on Saturn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How do you do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set in an age of discovery at the dawn of the industrial revolution, Grandia initially tells the tale of young Justin — a 14-year-old fearless adolescent who can’t help but dream of adventure. When he isn’t playing at “hero” with his town friends, he’s dreaming of great expeditions to find the lost civilization of Angelou. He is joined by his friend Sue — an 8-year-old girl whose maturity belies her age, and who tries desperately to keep young Justin in line. Justin’s mom Lily runs the local Seagull Restaurant and does her best to raise Justin into a respectable young man… though in her youth, she was a scrappy pirate herself. In her heart, she knows her audacious spark has passed on to her son, and that Justin will one day take up the adventurer’s mantle and take off on a grand adventure of his own, so she does her best to prepare him for when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She gives Justin a Spirit Stone — a remnant of the Angelou civilization and a memento of his long-lost father — and in doing so, helps kick off a fantastic voyage that sees young Justin explore, learn, overcome all manner of obstacles, and ultimately, grow and become the hero that he always imagined himself to be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During his quest, Justin encounters fascinating characters, both friend and foe. From quiet folk in sleepy villages to rambunctious youngsters eager for their own slice of adventure; from military platoons led by the most beautiful — but hopelessly shallow — lady sergeants to cunning merchants, towering warriors, alluring mermaids and ferocious dragons… Justin encounters them all, and for good or ill, manages to change the course of their lives in ways both subtle and grand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Justin, Sue, and Feena are the first three playable characters in Grandia. Young Sue tries to keep Justin in line, while Feena searches for the true meaning of being an adventurer – with Justin slowly moving from admiring her to showing her the way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game is clever in pulling the player in for a ride that for a very long while feels very lighthearted and innocent. Even as Justin’s adventure begins in earnest and the player is exposed to antagonists, mysteries, undercurrents and intrigues, Justin can’t help but distill it back to the very pure essence of boyhood adventure. Mysterious tower causing problems for a nearby village for years? No problem, Justin will fix it! A dragon from a nearby volcano terrorizing the locals? Justin’s got this. A ghost ship sailing in to harass a passenger steamer? Justin is the answer, in the same way that, as youngsters, we all knew – we knew! – that WE were the heroes, and that WE would save the day, armed only with our courage and our grand imaginations. It was our duty, after all. We had it in us to go forth boldly, and change the world (and naturally, all before being called home for dinner).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This point is driven home by Justin’s insatiable desire to uncover the mystery of his Spirit Stone, and the ancient Angelou civilization. After an unfortunate but entirely predictable mishap in the local museum, followed by a mysterious revelation in the nearby Sult Ruins, Justin’s curiosity is ignited, and his drive for real adventure becomes indomitable. Meanwhile, forces are at work that care not for Justin’s explorations, and inevitably, the lad finds himself pitted against the Garlyle Forces and some of its top commanders. Their aims are complex and their operations span the world, and this scope creates a wonderful juxtaposition with Justin’s innocent demeanor and singular focus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;On Screen!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Fifth Generation of consoles marked the rise of 3D graphics, but some genres made the leap easier than others. This shift was a struggle for RPGs, with many excellent titles continuing to employ 2D visuals, albeit in richer color and more sophisticated detail than seen in previous generations. Early attempts at the 3D RPG (Virtual Hydlide) highlighted how difficult it was to run this style of game on the hardware of the time without wrecking the framerate or keeping textures from looking like a checkerboard mess. Dungeon crawlers (Shining the Holy Ark) were among the first titles to get the 3D right, though the player’s scope of movement was very restricted. Finally, some fantasized that “3D” meant pre-rendered backgrounds and copious FMV clips, with the only real 3D being battle scenes. Ahem!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia took the traditional overhead RPG view and transformed the landscapes into fully realized 3D polygonal playfields that can be rotated and zoomed at will. Character and enemy sprites are then overlain on the 3D world to make the scenes come to life. The addition of the third dimension affords the use of depth in the environments: hills, cliffs, and valleys; minecar rails that ran higher or lower relative to other tracks, and so on. In this way, the player initially feels right at home with a view that looks comfortably familiar, but must quickly learn to constantly rotate the viewpoint to catch enemies in hiding, spy treasures only visible from certain angles, judge heights, and evaluate other geometric details to plot their best course forward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia wastes no time in getting gamers used to this new visual paradigm. One of the game’s first quests sees local frenemy Gantz challenge Justin and Sue to locate the three Legendary Treasures: the fabled helmet (Iron Pot), the storied shield (Pot Lid), and of course, the legendary (Wooden) Sword. The player must traverse all of Parm, climbing down river walkways, checking in enclosed spaces, and chasing down Gantz’s little brother to prove they are up to Gantz’ task — and in the process, get used to the game’s then-new control scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 3D is very well put together, both technical and artistically. The level of detail is truly phenomenal, from the tiniest objects and details, especially in the ‘in-town’ game sections. Justin is able to interact with some of the innocuous scenery — for example he can knock brooms over, disturb piles of plates, or bump into bells and chimes — just as any real, overly excited 14-year-old might clumsily do as they ran along. Animations, from little weathervanes rotating to laundry fluttering on a clothesline, to puffs of smoke coming up from fires or chimneys, all accentuate the feeling that these are real, living, bustling places. The level of detail, and all of it in 3D, is really special.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The coders at Game Arts made excellent use of the Saturn’s unique hardware when realizing Grandia’s locales. Where appropriate, textured infinite planes are used to draw floors, and they not only look good but also dramatically cut down on the usage of polygons in drawing the scene, leaving that much more in the processing budget to spend on other visual details. In later sections, those infinite planes take on a distortion effect to create some very cool-looking water flows — look for them initially in Parm’s pier, and later in places like the snowy Laine Village or the mysterious Castle of Dreams. The water shimmers as the player rotates their view to create a truly stunning effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game’s characters and enemies are all represented by sprites that animate quite well and take viewpoints into account as the player rotates the camera. In yet more attention to detail, the sprites darken and then lighten again as the player moves in and out of shadowed areas — an impressive little detail that accentuates the visuals even further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trio of General Baal, Colonel Mullen, and Leen is introduced in the game’s opening scene, and all three are more than they appear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The care that Game Arts took in crafting the visuals is commendable and Grandia comes off as one of the very best-looking 3D RPGs for the system, but Game Arts was perhaps a mite too ambitious. There are sections of the game where the framerate really chugs. Now, it must be acknowledged that low framerates were a hallmark of many 3D games in the 32-bit era, so some of this is to be expected, but the more detail Grandia is trying to show you, the more you will feel the Saturn huffing and puffing to get the job done. The game’s 3D framerate is not high at the best of times but it is passable, so it’s somewhat of a relief that the areas where it truly takes a dive aren’t too common.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pump up the Jam!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Game Arts’ attention to detail extends to the sound department. For Grandia, Game Arts commissioned Skywalker Sound to handle the game’s sound effects. The result is positional sound — effects like running water, crackling fire, etc. will fade in and out as Justin and co. move closer in or further away from the source. Often, if the effect is important, it will also somewhat dampen the volume of the BGM as it plays out. Additionally, the effects will pan left or right depending on the source, and especially as the player rotates the camera. These effects may be subtle, but they are very well implemented and add to the game’s overall polish.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game’s soundtrack was composed by Noriyuki Iwadare and is both varied and excellent. Iwadare’s use of instruments appropriate to the on-screen action is uncanny — for example, running around Parm we are treated to an industrial sounding theme, perfect for the town’s motif. The varied use of strings, drums and winds is frankly excellent and lends to the atmosphere, imitating the clang of metal and steel which so permeates the city. Equally impressive is that the music somehow manages to be exciting or somber or poignant without ever sounding overly (excuse the wordplay) grandiose. This keeps the soundtrack in line with the game’s more lighthearted narrative. Of course, where appropriate, the soundtrack does take on that epic quality. The desperate tones that play when the Garlyle forces appear contrast so well with the carefree, upbeat “Off Runs Sue” tune. Mullen’s theme is at once wistful and ambitious, and even the theme from the Sult Ruins dungeon is perfectly mood-setting. Multiple Grandia soundtracks have been released since the game’s debut and the soundtrack is universally praised.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How it Plays Out&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia’s gameplay, like so many RPGs before it, is split into two major gameplay slices: exposition-laden town sections and combat-focused dungeons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Players will spend a fair bit of time in the ‘in-town’ sections of the game. Here, you will wander around, take in the scenery, interact with the NPCs of the area, and almost always, find a quest that must be completed. A quick word about the NPCs — there are quite a number of them in each town, and everyone has something interesting to say… and almost always, each NCP has at least two separate conversation sequences to offer, making for a truly large amount of story to soak in. And it’s all entirely optional! It’s completely possible to make one’s way through Grandia with only minimal NCP interaction, but the option to enhance the adventure with these extensive NPC interactions is always there, as each character will present a unique view or focused response.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Predictably, the towns are filled with shops, though Grandia keeps things rather simple — there is but one general store which carries weapons, armor, accessories, and even magic all under the same roof. Buy, sell or trade up to the latest gear which gradually increases in the stat boosts it confers to your characters. Additionally, each town typically has one or more important locales, such as mayors’ offices or the chambers of village chiefs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is typically an inn or other house where the party can take rest, and at certain points in the game, resting triggers a shared meal scene that sees Justin break bread with his party mates. These meal scenes offer up critical dialogue, which the gamer can extend or keep short at their whim. When the critical conversation has been had, a bedtime icon will appear over Justin’s character sprite, and if the player is quite finished listening to the party chatter, they can select it to end the meal and get some rest. These mealtime conversations serve not only to flesh out what the party must tackle next, but also to offer a glimpse into the inner thoughts of the individual characters as they share their opinions, hopes and fears. Like so much in the game, Grandia implements this character exposition in a way that allows the player to decide how much of it to take in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The visuals in the town sections really stand out. The Saturn manages to shift not only impressive amounts of polygons for the various structures, but also vivid and complex textures. This technical prowess is coupled with lush and imaginative art direction, resulting in each locale feeling complete and distinct. The dense, humid and green surrounds of Luc Village, nestled deep within the Misty Forest and inhabited by humanoid creatures contrasts sharply with the seaside port town of Dight with its cerulean waves gently rolling in onto its sandy shores. Milda’s hometown village of Laine is covered in snow, and the ancient Zil Padon is an architectural wonder with a central fountain in the middle of the Savanna desert. Game Arts very clearly discarded their standard world building cookie cutters, and their efforts shine through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once a locale has been explored, it will appear as a selectable destination on a gorgeous, hand-drawn high-resolution world map. Exiting an area often brings our party to this world map, and the next destination can be selected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the towns serve to heal the party, upgrade equipment, and advance the story, then the dungeons of the game offer treasure hunting, exploration, and of course, combat! Dungeons in Grandia range from literal underground labyrinths to above-ground forest mazes, to even large open plains that Justin et al. must traverse. Some of the more noteworthy settings include scaling a giant wall that keeps the world divided into two separate societies, negotiating the bowels of a ghost ship which appears out of nowhere to molest a transcontinental steamer, and even conquering the inside of an unstable volcano that’s inhabited by an ancient dragon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here, the player really must use their L and R buttons to shift the 3D landscape around, to find all the nooks of treasure or paths forward. Some areas feature set pieces that Justin and party can activate — for example, knocking over a loose pillar to bridge a gap. These are usually indicated by an exclamation point icon when the party nears the set piece.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the while, treasure both great and small litters the landscape… but so do enemies! Enemies are visible in the dungeons and so can be avoided to an extent, but if Justin and party come in contact with an enemy, combat ensues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Grandia Grinder Alert!&lt;lb/&gt;Grind for Experience Points Using Environmental Damage!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are YOU a Grandia grinder?? Some sections of the game will deal damage to Justin and party outside of combat. First noticed in the Dom Ruins, rock faces painted into some of the dungeon walls will cause mild HP damage by springing out and poking the party when the party doesn’t want to be poked! The player can then use heal magic and spam this process to quickly increase Water magic levels. Although definitely a grind, it’s much faster than earning those experience points via combat. A few other areas in the game present similar opportunities — such as the basement in the Castle of Dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A New Kind of Kombat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia introduced an all-new combat system to the RPG genre, though it could be said to be a variant of other similar RPG battle systems. Essentially, all battle participants have icons that continuously move along a universal IP Gauge, until they reach the Command point. Here, the player will enter from a selection of commands which includes attacking, using an item or a spell, guarding, or even retreating. They then wait to reach the very end of the gauge to execute their selected action, and the more experienced the character, the faster that point is reached. A ton of strategy is introduced here as during this waiting period between selecting an action and executing it, they are vulnerable to both Cancels and Counterattacks from their opponents. Unlike many contemporary RPGs where the instinct is to simply unleash physical and magical attacks in a turn-based order, the player can take advantage of these waiting periods to cancel out incoming enemy attacks and push them back on their IP gauge. The system will take some getting used to, but can be used to devastating effect, especially in the more drawn-out boss battles. It is entirely possible to strategically get in a half-dozen actions by each character and prevent a boss from retaliating during the entire sequence, by carefully timing attacks. This makes combat a lot more involved and exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are also advantages to catching an enemy unawares — player characters start much further ahead on their IP Gauge, with the reverse being true if Justin’s party is ambushed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Players have a range of actions they can take when their IP Gauge is full, from the standard fare of using items, defending, running away, or even inspecting an enemy (is that slug-monster male or female, for example*).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nana, Saki, and Mio are Mullen’s three she-sergeants. Serving as comedic relief, they are nevertheless quite capable opponents in battle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;By Your Powers Combined… I Am Captain Planet!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earth. Fire. Wind. Water. These are the elemental forces that move the world, and most characters can master them! Learning magic in Grandia first requires that the party finds a Mana Egg. These rare items can then be exchanged in a shop for magic for a single character of your choice. That party member then learns the basics of your chosen magic element.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inside of the four elements, magic spells are further split into levels, from one to three, to indicate their potency. Level 1 spells are your most basic spells and are what a character starts off with should they buy magic with their mana egg. Players that use magic in combat will gain skill points in that particular element, and those skill points are applied to all spells of that element, regardless of spell level — so, use a Level 1 Fire spell, and all levels of your Fire magic gain skill. Spell skill progression is represented by five red stars that fill up like a gauge, turning yellow as they gain experience. Greater experience shortens casting time (which, remember, is a vulnerable time as your spell can be cancelled by an opponent) and at higher levels, allows your character to learn combined element magic spells. All magic spells consume MP making them a limited resource, though a character’s overall MP capacity will grow with experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outside of magic, each character can also execute special attacks that are unique to them. These attacks are usually more devastating than standard attacks and sometimes require that the character is using a particular weapon class. These, too, gain skill points represented by five red stars that slowly build up to yellow, though special attacks consume SP (skill points). SP works much the same way as MP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Grandia Grinder Alert!&lt;lb/&gt;Rare Enemies Give High XP&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Typically, the game’s monsters do a good job of seeking you out, but there are occasional difficult-to-catch enemies to be found as well. Notice, for instance, the Chameleon enemies in the Virgin Forest. These green creatures are shy and are hard to catch and engage. But persist, and finish them off for a huge load of experience points — well worth a grinding sesh or three.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Experience Required&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia has a complex (for the time) experience points system, which is cleverly segmented into several categories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To start, each playable character has a set of basic stats that slowly increase as they gain experience. Hit Points (HP) are your standard measure of health and these increase at level-ups. SP are your skill points, which increase the speed and potency of your special attacks, as well as unlock new special attacks as you accumulate experience. Finally, the same is true of the more traditional magic points (MP), with the difference between SP and MP being that special attacks are individualized whereas magic attacks are more common amongst party members and can be bought in exchange for Mana Eggs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As they adventure, Justin and company will occasionally find items that slightly boost a particular stat on a permanent basis. These items are rare indeed, but as with life, incremental gains tend to compound until the effects are undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most traditionally, defeating enemies grants experience points and accumulating the required amount grants characters a level-up, which slightly increases basic stats. Experience gained and gold / treasure collected is displayed on an after-battle screen. It is this type of XP that most contemporary RPGs concerned themselves with. Grandia ups the complexity a bit by introducing leveling for magic and skills, and further mixes things up by employing different weapon classes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Justin and company are each capable of wielding a few different types of weapons, of which there are seven in total, ranging from swords to maces to staffs to bows. Each weapon class has its advantages and disadvantages, be it speed of use (from Command input to Execution on the IP gauge), to range, to overall damage dealt. As party members use their weapons, they gain experience in those weapon types, separately from their character experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, Grandia features basic character experience points which boosts common stats, magic experience which results in spells being cast faster and the learning of higher-level spells for various element types, skill experience for faster execution of special attacks, and weapon experience points which increase how well a character will handle that weapon type. Cleverly, these different experience categories are implemented in such a way as to make it entirely possible for gamers to completely ignore this aspect of the game should they so fancy. Because the system is automated, gamers can pay all of it little heed and still progress and have a great time with the game. Alternately, gamers can dive right into the finer points of the system to make those minor tweaks to get their characters to exactly the state they prefer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mysterious Liete awaits at Alent. The enigmatic Puffy accompanies Sue wherever she goes. Lastly, Darlin is one of the many non-human denizens of Grandia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Go with the Flow&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia allows up to four playable characters to form Justin’s party at any one time. As the story progresses, some of the main characters will permanently step away from the adventure, for reasons practical and dramatic alike. One such parting in particular tugs at the heartstrings — it is nothing quite as dramatic as the year’s earlier death of Aeris (Aerith) from that big RPG on Sony’s lesser 32-bit machine, but it somehow feels more relatable, and more impactful. Players ought not be surprised by the need for tissues to manage an unexpected tear or two. And here, too, Grandia innovates: a portion of a departing playable character’s magic and weapon experience points are stored in the stashing place, to be retrieved and applied to whatever character you see fit. This strengthens their legacy in your party, as well as provide a practical reason not to neglect building up a character just because they may eventually leave the party. A nice touch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Is It Perfect?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grand as it sounds, the game isn’t without a few small flaws. Story-wise, players will be left wanting to know more about Justin’s father and how he came to be the keeper of his Spirit Stone. He is mentioned often in the early stages of the game, but as Justin’s adventure takes off, that arc never completes. Likewise for General Baal — we eventually learn his motivations, but not so much why he has become who he is today. A really well put together villain is one with whom we can empathise; someone whose circumstance we can understand. Both with Justin’s unnamed father and with Baal, there is a feeling that we are reading a book and that the answers lie just ahead, but despite some teasing, Grandia never lets us turn the page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Technically, the game’s 3D is solid and varied, with plenty of minor details and meticulous textures, especially in the town sections. Blending VDP2-drawn planes with solid geometry and animated sprites means the world of Grandia is beautifully rendered, but that comes at the cost of an oft-stuttering framerate. The more of Grandia’s world we are allowed to see at once, the more the framerate suffers. Now, these were the formative years of 3D gaming, but at times, that framerate simply chugs, and it’s noticeable to the point of distraction. Thankfully, for most of the game, the framerate sits comfortably in the ‘acceptable’ space, but you won’t get through the game without feeling the Saturn sweat as it works to display all that Grandia’s artists wanted you to see.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of 3D, the game often requires the shifting of camera angles when exploring. When in long dungeons or any other large space, this can quickly become disorienting, and the player will lose their sense of direction. The game compensates somewhat for this with the addition of the compass, though its implementation is somewhat clumsy as rather than point north, it points to an exit or other objective. There is also lookout points called Dungeon Scopes, where the player is given a bird’s eye view of their current location from a default ‘north is up’ viewpoint. This helps orientating, but those lookout points are few and far between and using them tends to break up the game’s flow. Players may well find themselves keeping their camera shifting to a minimum as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lastly, a technical note: Grandia sure gives the Saturn’s laser a workout, and there are some clever pre-loading techniques implemented to keep the game flowing as smoothly as possible. The cost here is that Grandia is very sensitive to disc quality. Those that have burnt their English-patched game onto CDs and are playing on real Saturn hardware may well find the game freeze, especially in battle when calling various spells. This is VERY annoying, especially as dungeon save points are sparse, and it is not uncommon to be in the heat of a battle only to have everyone freeze with the reset button being the only escape. This is remedied by using an ODE solution that omits discs entirely, but the game’s sensitivity to the quality of your CD-R burn needs to be called out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Final Word&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia is great. The visuals are gorgeous, the music is appropriately evocative, the combat is frenetically strategic, and the story is well paced. Tough battles and surprise plot twists await intrepid gamers, and sub-plots occasionally weave their way into the adventure, too — especially in sections where we briefly leave Justin. On occasion, players will follow Colonel Mullen with Feena, explore the mysterious past of Mullen’s attaché Leen, or even soak in the comedic antics of the three beautiful Garlyle generals Mio, Nana, and Saki.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, Grandia a delight to play. A total joy… but one that demands an intense time commitment. A player Justin’s age surely has the time, but what about those of us that are well into adulting? Some sections of the game, especially the longer dungeons, have few opportunities to save one’s game. In that sense, the game is a total hardcore, traditional JRPG. It is not easily digested in small play sessions, so playing Grandia is committing a huge slice of one’s discretionary time budget.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yet, perhaps paradoxically, playing Grandia has a way of making one feel young again. Grandia is grand in the same way we ourselves felt grand as youngsters — that, armed with a stick we’ve just picked up and nothing more than our imagination, our wits, and our indomitable spirit, we could go forth boldly and change the world. That’s the beauty of a main character like Justin — he is not yet jaded; he has not yet borne the burden of grown-up problems on his shoulders. In many ways, we were all Justin (or Sue!) at one point, and the game shines a light on that part of us that is now long behind (most of) us. Perhaps the most memorable aspect of Grandia is that it allows us, for a moment all too brief, to once again be that young boy or girl full of optimism and energy, and in today’s complex and stressful world, that feels simply wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Three Optional Dungeons&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia is generally a well-balanced affair, with experience accumulating at the right rate for players to progress in the game. That said, the world of Grandia plays host to three completely optional dungeons meant solely for increasing character abilities and experience — and goes so far as to explicitly point out that these areas are not part of the game’s story and are entirely optional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first such dungeon can be found just west of the first section of the Zil Desert. It’s a large, very dark brown multi-leveled maze with the only save point being at the entrance. The enemies are tougher than one would expect at this point in the game, but nothing is impossible for Justin et al. The key here is to find the four Soldier’s Souls, which grants access to the treasures of the dungeon, at the very end, past the boss. The boss is a remix of a previous boss from Feena’s failed wedding to Pakon and packs quite a punch. The main prize here is the excellent Godspeed Knife, which adds a huge ACT boost, to massively speed up the user’s IP gauge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second optional dungeon is also found to the west but is accessible from the second part of the Zil Desert. This dungeon is very small but has perhaps the most charm. Justin and company are greeted by a mysterious Lady at the castle entrance, begging for help but also warning of a curse on the castle. Once inside, there are several rooms to visit and loot to collect. Really simplistic and set to lure the player to lower their guard, just in time to battle the formidable Lord’s Ghost boss. This guy’s TOUGH, with strong multi-character attacks and cancelling moves. Take him down to claim the awesome Lightning Sword, which gives a 50 ATK boost and, as an elemental sword, has the Zap! spell built in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final optional dungeon is the mother of all dungeons in Grandia. Found tucked away in the Savanna Wilderness and accessible via a secret passage, the Tower of Temptation consists of an outside area and 12 (!) floors of punishing combat. Of course, the only save point is at the very start of the outside area, though Justin can activate a couple of shortcuts through the tower as he makes progress, so that backtracking to heal and save is a bit easier. Interestingly, the starting area is surrounded by six Zero Weapons – one of each kind of weapons that grants a 0 ATK value — ideal for training weapons on weaker enemies, as these will do nearly no damage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia Grinder Mini-Alert: many enemies in the Tower drop stat-increasing items, making this an ideal place to pull it all out and go for that growth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each floor of the Tower features maze sections, hidden doors, powerful enemies, and of course, switches to hit. Simply by making one’s way through the tower will increase the party’s levels, as there is so much battling to do. It is not uncommon to spend hours in the Tower, so it’s a welcome fact that the Tower is entirely optional. The final three floors are all boss — yes, there are three bosses to fight in a row. No saving, no healing. The final of the three bosses is tough as nails, but the reward is well worth it — NINE amazing items to pick up, including two items from the Grinder’s Gear™ premium collection: the Astral Miracle and the Ethereal Miracle, both accessories that double weapon or magic experience gained. VERY useful, but they better be, considering the pain just endured to complete the Tower of Temptation!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Universe is Grand…ia&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grandia went on to sell bucket-loads in Japan, especially during release week. It received a Digital Museum DLC-style disc, got a port on the mass-market PlayStation including a PS Greatest Hits re-release, and finally, a PlayStation English localization in 1999. The series continued in 2000 with the excellent Grandia 2 on Dreamcast, which itself was later poorly ported to Sony’s killer of dreams, the PlayStation 2. That system would also see the less-well received Grandia 3, which would spell the end of the main series’ run. The series also saw several spin-off games such as Grandia Xtreme and Grandia Online. Additionally, the first Grandia was recently remade for modern consoles with the release of the Grandia HD Collection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;*Note: you cannot inspect monsters’ genders in battle. That was just a joke. Also there is no Grinder’s Gear in Grandia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;I’m Not Crying, You’re Crying!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A bit of a personal story… The above screenshot is my favorite scene in all of Grandia. See, the game does a brilliant job of bringing us back to the days of youthful adventures where nothing at all was impossible, and despite whatever danger beset us, we knew deep down that in the end, we would be all right. But in the most subtle of ways, Grandia also covers personal growth and the passage of time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At some point, deep into the adventure, 8-year-old Sue gets tired. At first, she temporarily leaves the party whilst recuperating at a local sick house, with everyone hoping (and the player confidently knowing) that she will get better. But… she doesn’t. She puts on a brave face and re-joins the party, going on one final quest. As the gamer, I kept looking for the herb or special item that I could find to cure her, but no such moment ever came. There never was any single wound or ailment that Sue suffered, it’s just that one day, she simply… got tired, and ultimately, had to leave the party. She was a trooper through the entire adventure; completely indispensable she was, but there was a sunset to her time on the grand adventure, and she ended up leaving far too soon for my liking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In real life, this sometimes happens, too. People in our orbit — strong, vibrant people, whom we believe will be with us forever — sometimes, unexpectedly, undeservedly… get tired, and have to quit the great adventure. Sometimes they are even younger than us, or in better health than us, or benefitting from any number of other factors that make their leaving seem senseless and cruelly unfair. It’s a reminder of the finite nature of life, and that sometimes we are living oh so naively and innocently through what we will later call the best times of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes, we get a chance to say our goodbyes before they depart us, and this is something Justin and Feena were able to share with Sue. With tears in her eyes, even as she bade farewell, she wished for Justin to follow his dreams and complete his long quest to find Angelou. It’s this that ties all of these sentiments together, for me. We all get older. We all leave our childhood behind us and begin to lead our adult lives in earnest. Our carefree days of questing and playing our days away, confident that in the end, everything will be all right, are replaced by planning, worrying, pressure, stress, failure, and other harsh realities of life. Here, Sue reminds us of the importance of not forgetting our dreams. We may not have the time or the energy that we did then, but whatever the obstacles, we must always go boldly in the direction of our dreams, hand-in-hand with those who love us, for we, too, will one day exit the adventure. In our final moments, what sweeter satisfaction could there be than to warmly smile at those who walked with us, and to look back on our journey with pride.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46203138</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 09:48:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ZX Spectrum Next on the Internet: Xberry Pi ESP01 and Pi Zero Upgrades</title><link>https://retrogamecoders.com/zx-spectrum-next-on-the-internet-xberry-pi-esp01-and-pi-zero-upgrades/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e1ce3412480c97fa"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m enjoying my Xberry Pi ZX Spectrum Next, but I have to say the ‘simple’ upgrade of getting it onto Wifi via the cheap and cheerful ESP 8266 was not fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While I had every intention of setting up my Speccy keyboard on the board’s matrix connector, I need to wait for a socket of the correct pitch. It turns out the Xberry Pi needs 0.2mm spacing and I have none in my parts box. Instead I figured do the other main upgrades, namely add a Pi Zero “accelerator” and the Wifi upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ZX Next Pi Zero Accelerator Upgrade&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fully expecting the Pi Zero to be the thing that caused me trouble, I was shocked that not only my soldering had gone perfectly but also the flashing of the SD card.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So many community members had advised to use a highly specific Pi Zero, I thought my spare board would be wrong. But it worked first time!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My pin header made the soldering trickier than usual, maybe it soaked a lot of heat? Just remember the header needs to go on the ‘wrong’ side and take your time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Pi Zero upgrade is hardly used currently but the ZX Next team keep hinting at future utility, and at least one game is in development that uses it as a kind of math coprocessor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So after running a TZX file and some SID tunes, I moved on to the ESP figuring I would have everything done quick as a flash. Pardon the pun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Adding Wifi to the Next&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Next can come with Wifi already installed apparently, and some Xberry bundles come with one as standard, but the chosen module is an ESP 01 / 8266 which is something I have on hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s precious little documentation for this kind of thing out there, but I did find YouTube videos that made everything look very straightforward. That should have been the first red flag!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;None of them showed installing the correct ESP firmware, what baud rate the Next expects, or even attaching the ESP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I picked out a board I was confident was working fine, attached it, successfully ran the ESP Updater.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After it confirmed the update, I tried to connect to wifi using the built-in Next menu item …. and failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact the ESP Updater did its thing suggests also the board was fine therefore I tried and failed all the many ways to get the “driver” to install.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I quickly started to hate this “Installing Driver…” message. There is no indication if anything is happening when it gets stuck there for ages, but other times it quickly quits back to the menu, again with no feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert: Even with everything now ‘working’, it often takes a lot more attempts than you would expect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To save anyone else the bother I went through, and potentially Future Chris, the key was to NOT update the ESP 01 firmware. Just use whatever your board came with by default. My working firmware is not even listed on the ESP Updater repo …&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I rummaged around and found another ESP board that had never had its firmware flashed. Using a breadboard I confirmed it was working and responding to AT commands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;CircuitPython Code to Communicate with ESP01 via UART&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
import board,binascii
import adafruit_pio_uart
# Define the UART pins (example using GP16 for TX and GP17 for RX)
# The actual pins depend on your specific wiring/board configuration.
UART_TX = board.GP16
UART_RX = board.GP17
# Initialize the UART connection
# The baudrate for the ESP01 is typically 115200
uart = adafruit_pio_uart.UART(UART_TX, UART_RX, baudrate=115200)

def send(s):
    uart.write(s+'\r\n')
    print(uart.read(255).decode())
send('AT+RST')
send('AT')
send('AT+GMR')
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This code allows you to hook the ESP01 up to pins 16 and 17 for UART, and 3.3v and GND.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Wifi on the ZX Spectrum Next … Finally!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again it didn’t work on the ZX Next right away, but I persisted and finally signs of life!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hope this helps someone else out there! I found it incredibly frustrating but now I am back to having fun with my ZX Next experience rather than regretting my choices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seems life might have been easier if a Pi Zero W was used instead of a Pi and an ESP8266, or even an ESP32, but perhaps there is a good reason they went with the little old ESP01.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46203499</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 10:52:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: AlgoDrill – Interactive drills to stop forgetting LeetCode patterns</title><link>https://algodrill.io</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46203581</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 11:09:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Brent's Encapsulated C Programming Rules (2020)</title><link>https://retroscience.net/brents-c-programming-rules.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a6789b19a8451298"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Brent's Encapsulated C Programming Rules&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below are some rules that I have developed over a long period of time writing fully encapsulated C programs. C is my favorite language and I love the freedom and exploration it allows me. I also love that it is so close to Assembly and I love writing assembly for much of the same reasons!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE: You may see references to ‘perfect encapsulation’ throughout. I offer both a ‘performance’ and a ‘pure encapsulation’ approach to C here (first two headers). So feel free to interpret the rest of the rules based on the approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JMP&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pure encapsulation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No encapsulation performance&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Memory ownership&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Avoid void*&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t over-complicate strings&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t over-complicate stdlib&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use utf8 strings&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t use char for memory array, use uint8_t&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use standard bool&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t use static or global variables&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Prefer inline over macro&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Test your functions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Write functions to do one thing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t write systems, write modular pieces (think UNIX)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Warnings are errors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If there is a standard, use it&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use float epsilon for 0 checking&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Zero set your structs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Big types first&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;More to come&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pure encapsulation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the great things about C is that it allows for “pure encapsulation”. What this means is that you can explain all the intent of your code through the header file and the developer who uses your lib/code never has to look at the actual implementations of the code. Now to take this a step further, well all know that C supports the &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt; keyword to group data, and we can also make the members of a struct hidden completely from the developer using the library. For example, we could declare the following header and C files:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;vec3.h&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#ifndef VEC3_H
#define VEC3_H

struct Vec3;

#endif
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;vec3.c&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include "vec3.h"

struct Vec3 {
	float x;
	float y;
	float z;
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you can see in the above code sample, if you were just to have the header file, you would not know that this vector is implemented using 3 &lt;code&gt;floats&lt;/code&gt;. This is very important for pure encapsulation. With this, you can completely control the behavior of the struct and it’s contents using readable functions and not worry about the developer using the code directly mutating the members of your &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt;. Now that you’ve created pure encapsulation, you are able to feel safe knowing that developers can’t new up the struct or abuse it’s contents from anywhere other than through the code you’ve written in your &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;No encapsulation performance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the flaws with pure encapsulation is that you can see a drop in performance. Having a bunch of functions to get inner members of a structure also blocks the compiler from optimizing it’s best. Member hiding is not usually because we don’t trust the end developer with the secrets of our structures, but is often so they don’t make mistakes by changing things they shouldn’t. Also member hiding helps so that we can easily update our code without changing the interface that developers rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That being said, if we are dealing with performance critical code, or just want extra optimization by our compiler (and/or to write less code); we can expose the members of our structure. However, let’s be smart about exposing these members so that developers don’t accidentally make mistakes with their new found power.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;, our best friend in this scenario. We can not only mark our members as &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; before their type, but also after their type. The general rule of thumb to remember is, if it is a pointer, the &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; goes after the type, otherwise put it before the type. In the simple example below, you can see how pointers have the &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; after, and the rest have &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; before their type declaration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct Employer {
	char* const name;
	const int years;
};

struct Employee {
	struct Employer* const employer;
	char* const name;
	const int age;
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this way we are able to expose the fields of the struct to the rest of the code for compiler optimizations, ease of access, etc; while also being able to prevent developers from directly assigning/changing the values of those fields. The obvious downside to this is that you will need to either create a macro, or manually cast assign the fields to change them in the implementation C file. I would recommend, if you are using C17, to use &lt;code&gt;_Generic&lt;/code&gt; and macros so you can create a single &lt;code&gt;#define OVERRIDE(field)&lt;/code&gt; type of macro and have the compiler throw if it finds an un-expected type. Of course, if you don’t want to use a macro, you can also create separate &lt;code&gt;inline&lt;/code&gt; functions to do the same (just might be harder to manage). Below is an example of how we can tell the compiler we want to explicitly change the value in the implementation c file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// employee.c file

void employee_set_age(struct Employee* employee, int newAge) {
	// Cast away the const and set it's value, the compiler should optimize this for you
	*(int*)&amp;amp;employee-&amp;gt;age = newAge;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Memory ownership&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With perfect encapsulation you are most of the way towards having good memory ownership. If you purely encapsulate your structs the only way for a developer to create a new instance of the struct would be through functions you create yourself. From this point you can create the &lt;code&gt;new&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;free&lt;/code&gt; functions to manage the memory of your struct. Below is an example building upon the previous code sample.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;vec3.h&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#ifndef VEC3_H
#define VEC3_H

struct Vec3;

struct Vec3* Vec3_new();
void Vec3_free(struct Vec3* vector);
void Vec3_print(struct Vec3* vector);

#endif
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;vec3.c&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include "vec3.h"
#include &amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt;

struct Vec3 { /* ... */ };

struct Vec3* Vec3_new()
{
	struct Vec3* v = malloc(sizeof(struct Vec3));
	v-&amp;gt;x = 0.0F;
	v-&amp;gt;y = 0.0F;
	v-&amp;gt;z = 0.0F;
	return v;
}

void Vec3_free(struct Vec3* vector)
{
	free(vector);
}

void Vec3_print(struct Vec3* vector)
{
	printf("&amp;lt;%f, %f, %f&amp;gt;", vector-&amp;gt;x, vector-&amp;gt;y, vector-&amp;gt;z);
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Above you can see that we encapsulate the creation, usage, and freeing of our &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt;. You would think, well with this, what else do we need to know about memory management? Well there is one more thing, more of a rule that you must follow more than anything else. The thing that declares the memory is the thing that should free the memory. We see this in action above, the &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; file that creates the memory in turn has a function for freeing the memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now let’s look at another example using a &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; to represent a string function. Here we have a function that takes a string and clones it (wrong way):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;char* strclone(const char* str)
{
	size_t len = strlen(s) + 1;
	char* clone = malloc(len);
	memcpy(clone, str, len);
	return clone;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now what is wrong with the memory management on this code? Answer, we are using &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt; to create memory and then return the string. Let’s take a look at the developer using this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;char* str = "Hello Brent!\0";
char* cpy = strclone(str);
printf(cpy);
free(cpy);	// Allowed?
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How is the developer suppose to know that they are to free the &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt;? For all they know the &lt;code&gt;strclone&lt;/code&gt; uses some-sort of pooling functionality to re-use a pool of memory, we can’t free that otherwise you risk seg-faulting. What is a better version of this?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;void strclone(const char* str, char** outCpy)
{
	size_t len = strlen(s) + 1;
	*outCpy = malloc(len);
	memcpy(outCpy, str, len);
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now with this version we make it explicit that the developer should manage their own object that they pass in. We use the hint name out as a prefix to the argument name to let them know memory will be allocated for this input variable. What does this look like to the developer?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;char* str = "Hello Brent!\0";
char* cpy;
strclone(str, &amp;amp;cpy);
printf(cpy);
free(cpy);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at this version, the developer knows they are in charge of freeing the &lt;code&gt;cpy&lt;/code&gt;, this is because they declare the variable in the first place, rather than being assigned from a function. If the developer follows our rule (The thing that declares the memory is the thing that should free the memory), they declared the variable/pointer so they should be the ones freeing it. Now I know you can argue all sorts of alternative setups for the return value, but the fact of the matter is that passing in a pointer to a pointer is much more clear of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Avoid void*&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One stigma people have against C is the use of &lt;code&gt;void*&lt;/code&gt;, some think it is necessary, some use it to solve problems quickly through the path of least resistance, I say that there are very few cases when &lt;code&gt;void*&lt;/code&gt; is acceptable and most of the time your current problem isn’t it. Like &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;void*&lt;/code&gt; is a lazy solution to a problem and causes all kinds of un-necessary runtime checking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In most cases you should create a &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt; that explicitly defines what type is accepted or stored. The biggest advantage of this approach is that you put the compiler to work for you. There are all sorts of compile-time checks that will prevent you from doing something you shouldn’t do. Also your IDE will be much more helpful when trying to navigate code as the IDE, nor the compiler, have any idea where a void* comes from or what it points to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t over-complicate strings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I want to live in the 2020 era of programming, that means I probably will wind up using more than one library to solve a problem. My new problem is that people think it is cute to typedef &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; to some other name and only accept that name in their code. In the era of UTF8, that is completely un-necessary and makes me have to do a lot of senseless casting. If you want to encapsulate that you are using a string (so I don’t know it) then cool, do that, but &lt;code&gt;typedef unsigned char* string&lt;/code&gt; is not it. Please stick to the good ol’ &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; for strings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t over-complicate stdlib&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TBD&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Use utf8 strings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Talking about strings, I’d like to point out that UTF-8 is fully compatible with ASCII, this means we don’t need special functions for special characters or non English characters. All of our usual suspects of functions work on UTF-8 such as &lt;code&gt;fopen&lt;/code&gt;! There are some helpful other things we can use thanks to compilers such as placing &lt;code&gt;u8&lt;/code&gt; in front of an in-line string:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;char* utf8 = u8"Hello World!";
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So in closing on the UTF-8 topic, please stop using &lt;code&gt;wchar_t&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;char16_t&lt;/code&gt;, and all those other variants (except when you are forced to, due to 3rd party libraries). With that, I’ll leave you with this helper function to get you started:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;size_t utf8len(const char* const str) {
    size_t len = 0;
    for (size_t i = 0; *str != 0; ++len) {
        int v0 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x80) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 7;
        int v1 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x40) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 6;
        int v2 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x20) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 5;
        int v3 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x10) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 4;
        str += 1 + v0 * v1 + v0 * v1 * v2 + v0 * v1 * v2 * v3;
    }
    return len;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE 1: A simplified version of this was proposed by Max Brauer on Stack Overflow to be:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;size_t utf8len(const char* str) {
    size_t len = 0;
    for (size_t i = 0; *str != 0; ++len) {
        int v01 = ((*str &amp;amp; 0x80) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 7) &amp;amp; ((*str &amp;amp; 0x40) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 6);
        int v2 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x20) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 5;
        int v3 = (*str &amp;amp; 0x10) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 4;
        str += 1 + ((v01 &amp;lt;&amp;lt; v2) | (v01 &amp;amp; v3));
    }
    return len;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE 2: This does not validate the utf8 string. I am not fond of making the length function also validate the string, for that we should create a separate method for validation. Using this table I found on Wikipedia we can construct a validation function (also this table was used for the length function).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;bool utf8valid(const char* const str) {
    if (str == NULL)
        return false;
    const char* c = str;
    bool valid = true;
    for (size_t i = 0; c[0] != 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; valid;) {
        valid = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x80) == 0
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xE0) == 0xC0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80)
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xF0) == 0xE0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[2] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80)
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xF8) == 0xF0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[2] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[3] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80);
        int v0 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x80) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 7;
        int v1 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x40) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 6;
        int v2 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x20) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 5;
        int v3 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x10) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 4;
        i += 1 + v0 * v1 + v0 * v1 * v2 + v0 * v1 * v2 * v3;
        c = str + i;
    }
    return valid;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE 3: Based on the same simplification previously discussed, this would become:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;bool utf8valid(const char* const str) {
    if (str == NULL)
        return false;
    const char* c = str;
    bool valid = true;
    for (size_t i = 0; c[0] != 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; valid;) {
        valid = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x80) == 0
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xE0) == 0xC0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80)
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xF0) == 0xE0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[2] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80)
            || ((c[0] &amp;amp; 0xF8) == 0xF0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[1] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[2] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (c[3] &amp;amp; 0xC0) == 0x80);
        int v01 = ((*str &amp;amp; 0x80) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 7) &amp;amp; ((*str &amp;amp; 0x40) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 6);
        int v2 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x20) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 5;
        int v3 = (c[0] &amp;amp; 0x10) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; 4;
        i += 1 + ((v01 &amp;lt;&amp;lt; v2) | (v01 &amp;amp; v3));
        c = str + i;
    }
    return valid;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE 4: Something that developers trip on is the file encoding for their source file. Be sure you are using UTF-8 encoding for your source file when typing UTF-8 strings directly into your source code. If you use the wrong encoding, the compiler may compile the inline string with the incorrect encoding, even with the &lt;code&gt;u8&lt;/code&gt; prefix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t use char for memory array, use uint8_t&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In making code readable, you should only use &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;unsigned char*&lt;/code&gt; for strings (character arrays). If you want a block of bytes/memory pointer, then you should use &lt;code&gt;uint8_t*&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;uint8_t&lt;/code&gt; is part of &lt;code&gt;stdint.h&lt;/code&gt;. This makes the code much more readable where memory is represented as an unsighned 8-bit array of numbers (byte array). Now you can trust when you see a &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; that it is referring to a UTF-8 (or ASCII) character array (text).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Use standard bool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one is easy:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include &amp;lt;stdbool.h&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t make defines for &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;False&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;FALSE&lt;/code&gt; and it’s true counterpart, please just use the standard library.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t use static or global variables&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So &lt;code&gt;static&lt;/code&gt; functions are fine, they are great for breaking up functions to be readable. However, &lt;code&gt;static&lt;/code&gt; variables are bad and almost always not needed. Remember that we are living in a world where our CPUs are not getting faster, they are just coming in larger quantities. Always think about threadability and controlling mutation. Even with a variable that is static to a &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; file and not global, you never know if someone is using threads to call your functions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Prefer inline over macro&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Functions that are &lt;code&gt;inline&lt;/code&gt; are much more readable, work better with your IDE code searching, and are much more readable when you get errors/warnings from the compiler. Some macros are great, don’t ban them altogether, but do consider if you can do what you need through an inline function first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Test your functions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;C is beautiful in the fact that you don’t need unit test frameworks to fully test your code. It’s lack of objects and hidden state make it even better for testing. If you create a function, make a test for it and give it your known test case arguments. Did I mention that I love not having to have a big complicated mocking library to fully test my code? If your function takes in a complicated struct for some reason, feel free to &lt;code&gt;define&lt;/code&gt; out/in a test function for creating the struct you expect to be testing (do NOT comprimise perfect encapsulation for the sake of testing).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Write functions to do one thing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, this isn’t a C only thing, but make sure your functions are not creating large call stacks. Feel free to use &lt;code&gt;static&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;static inline&lt;/code&gt; local functions to break up the readability of large functions if you just can’t seem to make functions do a single thing (for performance for example).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Don’t write systems, write modular pieces (think UNIX)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t write big complicated systems to cover many problems, even if things are losely related in many ways. It is better to break up your code into useful functional pieces and cleverly put them together to have complex behavior. The beauty of Unix is that you can get many things done through many small programs pieced together. In the same way, you should develop useful functions that can be pieced together through data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Warnings are errors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This one is a bit short. The idea is simple, warnings are errors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make sure ALL warnings are enabled (&lt;code&gt;/Wall&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make sure that you turn on warnings as errors&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: If you copied some source code from the internet that you need and it is producing warnings, turn it into a lib and use the lib, do not comprimise your code for other people’s un-checked code. You’d be surprised how many popular libraries fail warnings as errors test (often they develop assuming 32-bit code).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;If there is a standard, use it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was touched on before with &lt;code&gt;stdbool.h&lt;/code&gt;, but if there is a standard function or type, use it. Use things like &lt;code&gt;int32_t&lt;/code&gt; over just &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt; hoping that &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt; will be 32-bit. If there is a standard function for doing something, don’t re-invent the wheel. Wrapping standard functions such as &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;free&lt;/code&gt; I would consider a necessary evil if you are creating tools to detect memory leaks and the like though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Use float epsilon for 0 checking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First of all, don’t check a floating point value against &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;0.0F&lt;/code&gt;. Instead check it against Epsilon like in the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include &amp;lt;math.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;float.h&amp;gt;

int main(void)
{
	float x = 1.0F;
	x -= 1.0F;
	if (fabsf(x) &amp;lt;= FLT_EPSILON)
	{
		// ... The value is basically 0, do some stuff
	}
	return 0;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alternatively you can choose a fractionally small number like &lt;code&gt;0.0001F&lt;/code&gt; to check against if that is your cup of tea as well. The reason is floating point precision errors (which you probably know or have heard of by now). I enjoy &lt;code&gt;FLT_EPSILON&lt;/code&gt; because it is part of the &lt;code&gt;float.h&lt;/code&gt; lib and a standard for everyone to use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Zero Set Your Structs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One thing that would get me when developing in C is pointers inside of objects not being set to &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt;. Now I know I speak about hating that the idea of &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt; exists, but when working with other people’s code it is impossible for you not to run into a situation where you need to set a pointer to &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt;, pass a &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt; or check a pointer against &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt;. So do yourself a favor and always use &lt;code&gt;calloc&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;memset(&amp;amp;thing, 0, sizeof(thing))&lt;/code&gt; if it isn’t a pointer or new memory). Of course this doesn’t ban the use of &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt;, in fact you should continue to use it on buffers, but as programmers, we have a problem with not touching code that works and you think it is fine to just add in that extra field, but if it is a pointer and you don’t initialize it to &lt;code&gt;NULL&lt;/code&gt; where needed, you’re in for a world of hurt.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Big types first&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you create a structure, put the biggest types at the top of your struct and the smallest types at the bottom. Platforms like the x86 will magically help you with this (at a cost), but other platforms (like ARM) will generate SEGFALT if you don’t properly do this. This is because of padding in a struct. If you put a &lt;code&gt;bool&lt;/code&gt; as the first field and a &lt;code&gt;int32_t&lt;/code&gt; as the second field in a struct, like the one below, you will have a problem where you pack 1 byte, then 4 bytes into the struct, effectively having a 5 byte struct. The problem here is that the CPU is optimized to read along memory boundaries. When you &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt;, you won’t get an odd memory address for example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;struct Bad {
	bool first;
	int32_t second;
};

struct Good {
	int32_t first;
	bool second;
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More to come&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are inevitably more things I’ve forgotten about, but I’ve written this all in one sitting so this is good enough for now until I can update!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46203611</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 11:16:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mazda suitcase car, a portable three-wheeled vehicle that fits in the luggage</title><link>https://www.designboom.com/technology/rediscover-mazda-suitcase-car-portable-three-wheeled-vehicle-fits-luggage-12-06-2025/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf393ec4e326b4e5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;KEEP UP WITH OUR DAILY AND WEEKLY NEWSLETTERS&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;happening now! swiss mobility specialist schindler introduces its 2025 innovation, the schindler X8 elevator, bringing the company’s revolutionary design directly to cities like milan and basel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SOLARIS features retractable photovoltaic wings that form the core of the motorcycle's solar-harvesting system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the backpack helps users looking for housing to sustainably navigate their situation until they obtain permanent shelter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the enduring MINI x paul smith collaboration thrives on irreverent design, shared confidence, and joyful, hidden details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;connections: +1210&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;dubbed the austrian power giants, these electricity structures are molded depending on the fauna representing the state.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;connections: +700&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46204139</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 12:20:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kaiju – General purpose 3D/2D game engine in Go and Vulkan with built in editor</title><link>https://github.com/KaijuEngine/kaiju</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d71a40118926331e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kaiju is a 2D/3D game engine written in Go (Golang) backed by Vulkan. The goal of the engine is to use a modern, easy, systems level programming language, with a focus on simplicity, to create a new kind of game engine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📄 2D / 🧊 3D Game Engine&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🪟 Windows&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🐧 Linux&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🤖 Android (NEW, support now functional)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🍎 Mac (support is currently WIP)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🤖👉⌨️ Local AI (LLM) interop&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;g-emoji&gt;⚠️&lt;/g-emoji&gt;🚧🏗️👷♂️ Work in progress, under heavy development&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🚚 Faster builds than other game engines&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🔥 Better performance than other game engines (9x faster than Unity out of the box)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;💾 Less memory than other engines&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mailing list &amp;lt;- Recommended for detailed updates&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Discord server&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Brent Farris on X/Twitter&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The current version of the base engine renders extremely fast, faster than most would think a garbage collected language could go. In my testing a release mode build of a game in Unity with nothing but a black background and a cube runs at about 1,600 FPS. In Kaiju, the same thing runs at around 5,400 FPS on the same machine. In fact, a complete game, with audio, custom cursors, real time PBR rendering with real time shadows, UI, and more runs at 2,712 FPS (in "debug" mode) screenshots or it didn't happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love C, and because I love C and found out that Ken Thompson played a part in designing Go, I gave Go a chance. It has been such a joy to use and work with I decided to port my C game engine to Go. Go is a modern system-level language that allows me to write code the way I want to write code and even have the opportunity to do some crazy things if I want to (no strings attached). Also the simplicity and "just works" of writing Assembly code was a great boost to my happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's more, it's a language that other developers can easily learn and jump right into extending the engine/editor. No need for developers to re-figure out some bespoke macros or crazy templating nonsense. It's flat, easy, straight forward, and the foot-gun is hidden behind some walls, but there if you want it. Furthermore, developers can write their games in Go directly, no need for some alternative language that is different from the engine code (but we'll include Lua for modding).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am creating this section because I get asked about it when I mention "Go", possibly not realizing that most public game engines use a garbage collector (GC).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The GC is actually a feature I'm happy with (shocker coming from a C guy). Well, the reason is simple, if you're going to make a game engine that the public will use and needs to be stable, you need a garbage collector. Unity has C# (and possibly an internal GC as well), Unreal has a GC (and it could use a tune up if you ask me), Godot has a GC albeit their scripting language or when you use C#. It is actually very important for public engines to have a GC because people are only human and make a lot of mistakes, mistakes they'll blame on you (the engine developer) before they blame themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Coincidentally, the overall design I have for the engine plays very well with the GC and last I measured, I have a net-0 heap allocation while running (may need a new review). If you don't abuse the GC, you shouldn't generally feel it, it runs concurrently as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'll be the first to admit, I think the developers of Go can create a better GC than I can, and probably better than Unreal and Unity too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though the engine is production ready, the editor is not, feel free to join and contribute to its development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the latest updates, please join the Discord or check my Twitter/X.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please review the Ad-Hoc editor readme&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please see the documentation on how to get started and compile the engine&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46205519</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 14:51:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Engineers: Stop trying to win other people's game</title><link>https://www.anthonyputignano.com/p/the-western-front-advantage-how-junior</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46205532</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 14:53:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New Pebble Device</title><link>https://repebble.com/blog/meet-pebble-index-01-external-memory-for-your-brain</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5c6b48dfd9872b65"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Catch your best ideas before they slip through your fingers&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you ever have flashes of insight or an idea worth remembering? This happens to me 5-10 times every day. If I don’t write down the thought immediately, it slips out of my mind. Worst of all, I remember that I’ve forgotten something and spend the next 10 minutes trying to remember what it is. So I invented external memory for my brain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Introducing Pebble Index 01 - a small ring with a button and microphone. Hold the button, whisper your thought, and it’s sent to your phone. It’s added to your notes, set as a reminder, or saved for later review.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Index 01 is designed to become muscle memory, since it’s always with you. It’s private by design (no recording until you press the button) and requires no internet connection or paid subscription. It’s as small as a wedding band and comes in 3 colours. It’s made from durable stainless steel and is water-resistant. Like all Pebble products, it’s extremely customizable and built with open source software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the best part: the battery lasts for years. You never need to charge it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-order today for $75. After worldwide shipping begins in March 2026, the price will go up to $99.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;#Design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve worn my Index 01 for several months, I can safely say that it has changed my life - just like with Pebble, I couldn’t go back to a world without this. There are so many situations each day where my hands are full (while biking or driving, washing dishes, wrangling my kids, etc) and I need to remember something. A random sampling of my recent recordings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Set a timer for 3pm to go pick up the kids&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Remind me to phone the pharmacy at 11am&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Peter is coming by tomorrow at 11:30am, add that to my calendar&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Jerry recommends reading Breakneck&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mark wants a Black/Red PT2&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before, I would take my phone out of my pocket to jot these down, but I couldn’t always do that (eg, while bicycling). I also wanted to start using my phone less, especially in front of my kids.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially, we experimented by building this as an app on Pebble, since it has a mic and I’m always wearing one. But, I realized quickly that this was suboptimal - it required me to use my other hand to press the button to start recording (lift-to-wake gestures and wake-words are too unreliable). This was tough to use while bicycling or carrying stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then a genius electrical engineer friend of mine came up with an idea to fit everything into a tiny ring. It is the perfect form factor! Honestly, I’m still amazed that it all fits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The design needed to satisfy several critical conditions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Must work reliably 100% of the time. If it didn’t work or failed to record a thought, I knew I would take it off and revert back to my old habit of just forgetting things.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It had to have a physical press-button, with a satisfying click-feel. I want to know for sure if the button is pressed and my thought is captured.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Long battery life - every time you take something off to charge, there’s a chance you’ll forget to put it back on.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Must be privacy-preserving. These are your inner thoughts. All recordings must be processed and stored on your phone. Only record when the button is pressed.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It had to be as small as a wedding band. Since it’s worn on the index finger, if it were too large or bulky, it would hit your phone while you held it in your hand.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Water resistance - must be able to wash hands, shower, and get wet.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve been working on this for a while, testing new versions and making tweaks. We’re really excited to get this out into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are a few of my favourite things about Index 01:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It does one thing really well - it helps me remember things.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It’s discreet. It's not distracting. It doesn't take you out of the moment.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There’s no AI friend persona and it’s not always recording.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It’s inexpensive. We hope you try it and see if you like it as well!&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;#Key Details&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Available in 3 colours and 8 sizes &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Colours: polished silver, polished gold, and matte black&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;US ring sizes: 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;You can pre-order now and pick your size/colour later before your ring ships.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cost and availability: Pre-order price is $75, rises to $99 later. Ships worldwide, beginning in March.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Works with iPhone and Android: We overcame Apple’s best efforts to make life terrible for 3rd party accessory makers and have Index 01 working well on iOS and Android.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Extremely private and secure: Your thoughts are processed by open source speech-to-text (STT) and AI models locally on your phone. You can read the code and see exactly how it works - our Pebble mobile app is open source. Higher-quality STT is available through an optional cloud service.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No charging: The battery lasts for up to years of average use. After the end of its life, send your ring back to us for recycling.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;On-ring storage: Recording works even if your phone is out of range. Up to 5 minutes of audio can be stored on-ring, then synced later.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No speaker or vibrating motor: This is an input device only. There is an RGB LED, but it’s rarely used (to save battery life and to reduce distraction).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Works great with Pebble or other smartwatches: After recording, the thought will appear on your watch, and you can check that it’s correct. You can ask questions like ‘What’s the weather today?’ and see the answer on your watch.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Raw audio playback: Very helpful if STT doesn’t work perfectly due to wind or loud background noises.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Actions: While the primary task is remembering things for you, you can also ask it to do things like ’Send a Beeper message to my wife - running late’ or answer simple questions that could be answered by searching the web. You can configure button clicks to control your music - I love using this to play/pause or skip tracks. You can also configure where to save your notes and reminders (I have it set to add to Notion).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Customizable and hackable: Configure single/double button clicks to control whatever you want (take a photo, turn on lights, Tasker, etc). Add your own voice actions via MCP. Or route the audio recordings directly to your own app or server!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;99+ languages: Speech to text and local LLM support over 99 languages! Naturally, the quality of each may vary.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;#Future Plans&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let me be very clear - Index 01 is designed at its core to be a device that helps you remember things. We want it to be 100% reliable at its primary task. But we’re leaving the side door open for folks to customize, build new interactions and actions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s how I’m thinking about it - a single click-hold + voice input will be routed to the primary memory processing path. Double-click-hold + voice input would be routed to a more general purpose voice agent (think ChatGPT with web search). Responses from the agent would be presented on Pebble (eg ‘What’s the weather tomorrow?’, ‘When’s the next northbound Caltrain?’) or other smartwatches (as a notification). Maybe this could even be an input for something like ChatGPT Voice Mode, enabling you to hear the AI response from your earbuds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The built in actions, set reminder, create note, alarms, etc, are actually MCPs - basically mini apps that AI agents know how to operate. They run locally in WASM within the Pebble mobile app (no cloud MCP server required). Basically any MCP server can be used with the system, so intrepid folks may have fun adding various actions like Beeper, Google Calendar, weather, etc that already offer MCPs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not everything will be available at launch, but this is the direction we are working towards. There will be 3 ways to customize your Index 01:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trigger actions via button clicks - configure a single or double click to do things like take a photo, control your Home Assistant smart home, Tasker function, unlock your car. This will work better on Android since iOS Shortcuts doesn’t have an open API.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trigger actions via voice input - write an MCP to do….basically anything? This is pretty open ended.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Route your voice recordings and/or transcriptions to your own webhook - or skip our AI processing entirely and send every recording to your own app or webapp.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How does it work?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People usually wear it on the index finger. Inside the ring is a button, a microphone, a Bluetooth chip, memory, and a battery that lasts for years. Click the button with your thumb, talk into the mic, and it records to internal memory. When your phone is in range, the recording is streamed to the Pebble app. It’s converted to text on-device, then processed by an on-device large language model (LLM) which selects an action to take (create note, add to reminders, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When do I pick my size?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll be able to pick your ring size and color after placing a pre-order. If you have a 3D printer, you can print our CAD designs to try on. We’re also planning a sizing kit. You can view the measurements of the inner diameter of each ring size.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How long does the battery last?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Roughly 12 to 15 hours of recording. On average, I use it 10-20 times per day to record 3-6 second thoughts. That’s up to 2 years of usage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is it secure and private?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, extremely. The connection between ring and phone is encrypted. Recordings are processed locally on your phone in the open-source Pebble app. The app works offline (no internet connection) and does not require a cloud service. An optional cloud storage system for backing up recordings is available. Our plan is for this to be optionally encrypted, but we haven’t built it yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is a paid subscription required?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What kind of battery is inside?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Index 01 uses silver-oxide batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why can’t it be recharged?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We considered this but decided not to for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You’d probably lose the charger before the battery runs out!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adding charge circuitry and including a charger would make the product larger and more expensive.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You send it back to us to recycle.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wait, it’s single use?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes. We know this sounds a bit odd, but in this particular circumstance we believe it’s the best solution to the given set of constraints. Other smart rings like Oura cost $250+ and need to be charged every few days. We didn’t want to build a device like that. Before the battery runs out, the Pebble app notifies and asks if you’d like to order another ring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is it always listening?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No. It only records while the button is pressed. It’s not designed to record your whole life, or meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if the speech-to-text processing misses a word or something?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can always listen to the each recording in the app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why no touchpad?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We experimented with a touchpad, but found it too easy to accidentally swipe and press. Also, nothing beats the feedback of a real gosh darn pressable button.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is there a speaker or vibrating motor?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No. The button has a great click-feel to indicate when you are pressing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does it do health tracking like Oura?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nope&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How durable and water-resistant is it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s primarily made from stainless steel 316, with a liquid silicone rubber (LSR) button. It’s water-resistant to 1 meter. You can wash your hands, do dishes, and shower with it on, but we don’t recommend swimming with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does it work with iPhone and Android?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love customizing and hacking on my devices. What could I do with Index 01?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lots of stuff! Control things with the buttons. Route raw audio or transcribed text directly to your own app via webhook. Use MCPs (also run locally on-device! No cloud server required) to add more actions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is this an AI friend thingy or always-recording device?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How far along is development?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve been working on this in the background to watch development. It helps that our Pebble Time 2 partner factory is also building Index 01! We’re currently in the DVT stage, testing pre-production samples. We’ll start a wider alpha test in January with a lot more people. Here’s some shots from the pre-production assembly line:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46205661</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 15:03:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple's Slow AI Pace Becomes a Strength as Market Grows Weary of Spending</title><link>https://finance.yahoo.com/news/apple-slow-ai-pace-becomes-104658095.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5f1d1981b3685bf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Bloomberg) -- Shares of Apple Inc. were battered earlier this year as the iPhone maker faced repeated complaints about its lack of an artificial intelligence strategy. But as the AI trade faces increasing scrutiny, that hesitance has gone from a weakness to a strength — and it’s showing up in the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through the first six months of 2025, Apple was the second-worst performer among the Magnificent Seven tech giants, as its shares tumbled 18% through the end of June. That has reversed since then, with the stock soaring 35%, while AI darlings like Meta Platforms Inc. and Microsoft Corp. slid into the red and even Nvidia Corp. underperformed. The S&amp;amp;P 500 Index rose 10% in that time, and the tech-heavy Nasdaq 100 Index gained 13%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most Read from Bloomberg&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;NJ’s Montclair Cuts School Staff and Mulls March Tax-Hike Vote&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Trump Replaces Architect to Lead $300 Million Ballroom Design&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Owner of NYC’s Fordham Landing Housing Project Files Bankruptcy&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Democrats Want Probe of Trump Officials and Immigration Deals&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It is remarkable how they have kept their heads and are in control of spending, when all of their peers have gone the other direction,” said John Barr, portfolio manager of the Needham Aggressive Growth Fund, which owns Apple shares.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a result, Apple now has a $4.1 trillion market capitalization and the second biggest weight in the S&amp;amp;P 500, leaping over Microsoft and closing in on Nvidia. The shift reflects the market’s questioning of the hundreds of billions of dollars Big Tech firms are throwing at AI development, as well as Apple’s positioning to eventually benefit when the technology is ready for mass use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“While they most certainly will incorporate more AI into the phones over time, Apple has avoided the AI arms race and the massive capex that accompanies it,” said Bill Stone, chief investment officer at Glenview Trust Company, who owns the stock and views it as “a bit of an anti-AI holding.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, the rally has made Apple’s stock pricier than it has been in a long time. The shares are trading for around 33 times expected earnings over the next 12 months, a level they’ve only hit a few times in the past 15 years, with a high of 35 in September 2020. The stock’s average multiple over that time is less than 19 times. Apple is now the second most expensive stock in the Bloomberg Magnificent Seven Index, trailing only Tesla Inc.’s whopping valuation of 203 times forward earnings. Apple’s shares climbed about 0.5% in early Tuesday trading.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s really hard to see how the stock can continue to compound value at a level that makes this a compelling entry point,” said Craig Moffett, co-founder of research firm MoffettNathanson. “The obvious question is, are investors overpaying for Apple’s defensiveness? We think so.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46205724</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 15:08:24 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>