<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 23:09:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Teardown of Apple 40W Dynamic Power Adapter with 60W Max (A3365)</title><link>https://www.chargerlab.com/teardown-of-apple-40w-dynamic-power-adapter-with-60w-max-a3365/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b55b1e21c132dd0a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On September 10th, Apple held its 2025 Fall Event, unveiling the iPhone 17 lineup alongside a brand-new product category—iPhone Air. Among the announcements, one product that stood out was Apple’s new 40W Dynamic Power Adapter, which gained attention for its compact design and ability to dynamically deliver up to 60W of total output power.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The charger is now available on Apple’s official website, priced at $39 USD. According to Apple, when used with an iPhone 17 series device, the adapter can charge the phone to 50% in approximately 20 minutes—offering significantly faster charging performance compared to the previous generation. Despite the substantial power upgrade, the adapter maintains a highly compact form factor—roughly the same size as Apple’s standard 20W charger. It also features foldable prongs for improved portability and travel convenience. In the following teardown, we take a closer look at the internal design and power distribution architecture of Apple’s latest fast charger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Product Appearance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The front of the packaging features the Apple logo, product name, and an image of the adapter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The back of the packaging displays a simplified diagram of the adapter and its ports, along with CE certification and other information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One side of the packaging has a specification label attached.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The opposite side features a label indicating the manufacturing date and "Made in China" origin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The packaging includes the charger along with the user manual and other documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The charger is wrapped in protective paper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It features a design similar to the 35W dual USB-C charger (model A2579).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The small recessed areas on both sides of the body facilitate easy plugging and unplugging.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The output side features a single USB-C port with a white plastic insert.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bottom is printed with specification details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Model: A3365&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Input: 100-240V\~ 50/60Hz 1.5A (USB PD)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Output: (AVS) 15-20V 2A \[3.0A DPS] or (AVS) 9-15V 2.67A \[3.0A DPS] or 9V 3A or 5V 3A&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maximum total output power: 60W LPS&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The charger has passed CCC certification and Level VI energy efficiency certification.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It features foldable prongs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The length of the charger is about 45.72 mm (1.8 inches).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The width is about 45.73 mm (1.8 inches).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thickness is about 28.11 mm (1.11 inches).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Its size is nearly identical to that of the Apple 20W charger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is slightly smaller than the 35W dual USB-C charger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's how big it is in the hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The weight is about 80 g (2.82 oz).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChargerLAB POWER-Z KM003C shows that it supports PD3.0 and DCP charging protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it has four fixed PDOs of 5V3A, 9V3A, 15V2.67A, and 20V2A.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When used to charge the iPhone 16 Pro Max, the charging power is about 27.23W.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When charging the MacBook Air M3 2024, the charging power is about 55.94W, successfully activating the 60W dynamic fast charging feature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Teardown&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, let's take it apart to see its internal components and structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remove the bottom casing, and it is revealed that the enclosure uses a combination of snap-fit clips and ultrasonic welding for sealing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The input side features a contact-based power delivery design. The inner side of the casing is lined with a graphite thermal pad and has been treated for insulation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remove the PCBA module.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The inner side of the other half of the casing is lined with the graphite thermal insulation pad and the protective rubber cushion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;High-temperature resistant insulating tape is also applied along the sides.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The length of the PCBA module is about 42.12 mm (1.66 inches).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The width is about 39.66 mm (1.56 inches).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thickness is about 23.27 mm (0.92 inches).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One side of the PCBA module and the top of the output end are covered with protective foam pads.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A protective pad is also placed between the two high-voltage electrolytic filter capacitors on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The top-mounted high-voltage electrolytic filter capacitor and the transformer are secured with adhesive for added stability and insulation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The solid capacitors for output filtering are also secured with adhesive, and an insulating sheet is attached to the left side of the plastic casing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remove the foam pads and black adhesive. The transformer is wrapped in copper foil, and the side near the secondary winding is reinforced and insulated with a plastic casing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The PCBA module's input side features metal contact plates for power delivery along with a supporting plastic frame.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This side contains common mode chokes, a capacitor supplying power to the master control chip, and Y capacitors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the opposite side, two high-voltage electrolytic capacitors are mounted horizontally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On both sides of the output, there are Y capacitors and solid capacitors, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remove the capacitors, transformer, and other components. A plastic bracket is installed at the bottom to provide support and isolate the PCB.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The front side of the PCB features an SMD fuse and the master control chip.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The back side of the PCB contains the bridge rectifier, differential mode choke, synchronous rectifier, protocol chip, and output VBUS MOSFET.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disassemble the capacitors, transformer, and other components. Let’s take a closer look at the specifications and functions of these individual components.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The SMD fuse is from WalterFuse with a rated current of 3.15A.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two common mode chokes are arranged in a two-stage design to more effectively filter out EMI interference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The safety X2 capacitor is wrapped with copper foil for shielding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has a specification of 0.1μF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is connected via soldered copper strips.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The input-side bridge rectifier is from DIODES, model RTT10KL, and uses a TTL package.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The high-voltage filter capacitors are from NCC, each rated at 400V 47μF, connected in parallel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The differential mode choke has a specification of 13μH.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The master control chip is from PI, marked with ZN1612F, a custom model for Apple. It integrates the primary controller, high-voltage MOSFET, synchronous rectifier controller, and feedback functions, offering high integration and reduced external components. This simplifies fast charging power circuit design. The chip uses an InSOP-T28D package.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The capacitor supplying power to the master control chip is from Lelon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is rated at 50V, 22μF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The transformer is manufactured by Sumida.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Close-up of three black Y capacitors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The synchronous rectifier is from RECTRON, model RM85N100DF. It is an NMOS transistor with a voltage rating of 100V and an on-resistance of 4.6mΩ, packaged in a DFN 5x6-8L form factor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The three solid capacitors for output filtering are from Nichicon, each rated at 25V 270μF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The protocol chip is from Infineon, model CYPDC1185B2-32E, housed in a 32-pin QFN package.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The TI TLV9001 is a single-channel, 1MHz, rail-to-rail input and output operational amplifier with a voltage range of 1.8–5.5V, packaged in a SOT-23 (5) form factor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The VBUS MOSFET is also from RECTRON, model RM80N30DN. It is an NMOS transistor rated for 30V with an on-resistance of 3.8mΩ, packaged in a DFN 3x3 form factor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thermistor monitors the internal temperature and dynamically adjusts the power level to reduce output power when the temperature rises.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Close-up of the sampling resistor used to detect the output current.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pins of the USB-C socket are extended and soldered onto the PCBA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, those are all components of the Apple 40W Dynamic Power Adapter with 60W Max.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Summary of ChargerLAB&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the component list of the Apple 40W Dynamic Power Adapter with 60W Max for your convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It features a design similar to the 35W dual USB-C charger and comes with foldable prongs. The unique dynamic power delivery can be understood as "peak 60W, stable 40W," intelligently adjusting output power based on the device’s needs. This ensures it meets the charging requirements of the iPhone while also accommodating high-power charging scenarios for the MacBook. Given the increased charging power of the iPhone 17 series, this new adapter is definitely worth considering for new device users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After taking it apart, we found that it uses the highly integrated PI power chip ZN1612F, paired with the RECTRON RM85N100DF synchronous rectifier. The output is controlled by an Infineon CYPDC1185B2-32E protocol chip, with filtering handled by capacitors from NCC and Nichicon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The internal thermistor monitors the internal temperature to enable dynamic power switching. The charger’s casing remains robust as usual, with graphite thermal pads and foam cushions applied on the inside to assist with heat dissipation and protection. The PCBA module is further reinforced and insulated with foam pads and a plastic bracket, demonstrating reliable workmanship.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Related Articles：&lt;lb/&gt;1. Apple iPhone 17 Series Debuts With 40W Dynamic Power Adapter and PD 3.2 AVS Fast Charging&lt;lb/&gt;2. Hands-On Guide: ChargerLAB POWER-Z KM003C Load Test of Apple’s 40W Dynamic Power Adapter&lt;lb/&gt;3. What's Difference Between Two Apple 35W Charger (Compact and Traditional)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45289150</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 13:04:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: I Parallelized RNN Training from O(T) to O(log T) Using CUDA</title><link>https://dhruvmsheth.github.io/projects/gpu_pogramming_curnn/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e691829d45368af0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;An implementation of parallelizable GRUs and LSTMs for CS179 in CUDA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Resource&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Link&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Project Repository&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;GitHub&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;For my final project in CS179: GPU Programming, I decided to implement the paper “Were RNNs All We Needed?” by Feng et al. The paper’s core claim is that by making minor simplifications to LSTMs and GRUs, their recurrence can be expressed in a form amenable to the parallel scan algorithm. This changes their training and inference from an $O(T)$ sequential process into an $O(\log T)$ parallel one, which helps with GPU acceleration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My goal was to verify this claim by building both the simplified models (minGRU and minLSTM) and a custom CUDA implementation of the parallel scan to see how much of a speedup was actually achievable. The focus was less on the machine learning application and more on the raw computational performance and the experience of parallelizing a traditionally sequential algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recurrent Neural Networks, by their very nature, process sequences one step at a time. The hidden state at time step $t$, denoted $h_t$, is a function of the input $x_t$ and the previous hidden state, $h_{t-1}$. This dependency is the fundamental barrier to parallelization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at a standard GRU. The update equations are: \(r_t = \sigma(W_{ir}x_t + b_{ir} + W_{hr}h_{t-1} + b_{hr})\) \(z_t = \sigma(W_{iz}x_t + b_{iz} + W_{hz}h_{t-1} + b_{hz})\) \(n_t = \tanh(W_{in}x_t + b_{in} + r_t \odot (W_{hn}h_{t-1} + b_{hn}))\) \(h_t = (1 - z_t) \odot n_t + z_t \odot h_{t-1}\)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reset gate ($r_t$) and update gate ($z_t$) both explicitly depend on $h_{t-1}$. You simply cannot compute the gates for the entire sequence in one shot, because each step requires the output from the one before it. This forces a sequential loop, which is notoriously inefficient on parallel hardware like GPUs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crux of the paper is to remove this direct dependency. The simplified models, minGRU and minLSTM, redefine the gates to depend only on the current input, $x_t$.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For minGRU, the gates are simplified to:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recurrence then becomes: \(h_t = (1 - z_t) \odot h_{t-1} + z_t \odot \tilde{h}_t\)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This equation is now in the form $h_t = a_t \odot h_{t-1} + b_t$, where:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crucially, because $z_t$ and $\tilde{h}_t$ only depend on $x_t$, we can compute the entire sequence of $(a_t, b_t)$ pairs in parallel with a single, large matrix multiplication. The problem has now shifted from a complex sequential dependency to resolving a linear recurrence relation. A similar simplification is applied to LSTMs to create minLSTM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This linear recurrence is a classic computer science problem that can be solved efficiently with a parallel scan (also known as a prefix sum). The scan operation takes a sequence and an associative binary operator $\oplus$, and computes the prefix results. For our recurrence, the operator is slightly more complex than simple addition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we have a transformation $(A, B)$ representing $h_{out} = A \cdot h_{in} + B$, we can define an associative operator $\oplus$ to compose two such transformations: \((A_2, B_2) \oplus (A_1, B_1) = (A_2 A_1, A_2 B_1 + B_2)\)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With this operator, we can use an algorithm like Blelloch’s scan, which performs the computation in two phases (up-sweep and down-sweep) on a tree-like structure. This reduces the number of sequential steps from $O(T)$ to $O(\log T)$, making it a perfect fit for the GPU’s architecture. For numerical stability, the paper and my implementation use a log-space version of this scan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To measure the real-world impact, I compared three implementation paths:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;for t in range(T): h_t = cell(x_t, h_{t-1})&lt;/code&gt;. This represents the classic, non-parallelizable RNN.&lt;p&gt;I ran benchmarks on my personal machine (Intel i9-12900K, RTX 4090).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;$T$&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;CPU-seq&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;CPU-scan&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;GPU-scan&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;256&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;634 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;32.8 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;25.8 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1,024&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2,395 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;97.6 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;92.1 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4,096&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5,493 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;300 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;340 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;16,384&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;–&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2,683 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1,333 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;65,536&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;–&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;10,989 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5,330 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;T&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;CPU-seq&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;CPU-scan&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;GPU-scan&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;256&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;701.0 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;37.0 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;22.0 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1,024&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2,966.7 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;96.8 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;107.8 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4,096&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;12,035.1 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;416.5 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;431.5 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;16,384&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;–&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2,993.6 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1,693.9 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;65,536&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;–&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;13,005.4 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;6,709.8 ms&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Observations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;CPU-seq&lt;/code&gt; vs &lt;code&gt;CPU-scan&lt;/code&gt;) provides a massive, constant-factor speedup (around 10x), but the runtime still scales linearly, $O(T)$.&lt;p&gt;To understand the GPU performance better, I used NVIDIA’s Nsight Compute profiler. The initial implementation launched thousands of tiny kernels, one for each time step, which is a classic anti-pattern in GPU programming due to launch overhead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My first major optimization was to fuse the gate computations for all time steps into a single, large kernel (&lt;code&gt;min_gru_extract_scan_params_kernel&lt;/code&gt;) that uses shared memory tiling to manage weights and inputs efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s a snapshot of the kernel performance breakdown at $T=4096$ after this optimization:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="5"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Rank&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Kernel&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Time/launch&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Launches&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;% wall-time&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="5"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;min_gru_extract_scan_params_kernel&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;180 $\mu$s&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;8 %&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="5"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2–9&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;compose_offset_kernel&lt;/code&gt; (Scan Up-Sweep)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;~3 $\mu$s&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;12&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;&amp;lt; 1 %&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="5"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;10–&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;apply_scan_op_kernel&lt;/code&gt; (Scan Down-Sweep)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;~2 $\mu$s&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4096&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;10 %&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;11–&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;matvec_kernel&lt;/code&gt; (Output Projection)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;~93 $\mu$s&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4096&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;72 %&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The profiling revealed a few things:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;matvec_kernel&lt;/code&gt;), which consumes 72% of the runtime. This is because I was still launching one kernel per time step (4096 launches!), leading to low occupancy and terrible memory bandwidth utilization (only 23 GB/s).&lt;code&gt;matvec&lt;/code&gt; launches with a single cuBLAS GEMM call ($C = A \cdot W^T$). This would eliminate the kernel launch overhead and leverage a highly optimized library routine, likely bringing the total latency down significantly.&lt;p&gt;I made this project as part of my final assignment for my GPU Programming course, CS 179 at Caltech. This project was a great hands-on lesson in parallel algorithms. The claims in “Were RNNs All We Needed?” did seem to hold up: by reformulating the recurrence, RNNs can indeed be parallelized, and the performance gains on GPUs are substantial for long sequences. One of the reasons why this paper gained criticism from the CS commmunity was because there weren’t many experiments to back the claim that miniRNNs performed any better than transformers - and from my rusty recollection of the paper - the only benchmarks the miniRNNs outperformed transformers were niche targetted datasets that did not transfer to real-world benchmarks. Sure, with the parallelization and ripping away unncessary complexity from RNNs, miniRNNs were much more efficient but it was never the end-all be-all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I remember Francois’s quote on this paper from his X thread:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interesting work on reviving RNNs. https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01201 – in general the fact that there are many recent architectures coming from different directions that roughly match Transformers is proof that architectures aren’t fundamentally important in the curve-fitting paradigm (aka deep learning)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Curve-fitting is about embedding a dataset on a curve. The critical factor is the dataset, not the specific hard-coded bells and whistles that constrain the curve’s shape. As long as your curve is sufficiently expressive all architectures will converge to the same performance in the large-data regime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have a different take on this. All progress in the language modelling in the last decade has come from changes in architectures to be able to generate rich, more expressive curves that fit the target dataset better. If we blindly apply the bitter lesson and throw enough compute to different architectures (reasonable ones), it would be a good signal to see which architecture hits the wall the fastest and which one continues generalizing rather than all converging in the same way eventually.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45291903</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 16:47:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MapSCII – World map in terminal</title><link>https://github.com/rastapasta/mapscii</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ecc3b87ab9807886"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A node.js based Vector Tile to Braille and ASCII renderer for xterm-compatible terminals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ telnet mapscii.me&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're on Windows, use the open source telnet client PuTTY to connect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use your mouse to drag and zoom in and out!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Discover Point-of-Interests around any given location&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Highly customizable layer styling with Mapbox Styles support&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Connect to any public or private vector tile server&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Or just use the supplied and optimized OSM2VectorTiles based one&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Work offline and discover local VectorTile/MBTiles&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compatible with most Linux and OSX terminals&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Highly optimized algorithms for a smooth experience&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;100% pure JavaScript! 😎&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With a modern node installation available, just start it with&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npx mapscii
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you haven't already got Node.js &amp;gt;= version 10, then go get it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install -g mapscii
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're on OSX, or get an error about file permissions, you may need to do &lt;code&gt;sudo npm install -g mapscii&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In any of the supported Linux distros:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo snap install mapscii
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(This snap is maintained by @nathanhaines)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is pretty simple too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;mapscii
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Arrows up, down, left, right to scroll around&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Press a or z to zoom in and out&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Press c to switch to block character mode&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Press q to quit&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your terminal supports mouse events you can drag the map and use your scroll wheel to zoom in and out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;x256&lt;/code&gt;for converting RGB values to closest xterm-256 color code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;term-mouse&lt;/code&gt;for mouse handling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;keypress&lt;/code&gt;for input handling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;string-width&lt;/code&gt;to determine visual string lengths&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;vector-tile&lt;/code&gt;for VectorTile parsing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;pbf&lt;/code&gt;for Protobuf decoding&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;mbtiles&lt;/code&gt;for MBTiles parsing&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;earcut&lt;/code&gt;for polygon triangulation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;rbush&lt;/code&gt;for 2D spatial indexing of geo and label data&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;bresenham&lt;/code&gt;for line point calculations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;simplify-js&lt;/code&gt;for polyline simplifications&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;node-fetch&lt;/code&gt;for HTTP requests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;env-paths&lt;/code&gt;to determine where to persist downloaded tiles&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;MapSCII&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;GeoJSON support via geojson-vt&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;CLI support&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
              &lt;item&gt;[-] startup parameters &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;TileSource&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Style&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;center position&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;zoom&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;demo mode?&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
            &lt;/list&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;[-] startup parameters &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;mouse control&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
              &lt;item&gt;hover POIs/labels&lt;/item&gt;
              &lt;item&gt;hover maybe even polygons/-lines?&lt;/item&gt;
            &lt;/list&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Styler&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;respect zoom based style ranges&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Renderer&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;TileSource&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;implement single vector-tile handling&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;lukasmartinelli &amp;amp; manuelroth for all their work on OSM2VectorTiles (global vector tiles from OSM Planet)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;mourner for all his work on mindblowing GIS algorithms (like the used earcut, rbush, simplify-js, ..)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenStreetMap is open data, licensed under the Open Data Commons Open Database License (ODbL) by the OpenStreetMap Foundation (OSMF).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are free to copy, distribute, transmit and adapt our data, as long as you credit OpenStreetMap and its contributors. If you alter or build upon our data, you may distribute the result only under the same licence. The full legal code explains your rights and responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cartography in our map tiles, and our documentation, are licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 2.0 licence (CC BY-SA).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45293012</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 18:12:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PYREX vs. pyrex: What's the difference?</title><link>https://www.corning.com/worldwide/en/products/life-sciences/resources/stories/in-the-field/pyrex-vs-pyrex-whats-the-difference.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bc309c5290c9256b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;PYREX vs pyrex Construction Differences&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Corning used borosilicate to produce all Pyrex products. However, the company that purchased the cookware products switched to soda-lime glass, adopting the name pyrex (spelled with all lowercase letters).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Corning continued to make its lab tools with borosilicate, dubbing these products to be PYREX (spelled with all uppercase letters). Borosilicate glassware can sustain the large, sudden temperature changes that frequently occur in labs without shattering. These products are also less likely to react to chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Corning sold the consumer products or cookware business in 1998. The new owner, known as Borden at the time, later rebranding to World Kitchen in 2000, recognized that the cookware didn't need to be quite as strong, and — to make it accessible to the average customer — it needed to be more affordable. With this in mind, they switched the cookware to soda-lime glass, a less expensive component. Soda-lime glass, now called pyrex, isn't as resistant to thermal shock, but it is durable enough for everyday cooking.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Benefits of PYREX Labware&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;PYREX labware is designed to meet the rigorous demands of scientific experimentation. In fact, these scientific glassware products were integral in developing penicillin during World War II and the polio vaccine during the 1950s.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Corning laboratory glassware products have long been manufactured to meet the quality and reliability standards created by the American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM). Corning advanced its quality control for accuracy and precision further by testing its volumetric glassware in an ISO/IEC 17025 accredited laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;PYREX glass is well-suited for lab work because Corning uses borosilicate to produce beakers, flasks, test tubes, and other lab glassware. PYREX lab glassware made with borosilicate can withstand harsh, corrosive chemicals, handle extremely low and high temperatures, and it can survive rapid temperature changes without sustaining damage. PYREX beakers, Erlenmeyer flasks, and round- and flat-bottom boiling flasks can be repeatedly heated up to 230ºC. PYREX volumetric laboratory ware can be brought to 150ºC. Overall, PYREX laboratory glassware has a temperature shock limit — or allowable difference between the temperature of the glass and any medium in contact with the glass (air, liquid, or solid) — of 160ºC.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Always check laboratory glassware for any cracks, scratches, chips, or hazing — these damages can cause the product to break while in use. If properly cleaned and not damaged, PYREX laboratory glassware is reusable.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Unique Cleaning Procedures for PYREX Lab Glassware&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Despite being made of a strong, durable material, PYREX lab glassware requires specific care and maintenance. Ignoring the specific cleaning differences of PYREX labware can undermine the glassware's integrity and stability. If handled improperly, these products could shatter when exposed to high temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Always clean PYREX products with a non-abrasive glassware detergent either by hand or in a dishwasher. Do not exceed temperatures above 110°C during the cleaning process. Do not use abrasive brushes or scrubbing pads that can scratch the glass or its coating. In addition, limit exposure to any aldehydes, ketones, chlorinated solvents, or concentrated acids, because they can damage the glassware.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For over 100 years, Corning has been a trailblazer in creating innovative glassware products that can reliably and repeatedly meet users' needs. These products have accelerated scientific discoveries and enhanced human health.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45310995</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 06:37:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FLX1s phone is launched</title><link>https://furilabs.com/flx1s-is-launched/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="dfe351495ea32377"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is with great excitement that we can now release the FLX1s. Pre-sales are open and the phone is in production which is due to complete end of October 2025. Following that we can start shipping. Existing orders will be opted into the FLX1s or refunded.&lt;lb/&gt;To all our amazing FLX1 owners and those waiting patiently for their order, you have been the most wonderful and supportive community that we could ever have imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Thank-you from the FuriLabs Team.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45312326</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 11:20:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Images over DNS</title><link>https://dgl.cx/2025/09/images-over-dns</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="fec80dd7a0729493"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's the limit of what can be in a TXT record?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some places say 255 bytes. They are wrong. Within a TXT record there are multiple character-strings (RFC 1035 section 3.3.14) and those are limited in length (because a single byte is used for their length), however there can be many of them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The actual limit is limited by the size of the DNS payload, which for UDP is these days around 1232 bytes. That is obviously quite low. However if we use TCP, which doesn't require anything special, other than the normal fallback to TCP that DNS does, then we can serve up to 64KB.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I set out to demonstrate exactly that, by using Google Public DNS's JSON API and then serving large TXT responses over TCP, from a custom server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This mostly just works, the main issue is not with the length, but with binary data, because JSON isn't really designed to handle binary data. Therefore there is some slightly custom JSON parsing. Using raw binary data in a TXT record avoids the overhead of Base64 or another encoding, meaning more data can be packed in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👉 See it in action. For more read the comments in image.html.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Non-browser&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is possible to query this via dig. Although turning it back into binary output is a bit tricky, as the presentation form of DNS responses is escaped for output.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can retrieve the data with dig and a little Perl to unescape and combine the character sequences:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ dig +short dog.log.battery.st TXT | perl -pe'chomp; s/" "//g; s/^"//; s/"$//; s/\\(\d{3})/chr $1/eg; s/\\([\\"])/$1/g' &amp;gt; dog.avif
$ sha256sum dog.avif
7058fbd20ef2af84d5efb0ae7d91f87ce7a912380636c468b32f2c759cbb9130  dog.avif
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(This is actually just a modified version of the Perl one liner from my Wikipedia over DNS from 2008, nothing changes.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because the web version uses Google's JSON resolver we know it doesn't have problems querying very large TXT records, however your local recursor may not support this. If it doesn't work you can add &lt;code&gt;@dns.google&lt;/code&gt; to the dig command
line to send the query to Google's Public DNS servers (or any other open
recursor, &lt;code&gt;@9.9.9.9&lt;/code&gt; seems to work too).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought it was a cute hack when I realised it was possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For those interested in security there is a consideration here, attackers have long tunnelled over DNS, but tunnelling large payloads to a browser is potentially something new. Because Google Public DNS has a certificate that includes &lt;code&gt;8.8.8.8&lt;/code&gt; and so on, HTTPS
traffic can go directly from a browser without a DNS lookup. This may be
unexpected in environments that use DNS filtering. This is something that will
become more common once Lets Encrypt fully rolls out IP address
certificates,
the difference here is piggybacking on an existing IP address certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This deliberately uses a low TTL (10 seconds) to avoid filling DNS recursor's caches with useless content. It would be possible to increase this and therefore get caching from the recursors, a bit like a free distributed CDN (although I suspect if someone actually did this they would adaptively limit TTLs, if something like that isn't already done).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Server side&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The server is a custom Go DNS server. To be honest it was written by ChatGPT because it's not that clever, the idea is what matters. (Although ChatGPT did get some details like truncation wrong so I fixed the code myself.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the code is here. AI was only used for the server component, this blog post and the client HTML code is my own work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45312515</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 11:50:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bezier Curve as Easing Function in C++</title><link>https://asawicki.info/news_1790_bezier_curve_as_easing_function_in_c</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bdfd9b9b882b23db"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fri &lt;lb/&gt;19 &lt;lb/&gt;Sep 2025 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a guest post from my friend Łukasz Izdebski Ph.D.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since my last guest post on Adam’s blog, but I’m back with something short and practical—think of it as an epilogue to this earlier post on Bézier curves in animation. The last post focused on the theory and mathematics behind Bézier curves. What it lacked was a practical perspective—an opportunity to see the implementation in action. I wanted to share with you a simple library that I have created. Its purpose is to directly represent cubic Bézier Curves as Easing Functions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The library is designed with C++20 and newer standards in mind, taking advantage of modern language features for clarity and performance. If needed, support for earlier versions of C++ can be added to ensure broader compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;EasingCubicBezier&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. This class handles the interpolation of parameters used in the keyframe method. The interpolation of parameters follows the same principles as standard Bézier curve evaluation.&lt;code&gt;evaluate&lt;/code&gt; function with a parameter &lt;code&gt;t&lt;/code&gt;, which should lie between x0 (the X coordinate of the first control point, representing the start time of the frame) and x3 (the X coordinate of the fourth control point, representing the end time). &lt;p&gt;As presented in previous blog post, the &lt;code&gt;EasingCubicBezier&lt;/code&gt; character as a easing function depends solely on the X coordinates of the control points.&amp;#13;
The tests were prepared for a single, fixed value of the Y coordinates of the Bézier curve control points (their value does not affect the interpolation performance in any way), and for a set of 256 different variants of the X coordinates of the control points.&amp;#13;
The aim was to cover as wide a range of control point locations as possible (in particular, the two inner points).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Performance measurements were carried out using the Google Benchmark framework, ensuring reliable and consistent results. Further details and test results are available in the library repository.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new approach using &lt;code&gt;EasingCubicBezier&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; has been benchmarked against two commonly used methods in game engines and graphics applications. Both of these alternatives rely on solving cubic polynomial equations, either through algebraic solutions or numerical  techniques.&amp;#13;
In the case of numerical methods, a critical factor is the choice of the initial starting point. This selection plays a major role in determining the algorithm’s convergence speed and stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following tests compared 5 different algorithms:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;0.5&lt;/code&gt; (because the X coordinates of the curve were previously normalised to the interval &lt;code&gt;[0, 1]&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;code&gt;t&lt;/code&gt;, where &lt;code&gt;t&lt;/code&gt; is the input parameter for which the Bézier curve interpolation is being evaluated.&lt;p&gt;The chart and the table below presents the benchmark results using a box plot, highlighting the distribution and variability of each algorithm’s performance in PRECISE mode with AVX2 extensions turned On.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Algorithm&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Min&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Q1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Median&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Q3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Max&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Average&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Std dev&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Easing Cubic Bezier&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1562.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;21875.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;32812.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;32812.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;39062.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;28991.7&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;7803.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Numeric Solution 1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;7812.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;17187.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;23437.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;53515.6&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;150000.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;40856.9&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;32900.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Numeric Solution 2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4687.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;15625.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;21093.8&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;52343.8&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;173438.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;37292.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;31220.9&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Original Blender&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;40625.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;54687.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;56250.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;56250.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;60937.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;55096.4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2659.2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Optimised Blender&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;12500.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;40625.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;42187.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;43750.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;45312.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;41003.4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5931.3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The chart and the table below presents the benchmark results using a box plot, highlighting the distribution and variability of each algorithm’s performance in FAST mode mode with AVX2 extensions turned On.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Algorithm&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Min&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Q1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Median&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Q3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Max&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Average&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Std dev&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Easing Cubic Bezier&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3125.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;15625.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;21875.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;23437.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;23437.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;19714.4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4838.2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Numeric Solution 1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;7812.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;17187.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;23437.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;59375.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;331250.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;42059.3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;37539.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Numeric Solution 2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4687.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;15625.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;20312.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;48437.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;156250.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;36926.3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;31357.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="8"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Original Blender&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;32812.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;44921.9&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;50000.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;50000.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;50000.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;47418.2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3817.4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Optimised Blender&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;12500.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;35937.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;42187.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;42187.5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;43750.0&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;39953.6&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5554.2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The table below summarizes the key conclusions drawn from the benchmark tests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Algorithm&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Performance&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Variation&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Easing Cubic Bezier&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Very stable and consistently low execution time&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Minimal&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Most predictable and effective in typical use cases&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Numeric Solution 1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Highly variable — ranging from excellent to extremely slow&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Huge, with many outliers&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Efficient in some cases, but unstable and prone to severe slowdowns&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Numeric Solution 2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Similar to Numeric Solution 1, but with more symmetrical behavior&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Large, but less extreme&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;More balanced overall, though still susceptible to performance issues&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="4"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Original Blender&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;High execution time&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Very small&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Stable and predictable; useful when consistency is more important than speed&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Optimised Blender&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Moderate execution time&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Small&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;A good compromise between speed and stability&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;By representing Bézier curves explicitly in just 28 bytes (&lt;code&gt;float&lt;/code&gt;) or 56 bytes (&lt;code&gt;double&lt;/code&gt;) using the proposed method, this approach delivers both speed and stability—making it ideal for real-time animation systems. By storing the curve in this form, runtime execution becomes straightforward: it directly interpolates parameter values without the need to solve cubic polynomial equations.This eliminates the overhead typically associated with solving cubic polynomials during runtime.&amp;#13;
The cost of determining the interpolating function corresponding to a given Bézier curve is deferred to the construction of an EasingCubicBezier&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is just the beginning of my journey with easing functions. I am working on another solution, whose main goal will be maximum performance in runtime, while maintaining flexibility comparable to that offered by cubic Bézier curves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comments | #math #rendering Share&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45313194</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 13:27:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Vapor chamber tech keeps iPhone 17 Pro cool</title><link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/iphone-17-pro-vapor-chamber</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9533a64f32e316ed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On 9 September, Apple introduced its newest lineup, including the iPhone 17 series. Much of the attention went to a new ultrathin model and a bright orange color option (a shade not dissimilar to that of the IEEE Spectrum logo). The new smartphones will also ship with the latest operating system and its “Liquid Glass” software design—but the liquid in these phones goes beyond software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The iPhone 17 Pro and iPhone 17 Pro Max contain thin, hermetically sealed chambers with a drop of water inside that cycles between liquid and gas to help dissipate heat. Known as vapor chambers, the cooling system is becoming more common in smartphones built for sustained high performance. Some high-end Samsung Galaxy and Google Pixel models, among others, have introduced vapor-chamber cooling in the past few years. Now, Apple is following their lead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Cooling of smaller portables like phones must focus on spreading heat as widely as possible to the surface of the device, with particular attention to heat-generating components, like the chip,” says Kenneth Goodson, a professor of mechanical engineering at Stanford who specializes in heat transfer and energy conversion. To cool down those hot spots, the industry seems to be moving toward vapor chambers and other phase-change technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How vapor chambers keep phones cool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The standard approach to cooling smartphones uses a solid, highly conductive plate made from a material like copper to spread heat. This approach relies on having a surface where heat can spread. Sometimes, fins are added to extend that surface, but this can lead to a thicker device. Most companies, however, are intent on making thinner and thinner phones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Phase-change technology—which has been used in laptops for decades, Goodson notes—achieves the same goal more effectively with fluid that boils and condenses to dissipate heat. These two-phase solutions include vapor chambers, like those used in the new iPhone, as well as narrow, fingerlike structures called heat pipes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Phones have limited volume to work with, and “performance per volume is critical,” says Victor Chiriac, the CEO and cofounder of Global Cooling Technology Group, based in Phoenix. Thin and wide vapor chambers have a high heat-removal capacity and offer an effective solution. The cycle between liquid and vapor is “a powerful mechanism for absorbing heat,” he says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple’s vapor chamber efficiently spreads heat across the phone’s body.Apple&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Apple’s version, a small amount of deionized water is sealed in the chamber. The water evaporates when near heat sources, then condenses back into a liquid when the heat dissipates into the phone’s surrounding aluminum body. Water is often used in vapor chambers, though sometimes other materials are mixed in to prevent it from freezing and cracking the seal, Chiriac says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Vapor-chamber manufacturing faces challenges&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Apple, Samsung, and others push the boundaries of how thin phones can get, manufacturing vapor chambers may become a challenge. While solid materials can easily be shaved down, these chambers need to have enough space for coolant to travel through channels. The chambers have to be perfectly sealed in order to work properly, and “the thinner you make it, the less space you have for that secret sauce to do its thing,” Chiriac says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It comes down to physics: “A big challenge in small devices like phones is that as you scale down the thickness of a vapor chamber, the fluid physics aggressively scale back their performance relative to copper and other solid heat conductors,” Goodson explains. (This is a problem that researchers, including his students, are working to address with new microstructures.) Plus, vapor chambers tend to be expensive to manufacture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, Apple and other companies have decided to invest in this technology for their most powerful phone models. Goodson suspects part of that decision is to leverage the “wow” factor. But, he says, “with time this approach will likely become an industry standard.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All-Silicon “Fan-on-a-Chip” Keeps Thin Devices Cool ›&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Superslim Liquid Loop Will Keep Future Smartphones Cool ›&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gwendolyn Rak is an assistant editor at IEEE Spectrum covering consumer electronics and careers. She holds a master’s degree in science journalism from New York University and a bachelor’s degree in astrophysics and history from Swarthmore College.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45313415</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 13:50:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Living microbial cement supercapacitors with reactivatable energy storage</title><link>https://www.cell.com/cell-reports-physical-science/fulltext/S2666-3864(25)00409-6</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45313418</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 13:51:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cormac McCarthy's tips on how to write a science paper (2019) [pdf]</title><link>https://gwern.net/doc/science/2019-savage.pdf</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45313557</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 14:08:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Systemd can be a cause of restrictions on daemons</title><link>https://utcc.utoronto.ca/~cks/space/blog/linux/SystemdCanBeRestrictionCause</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f732f94725c702d9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;These days, systemd can be a cause of restrictions on daemons&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the traditional rites of passage for Linux system administrators is having a daemon not work in the normal system configuration (eg, when you boot the system) but work when you manually run it as root. The classical cause of this on Unix was that $PATH wasn't fully set in the environment the daemon was running in but was in your root shell. On Linux, another traditional cause of this sort of thing has been SELinux and a more modern source (on Ubuntu) has sometimes been AppArmor. All of these create hard to see differences between your root shell (where the daemon works when run by hand) and the normal system environment (where the daemon doesn't work). These days, we can add another cause, an increasingly common one, and that is systemd service unit restrictions, many of which are covered in systemd.exec.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(One pernicious aspect of systemd as a cause of these restrictions is that they can appear in new releases of the same distribution. If a daemon has been running happily in an older release and now has surprise issues in a new Ubuntu LTS, I don't always remember to look at its .service file.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of systemd's protective directives simply cause failures to do things, like access user home directories if ProtectHome= is set to something appropriate. Hopefully your daemon complains loudly here, reporting mysterious 'permission denied' or 'file not found' errors. Some systemd settings can have additional, confusing effects, like PrivateTmp=. A standard thing I do when troubleshooting a chain of programs executing programs executing programs is to shim in diagnostics that dump information to /tmp, but with PrivateTmp= on, my debugging dump files are mysteriously not there in the system-wide /tmp.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(On the other hand, a daemon may not complain about missing files if it's expected that the files aren't always there. A mailer usually can't really tell the difference between 'no one has .forward files' and 'I'm mysteriously not able to see people's home directories to find .forward files in them'.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes you don't get explicit errors, just mysterious failures to do some things. For example, you might set IP address access restrictions with the intention of blocking inbound connections but wind up also blocking DNS queries (and this will also depend on whether or not you use systemd-resolved). The good news is that you're mostly not going to find standard systemd .service files for normal daemons shipped by your Linux distribution with IP address restrictions. The bad news is that at some point .service files may start showing up that impose IP address restrictions with the assumption that DNS resolution is being done via systemd-resolved as opposed to direct DNS queries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(I expect some Linux distributions to resist this, for example Debian, but others may declare that using systemd-resolved is now mandatory in order to simplify things and let them harden service configurations.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right now, you can usually test if this is the problem by creating a version of the daemon's .service file with any systemd restrictions stripped out of it and then seeing if using that version makes life happy. In the future it's possible that some daemons will assume and require some systemd restrictions (for instance, assuming that they have a /tmp all of their own), making things harder to test.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45314157</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 15:26:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Are touchscreens in cars dangerous?</title><link>https://www.economist.com/science-and-technology/2025/09/19/are-touchscreens-in-cars-dangerous</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45314432</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 15:57:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ultrasonic Chef's Knife</title><link>https://seattleultrasonics.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="c4ae7ddc24d05992"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The World's First&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Ultrasonic Chef's Knife&lt;lb/&gt;For Home Cooks&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Switch on the ultrasonics and feel the blade glide effortlessly through food. Clean cuts, minimal force, less sticking.&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regular price $399.00 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Regular price &lt;del class="price-item price-item--regular" data-product-id="7320581177440" rend="overstrike"&gt; $399.00 &lt;/del&gt; Sale price $399.00 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-Order now for estimated shipping by January, 2026 (Batch 1). Cancel anytime before your order ships. What is a Pre-Order?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regular price $499.00 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Regular price &lt;del class="price-item price-item--regular" data-product-id="7497201942624" rend="overstrike"&gt; $548.00 &lt;/del&gt; Sale price $499.00 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-Order now for estimated shipping by January 2026 (Batch 1). Cancel anytime before your order ships. What is a Pre-Order?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45314592</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 16:12:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Designing NotebookLM</title><link>https://jasonspielman.com/notebooklm</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf50da1b9d312eaa"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User Journey â¢ Annotated Overview&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Home&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design Lead&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UX + Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2024&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I led design for NotebookLM, shaping the productâs core user experience, brand identity, and visual system from experiment to launch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This remains one of my proudest projects, and Iâm incredibly grateful for the opportunity to design something entirely new from the ground up. It was a chance to explore fresh paradigms, invent new patterns, and bring a product to life that hadnât existed before. None of it wouldâve been possible without the tight-knit, cross-functional team I was fortunate to collaborate with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Podcast â¢ Sequoia&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raiza and I discuss the journey building NotebookLM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NotebookLM â¢ Winner!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recognized as one of TIMEâs Best Inventions of 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visual Assets&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UI Evolution&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early Prototype&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what the UI looked like when I first joined the early project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notes driven UI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exploratory chat UI introduced as an overlay on the note canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3-Panel Structure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synthesizes learnings into a scalable and adaptive layout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the core problems we set out to solve with NotebookLM was âtab overwhelmâ the scattered, fractured experience of jumping between tools while trying to synthesize ideas. We wanted to create a space where every part of the creation journey could happen in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â Inputs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outputs â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Citations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Multiple entry points&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This visual shows how the core building blocks came together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The structure you see now may seem obvious but it took After what felt like 1000 iterations to get there. Trying to put these blocks together in a way that allowed for a clear mental model and digstible UI. These early sketches are from a plane. I ran out of paper and ultimately found the final solution when drawing on a napkin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mental model of NotebookLM was built around the creation journey: starting with inputs, moving through conversation, and ending with outputs. Users bring in their sources (documents, notes, references), then interact with them through chat by asking questions, clarifying, and synthesizing before transforming those insights into structured outputs like notes, study guides, and Audio Overviews.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By grounding the design in this linear but flexible flow (Inputs â Chat â Outputs) we gave users a clear sense of place within the product while keeping the complexity of new AI interactions digestible and intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs rare to find a product that brings reading, writing, and creation together in a truly integrated way largely because juggling all three can be overwhelming. But with AI reducing friction, the opportunity emerged to design a space where every part of the creative process could coexist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make that possible, I designed a responsive panel system that adapts to the userâs needs, scaling fluidly while preserving quick access to key elements like sources and notes, even at the smallest sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default layout, offering a balanced view of sources, chat, and notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Optimized for referencing sources and generating responses with citations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A popular request, designed for users focused on drafting and iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ideal for composing while keeping source material in view.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To optimize spatial utility, I created a set of responsive panels that scale based on user needs, retaining essential icons for sources and notes even at minimal widths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scalability was a core principle. While the content within these panels can shift and evolve, the underlying system is built to support growth, accommodating new tools, modes, and workflows without breaking the structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Studio Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See how the team has continued to scale this system with the newest launch of flashcards, quizzes, professional reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hereâs what that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User Journey â¢ Annotated Overview&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read the full story&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Defining the brand identity was a fast-paced effort, made possible by close collaboration with Google Labs and the central brand team. Shoutout Feel Hwang, Nick Mcginnis, Jennifer Leartanasan and team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Home&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design Lead&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UX + Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2024&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I led design for NotebookLM, shaping the productâs core user experience, brand identity, and visual system from experiment to launch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This remains one of my proudest projects, and Iâm incredibly grateful for the opportunity to design something entirely new from the ground up. It was a chance to explore fresh paradigms, invent new patterns, and bring a product to life that hadnât existed before. None of it wouldâve been possible without the tight-knit, cross-functional team I was fortunate to collaborate with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brand Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visual Assets&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Takeaways&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UI Evolution&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early Prototype&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what the UI looked like when I first joined the early project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notes driven UI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exploratory chat UI introduced as an overlay on the note canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3-Panel Structure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synthesizes learnings into a scalable and adaptive layout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the core problems we set out to solve with NotebookLM was âtab overwhelmâ the scattered, fractured experience of jumping between tools while trying to synthesize ideas. We wanted to create a space where every part of the creation journey could happen in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â Inputs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outputs â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Citations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Multiple entry points&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This visual shows how the core building blocks came together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The structure you see now may seem obvious but it took After what felt like 1000 iterations to get there. Trying to put these blocks together in a way that allowed for a clear mental model and digstible UI. These early sketches are from a plane. I ran out of paper and ultimately found the final solution when drawing on a napkin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mental model of NotebookLM was built around the creation journey: starting with inputs, moving through conversation, and ending with outputs. Users bring in their sources (documents, notes, references), then interact with them through chat by asking questions, clarifying, and synthesizing before transforming those insights into structured outputs like notes, study guides, and Audio Overviews.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By grounding the design in this linear but flexible flow (Inputs â Chat â Outputs) we gave users a clear sense of place within the product while keeping the complexity of new AI interactions digestible and intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs rare to find a product that brings reading, writing, and creation together in a truly integrated way largely because juggling all three can be overwhelming. But with AI reducing friction, the opportunity emerged to design a space where every part of the creative process could coexist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make that possible, I designed a responsive panel system that adapts to the userâs needs, scaling fluidly while preserving quick access to key elements like sources and notes, even at the smallest sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default layout, offering a balanced view of sources, chat, and notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading + Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Optimized for referencing sources and generating responses with citations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To optimize spatial utility, I created a set of responsive panels that scale based on user needs, retaining essential icons for sources and notes even at minimal widths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scalability was a core principle. While the content within these panels can shift and evolve, the underlying system is built to support growth, accommodating new tools, modes, and workflows without breaking the structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Studio Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See how the team has continued to scale this system with the newest launch of flashcards, quizzes, professional reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hereâs what that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User Journey â¢ Annotated Overview&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read the full story&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Defining the brand identity was a fast-paced effort, made possible by close collaboration with Google Labs and the central brand team. Shoutout Feel Hwang, Nick Mcginnis, Jennifer Leartanasan and team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wanda Wingleton&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Home&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design Lead&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UX + Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2024&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I led design for NotebookLM, shaping the productâs core user experience, brand identity, and visual system from experiment to launch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This remains one of my proudest projects, and Iâm incredibly grateful for the opportunity to design something entirely new from the ground up. It was a chance to explore fresh paradigms, invent new patterns, and bring a product to life that hadnât existed before. None of it wouldâve been possible without the tight-knit, cross-functional team I was fortunate to collaborate with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Podcast â¢ Seqouia Training Data&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raiza and I discuss the journey building NotebookLM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NotebookLM â¢ Winner!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recognized as one of TIMEâs Best Inventions of 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brand Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visual Assets&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Takeaways&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design Evolution&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early Prototype&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what the UI looked like when I first joined the early project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notes driven UI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exploratory chat UI introduced as an overlay on the note canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3-Panel Structure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synthesizes learnings into a scalable and adaptive layout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the core problems we set out to solve with NotebookLM was âtab overwhelmâ the scattered, fractured experience of jumping between tools while trying to synthesize ideas. We wanted to create a space where every part of the creation journey could happen in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â Inputs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outputs â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Citations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Multiple entry points&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This visual shows how the core building blocks came together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The structure you see now may look obvious but it took what felt like a thousand iterations to get there. I was trying to arrange these blocks in a way that supported a clear mental model and a UI that felt intuitive and digestible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These sketches were done on a plane. I ran out of paper and ended up sketching the final solution across a few napkins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mental model of NotebookLM was built around the creation journey: starting with inputs, moving through conversation, and ending with outputs. Users bring in their sources (documents, notes, references), then interact with them through chat by asking questions, clarifying, and synthesizing before transforming those insights into structured outputs like notes, study guides, and Audio Overviews.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By grounding the design in this linear but flexible flow (Inputs â Chat â Outputs) we gave users a clear sense of place within the product while keeping the complexity of new AI interactions digestible and intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs rare to find a product that brings reading, writing, and creation together in a truly integrated way largely because juggling all three can be overwhelming. But with AI reducing friction, the opportunity emerged to design a space where every part of the creative process could coexist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make that possible, I designed a responsive panel system that adapts to the userâs needs, scaling fluidly while preserving quick access to key elements like sources and notes, even at the smallest sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default layout, offering a balanced view of sources, chat, and notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading + Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Optimized for referencing sources and generating responses with citations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat + Writing&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A popular request, designed for users focused on drafting and iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading + Writing&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ideal for composing while keeping source material in view.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To optimize spatial utility, I created a set of responsive panels that scale based on user needs, retaining essential icons for sources and notes even at minimal widths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scalability was a core principle. While the content within these panels can shift and evolve, the underlying system is built to support growth, accommodating new tools, modes, and workflows without breaking the structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Studio Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See how the team has continued to scale this system with the newest launch of flashcards, quizzes, professional reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hereâs what that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read the full story&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Defining the brand identity was a fast-paced effort, made possible by close collaboration with Google Labs and the central brand team. Shoutout Feel Hwang, Nick Mcginnis, Jennifer Leartanasan and team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45315312</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 17:25:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TV Time Machine: A Raspberry Pi That Plays Random 90s TV</title><link>https://quarters.captaintouch.com/blog/posts/2025-09-20-tv-time-machine-a-raspberry-pi-that-plays-random-90s-tv.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="aac6b06d71c2c067"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Growing up in the 90s, television was a different experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You turned on the TV, and whatever was playing at that moment would become your entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nowadays you yourself are in control, you choose what you want to see, whenever you want.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strangely enough, I miss that feeling of having something selected for me, something I cannot influence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's just my nostalgic musings, but why not create an afternoon project out of it and actually find out if there's something more to this nostalgic feeling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Take a Raspberry Pi (I used a cheap tiny Raspberry Pi 3A+)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Fill the SD card with all your favorite shows from your childhood&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Add a script that starts playing those shows in a random order at startup&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The idea is to have it plugged into a television or monitor and I can just turn it on whenever I feel like watching some random 90's tv.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's what's currently playing on my device:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Star Trek: The Next Generation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- StarGate SG-1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Saved by the Bell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Friends&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Dinosaurs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Family Matters&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- The Simpsons&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- X-Files&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Home Improvement&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Sliders&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- 3rd Rock from the Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- The Wonder Years&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Married with Children&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- ALF&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- MacGyver&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Xena: Warrior Princess&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is just a list to get started with, if you have any more 90's tips, let me know! (Mastodon details at the bottom)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This really only took an afternoon, it's that simple.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take an SD card and install Raspberry Pi OS Lite (64-bit) on it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can use Raspberry Pi's imaging software, make sure to preconfigure it so it connects to the wifi and that you have your authentication details set (I made a user account called 'retro')&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once the image is made, boot it up with your raspberry pi and ensure that you can log in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When logged in, create a video folder to store your files&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;mkdir video&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then take the SD card, plug it back into your computer (you might need a linux pc for this) and dump all your videos into a newly created 'video' folder in the root of your home directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the above is too much of a hassle for you, you can just as well just keep these videos on an attached USB stick, just make sure to update the path in the script.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install the software needed to play the videos:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo apt-get update sudo apt-get install vlc pulseaudio&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Save the following script in the root of your home directory as startVideo.sh (nano startVideo.sh):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;#!/bin/bash VIDEO_DIR=&amp;amp;quot/home/retro/video&amp;amp;quot pulseaudio --start pactl set-default-sink 1 mapfile -t video_files &amp;amp;lt &amp;amp;lt(find &amp;amp;quot$VIDEO_DIR&amp;amp;quot -type f | shuf) for video in &amp;amp;quot${video_files[@]}" do cvlc --fullscreen --play-and-exit &amp;amp;quot$video&amp;amp;quot done&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This just makes a list of all your videos, shuffles them and feeds them to VLC for playing. (use cvlc instead of vlc when you don't need an interface)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pactl command was needed in my case to ensure the audio also outputs over hdmi, if you are using the headphone jack, just leave out this line, note that this might differ on other Raspberry Pi devices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make sure to adjust the VIDEO_DIR path to wherever you are storing the videos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To ensure it's always playing, we'll make a systemd service so it auto starts playing at startup:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Save the following file as /etc/systemd/system/videoplayer.service (you can use sudo nano followed by the file location)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;[Unit] Description=Video Player Service After=multi-user.target [Service] User=retro Group=retro ExecStart=/home/retro/startVideo.sh Restart=always [Install] WantedBy=multi-user.target&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And then register it as a service:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo systemctl enable videoplayer&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reboot and cross your fingers!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right now I just have this plugged into a spare monitor (that has speakers built-in), but I'm looking for a small CRT to put in the corner of my office.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That would involve finding a HDMI to SCART, HDMI to s-video or similar convertor though.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TV, Nostalgia, HomeLab&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can get in touch through Mastodon:&lt;/p&gt;@rxpz@social.linux.pizza&lt;p&gt;TV Time Machine: A Raspberry Pi That Plays Random 90s TV was published on 2025-09-20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45316244</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 18:59:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A revolution in English bell ringing</title><link>https://harpers.org/archive/2025/10/a-change-of-tune-veronique-greenwood-bell-ringing/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f108bd6b5cc6fc83"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;October 2025 Issue [Annotation] A Change of Tune Download PDF Adjust Share A revolution in English bell ringing by Veronique Greenwood, Veronique Greenwood is a writer and bell ringer who lives in England. Tags Bell ringing England Adjust Share&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45316744</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 19:51:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Philips announces digital pathology scanner with native DICOM JPEG XL output</title><link>https://www.philips.com/a-w/about/news/archive/standard/news/articles/2025/philips-announces-digital-pathology-scanner-with-native-configurable-dicom-jpeg-and-jpeg-xl-output-in-world-first.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="1758be5a88b6ac93"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sep 08, 2025 | 2 minute read&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Pathology plays a crucial role in the diagnosis of a variety of diseases, particularly cancer, through examination of patient tissue samples. With an estimated 70% of important medical decisions involving laboratory or pathology tests [2], the availability of digitally stored pathology images is especially important as it has a significant impact on patient care. The digital transformation of pathology also means there is a growing need for scalable storage to meet new data volumes and computing resources, which also allows full AI adoption in clinical and research environments. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; DICOM (Digital Imaging and Communications in Medicine) is the international standard for medical images and related patient information. Because digital pathology is a relatively new imaging modality compared to radiology and others, there was no established DICOM standard in place. As a result, vendors created their own proprietary formats.&lt;lb/&gt; Today, Philips announced that it is expanding its SG300 and SG60 scanner offering with the Pathology Scanner SGi with configurable DICOM JPEG and DICOM JPEG XL output. As a result, it is the first in the world to offer native DICOM JPEG XL output. DICOM JPEG XL output files are up to 50% smaller while still providing the same high image quality [3], enabling pathology labs to store, manage, and analyze growing volumes of digital pathology data and enable more productive workflows in the cloud and on premise.&lt;lb/&gt; “The adoption of DICOM in pathology marks an important shift toward achieving scalable, interoperable imaging workflows, said Imogen Fitt, Principal Analyst at Signify Research. “As pathology labs face mounting data volumes and storage demands, the move to standardized formats helps reduce infrastructure costs and enables integration with a wider range of AI tools. Philips’ support for DICOM JPEG and DICOM JPEG XL as a native output from its scanners illustrates how vendors are aligning with these trends, intending to support capabilities such as centralized archiving, cross-modality diagnostics, and remote collaboration for customers.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Sources [1] Pathology Scanner SGi is under development and is not CE marked and is not yet available for sale. [2] Report of the Second Phase of the Review of NHS Pathology Services in England, Lord Carter of Coles (2008). Results are specific to the institution where they were obtained and may not reflect the results achievable at other institutions. [3] Based on preliminary test data on diverse slide types. Data representative of a typical clinical mix is not yet available.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45316833</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 20:00:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A brief history of threads and threading</title><link>https://eclecticlight.co/2025/09/20/a-brief-history-of-threads-and-threading/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="66748c770736d00a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The original 128K Mac from 1984 came with a single Motorola 68000 processor running at 8 MHz that could only run one app at a time. Yet today’s Macs come with multiple CPU cores that can comfortably run several substantial apps simultaneously, while running a Time Machine backup and other tasks in the background. This brief history outlines the journey between them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A processor with a single core and no support for multi-tasking runs one sequence of instructions at a time. When those call for an operating system function to be performed, the running app is interrupted to hand control over to the system, and once that has completed, control is passed back to the app. That’s what the first Macs did until Andy Hertzfeld wrote Switcher, released by Apple in April 1985. This allowed the user to switch between running more than one app, but was still limited to running just one of them at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Multitasking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the next couple of years, some third-party utilities were produced to go further than Switcher, but it wasn’t until 1987 that MultiFinder replaced Switcher, and was integrated into System 7 in 1991. Developed by Erich Ringewald and Phil Goldman, this brought cooperative multitasking, which was to become the mainstay of classic Mac OS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In computers with a single processor core, multitasking is a way of cheating to give the impression that the processor is doing several things at once, when in fact all it’s doing is switching rapidly between two or more different programs. There are two fundamental models for doing that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;cooperative multitasking, in which individual tasks yield to give others processing time;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;preemptive multitasking, in which a scheduler switches between tasks at regular intervals.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a processor switches from one task to the next, the current task state must be saved so it can be resumed later. Once that’s complete, the next task is loaded to complete the context switch. That incurs overhead, both in terms of processing and in memory storage, which are less when switching between lightweight tasks. Different strategies have been adopted to determine the optimum size of tasks and overhead imposed by context switching, and terminology differs between them, variously using words such as processes, threads and even fibres, which can prove thoroughly confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Classic Mac OS thus has a Process Manager that launches apps in cooperative multitasking. This works well much of the time, but lets badly behaved tasks hog the processor and block other tasks from getting their fair share. It’s greatly aided by the main event loop at the heart of Mac apps that waits for control input to direct the app to perform work for the user. But when an app charges off to spend many seconds tackling a demanding task without polling its main event loop, that app could lock the user out for what seems like an age.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In February 1988 Apple released the first Unix for Macintosh, A/UX, which came with preemptive multitasking. That was added to Mac OS in 1996 in System 7.5.3, in Multiprocessing Services, and further enhanced in Mac OS 8.6 three years later. Cooperative multitasking was also supported by the Thread Manager.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Threads&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2000 Apple’s hardware and software changed radically. Its first Macs with dual processors came in PowerPC 7400 (G4) chips in Power Mac G4 desktop systems, and Mac OS X brought several types of thread that could be used to manage processing on multiple processors or CPU cores, together with preemptive multitasking. Thread types include low-level Mach threads, higher-level POSIX threads or Pthreads that replaced Multiprocessing Services, Java Threads, Cocoa’s NSThreads, and cooperatively scheduled threads using the Carbon Thread Manager. The following diagram summarises Apple’s current terminology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In most cases, we’re considering applications with a GUI, normally run from a bundle structure. These can in turn run their own code, such as privileged helper apps used to perform work that requires elevated privileges. In recent years, there has been a proliferation of additional executable code associated with many apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When that app is run, there’s a single runtime instance created from its single executable code, and given its own virtual memory and access to system resources that it needs. This is a process, and listed as such in Activity Monitor, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each process has a main thread, a single flow of code execution, and may create additional threads, perhaps to run in the background. Threads don’t get their own virtual memory, but share that allocated to the process, although they have their own stack. On Apple silicon Macs they’re easy to tell apart as they can only run on a single core, although they may be moved between cores, sometimes rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Within each thread are individual tasks, each a quantity of work to be performed. These can be brief sections of code and are more interdependent than threads. They’re often divided into synchronous and asynchronous tasks, depending on whether they need to be run as part of a strict sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2005 the Power Mac G5 was the first Mac to use dual-core PowerPC G5 processors, then the iMac 17-inch of the following year used Apple’s first Intel Core Duo processor with two cores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Grand Central Dispatch&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2009 Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard introduced a new dispatcher, named Grand Central Dispatch (GCD) after Grand Central Terminal in New York City, and that was enhanced in macOS Sierra a decade later. More recently it has been referred to simply as Dispatch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At its heart, GCD is a dispatcher managing queues of tasks, activating those that need most to be run, and leaving the less pressing to wait a bit longer. It has its own queues, as well as those assembled by apps. Some are run as simple queues with a first in first out rule, others using sophisticated heuristics to determine relative priorities. There’s a detailed account of GCD internals in Jonathan Levin’s book *OS Internals volume 1, and Apple’s current developer documentation is here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GCD was introduced for Macs with multiple identical cores, to support their symmetric multiprocessing (SMP), and with the release of the first Apple silicon Macs in November 2020 it has managed queues of threads to be dispatched for execution on two CPU core types, Performance and Efficiency. Core allocation is now managed according to the Quality of Service (QoS) assigned to each thread. When used on SMP processors with no contention for core availability, QoS has limited effects on thread performance, but performance on P and E cores may differ by a factor of 10.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the last 41 years, macOS has gained thorough support for getting the best performance from multiple tasks, threads, and processes in chips that contain up to 32 CPU cores of two types – a far cry from that single 68000 processor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45317526</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 21:04:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>$2 WeAct Display FS adds a 0.96-inch USB information display to your computer</title><link>https://www.cnx-software.com/2025/09/18/2-weact-display-fs-adds-a-0-96-inch-usb-information-display-to-your-computer/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="aa305d1c39dee0f3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WeAct Display FS is an inexpensive 0.96-inch USB display dongle designed to add an information display or a tiny secondary display to your computer or SBC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve seen this type of information display with products such as the Turing Smart Screen, a larger 3.5-inch color display, or small OLEDs integrated into cases such as the Pironman 5 Max to disable text. The WeAct Display FS V1 may be tiny, but it’s also a full-color 160×80 resolution display that can be customized with software provided by WeAct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WeAct Display FS V1 specifications:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Display – 0.96-inch RGB565 display with 160×80 resolution&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Host interface – “Reversible” USB 2.0 Type-A Full Speed (FS) port showing as a CDC device&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dimensions – 43 x 14.5 mm&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since you wouldn’t want to get a display only for it to face the wrong direction, for instance, the desk or the wall, the company made the USB-A port reversible, and the user only needs to install one of the two provided pads on the unused side of the port to avoid short circuits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WeAct provides two programs for it. The first one is the WeAct Studio System Monitor based on a fork of Matthieu Houdebine’s Turing Smart Screen Python project. This allows users to create UIs/themes with text, images, weather, and other features… WeAct says the little device only works on Windows, but the open-source project is supposed to also work on macOS, Linux (including Raspberry Pi OS), and essentially any operating system with support for Python 3.9+.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second program is called WeAct Studio Screen Projection, and as I understand it, it emulates an actual display, so you could move any window/program to the USB display. I’m just not sure how a desktop OS like Windows will handle a tiny 160×80 “monitor”… I suppose it could be used to play a full-screen YouTube video or display photos for whatever reason. That one only works on Windows, and there’s no source code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll find the WeAct Display FS V1 (0.96-inch) on AliExpress for about $2 plus shipping, but while looking for information, I also noticed a 3.5-inch variant with 480×320 resolution for about $11.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jean-Luc started CNX Software in 2010 as a part-time endeavor, before quitting his job as a software engineering manager, and starting to write daily news, and reviews full time later in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support CNX Software! Donate via cryptocurrencies, become a Patron on Patreon, or purchase goods on Amazon or Aliexpress. We also use affiliate links in articles to earn commissions if you make a purchase after clicking on those links.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45317527</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 21:04:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US Gov acknowledges that 100K fee does not apply to existing H-1B visas holders [pdf]</title><link>https://www.uscis.gov/sites/default/files/document/memos/H1B_Proc_Memo_FINAL.pdf</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45318060</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 22:11:22 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>