<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2025 23:32:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Many hard LeetCode problems are easy constraint problems</title><link>https://buttondown.com/hillelwayne/archive/many-hard-leetcode-problems-are-easy-constraint/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="cd8a25908f10ff1f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Many Hard Leetcode Problems are Easy Constraint Problems&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Use the right tool for the job.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my first interview out of college I was asked the change counter problem:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Given a set of coin denominations, find the minimum number of coins required to make change for a given number. IE for USA coinage and 37 cents, the minimum number is four (quarter, dime, 2 pennies).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I implemented the simple greedy algorithm and immediately fell into the trap of the question: the greedy algorithm only works for "well-behaved" denominations. If the coin values were &lt;code&gt;[10, 9, 1]&lt;/code&gt;, then making 37 cents would take 10 coins in the greedy algorithm but only 4 coins optimally (&lt;code&gt;10+9+9+9&lt;/code&gt;). The "smart" answer is to use a dynamic programming algorithm, which I didn't know how to do. So I failed the interview.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But you only need dynamic programming if you're writing your own algorithm. It's really easy if you throw it into a constraint solver like MiniZinc and call it a day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;int: total;
array[int] of int: values = [10, 9, 1];
array[index_set(values)] of var 0..: coins;

constraint sum (c in index_set(coins)) (coins[c] * values[c]) == total;
solve minimize sum(coins);
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can try this online here. It'll give you a prompt to put in &lt;code&gt;total&lt;/code&gt; and then give you successively-better solutions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;coins = [0, 0, 37];
----------
coins = [0, 1, 28];
----------
coins = [0, 2, 19];
----------
coins = [0, 3, 10];
----------
coins = [0, 4, 1];
----------
coins = [1, 3, 0];
----------
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lots of similar interview questions are this kind of mathematical optimization problem, where we have to find the maximum or minimum of a function corresponding to constraints. They're hard in programming languages because programming languages are too low-level. They are also exactly the problems that constraint solvers were designed to solve. Hard leetcode problems are easy constraint problems.1 Here I'm using MiniZinc, but you could just as easily use Z3 or OR-Tools or whatever your favorite generalized solver is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;More examples&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was a question in a different interview (which I thankfully passed):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Given a list of stock prices through the day, find maximum profit you can get by buying one stock and selling one stock later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's easy to do in O(n^2) time, or if you are clever, you can do it in O(n). Or you could be not clever at all and just write it as a constraint problem:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;array[int] of int: prices = [3, 1, 4, 1, 5, 9, 2, 6, 5, 3, 5, 8];
var int: buy;
var int: sell;
var int: profit = prices[sell] - prices[buy];

constraint sell &amp;gt; buy;
constraint profit &amp;gt; 0;
solve maximize profit;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reminder, link to trying it online here. While working at that job, one interview question we tested out was:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Given a list, determine if three numbers in that list can be added or subtracted to give 0?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a satisfaction problem, not a constraint problem: we don't need the "best answer", any answer will do. We eventually decided against it for being too tricky for the engineers we were targeting. But it's not tricky in a solver;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;include "globals.mzn";
array[int] of int: numbers = [3, 1, 4, 1, 5, 9, 2, 6, 5, 3, 5, 8];
array[index_set(numbers)] of var {0, -1, 1}: choices;

constraint sum(n in index_set(numbers)) (numbers[n] * choices[n]) = 0;
constraint count(choices, -1) + count(choices, 1) = 3;
solve satisfy;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, one last one, a problem I saw last year at Chipy AlgoSIG. Basically they pick some leetcode problems and we all do them. I failed to solve this one:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Given an array of integers heights representing the histogram's bar height where the width of each bar is 1, return the area of the largest rectangle in the histogram.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The "proper" solution is a tricky thing involving tracking lots of bookkeeping states, which you can completely bypass by expressing it as constraints:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;array[int] of int: numbers = [2,1,5,6,2,3];

var 1..length(numbers): x; 
var 1..length(numbers): dx;
var 1..: y;

constraint x + dx &amp;lt;= length(numbers);
constraint forall (i in x..(x+dx)) (y &amp;lt;= numbers[i]);

var int: area = (dx+1)*y;
solve maximize area;

output ["(\(x)-&amp;gt;\(x+dx))*\(y) = \(area)"]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's even a way to automatically visualize the solution (using &lt;code&gt;vis_geost_2d&lt;/code&gt;), but I didn't feel like figuring it out in time for the newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Is this better?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now if I actually brought these questions to an interview the interviewee could ruin my day by asking "what's the runtime complexity?" Constraint solvers runtimes are unpredictable and almost always slower than an ideal bespoke algorithm because they are more expressive, in what I refer to as the capability/tractability tradeoff. But even so, they'll do way better than a bad bespoke algorithm, and I'm not experienced enough in handwriting algorithms to consistently beat a solver.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The real advantage of solvers, though, is how well they handle new constraints. Take the stock picking problem above. I can write an O(n²) algorithm in a few minutes and the O(n) algorithm if you give me some time to think. Now change the problem to&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maximize the profit by buying and selling up to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;max_sales&lt;/code&gt;stocks, but you can only buy or sell one stock at a given time and you can only hold up to&lt;code&gt;max_hold&lt;/code&gt;stocks at a time?&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's a way harder problem to write even an inefficient algorithm for! While the constraint problem is only a tiny bit more complicated:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;include "globals.mzn";
int: max_sales = 3;
int: max_hold = 2;
array[int] of int: prices = [3, 1, 4, 1, 5, 9, 2, 6, 5, 3, 5, 8];
array [1..max_sales] of var int: buy;
array [1..max_sales] of var int: sell;
array [index_set(prices)] of var 0..max_hold: stocks_held;
var int: profit = sum(s in 1..max_sales) (prices[sell[s]] - prices[buy[s]]);

constraint forall (s in 1..max_sales) (sell[s] &amp;gt; buy[s]);
constraint profit &amp;gt; 0;

constraint forall(i in index_set(prices)) (stocks_held[i] = (count(s in 1..max_sales) (buy[s] &amp;lt;= i) - count(s in 1..max_sales) (sell[s] &amp;lt;= i)));
constraint alldifferent(buy ++ sell);
solve maximize profit;

output ["buy at \(buy)\n", "sell at \(sell)\n", "for \(profit)"];
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most constraint solving examples online are puzzles, like Sudoku or "SEND + MORE = MONEY". Solving leetcode problems would be a more interesting demonstration. And you get more interesting opportunities to teach optimizations, like symmetry breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Update for the Internet&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was sent as a weekly newsletter, which is usually on topics like software history, formal methods, unusual technologies, and the theory of software engineering. You can subscribe here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Because my dad will email me if I don't explain this: "leetcode" is slang for "tricky algorithmic interview questions that have little-to-no relevance in the actual job you're interviewing for." It's from leetcode.com. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're reading this on the web, you can subscribe here. Updates are once a week. My main website is here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My new book, Logic for Programmers, is now in early access! Get it here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45222695</guid></item><item><title>UTF-8 is a brilliant design</title><link>https://iamvishnu.com/posts/utf8-is-brilliant-design</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a4bdbd10f83149ab"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;UTF-8 is a Brilliant Design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first time I learned about UTF-8 encoding, I was fascinated by how well-thought and brilliantly it was designed to represent millions of characters from different languages and scripts, and still be backward compatible with ASCII.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Basically UTF-8 uses 32 bits and the old ASCII uses 7 bits, but UTF-8 is designed in such a way that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Every ASCII encoded file is a valid UTF-8 file.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Every UTF-8 encoded file that has only ASCII characters is a valid ASCII file.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Designing a system that scales to millions of characters and still be compatible with the old systems that use just 128 characters is a brilliant design.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note: If you are already aware of the UTF-8 encoding, you can explore the UTF-8 Playground utility that I built to visualize UTF-8 encoding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How Does UTF-8 Do It?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UTF-8 is a variable-width character encoding designed to represent every character in the Unicode character set, encompassing characters from most of the world's writing systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It encodes characters using one to four bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first 128 characters (&lt;code&gt;U+0000&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;U+007F&lt;/code&gt;) are encoded with a single byte, ensuring backward compatibility with ASCII, and this is the reason why a file with only ASCII characters is a valid UTF-8 file.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other characters require two, three, or four bytes. The leading bits of the first byte determine the total number of bytes that represents the current character. These bits follow one of four specific patterns, which indicate how many continuation bytes follow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;1st byte Pattern&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;# of bytes used&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Full byte sequence pattern&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;0xxxxxxx&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;0xxxxxxx&lt;p&gt;(This is basically a regular ASCII encoded byte)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;110xxxxx&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;110xxxxx 10xxxxxx&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1110xxxx&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1110xxxx 10xxxxxx 10xxxxxx&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11110xxx&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11110xxx 10xxxxxx 10xxxxxx 10xxxxxx&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice that the second, third, and fourth bytes in a multi-byte sequence always start with 10. This indicates that these bytes are continuation bytes, following the main byte.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The remaining bits in the main byte, along with the bits in the continuation bytes, are combined to form the character's code point. A code point serves as a unique identifier for a character in the Unicode character set. A code point is typically represented in hexadecimal format, prefixed with "U+". For example, the code point for the character "A" is &lt;code&gt;U+0041&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So here is how a software determines the character from the UTF-8 encoded bytes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Read a byte. If it starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, it's a single-byte character (ASCII). Show the character represented by the remaining 7 bits on the screen. Continue with the next byte.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If the byte didn't start with a &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, then:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;If it starts with &lt;code&gt;110&lt;/code&gt;, it's a two-byte character, so read the next byte as well.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;If it starts with &lt;code&gt;1110&lt;/code&gt;, it's a three-byte character, so read the next two bytes.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;If it starts with &lt;code&gt;11110&lt;/code&gt;, it's a four-byte character, so read the next three bytes.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If it starts with &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Once the number of bytes are determined, read all the remaining bits except the leading bits, and find the binary value (aka. code point) of the character.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Look up the code point in the Unicode character set to find the corresponding character and display it on the screen.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Read the next byte and repeat the process.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Example: Hindi Letter "अ" (open in UTF-8 Playground)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Hindi letter "अ" (officially "Devanagari Letter A") is represented in UTF-8 as:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;11100000 10100100 10000101 Here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first byte 11100000 indicates that the character is encoded using 3 bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The remaining bits of the three bytes: xxxx0000 xx100100 xx000101 are combined to form the binary sequence 00001001 00000101 (&lt;code&gt;0x0905&lt;/code&gt; in hexadecimal). This is the code point of the character, represented as &lt;code&gt;U+0905&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code point &lt;code&gt;U+0905&lt;/code&gt; (see official chart) represents the Hindi letter "अ" in the Unicode character set.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Example Text Files&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we understood the design of UTF-8, let's look at a file that contains the following text:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;1. Text file contains: &lt;code&gt;Hey👋 Buddy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The text &lt;code&gt;Hey👋 Buddy&lt;/code&gt; has both English characters and an emoji character on it. The text file with this text saved on the disk will have the following 13 bytes in it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;01001000 01100101 01111001 11110000 10011111 10010001 10001011 00100000 01000010 01110101 01100100 01100100 01111001&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's evaluate this file byte-by-byte following the UTF-8 decoding rules:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Byte&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Explanation&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01001000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1001000&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'H'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01100101&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1100101&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'e'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01111001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1111001&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'y'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11110000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;11110&lt;/code&gt;, indicating it's the first byte of a four-byte character.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10011111&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;10&lt;/code&gt;, indicating it's a continuation byte.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10010001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;10&lt;/code&gt;, indicating it's a continuation byte.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10001011&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;10&lt;/code&gt;, indicating it's a continuation byte.&lt;p&gt;The bits from these four bytes (excluding the leading bits) combine to form the binary sequence 00001 11110100 01001011, which is&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;1F44B&lt;/code&gt; in hexadecimal, corresponds to the code point &lt;code&gt;U+1F44B&lt;/code&gt;. This code point represents the waving hand emoji "👋" in the Unicode character set (open in playground).&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;00100000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;0100000&lt;/code&gt; represent a whitespace character. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01000010&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1000010&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'B'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01110101&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1110101&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'u'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01100100&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1100100&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'd'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01100100&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1100100&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'd'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01111001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1111001&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'y'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now this is a valid UTF-8 file, but it doesn't have to be "backward compatible" with ASCII because it contains a non-ASCII character (the emoji). Next let's create a file that contains only ASCII characters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2. Text file contains: &lt;code&gt;Hey Buddy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The text file doesn't have any non-ASCII characters. The file saved on the disk has the following 9 bytes in it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;01001000 01100101 01111001 00100000 01000010 01110101 01100100 01100100 01111001&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's evaluate this file byte-by-byte following the UTF-8 decoding rules:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Byte&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Explanation&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01001000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1001000&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'H'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01100101&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1100101&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'e'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01111001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1111001&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'y'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;00100000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;0100000&lt;/code&gt; represent a whitespace character. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01000010&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1000010&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'B'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01110101&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1110101&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'u'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01100100&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1100100&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'd'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01100100&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1100100&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'd'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;01111001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Starts with &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;, so it's a single-byte ASCII character. The remaining bits &lt;code&gt;1111001&lt;/code&gt; represent the letter 'y'. (open in playground)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So this is a valid UTF-8 file, and it is also a valid ASCII file. The bytes in this file follows both the UTF-8 and ASCII encoding rules. This is how UTF-8 is designed to be backward compatible with ASCII.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Other Encodings&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I did a quick research on any other encoding that are backward compatible with ASCII, and there are a few, but they are not as popular as UTF-8, for example GB 18030 (a Chinese government standard). Another one is the ISO/IEC 8859 encodings are single-byte encodings that extend ASCII to include additional characters, but they are limited to 256 characters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The siblings of UTF-8, like UTF-16 and UTF-32, are not backward compatible with ASCII. For example, the letter 'A' in UTF-16 is represented as: &lt;code&gt;00 41&lt;/code&gt; (two bytes), while in UTF-32 it is represented as: &lt;code&gt;00 00 00 41&lt;/code&gt; (four bytes).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Bonus: UTF-8 Playground&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I was exploring the UTF-8 encoding, I couldn't find any good tool to interactively visualize how UTF-8 encoding works. So I built UTF-8 Playground to visualize and play around with UTF-8 encoding. Give it a try!.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read an ocean of knowledge and references that extends this post on Hacker News.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Joel Spolsky's famous 2003 article (still relevant): The Absolute Minimum Every Software Developer Absolutely, Positively Must Know About Unicode and Character Sets (No Excuses!)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"UTF-8 was designed, in front of my eyes, on a placemat in a New Jersey diner one night in September or so 1992." - Rob Pike on designing UTF-8 with Ken Thompson&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45225098</guid></item><item><title>FFglitch, FFmpeg fork for glitch art</title><link>https://ffglitch.org/gallery/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e7873f10cbba35f1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Gallery&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are some artists out there doing some amazing work using FFglitch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I put this page up so that I donât have to go hunting for examples every time I want to show someone what can be done with FFglitch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thomas Collet has a lot of work using FFglitch on vimeo, instagram, and reddit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A bunch more from Thomas:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://vimeo.com/366067869&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://vimeo.com/363105562&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://vimeo.com/323235580&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/glitch_art/comments/b9yfxc/study_on_crowd_movements/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/brokengifs/comments/grpwn4/tripping_in_manhattan/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/woahdude/comments/bg176f/i_went_to_ireland_filmed_the_ocean_and_glitched_it/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/woahdude/comments/ballm7/when_the_world_is_slowly_but_surely_falling_appart/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/glitch_art/comments/fhpwgp/falling_appart/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/glitch_art/comments/hxk6r1/when_it_kicks_in_the_middle_of_time_square/&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kaspar Ravel wrote a blog post about a collaboration he did with Thomas Collet which resulted in this gem:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hereâs the blog post: https://www.kaspar.wtf/blog/encoding-the-game-of-life-in-datamosh&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the post on reddit: https://www.reddit.com/r/brokengifs/comments/e25f6b/want_to_see_a_magic_trick/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.instagram.com/p/CPNaIp8qo-r&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go check out Myraâs beautiful work and exhibition Glitched Flowers (I wish I had been there to see it personallyâ¦)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.instagram.com/p/CYFo19HolJD&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go read about Jasonâs experimentations at https://www.jasonhallen.com/output, thereâs a lot more with FFglitch!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;glit_chbee (turn the volume up and enjoy the ride):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ben Cooper made this clip by using mainly avidemux, tomato.py, and FFglitch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jo Grys has posted some videos on Facebook:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are more if you search for #ffglitch on Facebook:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And some more random clips I found spread around the interwebz:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45227212</guid></item><item><title>Legal win</title><link>https://ma.tt/2025/09/legal-win/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="81bb3a195ed7607b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just got word that the court dismissed several of WP Engine and Silver Lake’s most serious claims — antitrust, monopolization, and extortion have been knocked out! These were by far the most significant and far-reaching allegations in the case and with today’s decision the case is narrowed significantly. This is a win not just for us but for all open source maintainers and contributors. Huge thanks to the folks at Gibson and Automattic who have been working on this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With respect to any remaining claims, we’re confident the facts will demonstrate that our actions were lawful and in the best interests of the WordPress community.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This ruling is a significant milestone, but our focus remains the same: building a free, open, and thriving WordPress ecosystem and supporting the millions of people who rely on it every day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45228692</guid></item><item><title>SkiftOS: A hobby OS built from scratch using C/C++ for ARM, x86, and RISC-V</title><link>https://skiftos.org</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e10fcdab2cdf53e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need to enable JavaScript to run this app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45229414</guid></item><item><title>Java 25's new CPU-Time Profiler</title><link>https://mostlynerdless.de/blog/2025/06/11/java-25s-new-cpu-time-profiler-1/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e298c11719f02744"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the first part of my series; the other parts are&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Java 25’s new CPU-Time Profiler: The Implementation (2)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Java 25’s new CPU-Time Profiler: Queue Sizing (3)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Java 25’s new CPU-Time Profiler: Removing Redundant Synchronization (4)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back to the blog post:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More than three years in the making, with a concerted effort starting last year, my CPU-time profiler landed in Java with OpenJDK 25. It’s an experimental new profiler/method sampler that helps you find performance issues in your code, having distinct advantages over the current sampler. This is what this week’s and next week’s blog posts are all about. This week, I will cover why we need a new profiler and what information it provides; next week, I’ll cover the technical internals that go beyond what’s written in the JEP. I will quote the JEP 509 quite a lot, thanks to Ron Pressler; it reads like a well-written blog post in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before I show you its details, I want to focus on what the current default method profiler in JFR does:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Current JFR Profiling Strategy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JDK 25’s default method profiler also changed, as my previous blog post, Taming the Bias: Unbiased* Safepoint-Based Stack Walking in JFR, described. However, the profiling strategy remained the same.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At every interval, say 10 or 20 milliseconds, five threads running in Java and one in native Java are picked from the list of threads and sampled. This thread list is iterated linearly, and threads not in the requested state are skipped (source).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Problems?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This strategy has problems, as also covered in a talk by Jaroslav Bachorik and me at this year’s FOSDEM:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The aggressive subsampling means that the effective sampling interval depends on the number of cores and the parallelism of your system. Say we have a large machine on which 32 threads can run in parallel. Then JFR on samples at most 19%, turning a sampling rate of 10ms into 53ms. This is an inherent property of wall-clock sampling, as the sampler considers threads on the system. This number can be arbitrarily large, so sub-sampling is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the sampling policy is not true wall-clock sampling, as it prioritizes threads running in Java. Consider a setting where 10 threads run in native and 5 in Java. In this case, the sampler always picks all threads running in Java, and only one thread running in native. This might be confusing and may lead users to the wrong conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if we gloss over this and call the current strategy “execution-time”, it might not be suitable for profiling every application. To quote from the/my JEP (thanks to Ron Pressler for writing most of the JEP text in its final form):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Execution time does not necessarily reflect CPU time. A method that sorts an array, e.g., spends all of its time on the CPU. Its execution time corresponds to the number of CPU cycles it consumes. In contrast, a method that reads from a network socket might spend most of its time idly waiting for bytes to arrive over the wire. Of the time it consumes, only a small portion is spent on the CPU. An execution-time profile will not distinguish between these cases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even a program that does a lot of I/O can be constrained by the CPU. A computation-heavy method might consume little execution time compared the program’s I/O operations, thus having little effect on latency — but it might consume most of the program’s CPU cycles, thus affecting throughput. Identifying and optimizing such methods will reduce CPU consumption and improve the program’s throughput — but in order to do so, we need to profile CPU time rather than execution time.&lt;/p&gt;JEP 509: JFR CPU-Time Profiling (Experimental)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Execution-time Example&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, consider a program,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;HttpRequests&lt;/code&gt;, with two threads, each performing HTTP requests. One thread runs a&lt;code&gt;tenFastRequests&lt;/code&gt;method that makes ten requests, sequentially, to an HTTP endpoint that responds in 10ms; the other runs a&lt;code&gt;oneSlowRequest&lt;/code&gt;method that makes a single request to an endpoint that responds in 100ms. The average latency of both methods should be about the same, and so the total time spent executing them should be about the same.&lt;p&gt;We can record a stream of execution-time profiling events like so:&lt;/p&gt;$ java -XX:StartFlightRecording=filename=profile.jfr,settings=profile.jfc HttpRequests clientJEP 509: JFR CPU-Time Profiling (Experimental)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find the program on GitHub. Be aware that it requires the server instance to run alongside, start it via&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;java HttpRequests server&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;At fixed time intervals, JFR records&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ExecutionSample&lt;/code&gt;events into the file&lt;code&gt;profile.jfr&lt;/code&gt;. Each event captures the stack trace of a thread running Java code, thus recording all of the methods currently running on that thread. (The file&lt;code&gt;profile.jfc&lt;/code&gt;is a JFR configuration file, included in the JDK, that configures the JFR events needed for an execution-time profile.)&lt;p&gt;We can generate a textual profile from the recorded event stream by using the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;jfr&lt;/code&gt;tool included in the JDK:$ jfr view native-methods profile.jfr Waiting or Executing Native Methods Method Samples Percent --------------------------------------------------------------- ------- ------- sun.nio.ch.SocketDispatcher.read0(FileDescriptor, long, int) 102 98.08% ...&lt;p&gt;This clearly shows that most of the program’s time is spent waiting for socket I/O.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can generate a graphical profile, in the form of a flame graph, by using the JDK Mission Control tool (JMC):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we see that the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;oneSlowRequest&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;tenFastRequests&lt;/code&gt;methods take a similar amount of execution time, as we expect.&lt;p&gt;However, we also expect&lt;/p&gt;JEP 509: JFR CPU-Time Profiling (Experimental)&lt;code&gt;tenFastRequests&lt;/code&gt;to take more CPU time than&lt;code&gt;oneSlowRequest&lt;/code&gt;, since ten rounds of creating requests and processing responses requires more CPU cycles than just one round. If these methods were run concurrently on many threads then the program could become CPU-bound, yet an execution-time profile would still show most of the program’s time being spent waiting for socket I/O. If we could profile CPU time then we could see that optimizing&lt;code&gt;tenFastRequests&lt;/code&gt;, rather than&lt;code&gt;oneSlowRequest&lt;/code&gt;, could improve the program’s throughput.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additionally, we point to a tiny but important problem in the JEP: the handling of failed samples. Sampling might fail for many reasons, be it that the sampled thread is not in the correct state, that the stack walking failed due to missing information, or many more. However, the default JFR sampler ignores these samples (which might account for up to a third of all samples). This doesn’t make interpreting the “execution-time” profiles any easier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;CPU-time profiling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As shown in the video above, sampling every thread every n milliseconds of CPU time improves the situation. Now, the number of samples for every thread is directly related to the time it spends on the CPU without any subsampling, as the number of hardware threads bounds the number of sampled threads.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ability to accurately and precisely measure CPU-cycle consumption was added to the Linux kernel in version 2.6.12 via a timer that emits signals at fixed intervals of CPU time rather than fixed intervals of elapsed real time. Most profilers on Linux use this mechanism to produce CPU-time profiles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some popular third-party Java tools, including async-profiler, use Linux’s CPU timer to produce CPU-time profiles of Java programs. However, to do so, such tools interact with the Java runtime through unsupported internal interfaces. This is inherently unsafe and can lead to process crashes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We should enhance JFR to use the Linux kernel’s CPU timer to safely produce CPU-time profiles of Java programs. This would help the many developers who deploy Java applications on Linux to make those applications more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;JEP 509: JFR CPU-Time Profiling (Experimental)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please be aware that I don’t discourage using async-profiler. It’s a potent tool and is used by many people. But it is inherently hampered by not being embedded into the JDK. This is especially true with the new stackwalking at safepoints (see Taming the Bias: Unbiased* Safepoint-Based Stack Walking in JFR), making the current JFR sampler safer to use. This mechanism is sadly not available for external profilers, albeit I had my ideas for an API (see Taming the Bias: Unbiased Safepoint-Based Stack Walking), but this project has sadly been abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s continue with the example from before.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;FR will use Linux’s CPU-timer mechanism to sample the stack of every thread running Java code at fixed intervals of CPU time. Each such sample is recorded in a new type of event,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;jdk.CPUTimeSample&lt;/code&gt;. This event is not enabled by default.&lt;p&gt;This event is similar to the existing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;jdk.ExecutionSample&lt;/code&gt;event for execution-time sampling. Enabling CPU-time events does not affect execution-time events in any way, so the two can be collected simultaneously.&lt;p&gt;We can enable the new event in a recording started at launch like so:&lt;/p&gt;$ java -XX:StartFlightRecording=jdk.CPUTimeSample#enabled=true,filename=profile.jfr ...&lt;p&gt;With the new CPU-time sampler, in the flame graph it becomes clear that the application spends nearly all of its CPU cycles in&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;tenFastRequests&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;p&gt;A textual profile of the hot CPU methods, i.e., those that consume many CPU cycles in their own bodies rather than in calls to other methods, can be obtained like so:&lt;/p&gt;$ jfr view cpu-time-hot-methods profile.jfr&lt;p&gt;However, in this particular example, the output is not as useful as the flame graph.&lt;/p&gt;JEP 509: JFR CPU-Time Profiling (Experimental)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably, the CPU-time profiler also reports failed and missed samples, but more on that later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Problems of the new Profiler&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I pointed out all the problems in the current JFR method sampler, so I should probably point out my problems, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most significant issue is platform support, or better, the lack of it: The new profiler only supports Linux for the time being. While this is probably not a problem for production profiling, as most systems use Linux anyway, it’s a problem for profiling on developer machines. Most development happens on Windows and Mac OS machines. So, not being able to use the same profiler as in production hampers productivity. But this is a problem for other profilers too. Async-profiler, for example, only supports wall-clock profiling on Mac OS and doesn’t support Windows at all. JetBrains has a closed-source version of async-profiler that might support cpu-time profiling on Windows (see GitHub issue). Still, I could not confirm as I don’t have a Windows machine and found no specific information online.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another issue, of course, is that the profiler barely got in at the last minute, after Nicolai Parlog, for example, filmed his Java 25 update video.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why did it get into JDK 25?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most users only use and get access to LTS versions of the JDK, so we wanted to get the feature into the LTS JDK 25 to allow people to experiment with it. To quote Markus Grönlund:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am approving this PR for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;item&gt;We have reached a state that is “good enough” – I no longer see any fundamental design issues that can not be handled by follow-up bug fixes.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;There are still many vague aspects included with this PR, as many has already pointed out, mostly related to the memory model and thread interactions – all those can, and should, be clarified, explained and exacted post-integration.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The feature as a whole is experimental and turned off by default.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Today is the penultimate day before JDK 25 cutoff. To give the feature a fair chance for making JDK25, it needs approval now.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot Johannes and all involved for your hard work getting this feature ready.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many thanks&lt;/p&gt;Comment on the PR&lt;lb/&gt;Markus&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Open Issues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, use the profiler with care. None of the currently known issues should break the JVM. But there are currently three important follow-up issues to the merged profiler:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Avoid using a spinlock as the synchronization point returning from native in CPU Time Profiler [Edit July: fixed]&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clarify the requirements and exact the memory ordering in CPU Time Profiler: I used acquire-release semantics for most atomic variables, which is not wrong, just not necessarily optimal from a performance perspective.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fix interval recomputation in CPU Time Profiler [Edit July: fixed]&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have already started work on the last issue and will be looking into the other two soon. Please test the profiler yourself and report all the issues you find.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The new CPUTimeSample Event&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where the old profiler had two events &lt;code&gt;jdk.ExecutionSample&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;jdk.NativeMethodSample&lt;/code&gt;The new profiler has only one for simplicity, as it doesn’t treat threads in native and Java differently. As stated before, this event is called &lt;code&gt;jdk.CPUTimeSample&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The event has five different fields:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;stackTrace&lt;/code&gt;(nullable): Recorded stack trace&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;eventThread&lt;/code&gt;: Sampled thread&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;failed&lt;/code&gt;(boolean): Did the sampler fail to walk the stack trace? Implies that&lt;code&gt;stackTrace&lt;/code&gt;is&lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;samplingPeriod&lt;/code&gt;: The actual sampling period, directly computed in the signal handler. More on that next week.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;biased&lt;/code&gt;(boolean): Is this sample safepoint biased (the stacktrace related to the frame at safepoint and not the actual frame when the sampling request has been created, see Taming the Bias: Unbiased* Safepoint-Based Stack Walking in JFR for more)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find the event on the JFR Events Collection page too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Internally, the profiler uses bounded queues, which might overflow; this can result in lost events. The number of these events is regularly recorded in the form of the &lt;code&gt;jdk.CPUTimeSampleLoss&lt;/code&gt; event. The event has two fields:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;lostSamples&lt;/code&gt;: Number of samples that have been lost since the last&lt;code&gt;jdk.CPUTimeSampleLoss&lt;/code&gt;event&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;eventThread&lt;/code&gt;: Thread for which the samples are lost&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both events allow a pretty good view of the program’s execution, including a relatively exact view of the CPU time used.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Configuration of the CPU-time Profiler&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The emission of two events of the current sampler is controlled via the &lt;code&gt;period&lt;/code&gt; property. It allows the user to configure the sampling interval. The problem now with the CPU-time profiler is that it might produce too many events depending on the number of hardware threads. This is why the &lt;code&gt;jdk.CPUTimeSample&lt;/code&gt; event is controlled via the &lt;code&gt;throttle&lt;/code&gt; setting. This setting can be either a sampling interval or an upper bound for the number of emitted events.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When setting an interval directly like “10ms” (as in the &lt;code&gt;default.jfc&lt;/code&gt;), then we sample every thread every 10ms of CPU-time. This can at most result in 100 * #[hardware threads] events per second. On a 10 hardware thread machine, this results in at most (when every thread is CPU-bound) 1000 events per second or 12800 on a 128 hardware thread machine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setting, on the other hand, &lt;code&gt;throttle&lt;/code&gt; to a rate like “500/s” (as in the &lt;code&gt;profile.jfc&lt;/code&gt;), limits the number of events per second to a fixed rate. This is implemented by choosing the proper sampling interval in relation to the number of hardware threads. For a rate of “500/s” and a ten hardware thread machine, this would be 20ms. On a 128 hardware thread machine, this would be 0.256.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have to mention that the issue Fix interval recomputation in CPU Time Profiler is related to the recomputation when the number of hardware threads changes mid-profiling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;New JFR Views&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to the two new events, there are two new views that you can use via &lt;code&gt;jfr view VIEW_NAME profile.jfr&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cpu-time-hot-methods&lt;/code&gt; shows you a list of the 25 most executed methods. These are methods that are on top of the stack the most (running the example with a 1ms throttle):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Java Methods that Execute the Most from CPU Time Sampler (Experimental) Method Samples Percent ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- ------- ------- jdk.jfr.internal.JVM.emitEvent(long, long, long) 35 72.92% jdk.jfr.internal.event.EventWriter.putStringValue(String) 1 2.08% jdk.internal.loader.NativeLibraries.load(NativeLibraries$NativeLibraryImpl, String, boolean, boolean) 1 2.08% jdk.internal.logger.LazyLoggers$LazyLoggerAccessor.platform() 1 2.08% jdk.internal.jimage.ImageStringsReader.unmaskedHashCode(String, int) 1 2.08% sun.net.www.ParseUtil.quote(String, long, long) 1 2.08% java.net.HttpURLConnection.getResponseCode() 1 2.08% java.io.BufferedInputStream.read(byte[], int, int) 1 2.08% java.util.HashMap.hash(Object) 1 2.08% sun.nio.ch.NioSocketImpl$1.read(byte[], int, int) 1 2.08% java.util.Properties.load0(Properties$LineReader) 1 2.08% java.lang.StringLatin1.regionMatchesCI(byte[], int, byte[], int, int) 1 2.08% java.util.stream.AbstractPipeline.exactOutputSizeIfKnown(Spliterator) 1 2.08% sun.nio.fs.UnixChannelFactory$Flags.toFlags(Set) 1 2.08%&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second view is &lt;code&gt;cpu-time-statistics&lt;/code&gt; which gives you the number of successful samples, failed samples, biased Samples, total samples, and lost samples:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;CPU Time Sample Statistics -------------------------- Successful Samples: 48 Failed Samples: 0 Biased Samples: 0 Total Samples: 48 Lost Samples: 14&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of the lost samples are caused by the sampled Java thread running VM internal code. This view is really helpful when checking whether the profiling contains the whole picture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Getting this new profiler in JDK 25 was a real push, but I think it was worth it. OpenJDK now has a built-in CPU-time profiler that records missed samples. The implementation builds upon JFR’s new cooperative sampling approach, which also got into JDK 25 just days before. CPU-time profiling has many advantages, especially when you’re interested in the code that is actually wasting your CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the first of a two-part series on the new profiler. You can expect a deep dive into the implementation of the profiler next week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This blog post is part of my work in the SapMachine team at SAP, making profiling easier for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;P.S.: I submitted to a few conferences the talk From Idea to JEP: An OpenJDK Developer’s Journey to Improve Profiling with the following description: Have you ever wondered how profiling, like JFR, works in OpenJDK and how we can improve it? In this talk, I’ll take you on my three-year journey to improve profiling, especially method sampling, with OpenJDK: from the initial ideas and problems of existing approaches to my different draft implementations and JEP versions, with all the setbacks and friends I made along the way. It’s a story of blood, sweat, and C++.&lt;lb/&gt;It has sadly not been accepted yet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45230265</guid></item><item><title>Show HN: A store that generates products from anything you type in search</title><link>https://anycrap.shop/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45231378</guid></item><item><title>My first impressions of gleam</title><link>https://mtlynch.io/notes/gleam-first-impressions/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7c882e31ab6d3836"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;My First Impressions of Gleam&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m looking for a new programming language to learn this year, and Gleam looks like the most fun. It’s an Elixir-like language that supports static typing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I read the language tour, and it made sense to me, but I need to build something before I can judge a programming language well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m sharing some notes on my first few hours using Gleam in case they’re helpful to others learning Gleam or to the team developing the language.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My project: Parsing old AIM logs 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I used AOL Instant Messenger from about 1999 to 2007. For most of that time, I used AIM clients that logged my conversations, but they varied in formats. Most of the log formats are XML or HTML, which make re-reading those logs a pain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The simplest AIM logs are the plaintext logs, which look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Session Start (DumbAIMScreenName:Jane): Mon Sep 12 18:44:17 2005
[18:44] Jane: hi
[18:55] Me: hey whats up
Session Close (Jane): Mon Sep 12 18:56:02 2005
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every decade or so, I try writing a universal AIM log parser to get all of my old logs into a consistent, readable format. Unfortunately, I always get bored and give up partway through. My last attempt was seven years ago, when I tried doing it in Python 2.7.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parsing logs is a great match for Gleam because some parts of the project are easy (e.g., parsing the plaintext logs), so I can do the easy parts while I get the hang of Gleam as a language and gradually build up to the harder log formats and adding a web frontend.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve also heard that functional languages lend themselves especially well to parsing tasks, and I’ve never understood why, so it’s a good opportunity to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My background in programming languages 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been a programmer for 20 years, but I’m no language design connoisseur. I’m sharing things about Gleam I find unintuitive or difficult to work with, but they’re not language critiques, just candid reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve never worked in a langauge that’s designed for functional programming. The closest would be JavaScript. The languages I know best are Go and Python.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How do I parse command-line args? 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first thing I wanted to do was figure out how to parse a command-line argument so I could call my app like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;./log-parser ~/logs/aim/plaintext
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there’s no Gleam standard library module for reading command-line arguments. I found glint, and it felt super complicated for just reading one command-line argument. Then, I realized there’s a simpler third-party library called argv.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can parse the command-line argument like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pub fn main() {
  case argv.load().arguments {
    [path] -&amp;gt; io.println("command-line arg is " &amp;lt;&amp;gt; path)
    _ -&amp;gt; io.println("Usage: gleam run &amp;lt;directory_path&amp;gt;")
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam run ~/whatever
   Compiled in 0.01s
    Running log_parser.main
command-line arg is /home/mike/whatever
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cool, easy enough!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What does &lt;code&gt;gleam build&lt;/code&gt; do? 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I got my program to run with &lt;code&gt;gleam run&lt;/code&gt;, but I was curious if I could compile an executable like &lt;code&gt;go build&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;zig build&lt;/code&gt; does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam build
   Compiled in 0.01s
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hmm, compiled what? I couldn’t see a binary anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The documentation for &lt;code&gt;gleam build&lt;/code&gt; just says “Build the project” but doesn’t explain what it builds or where it stores the build artifact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; directory, but it doesn’t produce an obvious executable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ rm -rf build &amp;amp;&amp;amp; gleam build
Downloading packages
 Downloaded 5 packages in 0.00s
  Compiling argv
  Compiling gleam_stdlib
  Compiling filepath
  Compiling gleeunit
  Compiling simplifile
  Compiling log_parser
   Compiled in 0.52s

$ ls -1 build/
dev
gleam-dev-erlang.lock
gleam-dev-javascript.lock
gleam-lsp-erlang.lock
gleam-lsp-javascript.lock
gleam-prod-erlang.lock
gleam-prod-javascript.lock
packages
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From poking around, I think the executables are under &lt;code&gt;build/dev/erlang/log_parser/ebin/&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ ls -1 build/dev/erlang/log_parser/ebin/
log_parser.app
log_parser.beam
log_parser@@main.beam
log_parser_test.beam
plaintext_logs.beam
plaintext_logs_test.beam
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those appear to be BEAM bytecode, so I can’t execute them directly. I assume I could get run the BEAM VM manually and execute those files somehow, but that doesn’t sound appealing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, I’ll stick to &lt;code&gt;gleam run&lt;/code&gt; to run my app, but I wish &lt;code&gt;gleam build&lt;/code&gt; had a better explanation of what it produced and what the developer can do with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Let me implement the simplest possible parser 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To start, I decided to write a function that does basic parsing of plaintext logs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, I wrote a test with what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pub fn parse_simple_plaintext_log_test() {
  "
Session Start (DumbAIMScreenName:Jane): Mon Sep 12 18:44:17 2005
[18:44] Jane: hi
[18:55] Me: hey whats up
Session Close (Jane): Mon Sep 12 18:56:02 2005
"
  |&amp;gt; string.trim
  |&amp;gt; plaintext_logs.parse
  |&amp;gt; should.equal(["hi", "hey whats up"])
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eventually, I want to parse all the metadata in the conversation, including names, timestamps, and session information. But as a first step, all my function has to do is read an AIM chat log as a string and emit a list of the chat messages as separate strings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That meant my actual function would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pub fn parse(contents: String) -&amp;gt; List(String) {
  // Note: todo is a Gleam language keyword to indicate unfinished code.
  todo
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just to get it compiling, I add in a dummy implementation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pub fn parse(contents: String) -&amp;gt; List(String) {
  ["fake", "data"]
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And I can test it like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
  Compiling log_parser
warning: Unused variable
  ┌─ /home/mike/code/gleam-log-parser2/src/plaintext_logs.gleam:1:14
  │
1 │ pub fn parse(contents: String) -&amp;gt; List(String) {
  │              ^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^ This variable is never used

Hint: You can ignore it with an underscore: `_contents`.

   Compiled in 0.22s
    Running log_parser_test.main
F
Failures:

  1) plaintext_logs_test.parse_simple_plaintext_log_test: module 'plaintext_logs_test'
     Values were not equal
     expected: ["hi", "hey whats up"]
          got: ["fake", "data"]
     output:

Finished in 0.008 seconds
1 tests, 1 failures
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cool, that’s what I expected. The test is failing because it’s returning hardcoded dummy results that don’t match my test.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Adjusting my brain to a functional language 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, now it’s time to implement the parsing for real. I need to implement this function:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pub fn parse(contents: String) -&amp;gt; List(String) {
  todo
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, I kind of froze up. It struck me that Gleam excludes so many of the tools I’m used to in other languages:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There are no &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;statements&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There are no loops&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There’s no &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt;keyword&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There are no list index accessors&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;e.g., you can’t access the n-th element of a &lt;code&gt;List&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;e.g., you can’t access the n-th element of a &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What do I even do? Split the string into tokens and then do something with that?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eventually, I realized for a simple implementation, I wanted to just split the string into lines, so I want to do this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pub fn parse(contents: String) -&amp;gt; List(String) {
  string.split(contents, on: "\n")
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I test again, I get this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
  Compiling log_parser
   Compiled in 0.21s
    Running log_parser_test.main
F
Failures:

  1) plaintext_logs_test.parse_simple_plaintext_log_test: module 'plaintext_logs_test'
     Values were not equal
     expected: ["hi", "hey whats up"]
          got: ["Session Start (DumbAIMScreenName:Jane): Mon Sep 12 18:44:17 2005", "[18:44] Jane: hi", "[18:55] Me: hey whats up", "Session Close (Jane): Mon Sep 12 18:56:02 2005"]
     output:

Finished in 0.009 seconds
1 tests, 1 failures
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, now I’m a little closer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How do I iterate over a list in a language with no loops? 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I turned my logs into a list of lines, but that’s where I got stuck again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m so used to &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loops that my brain kept thinking, “How do I do a &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loop to iterate over the elements?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I realized I needed to call &lt;code&gt;list.map&lt;/code&gt;. I need to define a function that acts on each element of the list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import gleam/list
import gleam/string

fn parse_line(line: String) -&amp;gt; String {
  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    line -&amp;gt; line
  }
}

pub fn parse(contents: String) -&amp;gt; List(String) {
  string.split(contents, on: "\n")
  |&amp;gt; list.map(parse_line)
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is my first time using pattern matching in any language, and it’s neat, though it’s still so unfamiliar that I find it hard to recognize when to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zooming in a bit on the pattern matching, it’s here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    line -&amp;gt; line
  }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It evaluates the &lt;code&gt;line&lt;/code&gt; variable and matches it to one of the subsequent patterns within the braces. If the line starts with &lt;code&gt;"Session Start"&lt;/code&gt; (the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; means the preceding string is a prefix), then Gleam executes the code after the &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, which in this case is just the empty string. Same for &lt;code&gt;"Session Close"&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the line doesn’t match the &lt;code&gt;"Session Start"&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;"Session Close"&lt;/code&gt; patterns, Gleam executes the last line in the &lt;code&gt;case&lt;/code&gt; which just matches any string. In that case, it evaluates to the same string. Meaning &lt;code&gt;"hi"&lt;/code&gt; would evaluate to just &lt;code&gt;"hi"&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where it struck me how strange it feels to not have a &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; keyword. In every other language I know, you have to explicitly return a value from a function with a &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; keyword, but in Gleam, the return value is just the value from the last line that Gleam executes in the function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I run my test, I get this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
  Compiling log_parser
   Compiled in 0.22s
    Running log_parser_test.main
F
Failures:

  1) plaintext_logs_test.parse_simple_plaintext_log_test: module 'plaintext_logs_test'
     Values were not equal
     expected: ["hi", "hey whats up"]
          got: ["", "[18:44] Jane: hi", "[18:55] Me: hey whats up", ""]
     output:

Finished in 0.009 seconds
1 tests, 1 failures
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, this is what I expected, and I’m a bit closer to my goal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve converted the &lt;code&gt;"Session Start"&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;"Session End"&lt;/code&gt; lines to empty strings, and the middle two elements of the list are the lines that have AIM messages in them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The remaining work is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Strip out the time and sender parts of the log lines.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Filter out empty strings.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Scraping an AIM message from a line 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, I have a string like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;[18:55] Me: hey whats up
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And I need to extract just the portion after the sender’s name to this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;hey whats up
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My instinct is to use a string split function and split on the &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; character. I see that there’s &lt;code&gt;string.split&lt;/code&gt; which returns &lt;code&gt;List(String)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s also a &lt;code&gt;string.split_once&lt;/code&gt; function, which should work because I can split once on &lt;code&gt;: &lt;/code&gt;(note the trailing space after the colon).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem is that &lt;code&gt;split_once&lt;/code&gt; returns &lt;code&gt;Result(#(String, String), Nil)&lt;/code&gt;, a type that feels scarier to me. It’s a two-tuple wrapped in a &lt;code&gt;Result&lt;/code&gt;, which means that the function can return an error on failure. It’s confusing that &lt;code&gt;split_once&lt;/code&gt; can fail whereas &lt;code&gt;split&lt;/code&gt; cannot, so for simplicity, I’ll go with &lt;code&gt;split&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fn parse_line(line: String) -&amp;gt; String {
  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    line -&amp;gt; {
      echo string.split(line, on: ": ")
      todo
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I run my test, I get this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
warning: Todo found
   ┌─ /home/mike/code/gleam-log-parser/src/plaintext_logs.gleam:10:7
   │
10 │       todo
   │       ^^^^ This code is incomplete

This code will crash if it is run. Be sure to finish it before
running your program.

Hint: I think its type is `String`.


   Compiled in 0.01s
    Running log_parser_test.main
src/plaintext_logs.gleam:9
["[18:44] Jane", "hi"]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good. That’s doing what I want. I’m successfully isolating the &lt;code&gt;"hi"&lt;/code&gt; part, so now I just have to return it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How do I access the last element of a list? 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, I feel close to victory. I’ve converted the line to a list of strings, and I know the string I want is the last element of the list, but how do I grab it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In most other languages, I’d just say &lt;code&gt;line_parts[1]&lt;/code&gt;, but Gleam’s lists have no accessors by index.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at the &lt;code&gt;gleam/list&lt;/code&gt; module, I see a &lt;code&gt;list.last&lt;/code&gt; function, so I try that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fn parse_line(line: String) -&amp;gt; String {
  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    line -&amp;gt; {
       string.split(line, on: ": ")
       |&amp;gt; list.last
       |&amp;gt; echo
       |&amp;gt; todo
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I run that, I get:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
  Compiling log_parser
warning: Todo found
   ┌─ /home/mike/code/gleam-log-parser/src/plaintext_logs.gleam:12:11
   │
12 │        |&amp;gt; todo
   │           ^^^^ This code is incomplete

This code will crash if it is run. Be sure to finish it before
running your program.

Hint: I think its type is `fn(Result(String, Nil)) -&amp;gt; String`.


   Compiled in 0.24s
    Running log_parser_test.main
src/plaintext_logs.gleam:11
Ok("hi")
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A bit closer! I’ve extracted the last element of the list to find &lt;code&gt;"hi"&lt;/code&gt;, but now it’s wrapped in a &lt;code&gt;Result&lt;/code&gt; type.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can unwrap it with &lt;code&gt;result.unwrap&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fn parse_line(line: String) -&amp;gt; String {
  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    line -&amp;gt; {
       string.split(line, on: ": ")
       |&amp;gt; list.last
       |&amp;gt; result.unwrap("")
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Re-running &lt;code&gt;gleam test&lt;/code&gt; yields:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
  Compiling log_parser
   Compiled in 0.22s
    Running log_parser_test.main
F
Failures:

  1) plaintext_logs_test.parse_simple_plaintext_log_test: module 'plaintext_logs_test'
     Values were not equal
     expected: ["hi", "hey whats up"]
          got: ["", "hi", "hey whats up", ""]
     output:

Finished in 0.008 seconds
1 tests, 1 failures
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Great! That did what I wanted. I reduced the messages lines to just the contents of the messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Filtering out empty strings 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only thing that’s left is to filter the empty strings out of the list, which is straightforward enough with &lt;code&gt;list.filter&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pub fn parse(contents: String) -&amp;gt; List(String) {
  string.split(contents, on: "\n")
  |&amp;gt; list.map(parse_line)
  |&amp;gt; list.filter(fn(s) { !string.is_empty(s) })
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And I re-run the tests:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
  Compiling log_parser
   Compiled in 0.22s
    Running log_parser_test.main
.
Finished in 0.007 seconds
1 tests, 0 failures
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Voilà! The tests now pass!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tidying up string splitting 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My tests are now passing, so theoretically, I’ve achieved my initial goal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I could declare victory and call it a day. Or, I could refactor!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ll refactor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I feel somewhat ashamed of my string splitting logic, as it didn’t feel like idiomatic Gleam. Can I do it without getting into result unwrapping?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Re-reading it, I realize I can solve it with this newfangled pattern matching thing. I know that the string will split into a list with two elements, so I can create a pattern for a two-element list:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fn parse_line(line: String) -&amp;gt; String {
  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    line -&amp;gt; {
       case string.split(line, on: ": ") {
          [_, message] -&amp;gt; message
          _ -&amp;gt; ""
       }
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That feels a little more elegant than calling &lt;code&gt;result.last&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Can I tidy this up further? I avoided &lt;code&gt;string.split_once&lt;/code&gt; because the type was too confusing, but it’s probably the better option if I expect only one split, so what does that look like?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fn parse_line(line: String) -&amp;gt; String {
  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    line -&amp;gt; {
       echo string.split_once(line, on: ": ")
       todo
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To inspect the data, I run my test again:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
[...]
src/plaintext_logs.gleam:9
Ok(#("[18:44] Jane", "hi"))
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, that doesn’t look as scary as I thought. Even though my first instinct is to unwrap the error and access the last element in the tuple (which actually is easy for tuples, just not lists), I know at this point that there’s probably a pattern-matchy way. And there is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fn parse_line(line: String) -&amp;gt; String {
  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    line -&amp;gt; {
       case string.split_once(line, on: ": ") {
        Ok(#(_, message)) -&amp;gt; message
        _ -&amp;gt; ""
       }
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Ok(#(_, message))&lt;/code&gt; pattern will match a successful result from &lt;code&gt;split_once&lt;/code&gt;, which is a two-tuple of &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt; wrapped in an &lt;code&gt;Ok&lt;/code&gt; result. The other &lt;code&gt;case&lt;/code&gt; option is the catchall that returns an empty string.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Getting rid of the empty string hack 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the compelling features of Gleam for me is its static typing, so it feels hacky that I’m abusing the empty string to represent a lack of message on a particular line. Can I use the type system instead of using empty strings as sentinel values?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pattern in Gleam for indicating that something might fail but the failure isn’t necessarily an error is &lt;code&gt;Result(&amp;lt;type&amp;gt;, Nil)&lt;/code&gt;, so let me try to rewrite it that way:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import gleam/list
import gleam/result
import gleam/string

fn parse_line(line: String) -&amp;gt; Result(String, Nil) {
  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; Error(Nil)
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; Error(Nil)
    line -&amp;gt; {
       case string.split_once(line, on: ": ") {
        Ok(#(_, message)) -&amp;gt; Ok(message)
        _ -&amp;gt; Error(Nil)
       }
    }
  }
}

pub fn parse(contents: String) -&amp;gt; List(String) {
  string.split(contents, on: "\n")
  |&amp;gt; list.map(parse_line)
  |&amp;gt; result.values
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Great! I like being more explicit that the lines without messages return &lt;code&gt;Error(Nil)&lt;/code&gt; rather than an empty string. Also, &lt;code&gt;result.values&lt;/code&gt; is more succinct for filtering empty lines than the previous &lt;code&gt;list.filter(fn(s) { !string.is_empty(s) })&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Overall reflections 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After spending a few hours with Gleam, I’m enjoying it. It pushes me out of my comfort zone the right amount where I feel like I’m learning new ways of thinking about programming but not so much that I’m too overwhelmed to learn anything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The biggest downside I’m finding with Gleam is that it’s a young language with a relatively small team. It just turned six years old, but it looks like the founder was working on it solo until a year ago. There are now a handful of core maintainers, but I don’t know if any of them work on Gleam full-time, so the ecosystem is a bit limited. I’m looking ahead to parsing other log formats that are in HTML and XML, and there are Gleam HTML and XML parsers, but they don’t seem widely used, so I’m not sure how well they’ll work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Love: Pipelines 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I love love love Gleam’s pipeline syntax. You can see me using it in the test with the &lt;code&gt;|&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; characters:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt; "..."
  |&amp;gt; string.trim
  |&amp;gt; plaintext_logs.parse
  |&amp;gt; should.equal(["hi", "hey whats up"])
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The non-pipeline equivalent of the test would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pub fn parse_simple_plaintext_log_test() {
  let input = "..."
  let trimmed = string.trim(input)
  let parsed = plaintext_logs.parse(trimmed)

  should.equal(parsed, ["hi", "hey whats up"])
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It looks like wet garbage by comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve seen pipelines, they feel so obvious and conspicuously missing in every other programming language I use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve enjoyed pipelining in bash, but it never occurred to me how strange it is that other programming languages never adopted it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Like: Example-centric documentation 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Gleam documentation is a bit terse, but I like that it’s so example-heavy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I learn best by reading examples, so I appreciate that so much of the Gleam standard library is documented with examples showing simple usage of each API function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Like: Built-in unused symbol warnings 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I like that the Gleam compiler natively warns about unused functions, variables, and imports. And I like that these are warnings rather than errors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Go, I get frustrated during debugging when I temporarily comment something out and then the compiler stubbornly refuses to do anything until I fix the stupid import, which I then have to un-fix when I finish whatever I was debugging.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Like: &lt;code&gt;todo&lt;/code&gt; keyword 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of my favorite dumb programming jokes happened at my first programming job about 15 years ago. On a group email thread with several C++ developers, my friend shared a hot tip about C++ development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He said that if we were ever got fed up with arcane C++ compilation errors, we could just add a special line to our source code, and then even invalid C++ code would compile successfully:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#pragma always_compile
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert: it’s not a real C++ preprocessor directive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I’ve found myself occasionally wishing languages had something like this when I’m in the middle of development and don’t care about whatever bugs the compiler is trying to protect me from.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gleam’s &lt;code&gt;todo&lt;/code&gt; is almost like a &lt;code&gt;#pragma always_compile&lt;/code&gt;. Even if your code is invalid, the Gleam compiler just says, “Okay, fine. I’ll run it anyway.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can see this when I was in the middle of implementing &lt;code&gt;parse_line&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fn parse_line(line: String) -&amp;gt; String {
  case line {
    "Session Start" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    "Session Close" &amp;lt;&amp;gt; _ -&amp;gt; ""
    line -&amp;gt; {
      echo string.split(line, on: ": ")
      todo
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I take out the &lt;code&gt;todo&lt;/code&gt;, Gleam refuses to run the code at all:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
  Compiling log_parser
error: Type mismatch
   ┌─ /home/mike/code/gleam-log-parser/src/plaintext_logs.gleam:8:5
   │
 8 │ ╭     line -&amp;gt; {
 9 │ │       echo string.split(line, on: ": ")
10 │ │     }
   │ ╰─────^

This case clause was found to return a different type than the previous
one, but all case clauses must return the same type.

Expected type:

    String

Found type:

    List(String)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right, I’m returning an incorrect type, so why would the compiler cooperate with me?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But adding &lt;code&gt;todo&lt;/code&gt; lets me run the function anyway, which helps me understand what the code is doing even though I haven’t finished implementing it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ gleam test
warning: Todo found
   ┌─ /home/mike/code/gleam-log-parser/src/plaintext_logs.gleam:10:7
   │
10 │       todo
   │       ^^^^ This code is incomplete

This code will crash if it is run. Be sure to finish it before
running your program.

Hint: I think its type is `String`.


  Compiling log_parser
   Compiled in 0.21s
    Running log_parser_test.main
src/plaintext_logs.gleam:9
["[18:44] Jane", "hi"]
F
[...]
Finished in 0.007 seconds
1 tests, 1 failures
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Like: Pattern matching 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I find pattern matching elegant and concise, though it’s the part of Gleam I find hardest to adjust to. It feels so different from procedural style of programming I’m accustomed to in other languages I know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The downside is that I have a hard time recognizing when pattern matching is the right tool, and I also find pattern matching harder to read. But I think that’s just inexperience, and I think with more practice, I’ll be able to think in pattern matching.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Dislike: Error handling 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I find Gleam’s error handling pretty awkward, especially because errors ruin the beauty of nice, tidy pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, if I had a string processing pipeline like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;string.split(line, on: "-")
|&amp;gt; list.last
|&amp;gt; result.unwrap("") // Ugly!
|&amp;gt; string.uppercase
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That &lt;code&gt;result.unwrap&lt;/code&gt; line feels so ugly and out of place to me. I wish the syntax was like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;string.split(line, on: ": ")
|&amp;gt; try list.last
|&amp;gt; string.uppercase
|&amp;gt; Ok
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code&gt;try&lt;/code&gt; causes the function to return an error, kind of like in Zig.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Dislike: Small core language 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t know if this is a long-term design choice or if it’s just small for now because it’s an indie-developed language, but the first thing about Gleam that stood out to me is how few built-in features there are.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, there’s no built-in feature for iterating over the elements of a &lt;code&gt;List&lt;/code&gt; type, and the type itself doesn’t expose a function to iterate it, so you have to use the &lt;code&gt;gleam/list&lt;/code&gt; module in the standard library.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, if a function can fail, it returns a &lt;code&gt;Result&lt;/code&gt; type, and there are no built-in functions for handling a &lt;code&gt;Result&lt;/code&gt;, so you have to use the &lt;code&gt;gleam/result&lt;/code&gt; module to check if the function succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To me, that functionality feels so core to the language that it would be part of the language itself, not the standard library.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Dislike: Limited standard library 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to the language feeling small, the standard library feels pretty limited as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are currently only 19 modules in the Gleam standard library. Conspicuously absent are modules for working with the filesystem (the de facto standard seems to be the third-party simplifile module).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For comparison, the standard libraries for Python and Go each have about 250 modules. Although, in fairness, those languages have about 1000x the resources as Gleam.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Source code 🔗︎&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The source code for this project is available on Codeberg:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commit 291e6d is the version that matches this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Isaac Harris-Holt for helpful feedback on this post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Read My Book&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm writing a book of simple techniques to help developers improve their writing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My book will teach you how to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create clear and pleasant software tutorials&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Attract readers and customers through blogging&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Write effective emails&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Minimize pain in writing design documents&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Be the first to know when I post cool stuff&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Subscribe to get my latest posts by email.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45231852</guid></item><item><title>Japan sets record of nearly 100k people aged over 100</title><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cd07nljlyv0o</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6ee893ba9e23bf7f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Japan sets record of nearly 100,000 people aged over 100&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The number of people in Japan aged 100 or older has risen to a record high of nearly 100,000, its government has announced.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setting a new record for the 55th year in a row, the number of centenarians in Japan was 99,763 as of September, the health ministry said on Friday. Of that total, women accounted for an overwhelming 88%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Japan has the world's longest life expectancy, and is known for often being home to the world's oldest living person - though some studies contest the actual number of centenarians worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is also one of the fastest ageing societies, with residents often having a healthier diet but a low birth rate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The oldest person in Japan is 114-year-old Shigeko Kagawa, a woman from Yamatokoriyama, a suburb of the city Nara. Meanwhile, the oldest man is Kiyotaka Mizuno, 111, from the coastal city of Iwata.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Health minister Takamaro Fukoka congratulated the 87,784 female and 11,979 male centenarians on their longevity and expressed his "gratitude for their many years of contributions to the development of society".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The figures were released ahead of Japan's Elderly Day on 15 September, a national holiday where new centenarians receive a congratulatory letter and silver cup from the prime minister. This year, 52,310 individuals were eligible, the health ministry said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the 1960s, Japan's population had the lowest proportion of people aged over 100 of any G7 country - but that has changed remarkably in the decades since.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When its government began the centenarian survey in 1963, there were 153 people aged 100 or over.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That figure rose to 1,000 in 1981 and stood at 10,000 by 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The higher life expectancy is mainly attributed to fewer deaths from heart disease and common forms of cancer, in particular breast and prostate cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Japan has low rates of obesity, a major contributing factor to both diseases, thanks to diets low in red meat and high in fish and vegetables.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The obesity rate is particularly low for women, which could go some way to explaining why Japanese women have a much higher life expectancy than their male counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As increased quantities of sugar and salt crept into diets in the rest of the world, Japan went in the other direction - with public health messaging successfully convincing people to reduce their salt consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it's not just diet. Japanese people tend to stay active into later life, walking and using public transport more than elderly people in the US and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radio Taiso, a daily group exercise, has been a part of Japanese culture since 1928, established to encourage a sense of community as well as public health. The three-minute routine is broadcast on television and practised in small community groups across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, several studies have cast doubt on the validity of global centenarian numbers, suggesting data errors, unreliable public records and missing birth certificates may account for elevated figures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A government audit of family registries in Japan in 2010 uncovered more than 230,000 people listed as being aged 100 or older who were unaccounted for, some having in fact died decades previously.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The miscounting was attributed to patchy record-keeping and suspicions that some families may have tried to hide the deaths of elderly relatives in order to claim their pensions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The national inquiry was launched after the remains of Sogen Koto, believed to be the oldest man in Tokyo at 111, were found in his family home 32 years after his death.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45232052</guid></item><item><title>Mago: A fast PHP toolchain written in Rust</title><link>https://github.com/carthage-software/mago</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3150525899f3e1de"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An extremely fast PHP linter, formatter, and static analyzer, written in Rust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mago is a comprehensive toolchain for PHP that helps developers write better code. Inspired by the Rust ecosystem, Mago brings speed, reliability, and an exceptional developer experience to PHP projects of all sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Installation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Getting Started&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Features&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Our Sponsors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Contributing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inspiration &amp;amp; Acknowledgements&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;License&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most common way to install Mago on macOS and Linux is by using our shell script:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;curl --proto '=https' --tlsv1.2 -sSf https://carthage.software/mago.sh | bash&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For all other installation methods, including Homebrew, Composer, and Cargo, please refer to our official Installation Guide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get started with Mago and learn how to configure your project, please visit our Getting Started Guide in the official documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;⚡️ Extremely Fast: Built in Rust for maximum performance.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🔍 Lint: Identify issues in your codebase with customizable rules.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🔬 Static Analysis: Perform deep analysis of your codebase to catch potential type errors and bugs.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🛠️ Automated Fixes: Apply fixes for many lint issues automatically.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📜 Formatting: Automatically format your code to adhere to best practices and style guides.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🧠 Semantic Checks: Ensure code correctness with robust semantic analysis.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🌳 AST Visualization: Explore your code’s structure with Abstract Syntax Tree (AST) parsing.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mago is a community-driven project, and we welcome contributions! Whether you're reporting bugs, suggesting features, writing documentation, or submitting code, your help is valued.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;See our Contributing Guide to get started.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Join the discussion on Discord.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mago stands on the shoulders of giants. Our design and functionality are heavily inspired by pioneering tools in both the Rust and PHP ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clippy: For its comprehensive linting approach.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OXC: A major inspiration for building a high-performance toolchain in Rust.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hakana: For its deep static analysis capabilities.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We deeply respect the foundational work of tools like PHP-CS-Fixer, Psalm, PHPStan, and PHP_CodeSniffer. While Mago aims to offer a unified and faster alternative, these tools paved the way for modern PHP development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mago is dual-licensed under your choice of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MIT License (LICENSE-MIT)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apache License, Version 2.0 (LICENSE-APACHE)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45232275</guid></item><item><title>Show HN: CLAVIER-36 – A programming environment for generative music</title><link>https://clavier36.com/p/LtZDdcRP3haTWHErgvdM</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="536fd5a56c585c00"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;×&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45232299</guid></item><item><title>‘Someone must know this guy’: four-year wedding crasher mystery solved</title><link>https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2025/sep/12/wedding-crasher-mystery-solved-four-years-bride-scotland</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="67528137d6155029"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A baffled bride has solved the mystery of the awkward-looking stranger who crashed her wedding four years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michelle Wylie and her husband, John, registered the presence of their unidentifiable guest only as they looked through photographs of their wedding in the days after the happy occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Who was the tall man in a dark suit, distinguished by the look of quiet mortification on his face? But their family and friends could offer no explanation, nor could hotel staff at the Carlton hotel in Prestwick, where the event took place in November 2021. An appeal on Facebook likewise yielded no clues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eventually, with the mystery still niggling, Wylie asked the popular Scottish content creator Dazza to cast the online net wider – and a sheepish Andrew Hillhouse finally stepped forward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In his explanatory post on Facebook, Hillhouse admitted that he had been “cutting it fine, as I’m known to do” when he pulled up at the wedding venue with five minutes to spare. Spotting a piper and other guests, he followed them into the hotel – “I remember thinking to myself: ‘Cool, this is obviously the right place’” – unaware that he had the address completely wrong and was supposed to be at a ceremony 2 miles away in Ayr.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He was initially unperturbed to find himself surrounded by strangers as the ceremony began – at the marriage he was due to attend, the only person he knew was the bride, Michaela, while his partner, Andrew, was part of the wedding party. It was when an entirely different bride came walking down the aisle that he realised: “OMG that’s not Michaela … I was at the wrong wedding!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hillhouse said: “You can’t exactly stand up and walk out of a wedding mid-ceremony, so I just had to commit to this act and spent the next 20 minutes awkwardly sitting there trying to be as inconspicuous as my 6ft 2 ass could be.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of the ceremony, Hillhouse, who is from Troon, was hoping to make a discreet exit, only to be waylaid by the wedding photographer, who insisted he join other guests for a group shot. He can be spotted looming uncomfortably at the very back of the crowd.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His post continued: “Rushed outside, made some phone calls and made my way to the correct wedding, where I was almost as popular as the actual bride and groom, and spent most of the night retelling that story to people.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Michelle Wylie, this amiable resolution brings to a close years of speculation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She told BBC Scotland: “It would come into my head and I’d be like: ‘Someone must know who this guy is.’ I said a few times to my husband: ‘Are you sure you don’t know this guy, is he maybe from your work?’ We wondered if he was a mad stalker.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She is now Facebook friends with Hillhouse and the pair have met in person to cement their coincidental bond.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I could not stop laughing,” said Wylie. “We can’t believe we’ve found out who he is after almost four years.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45232562</guid></item><item><title>486Tang – 486 on a credit-card-sized FPGA board</title><link>https://nand2mario.github.io/posts/2025/486tang_486_on_a_credit_card_size_fpga_board/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3a1d596421a49ee2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;486Tang - 486 on a credit-card-sized FPGA board&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yesterday I released 486Tang v0.1 on GitHub. It’s a port of the ao486 MiSTer PC core to the Sipeed Tang Console 138K FPGA. I’ve been trying to get an x86 core running on the Tang for a while. As far as I know, this is the first time ao486 has been ported to a non-Altera FPGA. Here’s a short write‑up of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;486Tang Architecture&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every FPGA board is a little different. Porting a core means moving pieces around and rewiring things to fit. Here are the major components in 486Tang:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compared to ao486 on MiSTer, there are a few major differences:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Switching to SDRAM for main memory. The MiSTer core uses DDR3 as main memory. Obviously, at the time of the 80486, DDR didn’t exist, so SDRAM is a natural fit. I also wanted to dedicate DDR3 to the framebuffer; time‑multiplexing it would have been complicated. So SDRAM became the main memory and DDR3 the framebuffer. The SDRAM on Tang is 16‑bit wide while ao486 expects 32‑bit accesses, which would normally mean one 32‑bit word every two cycles. I mitigated this by running the SDRAM logic at 2× the system clock so a 32‑bit word can be read or written every CPU cycle (“double‑pumping” the memory).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;SD‑backed IDE. On MiSTer, the core forwards IDE requests to the ARM HPS over a fast HPS‑FPGA link; the HPS then accesses a VHD image. Tang doesn’t have a comparable high‑speed MCU‑to‑FPGA interface—only a feeble UART—so I moved disk storage into the SD card and let the FPGA access it directly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Boot‑loading module. A PC needs several things to boot: BIOS, VGA BIOS, CMOS settings, and IDE IDENTIFY data (512 bytes). Since I didn’t rely on an MCU for disk data, I stored all of these in the first 128 KB of the SD card. A small boot loader module reads them into main memory and IDE, and then releases the CPU when everything is ready.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;System bring-up with the help of a whole-system simulator&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After restructuring the system, the main challenge was bringing it up to a DOS prompt. A 486 PC is complex—CPU and peripherals—more so than the game consoles I’ve worked on. The ao486 CPU alone is &amp;gt;25K lines of Verilog, versus a few K for older cores like M68K. Debugging on hardware was painful: GAO builds took 10+ minutes and there were many more signals to probe. Without a good plan, it would be unmanageable and bugs could take days to isolate—not viable for a hobby project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My solution was Verilator for subsystem and whole‑system simulation. The codebase is relatively mature, so I skipped per‑module unit tests and focused on simulating subsystems like VGA and a full boot to DOS. Verilator is fast enough to reach a DOS prompt in a few minutes—an order of magnitude better if you factor in the complete waveforms you get in simulation. The trick, then, is surfacing useful progress and error signals. A few simple instrumentation hooks were enough for me:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Bochs BIOS can print debug strings to port 0x8888 in debug builds. I intercept and print these (the yellow messages in the simulator). The same path exists on hardware—the CPU forwards them over UART—so BIOS issues show up immediately without waiting for a GAO build.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsystem‑scoped tracing. For Sound Blaster, IDE, etc., I added&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;--sound&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;--ide&lt;/code&gt;flags to trace I/O operations and key state changes. This is much faster than editing Verilog or using GAO.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Bochs BIOS assembly listings are invaluable. I initially used a manual disassembly—old console habits—without symbols, which was painful. Rebuilding Bochs and using the official listings solved that.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lot of the bugs were in the new glue I added, as expected. ao486 itself is mature. Still, a few issues only showed up on this toolchain/hardware, mostly due to toolchain behavior differences. In one case a variable meant to be static behaved like an automatic variable and didn’t retain state across invocations, so a CE pulse never occurred. Buried deep, it took a while to find.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s a simulation session. On the left the simulated 486 screen. On the right is the simulator terminal output. You can see the green VGA output and yellow debug output, along with other events like INT 15h and video VSYNCs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Performance optimizations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With simulation help, the core ran on Tang Console—just not fast. The Gowin GW5A isn’t a particularly fast FPGA. Initial benchmarks put it around a 25 MHz 80386.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The main obstacle to clock speed is long combinational paths. When you find a critical path, you either shorten it or pipeline it by inserting registers—both risks bugs. A solid test suite is essential; I used test386.asm to validate changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are a few concrete wins:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reset tree and fan-out reduction. Gowin’s tools didn’t replicate resets aggressively enough (even with “Place → Replicate Resources”). One reset net had &amp;gt;5,000 fan-out, which ballooned delays. Manually replicating the reset and a few other high‑fan-out nets helped a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instruction fetch optimization. A long combinational chain sat in the decode/fetch interface. In &lt;code&gt;decoder_regs.v&lt;/code&gt;, the number of bytes the fetcher may accept was computed using the last decoded instruction’s length:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;reg [3:0] decoder_count;
assign acceptable_1     = 4'd12 - decoder_count + consume_count;
always @(posedge clk) begin
  ...
  decoder_count &amp;lt;= after_consume_count + accepted;
end
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;code&gt;12&lt;/code&gt; is the buffer size, &lt;code&gt;decoder_count&lt;/code&gt; is the current occupancy, and &lt;code&gt;consume_count&lt;/code&gt; is the length of the outgoing instruction. Reasonable—but computing &lt;code&gt;consume_count&lt;/code&gt; (opcode, ModR/M, etc.) was on the Fmax‑limiting path. By the way, this is one of several well-known problems of the x86 - variable length instructions complicating decoding, another is complex address modes and “effective address” calculation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fix was to drop the dependency on &lt;code&gt;consume_count&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;assign acceptable_1    = 4'd12 - decoder_count;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This may cause the fetcher to “under‑fetch” for one cycle because the outgoing instruction’s space isn’t reclaimed immediately. But &lt;code&gt;decoder_count&lt;/code&gt; updates next cycle, reclaiming the space. With a 12‑byte buffer, the CPI impact was negligible and Fmax improved measurably on this board.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TLB optimization. The Translation Lookaside Buffer (TLB) is a small cache that translates virtual to physical addresses. ao486 uses a 32‑entry fully‑associative TLB with a purely combinational read path—zero extra cycles, but a long path on every memory access (code and data).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DOS workloads barely stress the TLB; even many 386 extenders use a flat model. As a first step I converted the TLB to 4‑way set‑associative. That’s simpler and already slightly faster than fully‑associative for these workloads. There’s room to optimize further since the long combinational path rarely helps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A rough v0.1 end‑to‑end result: about +35% per Landmark 6 benchmarks, reaching roughly 486SX‑20 territory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Reflections&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are a few reflections after the port:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clock speed scaling. I appreciate the lure of the megahertz race now. Scaling the whole system clock was the most effective lever—more so than extra caches or deeper pipelines at this stage. Up to ~200–300 MHz, CPU, memory, and I/O can often scale together. After that, memory latency dominates, caches grow deeper, and once clock speeds stop increasing, multiprocessing takes over—the story of the 2000s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;x86 vs. ARM. Working with ao486 deepened my respect for x86’s complexity. John Crawford’s 1990 paper “The i486 CPU: Executing Instructions in One Clock Cycle” is a great read; it argues convincingly against scrapping x86 for a new RISC ISA given the software base (10K+ apps then). Compatibility was the right bet, but the baggage is real. By contrast, last year’s ARM7‑based GBATang felt refreshingly simple: fixed‑length 32‑bit instructions, saner addressing, and competitive performance. You can’t have your cake and eat it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So there you have it—that’s 486Tang in v0.1. Thanks for reading, and see you next time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45232565</guid></item><item><title>Magical systems thinking</title><link>https://worksinprogress.co/issue/magical-systems-thinking/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a568110c0f83cf69"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Systems thinking promises to give us a toolkit to design complex systems that work from the ground up. It fails because it ignores an important fact: systems fight back.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The systems that enable modern life share a common origin. The water supply, the internet, the international supply chains bringing us cheap goods: each began life as a simple, working system. The first electric grid was no more than a handful of electric lamps hooked up to a water wheel in Godalming, England, in 1881. It then took successive decades of tinkering and iteration by thousands of very smart people to scale these systems to the advanced state we enjoy today. At no point did a single genius map out the final, finished product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this lineage of (mostly) working systems is easily forgotten. Instead, we prefer a more flattering story: that complex systems are deliberate creations, the product of careful analysis. And, relatedly, that by performing this analysis – now known as ‘systems thinking’ in the halls of government – we can bring unruly ones to heel. It is an optimistic perspective, casting us as the masters of our systems and our destiny.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The empirical record says otherwise, however. Our recent history is one of governments grappling with complex systems and coming off worse. In the United States, HealthCare.gov was designed to simplify access to health insurance by knitting together 36 state marketplaces and data from eight federal agencies. Its launch was paralyzed by technical failures that locked out millions of users. Australia’s disability reforms, carefully planned for over a decade and expected to save money, led to costs escalating so rapidly that they will soon exceed the pension budget. The UK’s 2014 introduction of Contracts for Difference, intended to speed the renewables rollout by giving generators a guaranteed price, overstrained the grid and is a major contributor to the 15-year queue for new connections. Systems thinking is more popular than ever; modern systems thinkers have analytical tools that their predecessors could only have dreamt of. But the systems keep kicking back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a better way. A long but neglected line of thinkers going back to chemists in the nineteenth century has argued that complex systems are not our passive playthings. Despite friendly names like ‘the health system’, they demand extreme wariness. If broken, a complex system often cannot be fixed. Meanwhile, our successes, when they do come, are invariably the result of starting small. As the systems we have built slip further beyond our collective control, it is these simple working systems that offer us the best path back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The world model&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1970, the ‘Club of Rome’, a group of international luminaries with an interest in how the problems of the world were interrelated, invited Jay Wright Forrester to peer into the future of the global economy. An MIT expert on electrical and mechanical engineering, Forrester had cut his teeth on problems like how to keep a Second World War aircraft carrier’s radar pointed steadily at the horizon amid the heavy swell of the Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Club of Rome asked an even more intricate question: how would social and economic forces interact in the coming decades? Where were the bottlenecks and feedback mechanisms? Could economic growth continue, or would the world enter a new phase of equilibrium or decline?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Forrester labored hard, producing a mathematical model of enormous sophistication. Across 130 pages of mathematical equations, computer graphical printout, and DYNAMO code,World Dynamics tracks the myriad relationships between natural resources, capital, population, food, and pollution: everything from the ‘capital-investment-in-agriculture-fraction adjustment time’ to the ominous ‘death-rate-from-pollution multiplier’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;World leaders had assumed that economic growth was an unalloyed good. But Forrester’s results showed the opposite. As financial and population growth continued, natural resources would be consumed at an accelerating rate, agricultural land would be paved over, and pollution would reach unmanageable levels. His model laid out dozens of scenarios and in most of them, by 2025, the world would already be in the first throes of an irreversible decline in living standards. By 2070, the crunch would be so painful that industrialized nations might regret their experiment with economic growth altogether. As Forrester put it, ‘[t]he present underdeveloped countries may be in a better condition for surviving forthcoming worldwide environmental and economic pressures than are the advanced countries.’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But, as we now know, the results were also wrong. Adjusting for inflation, world GDP is now about five times higher than it was in 1970 and continues to rise. More than 90 percent of that growth has come from Asia, Europe, and North America, but forest cover across those regions has increased, up 2.6 percent since 1990 to over 2.3 billion hectares in 2020. The death rate from air pollution has almost halved in the same period, from 185 per 100,000 in 1990 to 100 in 2021. According to the model, none of this should have been possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What happened? The blame cannot lie with Forrester’s competence: it’s hard to imagine a better systems pedigree than his. To read his prose today is to recognize a brilliant, thoughtful mind. Moreover, the system dynamics approach Forrester pioneered had already shown promise beyond the mechanical and electrical systems that were its original inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1956, the management of a General Electric refrigerator factory in Kentucky had called on Forrester’s help. They were struggling with a boom-and-bust cycle: acute shortages became gluts that left warehouses overflowing with unsold fridges. The factory based its production decisions on orders from the warehouse, which in turn got orders from distributors, who heard from retailers, who dealt with customers. Each step introduced noise and delay. Ripples in demand would be amplified into huge swings in production further up the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at the system as a whole, Forrester recognized the same feedback loops and instability that could bedevil a ship’s radar. He developed new decision rules, such as smoothing production based on longer-term sales data rather than immediate orders, and found ways to speed up the flow of information between retailers, distributors, and the factory. These changes dampened the oscillations caused by the system’s own structure, checking its worst excesses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Kentucky factory story showed Forrester’s skill as a systems analyst. Back at MIT, Forrester immortalized his lessons as a learning exercise (albeit with beer instead of refrigerators). In the ‘Beer Game’, now a rite of passage for students at the MIT Sloan School of Management, players take one of four different roles in the beer supply chain: retailer, wholesaler, distributor, and brewer. Each player sits at a separate table and can communicate only through order forms. As their inventory runs low, they place orders with the supplier next upstream. Orders take time to process, and shipments to arrive, and each player can see only their small part of the chain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The objective of the Beer Game is to minimize costs by managing inventory effectively. But, as the GE factory managers had originally found, this is not so easy. Gluts and shortages arise mysteriously, without obvious logic, and small perturbations in demand get amplified up the chain by as much as 800 percent (‘the bullwhip effect’). On average, players’ total costs end up being ten times higher than the optimal solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the failure of his World Model, Forrester had fallen into the same trap as his MIT students. Systems analysis works best under specific conditions: when the system is static; when you can dismantle and examine it closely; when it involves few moving parts rather than many; and when you can iterate fixes through multiple attempts. A faulty ship’s radar or a simple electronic circuit are ideal. Even a limited human element – with people’s capacity to pursue their own plans, resist change, form political blocs, and generally frustrate best-laid plans – makes things much harder. The four-part refrigerator supply chain, with the factory, warehouse, distributor and retailer all under the tight control of management, is about the upper limit of what can be understood. Beyond that, in the realm of societies, governments and economies, systems thinking becomes a liability, more likely to breed false confidence than real understanding. For these systems we need a different approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Le Chatelier’s Principle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1884, in a laboratory at the École des Mines in Paris, Henri Louis Le Chatelier noticed something peculiar: chemical reactions seemed to resist changes imposed upon them. Le Chatelier found that if, say, you have an experiment where two molecules combine in a heat-generating exothermic reaction (in his case, it was two reddish-brown nitrogen dioxide molecules combining into colorless dinitrogen tetroxide and giving off heat in the process), then you can speed things up by cooling the reactants. To ‘resist’ the drop in temperature, the system restores its equilibrium by creating more of the products that release heat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Le Chatelier’s Principle, the idea that the system always kicks back, proved to be a very general and powerful way to think about chemistry. It was instrumental in the discovery of the Haber-Bosch process for creating ammonia that revolutionized agriculture. Nobel Laureate Linus Pauling hoped that, even after his students had ‘forgotten all the mathematical equations relating to chemical equilibrium’, Le Chatelier’s Principle would be the one thing they remembered. And its usefulness went beyond chemistry. A century after Le Chatelier’s meticulous lab work, another student of systems would apply the principle to the complex human systems that had stymied Forrester and his subsequent followers in government.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;John Gall was a pediatrician with a long-standing practice in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Of the same generation as Forrester, Gall came at things from a different direction. Whereas Forrester’s background was in mechanical and electrical systems, which worked well and solved new problems, Gall was immersed in the human systems of health, education, and government. These systems often did not work well. How was it, Gall wondered, that they seemed to coexist happily with the problems – crime, poverty, ill health – they were supposed to stamp out?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Le Chatelier’s Principle provided an answer: systems should not be thought of as benign entities that will faithfully carry out their creators’ intentions. Rather, over time, they come to oppose their own proper functioning. Gall elaborated on this idea in his 1975 book Systemantics, named for the universal tendency of systems to display antics. A brief, weird, funny book, Systemantics (The Systems Bible in later editions) is arguably the best field guide to contemporary systems dysfunction. It consists of a series of pithy aphorisms, which the reader is invited to apply to explain the system failures (‘horrible examples’) they witness every day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These aphorisms are provocatively stated, but they have considerable explanatory power. For example, an Australian politician frustrated at the new headaches created by ‘fixes’ to the old disability system might be reminded that ‘NEW SYSTEMS CREATE NEW PROBLEMS’. An American confused at how there can now be 190,000 pages in the US Code of Federal Regulations, up from 10,000 in 1950, might note that this is the nature of the beast: ‘SYSTEMS TEND TO GROW, AND AS THEY GROW THEY ENCROACH’. During the French Revolution, in 1793 and 1794, the ‘Committee of Public Safety’ guillotined thousands of people, an early example of the enduring principles that ‘THE SYSTEM DOES NOT DO WHAT IT SAYS IT IS DOING’ and that ‘THE NAME IS EMPHATICALLY NOT THE THING’. And, just like student chemists, government reformers everywhere would do well to remember Le Chatelier’s Principle: ‘THE SYSTEM ALWAYS KICKS BACK’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These principles encourage a healthy paranoia when it comes to complex systems. But Gall’s ‘systems-display-antics’ philosophy is not a counsel of doom. His greatest insight was a positive one, explaining how some systems do succeed in spite of the pitfalls. Known as ‘Gall’s law’, it’s worth quoting in full:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A complex system that works is invariably found to have evolved from a simple system that worked. A complex system designed from scratch never works and cannot be patched up to make it work. You have to start over with a working simple system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting with a working simple system and evolving from there is how we went from the water wheel in Godalming to the modern electric grid. It is how we went from a hunk of germanium, gold foil, and hand-soldered wires in 1947 to transistors being etched onto silicon wafers in their trillions today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a dynamic we can experience on a personal as well as a historical level. A trivial but revealing example is the computer game Factorio. Released in 2012 and famously hazardous to the productivity of software engineers everywhere, Factorio invites players to construct a factory. The ultimate goal is to launch a rocket, a feat that requires the player to produce thousands of intermediate products through dozens of complicated, interlocking manufacturing processes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It sounds like a nightmare. An early flow chart (pictured – it has grown much more complicated since) resembles the end product of a particularly thorny systems thinking project. But players complete its daunting mission successfully, without reference to such system maps, in their thousands, and all for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The genius of the game is that it lets players begin with a simple system that works. As you learn to produce one item, another is unlocked. If you get something wrong, the factory visibly grinds to a halt while you figure out a different approach. The hours tick by, and new systems – automated mining, oil refining, locomotives – are introduced and iterated upon. Before you realize it, you have built a sprawling yet functioning system that might be more sophisticated than anything you have worked on in your entire professional career.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How to build systems that work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Government systems, however, are already established, complicated, and relied upon by millions of people every day. We cannot simply switch off the health system and ask everyone to wait a few years while we build something better. The good news is that the existence of an old, clunky system does not stop us from starting something new and simple in parallel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the 1950s, the US was in a desperate race against a technologically resurgent Soviet Union. The USSR took the lead in developing advanced rockets of the type that launched Sputnik into orbit and risked launching a nuclear device into Washington, DC. In 1954, the Eisenhower administration tasked General Bernard Schriever with helping the US develop its own Intercontinental Ballistic Missile (ICBM). An experienced airman and administrator, the top brass felt that Schriever’s Stanford engineering master’s degree would make him a suitable go-between for the soldiers and scientists on this incredibly technical project (its scope was larger even than the Manhattan Project, costing over $100 billion in 2025 dollars versus the latter’s $39 billion).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The organizational setup Schriever inherited was not fit for the task. With many layers of approvals and subcommittees within subcommittees, it was a classic example of a complex yet dysfunctional system. The technological challenges posed by the ICBM were extreme: everything from rocket engines to targeting systems to the integration with nuclear warheads had to be figured out more or less from scratch. This left no room for bureaucratic delay.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Schriever produced what many systems thinkers would recognize as a kind of systems map: a series of massive boards setting out all the different committees and governance structures and approvals and red tape. But the point of these ‘spaghetti charts’ was not to make a targeted, systems thinking intervention. Schriever didn’t pretend to be able to navigate and manipulate all this complexity. He instead recognized his own limits. With the Cold War in the balance, he could not afford to play and lose his equivalent of the Beer Game. Charts in hand, Schriever persuaded his boss that untangling the spaghetti was a losing battle: they needed to start over.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They could not change the wider laws, regulations, and institutional landscape governing national defense. But they could work around them, starting afresh with a simple system outside the existing bureaucracy. Direct vertical accountability all the way to the President and a free hand on personnel enabled the program to flourish. Over the following years, four immensely ambitious systems were built in record time. The uneasy strategic stalemate that passed for stability during the Cold War was restored, and the weapons were never used in anger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we look in more detail at recent public policy successes, we see that this pattern tends to hold. Operation Warp Speed in the US played a big role in getting vaccines delivered quickly. It did so by bypassing many of the usual bottlenecks. For instance, it made heavy use of ‘Other Transaction Authority agreements’ to commit $12.5 billion of federal money by March 2021, circumventing the thousands of pages of standard procurement rules. Emergency powers were deployed to accelerate the FDA review process, enabling clinical trial work and early manufacturing scale-up to happen in parallel. These actions were funded through an $18 billion commitment made largely outside the typical congressional appropriation oversight channels – enough money to back not just one vaccine candidate but six, across three different technology platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In France, the rapid reconstruction of Notre-Dame after the April 2019 fire has become a symbol of French national pride and its ability to get things done despite a reputation for moribund bureaucracy. This was achieved not through wholesale reform of that bureaucracy but by quickly setting up a fresh structure outside of it. In July 2019, the French Parliament passed Loi n° 2019-803, creating an extraordinary legal framework for the project. Construction permits and zoning changes were fast-tracked. President Macron personally appointed the veteran General Jean-Louis Georgelin to run the restoration, exempting him from the mandatory retirement age for public executives in order to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The long-term promise of a small working system is that over time it can supplant the old, broken one and produce results on a larger scale. This creative destruction has long been celebrated in the private sector, where aging corporate giants can be disrupted by smaller, simpler startups: we don’t have to rely on IBM to make our phones or laptops or Large Language Models. But it can work in the public sector too. Estonia, for example, introduced electronic ID in the early 2000s for signing documents and filing online tax returns. These simple applications, which nonetheless took enormous focus to implement, were popular, and ‘digital government’ was gradually expanded to new areas: voting in 2005, police in 2007, prescriptions in 2010, residency in 2014, and even e-divorce in 2024. By 2025, 99 percent of residents will have an electronic ID card, digital signatures are estimated to save two percent of GDP per year, and every state service runs online.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In desperate situations, such as a Cold War arms race or COVID-19, we avoid complex systems and find simpler workarounds. But, outside of severe crises, much time is wasted on what amounts to magical systems thinking. Government administrations around the world, whose members would happily admit their incompetence to fix a broken radio system, publish manifestos, strategies, plans, and priorities premised on disentangling systems problems that are orders of magnitude more challenging. With each ‘fix’, oversight bodies, administrative apparatus, and overlapping statutory obligations accumulate. Complexity is continuing to rise, outcomes are becoming worse, and voters’ goodwill is being eroded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We will soon be in an era where humans are not the sole authors of complex systems. Sundar Pichai estimated in late 2024 that over 25 percent of Google’s code was AI generated; as of mid-2025, the figure for Anthropic is 80–90 percent. As in the years after the Second World War, the temptation will be to use this vast increase in computational power and intelligence to ‘solve’ systems design for once and for all. But the same laws that limited Forrester continue to bind: ‘NEW SYSTEMS CREATE NEW PROBLEMS’ and ‘THE SYSTEM ALWAYS KICKS BACK’. As systems become more complex, they become more chaotic, not less. The best solution remains humility, and a simple system that works.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45233266</guid></item><item><title>RIP pthread_cancel</title><link>https://eissing.org/icing/posts/rip_pthread_cancel/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="262621567e35bc58"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;RIP pthread_cancel&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I posted about adding pthread_cancel use in curl about three weeks ago, we released this in curl 8.16.0 and it blew up right in our faces. Now, with #18540 we are ripping it out again. What happened?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;short recap&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pthreads define “Cancelation points”, a list of POSIX functions where a pthread may be cancelled. In addition, there is also a list of functions that may be cancelation points, among those &lt;code&gt;getaddrinfo()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;getaddrinfo()&lt;/code&gt; is exactly what we are interested in for &lt;code&gt;libcurl&lt;/code&gt;. It blocks
until it has resolved a name. That may hang for a long time and &lt;code&gt;libcurl&lt;/code&gt;
is unable to do anything else. Meh. So, we start a pthread and let that
call &lt;code&gt;getaddrinfo()&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;libcurl&lt;/code&gt; can do other things while that thread runs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But eventually, we have to get rid of the pthread again. Which means we either have to &lt;code&gt;pthread_join()&lt;/code&gt; it - which means a blocking wait. Or we
call &lt;code&gt;pthread_detach()&lt;/code&gt; - which returns immediately but the thread keeps
on running. Both are bad when you want to do many, many transfers. Either we block and
stall or we let pthreads pile up in an uncontrolled way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, we added &lt;code&gt;pthread_cancel()&lt;/code&gt; to interrupt a running &lt;code&gt;getaddrinfo()&lt;/code&gt;
and get rid of the pthread we no longer needed. So the theory. And, after
some hair pulling, we got this working.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;cancel yes, leakage also yes!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After releasing curl 8.16.0 we got an issue reported in #18532 that cancelled pthreads leaked memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Digging into the glibc source shows that there is this thing called &lt;code&gt;/etc/gai.conf&lt;/code&gt;
which defines how &lt;code&gt;getaddrinfo()&lt;/code&gt; should sort returned answers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The implementation in glibc first resolves the name to addresses. For these, it needs to allocate memory. Then it needs to sort them if there is more than one address. And in order to do that it needs to read &lt;code&gt;/etc/gai.conf&lt;/code&gt;. And in order to do that
it calls &lt;code&gt;fopen()&lt;/code&gt; on the file. And that may be a pthread “Cancelation Point”
(and if not, it surely calls &lt;code&gt;open()&lt;/code&gt; which is a required cancelation point).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, the pthread may get cancelled when reading &lt;code&gt;/etc/gai.conf&lt;/code&gt; and leak all
the allocated responses. And if it gets cancelled there, it will try to
read &lt;code&gt;/etc/gai.conf&lt;/code&gt; again the next time it has more than one address
resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, I decided that we need to give up on the whole &lt;code&gt;pthread_cancel()&lt;/code&gt;
strategy. The reading of &lt;code&gt;/etc/gai.conf&lt;/code&gt; is one point where a cancelled
&lt;code&gt;getaddrinfo()&lt;/code&gt; may leak. There might be others. Clearly, glibc is not really
designed to prevent leaks here (admittedly, this is not trivial).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;RIP&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Leaking memory potentially on something &lt;code&gt;libcurl&lt;/code&gt; does over and over again is
not acceptable. We’d rather pay the price of having to eventually wait on
a long running &lt;code&gt;getaddrinfo()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Applications using &lt;code&gt;libcurl&lt;/code&gt; can avoid this by using &lt;code&gt;c-ares&lt;/code&gt; which resolves
unblocking and without the use of threads. But that will not be able to do
everything that glibc does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DNS continues to be tricky to use well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45233713</guid></item><item><title>The Case Against Social Media Is Stronger Than You Think</title><link>https://arachnemag.substack.com/p/the-case-against-social-media-is</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45234323</guid></item><item><title>Safe C++ proposal is not being continued</title><link>https://sibellavia.lol/posts/2025/09/safe-c-proposal-is-not-being-continued/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d662bd2f20e73a5c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Safe C++ proposal is not being continued&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One year ago, the Safe C++ proposal was made. The goal was to add a safe subset/context into C++ that would give strong guarantees (memory safety, type safety, thread safety) similar to what Rust provides, without breaking existing C++ code. It was an extension or superset of C++. The opt-in mechanism was to explicitly mark parts of the code that belong to the safe context. The authors even state:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Code in the safe context exhibits the same strong safety guarantees as code written in Rust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The rest remains “unsafe” in the usual C++ sense. This means that existing code continues to work, while new or refactored parts can gain safety. For those who write Rust, Safe C++ has many similarities with Rust, sometimes with adjustments to fit C++’s design. Also, because C++ already has a huge base of “unsafe code”, Safe C++ has to provide mechanisms for mixing safe and unsafe, and for incremental migration. In that sense, all of Safe C++’s safe features are opt-in. Existing code compiles and works as before. Introducing safe context doesn’t break code that doesn’t use it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proposal caught my interest. It seemed like a good compromise to make C++ safe, although there were open or unresolved issues, which is completely normal for a draft proposal. For example, how error reporting for the borrow checker and lifetime errors would work, or how generic code and templates would interact with lifetime logic and safe/unsafe qualifiers. These are just some of the points, the proposal is very long and elaborate. Moreover, I am not a programming language designer, so there might be better alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway, today I discovered that the proposal will no longer be pursued. When I thought about the proposal again this morning, I realized I hadn’t read any updates on it for some time. So I searched and found some answers on Reddit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The response from Sean Baxter, one of the original authors of the Safe C++ proposal:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Safety and Security working group voted to prioririze Profiles over Safe C++. Ask the Profiles people for an update. Safe C++ is not being continued.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And again:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Rust safety model is unpopular with the committee. Further work on my end won’t change that. Profiles won the argument. All effort should go into getting Profile’s language for eliminating use-after-free bugs, data races, deadlocks and resource leaks into the Standard, so that developers can benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I went to read the documents related to Profiles[1][2][3][4]. I try to summarize what I understood: they are meant to define modes of C++ that impose constraints on how you use the language and library, in order to guarantee certain safety properties. They are primarily compile-time constraints, though in practice some checks may be implemented using library facilities that add limited runtime overhead. Instead of introducing entirely new language constructs, profiles mostly restrict existing features and usages. The idea is that you can enable a profile, and any code using it agrees to follow the restrictions. If you don’t enable it, things work as before. So it’s backwards-compatible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Profiles seem less radical and more adoptable, a safer-by-default C++ without forcing the Rust model that aims to tackle the most common C++ pitfalls. I think Safe C++ was more ambitious: introducing new syntax, type qualifiers, safe vs unsafe contexts, etc. Some in the committee felt that was too heavy, and Profiles are seen as a more pragmatic path. The main objection is obvious: one could say that Profiles restrict less than what Safe C++ aimed to provide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading comments here and there, there is visible resistance in the community toward adopting the Rust model, and from a certain point of view, I understand it. If you want to write like Rust, just write Rust. Historically, C++ is a language that has often taken features from other worlds and integrated them into itself. In this case, I think that safety subsets of C++ already exist informally somehow. Profiles are an attempt to standardize and unify something that already exists in practice. Technically, they don’t add new fundamental semantics. Instead, they provide constraints, obligations and guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my opinion, considering the preferences of the committee and the entire C++ community, although I appreciated the Safe C++ proposal and was looking forward to seeing concrete results, considering the C++ context I believe that standardizing and integrating the Profiles as proposed is a much more realistic approach. Profiles might not be perfect, but they are better than nothing. They will likely be uneven in enforcement and weaker than Safe C++ in principle. They won’t give us silver-bullet guarantees, but they are a realistic path forward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[1] Core safety profiles for C++26&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45234460</guid></item><item><title>An open-source maintainer's guide to saying “no”</title><link>https://www.jlowin.dev/blog/oss-maintainers-guide-to-saying-no</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="87c51250cd2f06fd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the hardest parts of maintaining an open-source project is saying ânoâ to a good idea. A user proposes a new feature. Itâs well-designed, useful, and has no obvious technical flaws. And yet, the answer is âno.â To the user, this can be baffling. To the maintainer, itâs a necessary act of stewardship.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having created and maintained two highly successful open-source projects, Prefect and FastMCP, helped establish a third in Apache Airflow, and cut my OSS teeth contributing to Theano, Iâve learned that this stewardship is the real work. The ultimate success of a project isnât measured by the number of features it has, but by the coherence of its vision and whether it finds resonance with its users. As Prefectâs CTO Chris White likes to point out:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;âPeople choose software when its abstractions agree with their mental model.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your job as an open-source maintainer is to first establish that mental model, then relentlessly build software that reflects it. A feature that is nominally useful but not spiritually aligned can be a threat just as much as an enhancement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This threat can take many forms. The most obvious is a feature thatâs wildly out of scope, like a request to add a GUI to a CLI tool â a valid idea that likely belongs in a separate project. More delicate is the feature that brilliantly solves one userâs niche problem but adds complexity and maintenance burden for everyone else. The most subtle, and perhaps most corrosive, is the API thatâs simply âspelledâ wrong for the project: the one that breaks established patterns and creates cognitive dissonance for future users. In many of the projects Iâve been fortunate to work on, both open- and closed-source, we obsess over this because a consistent developer experience is the foundation of a framework that feels intuitive and trustworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So how does a maintainer defend this soul, especially as a project scales? It starts with documenting not just how the project works, but why. Clear developer guides and statements of purpose are your first line of defense. They articulate the projectâs philosophy, setting expectations before a single line of code is written. This creates a powerful flywheel: the clearer a project is about why it exists, the more it attracts contributors who share that vision. Their contributions reinforce and refine that vision, which in turn justifies the projectâs worldview. Process then becomes a tool for alignment, not bureaucracy. As a maintainer, you can play defense on the repo, confident that the burden of proof is on the pull request to demonstrate not just its own value, but its alignment with a well-understood philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work has gotten exponentially harder in the age of LLMs. Historically, we could assume that since writing code is an expensive, high-effort activity, contributors would engage in discussion before doing the work, or at least seek some sign that time would not be wasted. Today, LLMs have inverted this. Code is now cheap, and we see it offered in lieu of discourse. A user shows up with a fully formed PR for a feature weâve never discussed. Itâs well-written, it âworks,â but it was generated without any context for the frameworkâs philosophy. Its objective function was to satisfy a userâs request, not to uphold the projectâs vision.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isnât to say all unsolicited contributions are unwelcome. There is nothing more delightful than the drive-by PR that lands, fully formed and perfectly aligned, fixing a bug or adding a small, thoughtful feature. We canât discourage these contributors. But in the last year, the balance of presumption has shifted. The signal-to-noise ratio has degraded, and the unsolicited PR is now more likely to be a high-effort review of a low-effort contribution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So whatâs the playbook? In FastMCP, we recently tried to nudge this behavior by requiring an issue for every PR. In a perfect example of unintended consequences, we now get single-sentence issues opened a second before the PRâ¦ which is actually worse. More powerful than this procedural requirement is sharing a simple sentence that we are unconvinced that the framework should take on certain responsibilities for users. If a contributor wants to convince us, we all only benefit from that effort! But as I wrote earlier, the burden of proof is on the contributor, never the repo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A more nuanced pushback against viable code is that as a maintainer, you may be uncomfortable or unwilling to maintain it indefinitely. I think this is often forgotten in fast-moving open-source projects: there is a significant transfer of responsibility when a PR is merged. If it introduces bugs, confusion, inconsistencies, or even invites further enhancements, it is usually the maintainer who is suddenly on the hook for it. In FastMCP, weâve introduced and documented the &lt;code&gt;contrib&lt;/code&gt; module as one solution to this problem. This module contains useful functionality that may nonetheless not be appropriate for the core project, and is maintained exclusively by its author. No guarantee is made that it works with future versions of the project. In practice, many contrib modules might have better lives as standalone projects, but itâs a way to get the ball rolling in a more communal fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One regret I have is that I observe a shift in my own behavior. In the early days of Prefect, we did our best to maintain a 15-minute SLA on our responses. Seven years ago, a user question reflected an amazing degree of engagement, and we wanted to respond in kind. Today, if I donât see a basic attempt to engage, I find myself mirroring that low-effort behavior. Frankly, if Iâm faced with a choice between a wall of LLM-generated text or a clear, direct question with an MRE, Iâll take the latter every time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know this describes a fundamentally artisanal, hand-made approach to open source that may seem strange in an age of vibe coding and YOLO commits. Iâm no stranger to LLMs. Quite the opposite. I use them constantly in my own work and we even have an AI agent (hi Marvin!) that helps triage the FastMCP repo. But in my career, this thoughtful, deliberate stewardship has been the difference between utility projects and great ones. We used to call it âcommunityâ and Iâd like to ensure it doesnât disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think I need to be clear that nothing in this post should be construed as an invitation to be rude or to stonewall users. As an open-source maintainer, you should be ecstatic every time someone engages with your project. After all, if you didnât want those interactions, you could have kept your code to yourself! The goal in scalable open-source must always be to create a positive, compounding community, subject to whatever invitation you choose to extend to your users. Your responsibility is to ensure that todayâs ânoâ helps guide a contributor toward tomorrowâs enthusiastic âyes!â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When this degree of thoughtfulness is well applied, it translates into a better experience for all usersâinto software whose abstractions comply with a universal mental model. Itâs a reminder that this kind of stewardship is worth fighting for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I was in a room that reminded me this fight is being won at the highest level. I had the opportunity to join the MCP Committee for meetings in New York and saw a group skillfully navigating a version of this very problem. MCP is a young protocol, and its place in the AI stack has been accelerated more by excitement than its own maturity. As a result, it is under constant assault that it should simultaneously do more, do less, and everything in between.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A weak or rubber-stamp committee would be absolutely overwhelmed by this pressure, green-lighting any plausible feature to appease the loudest voices in this most-hyped corner of tech. And yet, over a couple of days, what I witnessed was the opposite. The most important thing I saw was a willingness to debate, and to hold every proposal up to a (usually) shared opinion of what the protocol is supposed to be. There was an overriding reverence for MCPâs teleological purpose: what it should do and, more critically, what it should not do. I especially admired Davidâs consistent drumbeat as he led the committee: âThatâs a good idea. But is it part of the protocolâs responsibilities?â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sticking to your guns like that is the hard, necessary work of maturing a technology with philosophical rigor. I left New York more confident than ever in the team and MCP itself, precisely because of how everyone worked not only to build the protocol, but to act as its thoughtful custodians. It was wonderful to see that stewardship up close, and I look forward to seeing it continue in open-source more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Subscribe&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Comments&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reply to this post on Bluesky to join the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No comments yet...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ð¦ð¦ð¦&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45234593</guid></item><item><title>Heart attacks may be triggered by bacteria</title><link>https://www.tuni.fi/en/news/myocardial-infarction-may-be-infectious-disease</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6ecc39dea85fc3ca"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Myocardial infarction may be an infectious disease&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to the recently published research, an infection may trigger myocardial infarction. Using a range of advanced methodologies, the research found that, in coronary artery disease, atherosclerotic plaques containing cholesterol may harbour a gelatinous, asymptomatic biofilm formed by bacteria over years or even decades. Dormant bacteria within the biofilm remain shielded from both the patient’s immune system and antibiotics because they cannot penetrate the biofilm matrix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A viral infection or another external trigger may activate the biofilm, leading to the proliferation of bacteria and an inflammatory response. The inflammation can cause a rupture in the fibrous cap of the plaque, resulting in thrombus formation and ultimately myocardial infarction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professor Pekka Karhunen, who led the study, notes that until now, it was assumed that events leading to coronary artery disease were only initiated by oxidised low-density lipoprotein (LDL), which the body recognises as a foreign structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Bacterial involvement in coronary artery disease has long been suspected, but direct and convincing evidence has been lacking. Our study demonstrated the presence of genetic material – DNA – from several oral bacteria inside atherosclerotic plaques,” Karhunen explains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The findings were validated by developing an antibody targeted at the discovered bacteria, which unexpectedly revealed biofilm structures in arterial tissue. Bacteria released from the biofilm were observed in cases of myocardial infarction. The body’s immune system had responded to these bacteria, triggering inflammation which ruptured the cholesterol-laden plaque.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The observations pave the way for the development of novel diagnostic and therapeutic strategies for myocardial infarction. Furthermore, they advance the possibility of preventing coronary artery disease and myocardial infarction by vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study was conducted by Tampere and Oulu Universities, Finnish Institute for Health and Welfare and the University of Oxford. Tissue samples were obtained from individuals who had died from sudden cardiac death, as well as from patients with atherosclerosis who were undergoing surgery to cleanse carotid and peripheral arteries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The research is part of an extensive EU-funded cardiovascular research project involving 11 countries. Significant funding was also provided by the Finnish Foundation for Cardiovascular Research and Jane and Aatos Erkko Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The research article Viridans Streptococcal Biofilm Evades Immune Detection and Contributes to Inflammation and Rupture of Atherosclerotic Plaques was published in the Journal of the American Heart Association on 6 August 2025. Read the article online&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Further information&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professor Pekka Karhunen&lt;lb/&gt;Faculty of Medicine and Health Technology&lt;lb/&gt;Tampere University&lt;lb/&gt;pekka.j.karhunen [at] tuni.fi (pekka[dot]j[dot]karhunen[at]tuni[dot]fi)&lt;lb/&gt;Tel. +358 400 511361&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45235648</guid></item><item><title>AI Will Not Make You Rich</title><link>https://joincolossus.com/article/ai-will-not-make-you-rich/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bb051051dfb505ec"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortunes are made by entrepreneurs and investors when revolutionary technologies enable waves of innovative, investable companies. Think of the railroad, the Bessemer process, electric power, the internal combustion engine, or the microprocessor—each of which, like a stray spark in a fireworks factory, set off decades of follow-on innovations, permeated every part of society, and catapulted a new set of inventors and investors into power, influence, and wealth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet some technological innovations, though societally transformative, generate little in the way of new wealth; instead, they reinforce the status quo. Fifteen years before the microprocessor, another revolutionary idea, shipping containerization, arrived at a less propitious time, when technological advancement was a Red Queen’s race, and inventors and investors were left no better off for non-stop running.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyone who invests in the new new thing must answer two questions: First, how much value will this innovation create? And second, who will capture it? Information and communication technology (ICT) was a revolution whose value was captured by startups and led to thousands of newly rich founders, employees, and investors. In contrast, shipping containerization was a revolution whose value was spread so thin that in the end, it made only a single founder temporarily rich and only a single investor a little bit richer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is generative AI more like the former or the latter? Will it be the basis of many future industrial fortunes, or a net loser for the investment community as a whole, with a few zero-sum winners here and there?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are ways to make money investing in the fruits of AI, but they will depend on assuming the latter—that it is once again a less propitious time for inventors and investors, that AI model builders and application companies will eventually compete each other into an oligopoly, and that the gains from AI will accrue not to its builders but to customers. A lot of the money pouring into AI is therefore being invested in the wrong places, and aside from a couple of lucky early investors, those who make money will be the ones with the foresight to get out early.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The microprocessor was revolutionary, but the people who invented it at Intel in 1971 did not see it that way—they just wanted to avoid designing desktop calculator chipsets from scratch every time. But outsiders realized they could use the microprocessor to build their own personal computers, and enthusiasts did. Thousands of tinkerers found configurations and uses that Intel never dreamed of. This distributed and permissionless invention kicked off a “great surge of development,” as the economist Carlota Perez calls it, triggered by technology but driven by economic and societal forces.[1]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There was no real demand for personal computers in the early 1970s; they were expensive toys. But the experimenters laid the technical groundwork and built a community. Then, around 1975, a step-change in the cost of microprocessors made the personal computer market viable. The Intel 8080 had an initial list price of $360 ($2,300 in today’s dollars). MITS could barely turn a profit on its Altair at a bulk price of $75 each ($490 today). But when MOS Technologies started selling its 6502 for $25 ($150 today), Steve Wozniak could afford to build a prototype Apple. The 6502 and the similarly priced Zilog Z80 forced Intel’s prices down. The nascent PC community started spawning entrepreneurs and a score of companies appeared, each with a slightly different product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You couldn’t have known in the mid-1970s that the PC (and PC-like products, such as ATMs, POS terminals, smartphones, etc.) would revolutionize everything. While Steve Jobs was telling investors that every household would someday have a personal computer (a wild underestimate, as it turned out), others questioned the need for personal computers at all. As late as 1979, Apple’s ads didn’t tell you what a personal computer could do—it asked what you did with it.[2] The established computer manufacturers (IBM, HP, DEC) had no interest in a product their customers weren’t asking for. Nobody “needed” a computer, and so PCs weren’t bought—they were sold. Flashy startups like Apple and Sinclair used hype to get noticed, while companies with footholds in consumer electronics like Atari, Commodore, and Tandy/RadioShack used strong retail connections to put their PCs in front of potential customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The market grew slowly at first, accelerating only as experiments led to practical applications like the spreadsheet, introduced in 1979. As use grew, observation of use caused a reduction in uncertainty, leading to more adoption in a self-reinforcing cycle. This kind of gathering momentum takes time in every technological wave: It took almost 30 years for electricity to reach half of American households, for example, and it took about the same amount of time for personal computers.[3] When a technological revolution changes everything, it takes a huge amount of innovation, investment, storytelling, time, and plain old work. It also sucks up all the money and talent available. Like Kuhn’s paradigms in science, any technology not part of the wave’s techno-economic paradigm will seem like a sideshow.[4]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source: [3]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The nascent growth of PCs attracted investors—venture capitalists—who started making risky bets on new companies. This development incentivized more inventors, entrepreneurs, and researchers, which in turn drew in more speculative capital.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Companies like IBM, the computing behemoth before the PC, saw poor relative performance. They didn’t believe the PC could survive long enough to become capable in their market and didn’t care about new, small markets that wanted a cheaper solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Retroactively, we give the PC pioneers the powers of prophets rather than visionaries. But at the time, nobody outside of a small group of early adopters paid any attention. Establishment media like The New York Times didn’t take the PC seriously until after IBM’s was introduced in August 1981. In the entire year of 1976, when Apple Computer was founded, the NYT mentioned PCs only four times.[5] Apparently, only the crazy ones, the misfits, the rebels, and the troublemakers were paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source: [5]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s the element of surprise that should strike us most forcefully when we compare the early days of the computer revolution to today. No one took note of personal computers in the 1970s. In 2025, AI is all we seem to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Big companies hate surprises. That’s why uncertainty makes a perfect moat for startups. Apple would never have survived IBM entering the market in 1979, and only lived to compete another day after raising $100 million in its 1980 IPO. It was the only remaining competitor after the IBM-induced winnowing.[6]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source: [6]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the tech took hold and started to show promise, innovations in software, memory, and peripherals like floppy disk drives and modems joined it. They reinforced one another, with each advance putting pressure on the technologies adjacent to it. When any part of the system held back the other parts, investors rushed to fund that sector. As increases in PC memory allowed more complicated software, for example, there became a need for more external storage, which caused VC Dave Marquardt to invest in disk drive manufacturer Seagate in 1980. Seagate gave Marquardt a 40x return when it went public in 1981. Other investors noticed, and some $270 million was plowed into the industry in the following three years.[7]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Money also poured into the underlying infrastructure—fiber optic networks, chip making, etc.—so that capacity was never a bottleneck. Companies which used the new technological system to outperform incumbents began to take market share, and even staid competitors realized they needed to adopt the new thing or die. The hype became a froth which became an investment bubble: the dot-com frenzy of the late 1990s. The ICT wave was therefore similar to previous ones—like the investment mania of the 1830s and the Roaring ‘20s, which followed the infrastructure buildout of canals and railways, respectively—in which the human response to each stage predictably generated the next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the dot-com bubble popped, society found it disapproved of the excesses in the sector and governments found they had the popular support to reassert authority over the tech companies and their investors. This put a brake on the madness. Instead of the reckless innovation of the bubble, companies started to expand into proven markets, and financiers moved from speculating to investing. Entrepreneurs began to focus on finding applications rather than on innovating the underlying technologies. Technological improvements continued, but change became more evolutionary than revolutionary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As change slowed, companies gained the confidence to invest for the longer term. They began to combine various parts of the system in new ways to create value for a wider group of users. The massive overbuilding of fiber optic telecom networks and other infrastructure during the frenzy left plenty of cheap capacity, keeping the costs of expansion down. It was a great time to be a businessperson and investor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In contrast, society did not need a bubble to pop to start excoriating AI. Given that the backlash to tech has been going on for a decade, this seems normal to us. But the AI backlash differs from the general high regard, earlier in the cycle, enjoyed by the likes of Bill Gates, Steve Jobs, Jeff Bezos, and others who built big tech businesses. The world hates change, and only gave tech a pass in the ‘80s and ‘90s because it all still seemed reversible: it could be made to go away if it turned out badly. This gave the early computer innovators some leeway to experiment. Now that everyone knows computers are here to stay, AI is not allowed the same wait-and-see attitude. It is seen as part of the ICT revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perez, the economist, breaks each technological wave into four predictable phases: irruption, frenzy, synergy, and maturity. Each has a characteristic investment profile.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The middle two, frenzy and synergy, are the easy ones for investors. Frenzy is when everyone piles in and investors are rewarded for taking big risks on unproven ideas, culminating in the bubble, when paper profits disappear. When rationality returns, the synergy phase begins, as companies make their products usable and productive for a wide array of users. Synergy pays those who are patient, picky, and can bring more than just money to the table.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Irruption and maturity are more difficult to invest in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Investing in the 1970s was harder than it might look in hindsight. To invest from 1971 through 1975, you had to be either a true believer or a conglomerator with a knuckle-headed diversification strategy. Intel was a great investment, though it looked at first like a previous-wave electronics company. MOS Technologies was founded in 1969 to compete with Texas Instruments but sold a majority of itself to Allen-Bradley to stay afloat. Zilog was funded in 1975 by Exxon (Exxon!). Apple was a great investment, but it had none of the hallmarks of what VCs look for, as the PC was still a solution in search of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was later irruption, in the early 1980s, when great opportunities proliferated: PC makers (Compaq, Dell), software and operating systems (Microsoft, Electronic Arts, Adobe), peripherals (Seagate), workstations (Sun), and computer stores (Businessland), among others. If you invested in the winners, you did well. But there was still more money than ideas, which meant that it was no golden age for investing. By 1983, there were more than 70 companies competing in the disk drive sector alone, and valuations collapsed. There were plenty of people whose fortunes were established in the 1970s and 1980s, and many VCs made their names in that era. But the biggest advantage to being an irruption-stage investor was building institutional knowledge to invest early and well in the frenzy and synergy phases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Investing in the maturity phase is even more difficult. In irruption, it’s hard to see what will happen; in maturity, nothing much happens at all. The uncertainty about what will work and how customers and society will react is almost gone. Things are predictable, and everyone acts predictably.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lack of dynamism allows the successful synergy companies to remain entrenched (see: the Nifty 50 and FAANG), but growth becomes harder. They start to enter each other’s markets, conglomerate, raise prices, and cut costs. The era of products priced to entice new customers ends, and quality suffers. The big companies continue to embrace the idea of revolutionary innovation, but feel the need to control how their advances are used. R&amp;amp;D spending is redirected from product and process innovation toward increasingly fruitless attempts to find ways to extend the current paradigm. Companies frame this as a drive to win, but it’s really a fear of losing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Innovation can happen during maturity, sometimes spectacularly. But because these innovations only find support if they fit into the current wave’s paradigm, they are easily captured in the dominant companies’ gravity wells. This means making money as an entrepreneur or investor in them is almost impossible. Generative AI is clearly being captured by the dominant ICT companies, which raises the question of whether this time will be different for inventors and investors—a different question from whether AI itself is a revolutionary technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shipping containerization was a late-wave innovation that changed the world, kicked off our modern era of globalization, resulted in profound changes to society and the economy, and contributed to rapid growth in well-being. But there were, perhaps, only one or two people who made real money investing in it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The year 1956 was late in the previous wave. But that year, the company soon to be known as SeaLand revolutionized freight shipping with the launch of the first containership, the Ideal-X. SeaLand’s founder, Malcom McLean, had an epiphany that the job to be done by truckers, railroads, and shipping lines was to move goods from shipper to destination, not to drive trucks, fill boxcars, or lade boats. SeaLand allowed freight to transfer seamlessly from one mode to another, saving time, making shipping more predictable, and cutting costs—both the costs of loading, unloading, and reloading, and the cost of a ship sitting idly in port as it was loaded and unloaded.[8]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The benefits of containerization, if it could be made to happen, were obvious. Everybody could see the efficiencies, and customers don’t care how something gets to where they can buy it, as long as it does. But longshoremen would lose work, politicians would lose the votes of those who lost work, port authorities would lose the support of the politicians, federal regulators would be blamed for adverse consequences, railroads might lose freight to shipping lines, shipping lines might lose freight to new shipping lines, and it would all cost a mint. Most thought McLean would never be able to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;McLean squeezed through the cracks of the opposition he faced. He bought and retrofitted war surplus ships, lowering costs. He went after the coastal shipping trade, a dying business in the age of the new interstates, to avoid competition. He set up shop in Newark, NJ, rather than the shipping hub of Hell’s Kitchen, to get buy-in from the port authority and avoid Manhattan congestion. And he made a deal with the New York longshoremen’s union, which was only possible because he was a small player whom they figured was not a threat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source: [10]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But competitors and regulators moved too quickly for McLean to seize the few barriers to entry that might have been available to him: domination of the ports, exclusive agreements with shippers or other forms of transportation, standardization on proprietary technology, etc.[9] When it started to look like it might work, around 1965, the obvious advantages of containerization meant that every large shipping line entered the business, and competition took off. Even though containerized freight was less than 1% of total trade by 1968, the number of containerships was already ramping fast.[10] Capacity outstripped demand for years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The increase in competition led to a rate war, which led to squeezed profits, which in turn led to consolidation and cartels. Meanwhile, the cost of building ever-larger container ships and the port facilities to deal with them meant the business became hugely capital intensive. McLean saw the writing on the wall and sold SeaLand to R.J. Reynolds in January 1969. He was, perhaps, the only entrepreneur to get out unscathed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It took a long time for the end-to-end vision to be realized. But around 1980, a dramatic drop began in the cost of sea freight.[11] This contributed to a boom in international trade[12] and allowed manufacturers to move away from higher-wage to lower-wage countries, making containerization irreversible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source: [11]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some people did make money, of course; someone always does. McLean did, as did shipping magnate Daniel Ludwig, who had invested $8.5 million in SeaLand’s predecessor, McLean Industries, at $8.50 per share in 1965 and sold in 1969 for $50 per share.[13] Shipbuilders made money, too: between 1967 and 1972, some $10 billion ($80 billion in 2025 dollars) was spent building containerships. The contractors that built the new container ports also made money. And, later, shipping lines that consolidated and dominated the business, like Maersk and Evergreen, became very large. But, “for R.J. Reynolds, and for other companies that had chased fast growth by buying into container shipping in the late 1960s, their investments brought little but disappointment.”[14] Aside from McLean and Ludwig, it is hard to find anyone who became rich from containerization itself, because competition and capex costs made it hard to grow fast or achieve high margins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source: [12]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The business ended up being dominated primarily by the previous incumbents, and the margins went to the companies shipping goods, not the ones they shipped through. Companies like IKEA benefited from cheap shipping, going from a provincial Scandinavian company in 1972 to the world’s largest furniture retailer by 2008; container shipping was a perfect fit for IKEA’s flat-pack furniture. Others, like Walmart, used the predictability enabled by containerization to lower inventory and its associated costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With hindsight, it’s easy to see how you could have invested in containerization: not in the container shipping industry itself, but in the industries that benefited from containerization. But even here, the success of companies like Walmart, Costco, and Target was coupled with the failure of others. The fallout from containerization set Sears and Woolworth on downward spirals, put the final nail in the coffin of Montgomery Ward and A&amp;amp;P, and drove Macy’s into bankruptcy before it was rescued and downsized by Federated. Meanwhile, in North Carolina, “the furniture capital of the world,” furniture makers tried to compete with IKEA by importing cheap pieces from China. They ended up being replaced by their suppliers.[15]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there had been more time to build moats, there might have been a few dominant containerization companies, and the people behind them would be at the top of the Forbes 400, while their investors would be legendary. But moats take time to build and, unlike the personal computer, the adoption of containerization wasn’t a surprise—every business with interests at stake had a strategic plan immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The economist Joseph Schumpeter said “perfect competition is and always has been temporarily suspended whenever anything new is being introduced.”[16] But containerization shows this isn’t true at the end of tech waves. And because there is no economic profit during perfect competition, there is no money to be made by innovators during maturity. Like containerization, the introduction of AI did not lead to a period of protected profits for its innovators. It led to an immediate competitive free-for-all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s grant that generative AI is revolutionary (but also that, as is becoming increasingly clear, this particular tech is now already in an evolutionary stage). It will create a lot of value for the economy, and investors hope to capture some of it. When, who, and how depends on whether AI is the end of the ICT wave, or the beginning of a new one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If AI had started a new wave, there would have been an extended period of uncertainty and experimentation. There would have been a population of early adopters experimenting with their own models. When thousands or millions of tinkerers use the tech to solve problems in entirely new ways, its uses proliferate. But because they are using models owned by the big AI companies, their ability to fully experiment is limited to what’s allowed by the incumbents, who have no desire to permit an extended challenge to the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean AI can’t start the next technological revolution. It might, if experimentation becomes cheap, distributed and permissionless—like Wozniak cobbling together computers in his garage, Ford building his first internal combustion engine in his kitchen, or Trevithick building his high-pressure steam engine as soon as James Watt’s patents expired. When any would-be innovator can build and train an LLM on their laptop and put it to use in any way their imagination dictates, it might be the seed of the next big set of changes—something revolutionary rather than evolutionary. But until and unless that happens, there can be no irruption.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI is instead the epitome of the ICT wave. The computing visionaries of the 1960s set out to build a machine that could think, which their successors eventually did, by extending gains in algorithms, chips, data, and data center infrastructure. Like containerization, AI is an extension of something that came before, and therefore no one is surprised by what it can and will do. In the 1970s, it took time for people to wrap their heads around the desirability of powerful and ubiquitous computing. But in 2025, machines that think better than previous machines are easy for people to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider the extent to which the progress of AI rhymes with the business evolution of containerization:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the “AI rhymes” column, the first four items are already underway. How you should invest depends on whether you believe Nos. 5–7 are next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Economists are predicting that AI will increase global GDP somewhere between 1%[17] to more than 7%[18] over the next decade, which is $1–7 trillion of new value created. The big question is where that money will stick as it flows through the value chain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most AI market overviews have a score or more categories, breaking each of them into customer and industry served. But these will change dramatically over the next few years. You could, instead, just follow the money to simplify the taxonomy of companies:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What the history of containerization suggests is that, if you aren’t already an investor in a model company, you shouldn’t bother. Sam Altman and a few other early movers may make a fortune, as McLean and Ludwig did. But the huge costs of building and running a model, coupled with intense competition, means there will, in the end, be only a few companies, each funded and owned by the largest tech companies. If you’re already an investor, congratulations: There will be consolidation, so you might get an exit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Domain-specific models—like Cursor or Harvey—will be part of the consolidation. These are probably the most valuable models. But fine-tuning is relatively cheap, and there are big economies of scope. On the other hand, just as Google had to buy Invite Media in 2010 to figure out how to sell to ad agencies, domain-specific model companies that have earned the trust of their customers will be prime acquisition targets. And although it seems possible that models which generate things other than language—like Midjourney or Runway—might use their somewhat different architecture to carve out a separate technological path, the LLM companies have easily entered this space as well. Whether this applies to companies like Osmo remains to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While it’s too late to invest in the model companies, the profusion of those using the models to solve specific problems is ongoing: Perplexity, InflectionAI, Writer, Abridge, and a hundred others. But if any of these become very valuable, the model companies will take their earnings, either through discriminatory pricing or vertical integration. Success, in other words, will mean defeat—always a bad thesis. At some point, model companies and app companies will converge: There will simply be AI companies, and only a few of them. There will be some winners, as always, but investments in the app layer as a whole will lose money.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The same caveat applies, however: If an app company can build a customer base or an amazing team, it might be acquired. But these companies aren’t really technology companies at all; they are building a market on spec and have to be priced as such. A further caveat is that there will be investors who make a killing arbitraging FOMO-panicked acquirors willing to massively overpay. But this is not really “investing.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There might be an investment opportunity in companies that manage the interface between the AI giants and their customers, or protect company data from the model companies—like Hugging Face or Glean—because these businesses are by nature independent of the models. But no analogue in the post-containerization shipping market became very large. Even the successful intermediation companies in the AI space will likely end up mid-sized because the model companies will not allow them to gain strategic leverage—another consequence of the absence of surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When an industry is going to be big but there is uncertainty about how it will play out, it often makes sense to swim upstream to the industry’s suppliers. In the case of AI, this means the chip providers, data companies, and cloud/data center companies: SambaNova, Scale AI, and Lambda, as well as those that have been around for a long time, like Nvidia and Bloomberg.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The case for data is mixed. General data—i.e., things most people know, including everything anyone knew more than, say, 10 years ago, and most of what was learned after that—is a commodity. There may be room for a few companies to do the grunt work of collating and tagging it, but since the collating and tagging might best be done by AI itself, there will not be a lot of pricing leverage. Domain-specific models will need specialist data, and other models will try to answer questions about the current moment. Specific, timely, and hard to reproduce data will be valuable. This is not a new market, of course—Bloomberg and others have done well by it. A more concentrated customer base will lower prices for this data, while wider use will raise revenues. On balance, this will probably be a plus for the industry, though not a huge one. There will be new companies built, but only a couple worth investing in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The high capex of AI companies will primarily be spent with the infrastructure companies. These companies are already valued with this expectation, so there won’t be an upside surprise. But consider that shipbuilding benefited from containerization from 1965 until demand collapsed after about 1973.[19] If AI companies consolidate or otherwise act in concert, even a slight downturn that forces them to conserve cash could turn into a serious, sudden, and long-lasting decline in infrastructure spending. This would leave companies like Nvidia and its emerging competitors—who must all make long-term commitments to suppliers and for capacity expansion—unable to lower costs to match the new, smaller market size. Companies priced for an s-curve are overpriced if there’s a peak and decline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source: [19]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of which means that investors shouldn’t swim upstream, but fish downstream: companies whose products rely on achieving high-quality results from somewhat ambiguous information will see increased productivity and higher profits. These sectors include professional services, healthcare, education, financial services, and creative services, which together account for between a third and a half of global GDP and have not seen much increased productivity from automation. AI can help lower costs, but as with containerization, how individual businesses incorporate lower costs into their strategies—and what they decide to do with the savings—will determine success. To put it bluntly, using cost savings to increase profits rather than grow revenue is a loser’s game.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The companies that will benefit most rapidly are those whose strategies are already conditional on lowering costs. IKEA’s longtime strategy was to sell quality furniture for low prices and make it up on volume. After containerization made it possible for them to go worldwide, IKEA became the world’s largest retailer and Ingvar Kamprad (the IK of IKEA) became a billionaire. Similarly, Walmart, whose strategy was high volume and low prices in underserved markets, benefited from both cost savings and just-in-time supply chains, allowing increased product variety and lower inventory costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today’s knowledge-work companies that already prioritize the same values are the least risky way to bet on AI, but new companies will form or re-form with a high-volume, low-cost strategy, just as Costco did in the early 1980s. New companies will compete with the incumbents, but with a clean slate and hindsight. Regardless, there are few barriers to entry, so each of these firms will face stiff competition and operate in fragmented markets. Experienced management and flawless execution will be key.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being an entrepreneur will be a fabulous proposition in these sectors. Being an investor will be harder. Companies will not need much private capital—IKEA never needed to raise risk capital, and Costco raised only one round in 1983 before going public in 1985—because implementing cost-savings technology is not capital intensive. As with containerization, there will be a long lag between technology trigger and the best investments. The opportunities will be later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stock pickers will also make money, but they need to be choosy. At the high end of projections, an additional 7% in GDP growth over ten years within one third of the economy gives a tailwind of only about 2% per year to these companies—even less if productivity growth from older ICT products abates. The primary value shift will be to companies that are embracing the strategic implications of AI from companies that are not, the way Walmart benefited from Sears, which took advantage of cheaper goods prices but did not reinvent itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consumers, however, will be the biggest beneficiaries. Previous waves of mechanization benefited labor productivity in manufacturing, driving prices down and saving consumers money. But increased labor productivity in manufacturing also led to higher manufacturing wages. Wages in services businesses had to rise to compete, even though these businesses did not benefit from productivity gains. This caused the price of services to rise.[20] The share of household spending on food and clothing went from 55% in 1918 to 16% in 2023,[21] but the cost of knowledge-intensive services like healthcare and education have grown well above inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Something similar will happen with AI: Knowledge-intensive services will get cheaper, allowing consumers to buy more of them, while services that require person-to-person interaction will get more expensive, taking up a greater percentage of household spending. This points to obvious opportunities in both. But the big news is that most of the new value created by AI will be captured by consumers, who should see a wider variety of knowledge-intensive goods at reasonable prices, and wider and more affordable access to services like medical care, education, and advice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is nothing better than the beginning of a new wave, when the opportunities to envision, invent, and build world-changing companies leads to money, fame, and glory. But there is nothing more dangerous for investors and entrepreneurs than wishful thinking. The lessons learned from investing in tech over the last 50 years are not the right ones to apply now. The way to invest in AI is to think through the implications of knowledge workers becoming more efficient, to imagine what markets this efficiency unlocks, and to invest in those. For decades, the way to make money was to bet on what the new thing was. Now, you have to bet on the opportunities it opens up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jerry Neumann is a retired venture investor, writing and teaching about innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chart: Jovanovic, B., &amp;amp; Rousseau, P., “General purpose technologies. Handbook of Economic Growth”, 1(05), p. 1194. [Online] Available: https://doi.org/10.1016/S1574-0684(05)01018-X&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Certain sectors, like medical technology and pharma, are funded regardless of the dominant tech because they are too fundamental to ever be a sideshow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source: Author search of The New York Times archives for "microcomputer", "personal computer", and "home computer", no ads, no classified ads, no table of contents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chart: data from Dediu, H., “The Next 40”, Asymco, March 2016. [Online] Available: https://www.asymco.com/2016/03/28/the-next-40/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sahlman, W.A. and H.H. Stevenson. “Capital market myopia.” Journal of Business Venturing, 1985, 7-30.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This section draws very heavily from Marc Levinson’s The Box (Princeton University Press, 2006), both essential and a great read.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The United States Maritime Administration began a process to standardize containers as early as 1958, just two years after the initial voyage of the Ideal-X.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;McKinsey, “Brave New World: Container transport in 2043” [Online] Available: https://www.mckinsey.com/~/media/mckinsey/industries/travel-logistics-and-infrastructure/our-insights/brave-new-world-container-transport-in-2043/brave-new-world-container-transport-in-2043.pdf, 2018; chart: Levinson, p. 221.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chart data: OECD Economic Outlook, Volume 2007/1 No. 81, June. [Online] Available: http://dx.doi.org/10.1787/032883306727&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chart data: Michel Fouquin &amp;amp; Jules Hugot , 2016. "Two Centuries of Bilateral Trade and Gravity Data: 1827-2014," CEPII Working Paper 2016-14 , May 2016, CEPII. https://www.cepii.fr/pdf_pub/wp/2016/wp2016-14.pdf. Processed by Our World in Data&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;McLean couldn’t resist re-entering the shipping business, buying another shipping line, USL, in 1978. He had driven USL into bankruptcy by 1986 and declared personal bankruptcy soon after.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mullin, John, The Rise and Sudden Decline of North Carolina Furniture Making, Federal Reserve Bank of Richmond, Econ Focus, Fourth Quarter 2020. [Online] Available: https://www.richmondfed.org/publications/research/econ_focus/2020/q4/economic_history&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Acemoglu, Daron, “The Simple Macroeconomics of AI”, 2024. [Online] Available: https://economics.mit.edu/sites/default/files/2024-04/The%20Simple%20Macroeconomics%20of%20AI.pdf&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Goldman Sachs, “Generative AI could raise global GDP by 7%”, April 5, 2023. [Online] Available: https://www.goldmansachs.com/insights/articles/generative-ai-could-raise-global-gdp-by-7-percent&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45235676</guid></item></channel></rss>