<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 08:15:26 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Three Years from GPT-3 to Gemini 3</title><link>https://www.oneusefulthing.org/p/three-years-from-gpt-3-to-gemini</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d53915f1bb40691"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Three Years from GPT-3 to Gemini 3&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;From chatbots to agents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been testing Google’s new Gemini 3 model. It is very good. But rather than give you benchmark numbers, I’m going to show you how far AI has come in three years by asking the AI to demonstrate it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has been slightly less than three years since the release of ChatGPT. A few days before that launch, I wrote my first post on this Substack about OpenAI’s earlier GPT-3 model. Then ChatGPT came out, and I wrote immediately afterwards that “I am usually pretty hesitant to make technology predictions, but I think that this is going to change our world much sooner than we expect, and much more drastically. Rather than automating jobs that are repetitive &amp;amp; dangerous, there is now the prospect that the first jobs that are disrupted by AI will be more analytic; creative; and involve more writing and communication.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think I got that one right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I could explain the difference between the original ChatGPT and the new AI model from Google, Gemini 3, that launched today. But I don’t have to. Instead, I gave the screenshot above to Gemini 3 with a single prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Me: “show how far AI has come since this post by doing stuff.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini: “I can definitely show you the difference. The tweet you shared is from November 2022—right on the cusp of the modern AI boom. Back then, the “wow factor” was that an AI could write a coherent paragraph or a simple poem about a silly concept like a “candy-powered FTL drive escaping otters.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To demonstrate how far we’ve come, I’m not just going to write text about it. I have built you a fully interactive, playable Candy-Powered FTL Starship Simulator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2022, AI could describe the engine. In 2025, AI can code the engine, design the interface, and let you pilot the ship yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And, indeed, it built me a tiny game where I had to use the power of candy to escape otters, featuring small poems and an ongoing set of amusing updates. If you’re reading this blog, you probably knew AI could do that. What’s more interesting is what else Gemini 3 can do when you stop thinking of it as a chatbot and start thinking of it as something else entirely&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Coding tools that aren’t just coding tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along with Gemini 3, Google has launched Antigravity. For programmers, Antigravity should be familiar territory, it is similar to Claude Code and OpenAI Codex, specialized tools that can be given access to your computer and which can autonomously write computer programs with guidance. If you aren’t a programmer, you may dismiss Antigravity and similar tools. I think that is a mistake because the ability to code isn’t just about programming, it’s about being able to do anything that happens on a computer. And that changes what these tools actually are.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 is very good at coding, and this matters to you even if you don’t think of what you do as programming. A fundamental perspective powering AI development is that everything you do on a computer is, ultimately, code, and if AI can work with code it can do anything someone with a computer can: build you dashboards, work with websites, create PowerPoint, read your files, and so on. This makes agents that can code general purpose tools. Antigravity embraces this idea, with the concept of an Inbox, a place where I can send AI agents off on assignments and where they can ping me when they need permission or help.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t communicate with these agents in code, I communicate with them in English and they use code to do the work. Because Gemini 3 is good at planning, it is capable of figuring out what to do, and also when to ask my approval. For example, I gave Antigravity access to a directory on my computer containing all of my posts for this newsletter.1 I then asked Gemini 3,0: “I would like an attractive list of predictions I have made about AI in a single site, also do a web search to see which I was right and wrong about.” It then read through all the files, executing code, until it gave me a plan which I could edit or approve. The screenshot below is the first time the AI asked me anything about the project, and its understanding of what I wanted was impressive. I made a couple of small changes and let the AI work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It then did web research, created a site, took over my browser to confirm the site worked, and presented me the results. Just as I would have with a human, I went through the results and made a few suggestions for improvement. It then packaged up the results so I could deploy them here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was not that Gemini 3.0 was capable of doing everything correctly without human intervention — agents aren’t there yet. There were no hallucinations I spotted, but there were things I corrected, though those errors were more about individual judgement calls or human-like misunderstandings of my intentions than traditional AI problems. Importantly, I felt that I was in control of the choices AI was making because the AI checked in and its work was visible. It felt much more like managing a teammate than prompting an AI through a chat interface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;PhD Level Intelligence?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Antigravity isn’t the only way Gemini 3 surprised me. The other was in how it handled work that required genuine judgment. As I have mentioned many times on this site, benchmarking AI progress is a mess. Gemini 3 takes a definitive benchmark lead on most stats, (although it may still not be able to beat the $200 GPT-5 Pro Model, but I suspect that might change when Gemini 3’s inevitable Deep Think version comes out). But you will hear one phrase repeated a lot in the AI world - that a model has “PhD level intelligence.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I decided to put that to the test. I gave Gemini 3 access to a directory of old files I had used for research into crowdfunding a decade ago. It was a mishmash of files labelled things like “project_final_seriously_this_time_done.xls” and data in out-of-date statistical formats. I told the AI to “figure out the data and the structure and the initial cleaning from the STATA files and get it ready to do a new analysis to find new things.” And it did, recovering corrupted data and figuring out the complexities of the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then I gave it a typical assignment that you would expect from a second year PhD student, doing minor original research. With no further hints I wrote: “great, now i want you to write an original paper using this data. do deep research on the field, make the paper not just about crowdfunding but about an important theoretical topic of interest in either entrepreneurship or business strategy. conduct a sophisticated analysis, write it up as if for a journal.” I gave it no suggestions beyond that and yet the AI considered the data, generated original hypotheses, tested them statistically, and gave me formatted output in the form of a document. The most fascinating part was that I did not give it any hints about what to research, it walked the tricky tightrope of figuring out what might be an interesting topic and how to execute it with the data it had - one of the hardest things to teach. After a couple of vague commands (“build it out more, make it better”) I got a 14 page paper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aside from this, I was impressed that the AI came up with its own measure, a way of measuring how unique a crowdfunding idea was by using natural language processing tools to compare its description mathematically to other descriptions. It wrote the code, executed it and checked the results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So is this a PhD-level intelligence? In some ways, yes, if you define a PhD level intelligence as doing the work of a competent grad student at a research university. But it also had some of the weaknesses of a grad student. The idea was good, as were many elements of the execution, but there were also problems: some of its statistical methods needed more work, some of its approaches were not optimal, some of its theorizing went too far given the evidence, and so on. Again, we have moved past hallucinations and errors to more subtle, and often human-like, concerns. Interestingly, when I gave it suggestions with a lot of leeway, the way I would a student: (“make sure that you cover the crowdfunding research more to establish methodology, etc.”) it improved tremendously, so maybe more guidance would be all that Gemini needed. We are not there yet, but “PhD intelligence” no longer seems that far away.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Gemini 3&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3 is a very good thinking and doing partner that is available to billions of people around the world. It is also a sign of many things: the fact that we have not yet seen a significant slowdown in AI’s continued development, the rise of agentic models, the need to figure out better ways to manage smart AIs, and more. It shows how far AI has come.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three years ago, we were impressed that a machine could write a poem about otters. Less than 1,000 days later, I am debating statistical methodology with an agent that built its own research environment. The era of the chatbot is turning into the era of the digital coworker. To be very clear, Gemini 3 isn’t perfect, and it still needs a manager who can guide and check it. But it suggests that “human in the loop” is evolving from “human who fixes AI mistakes” to “human who directs AI work.” And that may be the biggest change since the release of ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Obligatory warning: Giving an AI agent access to your computer can be risky if you don’t know what you are doing. They can move or delete files without asking you and can potentially present a security risk as well by exposing your documents to others. I suspect many of these problems will be addressed as these tools are adapted to non-coders, but, for now, be very careful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46019898</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 01:25:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What OpenAI did when ChatGPT users lost touch with reality</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/23/technology/openai-chatgpt-users-risks.html</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46030799</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 05:58:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Build a Compiler in Five Projects</title><link>https://kmicinski.com/functional-programming/2025/11/23/build-a-language/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="4d007891504bb690"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Build a Compiler in Five Projects&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Class website here: https://kmicinski.com/cis531-f25&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are you interested in building a compiler? Learning how functional languages are implemented? Gaining a bit of practical experience with x86-64 assembly language? If so, I invite you to try your hand at the projects in my class, CIS531. CIS531 is a masters-level class on compiler design which assumes that (a) you know how to program, (b) you’ve had some exposure to C (know about stack allocation, malloc, etc.), and (c) have seen some assembly code. My class projects are in the Racket programming language, but if you don’t know Racket, it is quite easy to learn: I have a set of YouTube video lectures that teach Racket quickly! If you’ve never heard of Racket before, or you’re skeptical of functional programming, indulge me for a bit: there’s no hardcore FP theory or math in this course, and Racket is genuinely the best language to use for this specific setup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My class follows Prof. Jeremy Siek’s excellent book, “Essentials of Compilation.” While I highly recommend buying the book and supporting Prof. Siek, I will also note that there are free online preliminary editions floating around; in my class, I followed the free version and suggested that students buy the book if doing so fit their goals. However, along with the book, I also have a set of class slides along with sporadic course videos, both available on the class website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This class builds up to a compiler with the following features:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Variables and assignment via &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Integer arithmetic via &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reading inputs / printing output&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Booleans, conjunctions/disjunctions (and/or)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Branching via &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;, integer comparisons (&amp;lt;, etc.)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Heap-allocated vectors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Assignment / mutation (&lt;code&gt;set!&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;While loops&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fixed-arity functions and function application&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lambdas (closures at runtime)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The unique combination of features lets us tour an interesting cross-section of programming languages, exploring both imperative programming with loops and mutation but also functional programming with lists and recursion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Projects&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be specific, I challenge you to complete five projects, each including a comprehensive test suite that will seriously stress the correctness of your implementation. p1 is a warmup project (you should skip if you already know Racket), but p2-5 build a compiler for a set of increasingly-complex languages to x86-64. The languages nest inside of each other, with p2 giving us straight-line arithmetic, p3 giving us decision trees, p4 giving us loops and mutation, and p5 giving us functions, recursion, and lambdas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;p1 – Stack interpreter. This is a warmup project, if you know Racket and have some PL background, feel free to skip.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;p2 – Straight-line arithmetic / variables → x86-64 assembly language&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;p3 – Booleans and branching (if, and, or) → x86-64 assembly language&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;p4 – Vectors, heap allocation, set!, and loops → x86-64 assembly language&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;p5 – Functions, lambdas, and closure conversion → x86-64 assembly language&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The projects are designed with one key principle in mind: get us to the most expressive/fun language possible, as fast as possible. In doing this, we sacrifice a lot that might be typically covered:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Our languages aren’t type/memory safe, we assume the programmer is correct&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;No register allocation (possible to add, not too hard)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;No garbage collection of any kind: we just use malloc. We could trivially support the Boehm GC (I have done that in the past), but it was another static library to link in and I really wanted to make this self contained.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We support a very limited set of builtins (but it is trivial to add more)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So even after project 5, getting to a “real” compiler would take a bit of effort. The most important (in my opinion) are (a) memory safety (the language needs to be safe, period) via dynamic type tagging and (b) slightly more builtins, and (c) register allocation. That would get us to a respectable compiler. After that, we could add more language features, or optimize the ones we have, e.g., by using abstract interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;An Example Program&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our language will include functions, loops, branching, assignment, and even heap-allocated vectors. As an example of the power, here’s a Sudoku solver written in the language&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(program
 ;; =========================
 ;; List primitives
 ;; Empty list is (void)
 ;; =========================
 (define (is_nil x) (eq? x (void)))

 ;; cons cell as 2-element vector: [0] = head, [1] = tail
 (define (cons h t)
   (let ([c (make-vector 2)])
     (let ([_ (vector-set! c 0 h)])
       (let ([_ (vector-set! c 1 t)])
         c))))

 (define (head c) (vector-ref c 0))
 (define (tail c) (vector-ref c 1))

 ;; =========================
 ;; Cell representation
 ;; cell = (row col val) as nested cons
 ;; =========================
 (define (make_cell r c v)
   (cons r (cons c (cons v (void)))))

 (define (cell_row cell)
   (head cell))

 (define (cell_col cell)
   (head (tail cell)))

 (define (cell_val cell)
   (head (tail (tail cell))))

 ;; =========================
 ;; Block indexing (0,1,2) for rows/cols
 ;; =========================
 (define (block_index3 x)
   (if (&amp;lt; x 3)
       0
       (if (&amp;lt; x 6)
           1
           2)))

 (define (same_block? r1 c1 r2 c2)
   (if (eq? (block_index3 r1) (block_index3 r2))
       (eq? (block_index3 c1) (block_index3 c2))
       #f))

 ;; =========================
 ;; Lookup current value at (row, col) in board
 ;; board is a list of cells
 ;; Return 0 if not assigned
 ;; =========================
 (define (lookup board row col)
   (if (is_nil board)
       0
       (let ([cell (head board)])
         (let ([r (cell_row cell)])
           (let ([c (cell_col cell)])
             (if (and (eq? r row) (eq? c col))
                 (cell_val cell)
                 (lookup (tail board) row col)))))))

 ;; =========================
 ;; Conflict check:
 ;; #t if some cell in board has:
 ;;   - same value, and
 ;;   - same row OR same col OR same 3x3 block
 ;; =========================
 (define (conflicts? board row col val)
   (if (is_nil board)
       #f
       (let ([cell (head board)])
         (let ([r (cell_row cell)])
           (let ([c (cell_col cell)])
             (let ([v (cell_val cell)])
               (if (and (eq? v val)
                        (or (eq? r row)
                            (or (eq? c col)
                                (same_block? r c row col))))
                   #t
                   (conflicts? (tail board) row col val))))))))

 ;; =========================
 ;; Recursive backtracking solver over (row, col)
 ;; board: list of assignments
 ;; rows, cols = 0..8
 ;; =========================
 (define (solve_cell row col board)
   (if (eq? row 9)
       ;; All rows done: solved
       board
       (if (eq? col 9)
           ;; End of row: go to next row
           (solve_cell (+ row 1) 0 board)
           ;; Otherwise, try this cell
           (let ([existing (lookup board row col)])
             (if (eq? existing 0)
                 ;; Empty cell: try values 1..9
                 (let ([candidate 1])
                   (let ([solution (void)])
                     (begin
                       (while (and (&amp;lt; candidate 10)
                                   (eq? solution (void)))
                              (begin
				(if (conflicts? board row col candidate)
                                    ;; conflict, skip
                                    (set! solution solution)
                                    ;; no conflict, extend board and recurse
                                    (let ([s (solve_cell row
                                                         (+ col 1)
                                                         (cons (make_cell row col candidate)
                                                               board))])
                                      (if (eq? s (void))
                                          (set! solution solution)
                                          (set! solution s))))
				(set! candidate (+ candidate 1))))
                       solution)))
                 ;; Pre-filled cell: just move on
                 (solve_cell row (+ col 1) board))))))

 ;; =========================
 ;; Read initial board from input:
 ;; 81 integers, row-major, 0 = empty, 1..9 = given
 ;; Returns list of cells
 ;; =========================
 (define (read_board)
   (let ([board (void)])
     (let ([i 0])
       (begin
         (while (&amp;lt; i 9)
		(begin
                  (let ([j 0])
                    (while (&amp;lt; j 9)
			   (begin
			     (let ([v (read)])
                               (if (eq? v 0)
				   (set! board board)
				   (set! board (cons (make_cell i j v) board))))
			     (set! j (+ j 1)))))
                  (set! i (+ i 1))))
         board))))

 ;; =========================
 ;; Entry: read board, solve from (0,0), return solution
 ;; Solution is a list of (row col val) cells
 ;; =========================
 (let* ([board (read_board)]
        [solution (solve_cell 0 0 board)])
   (lookup solution 8 8)))
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Full Language&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The final language you’ll implement will be this one. In comments, I’ve also highlighted the sublanguages: for example, project 2 includes only numbers, input (read), binary plus, unary minus, variable references and let binding. It grows to all of &lt;code&gt;R5&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(define (R5-exp? e)
  (match e
    ;; Project 2
    [(? fixnum?) #t]
    ['(read) #t]
    [`(+ ,(? R5-exp? e0) ,(? R5-exp? e1)) #t]
    [`(- ,(? R5-exp? e)) #t]
    [(? symbol?) #t]
    [`(let ([,(? symbol? x) ,(? R5-exp? e)]) ,(? R5-exp? eb)) #t]
	;; Project 3
    [#t #t]
    [#f #t]
    ['(void) #t]
    [`(- ,(? R5-exp? e0) ,(? R5-exp? e1)) #t]
    [`(and ,(? R5-exp? e0) ,(? R5-exp? e1)) #t]
    [`(or  ,(? R5-exp? e0) ,(? R5-exp? e1)) #t]
    [`(not ,(? R5-exp? e1)) #t]
    [`(,(? cmp? c) ,(? R5-exp? e0) ,(? R5-exp? e1)) #t]
    [`(if ,(? R5-exp? e-g) ,(? R5-exp? e-t) ,(? R5-exp? e-f)) #t]
    ;; Project 4
    [`(let* ([,(? symbol? xs) ,(? R5-exp? es)] ...) ,(? R5-exp? eb)) #t]
    [`(begin ,(? R5-exp?) ... ,(? R5-exp? ret)) #t]
    [`(while ,(? R5-exp? e-g) ,(? R5-exp? es) ...) #t]
    [`(make-vector ,(? R5-exp? len)) #t]
    [`(vector-ref ,(? R5-exp? v) ,(? fixnum? i)) #t]
    [`(vector-set! ,(? R5-exp? v) ,(? fixnum? i) ,(? R5-exp? e-v)) #t]
    [`(set! ,(? symbol? x) ,(? R5-exp? e)) #t]
    ;; Project 5
    [`(,(? R5-exp? e-f) ,(? R5-exp? a-args) ...) #t]
    [`(lambda (,(? symbol? xs) ...) ,(? R5-exp? e-body)) #t]
	[_ #f]))

(define (R5-defn? defn)
  (match defn
    ;; Project 5 adds multiple function definitions
    [`(define (,(? symbol? f) ,(? symbol? formals) ...)  ,(? R5-exp? e-b)) #t]
    [_ #f]))

(define (R5? p)
  (match p
    [`(program ,(? R5-defn? defns) ... ,(? R5-exp?)) #t]
    [_ #f]))
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Compiler’s Structure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get you booted up fast as possible, every single project is designed the same way:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;compile.rkt&lt;/code&gt;– Your pass implementations. You will edit functions provided here. -&amp;gt; This is the only file you will edit! The rest are read-only&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;irs.rkt&lt;/code&gt;– IR definitions and predicates like&lt;code&gt;anf-program?&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;c1-program?&lt;/code&gt;, etc. (see also typed/shrunk variants)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;interpreters.rkt&lt;/code&gt;– Reference interpreters for several IRs (used by tests and for your own debugging).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;system.rkt&lt;/code&gt;– System/ABI configuration, pass names, runtime filenames, output paths, etc.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;main.rkt&lt;/code&gt;– Driver that runs all passes, can build a binary, and can launch a debug server.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;test.rkt&lt;/code&gt;– Test harness. Runs isolation tests or end-to-end native tests depending on&lt;code&gt;-m&lt;/code&gt;mode.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;runtime.c&lt;/code&gt;– Minimal runtime (&lt;code&gt;read_int64&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;print_int64&lt;/code&gt;, etc.).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;test-programs/&lt;/code&gt;– Example programs (&lt;code&gt;.scm&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;input-files/&lt;/code&gt;– Input streams for programs (lines of integers).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;goldens/&lt;/code&gt;– Instructor goldens (IR snapshots, interpreter outputs, and stdout baselines).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You write your code in &lt;code&gt;compile.rkt&lt;/code&gt;, which consists of a set of
passes. Each pass transforms an input language into an output
language, and these intermediate languages (IRs) are codified via
predicates in &lt;code&gt;irs.rkt&lt;/code&gt;. To define the meaning of each IR, we give an
interpreter for each in &lt;code&gt;interpreters.rkt&lt;/code&gt;. For the compiler to be
correct, it needs to be the case that–for all input streams–the
compiler produces the same output stream across all intermediate
IRs. There is some system-specific stuff in &lt;code&gt;system.rkt&lt;/code&gt;, which takes
care of things like Linux vs. Mac ABI issues, specifying register
names, etc. The &lt;code&gt;main.rkt&lt;/code&gt; file acts as a main compiler entrypoint,
and it carefully runs each pass of the compiler, checking predicates
before/after each pass and interpreting each IR, checking to ensure
consistency. This is a huge win for debugging, in my opinion: you
always want to localize errors to the proximate pass which causes
misinterpretation, and &lt;code&gt;main.rkt&lt;/code&gt; seriously aids debugging in my
experience. There is also more comprehensive test infrastructure in
&lt;code&gt;test.rkt&lt;/code&gt;; this test script is invoked by the Python-based test
scripts in &lt;code&gt;test/&lt;/code&gt;. These tests check the behavior of the compiler on
the programs in the &lt;code&gt;test-programs/&lt;/code&gt; directory, using the files from
&lt;code&gt;input-files&lt;/code&gt; as inputs and comparing to the outputs in &lt;code&gt;goldens/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why Is This Course Unique and Cool?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;You build a real compiler, all the way to actual x86-64 assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Each IR has a corresponding interpreter, which is easy to find/read and written in a familiar style, giving semantic clarity and testable correctness.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The project is language scalable, meaning that you can use it as a base for building your own language. Of course, this is thanks to Dr. Siek’s great “incremental” design.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;It is fully testable across multiple passes, which helps anticipate the thing we all fear most about writing a compiler: seeing a problem that is the ramification of far-away code from higher up in the compilation pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;It is written in a simple, pure recursive style. Just plain old pattern matching and recursion here, no need for any complex abstractions.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How Do I Get Started?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Familiarize yourself with the course webpage: https://kmicinski.com/cis531-f25&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you don’t know Racket, start with project 1: https://kmicinski.com/cis531-f25/projects/1&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Otherwise, start with project 2: https://kmicinski.com/cis531-f25/projects/2&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When you finish each project, move on to the next!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When you’re done, start building your own language. Consider adding type (checking/inference), classes, more builtins, pattern matching, continuations, exceptions, algebraic effects. The options are myriad, but once you’ve finished projects 2-5, you’ve built a whole compiler for a surprisingly expressive language.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Thank you to the National Science Foundation and Others&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you like this work and live in the United States, please feel commensurately less bad about paying your taxes. I made the whole class free, at least as free as I could given practical constraints. This class work on compilation is partially supported by our NSF PPoSS large, which has already produced many cool major results. In subsequent explorations, I am hoping that I can use this class compiler as a baseline for highly-scalable engines that reason about programs. Given the simple, self-contained nature–and the presence of per-pass interpreters and consistency testing–I see this as an awesome potential baseline for cool extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My course is of course heavily inspired by Prof. Siek’s book and course, along with inspiration from Thomas Gilray at Washington State. Eight years ago, Tom and I took a spontaneous trip to see the eclipse halfway across the country (skipping out on the ICSE ‘17 deadline basically); we discussed compiler design over a steamed seafood buffet in Myrtle Beach after napping in a cheap motel, having been awake for over 24 hours and feeling the eclipse had made it worth it. We sketched out his whole compiler on that roadtrip, and ever since that night eating steamed crabs, I wanted to build my own course compiler. Now that I have, I am not sure it compares to waking up for just four hours of twilight, only to consume copious amounts of butter and shellfish as the brisk ocean air wisps over your face, the closures and continuations softly washing rhythmically through the conversation as you walk along the beach back to your $50 motel room.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In closing, thanks for checking this out, this compiler was a ton of fun to build. Even as someone who has some amount of expertise in compiler design, building it and getting it 100% right (I hope!) was such a rewarding experience. My real sincere hope is that it offers students (and you!) a fun journey. If you end up doing anything this, please get in touch: kkmicins@syr.edu. I’d love to see what you come up with. Best wishes,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kristopher Micinski – Syracuse, November, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46031220</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 07:14:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fifty Shades of OOP</title><link>https://lesleylai.info/en/fifty_shades_of_oop/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7648da12caf69dc0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Fifty Shades of OOP&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OOP-bashing seems fashionable nowadays. I decided to write this article after seeing two OOP-related articles on Lobsters in quick succession. I’m not interested in defending or attacking OOP, but I do want to throw in my two cents and offer a more nuanced view.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The industry and the academy have used the term “object-oriented” to mean so many different things. One thing that makes conversations around OOP so unproductive is the lack of consensus on what OOP is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is Object-Oriented Programming? Wikipedia defines it as “a programming paradigm based on the concept of objects.” This definition is unsatisfactory, as it requires a definition of an “object” and fails to encompass the disparate ways the term is used in the industry. There is also Alan Kay’s vision of OOP. However, the way most people use the term has drifted apart, and I don’t want to fall into essentialism or etymological fallacy by insisting on a “true” meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, I think it is better to treat OOP as a mixed bag of interrelated ideas and examine them individually. Below, I will survey some ideas related to OOP and mention their pros and cons (in my subjective mind).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Classes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Object-oriented programming is a method of implementation in which programs are organized as cooperative collections of objects, each of which represents an instance of some class, and whose classes are all members of a hierarchy of classes united via inheritance relationships. — Grady Booch&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Classes extend the idea of a “struct” or “record” with support for the method syntax, information hiding, and inheritance. We will talk about those specific features later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Classes can also be viewed as blueprints for objects. It is not the only way to do that, and prototypes is an alternative pioneered by Self and, most famously, used by JavaScript. Personally, I feel that prototypes are harder to wrap one’s head around compared to classes. Even JavaScript tries to hide its usage of prototypes from newcomers with ES6 classes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Method Syntax&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In Japanese, we have sentence chaining, which is similar to method chaining in Ruby — Yukihiro Matsumoto&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The method syntax is one of the less controversial OOP features. It captures common programming use cases involving operations on a specific subject. Even in languages without methods, it is common to see functions effectively serve as methods by taking the relevant data as their first argument (or last, in languages with currying).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The syntax involves method definitions and method calls. Usually, languages supporting methods have both, unless you consider the “pipe operators” in functional languages as a form of method call.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The method call syntax aids IDE autocompletion, and method chaining is often more ergonomic than nested function calls (similar to the pipe operator in functional languages).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are some debatable aspects of the method syntax, too. First, in many languages, methods are often not definable outside of a class, which causes a power imbalance compared to functions. There are certain exceptions, such as Rust (methods are always defined outside of the struct), Scala, Kotlin, and C# (extension methods).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, in many languages, &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; is implicit. This keeps the code more concise, but it can also introduce confusion and increase the risk of accidental name shadowing. Another drawback of an implicit this is that it is always passed as a pointer, and its type cannot be changed. This means you cannot pass it as a copy, and sometimes this indirection leads to performance issues. More importantly, because the type of this is fixed, you cannot write generic functions that accept different &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; types. Python and Rust got this right from the start, and C++ just fixed this issue in C++23 with deducing this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Third, in languages with both “free functions” and methods, they become two incompatible ways to do the same thing. This can cause problems in generic code. Rust addresses this issue by allowing fully qualifying a method name and treating it as a function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fourth, the dot notation is used for both instance variable accesses and method calls in most languages. This is an intentional choice to make methods look more uniform with objects. In certain dynamically typed languages where methods are instance variables, this is fine and pretty much not even a choice. On the other hand, in languages like C++ or Java, this can cause confusion and shadowing problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Information Hiding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Its interface or definition was chosen to reveal as little as possible about its inner workings — [Parnas, 1972b]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Smalltalk, all instance variables are not directly accessible from outside the object, and all methods are exposed. More modern OOP languages support information hiding via access specifiers like &lt;code&gt;private&lt;/code&gt; at the class level. Even non-OOP languages usually support information hiding in some way, be it module systems, opaque types, or even C’s header separation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Information hiding is a good way to prevent invariant from being violated. It is also a good way to separate frequently changed implementation details from a stable interface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, aggressively hiding information may cause unnecessary boilerplate or abstraction inversion. Another criticism comes from functional programmers, who argue that you don’t need to maintain invariants and thus don’t need much information hiding if data is immutable. And, in a sense, OOP encourages people to write mutable objects that must be maintained as invariants.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Information hiding also encourages people to create small, self-contained objects that “know how to handle themselves,” which leads directly into the topic of encapsulation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Encapsulation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you can, just move all of that behavior into the class it helps. After all, OOP is about letting objects take care of themselves. — Bob Nystrom, Game Programming Patterns&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Encapsulation is often confused with information hiding, but the two are distinct. Encapsulation refers to bundling data with the functions that operate on it. OOP languages directly support encapsulation with classes and the method syntax, but there are other approaches (e.g., the module system in OCaml).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most common construct for encapsulation is objects, but it is not the only mechanism. Many modern languages also support closures (in fact, closures and objects can simulate each other). There are also other lesser-known approaches, such as modules found in the ML family.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data-oriented design has a lot to say about bundling data and functionality. When many objects exist, it is often much more efficient to process them in batches rather than individually. Having small objects with distinct behaviors can lead to poor data locality, more indirection, and fewer opportunities for parallelism. Of course, advocates of data-oriented design don’t reject encapsulation outright, but they encourage a more coarse-grained form of it, organized around how the code is actually used rather than how the domain model is conceptually structured.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Interfaces&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“No part of a complex system should depend on the internal details of any other part.” — Daniel, Ingalls. “The Smalltalk-76 Programming System Design and Implementation”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Separation of interface and implementation is an old idea closely related to information hiding, encapsulation, and abstract data type. In some sense, even C’s header files can be considered an interface, but OOP usage of “interface” most often refers to a specific set of language constructs that support polymorphism (typically implemented via inheritance). Usually, an interface can’t contain data, and in more restricted languages (e.g., early versions of Java), they can’t contain method implementations either. The same idea of an interface is also common in non-OOP languages: Haskell type classes, Rust traits, and Go interfaces all serve the role of specifying an abstract set of operations independent of implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interface is often considered a simpler, more disciplined alternative to full-blown class inheritance. It is a single-purpose feature and doesn’t suffer from the same diamond problem that plagues multiple inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interface is also extremely useful in combination with parametric polymorphism, since it allows you to constrain the operations a type parameter must support. Dynamically-typed languages (and C++/D template) achieve something similar through duck-typing, but even languages with duck-typing introduce interface constructs later to express constraints more explicitly (e.g., C++ concepts or TypeScript interfaces).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The interface as implemented in OOP languages often has a runtime cost, but that’s not always the case. For example, C++ concepts is an example that only supports compile-time, and Rust’s trait only has opt-in runtime polymorphism support via &lt;code&gt;dyn&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Late Binding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;OOP to me means only messaging, local retention and protection and hiding of state-process, and extreme late-binding of all things — Alan Kay&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Late binding refers to delaying the lookup of a method or a member until runtime. It is the default of most dynamic-typed languages, where method calls are often implemented as a hash table lookup, but can also be achieved with other means, such as dynamic loading or function pointers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A key aspect of late binding is that behaviour can be changed while the software is still running, enabling all kinds of hot-reloading and monkey-patching workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The downside of late binding is its non-trivial performance cost. Moreover, it can also be a footgun for breaking invariants or even interface mismatches. Its mutable nature can also introduce subtler issues, for example, the “late binding closures” pitfall in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Dynamic Dispatch&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A programming paradigm in C++ using Polymorphism based on runtime function dispatch using virtual functions — Back to Basics: Object-Oriented Programming - Jon Kalb - CppCon 2019&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A concept related to late binding is dynamic dispatch, in which the implementation of a polymorphic operation is selected at runtime. The two concepts overlap, though dynamic dispatch focuses more on selecting multiple known polymorphic operations rather than on name lookup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a dynamically typed language, dynamic dispatch is the default since everything is late-bound. In statically typed languages, it is usually implemented as a virtual function table that looks something like this under the hood:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These languages also provide compile-time guarantees that the vtable contains valid operations for the type.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dynamic dispatch can be decoupled from inheritance, whether by manually implementing a v-table (e.g., C++‘s “type-erased types” such as &lt;code&gt;std::function&lt;/code&gt;) or an interface/trait/typeclass kind of constructs. When not paired with inheritance, dynamic dispatch alone is usually not considered “OOP.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another thing to note is that the pointer to the v-table can be directly inside the object (e.g., C++) or embedded in “fat pointers” (e.g., Go and Rust).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Complaints about dynamic dispatch are usually about its performance. Although a virtual function call itself can be pretty fast, it opens room for missing compiler inlining opportunities, cache misses, and branch mispredictions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Inheritance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;programming using class hierarchies and virtual functions to allow manipulation of objects of a variety of types through well-defined interfaces and to allow a program to be extended incrementally through derivation — Bjarne Stroustrup&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inheritance has a long history, way backed to Simula 67. It is probably the most iconic feature of OOP. Almost every language marketed as “object-oriented” includes it, while languages that avoid OOP typically omit it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It can be damn convenient. In many cases, using an alternative approach will result in significantly more boilerplate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, inheritance is a very non-orthogonal feature. It is a single mechanism that enables dynamic dispatch, subtyping polymorphism, interface/implementation segregation, and code reuse. It is flexible, though that flexibility makes it easy to misuse. For that reason, some languages nowadays replace it with more restrictive alternative constructs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are some other problems with inheritance. First, using inheritance almost certainly means you are paying the performance cost of dynamic dispatch and heap allocation. In some languages, such as C++, you can use inheritance without dynamic dispatch and heap allocation, and there are some valid use cases (e.g., code reuse with CRTP), but the majority of uses of inheritance are for runtime polymorphism (and thus rely on dynamic dispatch).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, inheritance implements subtyping in an unsound way, requiring programmers to manually enforce the Liskov substitution principle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, inheritance hierarchies are rigid. They suffer from issues like the diagonal problem, and that inflexibility is one of the main reasons people prefer composition over inheritance. The component pattern chapter of Game Programming Patterns provides a good example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Subtyping Polymorphism&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If for each object&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;of type&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;there is another object&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;of type&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;such that for all programs&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;defined in terms of&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;, the behavior of&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;is unchanged when&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;is substituted for&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;, then&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;is a subtype of&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
      &lt;mjx-container&gt;. — Barbara Liskov, “Data Abstraction and Hierarchy”&lt;/mjx-container&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Subtyping describes an “is a” relation between two types. The Liskov substitution principle defines the property that safe subtyping relationships must uphold.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OOP languages often support subtyping via inheritance, but note that inheritance doesn’t always model subtyping, and it is not the only form of subtyping either. Various interface/trait constructs in non-OOP languages often support subtyping. And besides nominal subtyping, where one explicitly declares the subtyping relationship, there are also structural subtyping, where the subtyping is implicit if one type contains all the features of another type. Good examples of structural subtyping include OCaml (objects and polymorphic variants) and TypeScript interfaces. Subtyping also shows in all kinds of little places, such as Rust lifetime and TypeScript’s coercion from a non-nullable type to its nullable counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A related concept to subtyping is variance (not related to class-invariant), which bridges parametric polymorphism and subtyping. I won’t bother explaining variance here, as this topic probably needs an entire blog post to explain well. It is a great ergonomic boost (e.g., C++ pointers will be unusable for polymorphic use if they are not covariant), but most languages only implement a limited, hard-coded version, because it is hard to understand and also error-prone. In particular, mutable data types should usually be invariant, and Java/C#‘s covariant arrays are a primary example on this gone wrong. Only a few languages allow programmers to explicitly control variance, including Scala and Kotlin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Type conversion via subtyping relationships is often implicit. Implicit conversion has a bad reputation. Though doing it with subtyping is ergonomic, and is probably the least surprising kind of implicit conversion. Another way to view subtyping is as the dual of implicit conversions. We can “fake” a subtyping relation with implicit conversion. For example, C++ templated types are invariant, but &lt;code&gt;std::unique_ptr&lt;/code&gt; achieves covariance with an implicit conversion from &lt;code&gt;std::unique_ptr&amp;lt;Derived&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;std::unique_ptr&amp;lt;Base&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Does Go Have Subtyping? is a good article to further explore this idea.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One reason that language designers often try to avoid subtyping is the implementation complexity. Integrating bidirectional type inference and subtyping is notoriously difficult. Stephen Dolan’s 2016 thesis Algebraic Subtyping makes good progress addressing this issue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Message Passing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I thought of objects being like biological cells and/or individual computers on a network, only able to communicate with messages — Alan Kay&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Message passing means using objects that send each other “messages” as a way of execution. It is the centric theme of Alan Kay’s vision of OOP, though the definition can be pretty vague. An important point is that message names are late-bound, and the structures of these messages are not necessarily fixed at compile time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many early object-oriented concepts were influenced by distributed and simulation systems, where message passing is natural. However, in the era where most people work on single-threaded code, the message was gradually forgotten in languages such as C++ and Java. The method syntax only has limited benefit compared to the original message-passing idea (Bjarne Stroustrup was definitely aware of the idea from Simula, but there is practical constraint on how to make it fast). There was still some genuine message passing, but only in specific areas such as inter-process communication or highly event-driven systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Message passing gains a Renaissance in concurrent programming, ironically through non-OOP languages like Erlang and Golang, with constructs such as actors and channels. This kind of shared-nothing concurrency removed a whole range of data race and race condition bugs. In combination with supervision, actors also provide fault tolerance, so that the failure of one actor will not affect the entire program.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Open Recursion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In general, a rule of thumb is: use classes and objects in situations where open recursion is a big win. — Real World OCaml&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originating in the famous Types and Programming Languages, open recursion is probably the least well-known and understood term in this blog post. Nevertheless, it just describes a familiar property of object-oriented systems: methods for an object can call each other, even if they are defined in different classes in the inheritance hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The term is somewhat misleading, as there may not be recursive function calls, but here “recursion” means “mutually recursive.” The word “open” refers to “open to extension,” typically empowered by inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s easiest to see with an example:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For anyone with some familiarity with OOP, we probably take open recursion for granted, even though we may not be aware of its name. However, not all language constructs have this property. For example, in many languages, functions are not mutually recursive by default:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, in languages with late-bound functions, functions in the same module can always call each other (e.g., Python, JavaScript). There are other languages where functions are mutually recursive by default (e.g., Rust), or have forward declarations (C) or a &lt;code&gt;letrec&lt;/code&gt; construct (Scheme and ML family) to make functions mutually recursive. This solves the “recursion” part, but still not the “open” part yet:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s fix this problem by using a callback:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tada, we just reinvented prototype-style dispatch!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway, with my quick example above, I want to show that open recursion is a property that OOP gives for free, but reproducing it in languages without built-in support can be tricky. Open recursion allows interdependent parts of an object to be defined separately, and this property is used in many instances, for example, the entire idea of decorator pattern depends on open recursion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;OOP Best Practices&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps the more common complaints about OOP are not about specific language features, but rather about the programming styles it encourages. Many practices are taught as universal best practices, sometimes with rationales, but their downsides are often omitted. Some examples popped into my mind are&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Practice&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Advantages&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Disadvantage&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;preferring polymorphism over tagged union/if/switch/pattern matching&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Open to extension, easier to add new cases.&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Performance hit; Related behaviors get scattered in multiple places; harder to see the whole controll flow in one place&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;making all data members private&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Protect class invariants&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;More boilerplates; Often unnecessary to hide data without invariants; Getter/setter pairs work less well compared to direct access in languages without property syntax&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;preferring small “self-managed” objects over central “managers”&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Harder to violate invariants, cleaner code organization&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Potential bad data locality, missing parallelism opportunities, and duplicated references to common data (“back pointer”)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;preferring extension rather than modification&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Prevent new features from breaking the old one. Prevent API break&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;No reason to “close” a non-public module where you own its usage. Leads to unnecessary complexity and inheritance chain; poorly designed interfaces are not changed; Can cause abstraction inversion&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;preferring abstraction over concrete implementations&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Making more system swappable and testable&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Overuse sacrifices readability and debuggability. Performance cost of extra indirection&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This blog post is long enough, so I will not go into more details. Feel free to disagree with my “advantages and disadvantages”. What I want to convey is that almost all those practices come with trade-offs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;In the End&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Congratulations on making it to the end of this article! There are other topics I’d love to discuss, such as RAII and design patterns. However, this article is long enough, so I will leave those for you to explore on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46032148</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 09:40:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Shai-Hulud Returns: Over 300 NPM Packages Infected</title><link>https://helixguard.ai/blog/malicious-sha1hulud-2025-11-24</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46032539</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 10:40:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chrome Jpegxl Issue Reopened</title><link>https://issues.chromium.org/issues/40168998</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="732bc1ae2d485202"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sign in&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46033330</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:23:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Implications of AI to schools</title><link>https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/1993010584175141038</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d635f48b34542867"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve detected that JavaScript is disabled in this browser. Please enable JavaScript or switch to a supported browser to continue using x.com. You can see a list of supported browsers in our Help Center.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Help Center&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Terms of Service Privacy Policy Cookie Policy Imprint Ads info © 2025 X Corp.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46036878</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 17:51:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cool-retro-term: terminal emulator which mimics look and feel of CRTs</title><link>https://github.com/Swordfish90/cool-retro-term</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="afec61b99b81218b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;&amp;gt; Default Amber&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;C:\ IBM DOS&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;$ Default Green&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;cool-retro-term is a terminal emulator which mimics the look and feel of the old cathode tube screens. It has been designed to be eye-candy, customizable, and reasonably lightweight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It uses the QML port of qtermwidget (Konsole): https://github.com/Swordfish90/qmltermwidget.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This terminal emulator works under Linux and macOS and requires Qt5. It's suggested that you stick to the latest LTS version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Settings such as colors, fonts, and effects can be accessed via context menu.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to get a hold of the latest version, just go to the Releases page and grab the latest AppImage (Linux) or dmg (macOS).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alternatively, most distributions such as Ubuntu, Fedora or Arch already package cool-retro-term in their official repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check out the wiki and follow the instructions on how to build it on Linux and macOS.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46036895</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 17:52:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: I built an interactive HN Simulator</title><link>https://news.ysimulator.run/news</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="777ff7b7fede5c03"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46036908</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 17:52:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Bitter Lesson of LLM Extensions</title><link>https://www.sawyerhood.com/blog/llm-extension</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d546845b0b9b86be"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Bitter Lesson of LLM Extensions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three years ago, “using an LLM” meant pasting a wall of text into a chat box and hoping for something useful back. Today, we point agents at our codebases, our browsers, and let them go off and act on our behalf. A key question that has been brewing under the surface during this time has been: how do we let end users actually customize these systems?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As models have become more capable, the ways and mechanisms that end users have access to customize them have expanded as well. We've gone from simple system prompts to complex client-server protocols and back again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wanted to take a moment to reflect on the history of LLM extension over the last three years and where I see it going in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ChatGPT Plugins (March 2023)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just four months after launch, OpenAI announced ChatGPT Plugins. Looking back, these were wildly ahead of their time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The idea was ambitious: give the LLM a link to an OpenAPI spec and let it "run wild" calling REST endpoints. It was a direct line to AGI-style thinking: universal tool use via standard APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "schema_version": "v1",
  "name_for_human": "TODO Manager",
  "name_for_model": "todo_manager",
  "description_for_human": "Manages your TODOs!",
  "description_for_model": "An app for managing a user's TODOs",
  "api": { "url": "/openapi.json" },
  "auth": { "type": "none" },
  "logo_url": "https://example.com/logo.png",
  "legal_info_url": "http://example.com",
  "contact_email": "hello@example.com"
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem? The models weren't ready. GPT-3.5 (and even early GPT-4) struggled to navigate massive API specs without hallucinating or getting lost in context. Plus, the UX was clunky. You had to manually toggle plugins for every chat!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's what that looked like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it gave us a glimpse of the future: The Code Interpreter plugin (later Advanced Data Analysis) became indispensable, foreshadowing the powerful sandboxed execution environments we use today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Custom Instructions (July 2023)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom instructions were the "smooth brain" counter-reaction to the complexity of plugins. I did a double take when writing this because I thought for sure this feature was released before plugins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was just a user-defined prompt appended to every chat. Simple. Obvious. Yet it solved a huge problem: repetitive context setting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was the spiritual ancestor to every &lt;code&gt;.cursorrules&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CLAUDE.md&lt;/code&gt; file that followed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Custom GPTs (Nov 2023)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenAI repackaged instructions and tools into Custom GPTs. This was an attempt to "productize" prompt engineering. You could bundle a persona, some files, and a few actions into a shareable link.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was a retreat from the open-ended promise of plugins toward curated, single-purpose "apps."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Memory in ChatGPT (February 2024)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So far, we've discussed manual ways to extend LLMs. Memory represented a shift toward automatic personalization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChatGPT Memory records details from your conversations and quietly inserts them into future context. It's like a system prompt that writes itself. If you mention you're a vegetarian, it remembers that weeks later. It’s a small feature, but it marked the beginning of agents that maintain long-term state without user intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Cursor Rules (April 2024)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cursor changed the game by putting custom instructions where they belonged: in the repo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;.cursorrules&lt;/code&gt; file was a revelation. Instead of pasting context into a chat window, you committed it to git.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"We use tabs, not spaces."&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"No semicolons."&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Always use TypeScript."&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It started as a single file, then evolved into a &lt;code&gt;.cursor/rules&lt;/code&gt; folder with sophisticated scoping. You could organize multiple rule files, and even define when they applied, for example, only for certain file types or subdirectories. It was the first time extension felt "native" to the code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later Cursor introduced the ability to let the LLM decide when to apply a rule, which is a pattern we will see again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Model Context Protocol (Nov 2024)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By late 2024, models were finally smart enough to handle real tools reliably. Anthropic's Model Context Protocol (MCP) was the answer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MCP is a heavyweight solution. An MCP client needs to keep a persistent connection to an MCP server. The server serves up tool definitions, resources, and prompts to the client (in most cases is an agent) and it can send a message to the server saying a tool has been called and the server can respond with the result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike Custom Instructions (which just add context), MCP gives the model actual capabilities. It can read your repo, query your Postgres DB, or deploy to Vercel. Besides just providing tools, it also allows servers to provide resources (documents, logs) and prompts directly to the agent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's powerful, and perhaps a bit of overkill. While the complexity might be worth it for agent developers asking a user to set up and connect an MCP is a lot of friction and there is an entire ecosystem of startups like Smithery built around making it easier to use MCP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that ChatGPT apps which were announced in October 2025 are built on top of MCP as a base layer. This is an attempt to make it easier for end users to use MCP without having to actually think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Claude Code: New Agent, New Extensions (Feb 2025)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early 2025 brought us Claude Code, which essentially added every extension mechanism under the sun to an agent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;CLAUDE.md&lt;/code&gt;: The standard for repo-level instructions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MCP: For heavy-duty tool integration.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Slash Commands: Like Cursor's notebooks, for reusable prompts.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hooks: The ability to intercept and modify the agent's loop (e.g., "Stop if the tests fail").&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sub-agents: Spawning specialized workers to handle sub-tasks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Output Styles: (Deprecated) Configuring tone and format.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time will tell how many of these features will stick around in the long term. Anthropic has already tried to deprecate output styles.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Agent Skills (Oct 2025)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next extension mechanism added to Claude Code is significant enough to warrant a deeper dive. Agent Skills are the rebirth of ChatGPT Plugins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While MCP has a whole client-server protocol, Agent Skills are just folders of markdown files and scripts (in whatever language you choose).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The agent simply scans a &lt;code&gt;skills/&lt;/code&gt; directory, reads the frontmatter of every &lt;code&gt;SKILL.md&lt;/code&gt;, and builds a lightweight index. It then chooses to read the full contents of a skill only if it's appropriate for the current task. This solves one of the major problems with MCP: the context bloat that comes from having to load all of the tool definitions into the context window at once.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a snippet of the structure of a skill for doing e2e testing with Playwright taken from Anthropic's Skills examples repository:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;webapp-testing/
├── examples/
│   ├── console_logging.py
│   ├── element_discovery.py
│   └── static_html_automation.py
├── scripts/
│   └── with_server.py
└── SKILL.md
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a mix of scripts, examples, and plain text instructions. The only required file is the SKILL.md file. Let's take a look at that file:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;---
name: webapp-testing
description: Toolkit for interacting with and testing local web applications using Playwright. Supports verifying frontend functionality, debugging UI behavior, capturing browser screenshots, and viewing browser logs.
license: Complete terms in LICENSE.txt
---

# Web Application Testing

To test local web applications, write native Python Playwright scripts.

**Helper Scripts Available**:

- `scripts/with_server.py` - Manages server lifecycle (supports multiple servers)

**Always run scripts with `--help` first** to see usage. DO NOT read the source until you try running the script first and find that a customized solution is absolutely necessary. These scripts can be very large and thus pollute your context window. They exist to be called directly as black-box scripts rather than ingested into your context window.

... skill continues ...
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is just a plain markdown file with some metadata and a description of the skill. The agent reads the file which freely references other files that the agent can read. In contrast a playwright MCP server has dozens of tool definitions to control a browser, this skill just says "you have bash, this is how you write a playwright script".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Granted to use a skill the agent needs to have general purpose access to a computer, but this is the bitter lesson in action. Giving an agent general purpose tools and trusting it to have the ability to use them to accomplish a task might very well be the winning strategy over making specialized tools for every task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What the future holds&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Skills are the actualization of the dream that was set out by ChatGPT Plugins: just give the model instructions and some generic tools and trust it to do the glue work in-between. But I have a hypothesis that it might actually work now because the models are actually smart enough for it to work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Agent skills work because it assumes the agent has the ability to write its own tools (via bash commands). You can just give it code snippets and ask the agent to figure out how to run them generically for the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Importantly, I think that skills signal towards a new definition of what an agent really is. An agent isn't just a LLM in a while loop. It's an LLM in a while loop that has a computer strapped to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude Code is the piece of software that first made this click for me, but it is way too developer focused to be the final form. Other applications like Zo Computer try to package the llm and computer together into a single application, but I still think it still doesn't abstract the computer away enough from the end user. If I ask a coworker to do something, I don't need to see their entire file system, I just need to know that they have a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking forward into 2026 I expect more and more llm applications that we use will have a computer strapped to them in new and interesting ways, whether we know it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I could short MCP, I would, and I expect us to go back to extending our agents with the most accessible programming language: natural language.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46037343</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:32:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google's new 'Aluminium OS' project brings Android to PC</title><link>https://www.androidauthority.com/aluminium-os-android-for-pcs-3619092/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f86a0419b9c75e1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Affiliate links on Android Authority may earn us a commission. Learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Google's new 'Aluminium OS' project brings Android to PC: Here's what we know&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;13 hours ago&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Android operating system is incredibly versatile. Beyond smartphones, it officially powers tablets, watches, TVs, cars, and XR headsets. However, it has virtually no presence on traditional PCs, where Google instead relies on ChromeOS. Despite Google’s efforts to challenge the dominance of Windows and macOS, ChromeOS remains a distant third. To close this gap, the company is unifying ChromeOS and Android into a single desktop platform, codenamed ‘Aluminium OS.’ Here’s what we know so far.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Android on PCs: The story so far&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One year ago, Android Authority exclusively revealed Google’s plan to rally behind Android as its unified desktop OS. Our source indicated that this shift aims to create products that better compete with the iPad while making more effective use of development resources. In July, a Google executive confirmed part of our reporting, revealing that the company intends to merge ChromeOS and Android into a single platform. Finally, at Qualcomm’s Snapdragon Summit in September, Google officially announced it is bringing Android to the PC market. The company stated it is collaborating with Qualcomm to build a new platform that converges mobile and desktop computing, leveraging recent advancements in AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Would you miss Chrome OS if Google sunsets it for 'Aluminium OS'?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualcomm CEO Cristiano Amon (left) and Google SVP of Devices and Services Rick Osterloh (right) announcing a joint project to bring Android to PCs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While we now know Google is building Android for PCs, there are still many unknown details. Is Google retiring the ChromeOS brand? Will existing Chromebooks receive the new operating system, or will they be left behind? Will this OS arrive only on budget machines, or target premium PCs as well? What will the interface actually look like, and what new features can we expect?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are the burning questions as Google continues developing the platform. We likely won’t have all the answers until we get closer to launch, but thanks to job listings and bug reports, we’ve uncovered early details that offer some clues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t want to miss the best from Android Authority?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Set us as a favorite source in Google Discover to never miss our latest exclusive reports, expert analysis, and much more.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can also set us as a preferred source in Google Search by clicking the button below.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Aluminium OS: Google’s PC ambitions take shape&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, a tipster on Telegram named Frost Core shared a link to an intriguing Google job listing for a ‘Senior Product Manager, Android, Laptop and Tablets.’ While we already know Google is bringing Android to the PC, the listing explicitly states that the role involves ‘working on a new Aluminium, Android-based, operating system.’ This effectively confirms that Aluminium is the codename for the new unified platform. The name appears to be a nod to the project’s roots: like Chromium (the open-source version of ChromeOS), Aluminium is a metal ending in ‘-ium.’ The choice of the British spelling — emphasizing the ‘Al’ prefix — likely pays homage to Android serving as the project’s foundation.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Much like Android XR, Google says its new Aluminium OS is ‘built with artificial intelligence (AI) at the core.’ This implies deep integration with Gemini, Google’s AI chatbot and large language model (LLM). At the Snapdragon Summit, Rick Osterloh, Google’s SVP of Devices and Services, outlined the company’s plans to bring its AI stack to PCs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;“This is another way we can leverage all of the great work we’re doing together on our AI stack, our full stack, bringing Gemini models, bringing the assistant, bringing all of our applications and developer community into the PC domain. And I think this is another way in which Android is gonna be able to serve everyone in every computing category.”&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have yet to see exactly what new features Gemini will enable on Android PCs, but we hope the OS will fully leverage the hardware’s potential. On select premium smartphones, Gemini already powers an array of on-device AI features that demand significant memory and processing power from the CPU, GPU, and NPU. There were concerns that Google might restrict this new OS to the same budget-friendly niche where Chromebooks currently excel, ceding the high-end market to Microsoft and Apple. However, the job listing dispels those fears.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new Senior Product Manager role is tasked with “driving the roadmap and curating a portfolio of ChromeOS and Aluminium Operating System (ALOS) Commercial devices across all form factors (e.g. laptops, detachables, tablets, and boxes) and tiers (e.g., Chromebook, Chromebook Plus, AL Entry, AL Mass Premium, and AL Premium) that meets the needs of users and the business.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This confirms that Android won’t be limited to laptops; the roadmap explicitly includes detachables, tablets, and ‘boxes’ (likely mini-PCs akin to the Chromebox or Mac Mini). Furthermore, the tiered structure — listing ‘AL Mass Premium’ and ‘AL Premium’ alongside ‘AL Entry’ — indicates that Google intends to push Android beyond budget PC hardware. While exact pricing for these tiers is hard to predict, it is clear Google aims to compete across the entire spectrum — a strategy foreshadowed by the recent Chromebook Plus initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of Chromebooks, the job listing also raises questions about the future of ChromeOS. The listing notes that the person will help “drive ChromeOS and Aluminium (e.g., Android) platforms and devices,” creating a roadmap and product portfolio that encompasses both. This implies the two platforms will coexist for some time. However, the person is also explicitly tasked with developing a strategy for transitioning “Google from ChromeOS to Aluminium with business continuity in the future.” This confirms that Google aims to eventually replace ChromeOS entirely — a move that must be managed carefully to avoid disrupting enterprise customers. This transition will likely require a multi-pronged approach:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Legacy Support: Existing ChromeOS devices that cannot be migrated to Aluminium OS will likely receive updates until they reach their end-of-life. This means Google will need to maintain the legacy ChromiumOS codebase for several more years.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Optional Migration: Rather than forcing an immediate switch, Google may offer an optional upgrade path for capable hardware. The company is currently testing Aluminium OS on development boards featuring MediaTek Kompanio 520 and 12th Gen Intel Alder Lake processors, so existing Chromebooks with these chips could be eligible for the update. However, migrating an operating system on live hardware is a massive technical hurdle that will require meticulous execution.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And of course, there will be new PCs launching with Aluminium OS out of the box as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Is ChromeOS dead as we know it?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if Google replaces the entire foundation of ChromeOS with Android, the company may be reluctant to abandon the name. While it lacks the market share of Windows or macOS, the ChromeOS brand is widely recognized, particularly in the education and enterprise sectors. Although the job listing doesn’t confirm the final naming scheme, bug reports spotted by Frost Core hint that Google may retain the branding. Engineers have referred to the current platform as “ChromeOS Classic” and “non-Aluminium ChromeOS,” implying the new Android-based version could simply usurp the name “ChromeOS.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alternatively, Google might adopt “Android Desktop” as the name to align with its renewed focus on promoting Android as a brand. However, “Android Desktop” could merely be an internal designation for the form factor. Since these references have only appeared in bug reports, the final marketing name remains an open question.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;When will Android on PCs launch?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google is actively developing the platform, with bug reports confirming that the company is testing fresh builds of Android 16 on development hardware. The company has confirmed the project will launch in 2026, though it remains unclear whether it will arrive in the first or second half of the year. Given this timeline, it is highly likely that the initial public release will be built upon Android 17, which is due next year. We will continue to monitor the project to find further details ahead of its official debut.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you for being part of our community. Read our Comment Policy before posting.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46037591</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:49:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pebble Watch software is now 100% open source</title><link>https://ericmigi.com/blog/pebble-watch-software-is-now-100percent-open-source</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="dc4f4b1117d7e1f1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pebble Watch Software Is Now 100% Open Source + Tick Talk #4 - PT2 Demos!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[2025-11-24]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another big Pebble update today! TLDR:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yesterday, Pebble watch software was ~95% open source. Today, it’s 100% open source. You can download, compile and run all the software you need to use your Pebble. We just published the source code for the new Pebble mobile app!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pebble Appstore now has a publicly available backup and supports multiple feeds, providing long term reliability through decentralization. We’ve launched our own feed and Developer Dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pebble Time 2 schedule update (aiming to begin shipping in January, with most arriving on wrists in March/April)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the last year, and especially in the last week, I've chatted with tons of people in the Pebble community. One of the main questions people have is ‘how do I know that my new Pebble watch will continue to work long into the future?’. It’s an extremely valid question and concern - one that I share as a fellow Pebble wearer. I called this out specifically in my blog post announcing the relaunch in January 2025. How is this time round going to be different from last time?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two pieces to making Pebble sustainable long term - hardware and software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hardware&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nothing lasts forever, especially an inexpensive gadget like a Pebble. We want to be able to keep manufacturing these watches long into the future - mostly because I will always want one on my wrist! The company I set up to relaunch Pebble, Core Devices, is self funded, built without investors, and extremely lean. As long as we stay profitable (ie we don’t lose money), we will continue to manufacture new watches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re also making sure that our new watches are more repairable than old Pebble watches. The back cover of Pebble Time 2 is screwed in. You can remove the back cover and replace the battery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve also published electrical and mechanical design files for Pebble 2 Duo. Yes, you can download the schematic (includes KiCad project files) right now on Github! This should give you a nice jumpstart to designing your own PebbleOS-compatible device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Software&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last time round, barely any of the Pebble software was open source. This made it very hard for the Pebble community to make improvements to their watches after the company behind Pebble shut down. Things are different now! This whole relaunch came about primarily because Google open sourced PebbleOS (thank you!). Yesterday, the software that powers Pebble watches was around 95% open source. As of today, it’s now 100%. This means that if Core Devices were to disappear into a black hole, you have all the source code you need to build, run and improve the software behind your Pebble.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I confess that I misunderstood why 95% was much less sustainable than 100% until recently. I discuss this in more detail in my latest Tick Talk episode (check it out). Long story short - I’m an Android user and was happy to sideload the old Pebble APK on my phone, but iPhone and other Android users have basically been stuck without an easily available Pebble mobile companion app for years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s how we’re making sure the 3 main Pebble software components are open source and guaranteed to work long into the future:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PebbleOS - software that runs on your watch itself. This has been 100% open source since January and we’ve committed to open sourcing all the improvements we’ve made → github.com/coredevices/PebbleOS. You can download the source code, compile PebbleOS and easily install it over Bluetooth on your new Pebble. Textbook definition of open source!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pebble mobile companion app - the app that for your iPhone or Android. Without the app, your Pebble is basically a paperweight. When the Pebble Tech Corp died, the lack of an open source mobile app made it difficult for anyone to continue to use their watches. We had to build an entirely new app (get it here). Today, our app is now 100% open source on Github- ensuring that what happened before cannot happen again. Want to learn more about how we built the new app cross platform using Kotlin Multiplatform? Watch Steve’s presentation at Droidcon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developer tools and Pebble Appstore - this software enables people to build and share their watchapps and watchfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the case of dev tools, just being open source is not enough. They needed to be updated to work on modern computers. Before we made improvements, the state of the art of Pebble app development was using an Ubuntu virtualbox VM with Python2! Over the summer, our incredibly productive intern upgraded all the SDK and dev tools and created a new way to develop Pebble apps in the browser. You should check them out!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then there’s the Pebble Appstore. This is a collection of nearly 15,000 watchfaces and watchapps that you - the Pebble community - developed between 2012 and July 2018. When Fitbit pulled the plug on the original Pebble Appstore, the Rebble Foundation downloaded a copy of all the apps and faces, and set up a new web service to let users of the old Pebble app continue to download and use watchfaces. This was an incredible effort, one that I have used thousands of times and am a happy paying subscriber. But it’s still centralized - if their server disappears, there is no freely available backup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To compensate for that, today we’re launching two new things:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Pebble mobile app will soon (later this week) be able to subscribe to multiple appstore ‘feeds’. This is similar to open source package managers like pip, AUR, APT, etc. Anyone can create a Pebble-compatible appstore feed and users will be able to browse apps from that feed in the Pebble mobile app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve created our own Pebble Appstore feed (appstore-api.repebble.com) and new Developer Dashboard. Our feed (fyi powered by 100% new software) is configured to back up an archive of all apps and faces to Archive.org (backup will gradually complete over the next week). Today, our feed only has a subset of all Pebble watchfaces and apps (thank you aveao for creating Pebble Archive!). Developers - you can upload your existing or new apps right now! We hope that this sets a standard for openness and we encourage all feeds to publish a freely and publicly available archive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Important to note - developers will still be able to charge money for their apps and faces, using Kiezel pay or other services. This change does not preclude them from doing that, in fact it makes it even easier - I could see some developers creating a paid-only feed. As I recently wrote, we're also working on other ways for Pebble developers to earn money by publishing fun, beautiful and creative Pebble apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another important note - some binary blobs and other non-free software components are used today in PebbleOS and the Pebble mobile app (ex: the heart rate sensor on PT2 , Memfault library, and others). Optional non-free web services, like Wispr-flow API speech recognizer, are also used. These non-free software components are not required - you can compile and run Pebble watch software without them. This will always be the case. More non-free software components may appear in our software in the future. The core Pebble watch software stack (everything you need to use your Pebble watch) will always be open source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-production Pebble Time 2. These watches are not final quality! We are still tweaking and tuning everything.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PT2 Schedule Update&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re currently in the middle of Pebble Time 2 design verification test (DVT) phase. After we finish that, we go into production verification test (PVT) and then mass production (MP). So far, things are proceeding according to the schedule update I shared last month but that is extraordinarily subject to change. We still have a lot of testing (especially waterproof and environmental) to go. If we find problems (which is likely) we will push the schedule back to make improvements to the product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The one major complicating factor is the timing of Chinese New Year (CNY). It’s early next year - factories will shut down for 3 weeks starting around the end of January. After restarting, things always take a week or two to get back to full speed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are trying our best to get into mass production and ship out at most several thousand Pebble Time 2s before CNY. It’s going to be very tight 🤞. More likely is that production will begin after CNY, then we need to transfer the watches to our fulfillment center, and ship them out. Realistically, at this time we’re forecasting that the majority of people will receive their PT2 in March and April. Please keep in mind that things may still change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Picking a PT2 colour&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There will be 4 colour options for PT2 - black/black, black/red, silver/blue, silver/(white most likely). Let me be crystal very clear - no one has picked a colour yet 😃. In a few weeks, I will send out an email asking everyone who pre-ordered a Pebble Time 2 to select which colour they would like to receive. Please do not email us asking when this email will be sent out. No one has been invited yet to do this. I will post here after all emails have gone out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a related note, I am extremely happy that we built and shipped Pebble 2 Duo. Not only is it an awesome watch, it was also a phenomenal way for us to exercise our production muscles and ease back into the systematic flow of building and shipping smartwatches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A video is worth a million words - so I encourage you to watch me demo Pebble Time 2 watches I just received this week. Keep in mind these watches are PRE-PRODUCTION which means they parts have imperfect qualities! Subject to change!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The video below opens to the part of the video where I do the demo.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46037626</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:52:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Claude Opus 4.5</title><link>https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-opus-4-5</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5f7d0efe2f9bc06f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Introducing Claude Opus 4.5&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our newest model, Claude Opus 4.5, is available today. It’s intelligent, efficient, and the best model in the world for coding, agents, and computer use. It’s also meaningfully better at everyday tasks like deep research and working with slides and spreadsheets. Opus 4.5 is a step forward in what AI systems can do, and a preview of larger changes to how work gets done.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 is state-of-the-art on tests of real-world software engineering:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opus 4.5 is available today on our apps, our API, and on all three major cloud platforms. If you’re a developer, simply use &lt;code&gt;claude-opus-4-5-20251101&lt;/code&gt; via the Claude API. Pricing is now $5/$25 per million tokens—making Opus-level capabilities accessible to even more users, teams, and enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alongside Opus, we’re releasing updates to the Claude Developer Platform, Claude Code, and our consumer apps. There are new tools for longer-running agents and new ways to use Claude in Excel, Chrome, and on desktop. In the Claude apps, lengthy conversations no longer hit a wall. See our product-focused section below for details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;First impressions&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;As our Anthropic colleagues tested the model before release, we heard remarkably consistent feedback. Testers noted that Claude Opus 4.5 handles ambiguity and reasons about tradeoffs without hand-holding. They told us that, when pointed at a complex, multi-system bug, Opus 4.5 figures out the fix. They said that tasks that were near-impossible for Sonnet 4.5 just a few weeks ago are now within reach. Overall, our testers told us that Opus 4.5 just “gets it.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many of our customers with early access have had similar experiences. Here are some examples of what they told us:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Opus models have always been “the real SOTA” but have been cost prohibitive in the past. Claude Opus 4.5 is now at a price point where it can be your go-to model for most tasks. It’s the clear winner and exhibits the best frontier task planning and tool calling we’ve seen yet.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 delivers high-quality code and excels at powering heavy-duty agentic workflows with GitHub Copilot. Early testing shows it surpasses internal coding benchmarks while cutting token usage in half, and is especially well-suited for tasks like code migration and code refactoring.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 beats Sonnet 4.5 and competition on our internal benchmarks, using fewer tokens to solve the same problems. At scale, that efficiency compounds.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 delivers frontier reasoning within Lovable's chat mode, where users plan and iterate on projects. Its reasoning depth transforms planning—and great planning makes code generation even better.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 excels at long-horizon, autonomous tasks, especially those that require sustained reasoning and multi-step execution. In our evaluations it handled complex workflows with fewer dead-ends. On Terminal Bench it delivered a 15% improvement over Sonnet 4.5, a meaningful gain that becomes especially clear when using Warp’s Planning Mode.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 achieved state-of-the-art results for complex enterprise tasks on our benchmarks, outperforming previous models on multi-step reasoning tasks that combine information retrieval, tool use, and deep analysis.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 delivers measurable gains where it matters most: stronger results on our hardest evaluations and consistent performance through 30-minute autonomous coding sessions.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 represents a breakthrough in self-improving AI agents. For office automation, our agents were able to autonomously refine their own capabilities—achieving peak performance in 4 iterations while other models couldn’t match that quality after 10.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 is a notable improvement over the prior Claude models inside Cursor, with improved pricing and intelligence on difficult coding tasks.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 is yet another example of Anthropic pushing the frontier of general intelligence. It performs exceedingly well across difficult coding tasks, showcasing long-term goal-directed behavior.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 delivered an impressive refactor spanning two codebases and three coordinated agents. It was very thorough, helping develop a robust plan, handling the details and fixing tests. A clear step forward from Sonnet 4.5.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 handles long-horizon coding tasks more efficiently than any model we’ve tested. It achieves higher pass rates on held-out tests while using up to 65% fewer tokens, giving developers real cost control without sacrificing quality.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;We’ve found that Opus 4.5 excels at interpreting what users actually want, producing shareable content on the first try. Combined with its speed, token efficiency, and surprisingly low cost, it’s the first time we’re making Opus available in Notion Agent.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 excels at long-context storytelling, generating 10-15 page chapters with strong organization and consistency. It's unlocked use cases we couldn't reliably deliver before.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 sets a new standard for Excel automation and financial modeling. Accuracy on our internal evals improved 20%, efficiency rose 15%, and complex tasks that once seemed out of reach became achievable.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 is the only model that nails some of our hardest 3D visualizations. Polished design, tasteful UX, and excellent planning &amp;amp; orchestration - all with more efficient token usage. Tasks that took previous models 2 hours now take thirty minutes.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 catches more issues in code reviews without sacrificing precision. For production code review at scale, that reliability matters.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Based on testing with Junie, our coding agent, Claude Opus 4.5 outperforms Sonnet 4.5 across all benchmarks. It requires fewer steps to solve tasks and uses fewer tokens as a result. This indicates that the new model is more precise and follows instructions more effectively — a direction we’re very excited about.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;The effort parameter is brilliant. Claude Opus 4.5 feels dynamic rather than overthinking, and at lower effort delivers the same quality we need while being dramatically more efficient. That control is exactly what our SQL workflows demand.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;We’re seeing 50% to 75% reductions in both tool calling errors and build/lint errors with Claude Opus 4.5. It consistently finishes complex tasks in fewer iterations with more reliable execution.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Claude Opus 4.5 is smooth, with none of the rough edges we've seen from other frontier models. The speed improvements are remarkable.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Evaluating Claude Opus 4.5&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;We give prospective performance engineering candidates a notoriously difficult take-home exam. We also test new models on this exam as an internal benchmark. Within our prescribed 2-hour time limit, Claude Opus 4.5 scored higher than any human candidate ever1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The take-home test is designed to assess technical ability and judgment under time pressure. It doesn’t test for other crucial skills candidates may possess, like collaboration, communication, or the instincts that develop over years. But this result—where an AI model outperforms strong candidates on important technical skills—raises questions about how AI will change engineering as a profession. Our Societal Impacts and Economic Futures research is aimed at understanding these kinds of changes across many fields. We plan to share more results soon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Software engineering isn’t the only area on which Claude Opus 4.5 has improved. Capabilities are higher across the board—Opus 4.5 has better vision, reasoning, and mathematics skills than its predecessors, and it is state-of-the-art in many domains:2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The model’s capabilities outpace some of the benchmarks we use in our tests. A common benchmark for agentic capabilities is τ2-bench, which measures the performance of agents in real-world, multi-turn tasks. In one scenario, models have to act as an airline service agent helping a distressed customer. The benchmark expects models to refuse a modification to a basic economy booking since the airline doesn’t allow changes to that class of tickets. Instead, Opus 4.5 found an insightful (and legitimate) way to solve the problem: upgrade the cabin first, then modify the flights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Let me think about what options I have within my policy:

1. Modify flights - Basic economy cannot be modified. This is clear in the policy.
2. Change cabin - Wait, let me check this option! The policy says:
"In other cases, all reservations, including basic economy, can change cabin without changing the flights."

But he wants to change the flights, not just the cabin. However, what if we:
- Change the cabin first (which IS allowed for basic economy), then
- Change the flights (which is allowed for non-basic economy)

So the strategy could be:
1. Upgrade his cabin from basic economy to economy (or business)
2. Then modify the flights to be 2 days later

This would cost more money, but it’s a legitimate path within the policy!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;The benchmark technically scored this as a failure because Claude’s way of helping the customer was unanticipated. But this kind of creative problem solving is exactly what we’ve heard about from our testers and customers—it’s what makes Claude Opus 4.5 feel like a meaningful step forward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other contexts, finding clever paths around intended constraints could count as reward hacking—where models “game” rules or objectives in unintended ways. Preventing such misalignment is one of the objectives of our safety testing, discussed in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A step forward on safety&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;As we state in our system card, Claude Opus 4.5 is the most robustly aligned model we have released to date and, we suspect, the best-aligned frontier model by any developer. It continues our trend towards safer and more secure models:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our customers often use Claude for critical tasks. They want to be assured that, in the face of malicious attacks by hackers and cybercriminals, Claude has the training and the “street smarts” to avoid trouble. With Opus 4.5, we’ve made substantial progress in robustness against prompt injection attacks, which smuggle in deceptive instructions to fool the model into harmful behavior. Opus 4.5 is harder to trick with prompt injection than any other frontier model in the industry:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find a detailed description of all our capability and safety evaluations in the Claude Opus 4.5 system card.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;New on the Claude Developer Platform&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;As models get smarter, they can solve problems in fewer steps: less backtracking, less redundant exploration, less verbose reasoning. Claude Opus 4.5 uses dramatically fewer tokens than its predecessors to reach similar or better outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But different tasks call for different tradeoffs. Sometimes developers want a model to keep thinking about a problem; sometimes they want something more nimble. With our new effort parameter on the Claude API, you can decide to minimize time and spend or maximize capability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set to a medium effort level, Opus 4.5 matches Sonnet 4.5’s best score on SWE-bench Verified, but uses 76% fewer output tokens. At its highest effort level, Opus 4.5 exceeds Sonnet 4.5 performance by 4.3 percentage points—while using 48% fewer tokens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With effort control, context compaction, and advanced tool use, Claude Opus 4.5 runs longer, does more, and requires less intervention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our context management and memory capabilities can dramatically boost performance on agentic tasks. Opus 4.5 is also very effective at managing a team of subagents, enabling the construction of complex, well-coordinated multi-agent systems. In our testing, the combination of all these techniques boosted Opus 4.5’s performance on a deep research evaluation by almost 15 percentage points4.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re making our Developer Platform more composable over time. We want to give you the building blocks to construct exactly what you need, with full control over efficiency, tool use, and context management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Product updates&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Products like Claude Code show what’s possible when the kinds of upgrades we’ve made to the Claude Developer Platform come together. Claude Code gains two upgrades with Opus 4.5. Plan Mode now builds more precise plans and executes more thoroughly—Claude asks clarifying questions upfront, then builds a user-editable plan.md file before executing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Claude Code is also now available in our desktop app, letting you run multiple local and remote sessions in parallel: perhaps one agent fixes bugs, another researches GitHub, and a third updates docs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For Claude app users, long conversations no longer hit a wall—Claude automatically summarizes earlier context as needed, so you can keep the chat going. Claude for Chrome, which lets Claude handle tasks across your browser tabs, is now available to all Max users. We announced Claude for Excel in October, and as of today we've expanded beta access to all Max, Team, and Enterprise users. Each of these updates takes advantage of Claude Opus 4.5’s market-leading performance in using computers, spreadsheets, and handling long-running tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For Claude and Claude Code users with access to Opus 4.5, we’ve removed Opus-specific caps. For Max and Team Premium users, we’ve increased overall usage limits, meaning you’ll have roughly the same number of Opus tokens as you previously had with Sonnet. We’re updating usage limits to make sure you’re able to use Opus 4.5 for daily work. These limits are specific to Opus 4.5. As future models surpass it, we expect to update limits as needed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Footnotes&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;1: This result was using parallel test-time compute, a method that aggregates multiple “tries” from the model and selects from among them. Without a time limit, the model (used within Claude Code) matched the best-ever human candidate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2: We improved the hosting environment to reduce infrastructure failures. This change improved Gemini 3 to 56.7% and GPT-5.1 to 48.6% from the values reported by their developers, using the Terminus-2 harness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;3: Note that these evaluations were run on an in-progress upgrade to Petri, our open-source, automated evaluation tool. They were run on an earlier snapshot of Claude Opus 4.5. Evaluations of the final production model show a very similar pattern of results when compared to other Claude models, and are described in detail in the Claude Opus 4.5 system card.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;4: A fetch-enabled version of BrowseComp-Plus. Specifically, the improvement was from 70.48% without using the combination of techniques to 85.30% using it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Methodology&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All evals were run with a 64K thinking budget, interleaved scratchpads, 200K context window, default effort (high), default sampling settings (temperature, top_p), and averaged over 5 independent trials. Exceptions: SWE-bench Verified (no thinking budget) and Terminal Bench (128K thinking budget). Please see the Claude Opus 4.5 system card for full details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Related content&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Claude now available in Microsoft Foundry and Microsoft 365 Copilot&lt;/head&gt;Read more&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Microsoft, NVIDIA, and Anthropic announce strategic partnerships&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microsoft, NVIDIA and Anthropic announced new strategic partnerships. Anthropic is scaling its rapidly-growing Claude AI model on Microsoft Azure, powered by NVIDIA, which will broaden access to Claude and provide Azure enterprise customers with expanded model choice and new capabilities. Anthropic has committed to purchase $30 billion of Azure compute capacity and to contract additional compute capacity up to one gigawatt.&lt;/p&gt;Read more&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46037637</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:53:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Claude Advanced Tool Use</title><link>https://www.anthropic.com/engineering/advanced-tool-use</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b34d76d332b7ca8a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The future of AI agents is one where models work seamlessly across hundreds or thousands of tools. An IDE assistant that integrates git operations, file manipulation, package managers, testing frameworks, and deployment pipelines. An operations coordinator that connects Slack, GitHub, Google Drive, Jira, company databases, and dozens of MCP servers simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To build effective agents, they need to work with unlimited tool libraries without stuffing every definition into context upfront. Our blog article on using code execution with MCP discussed how tool results and definitions can sometimes consume 50,000+ tokens before an agent reads a request. Agents should discover and load tools on-demand, keeping only what's relevant for the current task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Agents also need the ability to call tools from code. When using natural language tool calling, each invocation requires a full inference pass, and intermediate results pile up in context whether they're useful or not. Code is a natural fit for orchestration logic, such as loops, conditionals, and data transformations. Agents need the flexibility to choose between code execution and inference based on the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Agents also need to learn correct tool usage from examples, not just schema definitions. JSON schemas define what's structurally valid, but can't express usage patterns: when to include optional parameters, which combinations make sense, or what conventions your API expects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we're releasing three features that make this possible:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tool Search Tool, which allows Claude to use search tools to access thousands of tools without consuming its context window&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Programmatic Tool Calling, which allows Claude to invoke tools in a code execution environment reducing the impact on the model’s context window&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tool Use Examples, which provides a universal standard for demonstrating how to effectively use a given tool&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In internal testing, we’ve found these features have helped us build things that wouldn’t have been possible with conventional tool use patterns. For example, Claude for Excel uses Programmatic Tool Calling to read and modify spreadsheets with thousands of rows without overloading the model’s context window.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on our experience, we believe these features open up new possibilities for what you can build with Claude.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tool Search Tool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The challenge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MCP tool definitions provide important context, but as more servers connect, those tokens can add up. Consider a five-server setup:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub: 35 tools (~26K tokens)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Slack: 11 tools (~21K tokens)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sentry: 5 tools (~3K tokens)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Grafana: 5 tools (~3K tokens)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Splunk: 2 tools (~2K tokens)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's 58 tools consuming approximately 55K tokens before the conversation even starts. Add more servers like Jira (which alone uses ~17K tokens) and you're quickly approaching 100K+ token overhead. At Anthropic, we've seen tool definitions consume 134K tokens before optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But token cost isn't the only issue. The most common failures are wrong tool selection and incorrect parameters, especially when tools have similar names like &lt;code&gt;notification-send-user&lt;/code&gt; vs. &lt;code&gt;notification-send-channel&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Our solution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of loading all tool definitions upfront, the Tool Search Tool discovers tools on-demand. Claude only sees the tools it actually needs for the current task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traditional approach:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All tool definitions loaded upfront (~72K tokens for 50+ MCP tools)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Conversation history and system prompt compete for remaining space&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Total context consumption: ~77K tokens before any work begins&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the Tool Search Tool:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Only the Tool Search Tool loaded upfront (~500 tokens)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tools discovered on-demand as needed (3-5 relevant tools, ~3K tokens)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Total context consumption: ~8.7K tokens, preserving 95% of context window&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This represents an 85% reduction in token usage while maintaining access to your full tool library. Internal testing showed significant accuracy improvements on MCP evaluations when working with large tool libraries. Opus 4 improved from 49% to 74%, and Opus 4.5 improved from 79.5% to 88.1% with Tool Search Tool enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How the Tool Search Tool works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Tool Search Tool lets Claude dynamically discover tools instead of loading all definitions upfront. You provide all your tool definitions to the API, but mark tools with &lt;code&gt;defer_loading: true&lt;/code&gt; to make them discoverable on-demand. Deferred tools aren't loaded into Claude's context initially. Claude only sees the Tool Search Tool itself plus any tools with &lt;code&gt;defer_loading: false&lt;/code&gt; (your most critical, frequently-used tools).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Claude needs specific capabilities, it searches for relevant tools. The Tool Search Tool returns references to matching tools, which get expanded into full definitions in Claude's context.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, if Claude needs to interact with GitHub, it searches for "github," and only &lt;code&gt;github.createPullRequest&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;github.listIssues&lt;/code&gt; get loaded—not your other 50+ tools from Slack, Jira, and Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This way, Claude has access to your full tool library while only paying the token cost for tools it actually needs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prompt caching note: Tool Search Tool doesn't break prompt caching because deferred tools are excluded from the initial prompt entirely. They're only added to context after Claude searches for them, so your system prompt and core tool definitions remain cacheable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Implementation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "tools": [
    // Include a tool search tool (regex, BM25, or custom)
    {"type": "tool_search_tool_regex_20251119", "name": "tool_search_tool_regex"},

    // Mark tools for on-demand discovery
    {
      "name": "github.createPullRequest",
      "description": "Create a pull request",
      "input_schema": {...},
      "defer_loading": true
    }
    // ... hundreds more deferred tools with defer_loading: true
  ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For MCP servers, you can defer loading entire servers while keeping specific high-use tools loaded:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "type": "mcp_toolset",
  "mcp_server_name": "google-drive",
  "default_config": {"defer_loading": true}, # defer loading the entire server
  "configs": {
    "search_files": {
"defer_loading": false
    }  // Keep most used tool loaded
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Claude Developer Platform provides regex-based and BM25-based search tools out of the box, but you can also implement custom search tools using embeddings or other strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;When to use the Tool Search Tool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like any architectural decision, enabling the Tool Search Tool involves trade-offs. The feature adds a search step before tool invocation, so it delivers the best ROI when the context savings and accuracy improvements outweigh additional latency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use it when:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tool definitions consuming &amp;gt;10K tokens&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Experiencing tool selection accuracy issues&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Building MCP-powered systems with multiple servers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;10+ tools available&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Less beneficial when:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Small tool library (&amp;lt;10 tools)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All tools used frequently in every session&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tool definitions are compact&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Programmatic Tool Calling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The challenge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traditional tool calling creates two fundamental problems as workflows become more complex:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Context pollution from intermediate results: When Claude analyzes a 10MB log file for error patterns, the entire file enters its context window, even though Claude only needs a summary of error frequencies. When fetching customer data across multiple tables, every record accumulates in context regardless of relevance. These intermediate results consume massive token budgets and can push important information out of the context window entirely.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inference overhead and manual synthesis: Each tool call requires a full model inference pass. After receiving results, Claude must "eyeball" the data to extract relevant information, reason about how pieces fit together, and decide what to do next—all through natural language processing. A five tool workflow means five inference passes plus Claude parsing each result, comparing values, and synthesizing conclusions. This is both slow and error-prone.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Our solution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programmatic Tool Calling enables Claude to orchestrate tools through code rather than through individual API round-trips. Instead of Claude requesting tools one at a time with each result being returned to its context, Claude writes code that calls multiple tools, processes their outputs, and controls what information actually enters its context window.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude excels at writing code and by letting it express orchestration logic in Python rather than through natural language tool invocations, you get more reliable, precise control flow. Loops, conditionals, data transformations, and error handling are all explicit in code rather than implicit in Claude's reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Example: Budget compliance check&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider a common business task: "Which team members exceeded their Q3 travel budget?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have three tools available:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;get_team_members(department)&lt;/code&gt;- Returns team member list with IDs and levels&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;get_expenses(user_id, quarter)&lt;/code&gt;- Returns expense line items for a user&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;get_budget_by_level(level)&lt;/code&gt;- Returns budget limits for an employee level&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traditional approach:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fetch team members → 20 people&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For each person, fetch their Q3 expenses → 20 tool calls, each returning 50-100 line items (flights, hotels, meals, receipts)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fetch budget limits by employee level&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All of this enters Claude's context: 2,000+ expense line items (50 KB+)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Claude manually sums each person's expenses, looks up their budget, compares expenses against budget limits&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;More round-trips to the model, significant context consumption&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Programmatic Tool Calling:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of each tool result returning to Claude, Claude writes a Python script that orchestrates the entire workflow. The script runs in the Code Execution tool (a sandboxed environment), pausing when it needs results from your tools. When you return tool results via the API, they're processed by the script rather than consumed by the model. The script continues executing, and Claude only sees the final output.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's what Claude's orchestration code looks like for the budget compliance task:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;team = await get_team_members("engineering")

# Fetch budgets for each unique level
levels = list(set(m["level"] for m in team))
budget_results = await asyncio.gather(*[
    get_budget_by_level(level) for level in levels
])

# Create a lookup dictionary: {"junior": budget1, "senior": budget2, ...}
budgets = {level: budget for level, budget in zip(levels, budget_results)}

# Fetch all expenses in parallel
expenses = await asyncio.gather(*[
    get_expenses(m["id"], "Q3") for m in team
])

# Find employees who exceeded their travel budget
exceeded = []
for member, exp in zip(team, expenses):
    budget = budgets[member["level"]]
    total = sum(e["amount"] for e in exp)
    if total &amp;gt; budget["travel_limit"]:
        exceeded.append({
            "name": member["name"],
            "spent": total,
            "limit": budget["travel_limit"]
        })

print(json.dumps(exceeded))&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude's context receives only the final result: the two to three people who exceeded their budget. The 2,000+ line items, the intermediate sums, and the budget lookups do not affect Claude’s context, reducing consumption from 200KB of raw expense data to just 1KB of results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The efficiency gains are substantial:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Token savings: By keeping intermediate results out of Claude's context, PTC dramatically reduces token consumption. Average usage dropped from 43,588 to 27,297 tokens, a 37% reduction on complex research tasks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reduced latency: Each API round-trip requires model inference (hundreds of milliseconds to seconds). When Claude orchestrates 20+ tool calls in a single code block, you eliminate 19+ inference passes. The API handles tool execution without returning to the model each time.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Improved accuracy: By writing explicit orchestration logic, Claude makes fewer errors than when juggling multiple tool results in natural language. Internal knowledge retrieval improved from 25.6% to 28.5%; GIA benchmarks from 46.5% to 51.2%.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Production workflows involve messy data, conditional logic, and operations that need to scale. Programmatic Tool Calling lets Claude handle that complexity programmatically while keeping its focus on actionable results rather than raw data processing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How Programmatic Tool Calling works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;1. Mark tools as callable from code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add code_execution to tools, and set allowed_callers to opt-in tools for programmatic execution:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "tools": [
    {
      "type": "code_execution_20250825",
      "name": "code_execution"
    },
    {
      "name": "get_team_members",
      "description": "Get all members of a department...",
      "input_schema": {...},
      "allowed_callers": ["code_execution_20250825"] # opt-in to programmatic tool calling
    },
    {
      "name": "get_expenses",
 	...
    },
    {
      "name": "get_budget_by_level",
	...
    }
  ]
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The API converts these tool definitions into Python functions that Claude can call.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;2. Claude writes orchestration code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of requesting tools one at a time, Claude generates Python code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "type": "server_tool_use",
  "id": "srvtoolu_abc",
  "name": "code_execution",
  "input": {
    "code": "team = get_team_members('engineering')\n..." # the code example above
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;3. Tools execute without hitting Claude's context&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the code calls get_expenses(), you receive a tool request with a caller field:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "type": "tool_use",
  "id": "toolu_xyz",
  "name": "get_expenses",
  "input": {"user_id": "emp_123", "quarter": "Q3"},
  "caller": {
    "type": "code_execution_20250825",
    "tool_id": "srvtoolu_abc"
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You provide the result, which is processed in the Code Execution environment rather than Claude's context. This request-response cycle repeats for each tool call in the code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;4. Only final output enters context&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the code finishes running, only the results of the code are returned to Claude:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "type": "code_execution_tool_result",
  "tool_use_id": "srvtoolu_abc",
  "content": {
    "stdout": "[{\"name\": \"Alice\", \"spent\": 12500, \"limit\": 10000}...]"
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is all Claude sees, not the 2000+ expense line items processed along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;When to use Programmatic Tool Calling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programmatic Tool Calling adds a code execution step to your workflow. This extra overhead pays off when the token savings, latency improvements, and accuracy gains are substantial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most beneficial when:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Processing large datasets where you only need aggregates or summaries&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Running multi-step workflows with three or more dependent tool calls&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Filtering, sorting, or transforming tool results before Claude sees them&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Handling tasks where intermediate data shouldn't influence Claude's reasoning&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Running parallel operations across many items (checking 50 endpoints, for example)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Less beneficial when:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Making simple single-tool invocations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Working on tasks where Claude should see and reason about all intermediate results&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Running quick lookups with small responses&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tool Use Examples&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The challenge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JSON Schema excels at defining structure–types, required fields, allowed enums–but it can't express usage patterns: when to include optional parameters, which combinations make sense, or what conventions your API expects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider a support ticket API:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "name": "create_ticket",
  "input_schema": {
    "properties": {
      "title": {"type": "string"},
      "priority": {"enum": ["low", "medium", "high", "critical"]},
      "labels": {"type": "array", "items": {"type": "string"}},
      "reporter": {
        "type": "object",
        "properties": {
          "id": {"type": "string"},
          "name": {"type": "string"},
          "contact": {
            "type": "object",
            "properties": {
              "email": {"type": "string"},
              "phone": {"type": "string"}
            }
          }
        }
      },
      "due_date": {"type": "string"},
      "escalation": {
        "type": "object",
        "properties": {
          "level": {"type": "integer"},
          "notify_manager": {"type": "boolean"},
          "sla_hours": {"type": "integer"}
        }
      }
    },
    "required": ["title"]
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The schema defines what's valid, but leaves critical questions unanswered:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Format ambiguity: Should &lt;code&gt;due_date&lt;/code&gt;use "2024-11-06", "Nov 6, 2024", or "2024-11-06T00:00:00Z"?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ID conventions: Is &lt;code&gt;reporter.id&lt;/code&gt;a UUID, "USR-12345", or just "12345"?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Nested structure usage: When should Claude populate &lt;code&gt;reporter.contact&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Parameter correlations: How do &lt;code&gt;escalation.level&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;escalation.sla_hours&lt;/code&gt;relate to priority?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These ambiguities can lead to malformed tool calls and inconsistent parameter usage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Our solution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tool Use Examples let you provide sample tool calls directly in your tool definitions. Instead of relying on schema alone, you show Claude concrete usage patterns:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
    "name": "create_ticket",
    "input_schema": { /* same schema as above */ },
    "input_examples": [
      {
        "title": "Login page returns 500 error",
        "priority": "critical",
        "labels": ["bug", "authentication", "production"],
        "reporter": {
          "id": "USR-12345",
          "name": "Jane Smith",
          "contact": {
            "email": "jane@acme.com",
            "phone": "+1-555-0123"
          }
        },
        "due_date": "2024-11-06",
        "escalation": {
          "level": 2,
          "notify_manager": true,
          "sla_hours": 4
        }
      },
      {
        "title": "Add dark mode support",
        "labels": ["feature-request", "ui"],
        "reporter": {
          "id": "USR-67890",
          "name": "Alex Chen"
        }
      },
      {
        "title": "Update API documentation"
      }
    ]
  }&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From these three examples, Claude learns:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Format conventions: Dates use YYYY-MM-DD, user IDs follow USR-XXXXX, labels use kebab-case&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Nested structure patterns: How to construct the reporter object with its nested contact object&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Optional parameter correlations: Critical bugs have full contact info + escalation with tight SLAs; feature requests have reporter but no contact/escalation; internal tasks have title only&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In our own internal testing, tool use examples improved accuracy from 72% to 90% on complex parameter handling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;When to use Tool Use Examples&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tool Use Examples add tokens to your tool definitions, so they’re most valuable when accuracy improvements outweigh the additional cost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most beneficial when:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Complex nested structures where valid JSON doesn't imply correct usage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tools with many optional parameters and inclusion patterns matter&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;APIs with domain-specific conventions not captured in schemas&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Similar tools where examples clarify which one to use (e.g., &lt;code&gt;create_ticket&lt;/code&gt;vs&lt;code&gt;create_incident&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Less beneficial when:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Simple single-parameter tools with obvious usage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Standard formats like URLs or emails that Claude already understands&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Validation concerns better handled by JSON Schema constraints&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Best practices&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building agents that take real-world actions means handling scale, complexity, and precision simultaneously. These three features work together to solve different bottlenecks in tool use workflows. Here's how to combine them effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Layer features strategically&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not every agent needs to use all three features for a given task. Start with your biggest bottleneck:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Context bloat from tool definitions → Tool Search Tool&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Large intermediate results polluting context → Programmatic Tool Calling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Parameter errors and malformed calls → Tool Use Examples&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This focused approach lets you address the specific constraint limiting your agent's performance, rather than adding complexity upfront.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then layer additional features as needed. They're complementary: Tool Search Tool ensures the right tools are found, Programmatic Tool Calling ensures efficient execution, and Tool Use Examples ensure correct invocation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Set up Tool Search Tool for better discovery&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tool search matches against names and descriptions, so clear, descriptive definitions improve discovery accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Good
{
    "name": "search_customer_orders",
    "description": "Search for customer orders by date range, status, or total amount. Returns order details including items, shipping, and payment info."
}

// Bad
{
    "name": "query_db_orders",
    "description": "Execute order query"
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add system prompt guidance so Claude knows what's available:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;You have access to tools for Slack messaging, Google Drive file management, 
Jira ticket tracking, and GitHub repository operations. Use the tool search 
to find specific capabilities.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep your three to five most-used tools always loaded, defer the rest. This balances immediate access for common operations with on-demand discovery for everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Set up Programmatic Tool Calling for correct execution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since Claude writes code to parse tool outputs, document return formats clearly. This helps Claude write correct parsing logic:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
    "name": "get_orders",
    "description": "Retrieve orders for a customer.
Returns:
    List of order objects, each containing:
    - id (str): Order identifier
    - total (float): Order total in USD
    - status (str): One of 'pending', 'shipped', 'delivered'
    - items (list): Array of {sku, quantity, price}
    - created_at (str): ISO 8601 timestamp"
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See below for opt-in tools that benefit from programmatic orchestration:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tools that can run in parallel (independent operations)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Operations safe to retry (idempotent)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Set up Tool Use Examples for parameter accuracy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Craft examples for behavioral clarity:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use realistic data (real city names, plausible prices, not "string" or "value")&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Show variety with minimal, partial, and full specification patterns&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Keep it concise: 1-5 examples per tool&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Focus on ambiguity (only add examples where correct usage isn't obvious from schema)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Getting started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These features are available in beta. To enable them, add the beta header and include the tools you need:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;client.beta.messages.create(
    betas=["advanced-tool-use-2025-11-20"],
    model="claude-sonnet-4-5-20250929",
    max_tokens=4096,
    tools=[
        {"type": "tool_search_tool_regex_20251119", "name": "tool_search_tool_regex"},
        {"type": "code_execution_20250825", "name": "code_execution"},
        # Your tools with defer_loading, allowed_callers, and input_examples
    ]
)&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For detailed API documentation and SDK examples, see our:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Documentation and cookbook for Tool Search Tool&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Documentation and cookbook for Programmatic Tool Calling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Documentation for Tool Use Examples&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These features move tool use from simple function calling toward intelligent orchestration. As agents tackle more complex workflows spanning dozens of tools and large datasets, dynamic discovery, efficient execution, and reliable invocation become foundational.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're excited to see what you build.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Written by Bin Wu, with contributions from Adam Jones, Artur Renault, Henry Tay, Jake Noble, Nathan McCandlish, Noah Picard, Sam Jiang, and the Claude Developer Platform team. This work builds on foundational research by Chris Gorgolewski, Daniel Jiang, Jeremy Fox and Mike Lambert. We also drew inspiration from across the AI ecosystem, including Joel Pobar's LLMVM, Cloudflare's Code Mode and Code Execution as MCP. Special thanks to Andy Schumeister, Hamish Kerr, Keir Bradwell, Matt Bleifer and Molly Vorwerck for their support.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46038047</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 19:21:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Unpowered SSDs slowly lose data</title><link>https://www.xda-developers.com/your-unpowered-ssd-is-slowly-losing-your-data/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3653bc3789b28fb8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SSDs have all but replaced hard drives when it comes to primary storage. They're orders of magnitude faster, more convenient, and consume less power than mechanical hard drives. That said, if you're also using SSDs for cold storage, expecting the drives lying in your drawer to work perfectly after years, you might want to rethink your strategy. Your reliable SSD could suffer from corrupted or lost data if left unpowered for extended periods. This is why many users don't consider SSDs a reliable long-term storage medium, and prefer using hard drives, magnetic tape, or M-Disc instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Your SSD data isn't as permanent as you think&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Non-volatile with an asterisk&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike hard drives that magnetize spinning discs to store data, SSDs modify the electrical charge in NAND flash cells to represent 0 and 1. NAND flash retains data in underlying transistors even when power is removed, similar to other forms of non-volatile memory. However, the duration for which your SSD can retain data without power is the key here. Even the cheapest SSDs, say those with QLC NAND, can safely store data for about a year of being completely unpowered. More expensive TLC NAND can retain data for up to 3 years, while MLC and SLC NAND are good for 5 years and 10 years of unpowered storage, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem is that most consumer SSDs use only TLC or QLC NAND, so users who leave their SSDs unpowered for over a year are risking the integrity of their data. The reliability of QLC NAND has improved over the years, so you should probably consider 2–3 years of unpowered usage as the guardrails. Without power, the voltage stored in the NAND cells can be lost, either resulting in missing data or completely useless drives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This data retention deficiency of consumer SSDs makes them an unreliable medium for long-term data storage, especially for creative professionals and researchers. HDDs can suffer from bit rot, too, due to wear and tear, but they're still more resistant to power loss. If you haven't checked your archives in a while, I'd recommend doing so at the earliest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;But, most people don't need to worry about it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Archival storage isn't that common&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scenario I described above isn't relevant to people outside enterprise, enthusiast, and solopreneur usage. The need to store tons of data for years on drives that aren't plugged in isn't a concern for most people, who use one or two SSDs on their PC that might be left without power for only a few months, at the maximum. You've probably lost data on your SSD due to a rare power surge or a faulty drive rather than voltage loss. Some factors, like temperature and the quality of the underlying NAND flash, can accelerate this voltage loss.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SSDs aren't eternal, even if you keep them powered on forever. The limited write cycles of NAND flash will eventually bring an SSD to the end of its lifecycle, but the majority of users will probably replace the drive before that ever happens. So, you don't need to worry about writing too much data to your SSD or leaving your PC turned off for days, weeks, or even months. Just don't trust an unpowered SSD that's gathering dust in the house for years, which brings me to my next point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;You should always have a backup anyway&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Prevention is better than cure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Backing up your data is the simplest strategy to counteract the limitations of storage media. Having multiple copies of your data on different types of storage ensures that any unexpected incidents protect your data from vanishing forever. This is exactly what the 3-2-1 backup rule talks about: 3 copies of data on at least 2 different storage media, with 1 copy stored off-site. For most people, this condition can easily be fulfilled by using their primary computer, a NAS, and cloud storage. Redundancy is the underlying principle that safeguards your data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whether it's the limited lifespan of your SSD, the potential for harmful exigencies like power failure, or the limits of data retention on flash storage, your backup will ensure your peace of mind. Yes, SSDs aren't the best choice for cold storage, but even if you're using hard drives, having a single copy of your data is asking for trouble. Every user will come face-to-face with drive failure sooner or later, so investing in a robust backup system isn't really optional if you care about your data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Store it and forget it doesn't work for SSDs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As long as you're using consumer SSDs for primary storage on your PC, it's all well and good. You'll most likely replace your drive long before exhausting its P/E cycles. For long-term storage, however, relying on SSDs is risky, since they can lose data if left without power for years. This data loss can occur anytime from 1 to 3 years of keeping your SSDs unpowered, so using alternate storage media and investing in a backup system should be your priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46038099</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 19:25:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PS5 now costs less than 64GB of DDR5 memory. RAM jumps to $600 due to shortage</title><link>https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/ddr5/64gb-of-ddr5-memory-now-costs-more-than-an-entire-ps5-even-after-a-discount-trident-z5-neo-kit-jumps-to-usd600-due-to-dram-shortage-and-its-expected-to-get-worse-into-2026</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="536a48fd8eb6f785"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;An entire PS5 now costs less than 64GB of DDR5 memory, even after a discount — simple memory kit jumps to $600 due to DRAM shortage, and it's expected to get worse into 2026&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to the AI boom devouring the majority of the world's memory and storage supply, end-consumers are now facing increasingly inflated prices for common components. DDR5 RAM, a necessity for building current-gen Intel or AMD systems, has now reached record highs in terms of pricing; a 64 GB kit of G.Skill's Trident Z5 Neo 6000 MT/s RAM is listed at $599.99 on Newegg right now — that's $200 more than a PS5 Slim or a Microsoft Xbox Series S, and just $50 shy off an entire PS5 Pro at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;G.SKILL Trident Z5 Neo RGB Series 64GB DDR5 6000 (PC5 48000)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;($599 in Black Friday sale, with $40 off and additional $20 off via code BFE2458)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Row 1 - Cell 2&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Row 2 - Cell 2&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Row 3 - Cell 2&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Row 4 - Cell 2&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Row 5 - Cell 2&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That $600 price tag has a 6% discount already applied to its original $640 ask, as part of a Black Friday deal. For context, a more exclusive 64 GB limited edition Corsair Dominator Titanium kit cost only $349 when we reviewed it a few months ago. Earlier this year, we posted about DDR5 deals on Prime Day where the standard edition of the same kit was just $299, and you could get other comparable 64 GB kits for as low as $140.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A quick glance at price tracking data, and G.Skill's Trident Z5 Neo kit has regularly sat at $205-$220 for the past few months, and it was only in late October that it started to pick up steam. From September 20th when it was listed at $220, to $640 now. In just 2 months we've witnessed an astounding ~190% surge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right as this particular Trident Z5 Neo kit began to skyrocket in price was when the industry first started to pick up on the affects of the AI crunch. A few days later we published our initial coverage on DDR5 RAM price hikes; from there, the situation has only worsened to reach worrying levels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Insane mark-up aside, the kit itself is one of the best on the market, recommend as the top pick for DDR5 memory in our roundup. Unfortunately, it seems like high prices are going to be the story going forward. The surge in demand for AI projects will see production lines will prioritizing serving AI clients, leaving consumers to pay through the nose or make the best of what they have. Experts speculate that both DRAM and NAND constraints will become normal throughout 2026 as Big Tech looks to pursue AGI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the meantime, hard drives are vanishing from store shelves to the point where microSD cards are serving as a feasible replacement for them. Large-capacity nearline HDDs are backordered for 2 years, as a result of which QLC SSDs are now being swept up at alarming rates. Many distributors are even selling memory and motherboards bundled together to combat the global shortage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even Valve's upcoming Steam Machine will end up costing more than expected due to the production window of the device aligning with the DRAM crisis. That being said, memory has almost always lived in a rollercoaster cycle, with manufacturers oversupplying for a couple of years, then undersupplying for the next few. Looking at it optimistically, you're probably going to find DDR5 at bargain prices again in 2027.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get Tom's Hardware's best news and in-depth reviews, straight to your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow Tom's Hardware on Google News, or add us as a preferred source, to get our latest news, analysis, &amp;amp; reviews in your feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hassam Nasir is a die-hard hardware enthusiast with years of experience as a tech editor and writer, focusing on detailed CPU comparisons and general hardware news. When he’s not working, you’ll find him bending tubes for his ever-evolving custom water-loop gaming rig or benchmarking the latest CPUs and GPUs just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;vanadiel007&lt;/header&gt;Initially I did not believe this, but then I went looking and wow. Memory kit I got a month ago is now 300% more!Reply&lt;lb/&gt;I guess this is how AI is generating money: increasing the prices of electronics.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;kerberos_20&lt;/header&gt;mkay, so we are looking now on high end sideReply&lt;lb/&gt;why not brag abot 128GB sticks at only 1.5k price point?&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.corsair.com/us/en/p/memory/CMH128GX5M2B6400C42/vengeance-rgb-128gb-2x64gb-ddr5-dram-6400mts-cl42-intel-xmp-memory-kit-cmh128gx5m2b6400c42&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;thestryker&lt;/header&gt;Reply&lt;quote/&gt;First of all those are 64GB modules and secondly that kit debuted in June at less than $400.kerberos_20 said:mkay, so we are looking now on high end side&lt;lb/&gt;why not brag abot 128GB sticks at only 1.5k price point?&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.corsair.com/us/en/p/memory/CMH128GX5M2B6400C42/vengeance-rgb-128gb-2x64gb-ddr5-dram-6400mts-cl42-intel-xmp-memory-kit-cmh128gx5m2b6400c42&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;yahrightthere&lt;/header&gt;Want prices to come down, stop buying it, just say no, that includes consumer and enterprise.Reply&lt;lb/&gt;See who blinks first.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;mikethepoor&lt;/header&gt;Reply&lt;quote/&gt;That's honestly what manufacturers want, is for consumers to stop buying so they can focus on the much more lucrative enterprise market. Same thing happened to GPUs.yahrightthere said:Want prices to come down, stop buying it, just say no, that includes consumer and enterprise.&lt;lb/&gt;See who blinks first.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;yahrightthere&lt;/header&gt;Reply&lt;quote/&gt;I did include enterprise, they are part of the equation.mikethepoor said:That's honestly what manufacturers want, is for consumers to stop buying so they can focus on the much more lucrative enterprise market. Same thing happened to GPUs.&lt;lb/&gt;If they don't, talking for myself, I don't need their over valued high priced tech items in my life.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;thestryker&lt;/header&gt;Reply&lt;quote/&gt;Generally speaking enterprise can't just stop buying, and here they're the driver of the current costs to begin with. They need it to make more money so the increased costs are part of doing business as long as that money they're making is higher.yahrightthere said:I did include enterprise, they are part of the equation.&lt;lb/&gt;If they don't, talking for myself, I don't need their over valued high priced tech items in my life.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;teeejay94&lt;/header&gt;Picked a Corsair Vengeance DDR5 48GB 7000 kit on ebay for $300 Canadian just a month or so now ago, just ordered a new 1300W Lian Li PSU on Friday and still waiting for the darn thing. That's what I get for paying the extra shipping $$ lolReply&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;g-unit1111&lt;/header&gt;Replyvanadiel007 said:Initially I did not believe this, but then I went looking and wow. Memory kit I got a month ago is now 300% more!&lt;lb/&gt;I guess this is how AI is generating money: increasing the prices of electronics.&lt;lb/&gt;The 32GB of G.Skill DDR5-6400 that I got last year is now close to $350. That is insane.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46038143</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 19:29:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why I (Still) Love Linux ?</title><link>https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/11/24/why-i-still-love-linux/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7f09913091afa7ec"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know, this title might come as a surprise to many. Or perhaps, for those who truly know me, it wonât. I am not a fanboy. The BSDs and the illumos distributions generally follow an approach to design and development that aligns more closely with the way I think, not to mention the wonderful communities around them, but that does not mean I do not use and appreciate other solutions. I usually publish articles about how much I love the BSDs or illumos distributions, but today I want to talk about Linux (or, better, GNU/Linux) and why, despite everything, it still holds a place in my heart. This will be the first in a series of articles where Iâll discuss other operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Where It All Began&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started right here, with GNU/Linux, back in 1996. It was my first real prompt after the Commodore 64 and DOS. It was my first step toward Unix systems, and it was love at first shell. I felt a sense of freedom - a freedom that the operating systems I had known up to that point (few, to be honest) had never given me. It was like a âblank sheetâ (or rather, a black one) with a prompt on it. I understood immediately that this prompt, thanks to command chaining, pipes, and all the marvels of Unix and Unix-like systems, would allow me to do anything. And that sense of freedom is what makes me love Unix systems to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was young, but my intuition was correct. And even though I couldn't afford to keep a full Linux installation on that computer long-term due to hardware limitations, I realized that this would be my future. A year later, a new computer arrived, allowing me to use Linux daily, for everything. And successfully, without missing Windows at all (except for a small partition, strictly for gaming).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I arrived at university, in 1998, I was one of the few who knew it. One of the few who appreciated it. One of the few who hoped to see a flourishing future for it. Everywhere. Widespread. A dream come true. I was a speaker at Linux Days, I actively participated in translation projects, and I wrote articles for Italian magazines. I was a purist regarding the "GNU/Linux" nomenclature because I felt it was wrong to ignore the GNU part - it was fundamental. Because perhaps the "Year of the Linux Desktop" never arrived, but Linux is now everywhere. On my desktop, without a doubt. But also on my smartphone (Android) and on those of hundreds of millions of people. Just as it is in my car. And in countless devices surrounding us - even if we donât know it. And this is the true success. Letâs not focus too much on the complaint that "itâs not compatible with my device X". It is your device that is not compatible with Linux, not the other way around. Just like when, many years ago, people complained that their WinModems (modems that offloaded all processing to obscure, closed-source Windows drivers) didn't work on Linux. For "early adopters" like me, this concept has always been present, even though, fortunately, things have improved exponentially.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linux was what companies accepted most willingly (not totally, but still...): the ongoing lawsuits against the BSDs hampered their spread, and Linux seemed like that "breath of fresh air" the world needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linux and its distributions (especially those untethered from corporations, like Debian, Gentoo, Arch, etc.) allowed us to replicate expensive "commercial" setups at a fraction of the cost. Reliability was good, updating was simple, and there was a certain consistency. Not as marked as that of the BSDs, but sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The world was ready to accept it, albeit reluctantly. Linus Torvalds, despite his sometimes harsh and undiplomatic tone, carried forward the kernel development with continuity and coherence, making difficult decisions but always in line with the project. The "move fast and break things" model was almost necessary because there was still so much to build. I also remember the era when Linux - speaking of the kernel - was designed almost exclusively for x86. The other architectures, to simplify, worked thanks to a series of adaptations that brought most behavior back to what was expected for x86.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the distributions, especially the more "arduous" ones to install, taught me a lot. The distro-hopping of the early 2000s made me truly understand partitioning, the boot procedure (Lilo first, then Grub, etc.), and for this, I must mainly thank Gentoo and Arch (and the FreeBSD handbook - but this is for another article). I learned the importance of backups the hard way, and I keep this lesson well in mind today. My Linux desktops ran mainly with Debian (initially), then Gentoo, Arch, and openSUSE (which, at the time, was still called "SUSE Linux"), Manjaro, etc. My old 486sx 25Mhz with 4MB (yes, MB) of RAM, powered by Debian, allowed me to download emails (mutt and fetchmail), news (inn + suck), program in C, and create shell scripts - at the end of the 90s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;When Linux Conquered the World&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then the first Ubuntu was launched, and many things changed. I don't know if it was thanks to Ubuntu or simply because the time was ripe, but attention shifted to Linux on the desktop as well (albeit mainly on the computers of us enthusiasts), and many companies began to contribute actively to the system or distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am not against the participation of large companies in Open Source. Their contributions can be valuable for the development of Open Source itself, and if companies make money from it, good for them. If this ultimately leads to a more complete and valid Open Source product, then I welcome it! It is precisely thanks to mass adoption that Linux cleared the path for the acceptance of Open Source at all levels. I still remember when, just after graduating, I was told that Linux (and Open Source systems like the BSDs) were "toys for universities". I dare anyone to say that today!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this must be done correctly: without spoiling the original idea of the project and without hijacking (voluntarily or not) development toward a different model. Toward a different evolution. The use of Open Source must not become a vehicle for a business model that tends to close, trap, or cage the user. Or harm anyone. And if it is oriented toward worsening the product solely for one's own gain, I can only be against it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Changed Along the Way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And this is where, unfortunately, I believe things have changed in the Linux world (if not in the kernel itself, at least in many distributions). Innovation used to be disruptive out of necessity. Today, in many cases, disruption happens without purpose, and stability is often sacrificed for changes that do not solve real problems. Sometimes, in the name of improved security or stability, a new, immature, and unstable product is created - effectively worsening the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To give an example, I am not against systemd on principle, but I consider it a tool distant from the original Unix principles - do one thing and do it well - full of features and functions that, frankly, I often do not need. I don't want systemd managing my containerization. For restarting stopped services? There are monit and supervisor - efficient, effective, and optional. And, I might add: services shouldn't crash; they should handle problems in a non-destructive way. My Raspberry Pi A+ doesn't need systemd, which occupies a huge amount of RAM (and precious clock cycles) for features that will never be useful or necessary on that platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But "move fast and break things" has arrived everywhere, and software is often written by gluing together unstable libraries or those laden with system vulnerabilities. Not to mention so-called "vibe coding" - which might give acceptable results at certain levels, but should not be used when security and confidentiality become primary necessities or, at least, without an understanding of what has been written.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are losing much of the Unix philosophy, and many Linux distributions are now taking the path of distancing themselves from a concept of cross-compatibility ("if it works on Linux, I don't care about other operating systems"), of minimalism, of "do one thing and do it well". And, in my opinion, we are therefore losing many of the hallmarks that have distinguished its behavior over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my view, this depends on two factors: a development model linked to a concept of "disposable" electronics, applied even to software, and the pressure from some companies to push development where they want, not where the project should go. Therefore, in certain cases, the GPL becomes a double-edged sword: on one hand, it protects the software and ensures that contributions remain available. On the other, it risks creating a situation where the most "influential" player can totally direct development because - unable to close their product - they have an interest in the entire project going in the direction they have predisposed. In these cases, perhaps, BSD licenses actually protect the software itself more effectively. Because companies can take and use without an obligation to contribute. If they do, it is because they want to, as in the virtuous case of Netflix with FreeBSD. And this, while it may remove (sometimes precious) contributions to the operating system, guarantees that the steering wheel remains firmly in the hands of those in charge - whether foundations, groups, or individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;And Why I Still Care&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so yes, despite all this, I (still) love Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because it was the first Open Source project I truly believed in (and which truly succeeded), because it works, and because the entire world has developed around it. Because it is a platform on which tons of distributions have been built (and some, like Alpine Linux, still maintain that sense of minimalism that I consider correct for an operating system). Because it has distributions like openSUSE (and many others) that work immediately and without problems on my laptop (suspension and hibernation included) and on my miniPC, a fantastic tool I use daily. Because hardware support has improved immensely, and it is now rare to find incompatible hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because it has been my life companion for 30 years and has contributed significantly to putting food on the table and letting me sleep soundly. Because it allowed me to study without spending insane amounts on licenses or manuals. Because it taught me, first, to think outside the box. To be free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So thank you, GNU/Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if your btrfs, after almost 18 years, still eats data in spectacular fashion. Even if you rename my network interfaces after a reboot. Even though, at times, I get the feeling that youâre slowly turning into what you once wanted to defeat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if you are not my first choice for many workloads, I foresee spending a lot of time with you for at least the next 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46042800</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 06:07:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Human brains are preconfigured with instructions for understanding the world</title><link>https://news.ucsc.edu/2025/11/sharf-preconfigured-brain/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="230b53ace9f3ddab"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Health&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Evidence suggests early developing human brains are preconfigured with instructions for understanding the world&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Assistant Professor of Biomolecular Engineering Tal Sharf’s lab used organoids to make fundamental discoveries about human brain development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Press Contact&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Key takeaways&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;New findings suggest the brain has preconfigured, structured activity patterns even before sensory experiences occur.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UC Santa Cruz researchers used brain organoids to study the brain’s earliest electrical activity.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Understanding early brain patterns could have important implications for diagnosing and treating developmental brain disorders.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Humans have long wondered when and how we begin to form thoughts. Are we born with a pre-configured brain, or do thought patterns only begin to emerge in response to our sensory experiences of the world around us? Now, science is getting closer to answering the questions philosophers have pondered for centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers at the University of California, Santa Cruz, are using tiny models of human brain tissue, called organoids, to study the earliest moments of electrical activity in the brain. A new study in Nature Neuroscience finds that the earliest firings of the brain occur in structured patterns without any external experiences, suggesting that the human brain is preconfigured with instructions about how to navigate and interact with the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“These cells are clearly interacting with each other and forming circuits that self-assemble before we can experience anything from the outside world,” said Tal Sharf, assistant professor of biomolecular engineering at the Baskin School of Engineering and the study’s senior author. “There’s an operating system that exists, that emerges in a primordial state. In my laboratory, we grow brain organoids to peer into this primordial version of the brain’s operating system and study how the brain builds itself before it’s shaped by sensory experience.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In improving our fundamental understanding of human brain development, these findings can help researchers better understand neurodevelopmental disorders, and pinpoint the impact of toxins like pesticides and microplastics in the developing brain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Studying the developing brain&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The brain, similar to a computer, runs on electrical signals—the firing of neurons. When these signals begin to fire, and how the human brain develops, are challenging topics for scientists to study, as the early developing human brain is protected within the womb.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organoids, which are 3D models of tissue grown from human stem cells in the lab, provide a unique window into brain development. The Braingeneers group at UC Santa Cruz, in collaboration with researchers at UC San Francisco and UC Santa Barbara, are pioneering methods to grow these models and take measurements from them to gain insights into brain development and disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organoids are particularly useful for understanding if the brain develops in response to sensory input—as they exist in the lab setting and not the body—and can be grown ethically in large quantities. In this study, researchers prompted stem cells to form brain tissue, and then measured their electrical activity using specialized microchips, similar to those that run a computer. Sharf’s background in both applied physics, computation, and neurobiology form his expertise in modelling the circuitry of the early brain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“An organoid system that’s intrinsically decoupled from any sensory input or communication with organs gives you a window into what’s happening with this self-assembly process,” Sharf said. “That self-assembly process is really hard to do with traditional 2D cell culture—you can’t get the cell diversity and the architecture. The cells need to be in intimate contact with each other. We’re trying to control the initial conditions, so we can let biology do its wonderful thing.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Sharf lab is developing novel neural interfaces, leveraging expertise in physics, materials science, and electrical engineering. On the right, Koushik Devarajan, an electrical and computer engineering Ph.D. student in the Sharf lab.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Pattern production&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The researchers observed the electrical activity of the brain tissue as they self-assembled from stem cells into a tissue that can translate the senses and produce language and conscious thought. They found that within the first few months of development, long before the human brain is capable of receiving and processing complex external sensory information such as vision and hearing, its cells spontaneously began to emit electrical signals characteristic of the patterns that underlie translation of the senses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through decades of neuroscience research, the community has discovered that neurons fire in patterns that aren’t just random. Instead, the brain has a “default mode” — a basic underlying structure for firing neurons which then becomes more specific as the brain processes unique signals like a smell or taste. This background mode outlines the possible range of sensory responses the body and brain can produce.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In their observations of single neuron spikes in the self-assembling organoid models, Sharf and colleagues found that these earliest observable patterns have striking similarity with the brain’s default mode. Even without having received any sensory input, they are firing off a complex repertoire of time-based patterns, or sequences, which have the potential to be refined for specific senses, hinting at a genetically encoded blueprint inherent to the neural architecture of the living brain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“These intrinsically self-organized systems could serve as a basis for constructing a representation of the world around us,” Sharf said. “The fact that we can see them in these early stages suggests that evolution has figured out a way that the central nervous system can construct a map that would allow us to navigate and interact with the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Knowing that these organoids produce the basic structure of the living brain opens up a range of possibilities for better understanding human neurodevelopment, disease, and the effects of toxins in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We’re showing that there is a basis for capturing complex dynamics that likely could be signatures of pathological onsets that we could study in human tissue,” Sharf said. “That would allow us to develop therapies, working with clinicians at the preclinical level to potentially develop compounds, drug therapies, and gene editing tools that could be cheaper, more efficient, higher throughput.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This study included researchers at UC Santa Barbara, Washington University in St. Louis, Johns Hopkins University, the University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf, and ETH Zurich.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46042928</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 06:31:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Most Stable Raspberry Pi? 81% Better NTP with Thermal Management</title><link>https://austinsnerdythings.com/2025/11/24/worlds-most-stable-raspberry-pi-81-better-ntp-with-thermal-management/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b55aba02285e8efe"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve written before about building microsecond-accurate NTP servers with Raspberry Pi and GPS PPS, and more recently about revisiting the setup in 2025. Both posts focused on the hardware setup and basic configuration to achieve sub-microsecond time synchronization using GPS Pulse Per Second (PPS) signals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there was a problem. Despite having a stable PPS reference, my NTP server’s frequency drift was exhibiting significant variation over time. After months (years) of monitoring the system with Grafana dashboards, I noticed something interesting: the frequency oscillations seemed to correlate with CPU temperature changes. The frequency would drift as the CPU heated up during the day and cooled down at night, even though the PPS reference remained rock-solid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like clockwork (no pun intended), I somehow get sucked back into trying to improve my setup every 6-8 weeks. This post is the latest on that never-ending quest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post details how I achieved an 81% reduction in frequency variability and 77% reduction in frequency standard deviation through a combination of CPU core pinning and thermal stabilization. Welcome to Austin’s Nerdy Things, where we solve problems that 99.999% of people (and 99% of datacenters) don’t have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Problem: Thermal-Induced Timing Jitter&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modern CPUs, including those in Raspberry Pis, use dynamic frequency scaling to save power and manage heat. When the CPU is idle, it runs at a lower frequency (and voltage). When load increases, it scales up. This is great for power efficiency, but terrible for precision timekeeping.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why? Because timekeeping (with NTP/chronyd/others) relies on a stable system clock to discipline itself against reference sources. If the CPU frequency is constantly changing, the system clock’s tick rate varies, introducing jitter into the timing measurements. Even though my PPS signal was providing a mostly perfect 1-pulse-per-second reference, the CPU’s frequency bouncing around made it harder for chronyd to maintain a stable lock.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But here’s the key insight: the system clock is ultimately derived from a crystal oscillator, and crystal oscillator frequency is temperature-dependent. The oscillator sits on the board near the CPU, and as the CPU heats up and cools down throughout the day, so does the crystal. Even a few degrees of temperature change can shift the oscillator’s frequency by parts per million – exactly what I was seeing in my frequency drift graphs. The CPU frequency scaling was one factor, but the underlying problem was that temperature changes were affecting the crystal oscillator itself. By stabilizing the CPU temperature, I could stabilize the thermal environment for the crystal oscillator, keeping its frequency consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at my Grafana dashboard, I could see the frequency offset wandering over a range of about 1 PPM (parts per million) as the Pi warmed up and cooled down throughout the day. The RMS offset was averaging around 86 nanoseconds, which isn’t terrible (it’s actually really, really, really good), but I knew it could be better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Discovery&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After staring at graphs for longer than I’d like to admit, I had an idea: what if I could keep the CPU at a constant temperature? If the temperature (and therefore the frequency) stayed stable, maybe the timing would stabilize too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The solution came in two parts:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. CPU core isolation – Dedicate CPU 0 exclusively to timing-critical tasks (chronyd and PPS interrupts) 2. Thermal stabilization – Keep the other CPUs busy to maintain a constant temperature, preventing frequency scaling&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what happened when I turned on the thermal stabilization system on November 17, 2025 at 09:10 AM:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That vertical red line marks when I activated the “time burner” process. Notice how the frequency oscillations immediately dampen and settle into a much tighter band? Let’s dive into how this works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Solution Part 1: CPU Core Pinning and Real-Time Priority&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first step is isolating timing-critical operations onto a dedicated CPU core. On a Raspberry Pi (4-core ARM), this means:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CPU 0: Reserved for chronyd and PPS interrupts&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CPUs 1-3: Everything else, including our thermal load&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had AI (probably Claude Sonnet 4 ish, maybe 4.5) create a boot optimization script that runs at system startup:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#!/bin/bash
# PPS NTP Server Performance Optimization Script
# Sets CPU affinity, priorities, and performance governor at boot

set -e

echo "Setting up PPS NTP server performance optimizations..."

# Wait for system to be ready
sleep 5

# Set CPU governor to performance mode
echo "Setting CPU governor to performance..."
cpupower frequency-set -g performance

# Pin PPS interrupt to CPU0 (may fail if already pinned, that's OK)
echo "Configuring PPS interrupt affinity..."
echo 1 &amp;gt; /proc/irq/200/smp_affinity 2&amp;gt;/dev/null || echo "PPS IRQ already configured"

# Wait for chronyd to start
echo "Waiting for chronyd to start..."
timeout=30
while [ $timeout -gt 0 ]; do
    chronyd_pid=$(pgrep chronyd 2&amp;gt;/dev/null || echo "")
    if [ -n "$chronyd_pid" ]; then
        echo "Found chronyd PID: $chronyd_pid"
        break
    fi
    sleep 1
    ((timeout--))
done

if [ -z "$chronyd_pid" ]; then
    echo "Warning: chronyd not found after 30 seconds"
else
    # Set chronyd to real-time priority and pin to CPU 0
    echo "Setting chronyd to real-time priority and pinning to CPU 0..."
    chrt -f -p 50 $chronyd_pid
    taskset -cp 0 $chronyd_pid
fi

# Boost ksoftirqd/0 priority
echo "Boosting ksoftirqd/0 priority..."
ksoftirqd_pid=$(ps aux | grep '\[ksoftirqd/0\]' | grep -v grep | awk '{print $2}')
if [ -n "$ksoftirqd_pid" ]; then
    renice -n -10 $ksoftirqd_pid
    echo "ksoftirqd/0 priority boosted (PID: $ksoftirqd_pid)"
else
    echo "Warning: ksoftirqd/0 not found"
fi

echo "PPS NTP optimization complete!"

# Log current status
echo "=== Current Status ==="
echo "CPU Governor: $(cat /sys/devices/system/cpu/cpu0/cpufreq/scaling_governor)"
echo "PPS IRQ Affinity: $(cat /proc/irq/200/effective_affinity_list 2&amp;gt;/dev/null || echo 'not readable')"
if [ -n "$chronyd_pid" ]; then
    echo "chronyd Priority: $(chrt -p $chronyd_pid)"
fi
echo "======================"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What this does:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Performance Governor: Forces all CPUs to run at maximum frequency, disabling frequency scaling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;PPS IRQ Pinning: Ensures PPS interrupt (IRQ 200) is handled exclusively by CPU 0&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chronyd Real-Time Priority: Sets chronyd to SCHED_FIFO priority 50, giving it preferential CPU scheduling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chronyd CPU Affinity: Pins chronyd to CPU 0 using &lt;code&gt;taskset&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ksoftirqd Priority Boost: Improves priority of the kernel softirq handler on CPU 0&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This script can be added to &lt;code&gt;/etc/rc.local&lt;/code&gt; or as a systemd service to run at boot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Solution Part 2: PID-Controlled Thermal Stabilization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setting the performance governor helps, but on a Raspberry Pi, even at max frequency, the CPU temperature will still vary based on ambient conditions and load. Temperature changes affect the CPU’s actual operating frequency due to thermal characteristics of the silicon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The solution? Keep the CPU at a constant temperature using a PID-controlled thermal load. I call it the “time burner” (inspired by CPU burn-in tools, but with precise temperature control).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a reminder of what we’re really doing here: we’re maintaining a stable thermal environment for the crystal oscillator. The RPi 3B’s 19.2 MHz oscillator is physically located near the CPU on the Raspberry Pi board, so by actively controlling CPU temperature, we’re indirectly controlling the oscillator’s temperature. Since the oscillator’s frequency is temperature-dependent (this is basic physics of quartz crystals), keeping it at a constant temperature means keeping its frequency stable – which is exactly what we need for precise timekeeping.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Read CPU temperature from &lt;code&gt;/sys/class/thermal/thermal_zone0/temp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;PID controller calculates how much CPU time to burn to maintain target temperature (I chose 54°C)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Three worker processes run on CPUs 1, 2, and 3 (avoiding CPU 0)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Each worker alternates between busy-loop (MD5 hashing) and sleeping based on PID output&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Temperature stabilizes at the setpoint, preventing thermal drift&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the core implementation (simplified for readability):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#!/usr/bin/env python3
import time
import argparse
import multiprocessing
import hashlib
import os
from collections import deque

class PIDController:
    """Simple PID controller with output clamping and anti-windup."""
    def __init__(self, Kp, Ki, Kd, setpoint, output_limits=(0, 1), sample_time=1.0):
        self.Kp = Kp
        self.Ki = Ki
        self.Kd = Kd
        self.setpoint = setpoint
        self.output_limits = output_limits
        self.sample_time = sample_time
        self._last_time = time.time()
        self._last_error = 0.0
        self._integral = 0.0
        self._last_output = 0.0

    def update(self, measurement):
        """Compute new output of PID based on measurement."""
        now = time.time()
        dt = now - self._last_time

        if dt &amp;lt; self.sample_time:
            return self._last_output

        error = self.setpoint - measurement

        # Proportional
        P = self.Kp * error

        # Integral with anti-windup
        self._integral += error * dt
        I = self.Ki * self._integral

        # Derivative
        derivative = (error - self._last_error) / dt if dt &amp;gt; 0 else 0.0
        D = self.Kd * derivative

        # Combine and clamp
        output = P + I + D
        low, high = self.output_limits
        output = max(low, min(high, output))

        self._last_output = output
        self._last_error = error
        self._last_time = now

        return output

def read_cpu_temperature(path='/sys/class/thermal/thermal_zone0/temp'):
    """Return CPU temperature in Celsius."""
    with open(path, 'r') as f:
        temp_str = f.read().strip()
    return float(temp_str) / 1000.0

def burn_cpu(duration):
    """Busy-loop hashing for 'duration' seconds."""
    end_time = time.time() + duration
    m = hashlib.md5()
    while time.time() &amp;lt; end_time:
        m.update(b"burning-cpu")

def worker_loop(worker_id, cmd_queue, done_queue):
    """
    Worker process:
    - Pins itself to CPUs 1, 2, or 3 (avoiding CPU 0)
    - Burns CPU based on commands from main process
    """
    available_cpus = [1, 2, 3]
    cpu_to_use = available_cpus[worker_id % len(available_cpus)]
    os.sched_setaffinity(0, {cpu_to_use})
    print(f"Worker {worker_id} pinned to CPU {cpu_to_use}")

    while True:
        cmd = cmd_queue.get()
        if cmd is None:
            break

        burn_time, sleep_time = cmd
        burn_cpu(burn_time)
        time.sleep(sleep_time)
        done_queue.put(worker_id)

# Main control loop (simplified)
def main():
    target_temp = 54.0  # degrees Celsius
    control_window = 0.20  # 200ms cycle time

    pid = PIDController(Kp=0.05, Ki=0.02, Kd=0.0,
                        setpoint=target_temp,
                        sample_time=0.18)

    # Start 3 worker processes
    workers = []
    cmd_queues = []
    done_queue = multiprocessing.Queue()

    for i in range(3):
        q = multiprocessing.Queue()
        p = multiprocessing.Process(target=worker_loop, args=(i, q, done_queue))
        p.start()
        workers.append(p)
        cmd_queues.append(q)

    try:
        while True:
            # Measure temperature
            current_temp = read_cpu_temperature()

            # PID control: output is fraction of time to burn (0.0 to 1.0)
            output = pid.update(current_temp)

            # Convert to burn/sleep times
            burn_time = output * control_window
            sleep_time = control_window - burn_time

            # Send command to all workers
            for q in cmd_queues:
                q.put((burn_time, sleep_time))

            # Wait for workers to complete
            for _ in range(3):
                done_queue.get()

            print(f"Temp={current_temp:.2f}C, Output={output:.2f}, "
                  f"Burn={burn_time:.2f}s")

    except KeyboardInterrupt:
        for q in cmd_queues:
            q.put(None)
        for p in workers:
            p.join()

if __name__ == '__main__':
    main()&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full implementation includes a temperature filtering system to smooth out sensor noise and command-line arguments for tuning the PID parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PID Tuning Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Kp=0.05: Proportional gain – responds to current error&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ki=0.02: Integral gain – eliminates steady-state error&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Kd=0.0: Derivative gain – set to zero because temperature changes slowly&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The target temperature of 54°C was chosen empirically – high enough to keep the CPU from idling down, but low enough to avoid thermal throttling (which starts around 80°C on Raspberry Pi).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Results: Numbers Don’t Lie&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The improvement was immediately visible. Here are the statistics comparing performance before and after the optimization:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A note on ambient conditions: The Raspberry Pi lives in a project enclosure in our master bedroom (chosen for its decent GPS reception and ADS-B coverage for a new aircraft AR overlay app idea I’m working on also running on this Pi). While the time burner maintains the CPU die temperature at 54°C, the enclosure is still subject to ambient temperature swings. Room temperature cycles from a low of 66°F (18.9°C) at 5:15 AM to a peak of 72°F (22.2°C) at 11:30 AM – a 6°F daily swing from our heating schedule. The fact that we see such dramatic frequency stability improvements despite this ambient variation speaks to how effective the thermal control is. The CPU’s active heating overwhelms the environmental changes, maintaining consistent silicon temperature where it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Frequency Stability&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Metric&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Before&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;After&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Improvement&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mean RMS Offset&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;85.44 ns&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;43.54 ns&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;49.0% reduction&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Median RMS Offset&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;80.13 ns&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;37.93 ns&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;52.7% reduction&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The RMS offset is chronyd’s estimate of the timing uncertainty. Cutting this nearly in half means the system is maintaining significantly better time accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Setup Instructions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Want to replicate this? Here’s the step-by-step process:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need a working GPS PPS NTP server setup. If you don’t have one yet, follow my 2025 NTP guide first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Step 0: Install Required Tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install linux-cpupower python3 util-linux&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Step 1: Create the Boot Optimization Script&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Save the optimization script from earlier as &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/bin/pps-optimize.sh&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo nano /usr/local/bin/pps-optimize.sh
# Paste the script content
sudo chmod +x /usr/local/bin/pps-optimize.sh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Step 2: Create Systemd Service for Boot Script&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;/etc/systemd/system/pps-optimize.service&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;[Unit]
Description=PPS NTP Performance Optimization
After=chronyd.service
Requires=chronyd.service

[Service]
Type=oneshot
ExecStart=/usr/local/bin/pps-optimize.sh
RemainAfterExit=yes

[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enable it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl enable pps-optimize.service&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Step 3: Install the Time Burner Script&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Save the time burner Python script as &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/bin/time_burner.py&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo nano /usr/local/bin/time_burner.py
# Paste the full time burner script
sudo chmod +x /usr/local/bin/time_burner.py&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Step 4: Create Systemd Service for Time Burner&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;/etc/systemd/system/time-burner.service&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;[Unit]
Description=CPU Thermal Stabilization for NTP
After=network.target

[Service]
Type=simple
User=root
ExecStart=/usr/bin/python3 /usr/local/bin/time_burner.py -t 54.0 -n 3
Restart=always
RestartSec=10

[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enable and start it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl enable time-burner.service
sudo systemctl start time-burner.service&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Step 5: Verify the Setup&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check that everything is running:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Verify CPU governor
cat /sys/devices/system/cpu/cpu0/cpufreq/scaling_governor
# Should output: performance

# Check chronyd CPU affinity and priority
ps -eo pid,comm,psr,ni,rtprio | grep chronyd
# Should show psr=0 (CPU 0) and rtprio=50

# Check time burner processes
ps aux | grep time_burner
# Should show 4 processes (1 main + 3 workers)

# Monitor NTP performance
chronyc tracking&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example output from &lt;code&gt;chronyc tracking&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Reference ID    : 50505300 (PPS)
Stratum         : 1
Ref time (UTC)  : Sun Nov 24 16:45:23 2025
System time     : 0.000000038 seconds fast of NTP time
Last offset     : -0.000000012 seconds
RMS offset      : 0.000000035 seconds
Frequency       : 1.685 ppm slow
Residual freq   : -0.001 ppm
Skew            : 0.002 ppm
Root delay      : 0.000000001 seconds
Root dispersion : 0.000010521 seconds
Update interval : 16.0 seconds
Leap status     : Normal&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice the RMS offset of 35 nanoseconds – this is the kind of accuracy you can achieve with thermal stabilization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Step 6: Monitor Over Time&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Topic for a future post)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set up Grafana dashboards to monitor:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Frequency offset (PPM)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;RMS offset (nanoseconds)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CPU temperature&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;System time offset&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll see the frequency stabilize within a few hours as the PID controller locks onto the target temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Monitoring and Troubleshooting&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Real-Time Monitoring&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Watch chronyd tracking in real-time:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;watch -n 1 "chronyc tracking"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check time burner status:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl status time-burner.service&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;View time burner output:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo journalctl -u time-burner.service -f&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Common Issues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Temperature overshoots or oscillates:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adjust PID gains – reduce Kp if oscillating, increase Ki if steady-state error&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Try different target temperatures (50-60°C range)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;High CPU usage (obviously):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;This is intentional – the time burner uses ~90% of 3 cores&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Not suitable for Pis running other workloads&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chronyd not pinned to CPU 0:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check that the optimization script runs after chronyd starts&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adjust the timing in the systemd service dependencies&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Trade-offs and Considerations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest about the downsides:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Power Consumption&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The time burner keeps 3 cores at ~30% average utilization. My Pi now draws about 3-4W continuously (vs 1-2W idle). Over a year, that’s an extra 15-25 kWh, or about $2-3 in electricity (depending on your rates).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Heat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running at 54°C means the Pi is warm to the touch. This is well within safe operating temperature (thermal throttling doesn’t start until 80°C), but you might want to ensure adequate ventilation. I added a small heatsink just to be safe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;CPU Resources&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’re dedicating 3 of 4 cores to burning cycles. This is fine for a dedicated NTP server, but not suitable if you’re running other services on the same Pi. That said, I am also running the feeder to my new ADS-B aircraft visualization app on it. My readsb instance regularly gets to 1200 msg/s with 200+ aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Is It Worth It?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For 99.999% of use cases: absolutely not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most applications don’t need better than millisecond accuracy, let alone the 35-nanosecond RMS offset I’m achieving. Even for distributed systems, microsecond-level accuracy is typically overkill.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When this might make sense:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Precision timing applications (scientific instrumentation, radio astronomy)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Distributed systems research requiring tight clock synchronization&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Network testing where timing precision affects results&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Because you can (the best reason for any homelab project)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For me, this falls squarely in the “because you can” category. I had the monitoring infrastructure in place, noticed the thermal correlation, and couldn’t resist solving the problem. Plus, I learned a lot about PID control, CPU thermal characteristics, and Linux real-time scheduling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Future Improvements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some ideas I’m considering:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Adaptive PID Tuning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The current PID gains are hand-tuned for a specific ambient temperature range. The fairly low P value is to avoid spikes when some load on the Pi kicks up the temp. The I is a balance to keep long term “burn” relatively consistent. Implementing an auto-tuning algorithm (like Ziegler-Nichols) or adaptive PID could handle seasonal temperature variations better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Hardware Thermal Control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of software thermal control, I could add an actively cooled heatsink with PWM fan control. This might achieve similar temperature stability while using less power overall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Oven-Controlled Crystal Oscillator (OCXO)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the ultimate in frequency stability, replacing the Pi’s crystal with a temperature-controlled OCXO would eliminate thermal drift at the source. This is how professional timing equipment works. I do have a BH3SAP GPSDO sitting next to me (subject to a future post)… Then again, I’m the person who just wrote 4000 words about optimizing a $50 time server, so who am I kidding?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through a combination of CPU core isolation and PID-controlled thermal stabilization, I achieved:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;81% reduction in frequency variability&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;77% reduction in frequency standard deviation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;74% reduction in frequency range&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;49% reduction in RMS offset&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The system now maintains 38-nanosecond median RMS offset from the GPS PPS reference, with frequency drift that’s barely detectable in the noise. The CPU runs at a constant 54°C, and in steady state, the frequency offset stays within a tight ±0.14 PPM band (compared to ±0.52 PPM before optimization).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Was this necessary? No. Did I learn a bunch about thermal management, PID control, and Linux real-time scheduling? Yes. Would I do it again? Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Resource&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I did come across a “burn” script that was the basis for this thermal management. I can’t find it at the moment, but when I do I’ll link it here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Related Posts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Microsecond-Accurate NTP with a Raspberry Pi and PPS GPS (2021)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Revisiting Microsecond-Accurate NTP for Raspberry Pi in 2025&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Further Reading&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have questions or suggestions? Drop a comment below. I’m particularly interested to hear if anyone has tried alternative thermal management approaches or has experience with OCXO modules for Raspberry Pi timing applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, and happy timekeeping!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46042946</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 06:35:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What you can get for the price of a Netflix subscription</title><link>https://nmil.dev/what-you-can-get-for-the-price-of-a-netflix-subscription</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2a40001c62042794"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What you can get for the price of a Netflix subscription&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, I decided to do away with my Netflix subscription. I simply was barely using it, and whenever I did it was more out of habit than it really being the thing I wanted to do with my time. Sure, there's still some decent stuff on there, but the vast majority of it feels absolutely moneyballed. Good, but somehow too good, and with no character.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As much as I'd love to elaborate on why I think Netflix is evil, that's not todays topic. What I wanted to share is how for approximately the price I was paying for my subscription (€19.99), I've snapped up three subscriptions that I'm using on a daily basis. They're all pretty much interchangeable with other alternatives. The main thing I want to highlight is the individual slot they each fill out for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;1. A subscription to Zed Pro (~€10)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Frankly, I haven't really put too much thought into whether the unit economics are the best here. The main point is, these are €10 that make my coding experience more pleasant, and get me writing more code in my spare time. In that sense it's money well spent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Does it matter if you get a Cursor subscription, or a Zed one, or whatever else is in vogue when you're reading? No, just get the thing that will get you excited to get your hands on the keyboard! To me, Zed feels more intentionally built than the VSClones: things flow nicely, it feels snappy, the ui is less cluttered... It's just nice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Editor preferences aside, the main takeaway is, invest in a hobby you actively engage in. Make that little bit more appealing and you have one more reason to be spending your time doing the thing that makes you feel good, rather than letting a couple hours a day evaporate watching another forgettable show.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;2. A Kagi subscription (~€5/month)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think we can mostly agree google kind of sucks nowadays. Whenever I search, I automatically scroll down to skip the sponsored posts and SEO maxxed websites, and still don't fully trust what I get. Maybe that's why we all started appending “reddit” the end of our searches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are the search results themselves better with Kagi? To be honest, I can't tell yet, others have written far more informed takes on the topic. What does it for me is the simple fact of being able to pay directly for a service that I use, and value, rather than having to trade my attention in and endure a wall of ads. Especially if it's something I use over and over, every day. That's what I mean to highlight here: we can support products that we enjoy by paying for them (who would have thought?) rather than letting them lobotomize us via ad feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3. A cheap server on Hetzner (~€4/month)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, the choice of provider here is secondary. The point is, I finally have my little stake on the internet. It's relatively barebones, and I like that. It forces me to learn and engage. In fact, that is where my blog is hosted!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So to sum it up: We don't have to default to a streaming subscription because that's become the standard human-being thing to do. For the same money you can build a suite of useful, well crafted tools that help you: – Get the most out of your hobbies – Spend less time looking at ads – Build things you can share with the world&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;P.S. Not one word here was written by AI. I plan on keeping it that way for anything that goes on this blog. So, if anything reads like slop, it's my slop :)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46042969</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 06:39:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>