<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 16:16:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Adafruit: Arduino’s Rules Are ‘Incompatible With Open Source’</title><link>https://thenewstack.io/adafruit-arduinos-rules-are-incompatible-with-open-source/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b6d09bd834b6311e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Adafruit: Arduino’s Rules Are ‘Incompatible With Open Source’&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The open source hardware community is debating Arduino’s new Terms and Conditions following the company’s acquisition by Qualcomm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chief microcontroller rival Adafruit has argued that the new terms threaten open principles by restricting reverse engineering of cloud tools, asserting perpetual licenses over user uploads and implementing broad monitoring for AI-related features.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arduino has defended the changes, claiming restrictions only apply to its SaaS cloud applications, that data handling is standard for modern platforms, and its commitment to open source hardware remains unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Debate Over Arduino’s New Terms and Conditions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last week, I spoke to Arduino, Adafruit and the EFF about Qualcomm’s October acquisition of the beloved company known for its single-board microcontroller kits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many criticisms came from rival Adafruit, whose products include Arduino-compatible hardware kits. In late November, Adafruit’s Managing Editor Phillip Torrone had warned its 36,000+ followers on LinkedIn that (among other things) Arduino’s users were now “explicitly forbidden from reverse engineering or even attempting to understand how the platform works unless Arduino gives permission.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Arduino responded in a blog post that “Restrictions on reverse engineering apply specifically to our Software-as-a-Service cloud applications. Anything that was open, stays open.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An Arduino spokesperson said their blog post reassured many readers, who’d said they felt “understanding and relief that our commitment to the open source spirit is unwavering and Arduino’s core mission remains unchanged.” Yet Adafruit’s critical LinkedIn post had drawn over 1,575 upvotes. I asked both sides to clarify their positions. Does this really represent a turning point since Arduino’s founding in 2004?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s what they had to say.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Reverse Engineering: Cloud Apps vs. Hardware Boards&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I asked Mitch Stoltz, EFF director for competition and IP litigation, who agreed that Arduino “isn’t imposing any new bans on tinkering with or reverse engineering Arduino boards.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like Adafruit, Arduino’s primary user base is at-home enthusiasts. Arduino provides an open source electronics platform — which includes single-board microcontrollers such as the Arduino UNO — and various kits/shields/accessories, as well as development software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, Adafruit founder Limor “Ladyada” Fried says Arduino’s response “downplays how central the cloud and web tools have become to the Arduino experience.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“If you go to the Arduino software page and the cloud page, you’re strongly encouraged to use the cloud editor/web IDE and cloud plans, especially on platforms like ChromeOS where the cloud editor is the recommended or only realistic path,” Fried said. “So when Arduino says ‘These restrictions only apply to SaaS,’ that still means the restrictions apply to the tools many new users are being steered into as their primary Arduino environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“On top of that, using those cloud tools generally requires an Arduino account, and the signup flow prominently presents marketing and profiling consents, including consent to processing personal data for commercial offers and to profiling for customized offers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“That is a very different model than ‘download a local IDE and just start hacking on hardware,'” Fried said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Even if the underlying firmware and libraries remain open source, the practical entry point for many users is moving”, she pointed out, in that accounts are tied to personal data, marketing and profiling prompts have been introduced, and are being linked to centralized, subscription-oriented cloud services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Understanding the License on User-Uploaded Content&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adafruit’s Torrone had also said Arduino’s new documents “introduce an irrevocable, perpetual license over anything users upload.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Arduino argues they’re instead clarifying that “content you choose to publish on the Arduino platform remains yours, and can be used to enable features you’ve requested, such as cloud services and collaboration tools.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a follow-up interview, an Arduino spokesperson provided clarifying examples:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“If a user uploads their code sketches on their Arduino Cloud subscription, the content remains their own, private to them, and the licensing rights granted to Arduino are strictly functional to perform the requested features (e.g. compiling the sketch in the cloud).”&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“If the user uploads code or content to Project Hub or to the Forum, where the content is visible to all other users, then Arduino requires the user, who retains the ownership of the content, to grant a license to handle the publication.”&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“[W]ithout this license, we could not run user projects on the cloud or display their posts in the forum, which is why this type of license is typically required to run any modern cloud service or social platform.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arduino’s old terms of use had also required a license for using material posted, notes EFF’s Stoltz, which he says is “normal for any online platform.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But then Stoltz adds that “Still, some of the changes to the terms are troubling.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arduino’s old terms “were unusual in giving users the ability to revoke that license at any time. The new terms remove that ability, making the license irrevocable. It’s disappointing to see a platform that was once especially user-protective revert to the norm.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;User Data and the Right To Delete Accounts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arduino also pointed out an additional privacy protection. “All users retain the right to request deletion of their account and/or content at any time. Upon such deletion, the relevant content will no longer be visible to other users.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Torrone had complained of “years-long retention of usernames even after account deletion,” but Arduino calls that “a misunderstanding of our policy … When a user requests account deletion, we immediately delete the account and remove the user’s username from all associated Forum posts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The five-year public retention of usernames applies only to users who simply have not logged into their Arduino user account for 24 months and have not submitted any data or account deletion requests.” (In those cases, Arduino seeks a status where “contributions remain attributed to inactive usernames, honoring their contribution to the community.”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, for those inactive-for-two-years users, accounts are automatically deactivated, Arduino’s blog post clarified, but with usernames preserved in the Arduino Forum “to address an explicit request from the Forum community to maintain attribution for user-generated content.” (And where a user does request account deletion, “the username would be promptly removed and related posts would become anonymous.”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even then, with those inactive accounts, “After five years the username is deleted,” Arduino’s spokesperson explained, “and relevant user posts or comments are de-identified.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This policy is not meant for data retention for commercial use, but instead solely to help preserve content attribution, something the community has emphasized as valuable.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Adafruit’s Fried still says there’s a troubling pattern in how usernames are retained and not deleted. “Policy choices that treat the community’s identity and data as a managed asset, rather than something users can fully control.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;AI Features and User Monitoring Policies on Arduino&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The culture difference is most clear where the new Terms and Conditions list several “prohibited uses of AI,” which include criminal use and violation of the law, intentions to harm (including dissemination of false information and manipulative or deceptive acts), generating facial recognition databases and military use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arduino’s blog post notes its new AI features are optional — including AI-powered computer vision and audio models and an IDE with pre-trained AI models. But in the new Terms and Conditions, Arduino “reserves the right to monitor User accounts and use of the AI Product … [for] verifying compliance with laws and this policy.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Arduino says the monitoring is “to comply with existing laws and regulations, including applicable privacy laws, export controls, and other global regulatory requirements” and “verify compliance with legal and policy standards.” And they add their ultimate goal is “protecting the users and Arduino” and to enable “robust and reliable operation of the AI products.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But their conditions also include the right to monitor for other reasons, including “administering and managing Arduino’s business.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adafruit’s Fried says Arduino “should, of course, comply with applicable laws and respond appropriately to clear evidence of criminal activity.” But “they should design their AI and cloud offerings so that monitoring is narrowly targeted, proportionate, and clearly explained, instead of defaulting to broad surveillance across all users.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“You cannot say ‘this code is open source, but it may not be used for military purposes’ and still call the license open source.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;— Adafruit Founder Limor Fried&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fried instead sees “an ongoing surveillance posture, not just responding to specific, well-founded reports of abuse.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So yes, an open source application can watch for the creation of facial-recognition databases or military use “as long as they are transparent about what they log, how long they keep it, and under what circumstances they review it.” But there are concerns about “broad continuous monitoring erodes user trust, especially in an educational/maker context where many people are minors or hobbyists who expect a relatively private environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And there’s an even larger issue of principle. “Genuine open source licenses do not allow field-of-use restrictions,” Fried said. “You cannot say ‘this code is open source, but it may not be used for military purposes’ and still call the license open source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you present something as open source, you no longer get to pick and choose ‘good’ versus ‘bad’ users.” Fried calls such restrictions “fundamentally incompatible with open source licensing,” and would like to see Arduino remove them. “If a project wants that kind of control, it should be honest and call itself ‘source-available’ or something similar, not open source.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Torrone noted that Arduino’s Terms and Conditions also state users will undertake not to use Arduino’s platform or services “to identify or provide evidence to support any potential patent infringement claim against Arduino … or any of Arduino’s or Arduino’s Affiliates’ suppliers and/or direct or indirect customers.” But the specifics almost seem beside the point. Fried says Arduino’s usage restrictions “effectively override the freedoms the license is supposed to guarantee.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s Next for Arduino and the Open Source Community?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Transparency and open dialogue are fundamental to the Arduino ethos,” its spokesperson said Friday, “and understanding the community’s concerns, we are eager to set the record straight and reaffirm our commitment to the open source community.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The representative also added that “We are committed to continuing to listen to community feedback.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what will Adafruit do next? Fried said Friday that Adafruit isn’t changing, and would “keep designing and shipping open source hardware, with hardware, firmware, and software available so people can learn from it, modify it, and build on it.” And the company supports “multiple” ecosystems, also continuing work on Wi-Fi/Bluetooth low-energy (BLE) chips, matter-based Internet of Things (IoT), and the Linux Foundation’s real-time OS Zephyr.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We are always open to working with other makers and companies, including Arduino, as long as the collaboration allows us to ship great products with strong documentation and truly open source licensing.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46265362</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 18:18:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>JSDoc is TypeScript</title><link>https://culi.bearblog.dev/jsdoc-is-typescript/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b424f3ff7b2d7285"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;JSDoc *is* TypeScript&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In May of 2023 an internal refactoring PR from the Svelte repo made it to the front page of the Hacker News forums. The (superficially) controversial PR seemingly vindicated TypeScript skeptics/luddites (which at the time included figures like Dan Abramov of the React team). The premier darling of web frameworks ostensibly rejecting the benefits of static typing was a big deal.1 So Rich Harris felt compelled to hop onto HN and explain how this was "not a vindication of anti-Typescript positions".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Harris offered a considered take on why moving type declarations from .ts files to JSDoc comments in .js files was not an anti-TypeScript take. In fact, Harris asserted that Svelte's "commitment to TypeScript [was] stronger than ever."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This event heralded (and served as a citation for) a flood of "TypeScript VS JSDoc" blog posts and forum threads that offered the somewhat novel defense of JSDoc as "all the benefits of TypeScript without the build step" (albeit with a sometimes clunkier syntax).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this is not the blog post lineage I hope to draw on with this post. Instead, I'd like to focus on a larger and more often misunderstood point. I take issue with the "vs" framing and offer a subtle but crucial substitution: JSDoc is TypeScript.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some background:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;TypeScript is C#?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back in the late aughts/early 10s, JavaScript was still mostly seen as an unserious language. The tooling for JavaScript development lacked autocomplete, rename symbol, type safety, etc. Microsoft developers were so allergic to it that they would write C# code and use a tool called ScriptSharp to generate slightly-more-typesafe JavaScript code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are the origins of TypeScript.2 It is, fundamentally, a build tool to make writing JS less crappy. In fact:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;TypeScript is IntelliSense!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if you don't write your code in .ts files, you're probably using TypeScript. That's because TypeScript is the IntelliSense engine. Even if you're not using VSCode, if your editor gives you code completion, parameter info, quick info, member lists, etc. while writing JS code, you are almost certainly running the TypeScript language service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;TypeScript is JSDoc :)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is also the TypeScript language service that is used to interpret JSDoc comments. That is why the TypeScript CHANGELOG often includes notes about JSDoc features.3 It also the reason your JSDoc-related IntelliSense can be governed by a &lt;code&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt; file and you can run &lt;code&gt;tsc&lt;/code&gt; on a project typed with JSDoc comments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are already using TypeScript.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My Own Experience&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I recently rewrote the front-end for an old project of mine completely typed with JSDoc comments and I wanted to share some of my takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Besides runtime features like enums, basically everything you can express in TypeScript you can express in JSDoc. Certain features like generics are much clunkier, forcing you to type the return in order to infer generic slots. But sometimes the clunkier syntax can actually encourage better TypeScript practices by pushing devs to rely more on type inference.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For packages typed with JSDoc, CTRL/CMD clicking on a function will take you to actual code rather than a type declarations file. I much prefer this experience as a dev.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TypeScript tooling is surprisingly reusable for JSDoc projects. This includes type generation libraries that take schemas (e.g. OpenApi or GraphQL) defined in your backend and generate corresponding types in your front-end. I found that most of these can be set up to generate types in JSDoc comments instead of TypeScript code.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take it from a massive TypeScript nerd: JSDoc is not an anti-TypeScript position to take. It is the same powerful static analysis without the build step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;EDIT: This got some discussion on HN and I've learned that webpack has also migrated to JSDoc↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;And the reason enums were, regrettably, added to the language↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A miserable sidenote: becoming a TypeScript expert means accepting that half of the TypeScript documentation is in the changelog. E.g.↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46266102</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 19:42:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Problem of Teaching Physics in Latin America (1963)</title><link>https://calteches.library.caltech.edu/46/2/LatinAmerica.htm</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="365551101ec38d58"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by Richard P. Feynman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The Problem of Teaching Physics in Latin America" is a transcript of the keynote speech given by Richard Feynman at the First Inter‑American Conference on Physics Education in Rio de Janeiro in June 1963. Dr. Feynman is Richard Chace Tolman Professor of Theoretical Physics at Caltech.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem of teaching physics in Latin America is only part of the wider problem of teaching physics anywhere. In fact, it is part of the problem of teaching anything anywhere – a problem for which there is no known satisfactory solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are many new plans in many countries for trying to teach physics, which shows that nobody is satisfied with any method. It is likely that many of the new plans look good, for nobody has tried them long enough to find out what is the matter with them; whereas all the old methods have been with us long enough to show their faults clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact is that nobody knows very well how to tell anybody else how to teach. So when we try to figure out how to teach physics we must he somewhat modest, because nobody really knows how. It is at the same time a serious problem and an opportunity for new discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem of teaching physics in Latin America can also be generalized in another way, to remind us of the problem of doing anything in Latin America. We must get at least partly involved in the special social, political, and economic problems that exist here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the problems come into sharper focus if there is before us a clear picture of the reasons for teaching physics in the first place. So I will try to give some reasons why I believe we should teach physics. We can then ask whether any particular educational plan is in fact satisfying any of the reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first reason is, of course, that physics is a basic science, and as such is used in engineering, chemistry, and biology, and has all kinds of applications in technology. Physics is the science, or knowledge of nature, that tells us how things work. In particular, I am stressing here how devices of various kinds – invented by men in present and forthcoming technology – work. Therefore, those who know physics will be much more useful in coping with the technical problems arising in local industry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It might be argued, and in practice it is argued, that in the earlier stages of industrial development that we have in Latin America, such talent is completely superfluous because it is so easy to import good technically‑trained personnel from more advanced countries outside. Therefore, is it really necessary to develop highly‑technically‑trained people locally?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I probably do not know enough economics to answer correctly, but I will try to give an opinion anyway. I think it is vitally important to improve the technical ability of the peoples of Latin America. By education, the man with higher technical ability is able to produce more, and I believe that in the improvement of the technical ability, and thus the productivity, of the people of Latin America lies the source of real economic advancement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is not economically sound to continuously import technically‑skilled people. If Latin American people were educated technically they would find positions in the developing industries here; it would soon be realized by the people who now import such workers that there is a supply of really able men in this country, and that this local supply has many advantages. The local people would not demand such high wages, would know the customs and ways of the country, and would be glad to take more permanent positions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is true that Latin Americans with the same degrees in science or engineering as their foreign counterparts seem to be very much less able. This (as I shall explain) is because they have not really been taught any science. This experience has probably conditioned industrialists to pay very little attention to the local universities and scientists. If they were wise the industrialists would see the problem quite the other way around and would be the first to clamor for a meeting of the kind we are having today, to find out what is the matter with the local product and how to teach physics in a really satisfactory manner in their countries. Yet none of them are here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A secondary reason for teaching physics, or any experimental science, is that it incidentally teaches how to do things with your hands. It teaches many techniques for manipulating things – as well as techniques of measurement and calculation, for example – which have very much wider applications than the particular field of study.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another major reason for teaching physics is for the science itself. Science is an activity of men; to many men it is a great pleasure and it should not be denied to the people of a large part of the world simply because of a fault or lack in the educational system. In other words, one of the reasons for teaching science is to make scientists who will not just contribute to the development of industry but also contribute to the development of knowledge, joining others in this great adventure of our times, and, of course, obtaining enormous pleasure in doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thirdly, there is good reason to study nature to appreciate its wonder and its beauty, even though one may not become an actively‑working professional scientist. This knowledge of nature also gives a feeling of stability and reality about the world and drives out many fears and superstitions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A fourth value in teaching science is to teach how things are found out. The value of questioning, the value of free ideas – not only for the development of science, but the value of free ideas in every field – becomes apparent. Science is a way to teach how something gets to be known, what is not known, to what extent things are known (for nothing is known absolutely), how to handle doubt and uncertainty, what the rules of evidence are, how to think about things so that judgments can be made, how to distinguish truth from fraud, and from show. These are certainly important secondary yields of teaching science, and physics in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, in learning science you learn to handle trial and error, to develop a spirit of invention and of free inquiry which is of tremendous value far beyond science. One learns to ask oneself: "Is there a better way to do it?" (And the answer to this is not the conditioned reflex: "Let's see how they do it in the United States," because there must certainly be a better way than that!) We must try to think of some new gimmick or idea, to find some improvement in the technique. This question is the source of a great deal of free independent thought, of invention, and of human progress of all kinds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This ends my list of reasons for the teaching of physics as a science. Let me turn now to a description of some of the major characteristics of science education in Latin America which appear to me to be of special concern for us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, and most serious, I believe, is the almost exclusive teaching and learning by means of pure abject memory. This in no way teaches physics as a science. Nothing is understood; it is only remembered. This in no way satisfies the reasons I outlined for teaching science. Memorization of laws does not permit one to make applications of these laws to new situations; it does not permit one the pleasure of ultimately making scientific contributions; it cannot teach any techniques with the hands. From memorizing, knowledge is not understood, and the beauty of nature is not appreciated. It does not tell how things were found out, or reveal the value of an inventive free mind.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, the telescope is an interesting device to make, understand, look through, and play with. It turned men's ideas and minds in new directions. It gave a great impetus to the modern revolution of thought. For a long while it was the sole revealer of the vastness of the heavens and man's modest place in it. But, in Latin America one learns that there are four kinds of telescopes: the Newtonian, the Cassigranian, etc., etc. In the first, the image is virtual and inverted, etc. (I put in all this "etc." because I really don't know how many kinds of telescopes there are, or what their names are, or which way the image is in each kind. But don't underestimate me; I know a very great deal about telescopes – how they work, how to make and use one, their powers and limitations, etc.) The result is that the telescope is lost. There is no more telescope, no lenses, no stars, no eyes, no light – just words memorized without requiring understanding. The examination is passed, for the question was "What are the four types of telescopes?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I must say immediately that I am not against memorizing. Some things, even many (though nothing special) may be learned by heart; for example, it is good, but not essential, to know by heart 7 x 8 = 56. What I oppose in any teaching philosophy is that the philosophy is used exclusively; but in this case it is especially serious because so little is left of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was incomprehensible to the people of my country when I reported how material is memorized in Latin America completely without understanding. Lectures are dictated so slowly that students can copy them word for word into their notebooks – and sentences are even repeated so they can check them back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When asked what Brewster's Law is, advanced students answer in a flash: "Light impinging on a material of index n is 100 percent polarized with the electric field perpendicular to the plane of incidence if the tangent of the angle of incidence equals the index of refraction."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To these same students I then say, "Look out at the bay from which the sunlight is being reflected. If I look at that reflection through this piece of polaroid and turn it, what will happen?" All I receive are blank stares. No one knows. But I get cries of surprise and delight when they try it and see the reflections getting brighter and dimmer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This shows something is completely wrong. There is no knowledge whatsoever of nature. With the wrong entrance clue the memorization is useless. These students are like books, no more. I can look in the index of a book under "Brewster's Law" and find a reference equivalent to the students' reply. But in the index I cannot find "sun reflecting on bay."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What do the students know that is not easily and directly available in a book? The things that can be looked up in a book are only a part of knowledge. Who wants such a student to work in a plant when a book requiring no food or maintenance stands day after day always ready to give just as adequate answers? Who wants to be such a student, to have worked so hard, to have missed so much of interest and pleasure, and to be outdone by an inanimate printed list of "laws"?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What experience I have makes me think that this is one of the main failures in the education of students in Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A second problem in Latin America is that the students are all alone. They cannot converse with other students; they cannot see how stupid some fellow students are. This is mainly for some psychological reason. They do not wish to be found unsure, for they will be ridiculed. They cannot ask questions in class because the others later say, "Why do you waste the time of all of us? Everyone knows that." So, to save face, they all put on a show of knowledge, thereby frustrating free discussion and the exchange of ideas – one of the pleasantest and easiest ways of learning things. There is too much show, and too much formality in the classroom for any exercise of free thought and discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A third problem is the lack of freedom in the university structure. You cannot move around from one subject to another or from one lab to another. Those who go abroad to learn find it difficult to communicate their new knowledge easily and directly to the university students when they return – for they cannot find a place in, and are not welcomed into, the university structure. For some reason or other, it becomes necessary for such people to create new and separate research institutes. The spirit of excitement in these institutions as their research progresses is not found in the universities, and this is quite unfortunate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another problem in Latin America is that there is very little outlet for the students who do not want to become complete scientists. It is not easy for them to obtain jobs in the developing industries here. Perhaps if these students were really adequately trained, the companies would gradually realize their value and this problem would disappear. But some of the enthusiastic students are not geniuses, and there must be some place for them to go – even though they are not going to make any scientific contribution, or become second Einsteins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I began studying at MIT I started in mathematics, and probably I thought I would be a mathematician. Then I discovered that the only use of higher mathematics is to teach more higher mathematics and I turned to something more practical – electrical engineering. Finally I realized I had gone too far in the other direction and chose something in between – physics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was all very easy because, for such closely related subjects, the courses taken by students in each discipline were almost exactly the same and were taught by the same professors. The engineers studied physics taught by the physicists, for instance, and the physicists learned some of their electricity in a course taught by the professors of electrical engineering. It is easy for students to move back and forth among related disciplines. If physics is too difficult for them, or mathematics too abstract, they can turn to engineering and can later expect to find a position somewhere. Such changes are much more difficult in Latin American universities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another characteristic of the situation in Latin America is the small number of people involved: the result is a rapid fluctuation and irregularity in the character of organizations and institutions. How something goes depends very much on particular individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, we must mention the problem of the best students leaving to go to other countries. This is because of the lack of opportunities in Latin America, the climate of rigidity that exists in the universities, and the vagaries of fortune of the research institutions as their budgets find uneven support from year to year, from the government and private sources of funds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I should now like to give some of the questions for which I think we must seek answers here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, how can we free the lower levels of secondary education from the drudge memorization that exists at the present time? It is well known that you can get children quite interested in science in a true, live, and active way while they are young. It is sometimes said you cannot get them interested by the time they are in the university, but this is not true – provided they have not been destroyed as thinking humans at the earlier levels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gibbon said: "The power of instruction is of little efficacy, except in those happy dispositions where it is nearly superfluous." This is not really true. It is true of good instruction, but bad instruction can be very efficacious indeed in impressing on one how impossibly dull some subject is. It is possible to destroy the excitement and interest that students may have gained by discovering a small book in the library, by buying a toy, a chemistry set, or a little electric motor – by playing around. In fact, one of the most important sources of motivation of interest in science is in a toy, or in a special book, and from those few teachers who are free enough from the bonds of an educational system to be able to keep children excited and inspired by supplying them with suggestions, demonstrations, and games.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is a well known experience in education that, in spite of all plans and programs, ultimately almost everything depends on teachers – on individual teachers. You can have poor teachers and, no matter what you try to do with them, the students learn very little. Or you can have good teachers and it doesn't make much difference what you do, provided you leave the teacher free. So I think we must find how to free those few teachers who can be inspiring to children. It is important that those inspiring teachers work along with children, suggesting experiments and trying them freely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second question we shall have to try to answer is how to bring engineers and other applied scientists closer to their real world of application. It is not enough for them to remember exactly how to use the formula, providing that the situation is exactly the same as the situation was in the engineering school when the professor dictated the lecture. We must do something to make the applied engineer more flexible, so that he is effective in a wide range of applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One way may be to have true scientists – and especially active research experimental physicists – teaching physics to some engineering students. Experimental physics generates technical problems. To succeed, you have to work with your hands; you have to meet reality; pure memory won't do. So, people who are good at experimental physics know what engineering problems are.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The development of industrial technology is in a great measure simply the wider application of techniques which in most cases were developed by scientists trying to do experiments. This is because, in trying to do some experiment in science, you have to push some technique to the extreme. In doing so, you learn how things can be done. Experimental physicists first pursued the problems of how to make a higher vacuum or a lower temperature than ever before, and now high vacuum and low temperatures are tools of industrial technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Therefore, experimental science is a source of engineering and experimental science should be taught to engineers in school to keep them aware of the wide range of techniques available and the open possibilities of the future. Perhaps, then, after we have created enough real engineers with real value to industry in Latin America, industry will see that there is no advantage to hiring engineers from overseas and will want more of the locally-trained men and will support the schools with methods of teaching which produce such engineers. Then we will have the ball rolling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I understand that the number of engineering schools in Latin America is growing rapidly. For example, in Brazil there are twice as many engineering schools as there were ten years ago. If this is the case, then maybe the problem can solve itself. If these schools are not all organized under the same system, if there is a variety in the schools, then one or another school may develop a way to produce excellent students – if the secondary school preparation has not first ruined them. Then this school will acquire a reputation, children will try to go there, other schools will try to compete and copy the better methods‑and so on until the problem solves itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The third problem that we have here is how to encourage the true research workers and keep them from leaving home permanently. We have to supply them with books, with experimental equipment, with money for visits abroad, and with a coterie of active interested students. No, excuse me – the coterie will form automatically if the researcher is good and can get to students in any way at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is imperative to encourage the true research worker who is making contributions to science to make his home base in his own country. This should not be hard because there are strong feelings of patriotism in these men; they know they have a great deal to give their country and want to give it. The difficulty is the terrible problems they have at home. For example, the physics research center in Rio, which is one of the leading ones in Latin America, has become isolated from the rest of the world because of a very simple thing: Nobody wants to pay for the Physical Review or Nuovo Cimento. Nobody wants to pay for the journals that can keep people informed of what happens somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This, along with the fact that salaries are absurdly low, shows a lack of interest by the Brazilian government, people, and industry, in the development of science in this country. It is an attitude that does not respect or understand the value of these men. These creating scientists should have a dignity and a power to control their own destiny, and that of science and of science education in their countries. It will be in safe, loving hands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is from the fountain of research workers who understand what science is really about that the true spirit of inquiry rains onto their students, and their students' students, and ultimately, if things are organized right, permeates the entire educational system and speeds the technical development of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fourth problem, then, is how to get these research workers back into the universities where they belong. Then the "rain" will have a far easier and direct passage to the students, the new scientists of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I should like to emphasize, by addressing my fifth and final question to the problem, the importance of doing any of these things in a steady, consistent, continuous, and modest way. It should not be done with a big show, the big money, with much advertising, unsupported in the future by any effective maintenance. Maintenance is lacking in many of these projects, for these things have happened before. Pulses of energy have been liberated, forward steps have been taken, only to slip back for lack of continued support. It is necessary to keep up anything that works out. It is necessary to provide a continuous, consistent, perpetual support and to make things more modest so that continuity of support can be maintained. A research group becomes world famous only after years of fruitful research. One year of no support and people drift away and there is nothing left.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I appreciate that this is a problem of great difficulty and seriousness because it involves so closely all of the social and economic circumstances in the country, and the difficulties are often (but not always) merely the reflection of the vastly more serious problems of the varying fortune of the country as a whole. Yet we ought to discuss it further here. We might try to see if there are ways to work out a scheme so that the educational system, or at least such critical parts of it as research scientists or especially good teachers, is partially independent of the variations in success of the government.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps it should not be completely supported by government. Perhaps greater efforts to obtain private funds might work. Possibly more reliance on, and contact with, more permanent institutions like religious schools might sustain the continuity of these efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have discussed the problems as directly. and frankly as possible, as I see them. I don't mean to make any criticism, except in the same spirit as any discussion we shall have later will represent a criticism. For surely we shall not all find everything well with the present situation in physics education in Latin America. If so, we would not have had such a meeting. I have tried to avoid making too many specific active suggestions on how to proceed, because this is our job for the rest of this meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46266717</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 20:47:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI agents are starting to eat SaaS</title><link>https://martinalderson.com/posts/ai-agents-are-starting-to-eat-saas/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="35659a7c195f15d9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;AI agents are starting to eat SaaS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We spent fifteen years watching software eat the world. Entire industries got swallowed by software - retail, media, finance - you name it, there has been incredible disruption over the past couple of decades with a proliferation of SaaS tooling. This has led to a huge swath of SaaS companies - valued, collectively, in the trillions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my last post debating if the cost of software has dropped 90% with AI coding agents I mainly looked at the supply side of the market. What will happen to demand for SaaS tooling if this hypothesis plays out? I've been thinking a lot about these second and third order effects of the changes in software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The calculus on build vs buy is starting to change. Software ate the world. Agents are going to eat SaaS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The signals I'm seeing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The obvious place to start is simply demand starting to evaporate - especially for "simpler" SaaS tools. I'm sure many software engineers have started to realise this - many things I'd think to find a freemium or paid service for I can get an agent to often solve in a few minutes, exactly the way I want it. The interesting thing is I didn't even notice the shift. It just happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I want an internal dashboard, I don't even think that Retool or similar would make it easier. I just build the dashboard. If I need to re-encode videos as part of a media ingest process, I just get Claude Code to write a robust wrapper round ffmpeg - and not incur all the cost (and speed) of sending the raw files to a separate service, hitting tier limits or trying to fit another API's mental model in my head.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is even more pronounced for less pure software development tasks. For example, I've had Gemini 3 produce really high quality UI/UX mockups and wireframes in minutes - not needing to use a separate service or find some templates to start with. Equally, when I want to do a presentation, I don't need to use a platform to make my slides look nice - I just get Claude Code to export my markdown into a nicely designed PDF.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other, potentially more impactful, shift I'm starting to see is people really questioning renewal quotes from larger "enterprise" SaaS companies. While this is very early, I believe this is a really important emerging behaviour. I've seen a few examples now where SaaS vendor X sends through their usual annual double-digit % increase in price, and now teams are starting to ask "do we actually need to pay this, or could we just build what we need ourselves?". A year ago that would be a hypothetical question at best with a quick 'no' conclusion. Now it's a real option people are putting real effort into thinking through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, most SaaS products contain many features that many customers don't need or use. A lot of the complexity in SaaS product engineering is managing that - which evaporates overnight when you have only one customer (your organisation). And equally, this customer has complete control of the roadmap when it is the same person. No more hoping that the SaaS vendor prioritises your requests over other customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The maintenance objection&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key objection to this is "who maintains these apps?". Which is a genuine, correct objection to have. Software has bugs to fix, scale problems to solve, security issues to patch and that isn't changing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think firstly it's important to point out that a lot of SaaS is poorly maintained (and in my experience, often the more expensive it is, the poorer the quality). Often, the security risk comes from having an external third party itself needing to connect and interface with internal data. If you can just move this all behind your existing VPN or access solution, you suddenly reduce your organisation's attack surface dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On top of this, agents themselves lower maintenance cost dramatically. Some of the most painful maintenance tasks I've had - updating from deprecated libraries to another one with more support - are made significantly easier with agents, especially in statically typed programming ecosystems. Additionally, the biggest hesitancy with companies building internal tools is having one person know everything about it - and if they leave, all the internal knowledge goes. Agents don't leave. And with a well thought through AGENTS.md file, they can explain the codebase to anyone in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, SaaS comes with maintenance problems too. A recent flashpoint I've seen this month from a friend is a SaaS company deciding to deprecate their existing API endpoints and move to another set of APIs, which don't have all the same methods available. As this is an essential system, this is a huge issue and requires an enormous amount of resource to update, test and rollout the affected integrations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm not suggesting that SMEs with no real software knowledge are going to suddenly replace their entire SaaS suite. What I do think is starting to happen is that organisations with some level of tech capability and understanding are going to think even more critically at their SaaS procurement and vendor lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The economics problem for SaaS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SaaS valuations are built on two key assumptions: fast customer growth and high NRR (often exceeding 100%).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think we can start to see a world already where demand from new customers for certain segments of tooling and apps begins to decline. That's a problem, and will cause an increase in the sales and marketing expenditure of these companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the more insidious one is net revenue retention (NRR) declines. NRR is a measure of how much existing customers spend with you on an ongoing basis, adjusted for churn. If your NRR is at 100%, your existing cohort of customers are spending the same. If it's less than that then they are spending less with you and/or customers are leaving overall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many great SaaS companies have NRR significantly above 100%. This is the beauty of a lot of SaaS business models - companies grow and require more users added to their plan. Or they need to upgrade from a lower priced tier to a higher one to gain additional features. These increases are generally very profitable. You don't need to spend a fortune on sales and marketing to get this uptick (you already have a relationship with them) and the profit margin of adding another 100 user licenses to a SaaS product for a customer is somewhere close to infinity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where I think some SaaS companies will get badly hit. People will start migrating parts of the solution away to self-built/modified internal platforms to avoid having to pay significantly more for the next pricing tier up. Or they'll ingest the data from your platform via your APIs and build internal dashboards and reporting which means they can remove 80% of their user licenses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Where this doesn't work (and what still has a moat)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The obvious one is anything that requires very high uptime and SLAs. Getting to four or five 9s is really hard, and building high availability systems gets really difficult - and it's very easy to shoot yourself in the foot building them. As such, things like payment processing and other core infrastructure are pretty safe in my eyes. You're not (yet) going to replace Stripe and all their engineering work on core payments easily with an agent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Equally, very high volume systems and data lakes are difficult to replace. It's not trivial to spin up clusters for huge datasets or transaction volumes. This again requires specialised knowledge that is likely to be in short supply at your organisation, if it exists at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other one is software with significant network effects - where you collaborate with people, especially external to your organisation. Slack is a great example - it's not something you are going to replace with an in-house tool. Equally, products with rich integration ecosystems and plugin marketplaces have a real advantage here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And companies that have proprietary datasets are still very valuable. Financial data, sales intelligence and the like stay valuable. If anything, I think these companies have a real edge as agents can leverage this data in new ways - they get more locked in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And finally, regulation and compliance is still very important. Many industries require regulatory compliance - this isn't going to change overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This does require your organisation having the skills (internally or externally) to manage these newly created apps. I think products and people involved in SRE and DevOps are going to have a real upswing in demand. I suspect we'll see entirely new functions and teams in companies solely dedicated to managing these new applications. This does of course have a cost, but this cost can be often managed by existing SRE or DevOps functions, or if it requires new headcount and infrastructure, amortised over a much higher number of apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Who's most at risk?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To me the companies that are at serious risk are back-office tools that are really just CRUD logic - or simple dashboards and analytics on top of their customers' own data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These tools often generate a lot of friction - because they don't work exactly the way the customer wants them to - and they are tools that are the most easily replaced with agents. It's very easy to document the existing system and tell the agent to build something, but with the pain points removed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SaaS certainly isn't dead. Like any major shifts in technology, there are winners and losers. I do think the bar is going to be much higher for many SaaS products that don't have a clear moat or proprietary knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's going to be difficult to predict is how quickly agents can move up the value chain. I'm assuming that agents can't manage complex database clusters - but I'm not sure that's going to be the case for much longer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And I'm not seeing a path for every company to suddenly replace all their SaaS spend. If anything, I think we'll see (another) splintering in the market. Companies with strong internal technical ability vs those that don't. This becomes yet another competitive advantage for those that do - and those that don't will likely see dramatically increased costs as SaaS providers try and recoup some of the lost sales from the first group to the second who are less able to switch away.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But my key takeaway would be that if your product is just a SQL wrapper on a billing system, you now have thousands of competitors: engineers at your customers with a spare Friday afternoon with an agent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46268452</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 23:48:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>If AI replaces workers, should it also pay taxes?</title><link>https://english.elpais.com/technology/2025-11-30/if-ai-replaces-workers-should-it-also-pay-taxes.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bb8d1adbf8f78ec5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;If AI replaces workers, should it also pay taxes?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The technological race among industry giants and the wave of layoffs they have announced has revived the debate about the advisability of taxing automation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It can’t be seen or touched, but it’s shaking up markets and attracting investment. Artificial intelligence (AI) has become the object of desire for Big Tech, which is pouring astronomical sums into its development, fueled by record profits. The other side of this frenzy is workforce reductions, with automation as the backdrop, announced by multinationals like Amazon, Meta, and UPS, which, incidentally, threaten to extend the impact of new technologies to another area: public coffers. Fewer people working means fewer taxpayers, so the question naturally arises: if machines and algorithms replace humans in their jobs, should they also have to cover the taxes that humans stop paying?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Labor, through income tax and social security contributions, is one of the pillars of the tax systems of almost all countries, and the impact of automation on the tax base — or, in other words, the potential decrease in revenue — is not a new concern. In 2019, Nobel laureate Edmund Phelps proposed a tax on robots to help maintain social benefits. Shortly before, Bill Gates, founder of one of the world’s largest technology companies, Microsoft, which has its own artificial intelligence (Copilot), had suggested applying the same tax burden to robots as would be borne by the workers they replace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The trend toward automation and AI could lead to a decrease in tax revenues. In the United States, for example, about 85% of federal tax revenue comes from labor income,” says Sanjay Patnaik, director of the Center for Regulation and Markets at the Brookings Institution. He suggests that governments address “the risks posed by AI” by increasing capital gains taxation rather than creating a specific tax on it, due to the difficulties in designing such a tax and the distortions it could generate. The repeated use of the conditional tense is because the impact of generative AI, the kind capable of creating content on demand, is still uncertain, both in positive terms — improved productivity and economic growth — and negative terms; job losses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even so, forecasts are mixed. Goldman Sachs, for example, estimates that AI will boost global GDP by 7% over the next decade; the IMF predicts it will contribute up to eight-tenths of a percentage point annually to growth between now and 2030. On the other hand, the International Labour Organization estimates that one in four workers worldwide, concentrated in high-income countries, holds a job with some degree of exposure to AI, but at the same time predicts that most jobs will be transformed rather than disappear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“We know there will be an impact, but it’s difficult to quantify,” confirms Luz Rodríguez, a professor of labor law and a former Spanish Secretary of State for Employment. “The previous wave of automation affected employment in the middle of the production chain; generative AI is targeting higher up the ladder, more skilled jobs that require critical thinking,” she summarizes. “I’m not optimistic, but I am positive: there are jobs being created that wouldn’t exist without new technologies, such as content moderators on social media or Bitcoin miners.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Daniel Waldenström, a professor at the Stockholm Institute for Industrial Economics, rejects the idea of a specific tax on AI, arguing that there has been no significant increase in unemployment, even in the United States, the birthplace of these new technologies and a leader in their implementation. He also emphasizes the difficulty in defining it precisely: “What are automation, robots, or AI? A chip, a humanoid machine, an application, or a computer program? We will never be able to define it precisely. We should continue taxing what already exists: income from labor, consumption, and capital gains.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The International Monetary Fund (IMF) has also joined the debate. In a report published last summer, the organization’s economists reached a mixed conclusion: they did not recommend specifically taxing AI — as this could stifle productivity and distort the market — but urged governments to remain vigilant against potential disruptive scenarios. Their proposals included raising taxes on capital — which have been decreasing as the tax burden on labor has increased — creating a supplementary tax on “excessive” corporate profits, and reviewing tax incentives for innovation, patents, and other intangible assets that, while boosting productivity, can also displace human jobs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carl Frey, associate professor of AI and Work at Oxford University and author of the book How Progress Ends (Princeton University Press, 2025), holds a similar view: he does not support an AI tax, but acknowledges that the tax system has become unbalanced. “In many OECD economies, we have seen an increase in income taxes and a decrease in capital taxes,” he notes. This system incentivizes companies to invest more in automation than in job-creating technologies. “Addressing this imbalance is essential to supporting the job-creating technologies of the future.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recent moves by major tech companies and the evolution of tax systems in recent years justify this concern. Amazon, for example, has announced a 38% increase in profits and multimillion-dollar investments in AI, while simultaneously reporting 14,000 job cuts worldwide. Meanwhile, corporate tax rates have plummeted in the last decade in OECD countries, from 33% in 2000 to the current 25%; the tax wedge for workers — income tax and social security contributions — has decreased by only 1.3 percentage points in the same period, from 36.2% to 34.9%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Susanne Bieller, secretary general of the International Federation of Robotics, argues that applying ad hoc taxes stems from “a problem that doesn’t exist,” since automation and robots “create new jobs by increasing productivity.” She warns that taxing production tools instead of business profits “would have a negative impact” on competitiveness and employment. “We need incentives for [European] companies to use technologies like robots and digitalization to remain competitive globally,” she concludes. “The world faces a labor shortage of approximately 40 million jobs per year [...] Robots cannot take over entire jobs, but they can handle certain tasks.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Inequality&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to employment, the soaring spending of major tech companies on AI and the surge in their stock prices are causing concern, raising fears of a bubble. Analysts also warn that the energy consumption of these technologies is so high that their climate footprint could offset the promised growth benefits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the best-case scenario, the new jobs created by AI could be “more productive, better paid, and more accessible,” offsetting job and tax losses, predicts Patnaik. However, the latent — and very likely — risk remains that the process will not be automatic. Job creation could be delayed, less-skilled professionals could struggle to adapt, and a gap could emerge between countries — and within them — and across productive sectors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MIT economists Daron Acemoğlu and Simon Johnson warned about this in 2023. “Over the past four decades, automation has increased productivity and multiplied corporate profits, but it has not led to shared prosperity in industrialized countries,” they cautioned in a document for the IMF. “Technology and artificial intelligence produce social impacts that are relevant to politics. We cannot allow technological determinism,” Rodríguez asserts. “The debate is necessary, and we will go wherever we want to go.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sign up for our weekly newsletter to get more English-language news coverage from EL PAÍS USA Edition&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tu suscripción se está usando en otro dispositivo&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;¿Quieres añadir otro usuario a tu suscripción?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Si continúas leyendo en este dispositivo, no se podrá leer en el otro.&lt;/p&gt;Flecha&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tu suscripción se está usando en otro dispositivo y solo puedes acceder a EL PAÍS desde un dispositivo a la vez.&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Si quieres compartir tu cuenta, cambia tu suscripción a la modalidad Premium, así podrás añadir otro usuario. Cada uno accederá con su propia cuenta de email, lo que os permitirá personalizar vuestra experiencia en EL PAÍS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;¿Tienes una suscripción de empresa? Accede aquí para contratar más cuentas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;En el caso de no saber quién está usando tu cuenta, te recomendamos cambiar tu contraseña aquí.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Si decides continuar compartiendo tu cuenta, este mensaje se mostrará en tu dispositivo y en el de la otra persona que está usando tu cuenta de forma indefinida, afectando a tu experiencia de lectura. Puedes consultar aquí los términos y condiciones de la suscripción digital.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More information&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Archived In&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Últimas noticias&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Most viewed&lt;/head&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Cartels in Mexico take a leap forward with narco-drones: ‘It is criminal groups that are leading the innovation race’&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;A mountaineer, accused of manslaughter for the death of his partner during a climb: He silenced his phone and refused a helicopter rescue&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The number of international tourists going to the US is decreasing, with one exception: Mexico&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Belle da Costa, the woman who concealed her origins in 1905 and ended up running New York’s most legendary library&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Christian Louboutin: ‘Young people don’t want to be like their parents. And if their parents wear sneakers, they’re going to look for something else’&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46268709</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:17:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Roomba maker goes bankrupt, Chinese owner emerges</title><link>https://news.bloomberglaw.com/bankruptcy-law/robot-vacuum-roomba-maker-files-for-bankruptcy-after-35-years</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f9da18deaae6b794"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Massachusetts-based consumer robot maker, which is currently listed, will be taken over by Chinaâs Shenzhen PICEA Robotics Co. and a subsidiary of the Chinese firm, according to a &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;iRobot enjoyed initial success with ...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Learn more about Bloomberg Law or Log In to keep reading:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;See Breaking News in Context&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bloomberg Law provides trusted coverage of current events enhanced with legal analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Already a subscriber?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Log in to keep reading or access research tools and resources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46268854</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>CapROS: Capability-Based Reliable Operating System</title><link>https://www.capros.org/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="29b6dd144fce0faf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CapROS is a new operating system that merges some very old ideas about capabilities with some newer ideas about performance and resource management. The result is a small, secure, real-time operating system that provides orthogonal persistence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CapROS Overview&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mailing List&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Programmer's Guide&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kernel Development Guide&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Building CapROS&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Project Summary on GitHub&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Design Notes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;The EROS System This is an archival site that is known to have some broken links.&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;The KeyKOS system&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CapROS is the continuation of the EROS project. CapROS owes a great debt to Jonathan Shapiro and all who supported that project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The CapROS project is hosted on GitHub. We thank GitHub for its support of open source software, including this project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Copyright 2005, 2008, 2009, 2016 by Strawberry Development Group. Copyright 2022 by Charles Landau. All rights reserved. For terms of redistribution, see the GNU General Public License&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46268869</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:39:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>SoundCloud has banned VPN access</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/SoundCloudMusic/comments/1pltd19/soundcloud_just_banned_vpn_access/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46269891</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 02:51:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>John Varley has died</title><link>http://floggingbabel.blogspot.com/2025/12/john-varley-1947-2025.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b4b038159542cfc9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;John Varley died two days ago on December 10, 2025. A great many will mourn him as a science fiction writer whose work they enjoyed. But this misses his moment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the mid-1970s, Varley exploded into science fiction like a phoenix. His "Eight Worlds" stories were set in a future where hyper-powerful aliens have killed everyone on Earth as a threat to its whales and porpoises and humanity survives everywhere else in the Solar System. Despite this bleak background, the stories were bright and inventive. People change gender on a whim. Wealthy and glorious cities turn to shacks and hovels when their holographic fronts are turned off at night. People bank their memories so that, upon death, they can be restarted with new memories. He wrote so many major stories per year that, in a resurrection of an old pulp-days practice, some had to be published under a pseudonym.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We were all dazzled. His work was full of impressive new ideas. And, outside of the Eight Worlds sequence, he wrote things like "In the Hall of the Martian Kings," which resurrected the possibility of intelligent life on Mars after the Mariner probes had apparently disproved that. Or "Air Raid," which made air travel terrifying again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His novel Titan looked to be the opening of a classic trilogy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Briefly--for almost a decade--John Varley seemed to be the new Robert Heinlein.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then, alas, he went to Hollywood.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hollywood paid him to write, rewrite, and rererewrite a script for Millennium (based on "Air Raid") while five directors came and went. Unsurprisingly, the result pleased nobody--most particularly Varley himself. His novelization of the movie made that abundantly clear. Then, by the man's own testimony, he was paid more and more and more money to write scripts that were never made.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After too long an absence, Varley returned to print. He was every bit as good a writer as he'd ever been. But his ideas were no longer new. In his absence, writers like William Gibson and Neal Stephenson had moved the cutting edge along.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thereafter, Varley was only a very good science fiction writer. It is this person that most of his readers will mourn.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I will mourn the man who, for a time, seemed to be the resurrection of science fiction, the New Heinlein, the kwisatz haderach of genre. Back then, he set the standard. His were the stories we all wanted to equal and perhaps surpass. He was the reason we read science fiction in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Long, long ago, when I was yet unpublished, I found myself talking with Isaac Asimov at I forget which convention, when John Varley cruised by, trailed by enthusiastic fans. Asimov gazed sadly after him and said, "Look at him. A decade ago, everybody was asking, 'Who is John Varley?' A decade from now, everybody will be asking, 'Who is Isaac Asimov?'"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that was John Varley's moment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Above: Photo taken from Worlds Without End. Go here to explore it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46269991</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 03:04:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rob Reiner has died</title><link>https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/movies/movie-news/rob-reiner-dead-harry-met-sally-princess-bride-all-in-family-1236450387/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b729d0fbbd07d1e7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rob Reiner, who directed such beloved Hollywood classics as This Is Spinal Tap, Stand by Me and When Harry Met Sally after starring in the trailblazing sitcom All in the Family, died Sunday along with his wife, Michele, in their Brentwood home. He was 78.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reiner and his wife, 70, were found dead in their home on Chadbourne Avenue, with the couple “suffering lacerations consistent with a knife,” law enforcement sources told TMZ. There reportedly was no sign of forced entry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Said a spokesperson for the family: “It is with profound sorrow that we announce the tragic passing of Michele and Rob Reiner. We are heartbroken by this sudden loss, and we ask for privacy during this unbelievably difficult time.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Related Stories&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Reiners’ son Nick, 32, has been arrested by the Los Angeles County Sheriff’s Department. He battled drug addiction and homelessness, had more than a dozen stints in rehab and co-wrote a film loosely based on his life, Being Charlie (2015), that was directed by his father.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Near the scene Sunday just before 9 p.m., LAPD chief of detectives Alan Hamilton said “we have not identified a suspect at this time,” there “was no person of interest” and that many family members would be interviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Los Angeles Fire Department had been called to the Reiners’ home at about 3:40 p.m. by an unidentified person, and LAPD Robbery Homicide Division detectives were investigating.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Princess Bride (1987), Misery (1990), the Oscar best picture nominee A Few Good Men (1992), The American President (1995) and The Bucket List (2007) also were among Rob Reiner’s 20-plus directing credits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reiner was also a co-founder of Castle Rock Entertainment, the production company behind such films as City Slickers (1991), The Shawshank Redemption (1994), Waiting for Guffman (1996), Miss Congeniality (2000), Best in Show (2000), Michael Clayton (2007) and Seinfeld, one of the most lucrative television properties of all time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the outset of his feature directorial career with This Is Spinal Tap (1984), Reiner seemed to reimagine Hollywood standards, creating and starring in the first mainstream mockumentary — a rock ’n’ roll satire so dead-on, film critic Roger Ebert called it “one of the funniest movies ever made.” From there, he would move seamlessly from comedy to drama, from fantasy to horror, as few directors ever have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reiner would establish yet another benchmark — this time for romantic comedies — with When Harry Met Sally (1989), screenwriter Nora Ephron’s ode to true love (based loosely on her and Reiner’s lives) that starred Billy Crystal and Meg Ryan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His biggest box office hit, the gripping courtroom drama A Few Good Men, based on Aaron Sorkin’s 1989 play and starring Tom Cruise and Jack Nicholson, could not have been more different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of Reiner’s movies took a while to capture the world’s attention. The Princess Bride, his timeless fairy tale adventure that was based on the William Goldman novel and starred Robin Wright, Mandy Patinkin and Peter Falk, was one of several films that grew in popularity over decades on the way to cult status.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On television, Reiner played to some of the biggest audiences in history, first in the role of Michael “Meathead” Stivic, the liberal antagonist of Carroll O’Connor’s Archie Bunker, on CBS’ All in the Family, and then as a ground-floor executive on NBC’s Seinfeld, which he fought to keep on the air.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We knew we had a great show,” Reiner told Howard Stern in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But after a rocky launch in the summer of 1989, the network was concerned that Seinfeld — famously a show “about nothing” — was a misfire. After four episodes, it was on the brink of cancellation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I went in there and had a screaming crazy thing with [NBC president] Brandon Tartikoff,” Reiner said. “And I promised him — there will be stories!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1993, Reiner and Castle Rock partners Andrew Scheinman, Alan Horn, Glenn Padnick and Martin Shafer sold their company to broadcast mogul Ted Turner for about $160 million. (It became part of Time Warner when it acquired Turner Broadcasting in 1996.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The principals stayed on, holding to their original ideal: to make independent movies outside the traditional studio system. But after a run of poorly performing films starting in the late ’90s, Castle Rock initiated layoffs and eventually was absorbed into Warner Bros.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2020, Reiner relaunched the company and revived its film division a year later, with Spinal Tap II: The End Continues (2025) among its offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“There’s not one film that I’ve ever made that could get made today by a studio, not one — even A Few Good Men,” Reiner said. “Every movie that I make, have made and will make is always going to be independently financed.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Throughout his behind-the-camera career, Reiner continued as a working actor. He played the well-intentioned plastic surgeon Dr. Morris Packman, who affectionately spars with Goldie Hawn, in The First Wives Club (1996); Tom Hanks’ pal in Ephron’s Sleepless in Seattle (1993); the father of Zooey Deschanel on the 2011-18 Fox sitcom New Girl; and restaurant consultant Albert Schnurr on Hulu’s The Bear this year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He was particularly memorable in Martin Scorsese’s The Wolf of Wall Street (2013) as stockbroker Max Belfort in scenes with Leonardo DiCaprio and Jonah Hill that were largely improvised.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reiner’s sense of what worked onscreen was honed early on — first at home as the oldest child of comedy icon Carl Reiner and later around his dad’s close friends, among them Sid Caesar, Neil Simon, Mel Brooks and the most influential of all, Norman Lear, the TV auteur whose 1970s activist comedies All in the Family, The Jeffersons, Good Times and Maude sparked seismic shifts in popular culture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Norman was the first guy who recognized that I had any talent,” Reiner wrote for The Hollywood Reporter in the wake of Lear’s 2023 death, noting that he viewed him as “a second father.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It wasn’t just that he hired me for All in the Family,” Reiner told American Masters in 2005. “It was that I saw, in how he conducted his life, that there was room to be an activist as well. That you could use your celebrity, your good fortune, to help make some change.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the Hollywood scion forged his directing career, it was Lear who put up the money for Stand by Me (1986) and Reiner’s other early films, including the John Cusack-Nicollette Sheridan romp The Sure Thing (1985), lauded for elevating the teen comedy genre.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stand by Me — regarded as among the finest of coming-of-age movies — marked Reiner’s ascent into Hollywood’s highest ranks, no longer just a sitcom actor or the genial ex-husband of a fellow TV comic, Penny Marshall, star of Laverne &amp;amp; Shirley. (Marshall too would go on to become a top Hollywood director.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Famed author-screenwriter Goldman, who penned the Misery screenplay, said Reiner became a success because his work is “funny, but not simpy.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“His films have a certain comedy style … a sweetness and toughness,” Goldman told The New York Times in 1987. “Stand by Me is not just about four kids coming of age before junior high school — they’re going to see a corpse. If John Hughes had made Stand by Me — and I’m not knocking Hughes — they would have been searching for a convertible.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stephen King, author of the 1982 novella The Body (on which Stand by Me was based) and the 1987 novel Misery, became one of Reiner’s most-steadfast collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among other King books turned into movies by Castle Rock — Reiner named the company for the fictional setting in many of the author’s novels — were Shawshank, The Green Mile (1999)and Dolores Claiborne (1995).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After several false starts, King finally agreed to develop Misery for the screen, but only if Reiner put “his name on it” as producer or director.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It was a very personal book to him,” Reiner told TCM in 2021. “It was all about himself as a writer and feeling trapped … And so he let us option the book for $1. In fact, I think we made seven Stephen King films, and each one of them we got an option for $1.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 1990 Kathy Bates-James Caan starrer remains one of Hollywood’s finest horror pieces, with Bates winning an Oscar for her role as the obsessive fan Annie Wilkes, who tortures author Paul Sheldon (Caan) while holding him hostage in her remote cabin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Rob had a fantastic crew of people — people he had worked with for years, just the creme de la creme,” Bates said of the Misery shoot in a 2020 interview with Vanity Fair. “I learned so much just hanging out [on set] and watching.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bates, 42 years old at the time, had predominantly been a stage actress. At the Academy Awards, where she bested Meryl Streep, Joanne Woodward, Anjelica Huston and Julia Roberts, she thanked Reiner “for taking a chance on me.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Often the most memorable scenes in Reiner’s filmography came from his comedies — notably Ryan’s climactic moment in When Harry Met Sally in which she feigns an orgasm over lunch with Crystal’s character at Katz’s Deli.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet it was Reiner’s mother, Estelle Reiner, who landed the film’s renowned punchline: “I’ll have what she’s having.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I said to her, mom, the line you have is the last line in the scene, and if it doesn’t pop and top everything that’s come before it, I won’t use it,” Reiner told the AFI in a joint interview with Ephron in 2009. “We’ll shoot it but be prepared, it might have to be cut.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“And she said, ‘I don’t care, I just wanna spend the day with you and be with you on the set. I don’t care if it’s in the movie or not.’”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Robert Reiner was born in the Bronx on March 6, 1947, one of three children of the former Estelle Lebost, an artist and set designer, and Carl Reiner, the comic and writer who got his start as an entertainer in the U.S. Army and then in Broadway musicals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The family lived just off Grand Concourse, across the street from Marshall and her brother, future writer-producer-director Garry Marshall. But it would be decades before Rob and Penny actually met — at the 1970 audition in Los Angeles for the roles of Mike and Gloria Stivik on All in the Family. (The role of Gloria, of course, would go to Sally Struthers.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Carl’s career gained steam (he would win 11 Emmys), the family moved to Bonnie Meadow Road in the bucolic New York suburb of New Rochelle. It was the very street where Reiner would set his landmark 1960s CBS sitcom The Dick Van Dyke Show, about a rising comedy writer, Rob Petrie, and his beautiful wife, Laura.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Basically he wrote his own life in The Dick Van Dyke Show,” Rob Reiner said of his father. “And my mother was Mary Tyler Moore.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rob got his start as an apprentice at the Bucks County Playhouse in Pennsylvania and with small guest roles on such shows as That Girl, Room 222 and The Beverly Hillbillies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After UCLA Film School in 1967, he was paired with another young comic, Steve Martin, as a writing team on CBS’ The Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour. The two were barely out of their teens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The All in the Family role, for which Reiner would win two Emmys, followed in 1971. Convinced the show’s incendiary subject matter would be rejected by viewers, he initially viewed the gig as a stopgap to tide him over between writing gigs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the sitcom became a hit (Reiner stayed for eight of its nine seasons), he continued writing anyway, penning four episodes of the show and co-writing (with Garry Marshall and Phil Mishkin) the first episode of ABC’s Happy Days in 1974.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a filmmaker notably surrounding himself with many of the industry’s top writers — Goldman, King, Sorkin, Ephron, Crystal — Reiner showcased their dialogue to everlasting effect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Princess Bride’s “Hello, my name is Inigo Montoya. You killed my father. Prepare to die”; Misery’s “I’m your No. 1 fan”; A Few Good Men’s “You can’t handle the truth”; and When Harry Met Sally’s “I’ll have what she’s having” (Crystal actually came up with that line) reigned in pop culture for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But as Penny Marshall would humorously point out, no matter how substantive their accomplishments, “For me, all they say is ‘Laverne,’ and for Rob … it’s ‘Meathead,’” she told the New Yorker in 2012. “We’re stuck with it.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The couple performed together infrequently but did co-star in the well-received 1978 romantic comedy More Than Friends. The ABC telefilm, written by Reiner and Mishkin and directed by James Burrows, was something of a precursor to When Harry Met Sally, about childhood pals unsure if they should pursue love as adults.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reiner also made an appearance as “Sheldn” (no “o”), the fiancé of Penny’s Myrna Turner, on Garry Marshall’s ABC series The Odd Couple.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Their 10-year marriage came to an end in 1981 — amid tension as Laverne &amp;amp; Shirley shot Marshall to superstardom while Reiner was quietly forging his post-sitcom film career.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upon Marshall’s death in 2018, Reiner professed his admiration for her, tweeting “so sad about Penny.” He added, “I loved Penny. I grew up with her. She was born with a great gift. She was born with a funny bone and the instinct of how to use it. I was very lucky to have lived with her and her funny bone. I will miss her.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The couple were the parents of actress Tracy Reiner, born in 1964 to Marshall during a brief first marriage and adopted by Reiner soon after their 1971 wedding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1989, Reiner married Michele Singer, a photographer whom he met on the set of When Harry Met Sally. He said she was the inspiration for the film’s happily-ever-after script change. In 2020, she joined Reiner in running Castle Rock and produced films.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to Nick, the couple had two other children, son Jake and daughter Romy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lifelong political activist who with King was among the public figures to urge President Joe Biden to hand the 2024 re-election reins to Kamala Harris, Reiner rarely missed a week on social media, penning calls to action on a range of social justice issues for his millions of followers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He was among Hollywood’s most vigorous and constant voices opposing Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among his other causes, Reiner was the co-founder of the American Foundation for Equal Rights, which fought to overturn California’s ban on same-sex marriage. In the late-’90s, he and his father were activists for higher taxes on cigarettes — money that was earmarked for prenatal care.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His advocacy was often part of his writing and filmmaking, from his earliest days with the Smothers brothers to LBJ (2016) and Shock and Awe (2017), about journalists investigating the Bush administration’s 2003 invasion of Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reiner was often a Hollywood peacemaker, well known for putting actors and crew at ease. When Bates and Caan clashed early in the production of Misery (she liked rehearsing; he preferred winging it), Reiner brokered a wary peace while using the tension to elicit superb performances.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I want everyone around me to feel comfortable and happy,” he told The Guardian in 2018. “People only act up out of insecurity, and when they make it difficult, I just say, ‘We’re playing make-believe here — enjoy yourself!’”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mike Barnes, Kimberly Nordyke and Scott Feinberg contributed to this report.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;THR Newsletters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sign up for THR news straight to your inbox every day&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46270273</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 03:54:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Unscii</title><link>http://viznut.fi/unscii/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a550b01e7a8d1955"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unscii is a set of bitmapped Unicode fonts based on classic system fonts. Unscii attempts to support character cell art well while also being suitable for terminal and programming use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two main variants are unscii-8 (8Ã8 pixels per glyph) and unscii-16 (8Ã16). There are also several alternative styles for unscii-8, as well as an 8x16 "full" variant that incorporates missing Unicode glyphs from Fixedsys Excelsior and GNU Unifont. "unscii-16-full" falls under GPL because of how Unifont is licensed; the other variants are in the Public Domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unscii was created by Viznut.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2020-03-10, the new Unicode version 13.0 added 214 graphics characters for "legacy computing" (including, among all, the missing PETSCII characters, and a majority of missing Teletext/Videotex characters). Most of these were already included in Unscii 1.x, but now I have been able to give them proper Unicode mappings as well. This is the main reason for the Unscii 2.0 release.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additionally, Unscii 2.0 fixes errors in some characters, legibility in some others and adds a bunch of new ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A test picture representing what is currently available in Unicode (feel free to copy-paste it to your editor to see what it looks like in other fonts):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;âââ â±ð½âð¾â² ð®²ð®³ ð®¸ð®ð®µð®¶ð®ð®ð®ð®ð®¼ð¯ð¯ð¯ âµ â â¬ â¶ââ´âºââ¸ â âââ â¹ â¸â£â¹ â¸ âââââ ð¯²ð¯·ð¯¶ â³ â´ â½ ââ¬â® â·ââ¬âââ¯âââ¤ââââ ð®· ð¼âð¿ â¸ âââââ ð¯¹ð¯µð¯± ð¯° âââââ âââ ââ ââ³â·â»â¹ â² ââ¼ââ¾â â©â¬â¬ âââ¼â¤ââ¿â¥ââªâ¡âââ â¹â± â³ â²â¸ âââââ ð¯´ð¯³ð¯¸ âð®ð® ð®âð®ð®ââ¹ â½ âââð®½â¶âºâ¸â¿ â® â¬â§â«â¨â¬ âµââ´âââ·âââ§ââââ¦ âââââ ð¬ð¬ð¬°ð¬ªð¬ ð®ð® ââ ââ¡â¯â¡ âðµ â¿ â¼ â â®ââ® â¬â¬âª â»ââ°âââ³â ââââ â®ââââ ð¬¥ð¬¦ð¬ð¬²ð¬µð¬¹ð¬±ð¬·ð¬ð¬ð¬ ð®ð® ð®âââ â¯ââ¯â¡âð´ â¾ â® â â¬ â ââ ââ¨â£ââ« âºâ½ââââ¾â â ââ ð¬ð¬¡ð¬ð¬»ð¬ð¬ð¬ð¬ºð¬¢ð¬ð¬§ ð®ââ â â¯â â ð³ â¿âº â¹ââ¸âââ»â ââµââââ¶ââââ ð¬ð¬¤ð¬«ð¬´ð¬ ð¬ð¬ð¬¸ð¬ð¬ð¬ ðð¬¼ ââ âð®£ð®¢ ð®¦ ð² â¹â¸ ð¯ ð®ââð® ð¯ âââ¶ââµ ââ¥â ââ¦ââ¢ââª ââ±â²â§ ð¬£ð¬¯ð¬ð¬¬ð¬ð¬ð¬ð¬ð¬ ð¬®ð¬ ð¢ð ð®â ð®¤ð®ªð®«ð®¥ð®§ ð± ð¯ ð®âð¬ââî¡±ââ®â«ð®»â§ ââââ²â¼â±âââ® âââ«â¢ð®ð®ð®â â¬â£ â¹â â¡â¹âºâ© ð¬³ð¬ð¬©ð¬ð¬ð¬ð¬ð¬¨ð¬ð¬ð¬¶ ðð¬¿ ð®â ð®©ð®¬ð®ð®¨ ð° â¢ð«â£ ð® â â¢ î¡°â®ðâª âââ·â¼â´ââââ ââ¨âð® ð®ââ©â ð¯ ð¯ ð¯ ð®£ð®¢ ð¯ ð¯ ð¥ð ð®âð®® ð®¡ð® â¸ð®ðªâð¨ð®ð®¿ð¬â°âð®¯ââ¯â¬â¯â¨ â³ââ°â°ââ¯ ââð®ð®ð®ââââð®ð®â¤â¤â¥â¥â¦â¦â©â©â§â§ð®ð®ð®ð®â¨â¨ð®ð®ð®ð® ðð ââð»ðºð¹ð¸ð·ð¶â â¥ð©â¤ ð â®â¯âª â±â° ââ¬ âââð®âââââð®ð®â¤â¤â¥â¥â¦â¦â©â©â§â§ð®ð®ð®ð®â¨â¨ð®ð®ð®ð® ð¦ð ð®° ðð¬¼ð ðð¬¿ ðð ââ¯â© â¯â® â«â»â¡â â¼âªâ¬Â· ð®âð® â²â± ðð¬¼ðð¬½ðð¬¾â¢â£ðððð¬¼ðððððð¬½ðððð¬¾ðððð¬½ð ð â¦ââ¯â¬¤ââ â¬«â¬¦â¬¨â¢ââââ¦â¬§â¬¥â¬©â¬ª âð®â ð¢ðð£ðð¤ðâ¥â¤ð¢ðððð£ð§ððððð¤ðððð£ðð ððð¡ âââ ð¢ð ð¥ð ð¦ð â¢&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some conversions of legacy character set art into Unscii.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amiga ansi: Divine Stylers by Hellbeard, as rendered with unscii-16. Source&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PC ansi: Ansi Love by Rad Man, as rendered with unscii-16. Source&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commodore 64 petscii pictures as rendered with unscii-8, using the 256-color xterm palette: I Has Floppy by Redcrab; The First Ball by Dr.TerrorZ; Gary by Mermaid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The source code package includes a generic bitmap-to-unscii converter. Here's an example of a conversion to unscii-8 using the 256-color xterm palette, without dithering:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;HEX and PCF are the only actual bitmapped formats here. HEX is the same simple hexdump format as used by the Unifont project. TTF, OTF and WOFF are vectorized.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NOTE: Due to format limitations, the PCF versions lack all the characters above U+FFFF! However, all the new graphics characters are provided in the good old PUA range as well. A mapping is in the file uns2uni.tr.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;unscii-16: hex pcf ttf otf woff&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;unscii-8-tall: hex pcf ttf otf woff&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;unscii-8-thin: hex pcf ttf otf woff&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;unscii-8-alt: hex pcf ttf otf woff&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;unscii-8-mcr: hex pcf ttf otf woff&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;unscii-8-fantasy: hex pcf ttf otf woff&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Years ago, I noticed that Unicode had a bunch of pseudographic characters that could be used to enrichen Ansi art. However, no one seemed to use them. Even MUDs that used the 256-color Xterm palette and had no issues with Unicode still preferred to stick to the blocks available in the MS-DOS codepage 437.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After looking into existing Unicode fonts, the reason became obvious: the implementation of non-CP437 graphics characters was shaky at best. Unicode Consortium doesn't even care how pseudographics are implemented. It was a kind of chicken-and-egg problem: No commonly accepted Unicode graphics font, no Unicode art scene; no art scene, no font support. The idea of an art-compatible Unicode font was born.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Unscii, I studied a bunch of classic system fonts and how their characters had been used in Ascii and "extended-Ascii" art.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;8Ã8 system fonts can be divided in two major categories according to their line thickness: 1-pixel and 2-pixel. 2-pixel-wide lines are used in more prominent classic systems, so I chose it. Also, 2-pixel 8Ã8 system fonts are surprisingly similar to one another which made it easier to choose neutral shapes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The basic look of the 8Ã8 variant of Unscii is based on the following systems:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 8Ã16 variant of Unscii has been mostly derived from the 8Ã8 variant by using a set of transformation principles. When in doubt, the following fonts have been looked at for additional reference:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In general, neutral shapes are preferred, unless art, legibility or readability require otherwise: The characters /\XY are connective because of their connetive use in ascii art, and the serifs in iIl are longer than in most classic systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Whenever a 8Ã16 shape has not been defined, Unscii falls back to height-doubled 8Ã8.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also studied game fonts and thin-line system fonts. This resulted in the variants unscii-8-thin, unscii-8-mcr and unscii-8-fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When studying legacy character sets, I found literally hundreds of characters without proper Unicode codepoints. These are mapped in the PUA range as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since Unicode 13.0, many of these are also available in Unicode, but the PUA mappings are retained for compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46270282</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 03:55:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Arborium: Tree-sitter code highlighting with Native and WASM targets</title><link>https://arborium.bearcove.eu/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="fe558a1f8be50886"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finding good tree-sitter grammars is hard. In arborium, every grammar:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We hand-picked grammars, added missing highlight queries, and updated them to the latest tree-sitter. Tree-sitter parsers compiled to WASM need libc symbols (especially a C allocator)—we provide arborium-sysroot which re-exports dlmalloc and other essentials for wasm32-unknown-unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; HTML — custom elements like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-k&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; instead of
                        &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;span class="keyword"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. More compact markup. No
                        JavaScript required.
                    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;span class="keyword"&amp;gt;fn&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-k&amp;gt;fn&amp;lt;/a-k&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;ANSI — 24-bit true color for terminal applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;macOS, Linux, Windows — tree-sitter handles generating native crates for these platforms. Just add the dependency and go.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WebAssembly — that one's hard. Compiling Rust to WASM with C code that assumes a standard library is tricky. We provide a sysroot that makes this work, enabling Rust-on-the-frontend scenarios like this demo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Highlight TOML, shell, and other languages in your rustdoc. Create &lt;code&gt;arborium-header.html&lt;/code&gt;:
                            &lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script defer src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/@arborium/arborium@1/dist/arborium.iife.js"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then in &lt;code&gt;Cargo.toml&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[package.metadata.docs.rs]
rustdoc-args = ["--html-in-header", "arborium-header.html"]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt; If you maintain docs.rs or rustdoc, you could integrate arborium directly! Either merge this PR for native rustdoc support, or use &lt;code&gt;arborium-rustdoc&lt;/code&gt; as a
                                post-processing step:
                            &lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Process rustdoc output in-place
arborium-rustdoc ./target/doc ./target/doc-highlighted&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt; It streams through HTML, finds &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;pre class="language-*"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
                                blocks, and highlights them in-place. Works with rustdoc's theme system.
                            &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Syntax highlighting for miette error diagnostics. Beautiful, accurate highlighting in your CLI error messages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;use miette::GraphicalReportHandler;
use miette_arborium::ArboriumHighlighter;

let handler = GraphicalReportHandler::new()
    .with_syntax_highlighting(ArboriumHighlighter::new());&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;An incremental static site generator with zero-reload live updates via WASM DOM patching, Sass/SCSS, image processing, font subsetting, and arborium-powered syntax highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nothing to configure—it just works. Arborium is built in and automatically highlights all code blocks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; 96 languages included, each behind a feature flag. Enable only what you need, or use &lt;code&gt;all-languages&lt;/code&gt; for everything.
                    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each feature flag comment includes the grammar's license, so you always know what you're shipping.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The highlighter supports themes for both HTML and ANSI output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundled themes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code/&gt;
    Alabaster
&lt;code/&gt;
    Ayu Dark
&lt;code/&gt;
    Ayu Light
&lt;code/&gt;
    Catppuccin Frappé
&lt;code/&gt;
    Catppuccin Latte
&lt;code/&gt;
    Catppuccin Macchiato
&lt;code/&gt;
    Catppuccin Mocha
&lt;code/&gt;
    Cobalt2
&lt;code/&gt;
    Dayfox
&lt;code/&gt;
    Desert256
&lt;code/&gt;
    Dracula
&lt;code/&gt;
    EF Melissa Dark
&lt;code/&gt;
    GitHub Dark
&lt;code/&gt;
    GitHub Light
&lt;code/&gt;
    Gruvbox Dark
&lt;code/&gt;
    Gruvbox Light
&lt;code/&gt;
    Kanagawa Dragon
&lt;code/&gt;
    Light Owl
&lt;code/&gt;
    Lucius Light
&lt;code/&gt;
    Melange Dark
&lt;code/&gt;
    Melange Light
&lt;code/&gt;
    Monokai
&lt;code/&gt;
    Nord
&lt;code/&gt;
    One Dark
&lt;code/&gt;
    Rosé Pine Moon
&lt;code/&gt;
    Rustdoc Ayu
&lt;code/&gt;
    Rustdoc Dark
&lt;code/&gt;
    Rustdoc Light
&lt;code/&gt;
    Solarized Dark
&lt;code/&gt;
    Solarized Light
&lt;code/&gt;
    Tokyo Night
&lt;code/&gt;
    Zenburn
&lt;p&gt;Custom themes can be defined programmatically using RGB colors and style attributes (bold, italic, underline, strikethrough).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arborium uses custom HTML elements to mark up syntax. Each tag corresponds to a semantic code element. To create custom themes, target these elements in your CSS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-k&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Keyword&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-f&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Function&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-s&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — String&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-c&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Comment&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-t&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Type&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-v&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Variable&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-co&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Constant&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-n&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Number&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-o&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Operator&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-p&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Punctuation&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-pr&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Property&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-at&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Attribute&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-tg&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Tag (HTML/XML)&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-m&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Macro&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-l&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Label&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-ns&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Namespace&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-cr&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Constructor&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-tt&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Title/Heading&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-st&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Strong/Bold&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-em&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Emphasis/Italic&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-tu&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Link/URL&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-tl&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Literal/Code&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-tx&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Strikethrough&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-da&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Diff Addition&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-dd&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Diff Deletion&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-eb&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Embedded&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a-er&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; — Error&lt;p&gt;For the complete reference with examples and CSS styling tips, see the HTML Tag Reference in the README.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each grammar includes the full tree-sitter runtime embedded in its WASM module. This adds a fixed overhead to every grammar bundle, on top of the grammar-specific parser tables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Language&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;C Lines&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Size&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Distribution&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every grammar is compiled to WASM with aggressive size optimizations. Here's the complete build pipeline:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We compile with nightly Rust using &lt;code&gt;-Zbuild-std&lt;/code&gt; to rebuild the standard library with our optimization flags:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-Cpanic=immediate-abort&lt;/code&gt;
                            Skip unwinding machinery
                        &lt;code&gt;-Copt-level=s&lt;/code&gt;
                            Optimize for size, not speed
                        &lt;code&gt;-Clto=fat&lt;/code&gt;
                            Full link-time optimization across all crates
                        &lt;code&gt;-Ccodegen-units=1&lt;/code&gt;
                            Single codegen unit for maximum optimization
                        &lt;code&gt;-Cstrip=symbols&lt;/code&gt;
                            Remove debug symbols
                        &lt;p&gt;Generate JavaScript bindings with &lt;code&gt;--target web&lt;/code&gt; for ES module output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Final size optimization pass with Binaryen's optimizer:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-Oz&lt;/code&gt;
                            Aggressive size optimization
                        &lt;code&gt;--enable-bulk-memory&lt;/code&gt;
                            Faster memory operations
                        &lt;code&gt;--enable-mutable-globals&lt;/code&gt;
                            Required for wasm-bindgen
                        &lt;code&gt;--enable-simd&lt;/code&gt;
                            SIMD instructions where applicable
                        &lt;p&gt;Despite all these optimizations, WASM bundles are still large because each one embeds the full tree-sitter runtime. We're exploring ways to share the runtime across grammars, but that's the architecture trade-off for now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those use regex-based tokenization (TextMate grammars). Regexes can't count brackets, track scope, or understand structure—they just pattern-match.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Tree-sitter actually parses your code into a syntax tree, so it knows that &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt; is a keyword only in the right
                                context, handles deeply nested structures correctly, and recovers
                                gracefully from syntax errors.
                            &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IDEs with LSP support (like rust-analyzer) can do even better with semantic highlighting—they understand types and dependencies across files—but tree-sitter gets you 90% of the way there without needing a full language server.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arbor is Latin for tree (as in tree-sitter), and -ium denotes a place or collection (like aquarium, arboretum).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's a place where tree-sitter grammars live.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes! Open an issue on the repo with a link to the grammar.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We'll review it and add it if the grammar and highlight queries are in good shape.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When doing full-stack Rust, it's nice to have exactly the same code on the frontend and the backend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rust crates compile to both native and WASM, so you get one dependency that works everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tree-sitter uses table-driven LR parsing. The grammar compiles down to massive state transition tables—every possible parser state and every possible token gets an entry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These tables are optimized for O(1) lookup speed, not size. A complex grammar like TypeScript can have tens of thousands of states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tradeoff is worth it: you get real parsing (not regex hacks) that handles edge cases correctly and recovers gracefully from syntax errors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46270298</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 03:57:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Whole App is a Blob</title><link>https://drobinin.com/posts/the-whole-app-is-a-blob/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2e201916cb60ccb1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Whole App is a Blob&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Coffee Problem ¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;School French worked perfectly until I tried to buy a coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My lessons must be familiar to all Brits out there: conjugate être until it’s muscle memory, role-play booking a hotel you will never book, then leave school with the comforting illusion that you “know French” in the same way you “know trigonometry”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first time French came in useful was a cafe in Chartres, a small town about an hour from Paris with a cathedral, nice streets, and, as far as I could tell that day, a collective commitment to not speaking English.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I walked into a cafe feeling reasonably confident: asked for coffee in my best French and apparently did very well, because the barista replied with the total. It wasn’t even a hard number. But as it arrived as one continuous noise, I instantly gave up and defaulted to the internationally recognised protocol of tapping my card and pretending I am too busy looking at my phone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s the gap language apps don’t really model: not “do you know the words?”, but “can you retrieve them when a human is waiting and you’ve got three seconds before you embarrass yourself?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More than a decade later, planning a few months in Québec, I did what I always do before a move: learn the minimum viable politeness. Hello, sorry, thank you, the numbers, and the scaffolding around “can I get...”–enough to not be a complete nuisance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried the usual apps: the streaks were pristine and the charts looked like I was becoming bilingual. But in my head I was still standing in Chartres, hearing “3,90” as “three-something-or-something” and sweating directly through my self-respect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I built a safety net for the specific failure mode: retrieval under pressure, or just a tiny rehearsal room I could open while the kettle boiled, practise the bits that reliably go wrong, and close again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And because I genuinely believe that constraints are important, I wrote down the rule that would make this harder than it needed to be:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The whole app is a blob.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Childhood Trauma ¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you grew up with Tamagotchis, you already understand why this was tempting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not the “cute pixel pet” part. The part where a device the size of a digestive biscuit turns into a low-resolution hostage negotiator. Feed me, clean me, entertain me. And if you don’t, I will beep during maths, get confiscated, and then die alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They were brilliant because they weren’t productivity tools. They were tiny relationships. Everything was implied, physical, slightly unfair, and somehow more motivating than any "Time to stand!" push notification has ever been. If you came back after a day away, the creature didn’t show you a progress chart, it showed you a mood.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s the shape I wanted for language drills: something that feels less like “open app → consume lesson” and more like “tap creature → it looks at you → you do a small thing together”. I wanted the warmth and the immediacy, without the emotional extortion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So my brief turned into a very narrow design constraint with a lot of consequences:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No “home screen” full of destinations.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No tests you have to take before you’re allowed to practise.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No progress cathedral you’re meant to worship in.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Just one scene, one character, and whatever information absolutely must leak through to make the interaction legible.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s easy to say “minimal”, but it’s so much harder to say “minimal and still usable by a human being who did not build it”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The blob wasn’t a mascot here, it was the interface. Which meant it had to do interface work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Teaching a Circle to Care ¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The moment you remove buttons, menus, and visible structure, you inherit a new responsibility: you still owe people answers, you just can’t give them in text.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you open a normal learning app, you get reassurance for free. There’s a big obvious “Start” button. There are labels and counters and little UI receipts that say “yes, you are in the right place, yes, tapping this will do something, yes, you did something yesterday”. It’s not glamorous, but it works, and the user doesn’t have to play detective.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you open a blob, the user is staring at an animated shape on a gradient background and thinking, with complete justification: are you sure this is an app?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So the first UX lesson was painfully simple: minimalism doesn’t grant telepathy. In a normal app the UI does a lot of quiet admin for you: it tells you what you can do next, what will happen if you tap, and whether you’re in the right place. When you delete all of that and leave a blob on a gradient, you’re basically asking the user to infer intent from body language. That can work–but only if the blob is unambiguous about two things: “yes, I’m interactive” and “yes, tapping me will lead somewhere predictable”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early Lexie was just a gently breathing circle. It looked calm, premium, vaguely spa-adjacent. It also looked like something you’d see right before a meditation app asks for an annual subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried to solve it the “pure” way first: more animation, more suggestion, more “if you notice the micro-shift in the shape you’ll understand you can begin”. That’s a fun idea if your users have nothing else going on in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the shipped version, there is a Start button. It’s small and it doesn’t dominate the scene. It’s not there because it’s pretty but because people deserve certainty within half a second, and a blob cannot deliver that guarantee on its own without becoming theatre.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once a drill starts, nothing “navigates”. A prompt appears near the blob, and as you take your time answering the question, it subtly changes posture like it’s paying attention–a little lean, eyes tracking, the idle breathing tightening slightly. It’s a tiny moment, but it matters because it reframes what’s happening: you’re not entering a mode, you’re getting the creature’s focus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then comes the most dangerous part of any character-driven UI: feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where every learning app turns into a casino if you let it. Confetti, fireworks, the whole 4th of July experience (I've seen it only in movies though, not sure why but it's not celebrated in the UK). “Amazing!” “Legendary!” “You’re on a roll!” If you answer correctly, a slot machine explodes. If you answer incorrectly, a disappointed owl files paperwork and probably takes away your dog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m not morally superior to particle effects and shaders. I built the confetti version and it was genuinely fun. It was also exhausting in the way a loud pub is exhausting: a bit of stimulation, then a sudden desire to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I stripped it down to feedback that reads instantly and ends quickly. A daily practice gets a small hop, a brief brightening, a few coins that pop out and arc back into the blob like it’s absorbing the reward to acknowledge, not to boost your dopamine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incorrect answers were a bigger design fight than correct ones, because the default instincts are all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first “honest” version made the blob sad. Eyes down, posture slumped, colour cooled. It was expressive and clear, but nobody wants to practise French numbers if it means disappointing a creature you made to be comforting. Tamagotchi could do that to children in the noughties, but adults today will simply uninstall you and go drink water in silence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I switched the emotion from judgment to confusion. Miss, and Lexie looks like it’s thinking, slightly puzzled, waiting. It still reacts–you still get information–but it doesn’t weaponise your mistake into shame.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of this is design work you don’t have to do if you use normal UI, which is the second UX lesson: removing UI doesn’t remove complexity. It relocates it into motion, timing, and body language, and those are harder to get right because you can’t label them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;When Minimalism Hits a Wall ¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The third UX lesson arrived a week into using my own app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The blob was fun, and I kept the drills short. The interaction felt calm in a way most learning apps don’t. I’d open it while waiting for the kettle, do a handful of prompts, watch the creature perk up, and then close it feeling vaguely responsible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then, at some point, I realised I had no idea whether I was improving or just maintaining a pet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the trade you make when you pursue a “single-scene” interface too aggressively: you can remove friction, but you can also remove evidence. If the app never tells you anything in words or numbers, you end up in an uncanny situation where you feel like you’re doing something, but you can’t verify it. It’s the UX equivalent of “trust me, mate.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Testers (aka my wife, who am I kidding here) said the same thing but in more flattering terms: “Cute!” “Less scary than Duolingo.” Then the one question that matters: “Is this actually helping?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Minimalism is only luxurious if the user still feels in control. But you can't manage something if you can't measure it. So I broke the “blob only” purity in a way I could live with: I added small receipts that don’t turn the experience into a dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, a ring. It fills as you answer, like a quiet “enough for today” signal. When it completes, it does a subtle shimmer and then goes back to being decorative. It’s not there to gamify, it’s there to answer the simplest question: did I do anything meaningful, or did I just tap a circle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, a tiny streak pill. Just a small indicator that you’ve done something today, and that you’ve been roughly consistent recently. If you miss a day, it resets without drama, because drama is the entire behaviour I was trying to design out of the interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Third, a stats sheet that’s deliberately buried. There’s a small icon. Tap it and you get a panel with a few plain facts: how much you’ve practised recently and which ranges you struggle with. If you never open it, the app never nags you with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the shape I ended up believing in: keep the main surface quiet, but give the user an audit trail if they ask for it. The blob stays the primary interface, but it no longer asks for blind trust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Lines I Refused to Cross ¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you add rings and streaks and coins, you’re standing at the top of a very slippery slope.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One more step and the ring becomes a flame, the streak turns into a guilt mechanic, the blob becomes a supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s clearly effective and there apps successfully pulling that off. It’s also the opposite of the thing I was trying to build, so I ended up with a few hard lines that survived every “maybe we should...” conversation I had with myself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lexie can’t die. No pixel funeral, no neglected-pet tragedy, no “you failed” screen. If you keep getting things wrong, it doesn’t spiral into shame–it just... resets. A quiet little rebirth loop, the most Buddhist mechanic I could ship (I am not, as you can tell, a designer). If you vanish for a week, it goes a bit dim and undercharged, like it’s been sat in Low Power Mode, and then wakes up the second you tap it. Your life is allowed to exist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is no “streak in danger” notification. If reminders ever exist, they’ll sound like a polite tap on the shoulder, not a fire alarm. I am not building a tiny manager that lives in your pocket and counts your absences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is no leaderboard. The blob does not know your friends, but you get to keep your very own blob, isn't it cool?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rewards are cosmetic and unserious. You can unlock colours. The blob can wear a beret. It can look slightly more smug after you finally stop mixing up seventy and seventeen. None of it changes the learning itself. It just gives the relationship a bit of texture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where the Tamagotchi inspiration loops back in a healthier form: the creature is there to make the interaction feel human, but it’s not allowed to punish you for being human.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Now That I'm in Québec ¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the time we actually arrived in Québec, I’d gained one extremely specific superpower: I can now hear a price and remain a person.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“3.99” registers as “money” instead of “incoming humiliation”. Phone numbers no longer turn into a single continuous noise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What Lexie didn’t solve–and was never meant to solve–is everything around the number. “Pour ici ou pour emporter” is currently my nemesis. The first time someone asked, I understood none of it and answered “oui” with enough confidence to make it everyone’s problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s fine though. The blob isn’t a French course. It drills what it can drill properly, like numbers, some core forms, the boring fundamentals that keep showing up, and then leaves the rest to real life. If you disappear for a week, it is not the end of the world–it just wakes up, gives you some hardcore numbers to translate again, and does a wee level-up jig like you’ve achieved something.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which, to be fair, I have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I like turning mildly humiliating real-world edge cases into shippable apps; if you have a few of those lying around, send them to work@drobinin.com.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46270386</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 04:09:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Common Rust Lifetime Misconceptions</title><link>https://github.com/pretzelhammer/rust-blog/blob/master/posts/common-rust-lifetime-misconceptions.md</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46270882</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 05:46:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Avoid UUIDv4 Primary Keys</title><link>https://andyatkinson.com/avoid-uuid-version-4-primary-keys</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7959529d20a27f9d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Introduction&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUID context for this post&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Scope of web app usage and and their scale&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Randomness is the issue&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why choose UUIDs at all? Generating values from one or more client applications&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Misconceptions: UUIDs are secure&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Creating obfuscated values using integers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reasons against UUIDs in general: they consume a lot of space&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reasons against: UUID v4s add insert latency due to index page splits, fragmentation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Excessive IO for lookups even with orderable UUIDs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Working with integers, UUID v4, and UUID v7&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inspecting density with the pageinspect extension&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUID Downsides: Worse cache hit ratio&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mitigations: Rebuilding indexes with UUID values&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mitigation: Shared buffers and work_mem memory sizing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mitigation in Rails: UUID and implicit order column Active Record&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mitigating poor performance by clustering on orderable field&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Recommendation: Stick with sequences, integers, and big integers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUID v4 alternatives: Use time-ordered UUIDs like Version 7&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Summary&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Learn More&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the last decade, when working on databases with UUID Version 41 as the primary key data type, these databases have usually have bad performance and excessive IO.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UUID is a native data type in Postgres can be stored as binary data. Various versions are in the RFC. Version 4 has mostly random bits, obfuscating information like when the value was created or where it was generated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Version 4 UUIDs are easy to generate in Postgres using the &lt;code&gt;gen_random_uuid()&lt;/code&gt;2 function since version 13 (released in 2020).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve learned there are misconceptions about UUID Version 4, and sometimes these are the reasons users pick this data type.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because of the poor performance, misconceptions, and available alternatives, I’ve come around to a simple position: Avoid UUID Version 4 for primary keys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My more controversial take is to avoid UUIDs in general, but I understand there are some legitimate reasons for them without practical alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a database enthusiast, I wanted to have an articulated position on this classic “Integer v. UUID” debate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among databases folks, debating this may be tired and clichéd. However, from my consulting work, I can say I work with databases using UUID v4 in 2024 and 2025, and still see the issues discussed in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s dig in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;UUID context for this post&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUIDs (or GUID in Microsoft speak)3) are long strings of 36 characters, 32 digits, 4 hyphens, stored as 128 bits (16 byte) values, stored using the binary &lt;code&gt;uuid&lt;/code&gt;data type in Postgres&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The RFC documents how the 128 bits are set&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The bits for UUID Version 4 are mostly random values&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUID Version 7 includes a timestamp in the first 48 bits, which works much better with database indexes compared with random values&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although unreleased as of this writing, and pulled from Postgres 17 previously, UUID V7 is part of Postgres 184 scheduled for release in the Fall of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What kind of app databases are in scope for this post?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Scope of web app usage and and their scale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The kinds of web applications I’m thinking of with this post are monolithic web apps, with Postgres as their primary OLTP database. The apps could be in categories like social media, e-commerce, click tracking, or business process automation apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The types of performance issues discussed here are related to inefficient storage and retrieval, meaning they happen for all of these types of apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s the core issue with UUID v4?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Randomness is the issue&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core issue with UUID Version 4, given 122 bits are “random or pseudo-randomly generated values”1 and primary keys are backed by indexes, is the impact to inserts and retrieval of individual items or ranges of values from the index.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Random values don’t have natural sorting like integers or lexicographic (dictionary) sorting like character strings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UUID v4s do have “byte ordering,” but this has no useful meaning for how they’re accessed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What use cases for UUID are there?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why choose UUIDs at all? Generating values from one or more client applications&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One use case for UUIDs is when there’s a need to generate an identifier on a client or from multiple services, then passed to Postgres for persistence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For web apps, generally they instantiate objects in memory and don’t expect an identifier to be used for lookups until after an instance is persisted as a row (where the database generates the identifier).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a microservices architecture where the apps have their own databases, the ability to generate identifiers from each database without collisions is a use case for UUIDs. The UUID could also identify the database a value came from later, vs. an integer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For collision avoidance (see HN discussion5), we can’t practically make the same guarantee with sequence-backed integers. There are hacks, like generating even and odd integers between two instances, or using different ranges in the int8 range.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are also alternative identifiers like using composite primary keys (CPKs), however the same set of 2 values wouldn’t uniquely identify a particular table.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The avoidance of collisions is described this way on Wikipedia:6&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The number of random version-4 UUIDs which need to be generated in order to have a 50% probability of one collision: 2.71 quintillion&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This number would be equivalent to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Generating 1 billion UUIDs per second for about 86 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are UUIDs secure?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Misconceptions: UUIDs are secure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One misconception about UUIDs is that they’re secure. However, the RFC describes that they shouldn’t be considered secure “capabilities.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From RFC 41221 Section 6 Security Considerations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Do not assume that UUIDs are hard to guess; they should not be used as security capabilities&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How can we create obfuscated codes from integers?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Creating obfuscated values using integers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While UUID V4s obfuscate their creation time, the values can’t be ordered to see when they were created relative to each other. We can achieve those properties with integers with a little more work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One option is to generate a pseudo-random code from an integer, then use that value externally, while still using integers internally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To see the full details of this solution, please check out: Short alphanumeric pseudo random identifiers in Postgres7&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll summarize it here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Convert a decimal integer like “2” into binary bits. E.g. a 4 byte, 32 bit integer: 00000000 00000000 00000000 00000010&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Perform an exclusive OR (XOR) operation on all the bits using a key&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Encode each bit using a base62 alphabet&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The obfuscated id is stored in a generated column. By reviewing the generated values, they are similar, but aren’t ordered by their creation order.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The values in insertion order were &lt;code&gt;01Y9I&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;01Y9L&lt;/code&gt;, then &lt;code&gt;01Y9K&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With alphabetical order, the last two would be flipped: &lt;code&gt;01Y9I&lt;/code&gt; first, then &lt;code&gt;01Y9K&lt;/code&gt; second, then &lt;code&gt;01Y9L&lt;/code&gt; third, sorting on the fifth character.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I wanted to use this approach for all tables, I’d try a centralized table that was polymorphic, storing a record for each table that’s using a code (and a foreign key constraint).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That way I’d know where the code was used.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why else might we want to skip UUIDs?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Reasons against UUIDs in general: they consume a lot of space&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UUIDs are 16 bytes (128 bits) per value, which is double the space of bigint (8 bytes), or quadruple the space of 4-byte integers. This extra space adds up once many tables have millions of rows, and copies of a database are being moved around as backups and restores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A more considerable impact to performance though is the poor characteristics of writing and reading random data into indexes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Reasons against: UUID v4s add insert latency due to index page splits, fragmentation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For random UUID v4s, Postgres incurs more latency for every insert operation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For integer primary key rows, their values are maintained in index pages with “append-mostly” operations on “leaf nodes,” since their values are orderable, and since B-Tree indexes store entries in sorted order.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For UUID v4s, primary key values in B-Tree indexes are problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inserts are not appended to the right most leaf page. They are placed into a random page, and that could be mid-page or an already-full page, causing a page split that would have been unnecessary with an integer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Planet Scale has a nice visualization of index page splits and rebalancing.8&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unnecessary splits and rebalancing add space consumption and processing latency to write operations. This extra IO shows up in Write Ahead Log (WAL) generation as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Buildkite reported a 50% reduction in write IO for the WAL by moving to time-ordered UUIDs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given fixed size pages, we want high density within the pages. Later on we’ll use pageinspect to check the average leaf density between integer and UUID to help compare the two.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Excessive IO for lookups even with orderable UUIDs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;B-Tree page layout means you can fit fewer UUIDs per 8KB page. Since we have the limitation of fixed page sizes, we at least want them to be as densely packed as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since UUID indexes are ~40% larger in leaf pages than bigint (int8) for the same logical number of rows, they can’t be as densely packed with values. As Lukas says, “All in all, the physical data structure matters as much as your server configuration to achieve the best I/O performance in Postgres.”9&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means that for individual lookups, range scans, or UPDATES, we will incur ~40% more I/O on UUID indexes, as more pages are scanned. Remember that even to access one row, in Postgres the whole page is accessed where the row is, and copied into a shared memory buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s insert and query data and take a look at numbers between these data types.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Working with integers, UUID v4, and UUID v7&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s create integer, UUID v4, and UUID v7 fields, index them, load them into the buffer cache with pg_prewarm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will use the schema examples from the Cybertec post Unexpected downsides of UUID keys in PostgreSQL by Ants Aasma.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;View andyatkinson/pg_scripts PR #20.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On my Mac, I compiled the &lt;code&gt;pg_uuidv7&lt;/code&gt; extension. Once compiled and enabled for Postgres, I could use the extension functions to generate UUID V7 values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another extension &lt;code&gt;pg_prewarm&lt;/code&gt; is used. It’s a module included with Postgres, so it just needs to be enabled per database where it’s used.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The difference in latency and the enormous difference in buffers from the post was reproducible in my testing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Holy behemoth buffer count batman” - Ants Aasma&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cybertec post results:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;27,332 buffer hits, index only scan on the &lt;code&gt;bigint&lt;/code&gt;column&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;8,562,960 buffer hits, index only scan on the UUID V4 index scan&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since these are buffer hits we’re accessing them from memory, which is faster than disk. We can focus then on only the difference in latency based on the data types.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How many more pages are accessed for the UUID index? 8,535,628 (8.5 million!) more 8KB pages were accessed, a 31229.4% increase. In terms of MB and MB/s that is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;68,285,024 MB or ~68.3 GB! more data that’s accessed&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Calculating a low and high estimate of access speeds for memory:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Low estimate: 20 GB/s&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;High estimate: 80 GB/s&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Accessing 68.3 GB of data from memory (&lt;code&gt;shared_buffers&lt;/code&gt; in PostgreSQL) would add:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;~3.4 seconds of latency (low speed)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;~0.86 seconds of latency (high speed)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s between ~1 and ~3.4 seconds of additional latency solely based on the data type. Here we used 10 million rows and performed 1 million updates, but the latencies will get worse as data and query volumes increase.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Inspecting density with the pageinspect extension&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can inspect the average fill percentage (density) of leaf pages using the pageinspect extension.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;uuid_experiments/page_density.sql&lt;/code&gt; (andyatkinson/pg_scripts PR #20) query in the repo gets the indexes for the integer and v4 and v7 uuid columns, their total page counts, their page stats, and the number of leaf pages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the leaf pages, the query calculates an average fill percentage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After performing the 1 million updates on the 10 million rows mentioned in the example, I got these results from that query:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt; idxname             | avg_leaf_fill_percent
---------------------+-----------------------
 records_id_idx      |                 97.64
 records_uuid_v4_idx |                 79.06
 records_uuid_v7_idx |                 90.09
(3 rows)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This shows the &lt;code&gt;integer&lt;/code&gt; index had an average fill percentage of nearly 98%, while the UUID v4 index was around 79%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;UUID Downsides: Worse cache hit ratio&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Postgres buffer cache is a critical part of good performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For good performance, we want our queries to produce cache “hits” as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The buffer cache has limited space. Usually 25-40% of system memory is allocated to it, and the total database size including table and index data is usually much larger than that amount of memory. That means we’ll have trade-offs, as all data will not fit into system memory. This is where the challenges come in!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When pages are accessed they’re copied into the buffer cache as buffers. When write operations happen, buffers are dirtied before being flushed.10&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the UUIDs are randomly located, additional buffers will need to be copied to the cache compared to ordered integers. Buffers might be evicted to make space that are needed, decreasing hit rates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Mitigations: Rebuilding indexes with UUID values&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the tables and indexes are more likely to be fragmented, it makes sense to rebuild the tables and indexes periodically.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rebuilding tables can be done using pg_repack, pg_squeeze, or &lt;code&gt;VACUUM FULL&lt;/code&gt; if you can afford to perform the operation offline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indexes can be rebuilt online using &lt;code&gt;REINDEX CONCURRENTLY&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the newly laid out data in pages, they will still not have correlation, and thus not be smaller. The space formerly occupied by deletes will be reclaimed for reuse though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Mitigation: Shared buffers and work_mem memory sizing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If possible, size your primary instance to have 4x the amount of memory of your size of database. In order words if your database is 25GB, try and run a 128GB memory instance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This gives around 32GB to 50GB of memory for buffer cache (&lt;code&gt;shared_buffers&lt;/code&gt;) which is hopefully enough to store all accessed pages and index entries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use pg_buffercache11 to inspect the contents, and pg_prewarm12 to populate tables into it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One tactic I’ve used when working with UUID v4 random values where sorting is happening, is to provide more memory to sort operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To do that in Postgres, we can change the &lt;code&gt;work_mem&lt;/code&gt; setting. This setting can be changed for the whole database, a session, or even for individual queries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check out Configuring work_mem in Postgres on PgMustard for an example of setting this in a session.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Mitigation in Rails: UUID and implicit order column Active Record&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since Rails 6, we can control implicit_order_column.13 The database_consistency gem even has a checker for folks using UUID primary keys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When ORDER BY is generated in queries implicitly, it may be worth ordering on a different high cardinality field that’s indexed, like a &lt;code&gt;created_at&lt;/code&gt; timestamp field.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Mitigating poor performance by clustering on orderable field&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cluster on a column that’s high cardinality and indexed could be a mitigation option.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, imagine your UUID primary table has a &lt;code&gt;created_at&lt;/code&gt; timestamp column that’s indexed with &lt;code&gt;idx_on_tbl_created_at&lt;/code&gt;, and clustering on that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;CLUSTER table_with_uuid_ok USING idx_on_tbl_created_at;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t see CLUSTER used ever really though as it takes an access exclusive lock. The CLUSTER is a one-time operation that would also need to be repeated regularly to maintain its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Recommendation: Stick with sequences, integers, and big integers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For new databases that may be small, with unknown growth, I recommend plain old integers and an identity column (backed by a sequence)14 for primary keys. These are signed 32 bit (4-byte) values. This provides about 2 billion positive unique values per table.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For many business apps, they will never reach 2 billion unique values per table, so this will be adequate for their entire life. I’ve also recommended always using bigint/int8 in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I guess it comes down to what you know about your data size, how you can project growth. There are plenty of low growth business apps out there, in constrained industries, and constrained sets of business users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Internet-facing consumer apps with expected high growth, like social media, click tracking, sensor data, telemetry collection types of apps, or when migrating an existing medium or large database with 100s of millions or billions of rows, then it makes sense to start with &lt;code&gt;bigint&lt;/code&gt; (int8), 64-bit, 8-byte integer primary keys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;UUID v4 alternatives: Use time-ordered UUIDs like Version 7&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since Postgres 18 is not yet released, generating UUID V7s now in Postgres is possible using the &lt;code&gt;pg_uuidv7&lt;/code&gt; extension.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have an existing UUID v4 filled database and can’t afford a costly migration to another primary key data type, then starting to populate new values using UUID v7 will help somewhat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortunately the binary &lt;code&gt;uuid&lt;/code&gt; data type in Postgres can be used whether you’re storing V4 or V7 UUID values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another alternative that relies on an extension is sequential_uuids.15&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Summary&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUID v4s increase latency for lookups, as they can’t take advantage of fast ordered lookups in B-Tree indexes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For new databases, don’t use &lt;code&gt;gen_random_uuid()&lt;/code&gt;for primary key types, which generates random UUID v4 values&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUIDs consume twice the space of &lt;code&gt;bigint&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUID v4 values are not meant to be secure per the UUID RFC&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUID v4s are random. For good performance, the whole index must be in buffer cache for index scans, which is increasingly unlikely for bigger data.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UUID v4s cause more page splits, which increase IO for writes with increased fragmentation, and increased size of WAL logs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For non-guessable, obfuscated pseudo-random codes, we can generate those from integers, which could be an alternative to using UUIDs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you must use UUIDs, use time-orderable UUIDs like UUID v7&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you see any errors or have any suggested improvements? Please contact me. Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Learn More&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Franck Pachot for AWS Heroes has an interesting take on UUID in PostgreSQL&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Brandur has a great post: Identity Crisis: Sequence v. UUID as Primary Key&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;5mins of Postgres: UUIDs vs Serial for Primary Keys - what’s the right choice?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;andyatkinson/pg_scripts PR #20&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc4122#section-4.4 ↩ ↩2 ↩3&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/functions-uuid.html ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universally_unique_identifier ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://andyatkinson.com/generating-short-alphanumeric-public-id-postgres ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://planetscale.com/blog/the-problem-with-using-a-uuid-primary-key-in-mysql ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://stringintech.github.io/blog/p/postgresql-buffer-cache-a-practical-guide/ ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/pgbuffercache.html ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://www.bigbinary.com/blog/rails-6-adds-implicit_order_column ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;https://www.cybertec-postgresql.com/en/uuid-serial-or-identity-columns-for-postgresql-auto-generated-primary-keys/ ↩&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46272487</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 10:08:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Largest U.S. recycling project to extend landfill life for Virginia residents</title><link>https://ampsortation.com/articles/largest-us-recycling-project-spsa</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="164c843ff9a12616"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;AI Takes Out the Trash: Largest U.S. Recycling Project to Extend Landfill Life for Virginia Residents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Southeastern Public Service Authority of Virginia contracts with AMP to cost-effectively process municipal solid waste, boost recycling and landfill diversion rates&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PORTSMOUTH, Va., NOVEMBER 21, 2025—The Southeastern Public Service Authority of Virginia (“SPSA”), the regional waste authority for South Hampton Roads, has signed a 20-year contract with Commonwealth Sortation LLC, an affiliate of AMP Robotics Corporation (together, “AMP”), to provide solid waste processing services for SPSA’s eight member communities and their 1.2 million residents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on a nearly two-year pilot project in Portsmouth—which featured an AMP ONE™ system capable of processing up to 150 tons of locally sourced municipal solid waste (“MSW”) per day—AMP will now scale its technology region-wide. Under this long-term partnership, which will facilitate the largest recycling project in the country, AMP will deploy additional MSW sortation lines and an organics management system capable of processing 540,000 tons annually to divert half of the waste SPSA brings to AMP facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AMP’s AI-based sorting technology uses cameras, robotics, and pneumatic jets to detect and remove recyclables and organics from bagged trash. With AMP’s solution, SPSA can:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Extend the life of its landfill;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Decrease long-term collection and disposal costs for communities; and&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adapt to evolving community needs, including organic waste management, to better support a growing, thriving region.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dennis Bagley, executive director of SPSA, said, “This project will enable us to improve how we manage waste from the communities we serve, turning all 1.2 million residents into active recyclers, while doubling the life of our landfill. This technology is demonstrating that there are effective ways to recover valuable resources from the trash, and we're proud to be on the cutting edge of providing high-quality and transparent waste management services.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Partnering with AMP guarantees the region will recycle 20% of its waste—more than double the recycling rate of the highest-performing community in the region—while eliminating the need for separate recycling facilities and trucks to process most recyclables. SPSA’s own waste characterization study found high rates of recyclables, mainly plastics and metals, in the Hampton Roads waste stream—even in communities with curbside recycling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tim Stuart, CEO of AMP, said, “Recycling rates have been stuck for both communities and the nation at large for the last decade and a half. Projects like this one offer a new model for recycling, one that’s better aligned with local waste infrastructure. Our approach to processing MSW will significantly reduce the volume of waste SPSA must landfill, enable the creation of useful end products, and do so with meaningfully lower emissions levels than those resulting from competing solutions. At the end of the day, it is a win-win for all involved, and will serve as a model for other communities seeking to adopt more sustainable waste management practices.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AMP will leverage two sortation facilities in Portsmouth to extract recyclables (plastics, metals, and fiber) and organics, while collaborating with SPSA to dispose of the residuals. A third facility, adjacent to a sortation facility on Victory Boulevard, will transform the captured organics via indirect heating into biochar, a charcoal-like substance that sequesters carbon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By creating processing capacity at multiple sites instead of centralizing at one location, SPSA gains operational resilience, reducing downtime risk and ensuring reliable landfill diversion. Beyond extending the life of SPSA’s landfill, each diverted ton of MSW reduces or sequesters more than 0.7 tons of carbon dioxide-equivalent greenhouse gases—equating to more than 378,000 tons of carbon dioxide avoided or removed annually across SPSA’s processable waste—roughly the same as taking more than 88,000 cars off the road for a year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AMP, which is backed by investors including Sequoia Capital, Congruent Ventures, XN, Blue Earth Capital, California State Teachers’ Retirement System (CalSTRS), and Microsoft Climate Innovation Fund, expects to create approximately 100 jobs and build numerous transferable skills in the local workforce. Unlike legacy waste processing facilities where the workforce is concentrated in manual sorting roles, AMP’s solution relies on production operators who have the opportunity to learn how to optimize the technology and automated systems they manage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About AMP™&lt;lb/&gt;AMP is applying AI-powered sortation at scale to modernize the world's recycling infrastructure and maximize the value in waste. AMP designs, builds, and operates advanced, cost-competitive facilities to process single-stream recycling and municipal solid waste. The company’s AI platform has identified more than 200 billion items and its systems have processed 2.8 million tons of recyclables. With three full-scale facilities and more than 400 AI systems deployed across North America, Asia, and Europe, AMP’s technology offers a transformational solution to waste sortation and changes the fundamental economics of recycling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About SPSA&lt;lb/&gt;The Southeastern Public Service Authority (SPSA) manages solid waste services for more than 1.2 million residents across eight southeastern Virginia communities: Chesapeake, Franklin, Isle of Wight County, Norfolk, Portsmouth, Southampton County, Suffolk, and Virginia Beach. Established in 1976, SPSA is dedicated to delivering environmentally responsible, cost-effective waste solutions. Learn more at www.spsava.gov or follow SPSA on Facebook, LinkedIn, and YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Media Contact&lt;lb/&gt;Carling Spelhaug&lt;lb/&gt;carling@ampsortation.com&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46273344</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 11:58:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Optery (YC W22) Hiring CISO, Release Manager, Tech Lead (Node), Full Stack Eng</title><link>https://www.optery.com/careers/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ca6bb85f43b74372"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Careers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;💡Page not loading? Optery’s Career page uses Cookies to display the full page content. If you’re not seeing anything, try opening the cookie banner (cookie icon in the bottom left corner) and Accept Personalization cookies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;💡Page not loading? Optery’s Career page uses Cookies to display the full page content. If you’re not seeing anything, try opening the cookie banner (cookie icon in the bottom left corner) and Accept Personalization cookies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ready to safeguard your personal data?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46273372</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 12:00:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>It seems that OpenAI is scraping [certificate transparency] logs</title><link>https://benjojo.co.uk/u/benjojo/h/Gxy2qrCkn1Y327Y6D3</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e5adc010ce207e8f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; lol. I minted a new TLS cert and it seems that OpenAI is scraping CT logs for what I assume are things to scrape from, based on the near instant response from this:&lt;code&gt;Dec 12 20:43:04 xxxx xxx[719]: 
l=debug 
m="http request" 
pkg=http 
httpaccess= 
handler=(nomatch) 
method=get 
url=/robots.txt 
host=autoconfig.benjojo.uk 
duration="162.176µs" 
statuscode=404 
proto=http/2.0 
remoteaddr=74.7.175.182:38242 
tlsinfo=tls1.3 
useragent="Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; Intel Mac OS X 10_15_7) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/131.0.0.0 Safari/537.36; compatible; OAI-SearchBot/1.3; robots.txt; +https://openai.com/searchbot" 
referrr= 
size=19 
cid=19b14416d95&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; wolf480pl@mstdn.io replied 12 Dec 2025 20:57 +0000 &lt;lb/&gt; in reply to: https://benjojo.co.uk/u/benjojo/h/Gxy2qrCkn1Y327Y6D3 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; benjojo replied 12 Dec 2025 21:10 +0000 &lt;lb/&gt; in reply to: https://mstdn.io/users/wolf480pl/statuses/115708595554461422 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; wolf480pl@mstdn.io replied 13 Dec 2025 12:59 +0000 &lt;lb/&gt; in reply to: https://benjojo.co.uk/u/benjojo/h/NgH2Xwlp4KhCTwHjRL &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; @benjojo&lt;lb/&gt;what if CT logs contained hash(domain, nonce) instead of containing the domain in plain, and the nonce was part of the CT inclusion proof?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; benjojo replied 13 Dec 2025 14:53 +0000 &lt;lb/&gt; in reply to: https://mstdn.io/users/wolf480pl/statuses/115712376924287199 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; @wolf480pl the point of certificate transparency logs is so that outside observers can do the double-checking of the CAs certificate and policy in full, if you mess with any part of this, the entire system becomes deeply exploitable and difficult to end to end verify&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; wolf480pl@mstdn.io replied 13 Dec 2025 15:55 +0000 &lt;lb/&gt; in reply to: https://benjojo.co.uk/u/benjojo/h/lPLWBh3YCbFJBH4Dt6 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; @benjojo and I'm guessing some people look at all certs issued by CAs and verify certain criteria that may require knowing the domains... it's kinda sad that it provides domain enumeration, but I guess putting addng zero-knowledge proofs to the mix would've been too complex&lt;lb/&gt;oh, duh I need to be able to find who's issuing carts for my domain &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; benjojo replied 13 Dec 2025 18:00 +0000 &lt;lb/&gt; in reply to: https://mstdn.io/users/wolf480pl/statuses/115713071072619432 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; @wolf480pl tbh domain's are not really that secret, and if you depended on that then something was very wrong. You can work around a lot of this stuff by "just" using wildcard certs instead&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; wolf480pl@mstdn.io replied 13 Dec 2025 18:07 +0000 &lt;lb/&gt; in reply to: https://benjojo.co.uk/u/benjojo/h/pyX28McwZyTh14hy55 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; benjojo replied 13 Dec 2025 23:29 +0000 &lt;lb/&gt; in reply to: https://mstdn.io/users/wolf480pl/statuses/115713588719701003 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; @wolf480pl tbh I would argue why bother with DNSSEC (outside of extremely marginal situations), but NSEC3 even more&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; jamesog@mastodon.soc.. replied 12 Dec 2025 21:09 +0000 &lt;lb/&gt; in reply to: https://benjojo.co.uk/u/benjojo/h/Gxy2qrCkn1Y327Y6D3 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; @benjojo It's interesting to watch web server logs to see what things pick up new CT entries the quickest&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46274478</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 13:48:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Carrier Landing in Top Gun for the NES</title><link>https://relaxing.run/blag/posts/top-gun-landing/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a7720af82959d20d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Top Gun's Carrier Landing: Exposed&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Best read with Danger Zone playing on loop&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like most people, you’re probably an absolute expert at landing on the aircraft carrier in Top Gun for the NES. But if you’re in the silent minority that have not yet mastered this skill, you’re in luck: I’ve done a little reverse engineerining and figured out precisely how landing works. Hopefully now you can get things really dialed in during your next practice session. Let’s get those windmill high-fives warmed up!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;tl;dr: Altitude must be in the range 100-299, speed must be in the range 238-337 (both inclusive), and you must be laterally aimed at the carrier at the end of the sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a reminder in case you haven’t played Top Gun in the last few decades (weird), the landing portion of the stage looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mercifully, the game suggests you aim right in the middle of the acceptable range per the “Alt. 200 / Speed 288” text on your MFD. Altitude and speed are both controlled by throttle input and pitch angle. There’s no on-screen heading indicator, but the game will tell you if you’re outside of the acceptable range (“Right ! Right !”). The ranges for speed and heading are pretty tight, so focus on those: the range for altitude is much wider.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After about a minute of flying the game checks your state and plays a little cutscene showing either a textbook landing or an expensive fireball. Either way, you get a “Mission Accomplished!” and go to the next level (after all, you don’t own that plane, the taxpayers do):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Stuff for nerds&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Memory locations of note:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Address&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Contents&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Acceptable range (inclusive)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$40-$41&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Speed stored as a binary coded decimal&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;238 - 337&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$3D-$3E&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Altitude stored as a BCD&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100 - 299&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$FD&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Heading, ranging from -32 to +32&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;0 - 7&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;$9E&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Landing state check result&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;0; other values change the plane’s trajectory during the crash cutscene&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speed and altitude are stored as binary coded decimals, likely to simplify the rendering of on-screen text. For example, the number 1234 is stored as 4660 (ie., hex 0x1234).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The function at $B6EA performs the state check and writes the result at $9E. If you’re just here to impress your friends and don’t want to put in the practice, the game genie code AEPETA will guarantee a landing that Maverick and Goose (spoiler: may he rest in peace ) would be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s my annotated disassembly for those following along at home:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;landing_skill_check:
    06:B6EA: LDA $3E    ; Load altitude High cent
    06:B6EC: BEQ $B724  ; Branch if High cent == 0 (altitude &amp;lt; 100)
    06:B6EE: CMP #$03
    06:B6F0: BCS $B720  ; Branch if High cent &amp;gt;= 3 (altitude &amp;gt;= 300)
    06:B6F2: LDA $41
    06:B6F4: CMP #$04
    06:B6F6: BCS $B720  ; Branch if High cent is &amp;gt;= 04 (speed &amp;gt;= 400)
    06:B6F8: CMP #$02
    06:B6FA: BCC $B724  ; Branch if High cent is &amp;lt; 02 (speed &amp;lt; 200)
    06:B6FC: BEQ $B706  ; Branch if High cent == 02 (speed &amp;gt;= 200 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; speed &amp;lt;= 299)
speed_300s:
    06:B6FE: LDA $40    ; Load speed Low cent
    06:B700: CMP #$38
    06:B702: BCS $B720  ; Branch if Low cent &amp;gt;= 38 (speed &amp;gt;= 338)
    06:B704: BCC $B70C  ; Branch if Low cent &amp;lt; 38 (speed &amp;lt; 338)
speed_200s:
    06:B706: LDA $40
    06:B708: CMP #$38
    06:B70A: BCC $B724  ; Branch if speed &amp;lt; 238
speed_ok:
    06:B70C: LDA $FD    ; Load heading
    06:B70E: BMI $B718  ; Branch if heading &amp;lt; 0 (too far left)
    06:B710: CMP #$08
    06:B712: BCS $B71C  ; Branch if heading &amp;gt;= 8 (too far right)
    06:B714: LDX #$00   ; speed ok, heading ok; 0 == success
    06:B716: BEQ $B726  ; Branch to return
too_far_left:
    06:B718: LDX #$02
    06:B71A: BNE $B726
too_far_right:
    06:B71C: LDX #$04
    06:B71E: BNE $B726
too_fast_or_too_high:
    06:B720: LDX #$08
    06:B722: BNE $B726
too_slow_or_too_low:
    06:B724: LDX #$04
return:
    06:B726: STX $9E
    06:B728: RTS
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now get out there, and snag that third wire.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46274822</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 14:16:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands of U.S. farmers have Parkinson's. They blame a deadly pesticide</title><link>https://www.mlive.com/news/2025/12/thousands-of-us-farmers-have-parkinsons-they-blame-a-deadly-pesticide.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6f901a9b9aa28db2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paul Friday remembers when his hand started flopping in the cold weather – the first sign nerve cells in his brain were dying.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He was eventually diagnosed with Parkinson’s, a brain disease that gets worse over time. His limbs got stiffer. He struggled to walk. He couldn’t keep living on his family farm. Shortly afterward, Friday came to believe that decades of spraying a pesticide called paraquat at his peach orchard in southwestern Michigan may be the culprit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It explained to me why I have Parkinson’s disease,” said Friday, who is now 83, and makes that claim in a pending lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The pesticide, a weed killer, is extremely toxic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With evidence of its harms stacking up, it’s already been banned in dozens of countries all over the world, including the United Kingdom and China, where it’s made. Yet last year, its manufacturer Syngenta, a subsidiary of a company owned by the Chinese government, continued selling paraquat in the United States and other nations that haven’t banned it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Health statistics are limited. Critics point to research linking paraquat exposure to Parkinson’s, while the manufacturer pushes back, saying none of it is peer-reviewed. But the lawsuits are mounting across the United States, as farmers confront Parkinson’s after a lifetime of use, and much of the globe is turning away from paraquat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has many critics wrestling with the question: What will it take to ban paraquat in the United States?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What we’ve seen over the course of decades is a systemic failure to protect farmworkers and the agricultural community from pesticides,” said Jonathan Kalmuss-Katz, a senior attorney at Earthjustice, an environmental law organization that advocates against paraquat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Thousands of lawsuits pile up&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was hard for Ruth Anne Krause to watch her husband of 58 years struggle to move his hands. He was an avid woodcarver, shaving intricate details into his creations, before it became too difficult for him to hold the tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jim Krause was diagnosed with Parkinson’s disease in 2019, after he spent decades operating a 20-acre stone fruit farm in central California. His wife says he often donned a mask and yellow rubber boots to spray paraquat on the fields.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Krause, who had no family history of neurological disease as is typical, died in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I want people to know what happened,” said Ruth Anne Krause, who is worried that paraquat is still being sold to American farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Krause is one of thousands of people who have sued Syngenta, a manufacturer, and Chevron USA, a seller, over paraquat exposure. They’re alleging the chemical companies failed to warn of the dangers of paraquat despite knowing it could damage human nerve cells and studies showing it’s linked to Parkinson’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chevron, which never manufactured paraquat and hasn’t sold it since 1986, has “long maintained that it should not be liable in any paraquat litigation.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“And despite hundreds of studies conducted over the past 60 years, the scientific consensus is that paraquat has not been shown to be a cause of Parkinson’s disease,” the company said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Syngenta has emphasized there is no evidence that paraquat causes Parkinson’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We have great sympathy for those suffering from the debilitating effects of Parkinson’s disease,” a Syngenta spokesperson said in a statement. “However, it is important to note that the scientific evidence simply does not support a causal link between paraquat and Parkinson’s disease, and that paraquat is safe when used as directed.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More than 6,400 lawsuits against Syngenta and Chevron that allege a link between paraquat and Parkinson’s are pending in the U.S. District Court of Southern Illinois. Another 1,300 cases have been brought in Pennsylvania, 450 in California and more are scattered throughout state courts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I do think it’s important to be clear that number is probably not even close to representative of how many people have been impacted by this,” said Christian Simmons, a legal expert for Drugwatch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Syngenta told its shareholders in March that an additional 1,600 cases have been voluntarily dismissed or resolved. In 2021, the company settled an unspecified number in California and Illinois for $187.5 million, according to a company financial report. Some others have been dismissed for missing court deadlines. None have gone to trial yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Behind these thousands of lawsuits, a list growing nearly every day, is a person suffering from Parkinson’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Ohio, there’s Dave Jilbert a winemaker who sprayed the pesticide on his vineyard south of Cleveland. He was diagnosed with Parkinson’s in 2020 and now he is suing and working to get paraquat banned. Terri McGrath believes years of exposure to paraquat at her family farm in rural Southwest Michigan likely contributed to her Parkinson’s. Six other family members also have the disease. And in south Alabama, Mac Barlow is suing after receiving a similar diagnosis following years of relying on paraquat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“For about 40 years off and on, I’ve been using that stuff,” Barlow said. “I’ll be honest with you, if I knew it was going to be that bad, I would have tried to figure out something else.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Paraquat in the United States&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since hitting the market in the 1960s, paraquat has been used in farming to quickly “burn” weeds before planting crops. The pesticide, originally developed by Syngenta and sold by Chevron, rips tissue apart, destroying plants on a molecular level within hours.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s used because it’s effective at what it does. It’s highly toxic. It’s very good at killing things,” said Geoff Horsfield, policy director at the Environmental Working Group. “And unfortunately, when a pesticide like this is so effective that also means there’s usually human health impacts as well.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the 1970s, it became a tool in the war on drugs, sprayed to kill Mexican marijuana plants. In 1998, that history landed it in Hollywood when the Dude in “The Big Lebowski” calls someone a “human paraquat,” a buzzkill.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, between 11 million and 17 million pounds of paraquat are sprayed annually to help grow cotton, soybean and corn fields, among other crops, throughout the country, the U.S. Geological Survey, USGS, reports. And despite the alleged known risks, its use is increasing, according to the most current federal data, more than doubling from 2012 to 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The USGS says on its website new pesticide use data will be released in 2025. It hasn’t been published yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because paraquat kills any growth it touches, it’s typically used to clear a field before any crops are planted. Low levels of paraquat residue can linger on food crops, but the foremost threat is direct exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pesticides are among the most common means of suicide worldwide, according to the World Health Organization, and paraquat is frequently used because of its lethality. After some nations, like South Korea and Sri Lanka, banned it, they saw a significant drop in suicides, research shows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency already restricts paraquat, labeling it as “registered use,” with a skull and crossbones, meaning it can only be used by people who have a license. Because of its toxicity, the federal government requires it to have blue dye, a sharp smell and a vomiting agent, according to the U.S. Centers for Disease Control, CDC. Sprayers are also told to wear protective gear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite those safety measures, U.S. poison centers have gotten hundreds of paraquat-related calls in the past decade, their annual reports show.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swallowing is the most likely way to be poisoned by paraquat, according to the CDC, but skin exposure can also be deadly. In fact, if it spills on someone, health officials say they should wash it off immediately and quickly cut off their clothes. That way they don’t risk spreading more deadly pesticide on their body as they pull their shirt over their head.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In one 2023 case documented by America’s Poison Centers, a 50-year-old man accidentally sipped blue liquid from a Gatorade bottle that turned out to be paraquat. After trying to throw it up, he went to the emergency room, struggling to breathe, nauseous and vomiting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doctors rushed to treat the man, but he turned blue from a lack of oxygen and his organs failed. He died within three days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In another poison center report, a 65-year-old man spilled paraquat on his clothes and kept working. Ten days later, he went to the emergency room with second-degree burns on his stomach. Dizzy and nauseous, he was admitted for two days before going home.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A week later, he went back to the ICU as his kidney, lungs and heart stopped working. He died 34 days after the spill.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These annual poison center case summaries provide insight into paraquat’s toxicity, but it’s unclear exactly how many people in the U.S. have been injured or killed by the weed killer, because there’s only a patchwork of data creating an uneven and incomplete picture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The latest annual National Poison Data System report logged 114 reports and one death caused by paraquat in 2023. Over a decade, from 2014 to 2023, this system documented 1,151 paraquat calls. And a separate database shows the EPA has investigated 82 human exposure cases since 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even secondary exposure can be dangerous. One case published in the Rhode Island Medical Journal described an instance where a 50-year-old man accidentally ingested paraquat, and the nurse treating him was burned by his urine that splashed onto her forearms. Within a day, her skin blistered and sloughed off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And a former Michigan State horticulture student is suing the university for $100 million, claiming that she developed thyroid cancer from her exposure to pesticides including paraquat, glyphosate and oxyfluorfen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, a much more widespread threat looms large in the background: long-term, low-level exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Parkinson’s on the rise&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parkinson’s disease is the fastest growing neurological disorder in the world, with cases projected to double by 2050, partly due to an aging population, according to a study published in The BMJ, a peer-reviewed medical journal. It occurs when the brain cells that make dopamine, a chemical that controls movement, stop working or die.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The exact cause is unknown, likely a mix of genetic and, largely, environmental factors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Parkinson’s Foundation study found that 87% of those with the disease do not have any genetic risk factors. That means, “for the vast majority of Americans, the cause of Parkinson’s disease lies not within us, but outside of us, in our environment,” said neurologist and researcher Ray Dorsey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s why Dorsey, who literally wrote the book on Parkinson’s, calls the disease “largely preventable.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a long list of environmental factors linked to Parkinson’s, but pesticides are one of the biggest threats, according to Dorsey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“If we clean up our environment, we get rid of Parkinson’s disease,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Research, dating back decades, has explored this link.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An early 1987 case report published in Neurology discusses the case of a 32-year-old citrus farmer who started experiencing tremors, stiffness and clumsiness after 15 years of spraying paraquat. But “a cause-and-effect relationship is difficult to establish,” a doctor wrote at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A decade later, an animal study from Parkinson’s researcher Deborah Cory-Slechta found that paraquat absorbed by mice destroys the specific type of dopamine neuron that dies in Parkinson’s disease. More recently, her research has found paraquat that’s inhaled can also bypass the blood-brain barrier, threatening neurons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s quite clear that it gets into the brain from inhalation models,” Cory-Slechta said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Critics point to other epidemiological studies being more definitive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2011, researchers studied farmworkers exposed to two pesticides, rotenone and paraquat, and determined those exposures increased the risk of developing Parkinson’s by 150%. Another study, published last year, looked at 829 Parkinson’s patients in central California. It found people who live or work near farmland where paraquat is used have a higher risk of developing the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s kind of like secondhand smoke,” Dorsey said. “You can just live or work near where it’s sprayed and be at risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a growing concern in American suburbs where new houses press up against well-maintained golf courses. A study published in JAMA this year found that living within a mile of a golf course increased the risk of Parkinson’s disease by 126%. It didn’t name specific chemicals but did point to pesticides.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EPA in 2021 banned paraquat from golf courses “to prevent severe injury and/or death” from ingestion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite all that, it’s difficult to prove whether paraquat directly causes Parkinson’s because it develops years after exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The disease unfolds over decades, and the seeds of Parkinson’s disease are planted early,” Dorsey said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Where do the lawsuits stand?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The legal case over paraquat inched toward a settlement earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of the lawsuits have been brought in Illinois under what’s known as multi-district litigation. Unlike a class-action lawsuit, this puts individual cases in front of one federal judge. A few bellwether cases are then chosen to represent the masses and streamline the legal process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Syngenta, Chevron and the plaintiffs agreed to settle in April, which would wrap up thousands of cases, but an agreement is still being hammered out, court records show. If details can’t be finalized, it will go to trial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Syngenta has adamantly denied the lawsuits’ allegations, saying it backs paraquat as “safe and effective” when it’s used correctly and emphasizing there has been no peer-reviewed scientific analysis that shows paraquat causes Parkinson’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Syngenta believes there is no merit to the claims, but litigation can be distracting and costly,” a spokesperson said. “Entering in the agreement in no way implies that paraquat causes Parkinson’s disease or that Syngenta has done anything wrong. We stand by the safety of paraquat.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chevron has also denied the claims saying the “scientific consensus is that paraquat has not been shown to be a cause of Parkinson’s disease.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What company files show&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A trove of internal documents released during litigation, as reported by The Guardian and the New Lede, appeared to show that the manufacturers were aware of evidence that paraquat could collect in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the New Lede acknowledged the documents do not show company scientists believed that paraquat causes Parkinson’s, Syngenta officials pointed out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trail of bread crumbs started as early as 1958 when a company scientist wrote about a study of 2.2 dipyridyl, a chemical in paraquat, saying it appears to have moderate toxicity “mainly by affecting the central nervous system, and it can be absorbed through the skin,” the internal documents said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Imperial Chemical Industries, which later became Syngenta, started selling paraquat under the brand name Gramoxone in 1962, according to research. Gramoxone contains nearly 44% paraquat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The internal documents show by 1974, the company updated safety precautions, recommending that anyone spraying the pesticide wear a mask, as there were the first reports of human poisoning and concerns about the effects of paraquat started to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A year later, Ken Fletcher from Imperial Chemical wrote a letter to Chevron scientist Dr. Richard Cavelli, saying the chemical company knew of “sporadic reports of CNS (central nervous system) effects in paraquat poisoning” that he believed to be coincidental.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Within months, Fletcher also indicated “possible chronic effects” of paraquat exposure, calling it “quite a terrible problem” that should be studied more, the documents say.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Due possibly to good publicity on our part, very few people here believe that paraquat causes any sort of problem in the field,” he wrote in the mid 1970s. “Consequently, any allegation of illness due to spraying never reaches serious proportions.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the 1980s, outside research started to pick at the question of paraquat and Parkinson’s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“As more researchers dug into it, it’s only been more firmly established,” said Horsfield with the Environmental Working Group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Syngenta pushes back on this, though, saying two recent reports cast doubt on these claims.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A 2024 scientific report from California pesticide regulators found recent evidence was “insufficient to demonstrate a direct causal association with exposure to paraquat and the increased risk of developing Parkinson’s disease.” And a September analysis from Douglas Weed, an epidemiologist and independent consultant, reached a similar conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Syngenta also claims on its website to be a target of a “mass tort machine” that hovers behind multi-district litigation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why hasn’t the EPA banned it?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1981, Norway became the first country to outlaw paraquat due to the risk of poisoning. One by one, more countries followed suit. In 2007, the European Union approved a blanket ban for all 27 member countries, according to media reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet Syngenta is still allowed to manufacture paraquat in countries that have banned its use. It’s been prohibited in the United Kingdom for 18 years and China banned paraquat to “safeguard people’s life, safety and health,” in 2012, according to a government announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet about two-thirds of the paraquat imported to the U.S. between 2022 and 2024 came from companies owned by the Chinese government, SinoChem and Red Sun Group, according to a joint report published by three advocacy organizations in October.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It found most of the 40 million and 156 million pounds imported annually over the past eight years comes from Chinese manufacturing facilities, in either China or Syngenta’s big factory in northern England.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although hundreds of companies sell paraquat, Syngenta says it accounts for a quarter of global sales.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to previous media reports, SinoChem, a Chinese state-owned conglomerate, acquired Syngenta in a 2020 merger. SinoChem posted $3.4 billion in profits last year, but it’s unclear how much came from paraquat sales because the company doesn’t make earnings reports public. Syngenta reported $803 million in sales of its “non-selective herbicides,” the class that includes paraquat-containing Gramoxone, according to its 2024 financial report.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While Chinese companies supply paraquat to American farmers, the report points out China is also a big purchaser of crops, like soybeans, that are grown with help from the pesticide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In these two ways, China economically benefits from the application of paraquat in the U.S., where it outsources many of its associated health hazards,” the report said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paraquat, now prohibited in more than 70 countries, according to the Environmental Working Group, was reauthorized by the EPA in 2021 when it passed a regularly scheduled 15-year review — a move challenged by critics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“EPA has the same information that those countries have,” said Kalmuss-Katz, the attorney with EarthJustice. “EPA has just reached a fundamentally different, and what we believe is a legally and scientifically unsupported position, which is: massive amounts of paraquat can continue to be sprayed without unreasonable risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The federal agency determined paraquat remains “an effective, inexpensive, versatile, and widely used method of weed control,” and any risks to workers are “outweighed by the benefits” of farms using the weed killer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It is one of the mostly highly regulated pesticides available in the United States,” the agency said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This decision allowed it to be used with “new stronger safety measures to reduce exposure,” like requiring buffer zones where pesticides can’t be sprayed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For plants like cotton, alfalfa, soybeans and peanuts, the EPA wrote in its decision “growers may need to switch to alternative (weed-killers), which could have financial impacts.” Unlike other pesticides, paraquat works well in low temperatures and early in the season, according to the agency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More than 200,000 public comments have been submitted to the EPA’s docket on paraquat over the years. Industry groups, farmers, advocacy organizations and others have all chimed in, arguing for or against the weed killer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One submitted by a North Dakota farmer, Trey Fischbach, urged the EPA to continue allowing paraquat to fight resistant weeds like kochia, writing it’s the “last tool in the toolbox.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EPA also noted there weren’t many other options. “The chemical characteristics of paraquat are also beneficial as a resistance management tool, where few alternatives are available.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But farmers can get trapped on what critics call the “pesticide treadmill,” in which broad pesticide use leads to “superweeds” that require stronger and stronger pesticides to be knocked down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A comment submitted by Kay O’Laughlin, from Massachusetts, urged instead: “Do your job and ban paraquat because it is killing people. I speak as someone who lost a brother to Parkinson’s. People should not be disposable so that big agro can make ever greater profits!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EPA’s 2021 decision was challenged within two months by environmental and farmworker groups who sued the EPA. Kalmuss-Katz said the groups challenged the EPA over reapproving paraquat without “truly grappling” with the connection to Parkinson’s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The EPA here failed to adequately protect farmworkers,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After that, the environmental agency shifted under President Joe Biden.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EPA decided to consider the issues raised in the lawsuits and started seeking additional information last year. In early 2025, it asked the courts for more time to assess the human health risks of paraquat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the EPA wasn’t focused on Parkinson’s, saying in its decision the “weight of evidence was insufficient” to link paraquat exposure to the neurological disease. Rather, the federal question was over how the weed killer turns into a vapor that could harm people when inhaled or touched. “Parkinson’s Disease is not an expected health outcome of pesticidal use of paraquat,” the EPA said in its review.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study could take up to four years, according to the EPA, saying it’s “complex, large scale and is conducted under real world conditions,” while paraquat remains on the market. The agency in October updated the review, saying it’s now seeking additional information from Syngenta.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the EPA has shifted again. The Trump administration this year put four former industry lobbyists or executives, from the agricultural, chemical and cleaning industries, in charge of regulating pesticides at the EPA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And while it’s not clear where the agency stands on paraquat, there has been an early sign of backing away from opposition to controversial pesticides. Shortly after Kyle Kunkler, a recent American Soybean Association lobbyist, was tapped to lead pesticide policy, the EPA moved to reapprove the use of a different, controversial weed killer that had previously been banned by federal courts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Growing pressure to ban it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But grassroots pressure to ban paraquat continues to mount.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This is a pivotal time for whether paraquat is going to remain active in the United States,” said Simmons, a legal expert for Drugwatch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last year, more than 50 Democratic lawmakers, expressing “grave concern” in letters, urged the EPA to ban paraquat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Due to their heightened exposure to paraquat, farmworkers and rural residents are hardest hit by the harmful health effects of paraquat like Parkinson’s,” said an Oct. 7, 2024, letter signed by U.S. representatives. A separate letter was signed by a small group of senators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;California, a heavy user of paraquat as the top agricultural state, became the first to move toward banning paraquat last year. But the bill ended up getting pared back with Gov. Gavin Newsom signing a law to fast-track reevaluating paraquat’s safety, reporting shows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pennsylvania lawmakers are also considering banning it under state bills introduced this year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“There are better, healthier alternatives,” said state Rep. Natalie Mihalek, a Republican who introduced the Pennsylvania legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a federal level, outside the EPA, pesticides appear to be in the crosshairs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Health and Human Services secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr., has criticized chemicals being used in farming. But a new Make America Healthy Again report shows Kennedy has backed away from restricting pesticides after agricultural groups pushed back on the “inaccurate story about American agriculture and our food system.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, there’s been a reported industry effort to pass state laws that would protect pesticide manufacturers from liability. Two states, North Dakota and Georgia, already passed these laws, according to the National Agricultural Law Firm. But a federal bill introduced this year would ensure the manufacturers can’t be held responsible for harming farmers in any state.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As this tug of war continues, paraquat continues to be sprayed on agricultural fields throughout the United States. The EPA is still assessing its risks. And nearly 90,000 Americans are getting diagnosed with Parkinson’s disease every year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile for critics, the evidence seems clear: it’s too dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The easiest thing to do is we should ban paraquat,” Dorsey said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AL.com reporter Margaret Kates contributed to this story.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46275079</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 14:37:12 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>