<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 16:10:10 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Handy – Free open-source speech-to-text app written in Rust</title><link>https://handy.computer/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="848aa87b53323fd2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Video Transcript&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CJ: Hello, I'm CJ and I want to show you Handy. Handy is an open source speech-to-text application that you can run on your own computer. Simply press a keyboard shortcut, speak, and release, and Handy will paste whatever you said into the text field you're typing into.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's take a look at the settings menu for Handy, and it's really simple. You have a push-to-talk mode that you can enable, this is enabled by default so you press and hold the keys or alternatively you can turn it off so the transcription starts when you press the key combination and it stops when you press it again. And you can also change what key binding you would like to use for the transcription.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So now it's mapped to Ctrl-Z and if I turn this off, when I hit control Z, when you look up in the top corner of my Mac here, this little transcription icon lights up. And when I click it again, it turns off and transcribes the audio. There's nothing to paste into. So it just does nothing here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So sit back, relax, and let Handy give you a hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Free&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Accessibility tooling belongs in everyone's hands, not behind a paywall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Open Source&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Together we can build further. Extend Handy for yourself and contribute to something bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Private&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your voice stays on your computer. Get transcriptions without sending audio to the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Simple&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One tool, one job. Transcribe what you say and put it into a text box.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Sponsors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Handy has some amazing sponsors who help keep it free and open source&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Want to sponsor Handy? Feel free to donate, use GitHub Sponsors, or reach out directly to contact@handy.computer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45399106</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 20:33:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Learn to play Go</title><link>https://online-go.com/learn-to-play-go</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d37fffed7efd5e8d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Loading...&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45400376</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 23:50:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Solar panels + cold = A potential problem</title><link>https://www.linspyre.com/ecoholics/temps.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e773707613a0d94b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order to determine what your maximum VoC of an array can be, use one of the conservative estimate tables below or you can compute the temperature coefficients precisely if you have the solar panel specs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example 1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might choose 0°C or 32°F as it almost never freezes in Georgia and the table shows 136.4v as your VoC maximum. The EcoFlow 400w portables have a VoC of 48.0v which means two solar panels in series have a VoC of 96v (Solar Rule #4 above)- well within the 136.4v limit. Three solar panels in series would exceed the 136.4v limit and result in black magic smoke.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example 2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since it gets really cold in Canada you would likely choose -40°C or -40°F and the table shows 48.0v as your VoC maximum at the coldest temperature. The EcoFlow 220w bifacial portables have a VoC of 21.8v which means you can safely put two solar panels in series (43.6v). Since the Delta 2 Max has two solar input XT60i ports, you can actually add four solar panels, two strands of two panels per port.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Published: September 20, 2023&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Updated:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45401051</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 01:48:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>IBM Intellistation 185 AIX workstation (2016)</title><link>http://www.ibmfiles.com/pages/intellipower185.htm</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b78ab9122b85b98d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;IBM IntelliStation POWER 185&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;System Type: 7047&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Released in 2006 after the 285, this system used the PowerPC 970 processors (sometimes erroneously categorized under POWER5 by 3rd parties and at IBM--it would technically be closer to a POWER4). Despite POWER5+ and DDR2 already being used on the 285, the 185 took a few steps back and used DDR1 and didn't bother with the POWER chips. While this may seem rather strange, it can be explained with System p5 185 (7037-A50). Perhaps IBM wanted to create a machine of their own with the PPC 970 or it was stuck in developmental hell for a bit, whatever the case IBM used the 7037 guts to be modified into the IntelliStation 185. This move could have been done to offer a workstation that used less power and was quieter / while still maintaining AIX compatibility. Hundreds went to use in government offices and engineering firms; as a result they mainly show up in the U.S. and Japan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of the POWER and AIX people don't even know that IBM badged the 970 under POWER and popped it into a workstation; therefore making the IntelliStation "POWER" 185 a source of confusion, horror and intrigue--and the fact it's relatively unknown means you'll get different responses as to what it can and cannot do. It is still a POWER system in firmware, and supports hardware virtualization like any other POWER system, which makes it completely different from a Power Mac G5 which uses the same CPU. If it didn't support hardware virtualization IBM wouldn't have been able to call the original System p5 185 a System p5... it would just be a plain PowerPC box. But this wasn't too unfamiliar as other AIX systems in the past also leveraged PowerPC chips like RS/6000s and PowerPC ThinkPads. I suspect the whole reason why the PowerPC 970MP had virtualization in the first place was because of IBM's exact requirement for this on their System p5 that they were intending to use it in (which Apple never did on the G5 as far as I know), and then of course Apple wanted AltiVec (which IBM didn't use in AIX as far as I know, but that doesn't mean you couldn't write AIX software to leverage it).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Downloads&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; Latest System Firmware (AT071-156, RPM package) - 05/11/2007&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to IBM's licensing agreements I am not entitled to distribute the firmware update as it's licensed code. Therefore the above link redirects to IBM's legacy firmware page where it can be downloaded. If the firmware ever gets pulled from the website I will consider mirroring it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; IBM IntelliStation POWER 185 Hardware Announcement - February 14, 2006&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; IBM IntelliStation POWER 185 RedBook Overview&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; Quick Start Guide for IntelliStation POWER 185&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; Installing SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 9 SP3 on POWER 185&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; Installing Red Hat Enterprise Linux AS 4 Update 3 on POWER 185&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; TAGITT-CATIA V4/ENOVIA DMU Evaluation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; UNIX Workstations Facts and Features (2006)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; System i &amp;amp; p PCI adapters (44 MB!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; System i &amp;amp; p fans&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; IBM IntelliStation POWER and IBM RS/6000 Graphics Performance Report&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; IBM Installation Toolkit 4.2 Release Notes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; IBM Installation Toolkit 4.2 User's Manual&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; RS/6000 SpaceBall Announcement on AIX&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; 3Dconnexion 3DxWare AIX Driver (1.6.0 11/29/2011)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; 3Dconnexion Xdriver AIX 5+ (4.66 11/18/2005)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: it seems that the 3DxWare driver should support the SpaceBall and SpaceMouse, along with offering new support for the SpacePilot and SpaceExplorer on AIX. However if that's not the case the older Xdriver can be used.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--&amp;gt; Open Sound System for AIX (OSS/AIX v3.9.8g)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: you must purchase a license from 4Front Technologies to activate OSS/AIX (while it's released as open source the old UNIX versions are not).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PowerPC 970MP running in single-core?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It may sound strange but the IntelliStation POWER 185 is in fact running the PowerPC 970MP "dual core" chip in single core mode. This is undocumented on the PPC 970MP datasheet and not implemented on anything else as far as I can tell. I'm not exactly sure how this was achieved but it's either a hidden switch on the PPC970MP or a special switch done through firmware. The reason why this was done was to reduce the thermal requirements for a smaller system and smaller heatsink; as a work-around IBM then offered adding a second PowerPC 970MP in the IntelliStation 185 (also running in single-core mode) to simulate a "dual-core" PowerPC 970MP setup through two discreet chips instead of one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;7037-A50 or 7047-185, which came first&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's easy to tell the 7037-A50 came first based on the fact documentation always shows the system with a 7037 bezel instead of the characteristic one present on 7047: even on the IntelliStation POWER 185's service diagram on the metal door. Furthermore based on the timing, where IBM felt they needed a lower-end IntelliStation POWER to complement the already released 285 / why create a system from scratch when the upcoming 7037 design could be used. It gets somewhat interesting because this means the IntelliStation 185's bezel was designed after-the-fact, as a result that's why it is so thick on the front to compensate for the slanting that's characeristic of (most) IntelliStations. However, vendors and IBM constantly mix 7037 and 7047 in stock photos and documentation. The photo below shows a 7037 and you can see how it is inspired by 9228--oh and the bezel is flush against the front:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The story doesn't end there... System p5 185 sold *so* poorly (and was more work for IBM to support due to the PPC 970 that really should have never been considered p5) that IBM discontinued it a year after its release in 2007, while the IntelliStation 185 continued to be sold until 2009.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deceptive as a Greyghost (PC Server 500)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The IntelliStation 185 POWER was aimed towards CAD running under AIX, and had a specific emphasis on quiet operations, as mentioned in the hardware announcement "A quiet deskside form factor". Unlike System x and the IntelliStation 9228 (which is based on a System x), these run amazingly quiet for what they are--which begs the question why couldn't have IBM calibrated the cooling of System x like the POWER 185 as the design (internally) is very similar to 9228?* In fact the original external appearance of 7037-A50 could be confused with 9228; so there was some inspiration between the two. A lot of attention was put into the acoustics as the system is lined extensively with foam, unlike the 9228 or even 7382 which hails as one of the poorest 'acoustic' performers and makes a similar sound to an IntelliStation POWER 285. The characteristic front fold baffle is also meant to reduce noise (and is actually a separate piece clipped in to the main bezel: the design would be rather complex to injection mold as a single piece).in).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;*I have confirmed System x towers can run fine with noctua fans / of course I suppose System x is not design to reside as a workstation, but still. The servers have thermal sensors so it would be VERY little effort for IBM to calibrate the fans at a slower RPM instead of hard-lining at a higher-than-necessary value--'desktop mode' could even be added to the UEFI. Even worse, the IntelliStation 6225 was never shipped with a rear fan when it's REALLY ideal to have one (else the FSB can get up to 90C), and when a rear fan is installed the controller throttles it down to a few *hundred* RPM. I suppose different engineers were involved with the RPM tuning on 7047-185, 7382, 9228, 9229 and 6225 so I shouldn't be that critical.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here with the IntelliStation POWER 185 opened up into pieces you can see the foam lining behind the front bezel along with the interior baffles being lined with foam. The foam on the front bezel was actually manually cut near the intake bezel to angle it off:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's a workstation not a server&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some mistake the IntelliStation POWER 185 as a "server" or try to say that IntelliStation POWERs in general are servers, but it was always meant as an end-user workstation typically involving CAD or industrial design. The correct "server" product would be system type 7037-A50, the A50 was modified to perform as a server and not a CAD workstation / and also features some differences supported PCI add-ons. It's still hard to distinguish the two when the workstations are directly derived from the servers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By all means you can use an IntelliStation POWER as a server, but then it's being under-utilizing for what it can really do and missing an opportunity for getting the most out of AIX as a "desktop" OS. Something which is rarely exhibited with the phasing out of the CAD components the IntelliStations first brought to the table.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNIX high-end CAD meets its death&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the ancients roamed the earth (2006), Dassault Systemes ported CATIA V5 and V6 to AIX, most likely by request from IBM. What's weird about this is that you'll be hard-pressed to find any references to CATIA being run on UNIX now, Dassault completely removed it but there's probably a story behind this as to why. If you go back to the Dassault Systemes website in early 2007, you'll see that they still reference support for Windows and all major flavours of UNIX--but there's one key phrase near the end where they say: "Dassault Systemes has set up a certification program... (blah blah blah)... since the launch of V5, natively developed on windows NT Platform". At that point Windows XP 32-bit was the most commonly used variant, and while you could run XP 64-bit (and IBM did have native support for it on the IntelliStation 9228), XP 64-bit had so many problems so most users were stuck with 3.9 GB of RAM. Therefore if we were to assume that UNIX and said UNIX hardware offered way more memory, it starts to make sense (not to mention that the drivers and video cards would be extremely optimized and had features nVidia and ATI didn't offer*--at the time--). This may be even supported further from the POWER 185 RedBook where IBM states: "The addition of native 64-bit capability brings significant performance enhancements of CATIA V5 and ENOVIA DMU Navigator. Initial benchmarks indicate that for memory-intensive operations, such as analysis of large models, global performance is significantly increased. In addition, improvements to clash analysis greatly reduces processing times for analysis of large assemblies." It's also worth pointing out that CATIA predates Windows, so Dassault probably rewrote V5 from scratch on NT.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;*HP's HP-UX hardware being an exception since they just sloppily hacked in standard ATI cards / which means you wouldn't get the extra benefits of running a GXT6500 on AIX as you would with a FireGL X3 on HP-UX. HP probably had the lowest share of the UNIX CAD market so they probably felt little need to invest much R&amp;amp;D: not to mention HP can't make a proper enterprise workstation or server ANYWAYS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the IntelliStation lineup was never involved with the sale of the PC division to Lenovo (and continued to press on for awhile), IBM dropped the x86 IntelliStations in 2006 and the POWER IntelliStations in 2009. Why did IBM bother to dedicate CAD resources to AIX when they were deliberately planning to phase out the platform? As established already, UNIX workstations were 'still a thing' back then and had advantages over the terrible x86 machines at the time (Windows XP with Pentium 4), and it was profitable for IBM (along with HP, SGI and Sun) to manufacture such computers. When x64 Windows 7 rolled by various changes in the market happened alongside it: Sun and SGI went out of business, HP started downsizing and split their enterprise into HPE, and Dassault Systemes dropped support for CAITA on UNIX. The UNIX CAD market had the carpet pulled from underneath and now UNIX was set aside for even more specialized applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The IntelliStation POWER lineup left a few remnants which are still gawked at by users of newer POWER7/8 systems, such as the high-performance CAD GPUs. AIX has never again received high performance video cards / apparently some IBM customers have complained of this, but not enough to warrant development on better AIX graphics cards. As a result, for more realistic graphics performance AIX users continue to use the IntelliStation cards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a story underneath the death march of AIX workstations, if you look carefully you'll notice the GXT6500P was originaly announced in 2002 (along with the IntelliStation POWER 265). IBM never refreshed any of the GXT135P, GXT4500P and GXT6500P cards, still keeping them as "current" offerings for the IntelliStation POWER 185 and 285. And soon as the last two of the POWER IntelliStations were made, other OEMs stopped making UNIX CAD stations and IBM quietly killed all IntelliStations, only leaving System x and System i behind (of course IBM has now even sold System x off in 2014 after the U.S. government reviewed the case as they used System x servers internally).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;POWER Linux vs AIX on the IntelliStation POWER 185&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's get it out of the way: many think AIX will be dead soon and stipulate IBM is wanting clients to all mass migrate to POWER Linux (in fact, Watson was even programmed in POWER Linux and not AIX). The truth of the matter is that AIX contains more features that IBM or anyone else does not add in Linux. For instance, going through the RedBooks and Hardware Announcement, the higher-end CAD cards are not supported under Linux, RAS is not supported, the sound card is not supported and it goes on and on. In other words you're not going to use be using Linux for CAD, graphical operations or sound any time soon. While it may 'seem' IBM wants everyone on POWER Linux and not AIX, you can't use it as a workstation operating system unlike AIX.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because the IntelliStation POWER 185 uses the aforementioned PowerPC 970, POWER Linux itself has limited support on the system. In the June 23 2009 hardware announcement, IBM confirms that SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11 has dropped support for the PowerPC 970:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11 (SLES 11) for POWER supports all POWER5 and POWER6 technology-based systems with the exception of the OpenPower line of servers. It does not support any 970 based systems, which includes JS20, JS21, IBM System p5 185, and the IBM Intellistation POWER 185."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whereas on AIX 7.1 PPC 970 is still supported (note that AIX 7.2 dropped it, but so was the IntelliStation POWER 285):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Only 64-bit Common Hardware Reference Platform (CHRP) machines running selected PowerPC 970, POWER4, POWER5, POWER6, and POWER7 processors that implement the POWER architecture Platform Requirements (PAPR) are supported."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's therefore far more logical to use AIX to get the most out of the IntelliStation's workstation-oriented hardware, since POWER Linux has virtually nothing to offer for graphics support. While AIX and UNIX workstations in general are dead, you won't see such features revisted on newer AIX hardware / and it's *completely* omitted under POWER Linux.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile HPE and Intel seem to be having a hard time maintaining their Itanium contracts and want HP-UX to die / whereas AIX and POWER are in a much better position due to IBM's contributions to Linux and (now) OpenPOWER.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OS Support&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AIX&lt;/p&gt;AIX 7.2 Not Supported&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure why (some) IBM documentation claims AIX 7.1 is not supported on the IntelliStation POWER 185 when it in fact is (yes! You can in fact run AIX 7.1 on a PowerPC 970 CPU).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WARNING: AIX 7.1 wasn't designed with the System p5 185, or AIX workstations in mind anymore; so if you run AIX 7.1 on a system with a single PSU, you will get the rc.powerfail:2 being generated in the console every so often because AIX 7.1 is looking for a redundant power supply that does not exist. Kind of strange considering the System p5 185 lacks a second power supply as well and was sold as a server rack unit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;POWER Linux&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; SUSE Linux Enterprise SLES 9 SP3&lt;lb/&gt; Red Hat Enterprise AS4U3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Great Purge of 2016&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Department of Defense was using a mass horde of IntelliStation POWER 185 units / and much of them have now been tossed back to IBM reselling channels. So, in early 2016 many appeared and obtaining one became a LOT cheaper. The timing is not a coincidence, IBM is phasing out the 185 in mid 2017 so corporate customers are being told to upgrade, or their leases are expiring (requiring a forced upgrade). The fact that some of these computers have been in service for 10 years is an example of how UNIX moves slowly and that the hardware was well built. Unlike other IBM systems, the IntelliStation POWER 185 is uniquely elusive for its age, I don't know if they will continue to drop in price or get more expensive as they reach unobtanium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In one of IBM's client case studies, it is explained that they sold the Polish government 400 IntelliStation POWER 185 workstations / so we can assume a similar amount was also sold to the U.S. government (and in other places, too):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The organization teamed with IBM Global Technology Services to implement a solution based on IBM Lotus Domino Collaboration Express software and the Lotus software-based iDoc offering from IBM Business Partner Advatech. The IBM staff loaded the new software on the client's fleet of 400 newly purchased IBM IntelliStation(R) POWER(TM) 185 Express workstations."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure how many of these IntelliStations were sold, maybe a few thousand at best? But if we were to take into consideration that a typical system would probably be around $8,000, times that by four hundred and you're looking at $3.2 million! Later the document explains that operating costs for the client were reduced as a result of using that IBM solution. I suppose in the grand scheme of things they would be--since they probably used them for 10 years / and since the hardware was so robust IBM wouldn't have to do any work on the service agreement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GPU options and caveats&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned throughout, the IntelliStation 185 was geared towards CAD design and as such supported GPU options. Here are the three main GPUs that the system supports, it may be possible to run others but I have not tried it:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; GXT4500P (FC 2842 - IBM)&lt;lb/&gt; GXT6500P (FC 2843 - IBM)&lt;lb/&gt; GXT135P (FC 1980 - Matrox)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GXT4500P and GXT6500P are the premier cards designed in-house by IBM; they only run properly on AIX and no Linux support exists. The GXT135P is a rebadged Matrox GT series card and runs under both AIX and Linux, but is far more limited in graphical capabilities. Apparently two GXT4500Ps can be ran in the IntelliStation, however I don't know if this will enable dual-monitor support. Only one GXT6500P can be ran in a system at a time. Up to FOUR GXT135Ps can be stuffed into an IntelliStation, this could theoreitcally allow eight monitors to be connected, however again, that would all depend if AIX could support it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Firmware options&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The IntelliStation POWER 185 has an array of its own unique firmware options, similar to a BIOS/UEFI on a regular x86 computer. Below is what options you get when selecting to go into the firmware menu upon when the machine first starts up:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Main Menu&lt;lb/&gt; 1 Select Language&lt;lb/&gt; 2 Setup Remote IPL (Initial Program Load)&lt;lb/&gt; 3 Change SCSI Settings&lt;lb/&gt; 4 Select Console&lt;lb/&gt; 5 Select Boot Options&lt;lb/&gt; 6 Power/Restart Control&lt;lb/&gt; 7 System Service Aids&lt;lb/&gt; 8 Set Beep Volume&lt;lb/&gt; 9 Select Keyboard&lt;lb/&gt; --------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;lb/&gt; Navigation keys:&lt;lb/&gt; M = return to Main Menu N = Next page of list&lt;lb/&gt; ESC key = return to previous screen X = eXit System Management Services&lt;lb/&gt; --------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;lb/&gt; Type menu item number and press Enter or select Navigation key&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Basically all of the options are self-explanatory really. I had to change the sound of the system beep since it was WAY too loud on its default setting. I chose 6.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PCI adapter placement&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike most computers, the IntelliStation POWER series can be sensitive what adapter is placed where: this is due to the way each slot is tied to the north bridge via the hyper transport tunnels and individual sub PCI bridges. There are a total of four PCI-X slots with a regular 32-bit PCI slot at the very top. Slots 2 &amp;amp; 3 have direct access and operate at 133 Mhz, slots 4 &amp;amp; 5 are shared and operate at 100 Mhz, slot 1 is a regular PCI slot and operates at 33 Mhz. Slot 5 can operate at 133 Mhz but only if slot 4 is empty, otherwise it runs at 100 Mhz.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Feature code (FC)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Base unit slot priority&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;7047-185 max. allowed adapters&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2842 (GXT4500P)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2843 (GXT6500P)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1954*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5/4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5740*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1984*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5/4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5706*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5/4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5707*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5/4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1983*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5/4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1978*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1979*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5700*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5701*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5759**&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4 3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1910**&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4 3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1905*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5758*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1986*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1987*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5713*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5714*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1977, 5716* (Fibre Channel Adapter)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1912* (Ultra320 LVD SCSI Adapter)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4, 1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5736*&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4, 1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1913* (Ultra320 LVD SCSI RAID Adapter)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5737* (Disk Controller)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 5, 4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2849, 1980 (GXT135P)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2, 3, 4, 5&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2947 (4-Port Multiprotocol Adapter)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;4, 5, 3, 2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;5723 (2-Port asynchronous Serial Adapter)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1, 4, 5, 3, 2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="3"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2943 (8-Port asynchronous Serial Adapter)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1, 4, 5, 3, 2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;8244 (Crystal PCI Audio Adapter)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;** Extra-high bandwidth (EHB) adapter. See the Performance notes before installing this adapter.&lt;lb/&gt; * High bandwidth (HB) adapter. See the Performance notes before installing this adapter. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Performance notes (for optimum performance)&lt;lb/&gt; System unit information:&lt;lb/&gt; -No more than three EHB adapters can be placed in the system. If an EHB adapter is placed in the system, it must be the only EHB or HB adapter attached to the PHB it uses.&lt;lb/&gt; -No more than four HB adapters can be placed in the system&lt;lb/&gt; -No more than three Gb Ethernet ports per PHB.&lt;lb/&gt; -No more than three 1 Gb Ethernet ports per one CPU in a system. More Ethernet adapters can be added for connectivity.&lt;lb/&gt; -If an adapter lists slot 5/4, this indicates the adapter can go in slot 5 or 4, but not both 5 and 4.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Control Panel Functions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the front of the IntelliStation POWER 185 the control panel pops out (pushing the tab sideways) and there are a fair bit of functions to choose from / the default boot (or IPL) would be set to 'N, F, P', then you simply press the power button and away it goes; you can also choose the 'service IPL' mode from the Open Firmware menu as well without ever having to touch the panel. Since some of these functions are specific to the IntelliStation 185 they're not entirely agnostic to other "IPL" systems or mainframes. I've extracted the function help from the IBM knowledgebase below. Quick trivia: the IntelliStation POWER 185's specific control panel has been borrowed and re-used in later POWER systems such as the Power 720 and Power S814, it's funny because not many know of this particular machine, yet parts of it live on, photo of it below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Function 01: Display selected system operating mode, IPL speed, and firmware IPL mode&lt;lb/&gt; This function displays the selected system operating mode, speed, and firmware mode for the next IPL on the 7037-A50 server and the 7047-185 workstation. This function is available in both normal and manual operating mode. This function displays the following information:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The valid logical key modes (N).&lt;lb/&gt; The IPL speed (F).&lt;lb/&gt; The firmware mode (P or T).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Function/Data&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action or description&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt; 0 1 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll to function 01.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0 1 _ _ _ _ _ N _ _ _ _ F _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ P _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Valid system operating mode is N.&lt;p&gt;Valid IPL speed display is F.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Valid firmware IPL modes are P and T.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;P = permanent side boot&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;T = temporary side boot&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0 1 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll through the control panel functions.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt; Function 02: Select firmware IPL mode&lt;lb/&gt; This function allows you to select the firmware IPL mode on the 7037-A50 server and the 7047-185 workstation. This function is available in both normal and manual operating mode.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Function/Data&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action or description&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt; 0 2 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll to function 02..&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0 2 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ P _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to start function 02. The current firmware mode is displayed.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0 2 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ T &amp;lt; _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll through the firmware IPL modes. Valid firmware IPL modes are P and T.&lt;p&gt;P = permanent side boot&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;T = temporary side boot&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0 2 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to select the firmware IPL mode and exit function 02.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0 2 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll through the control panel functions.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt; Function 04: Lamp test&lt;lb/&gt; This function performs a lamp test on the 7037-A50 server and the 7047-185 workstation. This function is available in both normal and manual operating mode. This function shows whether any control panel indicators are burned out and whether characters that are displayed in the Function/Data display on the control panel are valid. When you activate this test, all the control panel lights and indicators are lit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lamp test continues on the system control panel for four minutes. Use this procedure to verify that the lights on the system control panel are working correctly. If you cannot complete these steps, see "Starting Point for All Problems" in the Problem Analysis information for your system to start problem analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; 1. Power on the system.&lt;lb/&gt; 2. Press the Increment (up) or Decrement (down) buttons on the control panel to display function 04.&lt;lb/&gt; Press Enter on the control panel.&lt;lb/&gt; 3. Do all of the lights and indicators on the system control panel come on?&lt;lb/&gt; Yes No&lt;lb/&gt; -&amp;gt; Exchange the control panel or the replaceable unit that contains the control panel function [system unit backplane (MB1) or tower card (CB1)]. See "Removal and Installation Procedures" in the Problem Analysis information for your system.&lt;lb/&gt; 4. Do the expansion unit control panel lights all come on?&lt;lb/&gt; Yes No&lt;lb/&gt; -&amp;gt; Exchange the control panel on the expansion unit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lights on the system control panel are working correctly. This ends the procedure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Function 05: Remind mode&lt;lb/&gt; This function allows you to place the system fault-indicator LED in remind mode on the 7037-A50 server and the 7047-185 workstation. This function is available in both normal and manual operating mode.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the system fault-indicator LED is on solid, an error condition exists on the system. If you want to defer the repair of the error, you can place the system fault-indicator LED in remind mode. Placing the system in remind mode causes the system fault-indicator LED to flash instead of being on solid. The remind mode lets you know that a system fault that you have deferred still exists on the system. If any other serviceable event occurs on the system, the remind mode is changed back to system fault mode, where the LED is on solid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Function/Data&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action or description&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt; 0 5 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll to function 05.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;R E M I N D M O D E O N _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Press Enter to start function 05. Valid options are:&lt;p&gt;Remind mode ON&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remind mode OFF&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;R E M I N D M O D E O F F _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to toggle the option on or off.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0 5 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll through the control panel functions.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; Light path diagnostic card indicator LED layout for the 7037-A50 and 7047-185 models&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; 1 Power supply fault-indicator LED&lt;lb/&gt; 2 Voltage-regulator module fault-indicator LED&lt;lb/&gt; 3 Disk-drive bay fan fault-indicator LED&lt;lb/&gt; 4 Optical-media bay fault-indicator LEDs&lt;lb/&gt; 5 Disk-drive bay fault-indicator LEDs&lt;lb/&gt; 6 System backplane fault-indicator LED&lt;lb/&gt; 7 Front fan fault-indicator LED&lt;lb/&gt; 8 Battery fault-indicator LED&lt;lb/&gt; 9 PCI adapter fault-indicator LED&lt;lb/&gt; 10 Thermal fault-indicator LED&lt;lb/&gt; 11 Rear fan fault-indicator LED&lt;lb/&gt; 12 Memory fault-indicator LED&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Function 06: Display the BMC version&lt;lb/&gt; This function displays the base motherboard controller (BMC) version on the 7037-A50 server and the 7047-185 workstation. This function is available in both normal and manual operating mode. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Function/Data&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action or description&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt; 0 6 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll to function 06.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;B M C: A W 8 T x x A _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to start function 06. An example of the BMC version is AW8T23A.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0 6 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll through the control panel functions.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt; Function 09: Display the BMC fan speed&lt;lb/&gt; This function displays the base motherboard controller (BMC) fan speed on the 7037-A50 server and the 7047-185 workstation. This function is available in both normal and manual operating mode. The display alternates every two seconds between MAIN, DASD, and PCI fan speed.&lt;lb/&gt; The following table provides details about this function. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Function/Data&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action or description&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt; 0 9 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll to function 09.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;M A I N: 7 b 0 _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to start function 09. The main fan speed is listed in hexadecimal (rpm).&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;D A S D: 7 0 0 _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to start function 09. The DASD fan speed is listed in hexadecimal (rpm).&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;P C I: 7 b 0 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to start function 09. The PCI (I/O) fan speed is listed in hexadecimal (rpm).&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0 9 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll through the control panel functions.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt; Function 10: Display the temperature&lt;lb/&gt; This function displays the temperature on the 7037-A50 server and the 7047-185 workstation. This function is available in both normal and manual operating mode. The display alternates every two seconds between ambient, CPU1, and CPU2 temperature. The following table provides details about this function. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Function/Data&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action or description&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt; 1 0 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll to function 10.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;A m b i e n t : 3 e , 3 e _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Press Enter to start function 10. The ambient temperature is listed in hexadecimal (degrees Celsius).&lt;p&gt;The first value is the average temperature over a time span.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last value is the most recent temperature reading.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;C P U 1 : 5 0 , 6 f _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt; Press Enter to start function 10. The CPU1 temperature is listed in hexadecimal (degrees Celsius).&lt;p&gt;The first value is the average temperature over a time span.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last value is the most recent temperature reading.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;C P U 2 : 0 , 0 _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to start function 10. The CPU2 temperature is listed in hexadecimal (degrees Celsius).&lt;p&gt;The first value is the average temperature over a time span.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last value is the most recent temperature reading.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reading is 0 if the system is one-way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1 0 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll through the control panel functions.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt; Function 20: System type and model&lt;lb/&gt; This function displays the machine type and model on the 7037-A50 server and the 7047-185 workstation. This function is available in both normal and manual operating mode. The machine type and model is displayed in the following format:&lt;lb/&gt; p p p p - m m m _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;lb/&gt; The values are indicated as follows:&lt;lb/&gt; Values for p indicate the machine type.&lt;lb/&gt; Values for m indicate the machine model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Function 22: Partition dump&lt;lb/&gt; This function initiates a dump of a partition's operating system data on the 7037-A50 server and the 7047-185 workstation. This function is available in both normal and manual operating mode. You must perform two consecutive function 22 selections to initiate a partition dump. The following table shows an example of function 22. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Function/Data&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action or description&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2 2 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll to function 22.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2 2 _ _ _ _ 0 0 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to start function 22.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;A 1 0 0 3 0 2 2 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Displays the partition dump verification system reference code (SRC).&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2 2 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Use the Increment or Decrement buttons to scroll to function 22.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2 2 _ _ _ _ 0 0 _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;p&gt;_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Press Enter to start function 22.&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45401907</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 05:04:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Run 14 vintage OSes (Windows 1.01→XP, ReactOS, Haiku) in the browser</title><link>https://oses.ioblako.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d51f005e2f6331b5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experience vintage operating systems directly in your browser. No downloads, no installation - just pure nostalgia powered by cutting-edge WebAssembly technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-configured collection from Windows 1.01 to modern alternatives like ReactOS and Haiku. Each system optimized for best performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Near-native performance using WebAssembly technology. Full x86 processor emulation running entirely in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Complete mouse and keyboard support with special key injection. Hardware-accurate scancode generation for perfect compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upload your own .img and .iso files. Configurable memory settings and boot order for maximum compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everything runs in your browser. No plugins, no downloads, no security concerns. Just open and start computing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perfect for education, software preservation, and experiencing computing history. Learn how operating systems evolved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Explore decades of computing history with our curated collection&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45402197</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 06:31:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Beyond OpenMP in C++ and Rust: Taskflow, Rayon, Fork Union</title><link>https://ashvardanian.com/posts/beyond-openmp-in-cpp-rust/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="776ed3c34da494ba"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Most C++ and Rust thread-pool libraries leave significant performance on the table - often running 10× slower than OpenMP on classic fork-join workloads and micro-benchmarks. So I’ve drafted a minimal ~300-line library called Fork Union that lands within 20% of OpenMP. It does not use advanced NUMA tricks; it uses only the C++ and Rust standard libraries and has no other dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Update (Sep 2025): Since the v2 release, Fork Union supports NUMA and Huge Pages, as well as&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;tpause&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;wfet&lt;/code&gt;, and other “pro” features. Check the README for details.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenMP has been the industry workhorse for coarse-grain parallelism in C and C++ for decades. I lean on it heavily in projects like USearch, yet I avoid it in larger systems because:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fine-grain parallelism with independent subsystems doesn’t map cleanly to OpenMP’s global runtime.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Portability of the C++ STL and the Rust standard library is better than OpenMP.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Meta-programming with OpenMP is a pain - mixing &lt;code&gt;#pragma omp&lt;/code&gt;with templates quickly becomes unmaintainable.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I went looking for ready-made thread pools in C++ and Rust — only to realize most of them implement asynchronous task queues, a much heavier abstraction than OpenMP’s fork-join model. Those extra layers introduce what I call the four horsemen of low performance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Locks &amp;amp; mutexes with syscalls in the hot path.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Heap allocations in queues, tasks, futures, and promises.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compare-and-swap (CAS) stalls in the pessimistic path.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;False sharing unaligned counters thrashing cache lines.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With today’s dual-socket AWS machines pushing 192 physical cores, I needed something leaner than Taskflow, Rayon, or Tokio. Enter Fork Union.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hardware: AWS Graviton 4 metal (single NUMA node, 96× Arm v9 cores, 1 thread/core). Workload: “ParallelReductionsBenchmark” - summing single-precision floats in parallel. In this case, just one cache line (&lt;code&gt;float[16]&lt;/code&gt;) per core—small enough to stress synchronization cost of the thread pool rather than arithmetic throughput of the CPU.
In other words, we are benchmarking kernels similar to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google Benchmark numbers for the C++ version of Fork Union, compared to OpenMP, Taskflow, and allocating 96× &lt;code&gt;std::thread&lt;/code&gt; objects on-demand, are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’ve cleaned up the output, focusing only on the relevant rows and the reduction throughput.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Criterion.rs numbers for the Rust version of Fork Union, compared to Rayon, Tokio, and Smol’s Async Executors, are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The timing methods used in those two executables are different, but the relative observations should hold.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Spawning new threads is obviously too expensive.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Most reusable thread pools are still 10x slower to sync than OpenMP.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OpenMP isn’t easy to compete with and still outperforms Fork Union by 20%.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This clearly shows, how important it is to chose the right tool for the job. Don’t pick an asynchronous task pool for a fork-join blocking workload!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Four Horsemen of Performance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This article won’t be a deep dive into those topics. Each deserves its own article and a proper benchmark, with some good ones already available and linked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Locks and Mutexes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike the &lt;code&gt;std::atomic&lt;/code&gt;, the &lt;code&gt;std::mutex&lt;/code&gt; update may result in a system call, and it can be expensive to acquire and release.
Its implementations generally have 2 executable paths:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;the fast path, where the mutex is not contended, where it first tries to grab the mutex via a compare-and-swap operation, and if it succeeds, it returns immediately.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;the slow path, where the mutex is contended, and it has to go through the kernel to block the thread until the mutex is available.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Linux, the latter translates to a “futex” syscall and an expensive context switch. In Rust, the same applies to &lt;code&gt;std::async::atomic&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;std::sync::Mutex&lt;/code&gt;.
Prefer the former when possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Memory Allocations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most thread-pools use classes like &lt;code&gt;std::future&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;std::packaged_task&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;std::function&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;std::queue&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;std::conditional_variable&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Rust land, there will often be a&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;std::Box&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;std::Arc&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;std::collections::VecDeque&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;std::sync::mpsc&lt;/code&gt;or even&lt;code&gt;std::sync::mpmc&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of those, I believe, aren’t unusable in Big-Data applications, where you always operate in memory-constrained environments:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Raising a &lt;code&gt;std::bad_alloc&lt;/code&gt;exception when there is no memory left and just hoping that someone up the call stack will catch it is not a great design idea for Systems Engineering.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The threat of having to synchronize ~200 physical CPU cores across 2-8 sockets and potentially dozens of NUMA nodes around a shared global memory allocator practically means you can’t have predictable performance.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we focus on a simpler &lt;del&gt;concurrency&lt;/del&gt; parallelism model, we can avoid the complexity of allocating shared states, wrapping callbacks into some heap-allocated “tasks”, and a lot of other boilerplates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Less work = more performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Atomics and CAS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you get to the lowest-level primitives on concurrency, you end up with the &lt;code&gt;std::atomic&lt;/code&gt; and a small set of hardware-supported atomic instructions.
Hardware implements it differently:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;x86 is built around the “Total Store Order” (TSO) memory consistency model and provides &lt;code&gt;LOCK&lt;/code&gt;variants of the&lt;code&gt;ADD&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;CMPXCHG&lt;/code&gt;. These variants act as full-blown “fences” — no loads or stores can be reordered across them. This makes atomic operations on x86 straightforward but heavyweight.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Arm, on the other hand, has a “weak” memory model and provides a set of atomic instructions that are not fenced and match the C++ concurrency model. It offers &lt;code&gt;acquire&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;release&lt;/code&gt;, and&lt;code&gt;acq_rel&lt;/code&gt;variants of each atomic instruction — such as&lt;code&gt;LDADD&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;STADD&lt;/code&gt;, and&lt;code&gt;CAS&lt;/code&gt;— which allow precise control over visibility and order, especially with the introduction of “Large System Extension” (LSE) instructions in Armv8.1-A.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A locked atomic on x86 requires the cache line in the Exclusive state in the requester’s L1 cache. This would incur a coherence transaction (Read-for-Ownership) if another core had the line. Both Intel and AMD handle this similarly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It makes Arm and Power much more suitable for lock-free programming and concurrent data structures, but some observations hold for both platforms. Most importantly, “Compare and Swap” (CAS) is costly and should be avoided at all costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On x86, for example, the &lt;code&gt;LOCK ADD&lt;/code&gt; can easily take 50 CPU cycles.
It is 50x slower than a regular &lt;code&gt;ADD&lt;/code&gt; instruction but still easily 5-10x faster than a &lt;code&gt;LOCK CMPXCHG&lt;/code&gt; instruction.
Once the contention rises, the gap naturally widens, further amplified by the increased “failure” rate of the CAS operation when the value being compared has already changed.
That’s why, for the “dynamic” mode, we resort to using an additional atomic variable rather than more typical CAS-based implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Alignment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Assuming a thread pool is a heavy object anyway, nobody will care if it’s a bit larger than expected. That allows us to over-align the internal counters to &lt;code&gt;std::hardware_destructive_interference_size&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;std::max_align_t&lt;/code&gt; to avoid false sharing.
In that case, even on x86, where the entire cache will be exclusively owned by a single thread, in eager mode, we end up effectively “pipelining” the execution, where one thread may be incrementing the “in-flight” counter while the other is decrementing the “remaining” counter.
Others are executing the loop body in between.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Comparing APIs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Fork Union&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fork Union has a straightforward goal, so its API is equally clear. There are only 4 core interfaces:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;for_each_thread&lt;/code&gt;- to dispatch a callback per thread, similar to&lt;code&gt;#pragma omp parallel&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;for_each_static&lt;/code&gt;- for individual evenly-sized tasks, similar to&lt;code&gt;#pragma omp for schedule(static)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;for_each_slice&lt;/code&gt;- for slices of evenly-sized tasks, similar to nested&lt;code&gt;#pragma omp for schedule(static)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;for_each_dynamic&lt;/code&gt;- for individual unevenly-sized tasks, similar to&lt;code&gt;#pragma omp for schedule(dynamic, 1)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They all receive a C++ lambda or a Rust closure and a range of tasks to execute. The construction of the thread pool itself is a bit trickier than typically in standard libraries, as “exceptions” and “panics” are not allowed. So, the constructor can’t perform any real work. In C++, the &lt;code&gt;try_spawn&lt;/code&gt; method can be called to allocate all the threads:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you may have noticed, the lambdas are forced to be&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;noexcept&lt;/code&gt;and can’t return anything. This is a design choice that vastly simplifies the implementation.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Rust, similarly, the &lt;code&gt;try_spawn&lt;/code&gt; method can be used:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Assuming Rust has no function overloading, there are a few alternatives:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;try_spawn&lt;/code&gt;- to spawn a thread pool with the main allocator.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;try_spawn_in&lt;/code&gt;- to spawn a thread pool with a custom allocator.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;try_named_spawn&lt;/code&gt;- to spawn a thread pool with the main allocator and a name.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;try_named_spawn_in&lt;/code&gt;- to spawn a thread pool with a custom allocator and a name.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Rayon&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rayon is the go-to Rust library for data parallelism. It suffers from the same core design issues as every other thread pool I’ve looked at on GitHub, but it’s fair to say that at the high level, it provides outstanding coverage for various parallel iterators! As such, there is an open call to explore similar “Map-Reduce” and “Map-Fork-Reduce” patterns in Fork Union to see if they can be implemented efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default &lt;code&gt;.par_iter()&lt;/code&gt; API of Rayon, at the start of the README.md, is not how I’ve used it in “Parallel Reductions Benchmark”.
To ensure that we are benchmarking the actual synchronization cost of the thread pool, I’ve gone directly to the underlying &lt;code&gt;rayon::ThreadPool&lt;/code&gt; API:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Taskflow&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Taskflow is one of the most popular C++ libraries for parallelism. It has many features, including async execution graphs on CPUs and GPUs. The most common example looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite being just an example, it clearly shows how different Taskflow’s core objectives are from OpenMP and Fork Union. It is still probably mainly used for simple static parallelism, similar to our case without complex dependencies and the &lt;code&gt;taskflow&lt;/code&gt; can be reused.
Here is how “Parallel Reductions Benchmark” wraps Taskflow:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only the &lt;code&gt;operator()&lt;/code&gt; method is timed, leaving the construction costs out of the equation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusions &amp;amp; Observations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fork Union shows that a lean, 300-line fork-join pool can sit within ~20% of OpenMP, while more functional pools trail by an order of magnitude. That margin will shift as more workloads, CPUs, and compilers are tested, so treat today’s numbers as directional, not gospel. There may still be subtle memory-ordering bugs lurking in Fork Union, but the core observations should hold: dodge mutexes, dynamic queues, likely-pessimistic CAS paths, and false sharing — regardless of language or framework.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rust is still new territory for me. The biggest surprise is the missing allocator support in &lt;code&gt;std::collections&lt;/code&gt; on the stable toolchain.
Nightly’s &lt;code&gt;Vec::try_reserve_in&lt;/code&gt; helps, but until stable lands, ergonomic custom allocation remains tricky.
The machinery exists in C++, yet most projects ignore it — so the culture needs to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PS: Spot dubious memory-ordering? Open an issue. Want to close the remaining 20% gap? Happy forking 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fork Union, arguably the most unusual parallel-processing library on GitHub, just crossed its first 100 stars — my 12th project to reach that milestone 🥳&lt;/p&gt;— Ash Vardanian (@ashvardanian) September 7, 2025&lt;lb/&gt;Repository: https://t.co/Gyg43GW6d7&lt;lb/&gt;Unlike typical thread-pools, it avoids not only mutexes but even Compare-and-Swap… pic.twitter.com/H2H7fgaXl4&lt;/quote&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45402820</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 08:53:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Curated gamedev specific search engine</title><link>https://gamedevtorch.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="1d0eae37a1e6ef04"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GameDev Torch is a small gamedev specific search engine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Search gamedev related articles, game engines, frameworks, blog posts and more from a manually curated set of websites. Use it to complement your general purpose search engines to easily find niche resources.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;What can I do?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Looking for inspiration? Learn more about "npc ai"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Something's missing? Suggest a new resource to index&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Want to know more? Learn how to query effectively&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Or browse the list of all indexed websites&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Who made this?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find me on bsky&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45403288</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 10:36:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fred Dibnah shows how to erect a chimney scaffold at 200 feet (1982) [video]</title><link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w3ma9iYx4rg</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7055905545553646"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Press Copyright Contact us Creators Advertise Developers Terms Privacy Policy &amp;amp; Safety How YouTube works Test new features NFL Sunday Ticket © 2025 Google LLC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45403373</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 10:52:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Failing to Understand the Exponential, Again</title><link>https://www.julian.ac/blog/2025/09/27/failing-to-understand-the-exponential-again/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2e54f1f6ac5acc0a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Failing to Understand the Exponential, Again&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sat 27 September 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The current discourse around AI progress and a supposed âbubbleâ reminds me a lot of the early weeks of the Covid-19 pandemic. Long after the timing and scale of the coming global pandemic was obvious from extrapolating the exponential trends, politicians, journalists and most public commentators kept treating it as a remote possibility or a localized phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Something similarly bizarre is happening with AI capabilities and further progress. People notice that while AI can now write programs, design websites, etc, it still often makes mistakes or goes in a wrong direction, and then they somehow jump to the conclusion that AI will never be able to do these tasks at human levels, or will only have a minor impact. When just a few years ago, having AI do these things was complete science fiction! Or they see two consecutive model releases and donât notice much difference in their conversations, and they conclude that AI is plateauing and scaling is over.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;METR&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Accurately evaluating AI progress is hard, and commonly requires a combination of both AI expertise and subject matter understanding. Fortunately, there are entire organizations like METR whose sole purpose is to study AI capabilities! We can turn to their recent study "Measuring AI Ability to Complete Long Tasks", which measures the length of software engineering tasks models can autonomously perform:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can observe a clear exponential trend, with Sonnet 3.7 achieving the best performance by completing tasks up to an hour in length at 50% success rate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, at this point Sonnet 3.7 is 7 months old, coincidentally the same as the doubling rate claimed by METR in their study. Can we use this to verify if METR's findings hold up?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes! In fact, METR themselves keep an up-to-date plot on their study website:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can see the addition of recent models such as Grok 4, Opus 4.1, and GPT-5 at the top right of the graph. Not only did the prediction hold up, these recent models are actually slightly above trend, now performing tasks of more than 2 hours!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;GDPval&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A reasonable objection might be that we can't generalize from performance on software engineering tasks to the wider economy - after all, these are the tasks engineers at AI labs are bound to be most familiar with, creating some overfitting to the test set, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortunately, we can turn to a different study, the recent GDPval by OpenAI - measuring model performance in 44 (!) occupations across 9 industries:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The evaluation tasks are sourced from experienced industry professionals (avg. 14 years' experience), 30 tasks per occupation for a total of 1320 tasks. Grading is performed by blinded comparison of human and model-generated solutions, allowing for both clear preferences and ties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again we can observe a similar trend, with the latest GPT-5 already astonishingly close to human performance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might object that this plot looks like it might be levelling off, but this is probably mostly an artefact of GPT-5 being very consumer-focused. Fortunately for us, OpenAI also included other models in the evaluation[1], and we can see that Claude Opus 4.1 (released earlier than GPT-5) performs significantly better - ahead of the trend from the previous graph, and already almost matching industry expert (!) performance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to especially commend OpenAI here for releasing an eval that shows a model from another lab outperforming their own model - this is a good sign of integrity and caring about beneficial AI outcomes!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Outlook&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given consistent trends of exponential performance improvements over many years and across many industries, it would be extremely surprising if these improvements suddenly stopped. Instead, even a relatively conservative extrapolation of these trends suggests that 2026 will be a pivotal year for the widespread integration of AI into the economy:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Models will be able to autonomously work for full days (8 working hours) by mid-2026.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;At least one model will match the performance of human experts across many industries before the end of 2026.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;By the end of 2027, models will frequently outperform experts on many tasks.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It may sound overly simplistic, but making predictions by extrapolating straight lines on graphs is likely to give you a better model of the future than most "experts" - even better than most actual domain experts!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a more concrete picture of what this future would look like I recommend Epoch AI's 2030 report and in particular the in-depth AI 2027 project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The underperformance of both Grok 4 and Gemini 2.5 Pro is also notable, especially given state-of-the-art claims on many benchmarks when released. Beware of Goodhart's law! â©&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tags: ai, progress, agi, safety, productivity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;italics&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;surround text with &lt;quote&gt;*asterisks*&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;bold&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;surround text with &lt;quote&gt;**two asterisks**&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;hyperlink&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;quote&gt;[hyperlink](https://example.com)or just a bare URL&lt;/quote&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;quote&gt;code&lt;/quote&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;surround text with &lt;quote&gt;`backticks`&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;surround text with &lt;quote&gt;~~two tilde characters~~&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;quote&gt;quote&lt;/quote&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;prefix with &lt;quote&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Loading comments...&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45403803</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 12:19:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Privacy Badger is a free browser extension made by EFF to stop spying</title><link>https://privacybadger.org/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6511c9540fb41697"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Privacy Badger&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What is Privacy Badger?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How is Privacy Badger different from other blocking extensions?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Who makes Privacy Badger?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How does Privacy Badger work?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What is a third party tracker?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What do the red, yellow and green sliders in the Privacy Badger menu mean?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why does Privacy Badger block ads?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why doesn't Privacy Badger block all ads?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What is Global Privacy Control (GPC)?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What about tracking by the sites I actively visit, like NYTimes.com or Facebook.com?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Does Privacy Badger contain a list of blocked sites?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How was the cookie blocking yellowlist created?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Does Privacy Badger prevent fingerprinting?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Does Privacy Badger consider every cookie to be a tracking cookie?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Will you be supporting any other browsers besides Chrome, Firefox, Edge and Opera?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Can I download Privacy Badger directly from eff.org?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I run a domain that uses cookies or other tracking. How do I stop Privacy Badger from blocking me?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Where can I find general information about Privacy Badger that I can use for a piece I'm writing?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;As an administrator, how do I configure Privacy Badger on my managed devices?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What is the Privacy Badger license? Where is the Privacy Badger source code?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How can I support Privacy Badger?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How does Privacy Badger handle social media widgets?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How do I uninstall/remove Privacy Badger?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Is Privacy Badger compatible with other extensions, including adblockers?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Is Privacy Badger compatible with Firefox's built-in privacy protections?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why does my browser connect to fastly.com IP addresses on startup after installing Privacy Badger?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why does Privacy Badger need access to my data for all websites?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why aren't videos loading on YouTube? Why isn't Privacy Badger blocking ads on YouTube?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I need help! I found a bug! What do I do now?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What is Privacy Badger?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger is a browser extension that stops advertisers and other third-party trackers from secretly tracking where you go and what pages you look at on the web. If an advertiser seems to be tracking you across multiple websites without your permission, Privacy Badger automatically blocks that advertiser from loading any more content in your browser. To the advertiser, it’s like you suddenly disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How is Privacy Badger different from other blocking extensions?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger was born out of our desire to be able to recommend a single extension that would:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Automatically analyze and block any tracker or ad that violated the principle of user consent&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Function well without any settings, knowledge, or configuration by the user&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use algorithmic methods to decide what is and isn’t tracking&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Be produced by an organization that is unambiguously working for its users rather than for profit&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a result, Privacy Badger differs from traditional ad-blocking extensions in two key ways. First, while most other blocking extensions prioritize blocking ads, Privacy Badger doesn’t block ads unless they happen to be tracking you; in fact, one of our goals is to incentivize advertisers to adopt better privacy practices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, most other blockers rely on a human-curated list of domains or URLs to block. Privacy Badger is an algorithmic tracker blocker – we define what âtrackingâ looks like, and then Privacy Badger blocks or restricts domains that it observes tracking in the wild. What is and isnât considered a tracker is entirely based on how a specific domain acts, not on human judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger sends the Global Privacy Control signal to opt you out of data sharing and selling, and the Do Not Track signal to tell companies not to track you. If trackers ignore these signals, Privacy Badger will learn to block them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond this, Privacy Badger comes with other advantages like cookie blocking, click-to-activate placeholders for potentially useful tracker widgets (video players, comments widgets, etc.), and outgoing link click tracking removal on Facebook and Google.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By using Privacy Badger, you support the Electronic Frontier Foundation and help fight for a better Web for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Who makes Privacy Badger?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger was created by the Electronic Frontier Foundation, a nonprofit organization that protects your privacy and free expression online. We make free tools like Privacy Badger, publish educational guides, testify before lawmakers about technology, and fight for the public interest in courtâall thanks to support from EFFâs members. If you want a better internet and a strong democracy, join the fight against creepy online surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How does Privacy Badger work?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you view a webpage, that page will often be made up of content from many different sources. For example, a news webpage might load the actual article from the news company, ads from an ad company, and the comments section from a different company that’s been contracted out to provide that service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger keeps track of all of this. If the same source seems to be tracking across different websites, then Privacy Badger springs into action, telling the browser not to load any more content from that source. And when your browser stops loading content from a source, that source can no longer track you. Voila!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At a more technical level, Privacy Badger keeps track of the “third party” domains that embed images, scripts and advertising in the pages you visit. Privacy Badger looks for tracking techniques like uniquely identifying cookies, local storage “supercookies,” and canvas fingerprinting. If it observes the same third-party host tracking on three separate sites, Privacy Badger will automatically disallow content from that third-party tracker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, Privacy Badger receives periodic learning updates from Badger Sett, our Badger training project. This “remote learning” automatically discovers trackers present on thousands of the most popular sites on the Web.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What is a third party tracker?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you visit a webpage parts of the page may come from domains and servers other than the one you asked to visit. This is an essential feature of hypertext. On the modern Web, embedded images and code often use cookies and other methods to track your browsing habits â often to display advertisements. The domains that do this are called “third party trackers”, and you can read more about how they work here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What do the red, yellow and green sliders in the Privacy Badger menu mean?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Red means that content from this third party domain has been completely disallowed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yellow means that the third party domain appears to be trying to track you, but it is on Privacy Badger’s cookie-blocking “yellowlist” of third party domains that, when analyzed, seemed to be necessary for Web functionality. In that case, Privacy Badger will load content from the domain but will try to screen out third party cookies and referrers from it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Green means “no action”; Privacy Badger will leave the domain alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why does Privacy Badger block ads?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actually, nothing in the Privacy Badger code is specifically written to block ads. Rather, it focuses on disallowing any visible or invisible “third party” scripts or images that appear to be tracking you even though you specifically denied consent by sending Do Not Track and Global Privacy Control signals. It just so happens that most (but not all) of these third party trackers are advertisements. When you see an ad, the ad sees you, and can track you. Privacy Badger is here to stop that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why doesn't Privacy Badger block all ads?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because Privacy Badger is primarily a privacy tool, not an ad blocker. Our aim is not to block ads, but to prevent non-consensual invasions of people’s privacy because we believe they are inherently objectionable. We also want to create incentives for advertising companies to do the right thing. Of course, if you really dislike ads, you can also install a traditional ad blocker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What is Global Privacy Control (GPC)?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Global Privacy Control (GPC) is a new specification that allows users to tell companies they’d like to opt out of having their data shared or sold. By default, Privacy Badger sends the GPC signal to every company you interact with alongside the Do Not Track (DNT) signal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s the difference? Do Not Track is meant to tell companies that you don’t want to be tracked in any way (learn more about what we mean by “tracking” here). Privacy Badger gives third-party companies a chance to comply with DNT by adopting our DNT policy, and blocks those that look like they’re tracking you anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When DNT was developed, many websites simply ignored usersâ requests not to be tracked. That’s why Privacy Badger has to act as an enforcer: trackers that don’t want to comply with your wishes get blocked. Today, users in many jurisdictions have the legal right to opt out of some kinds of tracking. That’s where GPC comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPC is meant to be a legally-binding request to all companies in places with applicable privacy laws. For example, the California Consumer Privacy Act gives California residents the right to opt out of having their data sold. By sending the GPC signal, Privacy Badger is telling companies that you would like to exercise your rights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The CCPA and other laws are not perfect, which is why Privacy Badger uses both approaches. It asks websites to respect your privacy, and it blocks known trackers from loading at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What about tracking by the sites I actively visit, like NYTimes.com or Facebook.com?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At present, Privacy Badger primarily protects you against tracking by third party sites. As far as privacy protections for “first party” sites (sites that you visit directly), Privacy Badger removes outgoing link click tracking on Facebook and Google. We plan on adding more first party privacy protections in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are doing things in this order because the most scandalous, intrusive and objectionable form of online tracking is that conducted by companies you’ve often never heard of and have no relationship with. First and foremost, Privacy Badger is there to enforce Do Not Track against these domains by providing the technical means to restrict access to their tracking scripts and images. The right policy for whether nytimes.com, facebook.com or google.com can track you when you visit that site â and the technical task of preventing it â is more complicated because often tracking is interwoven with the features the site offers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Does Privacy Badger contain a list of blocked sites?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike other blocking tools, we have not made decisions about which sites to block, but rather about which behavior is objectionable. Domains will only be blocked if Privacy Badger observes the domain collecting unique identifiers after it was sent Do Not Track and Global Privacy Control signals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger does contain a “yellowlist” of some sites that are known to provide essential third party resources; those sites show up as yellow and have their cookies blocked rather than being blocked entirely. This is a compromise with practicality, and in the long term we hope to phase out the yellowlist as these third parties begin to explicitly commit to respecting Do Not Track. The criteria for including a domain on the yellowlist can be found here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How was the cookie blocking yellowlist created?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The initial list of domains that should be cookie blocked rather than blocked entirely was derived from a research project on classifying third party domains as trackers and non-trackers. We will make occasional adjustments to it as necessary. If you find domains that are under- or over-blocked, please file a bug on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Does Privacy Badger prevent fingerprinting?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Browser fingerprinting is an extremely subtle and problematic method of tracking, which we documented with the Cover Your Tracks project. Privacy Badger can detect canvas-based fingerprinting, and will block third party domains that use it. Detection of other forms of fingerprinting and protections against first-party fingerprinting are ongoing projects. Of course, once a domain is blocked by Privacy Badger, it will no longer be able to fingerprint you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Does Privacy Badger consider every cookie to be a tracking cookie?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No. Privacy Badger analyzes the cookies from each site; unique cookies that contain tracking IDs are disallowed, while “low entropy” cookies that perform other functions are allowed. For instance a cookie like LANG=fr that encodes the user’s language preference, or a cookie that preserves a very small amount of information about ads the user has been shown, would be allowed provided that individual or small groups of users’ reading habits could not be collected with them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Will you be supporting any other browsers besides Chrome, Firefox, Edge and Opera?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are working towards Safari on macOS support. Safari on iOS seems to lack certain extension capabilities required by Privacy Badger to function properly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chrome on Android does not support extensions. To use Privacy Badger on Android, install Firefox for Android.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger does not work with Microsoft Edge Legacy. Please switch to the new Microsoft Edge browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Can I download Privacy Badger directly from eff.org?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you use Google Chrome, you have to install extensions from Chrome Web Store. To install Privacy Badger in Chrome, visit Privacy Badger’s Chrome Web Store listing and click the “Add to Chrome” button there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Otherwise, you can use the following links to get the latest version of Privacy Badger directly from eff.org:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Firefox: https://www.eff.org/files/privacy-badger-latest.xpi&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Chromium: https://www.eff.org/files/privacy_badger-chrome.crx&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;I run a domain that uses cookies or other tracking. How do I stop Privacy Badger from blocking me?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One way is to stop tracking users who have turned on Global Privacy Control or Do Not Track signals (i.e., stop collecting cookies, supercookies or fingerprints from them). Privacy Badger will stop learning to block that domain. The next version of Privacy Badger to ship with an updated pre-trained list will no longer include that domain in the list. Most Privacy Badger users will then update to that list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also unblock yourself by promising to meaningfully respect the Do Not Track signal. To do so, post a verbatim copy of EFF’s Do Not Track policy to the URL https://example.com/.well-known/dnt-policy.txt, where “example.com” is replaced by your domain. Posting EFF’s DNT policy on a domain is a promise of compliance with EFF’s DNT Policy by that domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your domain is compliant with EFF’s DNT policy and declares this compliance, most Privacy Badgers will see this declaration the next time they encounter your domain. Also, the next version of Privacy Badger to ship with an updated pre-trained list will probably include your declaration of compliance in the list.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that the domain must support HTTPS, to protect against tampering by network attackers. The path contains “.well-known” per RFC 5785. Also note that you must post a copy of the policy at each compliant subdomain you control. For example, if you wish to declare compliance by both sub1.example.com and sub2.example.com, you must post EFF’s DNT policy on each domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Where can I find general information about Privacy Badger that I can use for a piece I'm writing?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Glad you asked! Check out this downloadable press kit that we’ve put together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;As an administrator, how do I configure Privacy Badger on my managed devices?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please see our enterprise deployment and configuration document.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What is the Privacy Badger license? Where is the Privacy Badger source code?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger’s source code is licensed under GPLv3+. This website’s source code is licensed under AGPLv3+.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How can I support Privacy Badger?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for asking! Individual donations make up about half of EFF’s support, which gives us the freedom to work on user-focused projects. If you want to support the development of Privacy Badger and other projects like it, you can throw us a few dollars here. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to help directly with the project, we appreciate that as well. Please see Privacy Badger’s CONTRIBUTING document for ways to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How does Privacy Badger handle social media widgets?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social media widgets (such as the Facebook Like button) often track your reading habits. Even if you don’t click them, the social media companies often see exactly which pages you’re seeing the widget on. When blocking social buttons and other potentially useful (video, audio, comments) widgets, Privacy Badger can replace them with click-to-activate placeholders. You will not be tracked by these replacements unless you explicitly choose to click them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How do I uninstall/remove Privacy Badger?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firefox: See the Disable or remove Add-ons Mozilla help page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chrome: See the Install and manage extensions Chrome Web Store help page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edge: See the Add or remove browser add-ons, extensions, and toolbars Microsoft help page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Is Privacy Badger compatible with other extensions, including adblockers?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger should be compatible with other extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While there is likely to be overlap between the various manually-edited advertising/tracker lists and Privacy Badger, unlike adblockers, Privacy Badger automatically learns to block trackers based on their behavior. This means that Privacy Badger may learn to block trackers your adblocker doesn’t know about.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Is Privacy Badger compatible with Firefox's built-in privacy protections?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s fine to use Firefox’s built-in content blocking (Enhanced Tracking Protection or ETP) and Privacy Badger together. While there is overlap between Firefox’s tracker lists and Privacy Badger, Privacy Badger automatically learns to block trackers based on their behavior. This means that Privacy Badger’s automatically-generated and regularly updated blocklist contains trackers not found in Firefox’s human-generated lists. Additionally, Firefox does not fully block “tracking content” in regular (non-“private”) windows by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What about Firefox’s Total Cookie Protection (dynamic First Party Isolation or dFPI)? Total Cookie Protection works by keeping third-party cookies isolated to the site they were set on. However, if unblocked, trackers can still use techniques like first-party cookie syncing and browser fingerprinting. They can track your IP address, or they can use some combination of these techniques. Trackers harvest sensitive information, and serve as vectors for malware. Not to mention, unblocked trackers slow down websites and waste your bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that Privacy Badger is not just a tracker blocker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why does my browser connect to fastly.com IP addresses on startup after installing Privacy Badger?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EFF uses Fastly to host EFF’s Web resources: Fastly is EFF’s CDN. Privacy Badger pings the CDN for the following resources to ensure that the information in them is fresh even if there hasn’t been a new Privacy Badger release in a while:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EFF does not set cookies or retain IP addresses for these queries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why does Privacy Badger need access to my data for all websites?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you install Privacy Badger, your browser warns that Privacy Badger can “access your data for all websites” (in Firefox), or “read and change all your data on the websites you visit” (in Chrome). You are right to be alarmed. You should only install extensions made by organizations you trust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy Badger requires these permissions to do its job of automatically detecting and blocking trackers on all websites you visit. We are not ironically (or unironically) spying on you. For more information, see our Privacy Badger extension permissions explainer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that the extension permissions warnings only cover what the extension has access to, not what the extension actually does with what it has access to (such as whether the extension secretly uploads your browsing data to its servers). Privacy Badger will never share data about your browsing unless you choose to share it (by filing a broken site report). For more information, see EFF’s Privacy Policy for Software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why aren't videos loading on YouTube? Why isn't Privacy Badger blocking ads on YouTube?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is YouTube not working? Try disabling Privacy Badger on YouTube. If that resolves the issue, see if re-enabling Privacy Badger breaks YouTube again. If YouTube goes back to not working, please tell us so we can look into what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are you surprised that ads aren’t being blocked on YouTube? Privacy Badger is primarily a privacy tool, not an ad blocker. When you visit YouTube directly, Privacy Badger does not block ads on YouTube because YouTube does not use “third party” trackers. If you really dislike ads, you can also install a traditional ad blocker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;I need help! I found a bug! What do I do now?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If a website isn’t working like it should, you can disable Privacy Badger just for that site, leaving Privacy Badger enabled and protecting you everywhere else. To do so, navigate to the site with the problem, click on Privacy Badger’s icon in your browser toolbar, and click the “Disable for this site” button in Privacy Badger’s popup. You can also let us know about broken sites using the “Report broken site” button.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get help or to report bugs, please email extension-devs@eff.org. If you have a GitHub account, you can use our GitHub issue tracker.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45404021</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 12:59:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>When I say "alphabetical order", I mean "alphabetical order"</title><link>https://sebastiano.tronto.net/blog/2025-09-28-alphabetic-order/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="144ce85c2ae519d5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;When I say “alphabetical order”, I mean “alphabetical order”&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last month I have been on a multi-day hike with my dad. Each of us took many pictures, and when we came back we put them all in a shared folder. We both have Android phones, and the naming scheme used for our pictures was the same: &lt;code&gt;IMG_YYYYMMDD_HHmmss&lt;/code&gt; followed maybe by some other numbers
and then a &lt;code&gt;.jpg&lt;/code&gt;. Here &lt;code&gt;YYYY&lt;/code&gt; stands for the year, &lt;code&gt;MM&lt;/code&gt; for month and
so on, so that sorting the pictures in alphabetical order is the same as
sorting them by date.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or so I thought. Strangely, when I looked at the files from my dad’s Windows PC, they were not sorted correctly: all the pictures took with my phone came first, followed by all the pictures took by him. I thought this was surely some weird Microsoft bug - after using Windows 11 at work for a while, I would not be surprised if you told me their file explorer can’t figure out how to sort strings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But then I looked at the same files in a shared Google Drive folder, and again they were in the wrong order:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you can see, the picture taken at 5:54 (with my dad’s phone) comes before the one taken at 9:20 (also with my dad’s phone), but after the one taken at 12:11 (with my phone).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Weird. Well, maybe Microsoft and Google got this wrong. But that seems unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Indeed, KDE’s Dolphin file manager does the same thing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ll spare you the screenshots, but Gnome and both the file managers that I have on my phone also get the alphabetical order wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point I thought that maybe one of the two phones is using some weird alternative unicode character instead of the underscore &lt;code&gt;_&lt;/code&gt;. Really,
I could not see any other explanation. But nope, this is not it, because
the good old &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; sorts my files correctly:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ ls -l

total 218572
-rw-r--r-- 1 seba seba 1866185 Aug 28 18:51 IMG_20250820_055436307.jpg
-rw-r--r-- 1 seba seba 4749899 Aug 28 18:50 IMG_20250820_092016029_HDR.jpg
-rw-r--r-- 1 seba seba 6201609 Aug 28 18:52 IMG_20250820_092440966_HDR.jpg
-rw-r--r-- 1 seba seba 7694802 Aug 28 18:51 IMG_20250820_092832138_HDR.jpg
-rw-r--r-- 1 seba seba 1536520 Aug 20 09:57 IMG_20250820_095716_607.jpg
-rw-r--r-- 1 seba seba 1054553 Aug 20 10:38 IMG_20250820_103857_991.jpg
-rw-r--r-- 1 seba seba  965353 Aug 20 10:39 IMG_20250820_103903_811.jpg
(and so on)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was consistent among the couple of Linux distros I use, as well as my OpenBSD server. On the one hand this is good: not every single piece of software fucks up something as basic as string sorting. On the other hand, this makes it harder to debug what the fuck is going on with all the other file managers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It took me more than a month to figure this one out. Tell me, which file do you think comes first in alphabetical order, &lt;code&gt;file-9.txt&lt;/code&gt; or
&lt;code&gt;file-10.txt&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, the user who named those files probably wants &lt;code&gt;file-9.txt&lt;/code&gt; to
come before &lt;code&gt;file-10.txt&lt;/code&gt;. But &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; is smaller than &lt;code&gt;9&lt;/code&gt;, so &lt;code&gt;file-10.txt&lt;/code&gt;
should be first in alphabetical order. Everyone understands that, and
soon people learn to put enough leading zeros if they want their files
to stay sorted the way they like.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, apparently all these operating systems have decided that no, users are too dumb and they cannot possibly understand what alphabetical order means. So when you ask them to sort your files alphabetically, they don’t. Instead, they decide that if some piece of the file name is a number, the real numerical value must be used.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don’t know when this became the norm, to be honest I have not used a normal graphical file manager in a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know you asked for the files to be sorted in alphabetical order, but you don’t want &lt;code&gt;file-10.txt&lt;/code&gt; to come before &lt;code&gt;file-9.txt&lt;/code&gt;, do
you? No, I know you don’t. I am not even going to ask you, your
mushy human brain is too small to comprehend the intricacies of
such a question. I’ll spare you the thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So it turns out that my dad’s phone wrote the milliseconds in the file name right after the seconds, while mine added an extra underscore to separate them from the seconds. Which in my mind it should not have mattered, because alphabetically they should still have been sorted correctly to the second. But with this “modern” interpretation of the alphabetical order, the files without the extra separator in the name had a much higher number, so they come last.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that I know what the issue is, I can solve it by renaming the files with a consistent scheme. I have also found a setting to fix Dolphin’s behavior, but it was very much buried into its many configuration options. And I would rather not have to change this setting in every application I use, assuming they even allow it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I miss the time when computers did what you told them to, instead of trying to read your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45404022</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 13:00:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Demon-Haunted World</title><link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Demon-Haunted_World</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2b995bdc9da599c9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Demon-Haunted World&lt;/head&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Author&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Carl Sagan&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Language&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;English&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Subjects&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Scientific skepticism&lt;p&gt;Science&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Philosophy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Publisher&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Random House&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;&lt;p&gt;Publication date&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;1995/1997&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Publication place&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;United States&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Media type&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Print (hardcover and paperback)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Pages&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;457&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;ISBN&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;0-345-40946-9&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;OCLC&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;32855551&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;001.9 20&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;LC Class&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Q175 .S215 1995&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Preceded by&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Pale Blue Dot&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Followed by&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Billions and Billions&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Demon-Haunted World: Science as a Candle in the Dark is a 1995 book by the astronomer and science communicator Carl Sagan. (Four of the 25 chapters were written with Ann Druyan.[1]: x ) In it, Sagan aims to explain the scientific method to laypeople and to encourage people to learn critical and skeptical thinking. He explains methods to help distinguish between ideas that are considered valid science and those that can be considered pseudoscience. Sagan states that when new ideas are offered for consideration, they should be tested by means of skeptical thinking and should stand up to rigorous questioning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Themes&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;Sagan explains that science is not just a body of knowledge, but is a way of thinking. Sagan shows how scientific thinking is both imaginative and disciplined, bringing humans to an understanding of how the universe is, rather than how they wish to perceive it. He says that science works much better than any other system because it has a "built-in error-correcting machine".[2]: 27 Superstition and pseudoscience get in the way of the ability of many laypersons to appreciate the beauty and benefits of science. Skeptical thinking allows people to construct, understand, reason, and recognize valid and invalid arguments. Wherever possible, there must be independent validation of the concepts whose truth should be proved. He states that reason and logic would succeed once the truth was known. Conclusions emerge from premises, and the acceptability of the premises should not be discounted or accepted because of bias.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Dragon in my garage&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;As an example of skeptical thinking, Sagan offers a story concerning a fire-breathing dragon who lives in his garage. When he persuades a rational, open-minded visitor to meet the dragon, the visitor remarks that they are unable to see the creature. Sagan replies that he "neglected to mention that she's an invisible dragon". The visitor suggests spreading flour on the floor so that the creature's footprints might be seen, which Sagan says is a good idea, "but this dragon floats in the air". When the visitor considers using an infrared camera to view the creature's invisible fire, Sagan explains that her fire is heatless. He continues to counter every proposed physical test with a reason why the test will not work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sagan concludes by asking: "Now what's the difference between an invisible, incorporeal, floating dragon who spits heatless fire and no dragon at all? If there's no way to disprove my contention, no conceivable experiment that would count against it, what does it mean to say that my dragon exists? Your inability to invalidate my hypothesis is not at all the same thing as proving it true."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Continuing with concepts relevant to the 'dragon in my garage' story, Sagan writes about a patient of John Mack who claimed to have scars on her body which were from encounters with aliens. Sagan writes that if the patient is asked what her scars look like, she is unable to show them because, unfortunately, they are located in the private areas of her body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Baloney detection kit&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;Sagan presents a set of tools for skeptical thinking that he calls the "baloney detection kit".[3][4]: 210 [5] Skeptical thinking consists both of constructing a reasoned argument and recognizing a fallacious or fraudulent one. In order to identify a fallacious argument, Sagan suggests employing such tools as independent confirmation of facts, debate, development of different hypotheses, quantification, the use of Occam's razor, and the possibility of falsification. Sagan's "baloney detection kit" also provides tools for detecting "the most common fallacies of logic and rhetoric", such as argument from authority and statistics of small numbers. Through these tools, Sagan argues the benefits of a critical mind and the self-correcting nature of science can take place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sagan provides nine tools as the first part of this kit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;There must be independent confirmation of the facts given when possible.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Encourage debate on the evidence from all points of view.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Realize that an argument from authority is not always reliable. Sagan supports this by telling us that "authorities" have made mistakes in the past and they will again in the future.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Consider more than one hypothesis. Sagan adds to this by telling us that we must think of the argument from all angles and think all the ways it can be explained or disproved. The hypothesis that then still hasn't been disproved has a much higher chance of being correct.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Try to avoid clinging obdurately to your own hypothesis and so become biased. Sagan tells us to compare our own hypothesis with others to see if we can find reasons to reject our own hypothesis.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Quantify. Sagan tells us that if whatever we are trying to explain has numerical value or quantitative data related to it, then we'll be much more able to compete against other hypotheses.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;If there is a chain of argument, every link in that chain must be correct.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The use of Occam's razor, which says to choose the hypothesis that is simpler and requires the fewest assumptions.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Ask if a given hypothesis can be falsified. Sagan tells us that if a hypothesis cannot be tested or falsified then it is not worth considering.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sagan suggests that with the use of this "baloney detection kit" it is easier to critically think and find the truth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Logical fallacies&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;There is a second part to the kit. This consists of twenty logical fallacies that one must not commit when offering up a new claim.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Ad hominem. An arguer attacks the opposing arguer and not the actual argument.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Argument from authority. Someone expects another to immediately believe that a person of authority or higher knowledge is correct.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Argument from adverse consequences. Someone says that something must be done a certain way or else there will be adverse consequences.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Appeal to ignorance. One argues a claim in that whatever has not been proved false must be true, and vice versa.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Special pleading. An arguer responds to a deeply complex or rhetorical question or statement by, usually, saying "oh you don't understand how so and so works."&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Begging the question. An arguer assumes the answer and makes a claim such as, this happened because of that, or, this needs to happen in order for that to happen.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Observational selection. Someone talks about how great something is by explaining all of the positive aspects of it while purposely not mentioning any of the negative aspects.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Statistics of small numbers. Someone argues something by giving the statistics in small numbers, which isn't very reliable.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Misunderstanding of the nature of statistics. Someone misinterprets statistics given to them.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Fallacy of inconsistency. An arguer is very inconsistent in their claims.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Non sequitur. This is Latin for "it doesn't follow". A claim is made that doesn't make much sense, such as "Our nation will prevail because God is great."&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Post hoc ergo propter hoc. Latin for "it happened after, so it was caused by". An arguer claims that something happened because of a past event when really it probably didn't.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Meaningless question. Someone asks a question that has no real meaning or doesn't add to the argument at all.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The excluded middle. An arguer only considers or mentions the two opposite extremes of the conversation and excludes the aspects in between the two extremes.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Short-term vs. long-term. A subset of the excluded middle, but so important it was pulled out for special attention.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Slippery slope, related to excluded middle (e.g., If we allow abortion in the first weeks of pregnancy, it will be impossible to prevent the killing of a full-term infant. Or, conversely: If the state prohibits…).&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Confusion of correlation and causation. The latter causes the former.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Straw man. Caricaturing a position to make it easier to attack. This is also a short-term/long-term fallacy.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Suppressed evidence, or half-truth.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Weasel word. Talleyrand said: "An important art of politicians is to find new names for institutions which under old names have become odious to the public."&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sagan provides a skeptical analysis of several examples of what he refers to as superstition, fraud, and pseudoscience such as witches, UFOs, ESP, and faith healing. He is critical of organized religion.[citation needed]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a 2020 interview for Skeptical Inquirer, when Sagan's wife Ann Druyan was asked about the origin of the phrase "baloney detection kit", she said that&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It didn't really come from Carl. It actually came from a friend of mine named Arthur Felberbaum who died about forty years ago. He and Carl and I once sat down for dinner together. His politics were very left wing, so Carl and Arthur and I were trying to find common ground so that we could have a really good dinner together. And at one point, Arthur said, "Carl, it's just that I dream that every one of us would have a baloney detection kit in our head." And that's where that idea came from.[3]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Misuse of science&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;Sagan indicates that science can be misused. Thus, he is highly critical of Edward Teller, the "father of the hydrogen bomb", and Teller's influence on politics, and contrasts his stance to that of Linus Pauling and other scientists who took moral positions.[citation needed]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sagan also discusses the misuse of science in representation. He relates to the depiction of the mad scientist character in children's TV shows and is critical of this occurrence. Sagan suggests an addition of scientific television programs, many of which would take a look at believed hoaxes of the past and encourage viewers to engage in critical thinking to better represent science on popular television.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Misuse of psychiatric authority&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;Sagan indicates that therapists can contribute to the growth of pseudoscience or the infusion of "false stories". He is critical of John Mack and his support of abduction cases, which were represented in his patients.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sagan writes about the story of Paul Ingram. Ingram's daughter reported that her father had sexually abused her. He was told that "sex offenders often repressed memories of their crimes."[6] Ingram was eventually able to have a foggy visualization of the claimed events, and he suggested that perhaps "a demon might be responsible."[6] Sagan describes how once Ingram started remembering events, so did several other individuals and family members. A "memory recovery" technique was performed on Ingram, and he confessed to the crimes. A medical examination was done on his daughter, where none of the scars she described were actually found. Sagan writes that Ingram later tried to plead innocence once "away from his daughters, his police colleagues, and his pastor."[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Hoaxes&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;Hoaxes have played a valuable role in the history of science by revealing the flaws in our thinking and helping us advance our critical thinking skills. One of Sagan's examples is the "Carlos hoax" by James Randi that revealed flaws in reporting by news media. Carlos was described as an ancient spirit that supposedly possessed José Alvarez and provided Alvarez with advanced knowledge about the universe. Many news outlets assumed this was true and reported it as such, which spread misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sagan also cites crop circles as hoaxes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Reception and legacy&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;The book was a New York Times bestseller.[7] The contemporary skeptical movement considers it an important book.[8][9][10][11] The Demon-Haunted World has been criticized (in Smithsonian magazine and The New York Times) for not incorporating certain information relevant to the items he discusses in his book. The Smithsonian article by Paul Trachtman argues that Sagan relates issues of government choices and declining scientific thinking skills to pseudoscience topics like astrology and faith healing but ignores other issues that may be causing governmental bodies and other individuals to turn away from science. One such issue is consequences of pouring governmental money into cancer research. Trachtman writes, "it is not because of such beliefs that Congress now approaches the NIH budget with an ax. In fact, billions of dollars spent on years of research in the war on cancer have spawned growing professional bureaucracies and diminishing medical benefits." Trachtman argues that Sagan does not include problems like growing bureaucracies and diminishing medical benefits as reasons for a lack of scientific attention.[12] In his review for The New York Times, James Gorman also argues for an unaddressed issue in Sagan's book, saying Sagan fails to emphasize the idea that scientists should take a more active role in teaching science to the public, while he does mention the failures of the education system to do so.[13]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review in the Smithsonian magazine and a review by academic biologist Richard Lewontin in the New York Review of Books provide a range of opinions on Sagan's attitude towards religious ideas. Per the New York Review article, "when it comes to the Supreme Extraterrestrial he is rather circumspect."[14] The Smithsonian article suggests Sagan was very clear about his religious beliefs in the book, for he "splits his universe in two, into science and irrationality." The Smithsonian goes on to say that Sagan's defined religious views fall within the area of an untestable claim, a type of claim he argues against in The Demon-Haunted World.[12]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lewontin's review also claims that Sagan includes something in The Demon-Haunted World which he also is arguing against in that same text. The article mentions how Sagan discusses a natural predisposition people have towards science; but, the article says, "He does not tell us how he used the scientific method to discover the "embedded" human proclivity for science."[14] Sagan heavily discusses the importance of using the scientific method in his book, and this article claims he strays away from his own message by not including a description of his use of the scientific method on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A review by Lee Dembart in the Los Angeles Times was positive. It described Sagan's book as "a manifesto for clear thought", with the main issue being the length of eight chapters.[15] Gorman's review in The New York Times also criticised the length of the book.[16]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The book has received a number of retrospective reviews. An article in The Guardian, 2012, described the book as somewhat dated, though still insightful.[17] Another article from The Verge in 2017 noted that a quote from the book regarding Sagan's pessimistic prediction for a future America had gone viral on Twitter, which the article described as "chillingly prescient". The article praised the book, stating that Sagan "practiced the scientific skepticism and thinking that he preached, and that's what helped him accurately analyze the trends of his time and forecast their eventual outcomes in ours.".[18]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;See also&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Extraordinary Popular Delusions and the Madness of Crowds – 1841 book by Charles Mackay&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Junk science – Scientific data considered to be spurious or fraudulent&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Pathological science – Area of research which persists despite being widely discredited&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Rationalism – Epistemological view centered on reason&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p/&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;References&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Sagan, Carl (1997). The Demon-Haunted World: Science As a Candle in the Dark (Reprint ed.). Ballantine Books. ISBN 978-0345409461.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Sagan, Carl (1997). The Demon-Haunted World: Science As a Candle in the Dark (Reprint ed.). Ballantine Books. ISBN 978-0345409461.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b Palmer, Rob (March 31, 2020). "Exploring 'Possible Worlds' With Ann Druyan". Skepticalinquirer.org. CFI. Archived from the original on April 1, 2020. Retrieved April 17, 2020.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Sagan, Carl (March 1997). The Demon-Haunted World: Science As a Candle in the Dark (Paperback ed.). Ballantine Books. ISBN 978-0-345-40946-1.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Sagan, Carl (1995). The Demon-Haunted World: Science As a Candle in the Dark (Hardback ed.). Random House. ISBN 978-0-394-53512-8.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b c Carl Sagan,(1997). The Demon-Haunted World: Science As a Candle in the Dark (Reprint ed.). Ballantine Books. ISBN 978-0345409461.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ "Best Sellers". The New York Times. June 16, 1996. Retrieved February 17, 2017.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Bernstein, Evan (November 9, 2015). "Happy Carl Sagan Day!". The Skeptics' Guide to the Universe. Retrieved February 17, 2017.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Novella, Steven (November 9, 2009). "NeuroLogica Blog » Carl Sagan Day". New England Skeptical Society. Retrieved February 17, 2017.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Meadon, Michael (October 8, 2009). "Books IV". ionian-enchantment.blogspot.com. Retrieved February 17, 2017.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Swiss, Jamy Ian (May 9, 2013). "I, Skeptic". Northeast Conference on Science and Skepticism. Retrieved February 17, 2017 – via YouTube.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b Trachtman, Paul (May 1997). "Review of 'The Demon-Haunted World', 'Einstein, History, and Other Passions', 'The End of Science'". Smithsonian. Archived from the original on September 27, 2009.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Gorman, James (April 7, 1996). "Invasion of the Body Snatchers: Review of The Demon-Haunted World Science as a Candle in the Dark by Carl Sagan". The New York Times. Retrieved August 29, 2024.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b Lewontin, Richard C. "Billions and Billions of Demons." The New York Review of Books, January 9, 1997, www.nybooks.com/articles/1997/01/09/billions-and-billions-of-demons/?lp_txn_id=997302.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Dembart, Lee "Book Review / Non Fiction : For This Scientist, the Truth Is Out There: The Demon-Haunted World: Science as a Candle in the Dark by Carl Sagan; Random House $25, 452 Pages." Los Angeles Times, 18 Apr. 1996, www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1996-04-18-ls-60022-story.html.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Gorman, James (April 7, 1996). "Invasion of the Body Snatchers: Review of The Demon-Haunted World Science as a Candle in the Dark by Carl Sagan". The New York Times. Retrieved August 29, 2024.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Radford, Tim (July 20, 2012). "The Demon-Haunted World by Carl Sagan – review". The Guardian. ISSN 0261-3077. Retrieved August 29, 2024.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Savov, Vlad (January 24, 2017). "The world needs Carl Sagan now more than ever". The Verge. Retrieved August 29, 2024.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Further reading&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Ayala, F. J. Ayala (July 26, 1996). "The Demon-Haunted World, reviewed". Science. Vol. 273, no. 5274. pp. 442–444. Bibcode:1996Sci...273..442S. doi:10.1126/science.273.5274.442.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Dembart, Lee (April 18, 1996). "Book Review / Non Fiction : For This Scientist, the Truth Is Out There : The Demon-Haunted World: Science as a Candle in the Dark by Carl Sagan". Los Angeles Times.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Gorman, James (April 7, 1996). "Invasion of the Body Snatchers". The New York Times.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Schult, Jeff (April 1996). "The Case for Science (Carl Sagan: The Demon-Haunted World – Science as a Candle in the Dark)". American Reporter.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45404373</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 14:00:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Plan 9 from User Space</title><link>https://github.com/9fans/plan9port</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a605bc5c90f1b0c2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a port of many Plan 9 libraries and programs to Unix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To install, run ./INSTALL. It builds mk and then uses mk to run the rest of the installation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more details, see install(1), at install.txt in this directory and at https://9fans.github.io/plan9port/man/man1/install.html.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See https://9fans.github.io/plan9port/man/ for more documentation. (Documentation is also in this tree, but you need to run a successful install first. After that, "9 man 1 intro".)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intro(1) contains a list of man pages that describe new features or differences from Plan 9.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you'd like to help out, great!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you port this code to other architectures, please share your changes so others can benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can use Git to keep your local copy up-to-date as we make changes and fix bugs. See the git(1) man page here ("9 man git") for details on using Git.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Mailing list: https://groups.google.com/group/plan9port-dev&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Issue tracker: https://github.com/9fans/plan9port/issues&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Submitting changes: https://github.com/9fans/plan9port/pulls&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Russ Cox rsc@swtch.com&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45404573</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 14:27:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Toolbrew – Free little tools without signups or ads</title><link>https://toolbrew.co/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45404667</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 14:40:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple threatens to stop selling iPhones in the EU</title><link>https://pluralistic.net/2025/09/26/empty-threats/#500-million-affluent-consumers</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b54d1919092e9454"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Today's links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apple threatens to stop selling iPhones in the EU: Yeah, right.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hey look at this: Delights to delectate.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Object permanence: Thomas Ligotti's anhedonic philosophy; Catalan elections; Molly Crabapple's Syria.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Upcoming appearances: Where to find me.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Recent appearances: Where I've been.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Latest books: You keep readin' em, I'll keep writin' 'em.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Upcoming books: Like I said, I'll keep writin' 'em.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Colophon: All the rest.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Apple threatens to stop selling iPhones in the EU (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple has threatened to stop selling iPhones and other devices in the European Union (home to over 500,000,000 affluent consumers) if the bloc doesn't rescind the Digital Markets Act, a democratically accountable anti-monopoly law that bans Apple from blocking third parties from offering services to iPhone owners:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple has a staunch ally in this campaign to overturn European laws: Donald Trump has threatened the EU with tariffs unless it halts its attempts to regulate US tech giants like Apple, whose billionaire CEO Tim Cook gave Donald Trump $1m in exchange for a seat on the dais at Trump's inauguration and then traveled to DC again to hand-assemble a gilded participation trophy as a gift to America's fascist would-be dictator:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2025/08/07/tim-cook-trump-gift/85555805007/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a painfully stupid threat and the EU should call Apple's bluff. The company claims that it is acting in the interest of European owners of Apple products. Apple claims that by blocking Europeans from using their Apple devices with third-party software and hardware, they are protecting their customers' privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is nonsense. While it's true that Apple protects its customers' privacy from some external threats, Apple also spies on its users, without their consent, in order to gather behavioral data that's used for Apple's ad-targeting system. When this came to light, Apple lied to its customers about it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://pluralistic.net/2022/11/14/luxury-surveillance/#liar-liar&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple has used its exclusive control over which software can operate on its devices to expose every Chinese iOS user to unrestricted government surveillance. Apple removed all working VPNs from its Chinese app store:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.cnet.com/news/apple-removes-vpn-apps-from-china-app-store/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company then backdoored its iCloud backup for unrestricted access by Chinese authorities:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/05/17/technology/apple-china-censorship-data.html&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then they removed the ability to anonymously share messages via Airdrop to curb the tool's usage to spread opposition messages during a wave of mass protests in China (they took away this functionality for every Airdrop user in the world):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The idea that Apple is so committed to its users' privacy that it will exit a major market rather than expose users to surveillance risks is an obvious lie – just ask China.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why would Apple tell this lie? Because it wants to protect its profits – not its customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple lies when it claims that control over its platforms is primarily about protecting users. The App Store is "teeming with scams":&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, by forcing Apple customers to get apps from Apple's own store, the company can skim a 30% commission on every dollar its customers send to an app maker, a Patreon performer, a news outlet or any other app supplier – a business that's worth $100b/year to Apple. Remember, in the EU, the cost of processing a payment is between 0% and 1%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple claims that it protects its customers from privacy risks by blocking third-party repair depots and by requiring its customers to pay through the nose for official repair. But Apple's own repair technicians have been caught plundering and sharing nude images of its own customers, stolen from phones that were sent to Apple:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This has happened repeatedly:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All over the world:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://9to5mac.com/2016/10/12/apple-australia-photo-sharing-ring-nsfw/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(And of course, these are just the instances that we know about).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple protects its customers from privacy threats, but not from Apple's own predatory, privacy-invasive, rent-extracting conduct. Apple also gets to unilaterally decide which scams are permitted on its platform and which ones are not, and they alone get to decide when to allow secret, pervasive surveillance of Apple customers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple's threats are lies, but the privacy risks of interop are very real. It's entirely possible to plug something into a secure tool that renders it insecure. It's nice when companies test third party add-ons and warn their customers about defective or risky aftermarket mods, and to the extent that Apple does this, it's doing good work. But Apple has an irreconcilable conflict of interest when it comes to vetoing its customers' decisions about which non-Apple products they use. Apple has some genuinely stonking margins on its payment processing, repair, and other lines of business, and Apple's CEO has openly boasted about using deliberately engineered incompatibilities to drive people to switch to Apple products:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.businessinsider.com/tim-cook-buy-your-mom-iphone-doj-apple-complaint-2024-3&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How do we get Apple to protect its customers' privacy without picking their pockets or invading their privacy? By removing the company's veto over who can make software and hardware that works with Apple's competing offerings. The ultimate decision about which products are too dangerous for Europeans to use can't be vested with Apple – instead, it should be vested with expert agencies working for democratically accountable governments. This is the point that Bennett Ciphers and I made at length in our EFF white-paper "Privacy Without Monopoly," which has a whole section explaining how the EU's big, muscular privacy law, the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), makes this an especially attractive proposition in the EU:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.eff.org/document/privacy-without-monopoly-data-protection-and-interoperability&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's also a point that EFF board member and infosec legend Bruce Schneier made in his open letter to the Senate Judiciary Committee, discussing opening up app stores:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.eff.org/document/letter-bruce-schneier-senate-judiciary-regarding-app-store-security&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple isn't going to exit a market with half a billion affluent consumers. If it does, expect its shareholders to wreak swift and terrible vengeance on the company. You know how people are always complaining that investors are only interested in short-term returns? It's true and here's a place where that cuts in our favor: shareholders aren't going to accept a half-billion-person market exit tomorrow in anticipation of forcing the EU to capitulate next year and thereafter safeguard Apple's continental scale rent-extraction racket. They want returns to their capital tomorrow, not in some hypothetical future in which Tim Cook tears out Henna Virkkunen's still-beating heart with his bare hands and parades it through Strasbourg, brandishing it at legions of trembling, vanquished eurocrats.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But let's say Apple does exit the EU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EU needs to get the hell off US tech infrastructure. Under Trump, Big Tech and the US government have stopped even pretending that American tech companies are independent of the US government. We know (from China) that Apple will happily backdoor its cloud servers to assuage authoritarian governments like Xi Xinping's. You know, Xi Xinping, the guy that Trump says he wants to emulate?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://www.politico.com/news/2023/12/18/trump-praise-authoritarians-00132350&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;US Big Tech companies keep demonstrating that they are de facto arms of the US and constitute a hostile foreign power operating on European soil. When the International Criminal Court indicted Israeli génocidaires, Trump issued an executive order sanctioning the body. Immediately thereafter, Microsoft deleted the email and cloud accounts of ICC prosecutor Karim Khan – named in the Trump EO – and then Microsoft President Brad Smith perjured himself in his denial:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft publicly admitted that it can't stop US authorities from conducting secret surveillance of EU citizens' (and EU governments') data, even when that data is stored on a server in the EU:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EU's response is something called "Eurostack" – a top-to-bottom "stack" of technologies from data-centers to operating systems and applications made and maintained by EU entities (for-profits, nonprofits, and public bodies):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://pluralistic.net/2025/06/25/eurostack/#viktor-orbans-isp&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nearly all of the emphasis on Eurostack has been on building the data-centers and creating these applications, but in some ways, this is the least important part of the project. Cloning GDocs or Office365 or iWork is the easy part. The hard part is migrating from US-controlled platforms to their Eurostack equivalents. If leaving Office365 means leaving all the documents your company, organization or government agency has ever created, or losing all the sharing and collaboration permissions, or losing all the edit-histories, well, no one is gonna migrate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thankfully, this is something technology can easily fix: all you need to do is reverse-engineer the US offering and create a tool that extracts and transforms the data to the new format, and moves a copy of it into the new Eurostack services. This is called "adversarial interoperability" and is eminently do-able, as Apple proved when they broke open Microsoft Office by creating the iWork suite (Pages, Numbers and Keynote):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The major impediment to this kind of seamless bulk migration tool isn't the technological challenge – it's the law. In 2001, the EU – under pressure from the USA – included an "anticircumvention" rule in the EU Copyright Directive (EUCD). Article 6 of the EUCD mirrors the language of Section 1201 of America's Digital Millennium Copyright Act, banning reverse-engineering and adversarial interoperability, even where no copyright infringement takes place. That means that a European company that made an account migration tool to help European companies or government agencies move their own data out of a US Big Tech silo could face liability under Article 6 of the EUCD, with severe criminal and civil penalties. EUCD 6 gives American tech giants more rights to Europeans' copyrighted works than the Europeans who created those works. It's a terrible law, and after a quarter century, it's long past its expiry date.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bringing this full circle: Article 6 of the EUCD is also the law that stops European companies from reverse-engineering the iPhone and creating their own app stores, without having to rely on Apple's help. Given that Apple has flagrantly violated laws that order it to open its app store, it's time to unleash Europe's accomplished legion of top technologists on the problem:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://pluralistic.net/2024/02/06/spoil-the-bunch/#dma&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doing that becomes even easier if Apple exits the EU and abandons EU customers, cutting off their supply of security patches and application updates. After all, Europeans own their Apple devices. It's up to them – not Apple – whether they want to trust their fellow Europeans to protect their security and add new functionality of their own property.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EU doesn't need to be a technology-taker – it can be a technology maker. The Apple/Google duopoly may have sewn up the mobile market with illegal monopoly tactics, but that doesn't mean that the EU will never spawn another Nokia or Ericsson. The shortest, most efficient, most reliable path to reestablishing technological sovereignty for the EU's half-billion residents and 27 member-states is to allow domestic firms to take over the relationship between the Trump-controlled American tech giants and the Europeans who rely on their technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If Trump can seize Chinese companies like Tiktok and sell them to his major donors at a 90% discount, then American companies have no right to cry foul when the EU gets rid of the America First Copyright Directive and lets Europeans choose to get their software, updates, and hardware from European companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Image: Alex Popovkin, Bahia, Brazil from Brazil, CC BY 2.0; Hubertl, CC BY-SA 4.0; modified)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Hey look at this (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They Pump So Much Stuff Into Those Beautiful Little Babies https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/they-pump-so-much-stuff-into-those-beautiful-little-babies&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The climate solution both the right and the left can get behind https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/ng-interactive/2025/sep/07/solar-power-rightwing-trump&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Anti-Religious Politics https://www.hamiltonnolan.com/p/anti-religious-politics&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;She Fought the Far Right Online for Years. Now She Wants to Do It in Congress https://www.wired.com/story/kat-abughazaleh-youtuber-for-congress/&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Day Two: Can the Open Web Be Restored? And an Annoyed Judge Tries to Move Things Along. https://www.bigtechontrial.com/p/day-two-can-the-open-web-be-restored&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Object permanence (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#20yrsago MPAA/RIAA subvert democracy with super-broadcast-flag bid https://web.archive.org/web/20050926233646/http://www.eff.org/deeplinks/archives/004000.php&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#20yrsago Islam in science fiction https://web.archive.org/web/20051002030829/https://www.cs.rit.edu/~maa2454/SCIFI/sci_lit.html&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#15yrsago Philosophy of Thomas Ligotti, a horror writer who can’t feel happiness https://web.archive.org/web/20061119163754/https://theteemingbrain.wordpress.com/interview-with-thomas-ligotti/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Hilo: The Boy Who Crashed to Earth, a fantastic middle-grade adventure comic https://memex.craphound.com/2015/09/26/hilo-the-boy-who-crashed-to-earth-a-fantastic-middle-grade-adventure-comic/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Molly Crabapple’s illustrations from Syria https://www.vanityfair.com/news/2015/07/inside-aleppo-syria&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago 1 in 40 London cops have been arrested in the past five years https://www.ibtimes.co.uk/1600-uk-police-officers-arrested-criminal-offences-5-years-1519573&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Tomorrow’s Catalan elections are a referendum on independence https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/sep/25/catalonia-votes-democracy-election-independence-spain&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#10yrsago Dustin Yellin’s stupendous, life-sized glass-pane humanoids made from NatGeo clippings https://memex.craphound.com/2015/09/26/dustin-yellins-stupendous-life-sized-glass-pane-humanoids-made-from-natgeo-clippings/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;#1yrago When prophecy fails, election polling edition https://pluralistic.net/2024/09/26/dewey-beats-truman/#past-performance-is-no-guarantee-of-future-results&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Upcoming appearances (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Boston: Enshittification with Randall Munroe (Brattle Theater), Oct 7&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/cory-doctorow-at-the-brattle-theatre-tickets-1591235180259?aff=oddtdtcreator&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;DC: Enshittification with Rohit Chopra (Politics and Prose), Oct 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://politics-prose.com/cory-doctorow-10825&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;NYC: Enshittification with Lina Khan (Brooklyn Public Library), Oct 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.bklynlibrary.org/calendar/cory-doctorow-discusses-central-library-dweck-20251009-0700pm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;New Orleans: DeepSouthCon63, Oct 10-12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;http://www.contraflowscifi.org/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;New Orleans: Enshittification at Octavia Books, Oct 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.octaviabooks.com/event/enshittification-cory-doctorow&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chicago: Enshittification with Anand Giridharadas (Chicago Humanities), Oct 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.oldtownschool.org/concerts/2025/10-15-2025-kara-swisher-and-cory-doctorow-on-enshittification/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Los Angeles: Enshittification with David Dayen (Diesel), Oct 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://dieselbookstore.com/event/2025-10-16/cory-doctorow-enshittification&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;San Francisco: Enshittification at Public Works with Jenny Odell (The Booksmith), Oct 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://app.gopassage.com/events/doctorow25&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;PDX: Enshittification at Powell's, Oct 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.powells.com/events/cory-doctorow-10-21-25&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seattle: Enshittification and the Rot Economy, with Ed Zitron (Clarion West), Oct 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.clarionwest.org/event/2025-deep-dives-cory-doctorow/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Madrid: Conferencia EUROPEA 4D (Virtual), Oct 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://4d.cat/es/conferencia/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Miami: Enshittification at Books &amp;amp; Books, Nov 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/an-evening-with-cory-doctorow-tickets-1504647263469&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Miami: Cloudfest, Nov 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.cloudfest.com/usa/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burbank: Burbank Book Festival, Nov 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.burbankbookfestival.com/&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recent appearances (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enshittification (Cornell)&lt;lb/&gt;https://ecornell.cornell.edu/keynotes/view/K091225/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Escaping Big Tech, Privacy Battles &amp;amp; “Enshittification” (Revolution.social)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=exvpetQRSVo&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nerd Harder! (This Week in Tech)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://twit.tv/shows/this-week-in-tech/episodes/1047&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Latest books (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Picks and Shovels": a sequel to "Red Team Blues," about the heroic era of the PC, Tor Books (US), Head of Zeus (UK), February 2025 (https://us.macmillan.com/books/9781250865908/picksandshovels).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Bezzle": a sequel to "Red Team Blues," about prison-tech and other grifts, Tor Books (US), Head of Zeus (UK), February 2024 (the-bezzle.org).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Lost Cause:" a solarpunk novel of hope in the climate emergency, Tor Books (US), Head of Zeus (UK), November 2023 (http://lost-cause.org).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Internet Con": A nonfiction book about interoperability and Big Tech (Verso) September 2023 (http://seizethemeansofcomputation.org). Signed copies at Book Soup (https://www.booksoup.com/book/9781804291245).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"Red Team Blues": "A grabby, compulsive thriller that will leave you knowing more about how the world works than you did before." Tor Books http://redteamblues.com.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"Chokepoint Capitalism: How to Beat Big Tech, Tame Big Content, and Get Artists Paid, with Rebecca Giblin", on how to unrig the markets for creative labor, Beacon Press/Scribe 2022 https://chokepointcapitalism.com&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Upcoming books (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Canny Valley": A limited edition collection of the collages I create for Pluralistic, self-published, September 2025&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Enshittification: Why Everything Suddenly Got Worse and What to Do About It," Farrar, Straus, Giroux, October 7 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;https://us.macmillan.com/books/9780374619329/enshittification/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"Unauthorized Bread": a middle-grades graphic novel adapted from my novella about refugees, toasters and DRM, FirstSecond, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"Enshittification, Why Everything Suddenly Got Worse and What to Do About It" (the graphic novel), Firstsecond, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Memex Method," Farrar, Straus, Giroux, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"The Reverse-Centaur's Guide to AI," a short book about being a better AI critic, Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Colophon (permalink)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today's top sources:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently writing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"The Reverse Centaur's Guide to AI," a short book for Farrar, Straus and Giroux about being an effective AI critic. FIRST DRAFT COMPLETE AND SUBMITTED.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A Little Brother short story about DIY insulin PLANNING&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This work – excluding any serialized fiction – is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license. That means you can use it any way you like, including commercially, provided that you attribute it to me, Cory Doctorow, and include a link to pluralistic.net.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quotations and images are not included in this license; they are included either under a limitation or exception to copyright, or on the basis of a separate license. Please exercise caution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How to get Pluralistic:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blog (no ads, tracking, or data-collection):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Newsletter (no ads, tracking, or data-collection):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://pluralistic.net/plura-list&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mastodon (no ads, tracking, or data-collection):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Medium (no ads, paywalled):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Twitter (mass-scale, unrestricted, third-party surveillance and advertising):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tumblr (mass-scale, unrestricted, third-party surveillance and advertising):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://mostlysignssomeportents.tumblr.com/tagged/pluralistic&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"When life gives you SARS, you make sarsaparilla" -Joey "Accordion Guy" DeVilla&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;READ CAREFULLY: By reading this, you agree, on behalf of your employer, to release me from all obligations and waivers arising from any and all NON-NEGOTIATED agreements, licenses, terms-of-service, shrinkwrap, clickwrap, browsewrap, confidentiality, non-disclosure, non-compete and acceptable use policies ("BOGUS AGREEMENTS") that I have entered into with your employer, its partners, licensors, agents and assigns, in perpetuity, without prejudice to my ongoing rights and privileges. You further represent that you have the authority to release me from any BOGUS AGREEMENTS on behalf of your employer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ISSN: 3066-764X&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45404783</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 14:55:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How did we all miss the bacteria taking over her body?</title><link>https://www.theguardian.com/world/2025/sep/28/as-my-daughter-got-sicker-and-sicker-our-quest-for-answers-dragged-on-how-did-we-all-miss-the-bacteria-taking-over-her-body</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ad9891132be605d3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are many reasons to feel guilty. I’m a nature writer who preaches about the importance of wild childhoods, and my daughter has been made chronically ill by one trip to the countryside. I’m a journalist whose job it is to interrogate information and yet I didn’t demand better answers for her from NHS doctors. But the guilt is most painful when I remember a freezing wet day in October 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Milly’s U10s football club were playing the league’s top team. Milly, player of the year the previous season, a whirl of blond energy across the pitch, had lost her enthusiasm for the beautiful game. That morning, she really didn’t want to play: she was tearful and exhausted. There was nothing obviously wrong: no cough, sickness, temperature. Her twin, Esme, was playing but without Milly the team were a player short. I told Milly they needed her. Stoic, she staggered off but couldn’t step on to the pitch. Instead, she curled into a ball of misery and fatigue beside her coach. The rain fell. Her team lost 15-1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I cringe when I flick through the notebook where I recorded my daughters’ football matches (I was tragically keen). Below most results from the 21/22 season, I’ve written “Milly ill” or, worse, “Milly played ¼” or “Milly played ½”. All the time, cajoled or compelled to lead her “normal” life, Milly was getting sicker and sicker. We had no idea what was wrong. Every morning she looked terrible, dark circles beneath her eyes. She complained of perpetual tiredness, talked of being “disconcentrated” – she later learned to call this “brain fog” – and mentioned strange stabbing pains, mostly in her feet when she walked. Soon, she was too ill to go to school. Lockdown was over but it had become a permanent state for Milly, my wife, Lisa, and me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What we didn’t know then, and wouldn’t discover until this spring, was that Milly’s body was being invaded by an insidious bacterium, Borrelia burgdorferi, which hides in connective tissue, confounding immune systems, wreaking havoc. Milly had Lyme disease, which takes its name from Old Lyme, a coastal town in Connecticut. This bacterial infection is not contagious but is transmitted by a tick, a tiny, blood-sucking insect that hops on to human skin in the countryside, where it is transported by other mammals, particularly deer. There are 476,000, and rising, annual cases in North America alone. Global heating is making ticks, their bacteria – and human illnesses – much more prevalent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In North America, where there’s even a tick species carrying another bacteria that triggers a bizarre allergy to meat, awareness is rising. Numerous American and Canadian celebrities have spoken out about their years-long struggle with Lyme, from Bella Hadid and Avril Lavigne to Justins Bieber and Timberlake. But for many years it has been a disease mired in controversy, particularly when it comes to the idea of a long-term, treatment-resistant form of the disease. Most established medical thinking questions the existence of so-called “chronic Lyme disease”. The numbers of people diagnosed with Lyme disease tell their own story. The UK Health Security Agency logged 1,581 confirmed cases of Lyme in 2024. But according to Jack Lambert, consultant in infectious diseases at the Mater hospital in Ireland, France records 70,000 cases a year. “In both the UK and France, 5-10% of ticks are found to carry borrelia. So ticks only like to bite French people?” Lambert says. “Or maybe the UK is under-reporting. Ticks are all over the place. We have all these people with mystery illnesses – summer flu, migratory arthritis, funny neurological problems. And for GPs, neurologists, rheumatologists and infectious disease experts asking why, Lyme disease is at the bottom of the list.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How did we and everyone else miss the bacteria silently taking over Milly’s body? Back in 2021, Lisa took her to the GP. It was a relief when blood tests ruled out various life-threatening possibilities – it wasn’t cancer, thank goodness. On account of the stabbing pains, we had an appointment with a neurologist, who was unhelpful and never considered Lyme. Our requests for a second opinion from a general paediatrician were rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nine-year-old Milly was not only a footballer; she also adored dance and swimming, and loved school. We still joke she is one of those annoying people who excels at whatever they do (she doesn’t get that from me). Her uncle nicknamed her “Mensa Milly” because she was laser-quick at maths and English. She was also dreamy and creative, sociable, angelically kind and possessed of a very silly sense of humour and the most infectious giggle. We don’t hear that so much now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Milly was increasingly exhausted and attended school less and less. Lisa is a youth counsellor, which came in handy, and we both juggled jobs so someone could be at home with Milly. We tried to create a restful and positive environment. Milly had plenty of sleep and healthy, home-cooked food. She was not bedridden but rose with tousled hair after 11am each day. She filled her bedroom with fluffy blankets, a Jellycat Snow Dragon and plants. Our dog, Betty, was another source of comfort, licking her hands daily, as if she needed healing. She read, listened to audiobooks and watched telly. When Esme and her younger brother Ted returned from school, Milly would play Minecraft with them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We needed a formal diagnosis – for Milly and for ourselves, but also to explain her increasing absence from school. The headteacher was understanding. We were lucky that healthy Esme attended primary school every day, so we weren’t suspected of being one of those families blamed for fostering school avoidance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not everyone was so understanding. I don’t blame them. We didn’t understand Milly’s illness either. As time went on, she became more and more withdrawn. What was wrong with her? Was she just anxious? Was it all in her head? Could we encourage her to get up and go out? We clung to our reality: Milly was a vibrant, energetic girl who loved life and got sick.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eventually, the NHS diagnosis came through: ME/CFS (chronic fatigue syndrome). This was frustrating. Milly had become unwell just after a global pandemic. Occam’s razor – the principle that the simplest explanation is probably the correct one – suggested she had long Covid. We believed she caught the virus in the summer of 2021, but was undiagnosed. Shortly after, we were refused an antibody test, then Milly definitely got Covid with the rest of her family in early 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We consoled ourselves that there seemed no great advantage in being attached to a long Covid clinic. The NHS help for both long Covid and ME/CFS, in our region at least, is minimal. There is no cure and no monitoring. The expert assigned to Milly moved jobs; we have not been offered an appointment with the specialist clinic since February 2024. We were given the usual advice about pacing – gradually increasing exercise – which is challenged by some ME patient groups.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a diagnosis without a treatment pathway, ME/CFS is a dangerous predicament. The syndrome is clearly an umbrella term for different illnesses that are poorly understood by modern medicine. We met people who had recovered thanks to talking cures. One told me his ME disappeared when he took a course of psychological treatment in his 20s and understood what he had to gain from being “tired” all the time: respite from being under pressure and daunted by the world. What did Milly have to gain from being tired, we wondered? Why would a nine-year-old decide to be ill? Were we, without meaning to, putting her under too much pressure?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We tried to remain open-minded. We tried a type of talking cure called the MindBody Reconnect which had revitalised a friend. Milly didn’t enjoy the expensive online sessions but doggedly stuck with it. I’m sure it works for some sick people. For Milly, it was a disaster. She became convinced she was responsible for her illness because she could not think herself well. More guilt for us. Lisa sourced alternative treatments: gut biome studies and nutritionists, mushroom tinctures, reiki, biodynamic massage, healers and even a psychic, who dispatched 17 spirits who were apparently haunting our house. None of it cured Milly, although we continued the massage because that gave her a weekly lift.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During her final year at primary school, the most Milly could manage was half a late morning. We would walk her there, hoping the gentle exercise would help. She’d shuffle along, hidden in her coat. When she moved up to high school, we and the super-nice Send staff devised a part-time schedule. Milly managed a week. We had to stop school. Lacking easy social connections, Milly felt too anxious or tired to sustain her friendships.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“How’s Milly?” people would ask. Same-same, we’d reply. Actually, she was slowly becoming more fatigued and more withdrawn. “So you home-educate her?” Not exactly, we’d reply. She was too exhausted most of the time. On the two days I was off work, I planned little educational trips – to the Castle Museum in Norwich or to the coast to see erosion in action – but she was too ill. Even minuscule walks were too much. She just about managed an hour of weekly maths with a teacher friend.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By autumn 2024, Milly had spent more than a quarter of her life sick, and a year completely out of school. She developed a keen interest in Japanese food and cooked, a lot, at home. She attended a Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons group every fortnight and loved its deep fantasy worlds. She was still empathic, sensitive and, on occasions, unexpectedly physically strong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As she turned 13, it was Milly who took the decisive step to discover what was really wrong with her. After hearing about Miranda Hart’s health struggles, she bought her audiobook. In I Haven’t Been Entirely Honest With You, the comedian writes of her 30-year battle with debilitating fatigue and disbelieving doctors, with the eventual revelation that she was suffering from Lyme disease. Unusually, Milly asked me and Lisa to read Hart’s book. She really identified with her.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Did we get Milly tested for Lyme?” I asked Lisa. It had crossed our minds before. Lisa checked the GP’s blood tests and found everything was looked at in the early stages. Milly was negative: she had no Lyme antibodies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What we didn’t know then was that there are so many medical shibboleths around Lyme. These, the few real experts in the disease believe, are almost certainly causing thousands of cases to be missed in Britain alone. We only knew what most people understand about Lyme: if you’re bitten by a tick, look out for a bull’s-eye rash (it can also be solid red). If you find one, take an antibiotic called doxycycline and you will be cured.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is all true for many people but, unfortunately, this disease is much more complex. You may not be aware you’ve been bitten by a tick. A survey by the Lyme Resource Centre found that 41% of people diagnosed with Lyme disease could not recall receiving a tick bite at all. This is not carelessness: even a tick’s grain-of-sand-sized aphids can transmit the disease. Once you’re bitten, you may not develop a rash at all. If you’re treated with antibiotics, you may not get better. And if you have an NHS blood test, known as Elisa, it gives false negatives about 50% of the time. It looks for antibodies – but Lyme bacteria hides, and can fool the body into not producing them. This is what happened to Milly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Around the time we read Hart’s story, Lisa heard on a Long Covid Kids charity discussion group about a private doctor having good results with some patients. After waiting probably far too long, we paid for a second opinion from him. In December we attended a London clinic that felt more like a spa. Dr Ben Sinclair is a personable former prison doctor in his 40s. He caught long Covid and successfully treated himself; later he discovered he also had Lyme disease. Since April 2024, he and his small team have held consultations with 2,500 patients who present with symptoms of long Covid or Lyme or both. There may be a link: in many sufferers, Sinclair told us, Covid suppressed their immune system, allowing Lyme bacteria lurking at unproblematically low levels within the body to rapidly multiply (a study found that 13.5% of people in western Europe have serological evidence of the bacteria in their bodies).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He questioned us closely, in particular about a holiday we took to the Lake District in Whitsun 2021. I’d forgotten this but Lisa remembered Milly was bitten by a tick. It was not a dramatic experience. In 2020 I wrote a book called Wild Child, about the importance of nature in children’s lives. Our kids all attended forest school, where we learned to be tick-aware. We’d successfully removed ticks from Esme’s head and Ted’s skin, and monitored for the telltale rash that suggests infection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That holiday, Milly and her siblings played in the bracken. Then we found a tick on her neck. I extracted it cleanly, almost immediately. No rash developed. Photos show Milly glowing with health. There were no obvious symptoms afterwards, though Lisa remembers Milly feeling weary that summer. At the end of our consultation, Sinclair said he thought she had Lyme disease. I remember being surprised he was so confident.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rather than the Elisa test, Sinclair recommended a T-spot test, measuring the T-cell interferon response (a type of white blood cell) to bacterial antigens. It’s the gold standard for testing for tuberculosis, a bacteria that similarly creeps around the body, hiding in tissues and organs. The tests are not available on the NHS and we would have to dispatch bloods to a German lab. We stepped out of the consulting room in a daze and treated Milly to a quick look at the Jellycats of Selfridges before getting the train home. I felt like crying. Later, I did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It took two months to get the blood tests done, partly because Milly had developed a phobia of needles. The results were dramatic. Milly’s body showed a high level of borrelia activity, the bacteria the NHS blood test had missed. She had co-infections of babesia and bartonella, bacteria that are also believed to be spread by ticks and can cause severe illness. These were making her sicker. Her exhausted immune system couldn’t fight them off. Her borrelia infection was tracked with a baseline measurement: 430.50. Only later did Sinclair tell us it was one of the highest he had seen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This news sparked some big emotions. Mine involved guilt. I write about how beneficial nature is for children, in mind and body. In this instance, nature had made my daughter very sick. And why hadn’t I been more proactive in seeking answers? At least Lisa made it an unceasing quest. I can only say in my defence that I adapted to meet Milly’s needs. Together, Lisa and I had undertaken a big, loving job of care: giving Milly food, time, belief, comfort and, most of all, acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is harder to accept mainstream medicine’s denial of the disease. In Britain, the NHS and National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (Nice) do not recognise “chronic Lyme disease” (though they do acknowledge some people treated for Lyme can experience lingering symptoms, which the NHS calls “post-treatment Lyme disease syndrome”). Many infectious disease experts don’t believe borrelia can survive blasting by doxycycline, which is usually – but not universally – effective.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professor Jack Lambert was treating patients in New York in the 1980s before there was a test to diagnose HIV and Aids. He contrasts the willingness then of doctors to try novel treatments for HIV with the apparent lack of interest in Lyme. These days, based in Dublin, he has several thousand Lyme patients on his books and sees five new sufferers each week. Many, he says, are the victims of years of “medical gaslighting” by doctors who refuse to take their symptoms seriously or consider Lyme. “The strange thing about Lyme disease is the medical community have spent all their time denying its existence and its complexity,” he says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, over the last decade Lyme has become better understood, particularly in North America. Monica Embers, professor of microbiology and immunology at the Tulane National Primate Research Center in Louisiana, has shown that borrelia can survive treatment with doxycycline, as part of more than two decades of research into the Lyme bacteria across dozens of peer-reviewed studies. “This assumption that doxycycline is the be-all, end-all antibiotic is flawed. We need to do better,” Embers says. “No single one antibiotic is going to do the trick for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Her research backs up what doctors are finding: that a combination of antibiotics can get on top of the disease. Another recent, albeit small, study found combined antibiotics effective at providing “complete remission” from severe neurological symptoms. Doctors report a 60-70% success rate after treating hundreds of patients with a combination of antibiotics. But in the UK, Nice’s guidance – from 2018, so not including recent advances in medical science – states: “The evidence available for treating ongoing symptoms did not show benefit from prolonged treatment with antibiotics.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What evidence does the NHS have that people are cured after three weeks of doxycycline?” Lambert says. “None. I treat people for infections all the time. If, after two weeks of antibiotics, they’re not better, I treat for longer. But with Lyme, you say, ‘Oh, it’s post-treatment Lyme disease syndrome. We can’t give more antibiotics.’ Where’s the medical science there? It doesn’t make sense.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The medical establishment doesn’t recognise chronic Lyme disease, Embers says, because it is so tricky, with symptoms that can be autoimmune issues, inflammation or persistent infection. Lambert says doctors must treat all three, and while medical guidelines caution against using antibiotics over the long term, some doctors are willing to consider treatment for up to a year – if the patient is improving.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, Sinclair says 60–70% of his patients make a good recovery with a combination of antibiotics. “I’ve never made the claim that I can cure people,” he says. “But what I try to do is restore function, reduce symptoms and get people into a balance where their immune system should do the work.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll take those odds with Milly. But our quick-smart daughter has developed a profound scepticism about all treatments after experiencing the failure of NHS doctors and alternative remedies. It took weeks of careful discussion before she would try a combination of antibiotics. We didn’t yet tell her these antibiotics make some patients feel sicker. The Jarisch Herxheimer reaction – diarrhoea, extreme nausea, inflammation – is triggered when the body’s immune system responds to the toxins released as antibiotics start to kill borrelia. Some people can’t tolerate this treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In May she began Sinclair’s protocol of two antibiotics, alongside herbal supplements to support her gut health which would be compromised by the strong drugs. Those Nice guidelines mean none of this is available on the NHS. We returned to our GP with Milly’s blood test results and asked if the NHS could undertake ongoing monitoring of her heart and blood during her treatment. We were met with a firm no. The NHS had failed Milly. It had made a misdiagnosis, allowed a child to struggle with a chronic illness for a quarter of her life – and wouldn’t pick up the pieces now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Private treatment is beyond the reach of most people. We used cheaper herbal medicines provided via the not-for-profit Claid Clinic but the initial T-spot blood tests cost £2,000. The first three months of treatment, including drugs, supplements, consultations and tests, cost an additional £3,884.50. We are incredibly fortunate to be able to meet these bills – just.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the summer, Milly continued to rise late, look pretty ghostly and feel extremely tired. But was she a tiny bit stronger? We took her to a music festival and she didn’t crash afterwards. Was it just the holidays, having sunshine and siblings around? In August we got her blood test results after three months of antibiotics. We were stunned. Her borrelia levels had dropped from 430.50 to 6. The treatment had obliterated the infection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we are filled with hope, and caution. The numbers still need to reduce to 0.5, says Sinclair, who has tweaked the antibiotic regimen. We continue with herbal medicines, too. School has started again, without Milly, and she remains seriously fatigued. “Sometimes the physical recovery comes later,” Sinclair says. “That’s the hard thing about this. You often reach this period where you go: ‘We’ve done everything, all the figures look good, but the person in front of me is not feeling it.’” Certain types of Milly’s natural killer cells, markers of her immune system health, are still much too low. Sinclair likes a military analogy: “Imagine a battlefield after a war. It takes six to 12 months to clear away the burnt-out tanks. It’ll probably take a while to get back to full function when you’ve removed the enemy.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the future for all those people who unknowingly have Lyme or who will contract it over the coming years? In the US, the Steven &amp;amp; Alex Cohen Foundation has invested more than $50m in Lyme research projects over the last decade. Embers is encouraged that US government agencies are taking tick-borne disease much more seriously. She is developing an improved blood test called Lyme Seek which she hopes will reach the market next year. “Our sensitivity and specificity is over 90%,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Europe, Lambert is struck by the lack of EU or government funding for Lyme research. “It’s a disease waiting for compassionate physicians to acknowledge these patients’ condition, give them treatment and investigate better diagnostics, better treatment,” he says. “At present, the medical community is so against the whole idea that Lyme disease is complex. It deserves investment in scientific funding to better understand it.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And what’s the future for Milly? “Because I’ve tried loads of things, it’s hard to believe this will really work,” she says. “I’ve lost faith in medicine and practitioners. I’m not feeling much better either. It’s difficult to think of the future right now – where my life might lead.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mental scars run deep. But we hope Milly will physically recover. If her immune system can be repaired and conquer the borrelia, she could live an active, “normal” life. We are not sure whether she will ever reintegrate into school. And yet I collect stories of how childhood sickness has been a font of creativity for the person who recovers in adulthood, and I hope.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have a diagnosis, we have treatment and we have hope. Most hopefully of all, occasionally, in early evening, Milly starts mucking about with her brother. I hear an explosion of infectious giggling. The Milly giggle. She’s still here. She’s still Milly. How lucky are we to have her in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45404793</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 14:56:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The golden ratio as a number base</title><link>https://apieceofthepi.substack.com/p/the-golden-ratio-as-a-number-base</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45404803</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 14:57:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>She Sent Her iPhone to Apple. Repair Techs Uploaded Her Nudes to Facebook (2021)</title><link>https://www.vice.com/en/article/she-sent-her-iphone-to-apple-repair-techs-uploaded-her-nudes-to-facebook/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a66cd11d937711d1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple paid a multimillion dollar settlement to an Oregon woman after repair techs the company had contracted published nude photos of her from her phone on her Facebook. As first reported by The Telegraph, the unidentified woman sent her iPhone to Apple for repairs in 2016. According to court documents reviewed by Motherboard, two repair techs then posted “10 photos of her in various stages of undress and a sex video” to her personal Facebook page. The case highlights the personal nature of our devices and the need for Apple to relinquish its repair monopoly and let us repair our own stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to court records, the woman found out this happened when one of her friends reached out to say her nudes had been uploaded to Facebook. She pulled them down and threatened to sue Apple for invasion of privacy and emotional distress. In this case, the people who uploaded the photos and video worked for a company called Pegatron, which is a company Apple works with to do repairs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Videos by VICE&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For years, Apple has been arguing to legislators that it needs to tightly control who is able to do repairs on iPhones and other Apple products. One of the core arguments it makes is that allowing “unauthorized” repair companies to fix iPhones will lead to privacy violations and will cause security problems. This case shows how, even when Apple tightly controls its repair infrastructure, it cannot prevent disastrous cases like this from happening. In a world where repair is a free and open marketplace, consumers can choose to take their phone to someone who they trust, or can decide to repair their phone themselves. In the current world we live in, you often have to take your phone to Apple; your phone then goes to a giant repair facility somewhere. The phone is essentially entering a black hole.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only reason we know about this case is because of a dispute between Apple, Pegatron, and the AGLIC American Insurance Company. Apple and other large corporations pay for something called indemnity insurance. The basic idea is that when the big company screws up and has to pay a judgement in a case like this, the insurance reimburses them. In the lawsuit, Apple is named as a “customer” of Pegatron, but is not a party to the lawsuit. Apple fought (and succeeded) at filing details of the case under seal. Many of the documents remain sealed by the court.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple paid the multimillion dollar settlement, Pegatron reimbursed them, and then the insurance company refused to pay out the indemnity claim. The exact amount of the settlement isn’t known, but court records obtained by Motherboard discuss two transactions in dispute—one for $4.25 million and another for $1.7 million.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t the first time an Apple employee or contractor has sorted through a customer’s photo gallery and shared their nudes. It happens all the time. In 2019 an Apple genius texted himself a personal photograph of a customer who’d come in looking for help with her phone. In 2016, Apple fired a group of employees in Australia after uncovering evidence the group had set up a website to share customer’s photographs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our devices are extremely personal. They hold an incredible amount of information about us, from personal emails, to explicit photographs, private communications, and financial information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Companies like Apple intentionally manufacture devices to be repairable only by authorized companies. They often require special tools to diagnose and fix problems, which aren’t shared with the public or third-party repair shops. Apple and other companies have taken extraordinary steps to make sure people can’t repair their own devices, and even claim it’s unsafe for us to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Apple has been opposing Right to Repair bills by claiming that their service network is the only safe repair option for consumers,” Kyle Wiens, CEO of iFixit, told Motherboard. “But the only person that is totally guaranteed to be trustworthy to fix your iPhone is you. Any time you hand your data to another entity, you risk something like this. By withholding access to service tools and forcing customers to use their third party contractor, Apple is willfully compromising the security of their customers.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Laws enshrining the right-to-repair would fix these issues and pave the way for people to fix their own stuff. States across the country are considering legislation that would give people the power to fix their own stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple did not immediately respond to Motherboard’s request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45404907</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 15:09:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The AI coding trap</title><link>https://chrisloy.dev/post/2025/09/28/the-ai-coding-trap</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a549d23b2ab12319"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you ever watch someone “coding”, you might see them spending far more time staring into space than typing on their keyboard. No, they (probably) aren’t slacking off. Software development is fundamentally a practice of problem-solving, and so, as with solving a tricky crossword, most of the work is done in your head.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the software development lifecycle, coding is the letters filled into the crossword, only a small amount of effort compared to all the head scratching and scribbled notes. The real work usually happens alongside coding, as the developer learns the domain, narrows down requirements, maps out relevant abstractions, considers side effects, tests features incrementally, and finally squashes bugs that survived this rigorous process. It looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But with AI-driven coding, things play out very differently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;“Code first, ask questions later”&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI coding agents such as Claude Code are making it astonishingly fast to write code in isolation. But most software lives within complex systems, and since LLMs can't yet hold the full context of an application in memory at once, human review, testing, and integration needs will remain. And that is a lot harder when the code has been written without the human thinking about it. As a result, for complex software, much of the time will be spent on post hoc understanding of what code the AI has written.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the root of the difference between marketing copy that boasts of the paradigm shifting speed of writing code with AI (often framed as “10X faster”), and the marginal productivity gains in delivering working software seen in the wild (usually closer to 10%).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An even more dispiriting upshot of this is that, as developers, we spend an ever greater proportion of our time merely fixing up the output of these wondrous babbling machines. While the LLMs get to blast through all the fun, easy work at lightning speed, we are then left with all the thankless tasks: testing to ensure existing functionality isn’t broken, clearing out duplicated code, writing documentation, handling deployment and infrastructure, etc. Very little time is actually dedicated to the thing that developers actually love doing: coding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortunately, help is at hand. While LLMs are shaking up how software development is performed, this issue in itself is not actually new. In fact, it is merely a stark example of an age-old problem, which I call:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The tech lead’s dilemma&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As engineers progress in their careers, they will eventually step into the role of tech lead. They might be managing a team, or they could be a principal engineer, driving technical delivery without the people management. In either case, they are responsible for the team’s technical delivery. They are also usually the most experienced developer in the team: either in their career, in the specialised domain of the team, or in both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Software delivery is a team effort, but one in which experience can have a highly imbalancing effect on individual contribution velocity. As such, when the tech lead’s primary job is to maximise delivery, they will often face an internal conflict between two ways to deliver software:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fair delegation across the team, maximising learning and ownership opportunities for junior team members, but allowing delivery to be bottlenecked by the speed of the least productive team members.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Mollycoddling the team, by delegating only the easy or non-critical work to juniors, and keeping the hardest work for themselves, as the person on the team most capable of delivering at speed.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, while we shall see that mollycoddling is extremely harmful to long-term team health, it is also often a very effective way to accelerate delivery. The higher bandwidth of the tech lead is often most efficiently deployed by eating up all the hardest work:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As such, I have seen this pattern repeated time and again over the course of my career. And, of course, it comes at a cost. Siloing of experience in the tech lead makes the team brittle, it makes support harder, and it places ever greater pressure on the tech lead as a single point of failure. What follows next is predictable: burnout, departure, and ensuing crisis as the team struggles to survive without the one person who really knows how everything works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As is usually the case, the solution lies in a third way that avoids these two extremes and balances delivery with team growth. We might frame it as something like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Implement team practices that allow engineers to deliver working code within a framework that minimises rework, maximises effective collaboration, and promotes personal growth and learning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I was CTO of Datasine, we enshrined this attitude in a simple tech team motto:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Learn. Deliver. Have fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good tech leads expose their engineers to work at the limit of their capabilities, using processes and practices that minimise delivery risk while also enabling each team member to grow their skills, knowledge, and domain expertise. This is, in fact, the essence of good technical leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are many ways to accomplish it, from strict codified frameworks such as the Extreme Programming rules, through to looser sets of principles which we might broadly refer to as “best practices”:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Code reviews&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Incremental delivery&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Modular design&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Test-driven development&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pair programming&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Quality documentation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Continuous integration&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, for experienced engineers today, an urgent question is: how can we translate these practices into a world of AI-driven coding?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;LLMs are lightning fast junior engineers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2025, many engineers are finding themselves for the first time in a position familiar to every tech lead: overseeing a brilliant but unpredictable junior engineer. Harnessing and controlling such talent, in a way that benefits effective team collaboration, is one of the primary challenges of engineering leadership. But AI coding agents need different management to junior engineers, because the nature of their productivity and growth is fundamentally different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As software engineers gain experience, we tend to improve our productivity in multiple ways at the same time: writing more robust code, using better abstractions, spending less time writing and fixing bugs, understanding more complex architectures, covering edge cases more effectively, spotting repeated patterns earlier, etc. Engineering is a rich and complex discipline with many avenues for specialisation, but for simplicity we might group these dimensions into two broad themes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Quality: ability to deliver more complex, more performant, more maintainable code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Velocity: ability to develop working, bug-free code in a shorter space of time&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over time, good engineers will improve in both axes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early LLMs were fast to write code, but time spent fixing bugs and removing hallucinations meant they were slow to complete bug-free code. Over time, smarter LLMs and better use of context engineering and tools have meant that modern AI coding agents are much better at “one shot” writing of code. The current generation of commercially available agents can be incredibly fast at producing working code for problems that would challenge some mid-level engineers, though they cannot yet match the expertise of senior engineers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So we can think of the current generation of AI coding agents as junior engineers, albeit with two fundamental differences:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;LLMs deliver code much, much faster than junior engineers, constrained neither by thinking nor writing time;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;LLMs have no true capacity to learn, and instead only improve through more effective context engineering or the arrival of new foundation models.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As with junior engineering talent, there are broadly two ways that you can deploy them, depending on whether your focus is long-term or short-term:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AI-driven engineering: employing best practices, foregrounding human understanding of the code, moving slowly to make development sustainable.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vibe coding: throwing caution to the wind and implementing at speed, sacrificing understanding for delivery velocity, hitting an eventual wall of unsalvageable, messy code.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As might be expected, the long-term trajectories of choosing between these two approaches follow much the same pattern as choosing between parallel delegation and mollycoddling of a junior team:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is why the vibe coding approach is great for tiny projects or throwaway prototypes: applications of sufficient simplicity can be delivered without the need for any human thinking at all. By limiting the complexity of our projects and leaning into the capabilities of the tools, we can deliver end-to-end working software in no time at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But you will hit a wall of complexity that AI is incapable of scaling alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building prototypes is now easier than ever. But if we want to effectively use LLMs to accelerate delivery of real, complex, secure, working software, and to realise more than marginal efficiency gains, we need to write a new playbook of engineering practices tailored to maximise collaboration between engineering teams that include both humans and LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to avoid the AI coding trap&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI coding agents are dazzlingly productive, but lack in-depth knowledge of your business, codebase, or roadmap. Left unchecked, they will happily churn out thousands of lines of code with no heed paid to design, consistency, or maintainability. The job of the engineer, then, is to act as a tech lead to these hotshots: to provide the structure, standards, and processes that convert raw speed into sustainable delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need a new playbook for how to deliver working software efficiently, and we can look to the past to learn how to do that. By treating LLMs as lightning-fast junior engineers, we can lean on best practices from the software development lifecycle to build systems that scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just as tech leads don't just write code but set practices for the team, engineers now need to set practices for AI agents. That means bringing AI into every stage of the lifecycle:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Specification: exploring, analysing, and refining feature specifications to cover edge cases and narrow focus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Documentation: generating and reviewing documentation up front to provide reusable guardrails and lasting evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Modular Design: scaffolding modular architectures to control context scope and maximise comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Test-Driven Development: generating extensive test cases prior to implementation to guide implementation and prevent regression.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Coding Standards: applying house styles and best practice when generating code, through context engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Monitoring &amp;amp; Introspection: analysing logs and extracting insights faster than any human ever could.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By understanding that delivering software is so much more than just writing code, we can avoid the AI coding trap and instead hugely amplify our ability to deliver working, scalable software.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45405177</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 15:43:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why I'm not rushing to take sides in the RubyGems fiasco</title><link>https://justin.searls.co/posts/why-im-not-rushing-to-take-sides-in-the-rubygems-fiasco/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="cd771095c9b21fe4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why I'm not rushing to take sides in the RubyGems fiasco&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are in the midst of a Ruby drama for the ages. I'm sure a bunch of people figured we were all too old for this shit, but apparently we are not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This debate has been eating at me ever since the news first broke, but I've tried to keep the peace by staying out of it. Unlike most discourse about what's going on, my discomfort stems less from the issue at hand—what Ruby Central did, how they did it, and how poorly it was communicated—and more to do with how one-sided the public discussion has been. Beneath the surface of this story are the consequences of a decade-old conflict that was never fully resolved. Then and now, one side—Andre Arko and many people associated with him—has availed itself of public channels to voice their perspective, while the other—which includes a surprisingly wide swath of well-known Ruby and Rails contributors—has chosen to stay silent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The losers in this dynamic are the vast majority normal everyday Ruby developers, most of whom are operating on very little information and who understandably feel confused and concerned. People whose livelihood depends on the health of the Ruby ecosystem deserve more information than they're getting, especially now that its operational stability has come under threat. The future of that ecosystem is once again uncertain, but—just like last time—the outcome is being shaped by a history that's been kept from the public, widening the rift between its key decision-makers and the communities they serve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't have the answers to what's going on in 2025. A few details have been shared with me—details that would contradict fact-checks and timelines others have pieced together and published—but I can't pretend to have a clear picture of what actually happened, why no one is setting the record straight, or when we'll have clarity on what the future holds. All I can do is offer a little bit of context to explain why I'm dubious of the dominant narrative that has taken shape online. Namely, I don't believe this is a cut-and-dry case of altruistic open-source maintainers being persecuted by oppressive corporate interests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After you read this, perhaps your perspective will shift as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The relevant proper nouns to know&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before anything else can make sense, it's important to understand how weird the governance of the Ruby ecosystem is. There are three moving parts involved that are ostensibly managed by three different groups, but whose members have such broadly overlapping systems access that it has now led to disputes over who owns what:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ruby itself, created by Matz and maintained by a large group of (mostly Japanese) committers, who host ruby-lang.org, control the @ruby GitHub organization, and are supported by the Ruby Association&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;RubyGems, specifically the &lt;code&gt;gem&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;bundler&lt;/code&gt;CLI tools distributed with the Ruby language, which is hosted under @rubygems on GitHub&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;RubyGems.org, the website, API, and host from which gem dependencies are installed and which has been run by Ruby Central for ages&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If Ruby were invented today, a single party would probably control all three of these things, but it took nearly fifteen years for today's status quo to take shape. Ruby was invented by someone in Japan in the 1990s. RubyGems was created at a conference in Texas by a few Americans in the early 2000s. RubyGems.org only became the de facto canonical host for gems six years later. My impression is that at no point was communication and coordination particularly fluent between the various parties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adding to this, Bundler—a meta tool for resolving the correct versions of all of a project's gem dependencies and which quickly became vital to nearly all Ruby application development—was created independently of the above players by Yehuda Katz and Carl Lerche. Andre Arko later became the lead maintainer of Bundler, and in 2015 he founded a 501(c)(6) nonprofit called Ruby Together. In 2019, Bundler was folded into RubyGems. In 2022, Ruby Together was absorbed by Ruby Central.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those last two events—the merging of Bundler and the unwinding of Ruby Together—came about after years of bitter conflict and simmering discord that I hope to shed some light on below. My direct involvement with any of these events was extremely minimal, but I had contemporaneous discussions with dozens of the principals involved. I never donated to Ruby Together and have never materially contributed to Bundler or RubyGems. That said, simply being made aware of several incidents as they were playing out in private was enough to leave behind a scar that has never fully healed. I can only imagine how others are feeling right now. Based on how badly things are playing out this time, it seems they were deeply impacted, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The things people told me&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The earliest recollection I have of someone telling me about Andre Arko was in the summer of 2015, after getting dinner with a friend who happened to be a Ruby Together board member. The friend explained that Andre believed programmers working on open source tools deserve to earn an income that's commensurate with what salaried engineers earn at the companies who benefit from those tools. As such, Andre's goal with Ruby Together was characterized as an effort to fund development activities—initially his own, but eventually others—by paying themselves a market hourly rate. I remember being extremely sympathetic to this perspective, having also wasted countless hours of my life maintaining open source for free only for others to benefit from it. I also recall a figure like either $200 or $250 per hour being mentioned as the rate he was effectively paying himself. Whatever the rate actually was, I distinctly remember thinking, "holy shit, that's a lot higher than individual donors would probably assume."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first time I remember meeting Andre in person was at Ruby on Ales 2016. I remember trying to make a good impression, because growing my network in the community was the primary reason I spoke at conferences. I was presenting with my beloved 12-inch MacBook, which meant I was traveling with the first iteration of this cursed dongle. Andre needed an adapter, so I ran up to lend him mine. As he was giving it back, I recall him making a half-joking, flippant remark about either his dongle or his computer, saying that "Ruby Together will just buy me another one." It really rubbed me the wrong way. Over the years to follow, more than one person told me stories of Andre paying for shared meals on behalf of Ruby Together without an apparent legitimate justification. They told those stories, I assume, because the attitude he exhibited made them uncomfortable. If I had donated money to Ruby Together and heard the same stories, I would have been upset.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For how little has been said about this publicly, a lot of different people told me a lot of concerning stories about Ruby Together over the years, often providing evidence to back it up. I'll do my best to stick to the highlights in this post. Hopefully they will explain why I have not joined the rush to defend the maintainers whose access was recently removed. What Ruby Central did was undoubtedly handled very poorly, but I don't think their bungling of its execution and communication alone is enough to answer the question of what should happen to the future custody and direction of Bundler, RubyGems, and RubyGems.org.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2015&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Ruby Together first launched in 2015, the website suggested donations went to pay "our team", which initially linked to a list of the board members without any explanation of how the money was being allocated. This resulted in a nonzero number of donors believing they were funding the work of people like Steve Klabnik, Aaron Patterson, and Sarah Mei, when in fact only Andre was being paid at the time. Shortly after the wording was raised as misleading, the team page was updated accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In May of 2015, Andre suggested making support for older versions of Bundler contingent on Heroku paying Ruby Together, which was interpreted as leveraging his control over Bundler as a pay-to-play scheme. Because Heroku serves other people's Ruby apps—many of which aren't updated for very long stretches—the security of their service depends on clear and predictable support windows for Ruby's core technologies, it seems reasonable they would interpret this sudden revocation of support as a pressure tactic, aimed to solicit corporate sponsorship for Ruby Together. (Years later, Andre responded to a feature request from a Heroku engineer, which was interpreted at the time as indicating the feature would be withheld from Bundler because Heroku had failed to pay Ruby Together.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2016&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The minutes of a December 2016 Ruby Together board meeting were leaked. The document acknowledged who was paying for the RubyGems.org service at the time: "Fastly is comping us something like $35k worth of CDN service per month. And that's on top of Ruby Central paying for $5k of servers and Ruby Together paying for about $15k of dev work every month." The use of "us" in that sentence suggests that Ruby Together was responsible for hosting RubyGems.org, which Ruby Central later went on to publicly dispute. Additionally, one presumes the number of hours and rate paid for development work was determined by Ruby Together itself, rather than being a hard operational cost. Later in the document was a discussion of potential strategies to increase revenue after "new memberships [had] flatlined." Several ideas were discussed, culminating in a proposal to rate-limit access to RubyGems.org as the apparent best option:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rate limiting RubyGems.org seems like the option that scales most linearly with our costs. Companies that cost us money need to pay more (or stop costing us money), and companies that don't cost us money can continue to have a free ride. To be clear, this would not mean cutting off anyone's access to RubyGems.org. I'm imagining that it would work something like GitHub's model: anonymous access has a low limit, registered accounts have a higher limit, and even higher limits are available at each Ruby Together membership level. There are a lot of implementation details that would need to be worked out, but in general I feel like this is probably the most effective option to make companies feel like they are paying money for something they use and that covers our costs well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The leaked minutes were widely circulated in private at the time, due largely to outrage over the document's presupposition that Ruby Together was paying to host RubyGems.org (citing "our costs" as scaling with usage), as opposed to paying for developer effort (the costs of which do not scale with usage). The leak left myself and others worried that Andre might leverage his systems access to effectively hold the Ruby ecosystem hostage for the financial benefit of Ruby Together and—since it was compensating his own development efforts—Andre himself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2017&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In January 2017, Andre added a "post-install message" imploring users to fund Ruby Together, which would be displayed every time anyone installed Bundler. Unlike the aforementioned board meeting, this happened in the open and triggered an immediate backlash before eventually being rolled back. In one comment, Andre defended the action and pointed to Shopify's failure to pay Ruby Together, publicly conflating Ruby Together's sponsorship of development effort with "~$40k/mo worth of servers." But, as Ruby Together's own board minutes from the month prior directly stated, money sent to Ruby Together wasn't going to pay server expenses—server costs were covered by Fastly and Ruby Central.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In February 2017, following protracted discussion of the post-install message and the threat of rate-limiting access to gem installs, I agreed to put my name on a letter alongside 18 others (including one of Bundler's creators). The letter requested Ruby Together stop misleading the community in this way. My understanding is that some private one-on-one communication followed, that none of it was particularly productive, and that no formal communication occurred between the two groups afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In March 2017, Ruby Central went on the record, attempting to clear up confusion and reassure users that they alone were in control of RubyGems.org, stating that Ruby Together donations were immaterial to its continued operation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this past year has also given rise to some misunderstandings about this relationship in some quarters: chiefly, that by donating to Ruby Together, companies were paying for the operations of RubyGems. And in turn, that if enough companies didn't donate to Ruby Together, RubyGems would subsequently be in a perilous situation. This isn't so.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;No one in the Ruby community should worry about the availability or security of RubyGems being connected in any way to the fundraising of Ruby Together. Funds raised by Ruby Together go primarily towards paying developers to add features and fix bugs. Ruby Central, on the other hand, is wholly responsible for the operations and baseline stability of the system. While these two efforts go hand-in-hand, it's vitally important to understand that they are two different things. Ruby Together's requests for donations do not mean that there is any reason for concern about RubyGems' continued existence or operation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later, in August 2017, Andre accused Google Cloud Platform of wholesale copying gemstash's codebase, going so far as to threaten legal action in his opening message. He juxtaposed the accusation with the complaint that Google had, "repeatedly declined to support Ruby Together." The incident appeared to fit a pattern of behavior to pair high-conflict messaging with an admonition of the target's failure to fund the organization that paid him. Ultimately, Andre's claim turned out to be factually baseless—Google hadn't copied gemstash's code, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2018–2024&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Things quieted down and I didn't hear much about any of this stuff anymore. Eventually, Bundler became part of RubyGems and many folks from Ruby Together migrated to analogous roles at Ruby Central.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In August 2025, and seemingly out of nowhere, someone pointed me to the project spinel-coop/rv-ruby, an apparent fork of homebrew/homebrew-portable-ruby. I say "apparent", because rather than using GitHub's fork button—which would have maintained clear attribution of who created the upstream project—it looks like it was instead cloned and re-pushed by Andre. Specifically, I was sent this commit replacing references to Homebrew from late July. As evidence of Homebrew's authorship was being erased and obscured, no additional acknowledgement was added to credit Homebrew for having created and maintained Portable Ruby since 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It immediately reminded me of Andre's baseless accusation against Google. "Not only did you not credit the Gemstash project in any way," Andre wrote, "from an ethical standpoint, this is also super gross." His blatant copying of Portable Ruby (a project significant enough that the lead maintainer gave a talk about how they did it) struck me as brazenly hypocritical, given Andre's previous litigious and mistaken accusation against Google.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fairness to Andre, the rv-ruby repo continues to retain a copy of Homebrew's LICENSE.txt which names "Homebrew contributors" as the copyright holder. Andre also later added an explicit acknowledgement to the README, but that attribution came more than a month later, and (I'm told) only after he was directly asked to credit the original project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andre wrote this week that, "Ruby Together did not ever, at any point, demand any form of governance or control over the existing open source projects. Maintainers did their thing in the RubyGems and Bundler GitHub orgs, while Ruby Together staff and board members did their thing in the rubytogether GitHub org." However, while he was leading Ruby Together, he moved to restrict committer access to RubyGems in rubygems/rubygems, unilaterally erased the original authorship from Bundler's gemspec in bundler/bundler, and oversaw a number of contributors being removed from bundler/bundler-site in a redesign of Bundler's website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a result of this broader historical context and in spite of the serious claims and grave implications being thrown around this month, I'm trying my best not to rush to judgment about who's at fault in the current conflict and would urge others to do the same. The future of the Ruby ecosystem may depend on it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45405221</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 15:48:10 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>