<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 17:12:43 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Advent of Sysadmin 2025</title><link>https://sadservers.com/advent</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d370ffcfa78f27d3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Advent of Sysadmin is a 12-day Advent calendar of Linux and DevOps challenges of different difficulties that runs from December 1st to December 12th.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each day there will be an Advent of Sysadmin scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sign up for a free account (needed to keep track of your progress) and start solving the scenarios!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="5"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Day&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Name&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Level&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Time Limit&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2025-12-01&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;"Auderghem": containers miscommunication&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Easy&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 mins&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46102347</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 01:17:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>X210Ai is a new motherboard to upgrade ThinkPad X201/200</title><link>https://www.tpart.net/about-x210ai/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46103097</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 03:12:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Search tool that only returns content created before ChatGPT's public release</title><link>https://tegabrain.com/Slop-Evader</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d94012a3200d538b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A browser extension for avoiding AI slop. Download it for Chrome or Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a search tool that will only return content created before ChatGPT's first public release on November 30, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the public release of ChatGTPT and other large language models, the internet is being increasingly polluted by AI generated text, images and video. This browser extension uses the Google search API to only return content published before Nov 30th, 2022 so you can be sure that it was written or produced by the human hand.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46103376</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 04:06:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google Antigravity just deleted the contents of whole drive</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/google_antigravity/comments/1p82or6/google_antigravity_just_deleted_the_contents_of/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46103532</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 04:39:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>SmartTube Compromised</title><link>https://www.aftvnews.com/smarttubes-official-apk-was-compromised-with-malware-what-you-should-do-if-you-use-it/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ad2c930509fb3ed1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, the developer of SmartTube, the most popular alternative YouTube app for Android TV and Fire TV devices, announced that his app’s digital signature had been exposed. A new version of the app using a new digital signature has since been released. While everyone is encouraged to switch to the new app, SmartTube’s developer has shared more information with me about what happened that may make you want to take additional precautions if you’ve installed or updated the app recently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SmartTube’s developer told me that the computer used to create the APKs for the project’s official GitHub page was compromised by malware. As a result, some official SmartTube releases were unintentionally released with malware. It’s unclear which version was first affected, but the compromise seems to have first occurred earlier this month. SmartTube versions 30.43 and 30.47 from APKMirror are both being flagged as infected by malware scanners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is likely the presence of this malware that caused Google and Amazon to forcibly uninstall SmartTube on some devices, not the exposed digital signature as first suspected. SmartTube’s developer says the compromised machine has been wiped and is confident that both the new SmartTube releases and the machine that created them are malware-free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All older versions of SmartTube have been removed from the project’s GitHub in an abundance of caution. While there does not appear to be any evidence that the app’s digital signature was actually stolen or used by malicious actors, that too has been abandoned and replaced with a new one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SmartTube version 30.56 is the first release built by the uncompromised machine and with the new digital signature. It can be installed using my Downloader app by entering code &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It remains unknown what the malware that found its way into the official SmartTube APK files can actually do. Thankfully, SmartTube is programmed to only request minimal account permissions and does not ask for any login information directly. Even if you granted the app access to your Google Drive for backup purposes, your Google account and general Google Drive files remain out of the app’s scope of permissions. Permissions regarding control of your YouTube account seem like the only thing that could have easily been exposed to the malware, as far as account access is concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, since very little is know about the malware, you should assume the worst. If you use SmartTube and are concerned about your exposure to this malware, you should factory reset any device that had the app installed, especially if you installed or updated the app in November. It would also be a good idea to audit your Google account permissions and your YouTube account activity for anything unusual. Once your devices and account are in order, if you wish to reinstall SmartTube, be sure to only install the latest version through the codes/links above.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46103657</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 05:01:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>It’s been a very hard year</title><link>https://bell.bz/its-been-a-very-hard-year/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2e3a015411e7ab99"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;It’s been a very hard year&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike a lot of places in tech, my company, Set Studio/Piccalilli has no outside funding. Bootstrapped is what the LinkedIn people say, I think.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s been a hard year this year. A very hard year. I think a naive person would blame it all on the seemingly industry-wide attitude of “AI can just do this for us”. While that certainly hasn’t helped — as I see it — it’s been a hard year because of a combination of limping economies, tariffs, even more political instability and a severe cost of living crisis. It’s been a very similar year to 2020, in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why am I writing this? All of the above has had a really negative effect on us this year. Landing projects for Set Studio has been extremely difficult, especially as we won’t work on product marketing for AI stuff, from a moral standpoint, but the vast majority of enquiries have been for exactly that. Our reputation is everything, so being associated with that technology as it increasingly shows us what it really is, would be a terrible move for the long term. I wouldn’t personally be able to sleep knowing I’ve contributed to all of that, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What we do really well is produce websites and design systems that actually work for and with people. We also share our knowledge and experience via tonnes of free content on Piccalilli, funded by premium courses to keep the lights on. We don’t pepper our content with annoying adverts for companies you have no interest in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve spoken about my dream for us to run Piccalilli full time and heck, that may still happen. For that to happen though, we really needed this Black Friday period to do as well, if not better, as it did last year. So far, that’s not happening unfortunately, but there’s still time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I get it, money is so tight this year and companies are seemingly not investing in staff with training budgets quite like they did. We actually tried to stem that a bit by trialing a community funding model earlier in the year that I outlined in I’m getting fed up of making the rich, richer and we even started publishing some stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It went down incredibly well, but when push came to shove, we fell way short in terms of funding support. Like I say, we’re not swimming in investor money, so without the support on Open Collective, as much as it hurt, we had to pull the plug. It’s a real shame — that would have been incredible — but again, I get it, money is tight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t a woe is me post; that’s not how I roll. This is a post to give some context for what I’m going to ask next and how I’m trying to navigate the tough times. I’m asking folks to help us so we can try to help everyone, whether that’s with web projects that actually work for people or continuing to produce extremely high quality education material. Here’s some ways you can do it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Take advantage of our Black Friday deals&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll see messaging like “this is the most important time of year for us” and it’s extremely true. To break the fourth wall slightly, people buying courses at full price is a lot rarer than you might think. So often, discount events are what keeps the lights on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve launched two courses this year — JavaScript for Everyone and Mindful Design — that sit alongside my course, Complete CSS, which we launched last year. I know you’ve probably been burned by shit courses in the past, but these three courses are far from that. I promise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can’t stress enough how much Mat (JavaScript for Everyone) and Scott (Mindful Design) have put in to these courses this year. These two are elite level individuals with incredible reputations and they’ve shared a seemingly impossible amount of extremely high quality knowledge in their courses. I would definitely recommend giving them your time and support because they really will transform you for the better. For bosses reading this, all three courses will pay themselves back ten-fold — especially when you take advantage of bulk discounts — trust me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Share our courses and our studio with your network&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So many of you have purchased courses already and I’m forever thankful for that. I can’t stand the term “social proof” but it works. People might be on the fence about grabbing a course, and seeing one of their peers talk about how good it was can be the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You might think it’s not worth posting about the courses on social media but people do see it, especially on platforms like Bluesky with their custom feeds. We see it too!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Testimonials are always welcome because we can pop those on the course marketing pages, just like on mine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In terms of sharing the studio, if you think we’re cool, post about it! It’s all about eyes and nice words. We’ll do the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Hire Set Studio for projects&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re really good at what we do! I know every studio/agency says this, but we’re different. We’re actually different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re not going to charge you through the nose for substandard work — only deploying a fraction of our team, like a lot of agencies do. I set this studio up to be the antithesis of the way these — and I’ll say it out loud — charlatans operate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our whole focus is becoming your partners so you can do the — y’know — running of your business/organisation and we take the load off your shoulders. We’re hyper efficient and we fully own projects because they’re way above your normal duties. We get that. In fact, the most efficient way to get the most out of a studio like ours is to do exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know “numbers goes up” is really important and yes, numbers definitely go up when we work with you. We do that without exploiting your users and customers too. There’s no deceptive patterns coming from us. We instead put everything into branding, messaging, content architecture and making everything extremely fast and accessible. That’s what makes the numbers go up for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re incredibly fairly priced too. We’re not in the business of charging ridiculous fees for our work. We’re only a small team, so our overheads are nothing compared to a lot of agencies. We carry your budgets a long way for you and genuinely give you more bang for your buck with an equitable pricing model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve got availability starting from the new year because starting projects in December is never the ideal way to do things. Getting those projects planned and ready to go is a good idea in December though, so get in touch!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m also slowly getting back into CSS and front-end consulting. I’ve helped some of the largest organisations and the smallest organisations, such as Harley-Davidson, the NHS and Google write better code and work better together. Again, starting in the new year I’ll have availability for consulting and engineering support. It might just be a touch more palatable than hiring the whole studio for you. Again, get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m always transparent — maybe too transparent at times — but it’s really important for me to be honest. Man, we need more honesty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s taken a lot of pride-swallowing to write this but I think it’s more important to be honest than to be unnecessarily proud. I know this will be read by someone else who’s finding the year hard, so if anything, I’m really glad they’ll feel seen at least.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Getting good leads is harder than ever, so I’d really appreciate people sharing this with their network. You’ll never regret recommending Piccalilli courses or Set Studio. In fact, you’ll look really good at what you do when we absolutely smash it out of the park.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and if you’re also struggling, I’m sending as much strength your way as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👋 Hello, I’m Andy and this is my little home on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m the founder of Set Studio, a creative agency that specialises in building stunning websites that work for everyone and Piccalilli, a publication that will level you up as a front-end developer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve also got a CSS course called Complete CSS to help you get to a level in development that you never thought would be possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back to blog&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46103858</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 05:36:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Games using anti-cheats and their compatibility with GNU/Linux or Wine/Proton</title><link>https://areweanticheatyet.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d422fc810f425674"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Light theme&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A comprehensive and crowd-sourced list of games using anti-cheats and their compatibility with GNU/Linux or Wine/Proton.- Starz0r&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1136&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;194 Supported (17%)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;258 Running (23%)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2 Planned (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;635 Broken (56%)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;47 Denied (4%)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Search&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sort By&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sort Order&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Halo: The Master Chief Collection&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supported&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Denied&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Battlefield™ 2042&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paladins&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make sure to check recent updates, the game is known to break often (And the status may not update to reflect that)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Broken&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Black Desert Online&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Requires Proton GE or Proton Experimental&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Epic Games Store is broken on Linux. Steam Recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46104396</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 07:05:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DeepSeekMath-V2: Towards Self-Verifiable Mathematical Reasoning</title><link>https://huggingface.co/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-Math-V2</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="cd4a93503ddb8ad8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;DeepSeekMath-V2: Towards Self-Verifiable Mathematical Reasoning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Large language models have made significant progress in mathematical reasoning, which serves as an important testbed for AI and could impact scientific research if further advanced. By scaling reasoning with reinforcement learning that rewards correct final answers, LLMs have improved from poor performance to saturating quantitative reasoning competitions like AIME and HMMT in one year. However, this approach faces fundamental limitations. Pursuing higher final answer accuracy doesn't address a key issue: correct answers don't guarantee correct reasoning. Moreover, many mathematical tasks like theorem proving require rigorous step-by-step derivation rather than numerical answers, making final answer rewards inapplicable. To push the limits of deep reasoning, we believe it is necessary to verify the comprehensiveness and rigor of mathematical reasoning. Self-verification is particularly important for scaling test-time compute, especially for open problems without known solutions. Towards self-verifiable mathematical reasoning, we investigate how to train an accurate and faithful LLM-based verifier for theorem proving. We then train a proof generator using the verifier as the reward model, and incentivize the generator to identify and resolve as many issues as possible in their own proofs before finalizing them. To maintain the generation-verification gap as the generator becomes stronger, we propose to scale verification compute to automatically label new hard-to-verify proofs, creating training data to further improve the verifier. Our resulting model, DeepSeekMath-V2, demonstrates strong theorem-proving capabilities, achieving gold-level scores on IMO 2025 and CMO 2024 and a near-perfect 118/120 on Putnam 2024 with scaled test-time compute. While much work remains, these results suggest that self-verifiable mathematical reasoning is a feasible research direction that may help develop more capable mathematical AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;2. Evaluation Results&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Below are evaluation results on IMO-ProofBench (developed by the DeepMind team behind DeepThink IMO-Gold) and recent mathematics competitions including IMO 2025, CMO 2024, and Putnam 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IMO-ProofBench&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mathematics Competitions&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;4. Quick Start&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DeepSeekMath-V2 is built on top of DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp-Base. For inference support, please refer to the DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp github repository.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;6. License&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This repository and the model weights are licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (Apache 2.0).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;7. Citation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@misc{deepseek-math-v2,
  author = {Zhihong Shao, Yuxiang Luo, Chengda Lu, Z.Z. Ren, Jiewen Hu, Tian Ye, Zhibin Gou, Shirong Ma, Xiaokang Zhang},
  title = {DeepSeekMath-V2: Towards Self-Verifiable Mathematical Reasoning},
  year = {2025},
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;8. Contact&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, please raise an issue or contact us at service@deepseek.com.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="dl"&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dt-1"&gt;Downloads last month&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item rend="dd-1"&gt;4,434&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Model tree for deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-Math-V2&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unable to build the model tree, the base model loops to the model itself. Learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46105079</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 08:54:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Self-hosting a Matrix server for 5 years</title><link>https://yaky.dev/2025-11-30-self-hosting-matrix/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ae38b5519d233d94"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Self-hosting a Matrix server for 5 years&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experiences with the Matrix protocol, Matrix Synapse server, bridges, and Element mobile apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have been hosting a Matrix server for about five years now, mostly for text chats between a few relatives and close friends, and a bridge to WhatsApp for a few more people. These are my experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Matrix protocol&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't have many thoughts on the protocol itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only thing that I don't really understand is the decision on data replication. If a user on server A joins a room on server B, recent room data is copied from server B to server A and then kept in sync on both servers. I suppose this reduces the load on the original server at the expense of federation overhead and space on other servers. However, this also creates a situation where anything said across federation cannot be unsaid, which is an ironic situation for a protocol/system that often comes up when talking about privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IIRC, fediverse/ActivityPub uses a similar approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Synapse server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synapse is the only choice that supports bridges, which was why I wanted to try Matrix in the first place. And back in 2019-2020 this was the only choice anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As of right now, I run Synapse, PostgreSQL, and coturn directly, without containerization, on a small VPS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Works well&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Works fairly reliably, supports bridges, and is more efficient that it was in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;API is well documented, and allows authenticating and sending (unencrypted) messages via simple HTTP calls. At some point in time, I wanted to write a simple shell client to use with SXMO and such.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Does not have an admin panel&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is no admin page or panel. There was a third-party admin site, but it's an entire site just for making HTTP calls. So I ended up writing my own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Nowadays, the ESS deployment includes developer-made admin, see Future section)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Requires PostgreSQL&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While technically, Synapse can work with a sqlite database (and which at first seems like an OK choice for having &amp;lt;10 users on the server), it WILL become corrupted. So PostgreSQL is de-facto mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Already a part of new ESS)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Requires federation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initial setup presumes that the server is going to be federated, and there is no good way to turn it off. The best workaround involves a blank whitelist of federated servers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GitHub issue: Single config option to disable federation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't know the implications of disabling it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Needs constant cleanup&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Message retention policy can be set up server-wide, but also per-room. There are specific lines in the configuration that need to be set to actually enable a service that runs the cleanup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synapse keeps the room even after all of the members leave it, including federated rooms. This results in many (sometimes large) rooms without local members orphaned on the server, taking up database space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deleting messages (events) with attachments does not delete the attachment (because another message might refer to it?), which means that the sent files continue existing on the server indefinitely. Another privacy implication. A simple "delete all files older than X" script works great until it deletes avatars. So yeah, seems like this is something that should be handled by the Synapse server instead of cobbled-together scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even after extensive cleanup, PostgreSQL database might need to be vacuumed to reduce the disk space it takes up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Database grows out of control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even for my small server with &amp;lt;10 active users, database size reached several gigabytes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synapse keeps track of room states in an append-only (!) table named state_groups_state. Deleting a room does not delete the state_groups_state records. So it is never automatically cleaned up, and grows in size infinitely. It is possible to delete many of those records from the database directly, and Element (the company) provides some tool to "compress" those records, but again, something that should be handled by the server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good article about state_groups_state&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Users cannot be deleted&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is simply not an option in the API. Server admin can perform a "deactivate" (disable login) and "erase" (remove related data, which claims to be GDPR-compliant) on user accounts, but the accounts themselves stay on the server forever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wait, what? Why?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How this not considered a GDPR violation is a mystery to me. Even on my tiny server, I have users who use their first name as their ID and bridged WhatsApp users that use phone numbers as IDs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Future&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While Matrix-Element ecosystem has been catering towards government and corporate entities for some time, there have been multiple recent announcements about its future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Specifically, Element (the company) is now providing an all-in-one Element Server Suite (ESS) to replace the current setup, including&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;It is intended for non-professional use, evaluations, and small to mid-sized deployments (1â100 users).&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ESS Community includes 7 components/services, now requires a minimum of 2 CPUs, 2GB of RAM, and runs using... Kubernetes? IMO, this is an overkill for dozen users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For comparison, Snikket, an all-in-one solution with similar functionality using XMPP, requires a single CPU and 128MB (!) RAM for 10 or so users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, I have seen the ansible setup script setup recommended, but at this point, making setup easier does not address the issue of extra services being required in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matrix server setup using Ansible and Docker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, the ESS handles account creation and calls in an entirely different way, more on that later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Matrix-WhatsApp bridge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pretty great. Easy to install and set up, works really well, and needs only occasional (semi-yearly or so) updates when WhatsApp changes their web API. Does not support calls.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Element Classic&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Same on all platforms&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Element exists and looks consistent on Android, iOS, and web, making it easier for regular users and for troubleshooting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No image captions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is silly, but while (official?) bridges support image captions, official Element app does not. The answer in the FAQ? Get a better app. Well, OK.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No image caption in Element Classic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Image with a caption in SchildiChat Classic (the better app).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Slow notifications&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes it can take up to a few minutes to get a message, even between two Android clients using Google Cloud Messaging. Sometimes it is nearly instant. Still unsure of the cause.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No offline indication&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One unreliable way to tell that the server is unreachable is the endless loading bar. But even then, it eventually goes away without indicating any errors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, when sending a message, the user receives "Unable to send message". Frustration ensues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I know the app is trying to call the /sync endpoint. Why doesn't it show any errors when that fails?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Security key and device verification&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IIRC the first thing the app does is ask user to back up their signing keys and enter the key password, without a simple explanation. Not a great experience for regular users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some people reported issues with Element losing its keys or frequently requesting to be re-verified. Thankfully I have not encountered these.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Third-party services&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if you connect to a self-hosted server, Element Classic could attempt to connect to vector.im integration server and matrix.org key backup server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Element X&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Element X is now recommended as the new and better client. It is not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Slower&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Somehow, it is slower. Clicking on a conversation takes 0.5-1.0 seconds to load it, compared to almost instant load on Classic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps it does work better for accounts with many large rooms, but that is not my case.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Sorting&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conversations are sorted by... who knows. It is not recent nor alphabetical.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;No background sync&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Element X does not support periodic background sync, so you need to set up ntfy or something similar to use Element X on a de-googled device. Seems like a simple enough fail-safe (even WhatsApp does this), but it was dropped for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Requires "sliding sync" option on the server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This "sliding sync" option is available only for newer Synapse versions, and only if running with PostgreSQL database (which should already be the case - see above). Probably not an issue unless the user tries to connect Element X to an outdated Synapse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Calls are not backward compatible&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Calling with Element X requires Element Call (part of ESS). This supports group calls, but... only video calls at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You also might be asked to tell your contact to install the new app:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't regularly use calls, but some people I would like to invite to my server would want to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Onboarding is bad&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few years ago, I ended up either temporarily enabling unrestricted registration (a terrible idea), or creating my users' accounts manually, because the "invite" matrix.to link was broken, and registration tokens did not work correctly in mobile apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So let's see how it works now. Keep in mind, I am still on standalone Synapse, not ESS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Element X onboarding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am a user, and I was to register an account on my friend's server. I see that Element X is now a recommended app, so let's try that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click "Create account" (which is a different style that does not look like a button for some reason).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I want an account on a different server. Click "Change account provider".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Click "Other".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now I can search for the server my friend is hosting, and it should appear in the list below the search.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As server admin: I do not remember if Synapse server has to enable/keep federation for this to work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes! That is what I want, why is this so verbose?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WTF. So Element X cannot create even the simplest username+password account. That is all I want, I don't want to sign in with Google, Apple, or any other form of third-party authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Element Classic onboarding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was unable to register an account using Element X, so Element Classic should work better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ok, "CREATE ACCOUNT".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What difference does this make? Skip.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The current official app is telling me to use Element X. Just tried that. Click "EDIT" where it says "matrix.org" (which does not say "server", actually) and enter the server name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why not? No explanation. Sure, I'll use a web client.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, fuck me, I guess. Why can't I just create an account?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a server admin: Synapse is set to allow registrations via registration tokens, because unrestricted registration is a bad idea. I did not find where the /static/client/register path is set.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IIRC it is possible to register an account by going to a web-hosted Element app, such as app.element.io, which will allow to register an account using a registration token. But then the user has to deal with the headache of cross-verifying their mobile device to the web app (which they might never use).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;So now what?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matrix-Element is growing, building new features, and acquiring large customers (mostly government entities AFAIK). However, the new corporatesque ESS Community is not worth it in my opinion. I don't need fancy auth, third-party IDs, group video conferencing, or even federation for that matter. But it is clear that Synapse and Element X are severely crippled and are not designed to work without these services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will probably switch to Snikket, which is more efficient, has timely notifications, and very smooth onboarding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Who cares?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â¯\_(ã)_/Â¯&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46106132</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 11:26:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why xor eax, eax?</title><link>https://xania.org/202512/01-xor-eax-eax</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="989ffc0661139ed8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Written by me, proof-read by an LLM. &lt;lb/&gt;Details at end.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In one of my talks on assembly, I show a list of the 20 most executed instructions on an average x86 Linux desktop. All the usual culprits are there, &lt;code&gt;mov&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;add&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;lea&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;sub&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;jmp&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;call&lt;/code&gt; and so on, but the surprise interloper is &lt;code&gt;xor&lt;/code&gt; - “eXclusive OR”. In my 6502 hacking days, the presence of an exclusive OR was a sure-fire indicator you’d either found the encryption part of the code, or some kind of sprite routine. It’s surprising then, that a Linux machine just minding its own business, would be executing so many.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is, until you remember that compilers love to emit a &lt;code&gt;xor&lt;/code&gt; when setting a register to zero:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We know that exclusive-OR-ing anything with itself generates zero, but why does the compiler emit this sequence? Is it just showing off?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the example above, I’ve compiled with &lt;code&gt;-O2&lt;/code&gt; and enabled Compiler Explorer’s “Compile to binary object” so you can view the machine code that the CPU sees, specifically:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;31 c0           xor eax, eax
c3              ret
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you change GCC’s optimisation level down to &lt;code&gt;-O1&lt;/code&gt; you’ll see:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;b8 00 00 00 00  mov eax, 0x0
c3              ret
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The much clearer, more intention-revealing &lt;code&gt;mov eax, 0&lt;/code&gt; to set the EAX register to zero takes up five bytes, compared to the two of the exclusive OR. By using a slightly more obscure instruction, we save three bytes every time we need to set a register to zero, which is a pretty common operation. Saving bytes makes the program smaller, and makes more efficient use of the instruction cache.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It gets better though! Since this is a very common operation, x86 CPUs spot this “zeroing idiom” early in the pipeline and can specifically optimise around it: the out-of-order tracking systems knows that the value of “eax” (or whichever register is being zeroed) does not depend on the previous value of eax, so it can allocate a fresh, dependency-free zero register renamer slot. And, having done that it removes the operation from the execution queue - that is the &lt;code&gt;xor&lt;/code&gt; takes zero execution cycles!1 It’s essentially optimised out by the CPU!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may wonder why you see &lt;code&gt;xor eax, eax&lt;/code&gt; but never &lt;code&gt;xor rax, rax&lt;/code&gt; (the 64-bit version), even when returning a &lt;code&gt;long&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this case, even though &lt;code&gt;rax&lt;/code&gt; is needed to hold the full 64-bit &lt;code&gt;long&lt;/code&gt; result, by writing to &lt;code&gt;eax&lt;/code&gt;, we get a nice effect: Unlike other partial register writes, when writing to an &lt;code&gt;e&lt;/code&gt; register like &lt;code&gt;eax&lt;/code&gt;, the architecture zeros the top 32 bits for free. So &lt;code&gt;xor eax, eax&lt;/code&gt; sets all 64 bits to zero.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, when zeroing the “extended” numbered registers (like &lt;code&gt;r8&lt;/code&gt;), GCC still uses the &lt;code&gt;d&lt;/code&gt; (double width, ie 32-bit) variant:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note how it’s &lt;code&gt;xor r8d, r8d&lt;/code&gt; (the 32-bit variant) even though with the REX prefix (here &lt;code&gt;45&lt;/code&gt;) it would be the same number of bytes to &lt;code&gt;xor r8, r8&lt;/code&gt; the full width. Probably makes something easier in the compilers, as clang does this too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;xor eax, eax&lt;/code&gt; saves you code space and execution time! Thanks compilers!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See the video that accompanies this post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post is day 1 of Advent of Compiler Optimisations 2025, a 25-day series exploring how compilers transform our code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post was written by a human (Matt Godbolt) and reviewed and proof-read by LLMs and humans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support Compiler Explorer on Patreon or GitHub, or by buying CE products in the Compiler Explorer Shop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It still has to retire, so some on-chip resources are still allocated to it. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matt Godbolt is a C++ developer living in Chicago. He works for Hudson River Trading on super fun but secret things. Follow him on Mastodon or Bluesky.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46106556</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 12:22:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A vector graphics workstation from the 70s</title><link>https://justanotherelectronicsblog.com/?p=1429</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f327529063a64154"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This repair has been on the to do list for ages, so let’s finally get to it!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my mind, Tektronix is a brand that makes electronics lab equipment like oscilloscopes and logic analyzers. Turns out, they made quite a few terminals and a couple of computers! A good friend saw this one for sale local to him, and I poked him till he agreed on picking it up for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Picking it up may be the wrong wording, this thing is big and heavy! It weights about 35kg and it’s nearly a meter long!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So let’s have a look at what this is, what I needed to do to repair it and what it can do!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Some history&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The machine I got is a Tektronix 4051 graphics workstation, released in 1975, but let’s look a bit at the history from Tektronix before this was released. Tektronix started in late 1945 as Tekrad, but quickly got renamed to Tektronix. One of their first products was the 511 oscilloscope, the first oscilloscope with a trigger!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This turned out to be a good thing, and soon enough, Tektronix was synonymous with oscilloscopes and known as a company that made some of the best test and measurement equipment. In the 60s, mainframe and then minicomputers became more popular, which often needed a terminal. Tektronix at this point was making storage oscilloscopes, which use a storage CRT tube that can “remember” drawn signals. Using this technology, Tektronix released their first terminal in 1969, the 4002. A 11″ terminal that was capable of displaying graphics with a 400×300 pixel resolution. As the CRT rememebers the drawn data, there was no need for a RAM framebuffer!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few years later in 1971 they released the 4010, again 11″ but now with 1024*780 pixel resolution. As they used Storage CRTs, these terminals where a lot cheaper then the competitors. Mind you, cheap still means around $4000, or around $30.000 in 2025 money. But the IBM 2250 was priced at around $280.000 That’s 1970s dollars, so well over 2 million USD today!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before we move away from these terminals, one last cool tidbit. Tektronix made the 4010 in several sizes, the biggest being the 25″ 4016 with a 4096*3120 pixel resolution. 4K in 1974, sign me up!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The 405x computers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OK I promised computers, so let’s move to the Tek 4051 I got! Released in 1975, this was based on the 4010 series of terminals, but with a Motorola 6800 computer inside. This machine ran, like so many at the time, BASIC, but with extra subroutines for drawing and manipulating vector graphics. 8KB RAM was standard, but up to 32KB RAM could be installed. Extra software was installed via ROM modules in the back, for example to add DSP routines. Data could be saved on tape, and via RS232 and GBIP external devices could be attached!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All in all, a pretty capable machine, especially in 1975. BASIC computers where getting common, but graphics was pretty new. According to Tektronix the 4051 was ideal for researches, analysts and physicians, and this could be yours for the low low price of 6 grand, or around $36.000 in 2025. I could not find sales figures, but it seems that this was a decently successful machine. Tektronix also made the 4052, with a faster CPU, and the 4054, a 19″ 4K resolution behemoth! Tektronix continued making workstations until the 90s but like almost all workstations of the era, x86/Linux eventually took over the entire workstation market.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 4051 was also used in a few series/movies, the storage CRTs do not flicker when recorded like a normal CRT and as they run basic, getting something cool on screen was fairly easy to do! The best known example was Battlestar Galactica:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fixing a Tektronix computer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the history out of the way, what’s the shape of the one I got?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was stored in a shed for a long while, state unknown, but it looked like it’s in OK shape. A bit dirty but who isn’t at times. Fuse is intact, and when opening it up, nothing looked “off” no bulging caps or such. But turning it on and nothing happens. Anticlimactic…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A good bit of tracing wires later, it turned out the ON/OFF switch is broken. So to quicly remedy this, some wires can be used.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I do NOT recommend this. 230V via cheap breadboard wires is not smart. But with this, still nothing. Argh. So another bit of debugging later it turned out a wire of the mains transformer was not connected to the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s kind of visible in this photo, there are wires going from the transformer to the tabs to select voltages and one was broken. Luckily there was enough wire left to solder on and fix it, getting a replacement would have been impossible! After this fix, I got power! I disconnected as much as I could in order to check all the voltages I could check. We need 15V, 12V, 5V, -12, +20, -20 +185 and +365 and they turned out to all be in spec. Tektronix :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, time to slowly connect boards back in and see if something explodes!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wait I didn’t mean that as a suggestion… Sadly this resistor didn’t understand sarcasm and decided to go up in smoke. It’s a 47 ohm resistor that limits a 320V supply a bit. Perhaps it got a little too warm, or age got the better of it. I did check everything after the resistor and all measured OK. No transistor in a short or capacitor that imploded. So let’s just replace this and pray?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neat, that worked!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Calibrating that display&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Something appeared on the display, which is a BIG improvement, and it all looks like the machine wants to boot. But the display is completely unreadable, which means it’s time to calibrate all voltages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which means, measure a power supply that’s almost 4KV. Spicy!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Luckily I have a HV scope probe on loan from a friend! And the HV is in spec. So that’s good, but all the other voltages are not. These CRTs are pretty sensitive to all the needed voltages, sensitive enough that they are calibrated in the factory and the voltages for the exact CRT are written on them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;196V and 75V for this one, and I measured 160V and 55V. yeah that’ll do it! Quite a few calibration steps later the display turned out to be quite nicely readable and in great condition!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The single tape I got with mine is sadly broken. The belt snapped, which seems to be a common issue with these. The drive itself seems to work, and the tape I got is an OS backup tape, so likely nothing too important. This is fixable, but not too high on my to-do list for now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This turned out to be a less complex repair then expected. Some keyboard switches are a bit crusty, it needs a clean, but a 50 year old computer mostly just working is pretty amazing! So let’s end this repair on a few fun beauty shots of the inside and more:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What did I pick up exactly?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having a look at my machine, it has maxed out RAM at 32KB, sadly no serial port, but it did came with a ROM Expander!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The back of the 4051 has space for 2 ROM cards. These contain things like extra programs, subroutines for DSP algorithms and more. These can contain 8KB of ROM, and are memory mapped.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want more then 2 at any time, the Rom Expander allows you to have 8! Only one is memory mapped at any time, but the OS of the 4051 scans all ROMS on start, and when you run a program on a ROM, it makes sure to send a few commands to the expander to memory map the right one. This is all invisible as an end user and the machine acts like having 8 ROMs, or if you have 2 expanders, 16 ROMs!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I got 3 ROMs with mine, one for an editor program, one to load/store binary data to tape, and one for the optional external floppy drive. Oh, yes, there is a floppy drive! Sadly I don’t have it, but if someone has one collecting dust, do let me know :)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;But can it run DOOM?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;OK any games at all?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How about some monopoly!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Due to the display technique, most games don’t work very well. The display can’t easily be cleared, apart from a full erase of the display. So some games like tic tac toe or monopoly work but anything more active is difficult sadly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Luckily there are plenty of cool demo’s and programs for the 4051 and it’s bigger siblings. A TON of programs, manuals and more can be found on the Github page from Monty McGraw. There is also an emulator so you can try this all out using any modern computer!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s next&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the projects on Monty’s Github is a GBIP flash emulator. Currently my 4051 has no way to load/store programs, and typing a 1000 line BASIC file is a bit of a pain. So I’m definitely ordering parts for that!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is also quite a few ROM cards I do not have, so I am working on a ROM board to clone them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally having this beautiful machine up and running is a great step, and I’ll leave it at this for now!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As always, if you enjoyed this blog post, you can buy me a coffee!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46107177</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 13:31:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cartographers Have Been Hiding Covert Illustrations Inside of Switzerland's Maps</title><link>https://eyeondesign.aiga.org/for-decades-cartographers-have-been-hiding-covert-illustrations-inside-of-switzerlands-official-maps/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="1e0c0b5d326895fd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Penicillin Myth&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Competing theories seek to explain inconsistencies surrounding Alexander Fleming’s famed discovery.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I did not invent penicillin. Nature did that. I only discovered it by accident.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;—Alexander Fleming&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many know the story of Alexander Fleming’s chance discovery of penicillin. Fleming, a bit of an absent-minded professor (and a bit of a slob), left culture plates streaked with Staphylococcus on his lab bench while he went away on summer holiday. When he returned, he found that “a mould” had contaminated one of his plates, probably having floated in from an open window. Before discarding the plate, he noticed that, within a “ring of death” around the mold, the bacteria had disappeared. Something in the “mould juice” had killed the staphylococci.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming immediately began investigating this strange new substance. He identified the mold as Penicillium rubrum and named the substance penicillin.1 He published his findings in the spring of 1929 in The British Journal of Experimental Pathology.2 But a decade later, pharmacologist Howard Florey and biochemist Ernst Chain at Oxford would pick up where Fleming left off. Alongside a USDA lab in Peoria, Illinois, the pair would develop penicillin into a life-saving drug and usher in the era of antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the kind of science story everyone likes. One of serendipity and accidental discovery; a chance observation that changed the world. But is it true?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For decades, scientists and historians have puzzled over inconsistencies in Fleming’s story. For starters, the window to Fleming’s lab was rarely (if ever) left open, precisely to prevent the kind of contamination that supposedly led to penicillin’s discovery. Second, the story is strikingly similar to Fleming’s earlier discovery of lysozyme, another antibacterial substance, which also featured lucky contamination from an open window. Third, Fleming claimed to have discovered the historic culture plate on September 3rd, but the first entry in his lab notebook isn’t dated until October 30th, nearly two months later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last, and most important: penicillin only works if it’s present before the staphylococci. Fleming did not know it at the time, but penicillin interferes with bacterial cell wall synthesis, which only happens when bacteria are actively growing. Visible colonies, however, are composed mostly of mature or dead cells. By the time a colony can be seen, it is often too late for penicillin to have any effect. In fact, the Penicillium mold typically won’t even grow on a plate already filled with staphylococcus colonies. For years, scientists have attempted to replicate Fleming’s original discovery. All have met with failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thus, it’s difficult to reconcile Fleming’s story with these historical and scientific discrepancies. Did he misremember events from 15 years earlier? Could he have fudged the details to make for a more compelling narrative? Or, might Fleming’s experiment have been subject to an unusual confluence of chance events unbeknownst even to him?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speculation about how Fleming discovered penicillin is of little consequence compared to its practical impact. However, science is about evaluating evidence and moving closer to the “truth.” As we near the 100th anniversary of penicillin’s discovery — which undoubtedly will encourage even greater repetition of the story — it’s in this spirit that we must scrutinize the story’s veracity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The historical and scientific data are limited and often contradictory. Nevertheless, several scientists and historians have worked hard to piece together what facts are certain and fill the gaps with their most probable guesses. The result is a range of competing theories, each attempting to explain what really happened in that St. Mary’s Hospital laboratory in the summer of 1928.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Fleming’s Account&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The story of Fleming’s discovery of penicillin is primarily based on this passage from his 1929 paper:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While working with staphylococcus variants a number of culture-plates were set aside on the laboratory bench and examined from time to time. In the examinations these plates were necessarily exposed to the air and they became contaminated with various micro-organisms. It was noticed that around a large colony of a contaminating mould the staphylococcus colonies became transparent and were obviously undergoing lysis (see Fig. 1).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Fig. 1” refers to a “Photograph of a culture-plate.” It shows separate, well-grown staphylococcus colonies around 2-4 mm in diameter spread across most of the plate’s surface. But on one edge, a large mold colony of about 20 mm in diameter, plus a secondary satellite colony, is clearly visible. This is labeled “Penicillium colony.” Surrounding it is a zone of about 20 mm in which the staphylococcus colonies are either not visible or have become semi-transparent ghosts. Those nearest to the mold are smaller than the rest, only 0.4 to 0.8 mm, while those towards the periphery are a bit larger, 0.8 to 1.7 mm. Fleming has labeled these “Staphylococci undergoing lysis.” Later, Fleming and his colleagues would claim that this was the original contaminated plate from which Penicillium was first isolated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On its face, this seems simple enough. Everyone knows that penicillin destroys bacteria, and Fleming observed staphylococci seemingly being destroyed by a mold that produced penicillin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, upon closer reading of Fleming’s 1929 paper, it becomes clear that a great deal of work was either omitted or inadequately described. There is, for example, no description of the type of culture medium used; whether or not the plate had been incubated; how long it had been on the bench; and, most important of all, what species of Staphylococcus was being studied.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When publishing a scientific paper, scientists are expected to include a detailed description of their methods alongside their results. Like a recipe, these methods should clearly and comprehensively describe the materials used and the steps taken so that other scientists can replicate the experiment. And while incomplete or poorly-described methods are a perennial problem, the omission of these key experimental details (even in a report on an accidental discovery) is surprising.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This became a problem when, as interest in penicillin grew, other investigators tried to repeat Fleming’s discovery. In 1944, Margaret Jennings (who later married a long-time colleague and penicillin researcher, Howard Florey) spread purified penicillin onto plates of fully grown staphylococci. This should have had a more potent effect than Fleming’s pictured in Figure 1, which was allegedly produced only with the crude “mould juice” from an accidental contaminant. Jennings, however, observed no visible change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1965, the pathologist W.D. Foster attempted a similar experiment using penicillin crystals dropped directly onto staphylococcus colonies, creating “astronomical” concentrations within their vicinity. But still, the colonies remained unaffected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other attempts at replication called into question whether the mold could have even grown on a plate full of staphylococci. Pharmacologist D.B. Colquhoun claimed that, in 1955, he found that Penicillium mold refused to grow on a plate already full of staphylococcus colonies. Or, that, if it did, it produced no visible effect on the colonies. He could, however, see an effect if the sequence of events was reversed: if the mold was allowed to grow for several days first, and the staphylococci was later inoculated onto the plate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although these failures are hard to reconcile with Fleming’s account, they are in line with what we now know about the biology of penicillin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1940, the physician A.D. Gardner, researching alongside Florey, peered into his microscope to examine how penicillin affected individual bacterial cells. Surprisingly, adult cells seemed to be largely unaffected; however, when they divided, the young cells grew “as immense swollen filaments.” Like party balloons, they elongated and expanded, then popped.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The morphological changes,” observed bacteriologist J.P. Duguid in 1946, “suggest that penicillin in these concentrations interferes specifically with the formation of the outer supporting cell wall, while otherwise allowing growth to proceed until the organism finally bursts its defective envelope and so undergoes lysis.” At the time, this was largely speculation. Not much was known about the biology of bacterial cell walls. But after a decade of study — motivated in no small part by a desire to understand how penicillin worked — this hypothesis has largely been proven correct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bacterial cell wall is a rigid, mesh-like structure composed primarily of peptidoglycan, a large macromolecule consisting of small subunits cross-linked by specialized enzymes called transpeptidases. The job of the cell wall is to maintain the cell’s shape and keep it from absorbing too much water. If the outward pressure from the cell’s contents becomes too great for the delicate cell membrane to contain, it bursts, spilling the cell’s innards. The cell wall, like a heavy-duty bicycle tire around a rubber inner tube, helps to resist this pressure, protecting the cell from mechanical stresses both inside and out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike a bike tire, however, cell walls need to be able to grow with the cells they enclose. To accommodate increasing cell size, bacteria are continuously breaking and rebuilding the peptidoglycan mesh. This is where penicillin comes in. Because penicillin has a similar chemical structure to a peptidoglycan subunit, it can bind to the transpeptidases that complete the final step in cell wall biosynthesis.3 When this happens, penicillin forms a covalent bond in the transpeptidase’s active site, irreversibly inactivating the enzyme. As it grows, the cell continues to disassemble its cell wall, but without the use of its transpeptidases, it can no longer rebuild it. Over time, the cell wall weakens and eventually bursts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This explains why Jennings and others couldn’t replicate Fleming’s contaminated plate. A mature colony is mostly composed of adult or dead cells. These cells are unaffected by penicillin because they aren’t actively growing, and so aren’t actively breaking and rebuilding their cell wall. As a result, penicillin doesn’t cause mature cells to lyse, and the colony’s overall appearance doesn’t change. But if the penicillin is present before the staphylococci, it prevents the bacteria from growing and dividing, or they do so much more slowly. When that happens, they don’t form visible colonies. Thus, penicillin does not dissolve fully grown colonies, as Fleming had initially assumed, but inhibits their growth from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The difficulty replicating Fleming’s discovery is frustrated by the ease with which it’s possible to “rediscover” penicillin by reversing the order of growth. By first growing Penicillium mold until it becomes a large colony, then seeding the plate with staphylococci, the result is indistinguishable from Fleming’s original plate. However, no trained scientist would intentionally use a culture plate visibly contaminated with a large mold — and certainly not an expert bacteriologist like Fleming.4&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are no contemporary records to corroborate the story that Fleming discovered the contaminated culture plate when he returned from holiday on September 3rd: no lab notebook records, calendar notes, diary entries, or any letters. In the 1929 paper, the figure is simply labeled, “Photograph of a culture-plate.” The only evidence we have stems from recollections by Fleming and colleagues years later, after penicillin was recognized as a runaway clinical success. Fleming himself described the Figure 1 plate as the “original culture plate” in a 1944 paper. Yet, he also included the disclaimer that “after a lapse of fifteen years it is very difficult to say just what processes of thought were involved.”5&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The earliest recorded mention of the mold and penicillin is an experiment written in Fleming’s lab notebook dated October 30th, 1928 — nearly two months after he purportedly found the culture plate. Curiously, it does not describe the chance discovery of a contaminant, but a carefully constructed experiment that suggests Fleming had already spent some time isolating and characterizing the mold. In it, Fleming used the reversed-sequence culturing method: first, placing a mold spore on the plate and letting it grow into a large, penicillin-producing colony, then inoculating several pathogenic species of bacteria, including staphylococci, near the mold.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On October 30th, Fleming recorded the results: the mold affected a whole host of pathogens, including staphylococci, which could not grow near the mold. It’s a fine experiment, but it’s clearly not the discovery of an accidentally contaminated culture plate. This raises the question: What was Fleming doing for the previous two months, and if he was working with penicillin, why didn’t he bother recording any of it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For decades, these scientific inconsistencies and experimental failures have haunted the story of penicillin’s discovery. Amidst the incontrovertible Nobel Prize-winning scientific and clinical success of penicillin — and without a plausible alternative — the doubters kept quiet. At least, most of them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Ronald Hare’s Theory (1970)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1964, the bacteriologist Ronald Hare took up the puzzle of penicillin’s origins. After examining old lab notebooks and conducting experiments of his own, he would conclude that “the history of both the culture plate and the mould itself must have been very different from what had previously been thought to be the case.” Hare published his own theory on penicillin’s discovery in his 1970 book, The Birth of Penicillin, and the Disarming of Microbes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare was uniquely positioned to investigate this mystery. Not only was he an accomplished bacteriologist and expert on penicillin, having spent 20 years as a Professor of Bacteriology at the University of London, and the ten years before that at the University of Toronto, where he was largely responsible for planning and building the Canadian Government’s penicillin plant; he started his career in the same department as Fleming at St. Mary’s. In fact, he claims to have been in the laboratory the very day Fleming discovered the now-famous culture plate. (Despite this close professional association, however, Hare claims to have played no part in the discovery or original research on penicillin nor to have discussed them with Fleming.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although that discovery is now regarded as one of the most significant scientific events of the 20th century, Hare admits that, at the time, it made little to no impression on him or any of his colleagues. “The rest of us, being engaged in researches that seemed far more important than a contaminated culture plate, merely glanced at it, thought that it was no more than another wonder that Fleming seemed to be forever unearthing, and promptly forgot all about it.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yet, Hare had been skeptical from the start that penicillin could have been discovered by simple contamination of a culture plate. It was such a common occurrence in biology laboratories that “if this had been the sequence of events, penicillin would probably have been discovered while Fleming was still a child.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After retirement, Hare took up the penicillin question. He began by attempting to replicate Fleming’s discovery. He seeded an ordinary culture plate with staphylococci, incubated it until colonies were visible, then placed a few mold spores on the surface. As the microbiologists before him had observed, the mold refused to grow. He tried coaxing the mold’s growth by plating it further and further away from any staphylococcal colonies (without deviating too far from the overall appearance of Fleming’s Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this approach, he was finally able to get the mold to grow and produce penicillin, but still the staphylococcal colonies were unaffected. “No one looking at such a plate could possibly guess that a powerful antibacterial substance was emanating from the mould.” If, however, he reversed the order and plated the mold before the staphylococci, he could get a result “almost indistinguishable from that of Fleming’s original plate.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vexed, Hare reevaluated the evidence. He had shown the mold couldn’t have contaminated the plate after the staphylococci because the mold wouldn’t grow (or, if it did, the penicillin wouldn’t affect the staphylococcus colonies). He assumed that the contamination couldn’t have occurred before the staphylococci (though that reliably recreates the plate pictured) because no bacteriologist would knowingly use a contaminated plate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if the mold contaminated the plate at the same time, or within a few hours, of when it was seeded with staphylococci? And what if the staphylococci’s growth had been paused (somehow) until the mold colony had matured? To Fleming’s eyes, he would have assumed he had inoculated staphylococci onto a contamination-free culture plate. Yet, with the staphylococci’s growth delayed, the mold would have had time to fully develop into a large, penicillin-producing colony. When the staphylococci’s growth was restarted, it would be growing in effectively the same conditions as if it had been plated after the mold had grown.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare knew just the thing that could arrest the staphylococci’s growth: low temperature. Staphylococci grow most rapidly at 98.6 °F (37 °C). As a human pathogen, it has evolved to grow optimally at human body temperature. This is why microbiologists incubate culture plates: to speed up their growth into visible colonies. The lowest temperature at which any staphylococci growth occurs, and then only very slowly, is around 53 °F (12 °C). The Penicillium mold, on the other hand, prefers to grow around 77 °F (25 °C) but is not greatly affected by temperature ranges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It therefore seemed possible that penicillin could have been discovered as described in the original 1929 paper, but with the addition a few details Fleming was unaware of: first, the inoculation of staphylococci and contamination by mold occurred at the same time; second, Fleming forgot6 to incubate the plate; and third, the lab’s room temperature was low enough for long enough for the mold to grow and produce penicillin before the staphylococci began to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To test this theory, Hare simultaneously inoculated a culture plate with both staphylococci and Fleming’s mold and left it on his benchtop. The weather that day was cold, wet, and stormy, and the temperature was relatively low: 61 to 65 °F (16.1 to 18.3 °C). As expected, the staphylococci grew more slowly than they would have in an incubator, and only tiny transparent colonies were visible on the third day. The mold, however, grew much more prolifically, and a tiny colony was visible after just 48 hours, growing to 10 mm by the fourth day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the end of the fifth day, Hare had rediscovered penicillin. The result was practically indistinguishable from the photo in Fleming’s original paper: in a ten millimeter zone around the mold, the staphylococcus colonies were small and transparent, while those outside the zone were larger and opaque. Many experiments later, Hare found that penicillin could reliably be rediscovered in this manner so long as the temperature was kept below 68 °F (20 °C) for four or five days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where Hare the scientist had to become Hare the historian. Was the temperature in Fleming’s laboratory low enough for him to discover penicillin at the end of July or the beginning of August in accordance with the timeline of his canonical story?7&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare searched the records at the Meteorological Office for the maximum and minimum shade temperatures from the beginning of July to the end of September, 1928. In the weeks before Fleming left on holiday there was a heatwave; from July 10th to 27th, there were highs in the upper 70s and 80s. At these temperatures, the staphylococci would have grown too quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, on the 28th, the heatwave ended and was quickly replaced by a cold snap. For the next nine days, the maximum temperature only exceeded 68 °F on two occasions, and not by much. It was a slim window, in which the temperature in Fleming’s laboratory would have been low enough. But it coincided perfectly with Fleming’s holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare’s theory relies on a triple chance of unlikely events. First, the penicillin-producing Penicillium mold landed on Fleming’s culture plate; second, Fleming failed to incubate the plate; and third, the temperature was low enough for the five days required to favor mold growth.8 “Had only one link in this chain been broken,” Hare writes. “Fleming would have missed his opportunity.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare himself concedes that the combination of these contingencies seems exceptionally unlikely. The original story of chance discovery, on its own, was one of serendipity and good fortune. His theory required an additional layer of meteorological luck on top of chance contamination. “Far from the phenomenon that led to the discovery being a comparatively common event that had previously escaped detection, it must be so unusual an occurrence that it is doubtful whether it can have happened very often since bacteria were first cultivated in the laboratory.” Yet, however improbable it may seem, to quote Sherlock Holmes: “When you have eliminated all which is impossible, then whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Robert Root-Bernstein’s Theory (1989)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare’s theory is based on the assumption that the Figure 1 plate was indeed the source of the original contamination. It also overlooks the two-month gap between when Fleming allegedly noticed the contaminated plate and recorded the first penicillin experiment. These details, however, form the foundation of a competing theory on penicillin’s origins — that belonging to Robert Root-Bernstein, Professor of Physiology at Michigan State University.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Root-Bernstein described his theory in his 1989 book, Discovering: Inventing and Solving Problems at the Frontiers of Science.9 It’s an ambitious and unorthodox book, structured as a seminar between six characters discussing creativity and the scientific process. Each character represents various points of view on the sciences and scientists and, along the way, they also discuss the important chronological and methodological idiosyncrasies of Fleming’s discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Root-Bernstein’s theory is argued and defended by the character Imp (real name Ernest; apparently a stand-in for the author himself). After summarizing the key details of Hare’s theory, Imp focuses on the two-month gap. Fleming supposedly discovered the Fig. 1 contaminated plate when he returned from a holiday on September 3rd, but the first lab notebook entry about Penicillium and penicillin wasn’t written until October 30th. As described earlier, that entry does not record the discovery of a contaminated plate but a planned experiment in which the Penicillium mold was first isolated and tested against several bacteria, including staphylococci.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But why, Imp wonders, if Fleming already had that beautiful culture plate which so perfectly illustrated the staphylococci-killing power of penicillin, he would wait two months to record the finding? And why do so in the context of another experiment? Furthermore, this plate still exists within the British Museum. That means Fleming had to fix it with formaldehyde relatively soon after he found it. But if he thought the plate was important enough to preserve, why didn’t he note its discovery at the time?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It wasn’t in Fleming’s character to procrastinate. According to his research scholar, Merlyn Pryce: “[Fleming] didn’t confine himself to observing, but took action at once. Lots of people observe a phenomenon, feeling that it may be important, but they don’t get beyond being surprised — after which, they forget. That was never the case with Fleming.” So then, what was he doing for two months?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s in this context that Imp (Root-Bernstein) grounds his belief that Fleming’s discovery wasn’t the serendipitous chance of lore — at least, not completely. Instead, he proposes that Fleming wasn’t running a staphylococcus experiment when he discovered penicillin; he was looking for new sources of lysozyme.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming had a long-standing professional interest in antibacterial substances. His most important discovery before penicillin was the lysozymes, enzymes found in various bodily fluids (e.g., tears, saliva, and egg whites) that break down the cell walls of bacteria. He had also studied the antibacterial properties of mercuric chloride and bacteriophages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Between 1922 and 1928, Fleming’s team tested anything they could get their hands on: human mucus, tears, sputum, and blood; the eggs of dozens of fish and bird species; tears collected from horses, cows, hens, ducks, geese, and fifty other species from the London Zoo; earthworm and snail slime; large numbers of vegetables and flowers. They continued to publish on lysozymes into the 1930s. “Is it too much to suggest,” Imp asked, “that he also examined any fungus that happened to come his way?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we assume that Fleming was engaged in a systematic search for new sources of lysozyme, we can now reasonably fill in the gap between September 3rd, when he first spots the mold, and October 30th, when he first records the Penicillium experiment. Root-Bernstein’s theory about the discovery goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, Fleming begins by finding the mold, which may or may not have been on a staphylococcus plate. In the paper, Fleming only says that he found it at the time he was “working with staphylococcus variants.” Either way, the plate is not enough to incite a “Eureka!” moment, as the canonical version of the story suggests.10 Instead, like the hundreds of other unusual samples he’s tested, Fleming transfers the mold to a new culture plate, gives it a few days to establish itself, and then runs a routine experiment to test for lysozyme activity. He finds that it weakly affects a lysozyme-sensitive strain. Not terribly interesting — not even worth recording11 — but it warrants a follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A short time later, the Root-Bernstein theory goes, Fleming prepares a second experiment. After growing the mold for five days into a robust colony, he adds various lysozyme-sensitive and -resistant species to the plate, including Staphylococcus. This time, he records the results because (surprise!) the mold affects the lysozyme-resistant staphylococci. This experiment, whose results are recorded on October 30th, is exactly what it appears to be within the context of Fleming’s notebooks: “the first penicillin experiment — the first recognition by Fleming that he’s dealing with something unexpected and exciting!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet, if this is the true sequence of events, why didn’t Fleming record it as such in his 1929 paper? “The logic of presentation rarely corresponds to the logic of discovery,” said Imp. Few scientists actually document the chronological sequence of events that led to their discovery. “Just imagine for a moment trying to write into a research paper the account I’ve just given,” said Imp:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While looking essentially randomly for organisms producing lysozyme, a common but unidentified mold was isolated from the air of the laboratory. Initial experiments showed that the mold appeared to have lysozyme activity, so controls were set up, including staphylococci, which I just happened to have been working on at the time. Much to my surprise, the mold had unexpected properties, so I was now forced to further characterize and identify the mold …This subsequent research conclusively demonstrated that the product of the mold was not lysozyme, but rather a new substance having the following characteristics …&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s too circuitous and indirect for a scientific report. Better, instead, to start with the mold lysing the pathogen, because that was the important and novel observation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under this theory of events, the Figure 1 plate also becomes exactly what it appears to be in its proper context: an illustrative example of the fact that penicillin-secreting Penicillium can kill staphylococci. Not, as the story is typically told, the original contaminated plate. Reading further in the paper, similar examples are included as Figures 3 and 4, which illustrate other properties of penicillin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming still could have shown his colleagues a contaminated staphylococcus plate on September 3rd, but one which must not have had the telltale “ring of death.” Or perhaps he did pass around the plate that would become the famous Figure 1, but not until several months later, when he was preparing figures for his paper. Hare’s cold snap, too, may have played a role in the mold growing when it did, but it no longer has to coincide with Fleming inoculating his staphylococcus plate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That Fleming was originally searching for new sources of lysozyme could also explain why he thought the mold contaminated a staphylococcus plate after the colonies had fully grown (which, barring Hare’s theory of simultaneous contamination, should be impossible). Penicillin may not be able to lyse mature colonies, but lysozymes can. Fleming may have assumed penicillin lyses bacteria the same way as lysozymes, and therefore could lyse mature colonies. It’s a conceptual leap, but one made smaller if he was looking for lysozymes in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like Hare, Root-Bernstein does not claim his account of Fleming’s discovery is “true,” only that it’s compatible with available data. (Root-Bernstein does not, however, shy away from claiming that his theory is the more likely of the two. “Hare may be a good bacteriologist,” said Imp, “but I question his historical acumen. Dates — you’ve got to pay attention to dates.”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More important to Root-Bernstein than the specifics of Fleming’s discovery is the fact that it evidences Pasteur’s principle that “chance favors only the prepared mind.” Whether he was experimenting with staphylococci or lysozyme, Fleming kept his mind open to the possibility of discovering new bacteriolytic substances. He often gave the advice, “Never neglect an extraordinary appearance or happening. It may be — usually is, in fact — a false alarm that leads to nothing, but may on the other hand be the clue provided by fate to lead you to some important advance.”12&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming’s methods — which included testing strange samples and keeping plates around for longer than he needed them — increased the probability that he would stumble upon something new, and he was mentally prepared to recognize them when he did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Source of the Mold&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other important aspect of Fleming’s discovery is the source of the contaminating mold. According to the canonical version of the story, the Penicillium floated into Fleming’s lab from an open window. However, no such claim was made in the 1929 paper. In fact, nothing about its source was said until 1945 when Fleming told the writer George Lacken that it had blown through the window from Praed Street.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why Fleming would say this is a mystery. He had no evidence that was the case, and as Hare writes, opening a laboratory window is “thoroughly bad bacteriology.” Further, Fleming’s windowsill was often piled high with test tubes and beakers filled with pathogenic bacteria. It would have created quite a scandal should any of these have fallen out of an open window onto the heads of the vulnerable passersby below. Nevertheless, the story gained wide publicity after André Maurois repeated it in his 1959 biography, The Life of Sir Alexander Fleming. Maurois repeatedly referred to “the mysterious mould from Praed Street,” and “the spore carried by the wind.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming himself seemed unsure of its origins. In a 1946 speech at the Mayo Clinic, he claimed ignorance of its source, “a mould spore coming from I don’t know where, dropped on the plate.” But in another speech in Edinburgh that same year, he claimed, “penicillium had dropped through the window.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Hare’s account, the Penicillium came not from the window but the stairwell. In Hare’s 1970 book, he notes how immediately below Fleming’s laboratory, in the same turret of the building, was a mycology lab run by C.J. La Touche. La Touche studied how molds can trigger asthma. He spent much of his time swabbing carpets and curtains in homes inhabited by asthma patients and growing strange and uncommon species of mold from these samples. In the process, he had acquired quite a large collection. But, as Hare recalls from his time working in the same building, La Touche’s lab wasn’t equipped with the fume cupboards or hoods that most mycologists used to prevent mold spores from contaminating the air. As a result, the air in La Touche’s was liable to be full of floating spores, waiting to be carried wherever the breeze might take them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both La Touche and Fleming’s labs had doors that opened to a shared stairwell. It is therefore likely that the spore that contaminated Fleming’s plate had originated in La Touche’s laboratory, having traveled out the door of La Touche’s lab, up the stairs, and into Fleming’s. Yet even if none of La Touche’s spores took this journey, at the very least, La Touche himself did: Fleming cites La Touche as the mycologist who identified the mold as Penicillium.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Theories, Plausible and Implausible&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we approach the 100th anniversary of Fleming’s discovery of penicillin, no definitive answer to this mystery has emerged. Other scientists have proposed a handful of additional theories,13 some of which rely on events even less likely than Hare’s, but Hare and Root-Bernstein’s seem to be rooted in the most solid evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For what it’s worth, I believe Root-Bernstein’s theory. Hare’s is scientifically possible, but it relies on an exceptionally improbable sequence of events requiring luck on the order of picking the correct Powerball numbers three (or more) times in a row. Root-Bernstein’s is simpler and more in tune with the psychology and habits of working scientists. It only requires accepting that Fleming and his colleagues misremembered the identity of an unrecorded and, admittedly, forgettable culture plate from 15 years earlier — which seems entirely plausible. Occam’s razor suggests the simplest explanation is usually the best one, and that is Root-Bernstein’s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The story of Fleming’s discovery of penicillin is not just an interesting historical anecdote; it’s held up as a prime example of momentous inventions discovered by accident. It looms large among discussions about the nature of discovery and how to encourage it. But if Root-Bernstein’s theory is true, and Fleming actually found penicillin while searching for new lysozymes instead of while doing an unrelated staphylococcus experiment, can it really be called an accident?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, penicillin isn’t lysozyme, and a deliberate search for one thing that results in finding something else can still be deemed accidental. Yet, finding a new kind of bacteriolytic substance while looking for a different kind of bacteriolytic substance seems, at least, to be one of a lesser order. Fleming may have been fishing for lysozyme, but his methods — testing strange contaminants for the ability to lyse other microbes — formed a net that, sooner or later, was bound to catch something else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Root-Bernstein’s theory thus turns penicillin from an example of an “accidental discovery” into one that reflects what the computational biologists Itai Yanai and Martin Lercher have described as an “evolutionary process” in scientific research. In this conception, research isn’t a linear march, but an evolutionary tree, full of once-promising branches that proved fruitless and unexpected offshoots that led to new discoveries. Such an evolutionary history, they argue, “is generally obscured in the resulting scientific publication,” which favors neat teleology. &lt;lb/&gt;Fleming’s 1929 penicillin paper may have been written as a linear process, but that’s almost certainly not how the discovery occurred. And by eliminating these complicated twists and turns, Fleming inadvertently obscured what may be one of the most important lessons in scientific history: how combining a meticulous research program with the openness to branch out into new directions led him to Nobel Prize-winning success. Neither rigid plans nor the winds of chance are enough on their own; discovery requires both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, whatever sequence of events actually occurred, what mattered was that Fleming was primed to make the key observation when chance presented it and jumped on what he saw. The rest is history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kevin Blake is a scientific editor at Washington University in the Division of Laboratory and Genomic Medicine. He writes about microbiology, bioinformatics, and evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Header image by Ella Watkins-Dulaney.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cite: Blake, K. “The Penicillin Myth.” Asimov Press (2025). https://doi.org/10.62211/04kq-22ub&lt;lb/&gt;Further reading:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Hare, Ronald. 1970. The Birth of Penicillin, and the Disarming of Microbes. London: Allen &amp;amp; Unwin.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Root-Bernstein, Robert Scott. 1989. Discovering: Inventing and Solving Problems at the Frontiers of Scientific Knowledge. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Macfarlane, Gwyn. 1984. Alexander Fleming: The Man and the Myth. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Rosen, William. 2018. Miracle Cure: The Creation of Antibiotics and the Birth of Modern Medicine. New York, New York: Penguin Books.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reasons why Fleming did not pursue penicillin research further has been attributed to a multiple technical, institutional, and personal reasons, the history of which could be an essay in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because of how they were discovered, transpeptidases were originally named “penicillin binding proteins” (PBPs). However, binding to penicillin is not their normal function, to my great confusion as a microbiology undergraduate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1927, Fleming was the “obvious choice” to write the chapter on staphylococci in the large nine-volume System of Bacteriology. This was generally referred to as “the Bible” in bacteriology labs because it was supposed to contain the whole of existing knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Casting further doubt, Fleming stated in that same paper, that “what had originally been a well-grown staphylococcal colony was now a faint shadow of its former self,” but we now know that is not possible. Fleming’s colleagues have also claimed that was the plate Fleming showed them in September. Yet, here again, no records verify this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not incubating the plate may have been done intentionally. Fleming was known to make “agar art,” pictures on culture plates done by “painting” with colorful bacteria. Though incubation is standard practice because it grows bacteria quickly, it can affect how vivid the colors of the colonies appear. Some suspect Fleming may have deliberately failed to incubate his staphylococci just to see what would happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was before climate control systems and LEED-certified buildings. Though a gas fire kept Fleming’s laboratory warm in the winter, for the rest of the year the temperature could fluctuate violently from the heat of the sun and cold winds from the east and south.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actually, four unlikely events combine. Fleming later claimed that he had already discarded the plate onto a pile in a Lysol bath, and it was only later, while talking with his research scholar, Merlyn Pryce, that he noticed the historic plate, high and dry, and rescued it. Had the pile been cleared away a little sooner, or the antiseptic bath filled a little deeper, then that one-in-a-million plate would have been lost forever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was made aware of Root-Bernstein’s theory, and in turn the entire alternate universe of penicillin theories, by William Rosen’s 2018 book, Miracle Cure: The Creation of Antibiotics and the Birth of Modern Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actually, it has been claimed that, instead of “Eureka!” Fleming muttered the more modest, “that’s funny…”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Hare writes, “what mattered most to Fleming was not the recording of his experiments but his performance.” The absence of lab notebook entries, therefore, is not necessarily evidence that he didn’t run any experiments between September 3rd and October 30th. It could just as well have been that none were interesting enough to be recorded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lecture at Harvard University. Quoted in Joseph Sambrook, David W. Russell, Molecular Cloning (2001), Vol. 1, 153.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gwyn MacFarlane describes a handful of these in his 1984 book, Alexander Fleming: The man and the myth.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46107282</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 13:41:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Penicillin Myth</title><link>https://www.asimov.press/p/penicillin-myth</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="1e0c0b5d326895fd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Penicillin Myth&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Competing theories seek to explain inconsistencies surrounding Alexander Fleming’s famed discovery.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I did not invent penicillin. Nature did that. I only discovered it by accident.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;—Alexander Fleming&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many know the story of Alexander Fleming’s chance discovery of penicillin. Fleming, a bit of an absent-minded professor (and a bit of a slob), left culture plates streaked with Staphylococcus on his lab bench while he went away on summer holiday. When he returned, he found that “a mould” had contaminated one of his plates, probably having floated in from an open window. Before discarding the plate, he noticed that, within a “ring of death” around the mold, the bacteria had disappeared. Something in the “mould juice” had killed the staphylococci.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming immediately began investigating this strange new substance. He identified the mold as Penicillium rubrum and named the substance penicillin.1 He published his findings in the spring of 1929 in The British Journal of Experimental Pathology.2 But a decade later, pharmacologist Howard Florey and biochemist Ernst Chain at Oxford would pick up where Fleming left off. Alongside a USDA lab in Peoria, Illinois, the pair would develop penicillin into a life-saving drug and usher in the era of antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the kind of science story everyone likes. One of serendipity and accidental discovery; a chance observation that changed the world. But is it true?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For decades, scientists and historians have puzzled over inconsistencies in Fleming’s story. For starters, the window to Fleming’s lab was rarely (if ever) left open, precisely to prevent the kind of contamination that supposedly led to penicillin’s discovery. Second, the story is strikingly similar to Fleming’s earlier discovery of lysozyme, another antibacterial substance, which also featured lucky contamination from an open window. Third, Fleming claimed to have discovered the historic culture plate on September 3rd, but the first entry in his lab notebook isn’t dated until October 30th, nearly two months later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last, and most important: penicillin only works if it’s present before the staphylococci. Fleming did not know it at the time, but penicillin interferes with bacterial cell wall synthesis, which only happens when bacteria are actively growing. Visible colonies, however, are composed mostly of mature or dead cells. By the time a colony can be seen, it is often too late for penicillin to have any effect. In fact, the Penicillium mold typically won’t even grow on a plate already filled with staphylococcus colonies. For years, scientists have attempted to replicate Fleming’s original discovery. All have met with failure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thus, it’s difficult to reconcile Fleming’s story with these historical and scientific discrepancies. Did he misremember events from 15 years earlier? Could he have fudged the details to make for a more compelling narrative? Or, might Fleming’s experiment have been subject to an unusual confluence of chance events unbeknownst even to him?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speculation about how Fleming discovered penicillin is of little consequence compared to its practical impact. However, science is about evaluating evidence and moving closer to the “truth.” As we near the 100th anniversary of penicillin’s discovery — which undoubtedly will encourage even greater repetition of the story — it’s in this spirit that we must scrutinize the story’s veracity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The historical and scientific data are limited and often contradictory. Nevertheless, several scientists and historians have worked hard to piece together what facts are certain and fill the gaps with their most probable guesses. The result is a range of competing theories, each attempting to explain what really happened in that St. Mary’s Hospital laboratory in the summer of 1928.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Fleming’s Account&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The story of Fleming’s discovery of penicillin is primarily based on this passage from his 1929 paper:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While working with staphylococcus variants a number of culture-plates were set aside on the laboratory bench and examined from time to time. In the examinations these plates were necessarily exposed to the air and they became contaminated with various micro-organisms. It was noticed that around a large colony of a contaminating mould the staphylococcus colonies became transparent and were obviously undergoing lysis (see Fig. 1).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Fig. 1” refers to a “Photograph of a culture-plate.” It shows separate, well-grown staphylococcus colonies around 2-4 mm in diameter spread across most of the plate’s surface. But on one edge, a large mold colony of about 20 mm in diameter, plus a secondary satellite colony, is clearly visible. This is labeled “Penicillium colony.” Surrounding it is a zone of about 20 mm in which the staphylococcus colonies are either not visible or have become semi-transparent ghosts. Those nearest to the mold are smaller than the rest, only 0.4 to 0.8 mm, while those towards the periphery are a bit larger, 0.8 to 1.7 mm. Fleming has labeled these “Staphylococci undergoing lysis.” Later, Fleming and his colleagues would claim that this was the original contaminated plate from which Penicillium was first isolated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On its face, this seems simple enough. Everyone knows that penicillin destroys bacteria, and Fleming observed staphylococci seemingly being destroyed by a mold that produced penicillin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, upon closer reading of Fleming’s 1929 paper, it becomes clear that a great deal of work was either omitted or inadequately described. There is, for example, no description of the type of culture medium used; whether or not the plate had been incubated; how long it had been on the bench; and, most important of all, what species of Staphylococcus was being studied.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When publishing a scientific paper, scientists are expected to include a detailed description of their methods alongside their results. Like a recipe, these methods should clearly and comprehensively describe the materials used and the steps taken so that other scientists can replicate the experiment. And while incomplete or poorly-described methods are a perennial problem, the omission of these key experimental details (even in a report on an accidental discovery) is surprising.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This became a problem when, as interest in penicillin grew, other investigators tried to repeat Fleming’s discovery. In 1944, Margaret Jennings (who later married a long-time colleague and penicillin researcher, Howard Florey) spread purified penicillin onto plates of fully grown staphylococci. This should have had a more potent effect than Fleming’s pictured in Figure 1, which was allegedly produced only with the crude “mould juice” from an accidental contaminant. Jennings, however, observed no visible change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1965, the pathologist W.D. Foster attempted a similar experiment using penicillin crystals dropped directly onto staphylococcus colonies, creating “astronomical” concentrations within their vicinity. But still, the colonies remained unaffected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other attempts at replication called into question whether the mold could have even grown on a plate full of staphylococci. Pharmacologist D.B. Colquhoun claimed that, in 1955, he found that Penicillium mold refused to grow on a plate already full of staphylococcus colonies. Or, that, if it did, it produced no visible effect on the colonies. He could, however, see an effect if the sequence of events was reversed: if the mold was allowed to grow for several days first, and the staphylococci was later inoculated onto the plate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although these failures are hard to reconcile with Fleming’s account, they are in line with what we now know about the biology of penicillin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1940, the physician A.D. Gardner, researching alongside Florey, peered into his microscope to examine how penicillin affected individual bacterial cells. Surprisingly, adult cells seemed to be largely unaffected; however, when they divided, the young cells grew “as immense swollen filaments.” Like party balloons, they elongated and expanded, then popped.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The morphological changes,” observed bacteriologist J.P. Duguid in 1946, “suggest that penicillin in these concentrations interferes specifically with the formation of the outer supporting cell wall, while otherwise allowing growth to proceed until the organism finally bursts its defective envelope and so undergoes lysis.” At the time, this was largely speculation. Not much was known about the biology of bacterial cell walls. But after a decade of study — motivated in no small part by a desire to understand how penicillin worked — this hypothesis has largely been proven correct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bacterial cell wall is a rigid, mesh-like structure composed primarily of peptidoglycan, a large macromolecule consisting of small subunits cross-linked by specialized enzymes called transpeptidases. The job of the cell wall is to maintain the cell’s shape and keep it from absorbing too much water. If the outward pressure from the cell’s contents becomes too great for the delicate cell membrane to contain, it bursts, spilling the cell’s innards. The cell wall, like a heavy-duty bicycle tire around a rubber inner tube, helps to resist this pressure, protecting the cell from mechanical stresses both inside and out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike a bike tire, however, cell walls need to be able to grow with the cells they enclose. To accommodate increasing cell size, bacteria are continuously breaking and rebuilding the peptidoglycan mesh. This is where penicillin comes in. Because penicillin has a similar chemical structure to a peptidoglycan subunit, it can bind to the transpeptidases that complete the final step in cell wall biosynthesis.3 When this happens, penicillin forms a covalent bond in the transpeptidase’s active site, irreversibly inactivating the enzyme. As it grows, the cell continues to disassemble its cell wall, but without the use of its transpeptidases, it can no longer rebuild it. Over time, the cell wall weakens and eventually bursts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This explains why Jennings and others couldn’t replicate Fleming’s contaminated plate. A mature colony is mostly composed of adult or dead cells. These cells are unaffected by penicillin because they aren’t actively growing, and so aren’t actively breaking and rebuilding their cell wall. As a result, penicillin doesn’t cause mature cells to lyse, and the colony’s overall appearance doesn’t change. But if the penicillin is present before the staphylococci, it prevents the bacteria from growing and dividing, or they do so much more slowly. When that happens, they don’t form visible colonies. Thus, penicillin does not dissolve fully grown colonies, as Fleming had initially assumed, but inhibits their growth from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The difficulty replicating Fleming’s discovery is frustrated by the ease with which it’s possible to “rediscover” penicillin by reversing the order of growth. By first growing Penicillium mold until it becomes a large colony, then seeding the plate with staphylococci, the result is indistinguishable from Fleming’s original plate. However, no trained scientist would intentionally use a culture plate visibly contaminated with a large mold — and certainly not an expert bacteriologist like Fleming.4&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are no contemporary records to corroborate the story that Fleming discovered the contaminated culture plate when he returned from holiday on September 3rd: no lab notebook records, calendar notes, diary entries, or any letters. In the 1929 paper, the figure is simply labeled, “Photograph of a culture-plate.” The only evidence we have stems from recollections by Fleming and colleagues years later, after penicillin was recognized as a runaway clinical success. Fleming himself described the Figure 1 plate as the “original culture plate” in a 1944 paper. Yet, he also included the disclaimer that “after a lapse of fifteen years it is very difficult to say just what processes of thought were involved.”5&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The earliest recorded mention of the mold and penicillin is an experiment written in Fleming’s lab notebook dated October 30th, 1928 — nearly two months after he purportedly found the culture plate. Curiously, it does not describe the chance discovery of a contaminant, but a carefully constructed experiment that suggests Fleming had already spent some time isolating and characterizing the mold. In it, Fleming used the reversed-sequence culturing method: first, placing a mold spore on the plate and letting it grow into a large, penicillin-producing colony, then inoculating several pathogenic species of bacteria, including staphylococci, near the mold.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On October 30th, Fleming recorded the results: the mold affected a whole host of pathogens, including staphylococci, which could not grow near the mold. It’s a fine experiment, but it’s clearly not the discovery of an accidentally contaminated culture plate. This raises the question: What was Fleming doing for the previous two months, and if he was working with penicillin, why didn’t he bother recording any of it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For decades, these scientific inconsistencies and experimental failures have haunted the story of penicillin’s discovery. Amidst the incontrovertible Nobel Prize-winning scientific and clinical success of penicillin — and without a plausible alternative — the doubters kept quiet. At least, most of them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Ronald Hare’s Theory (1970)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1964, the bacteriologist Ronald Hare took up the puzzle of penicillin’s origins. After examining old lab notebooks and conducting experiments of his own, he would conclude that “the history of both the culture plate and the mould itself must have been very different from what had previously been thought to be the case.” Hare published his own theory on penicillin’s discovery in his 1970 book, The Birth of Penicillin, and the Disarming of Microbes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare was uniquely positioned to investigate this mystery. Not only was he an accomplished bacteriologist and expert on penicillin, having spent 20 years as a Professor of Bacteriology at the University of London, and the ten years before that at the University of Toronto, where he was largely responsible for planning and building the Canadian Government’s penicillin plant; he started his career in the same department as Fleming at St. Mary’s. In fact, he claims to have been in the laboratory the very day Fleming discovered the now-famous culture plate. (Despite this close professional association, however, Hare claims to have played no part in the discovery or original research on penicillin nor to have discussed them with Fleming.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although that discovery is now regarded as one of the most significant scientific events of the 20th century, Hare admits that, at the time, it made little to no impression on him or any of his colleagues. “The rest of us, being engaged in researches that seemed far more important than a contaminated culture plate, merely glanced at it, thought that it was no more than another wonder that Fleming seemed to be forever unearthing, and promptly forgot all about it.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yet, Hare had been skeptical from the start that penicillin could have been discovered by simple contamination of a culture plate. It was such a common occurrence in biology laboratories that “if this had been the sequence of events, penicillin would probably have been discovered while Fleming was still a child.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After retirement, Hare took up the penicillin question. He began by attempting to replicate Fleming’s discovery. He seeded an ordinary culture plate with staphylococci, incubated it until colonies were visible, then placed a few mold spores on the surface. As the microbiologists before him had observed, the mold refused to grow. He tried coaxing the mold’s growth by plating it further and further away from any staphylococcal colonies (without deviating too far from the overall appearance of Fleming’s Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this approach, he was finally able to get the mold to grow and produce penicillin, but still the staphylococcal colonies were unaffected. “No one looking at such a plate could possibly guess that a powerful antibacterial substance was emanating from the mould.” If, however, he reversed the order and plated the mold before the staphylococci, he could get a result “almost indistinguishable from that of Fleming’s original plate.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vexed, Hare reevaluated the evidence. He had shown the mold couldn’t have contaminated the plate after the staphylococci because the mold wouldn’t grow (or, if it did, the penicillin wouldn’t affect the staphylococcus colonies). He assumed that the contamination couldn’t have occurred before the staphylococci (though that reliably recreates the plate pictured) because no bacteriologist would knowingly use a contaminated plate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What if the mold contaminated the plate at the same time, or within a few hours, of when it was seeded with staphylococci? And what if the staphylococci’s growth had been paused (somehow) until the mold colony had matured? To Fleming’s eyes, he would have assumed he had inoculated staphylococci onto a contamination-free culture plate. Yet, with the staphylococci’s growth delayed, the mold would have had time to fully develop into a large, penicillin-producing colony. When the staphylococci’s growth was restarted, it would be growing in effectively the same conditions as if it had been plated after the mold had grown.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare knew just the thing that could arrest the staphylococci’s growth: low temperature. Staphylococci grow most rapidly at 98.6 °F (37 °C). As a human pathogen, it has evolved to grow optimally at human body temperature. This is why microbiologists incubate culture plates: to speed up their growth into visible colonies. The lowest temperature at which any staphylococci growth occurs, and then only very slowly, is around 53 °F (12 °C). The Penicillium mold, on the other hand, prefers to grow around 77 °F (25 °C) but is not greatly affected by temperature ranges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It therefore seemed possible that penicillin could have been discovered as described in the original 1929 paper, but with the addition a few details Fleming was unaware of: first, the inoculation of staphylococci and contamination by mold occurred at the same time; second, Fleming forgot6 to incubate the plate; and third, the lab’s room temperature was low enough for long enough for the mold to grow and produce penicillin before the staphylococci began to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To test this theory, Hare simultaneously inoculated a culture plate with both staphylococci and Fleming’s mold and left it on his benchtop. The weather that day was cold, wet, and stormy, and the temperature was relatively low: 61 to 65 °F (16.1 to 18.3 °C). As expected, the staphylococci grew more slowly than they would have in an incubator, and only tiny transparent colonies were visible on the third day. The mold, however, grew much more prolifically, and a tiny colony was visible after just 48 hours, growing to 10 mm by the fourth day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the end of the fifth day, Hare had rediscovered penicillin. The result was practically indistinguishable from the photo in Fleming’s original paper: in a ten millimeter zone around the mold, the staphylococcus colonies were small and transparent, while those outside the zone were larger and opaque. Many experiments later, Hare found that penicillin could reliably be rediscovered in this manner so long as the temperature was kept below 68 °F (20 °C) for four or five days.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where Hare the scientist had to become Hare the historian. Was the temperature in Fleming’s laboratory low enough for him to discover penicillin at the end of July or the beginning of August in accordance with the timeline of his canonical story?7&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare searched the records at the Meteorological Office for the maximum and minimum shade temperatures from the beginning of July to the end of September, 1928. In the weeks before Fleming left on holiday there was a heatwave; from July 10th to 27th, there were highs in the upper 70s and 80s. At these temperatures, the staphylococci would have grown too quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, on the 28th, the heatwave ended and was quickly replaced by a cold snap. For the next nine days, the maximum temperature only exceeded 68 °F on two occasions, and not by much. It was a slim window, in which the temperature in Fleming’s laboratory would have been low enough. But it coincided perfectly with Fleming’s holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare’s theory relies on a triple chance of unlikely events. First, the penicillin-producing Penicillium mold landed on Fleming’s culture plate; second, Fleming failed to incubate the plate; and third, the temperature was low enough for the five days required to favor mold growth.8 “Had only one link in this chain been broken,” Hare writes. “Fleming would have missed his opportunity.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare himself concedes that the combination of these contingencies seems exceptionally unlikely. The original story of chance discovery, on its own, was one of serendipity and good fortune. His theory required an additional layer of meteorological luck on top of chance contamination. “Far from the phenomenon that led to the discovery being a comparatively common event that had previously escaped detection, it must be so unusual an occurrence that it is doubtful whether it can have happened very often since bacteria were first cultivated in the laboratory.” Yet, however improbable it may seem, to quote Sherlock Holmes: “When you have eliminated all which is impossible, then whatever remains, however improbable, must be the truth.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Robert Root-Bernstein’s Theory (1989)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hare’s theory is based on the assumption that the Figure 1 plate was indeed the source of the original contamination. It also overlooks the two-month gap between when Fleming allegedly noticed the contaminated plate and recorded the first penicillin experiment. These details, however, form the foundation of a competing theory on penicillin’s origins — that belonging to Robert Root-Bernstein, Professor of Physiology at Michigan State University.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Root-Bernstein described his theory in his 1989 book, Discovering: Inventing and Solving Problems at the Frontiers of Science.9 It’s an ambitious and unorthodox book, structured as a seminar between six characters discussing creativity and the scientific process. Each character represents various points of view on the sciences and scientists and, along the way, they also discuss the important chronological and methodological idiosyncrasies of Fleming’s discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Root-Bernstein’s theory is argued and defended by the character Imp (real name Ernest; apparently a stand-in for the author himself). After summarizing the key details of Hare’s theory, Imp focuses on the two-month gap. Fleming supposedly discovered the Fig. 1 contaminated plate when he returned from a holiday on September 3rd, but the first lab notebook entry about Penicillium and penicillin wasn’t written until October 30th. As described earlier, that entry does not record the discovery of a contaminated plate but a planned experiment in which the Penicillium mold was first isolated and tested against several bacteria, including staphylococci.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But why, Imp wonders, if Fleming already had that beautiful culture plate which so perfectly illustrated the staphylococci-killing power of penicillin, he would wait two months to record the finding? And why do so in the context of another experiment? Furthermore, this plate still exists within the British Museum. That means Fleming had to fix it with formaldehyde relatively soon after he found it. But if he thought the plate was important enough to preserve, why didn’t he note its discovery at the time?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It wasn’t in Fleming’s character to procrastinate. According to his research scholar, Merlyn Pryce: “[Fleming] didn’t confine himself to observing, but took action at once. Lots of people observe a phenomenon, feeling that it may be important, but they don’t get beyond being surprised — after which, they forget. That was never the case with Fleming.” So then, what was he doing for two months?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s in this context that Imp (Root-Bernstein) grounds his belief that Fleming’s discovery wasn’t the serendipitous chance of lore — at least, not completely. Instead, he proposes that Fleming wasn’t running a staphylococcus experiment when he discovered penicillin; he was looking for new sources of lysozyme.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming had a long-standing professional interest in antibacterial substances. His most important discovery before penicillin was the lysozymes, enzymes found in various bodily fluids (e.g., tears, saliva, and egg whites) that break down the cell walls of bacteria. He had also studied the antibacterial properties of mercuric chloride and bacteriophages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Between 1922 and 1928, Fleming’s team tested anything they could get their hands on: human mucus, tears, sputum, and blood; the eggs of dozens of fish and bird species; tears collected from horses, cows, hens, ducks, geese, and fifty other species from the London Zoo; earthworm and snail slime; large numbers of vegetables and flowers. They continued to publish on lysozymes into the 1930s. “Is it too much to suggest,” Imp asked, “that he also examined any fungus that happened to come his way?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we assume that Fleming was engaged in a systematic search for new sources of lysozyme, we can now reasonably fill in the gap between September 3rd, when he first spots the mold, and October 30th, when he first records the Penicillium experiment. Root-Bernstein’s theory about the discovery goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, Fleming begins by finding the mold, which may or may not have been on a staphylococcus plate. In the paper, Fleming only says that he found it at the time he was “working with staphylococcus variants.” Either way, the plate is not enough to incite a “Eureka!” moment, as the canonical version of the story suggests.10 Instead, like the hundreds of other unusual samples he’s tested, Fleming transfers the mold to a new culture plate, gives it a few days to establish itself, and then runs a routine experiment to test for lysozyme activity. He finds that it weakly affects a lysozyme-sensitive strain. Not terribly interesting — not even worth recording11 — but it warrants a follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A short time later, the Root-Bernstein theory goes, Fleming prepares a second experiment. After growing the mold for five days into a robust colony, he adds various lysozyme-sensitive and -resistant species to the plate, including Staphylococcus. This time, he records the results because (surprise!) the mold affects the lysozyme-resistant staphylococci. This experiment, whose results are recorded on October 30th, is exactly what it appears to be within the context of Fleming’s notebooks: “the first penicillin experiment — the first recognition by Fleming that he’s dealing with something unexpected and exciting!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet, if this is the true sequence of events, why didn’t Fleming record it as such in his 1929 paper? “The logic of presentation rarely corresponds to the logic of discovery,” said Imp. Few scientists actually document the chronological sequence of events that led to their discovery. “Just imagine for a moment trying to write into a research paper the account I’ve just given,” said Imp:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While looking essentially randomly for organisms producing lysozyme, a common but unidentified mold was isolated from the air of the laboratory. Initial experiments showed that the mold appeared to have lysozyme activity, so controls were set up, including staphylococci, which I just happened to have been working on at the time. Much to my surprise, the mold had unexpected properties, so I was now forced to further characterize and identify the mold …This subsequent research conclusively demonstrated that the product of the mold was not lysozyme, but rather a new substance having the following characteristics …&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s too circuitous and indirect for a scientific report. Better, instead, to start with the mold lysing the pathogen, because that was the important and novel observation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under this theory of events, the Figure 1 plate also becomes exactly what it appears to be in its proper context: an illustrative example of the fact that penicillin-secreting Penicillium can kill staphylococci. Not, as the story is typically told, the original contaminated plate. Reading further in the paper, similar examples are included as Figures 3 and 4, which illustrate other properties of penicillin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming still could have shown his colleagues a contaminated staphylococcus plate on September 3rd, but one which must not have had the telltale “ring of death.” Or perhaps he did pass around the plate that would become the famous Figure 1, but not until several months later, when he was preparing figures for his paper. Hare’s cold snap, too, may have played a role in the mold growing when it did, but it no longer has to coincide with Fleming inoculating his staphylococcus plate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That Fleming was originally searching for new sources of lysozyme could also explain why he thought the mold contaminated a staphylococcus plate after the colonies had fully grown (which, barring Hare’s theory of simultaneous contamination, should be impossible). Penicillin may not be able to lyse mature colonies, but lysozymes can. Fleming may have assumed penicillin lyses bacteria the same way as lysozymes, and therefore could lyse mature colonies. It’s a conceptual leap, but one made smaller if he was looking for lysozymes in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like Hare, Root-Bernstein does not claim his account of Fleming’s discovery is “true,” only that it’s compatible with available data. (Root-Bernstein does not, however, shy away from claiming that his theory is the more likely of the two. “Hare may be a good bacteriologist,” said Imp, “but I question his historical acumen. Dates — you’ve got to pay attention to dates.”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More important to Root-Bernstein than the specifics of Fleming’s discovery is the fact that it evidences Pasteur’s principle that “chance favors only the prepared mind.” Whether he was experimenting with staphylococci or lysozyme, Fleming kept his mind open to the possibility of discovering new bacteriolytic substances. He often gave the advice, “Never neglect an extraordinary appearance or happening. It may be — usually is, in fact — a false alarm that leads to nothing, but may on the other hand be the clue provided by fate to lead you to some important advance.”12&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming’s methods — which included testing strange samples and keeping plates around for longer than he needed them — increased the probability that he would stumble upon something new, and he was mentally prepared to recognize them when he did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Source of the Mold&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other important aspect of Fleming’s discovery is the source of the contaminating mold. According to the canonical version of the story, the Penicillium floated into Fleming’s lab from an open window. However, no such claim was made in the 1929 paper. In fact, nothing about its source was said until 1945 when Fleming told the writer George Lacken that it had blown through the window from Praed Street.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why Fleming would say this is a mystery. He had no evidence that was the case, and as Hare writes, opening a laboratory window is “thoroughly bad bacteriology.” Further, Fleming’s windowsill was often piled high with test tubes and beakers filled with pathogenic bacteria. It would have created quite a scandal should any of these have fallen out of an open window onto the heads of the vulnerable passersby below. Nevertheless, the story gained wide publicity after André Maurois repeated it in his 1959 biography, The Life of Sir Alexander Fleming. Maurois repeatedly referred to “the mysterious mould from Praed Street,” and “the spore carried by the wind.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fleming himself seemed unsure of its origins. In a 1946 speech at the Mayo Clinic, he claimed ignorance of its source, “a mould spore coming from I don’t know where, dropped on the plate.” But in another speech in Edinburgh that same year, he claimed, “penicillium had dropped through the window.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Hare’s account, the Penicillium came not from the window but the stairwell. In Hare’s 1970 book, he notes how immediately below Fleming’s laboratory, in the same turret of the building, was a mycology lab run by C.J. La Touche. La Touche studied how molds can trigger asthma. He spent much of his time swabbing carpets and curtains in homes inhabited by asthma patients and growing strange and uncommon species of mold from these samples. In the process, he had acquired quite a large collection. But, as Hare recalls from his time working in the same building, La Touche’s lab wasn’t equipped with the fume cupboards or hoods that most mycologists used to prevent mold spores from contaminating the air. As a result, the air in La Touche’s was liable to be full of floating spores, waiting to be carried wherever the breeze might take them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both La Touche and Fleming’s labs had doors that opened to a shared stairwell. It is therefore likely that the spore that contaminated Fleming’s plate had originated in La Touche’s laboratory, having traveled out the door of La Touche’s lab, up the stairs, and into Fleming’s. Yet even if none of La Touche’s spores took this journey, at the very least, La Touche himself did: Fleming cites La Touche as the mycologist who identified the mold as Penicillium.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Theories, Plausible and Implausible&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we approach the 100th anniversary of Fleming’s discovery of penicillin, no definitive answer to this mystery has emerged. Other scientists have proposed a handful of additional theories,13 some of which rely on events even less likely than Hare’s, but Hare and Root-Bernstein’s seem to be rooted in the most solid evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For what it’s worth, I believe Root-Bernstein’s theory. Hare’s is scientifically possible, but it relies on an exceptionally improbable sequence of events requiring luck on the order of picking the correct Powerball numbers three (or more) times in a row. Root-Bernstein’s is simpler and more in tune with the psychology and habits of working scientists. It only requires accepting that Fleming and his colleagues misremembered the identity of an unrecorded and, admittedly, forgettable culture plate from 15 years earlier — which seems entirely plausible. Occam’s razor suggests the simplest explanation is usually the best one, and that is Root-Bernstein’s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The story of Fleming’s discovery of penicillin is not just an interesting historical anecdote; it’s held up as a prime example of momentous inventions discovered by accident. It looms large among discussions about the nature of discovery and how to encourage it. But if Root-Bernstein’s theory is true, and Fleming actually found penicillin while searching for new lysozymes instead of while doing an unrelated staphylococcus experiment, can it really be called an accident?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, penicillin isn’t lysozyme, and a deliberate search for one thing that results in finding something else can still be deemed accidental. Yet, finding a new kind of bacteriolytic substance while looking for a different kind of bacteriolytic substance seems, at least, to be one of a lesser order. Fleming may have been fishing for lysozyme, but his methods — testing strange contaminants for the ability to lyse other microbes — formed a net that, sooner or later, was bound to catch something else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Root-Bernstein’s theory thus turns penicillin from an example of an “accidental discovery” into one that reflects what the computational biologists Itai Yanai and Martin Lercher have described as an “evolutionary process” in scientific research. In this conception, research isn’t a linear march, but an evolutionary tree, full of once-promising branches that proved fruitless and unexpected offshoots that led to new discoveries. Such an evolutionary history, they argue, “is generally obscured in the resulting scientific publication,” which favors neat teleology. &lt;lb/&gt;Fleming’s 1929 penicillin paper may have been written as a linear process, but that’s almost certainly not how the discovery occurred. And by eliminating these complicated twists and turns, Fleming inadvertently obscured what may be one of the most important lessons in scientific history: how combining a meticulous research program with the openness to branch out into new directions led him to Nobel Prize-winning success. Neither rigid plans nor the winds of chance are enough on their own; discovery requires both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, whatever sequence of events actually occurred, what mattered was that Fleming was primed to make the key observation when chance presented it and jumped on what he saw. The rest is history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kevin Blake is a scientific editor at Washington University in the Division of Laboratory and Genomic Medicine. He writes about microbiology, bioinformatics, and evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Header image by Ella Watkins-Dulaney.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cite: Blake, K. “The Penicillin Myth.” Asimov Press (2025). https://doi.org/10.62211/04kq-22ub&lt;lb/&gt;Further reading:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Hare, Ronald. 1970. The Birth of Penicillin, and the Disarming of Microbes. London: Allen &amp;amp; Unwin.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Root-Bernstein, Robert Scott. 1989. Discovering: Inventing and Solving Problems at the Frontiers of Scientific Knowledge. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Macfarlane, Gwyn. 1984. Alexander Fleming: The Man and the Myth. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Rosen, William. 2018. Miracle Cure: The Creation of Antibiotics and the Birth of Modern Medicine. New York, New York: Penguin Books.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reasons why Fleming did not pursue penicillin research further has been attributed to a multiple technical, institutional, and personal reasons, the history of which could be an essay in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because of how they were discovered, transpeptidases were originally named “penicillin binding proteins” (PBPs). However, binding to penicillin is not their normal function, to my great confusion as a microbiology undergraduate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 1927, Fleming was the “obvious choice” to write the chapter on staphylococci in the large nine-volume System of Bacteriology. This was generally referred to as “the Bible” in bacteriology labs because it was supposed to contain the whole of existing knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Casting further doubt, Fleming stated in that same paper, that “what had originally been a well-grown staphylococcal colony was now a faint shadow of its former self,” but we now know that is not possible. Fleming’s colleagues have also claimed that was the plate Fleming showed them in September. Yet, here again, no records verify this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not incubating the plate may have been done intentionally. Fleming was known to make “agar art,” pictures on culture plates done by “painting” with colorful bacteria. Though incubation is standard practice because it grows bacteria quickly, it can affect how vivid the colors of the colonies appear. Some suspect Fleming may have deliberately failed to incubate his staphylococci just to see what would happen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was before climate control systems and LEED-certified buildings. Though a gas fire kept Fleming’s laboratory warm in the winter, for the rest of the year the temperature could fluctuate violently from the heat of the sun and cold winds from the east and south.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actually, four unlikely events combine. Fleming later claimed that he had already discarded the plate onto a pile in a Lysol bath, and it was only later, while talking with his research scholar, Merlyn Pryce, that he noticed the historic plate, high and dry, and rescued it. Had the pile been cleared away a little sooner, or the antiseptic bath filled a little deeper, then that one-in-a-million plate would have been lost forever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was made aware of Root-Bernstein’s theory, and in turn the entire alternate universe of penicillin theories, by William Rosen’s 2018 book, Miracle Cure: The Creation of Antibiotics and the Birth of Modern Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actually, it has been claimed that, instead of “Eureka!” Fleming muttered the more modest, “that’s funny…”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Hare writes, “what mattered most to Fleming was not the recording of his experiments but his performance.” The absence of lab notebook entries, therefore, is not necessarily evidence that he didn’t run any experiments between September 3rd and October 30th. It could just as well have been that none were interesting enough to be recorded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lecture at Harvard University. Quoted in Joseph Sambrook, David W. Russell, Molecular Cloning (2001), Vol. 1, 153.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gwyn MacFarlane describes a handful of these in his 1984 book, Alexander Fleming: The man and the myth.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46107658</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 14:13:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netflix Kills Casting from Its Mobile App to Most Modern TVs</title><link>https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/01/netflix-kills-casting-from-mobile-app-to-tvs/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="eca0a95555261bd4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Netflix Kills Casting From Its Mobile App to Most Modern TVs&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Netflix has quietly removed the ability to cast content from its mobile apps to most modern TVs and streaming devices, including newer Chromecast models and the Google TV Streamer.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;The change was first spotted by users on Reddit and confirmed in an updated Netflix support page (via Android Authority), which now states that the streaming service no longer supports casting from mobile devices to most TVs and TV-streaming devices. Users are instead directed to use the remote that came with their TV hardware and use its native Netflix app.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The only exception appears to apply to older Chromecast models without remotes, as well as TVs with built-in Google Cast support. However, even on these legacy devices, casting only remains for those on costlier ad-free plans, but it is unavailable for subscribers on Netflix's ad-supported plan.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;User reports appear to suggest Netflix began removing the Cast button from its mobile apps in mid-November, but the company provided no advance warning to users. One Reddit user said customer service explained that devices with remotes can no longer cast, claiming the decision was made to improve the customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;The move bears similarities to Netflix's 2019 decision to remove AirPlay support from its iOS app, citing an inability to distinguish between different AirPlay-enabled devices (i.e., what is an Apple TV vs. what isn't) as Apple expanded the technology to third-party TVs.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Popular Stories&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple recently teamed up with Japanese fashion brand ISSEY MIYAKE to create the iPhone Pocket, a limited-edition knitted accessory designed to carry an iPhone. However, it is now completely sold out in all countries where it was released. iPhone Pocket became available to order on Apple's online store starting Friday, November 14, in the United States, France, China, Italy, Japan, Singapore, ...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;While all Macs are now powered by Apple's custom-designed chips, a new rumor claims that Apple may rekindle its partnership with Intel, albeit in a new and limited way. Apple supply chain analyst Ming-Chi Kuo today said Intel is expected to begin shipping Apple's lowest-end M-series chip as early as mid-2027. Kuo said Apple plans to utilize Intel's 18A process, which is the "earliest...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Cellular carriers have always offered big savings on the newest iPhone models during the holidays, and Black Friday 2025 sales have kicked off at AT&amp;amp;T, Verizon, T-Mobile, and more. Right now we're tracking notable offers on the iPhone 17, iPhone 17 Pro, iPhone 17 Pro Max, and iPhone Air. For even more savings, keep an eye on older models during the holiday shopping season. Note: MacRumors is...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple's online store is going down for a few hours on a rolling country-by-country basis right now, but do not get your hopes up for new products. Apple takes its online store down for a few hours ahead of Black Friday every year to tease/prepare for its annual gift card offer with the purchase of select products. The store already went down and came back online in Australia and New Zealand, ...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;We've been focusing on deals on physical products over the past few weeks, but Black Friday is also a great time of year to purchase a streaming membership. Some of the biggest services have great discounts for new and select returning members this week, including Apple TV, Disney+, Hulu, Paramount+, Peacock, and more. Note: MacRumors is an affiliate partner with some of these vendors. When...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Cyber Monday is here, and you can find popular Apple products like AirPods, iPad, Apple Watch, and more at all-time low prices. In this article, the majority of the discounts will be found on Amazon. Note: MacRumors is an affiliate partner with some of these vendors. When you click a link and make a purchase, we may receive a small payment, which helps us keep the site running....&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Apple's disappointing iPhone Air sales are causing major Chinese mobile vendors to scrap or freeze their own ultra-thin phone projects, according to reports coming out of Asia. Since the iPhone Air launched in September, there have been reports of poor sales and manufacturing cuts, while Apple's supply chain has scaled back shipments and production. Apple supplier Foxconn has...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The updated specs of the M5 iPad Pro may point toward a major new feature for Apple's next-generation Studio Display expected in early 2026. Apple's latest iPad Pro debuted last month and contains one display-related change that stands out: it can now drive external monitors at up to 120Hz with Adaptive Sync. The feature should deliver lower latency, smoother motion, and fewer visual...&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46108106</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 14:50:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>WordPress plugin quirk resulted in UK Gov OBR Budget leak [pdf]</title><link>https://obr.uk/docs/dlm_uploads/01122025-Investigation-into-November-2025-EFO-publication-error.pdf</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46108243</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 15:00:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google, Nvidia, and OpenAI – Stratechery by Ben Thompson</title><link>https://stratechery.com/2025/google-nvidia-and-openai/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3aa0904099a625b7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Listen to this post:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A common explanation as to why Star Wars was such a hit, and continues to resonate nearly half a century on from its release, is that it is a nearly perfect representation of the hero’s journey. You have Luke, bored on Tatooine, called to adventure by a mysterious message borne by R2-D2, that he initially refuses; a mentor in Obi-Wan Kenobi leads him across the threshold of leaving Tatooine and facing tests while finding new enemies and allies. He enters the cave — the Death Star — escapes after the ordeal of Obi-Wan’s death, and carries the battle station’s plans to the rebels while preparing for the road back to the Death Star. He trusts the force in his final test and returns transformed. And, when you zoom out to the entire original trilogy, it’s simply an expanded version of the story: this time, however, the ordeal is the entire second movie: the Empire Strikes Back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The heroes of the AI story over the last three years have been two companies: OpenAI and Nvidia. The first is a startup called, with the release of ChatGPT, to be the next great consumer tech company; the other was best known as a gaming chip company characterized by boom-and-bust cycles driven by their visionary and endlessly optimistic founder, transformed into the most essential infrastructure provider for the AI revolution. Over the last two weeks, however, both have entered the cave and are facing their greatest ordeal: the Google empire is very much striking back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Google Strikes Back&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first Google blow was Gemini 3, which scored better than OpenAI’s state of the art model on a host of benchmarks (even if actual real-world usage was a bit more uneven). Gemini 3’s biggest advantage is its sheer size and the vast amount of compute that went into creating it; this is notable because OpenAI has had difficulty creating the next generation of models beyond the GPT-4 level of size and complexity. What has carried the company is a genuine breakthrough in reasoning that produces better results in many cases, but at the cost of time and money.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gemini 3’s success seemed like good news for Nvidia, who I listed as a winner from the release:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is maybe the most interesting one. Nvidia, which reports earnings later today, is on one hand a loser, because the best model in the world was not trained on their chips, proving once and for all that it is possible to be competitive without paying Nvidia’s premiums.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there are two reasons for Nvidia optimism. The first is that everyone needs to respond to Gemini, and they need to respond now, not at some future date when their chips are good enough. Google started its work on TPUs a decade ago; everyone else is better off sticking with Nvidia, at least if they want to catch up. Secondly, and relatedly, Gemini re-affirms that the most important factor in catching up — or moving ahead — is more compute.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This analysis, however, missed one important point: what if Google sold its TPUs as an alternative to Nvidia? That’s exactly what the search giant is doing, first with a deal with Anthropic, then a rumored deal with Meta, and third with the second wave of neoclouds, many of which started as crypto miners and are leveraging their access to power to move into AI. Suddenly it is Nvidia that is in the crosshairs, with fresh questions about their long term growth, particularly at their sky-high margins, if there were in fact a legitimate competitor to their chips. This does, needless to say, raise the pressure on OpenAI’s next pre-training, run on Nvidia’s Blackwell chips: the base model still matters, and OpenAI needs a better one, and Nvidia needs evidence one can be created on their chips.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is interesting to consider is which company is more at risk from Google, and why? On one hand Nvidia is making tons of money, and if Blackwell is good, Vera Rubin promises to be even better; moreover, while Meta might be a natural Google partner, the other hyperscalers are not. OpenAI, meanwhile, is losing more money than ever, and is spread thinner than ever, even as the startup agrees to buy ever more compute with revenue that doesn’t yet exist. And yet, despite all that — and while still being quite bullish on Nvidia — I still like OpenAI’s chances more. Indeed, if anything my biggest concern is that I seem to like OpenAI’s chances better than OpenAI itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Nvidia’s Moats&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you go back a year or two, you might make the case that Nvidia had three moats relative to TPUs: superior performance, significantly more flexibility due to GPUs being more general purpose than TPUs, and CUDA and the associated developer ecosystem surrounding it. OpenAI, meanwhile, had the best model, extensive usage of their API, and the massive number of consumers using ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The question, then, is what happens if the first differentiator for each company goes away? That, in a nutshell, is the question that has been raised over the last two weeks: does Nvidia preserve its advantages if TPUs are as good as GPUs, and is OpenAI viable in the long run if they don’t have the unquestioned best model?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nvidia’s flexibility advantage is a real thing; it’s not an accident that the fungibility of GPUs across workloads was focused on as a justification for increased capital expenditures by both Microsoft and Meta. TPUs are more specialized at the hardware level, and more difficult to program for at the software level; to that end, to the extent that customers care about flexibility, then Nvidia remains the obvious choice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CUDA, meanwhile, has long been a critical source of Nvidia lock-in, both because of the low level access it gives developers, and also because there is a developer network effect: you’re just more likely to be able to hire low level engineers if your stack is on Nvidia. The challenge for Nvidia, however, is that the “big company” effect could play out with CUDA in the opposite way to the flexibility argument. While big companies like the hyperscalers have the diversity of workloads to benefit from the flexibility of GPUs, they also have the wherewithal to build an alternative software stack. That they did not do so for a long time is a function of it simply not being worth the time and trouble; when capital expenditure plans reach the hundreds of billions of dollars, however what is “worth” the time and trouble changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A useful analogy here is the rise of AMD in the datacenter. That rise has not occurred in on-premises installations or the government, which is still dominated by Intel; rather, large hyperscalers found it worth their time and effort to rewrite extremely low level software to be truly agnostic between AMD and Intel, allowing the former’s lead in performance to win the battle. In this case, the challenge Nvidia faces is that its market is a relatively small number of highly concentrated customers, with the resources — mostly as yet unutilized — to break down the CUDA wall, as they already did in terms of Intel’s differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s clear that Nvidia has been concerned about this for a long time; this is from Nvidia Waves and Moats, written at the absolute top of the Nvidia hype cycle after the 2024 introduction of Blackwell:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This takes this Article full circle: in the before-times, i.e. before the release of ChatGPT, Nvidia was building quite the (free) software moat around its GPUs; the challenge is that it wasn’t entirely clear who was going to use all of that software. Today, meanwhile, the use cases for those GPUs is very clear, and those use cases are happening at a much higher level than CUDA frameworks (i.e. on top of models); that, combined with the massive incentives towards finding cheaper alternatives to Nvidia, means both the pressure to and the possibility of escaping CUDA is higher than it has ever been (even if it is still distant for lower level work, particularly when it comes to training).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Nvidia has already started responding: I think that one way to understand DGX Cloud is that it is Nvidia’s attempt to capture the same market that is still buying Intel server chips in a world where AMD chips are better (because they already standardized on them); NIM’s are another attempt to build lock-in.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In the meantime, though, it remains noteworthy that Nvidia appears to not be taking as much margin with Blackwell as many may have expected; the question as to whether they will have to give back more in future generations will depend on not just their chips’ performance, but also on re-digging a software moat increasingly threatened by the very wave that made GTC such a spectacle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blackwell margins are doing just fine, I should note, as they should be in a world where everyone is starved for compute. Indeed, that may make this entire debate somewhat pointless: implicit in the assumption that TPUs might take share from GPUs is that for one to win the other must lose; the real decision maker may be TSMC, which makes both chips, and is positioned to be the real brake on the AI bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;ChatGPT and Moat Resiliency&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChatGPT, in contrast to Nvidia, sells into two much larger markets. The first is developers using their API, and — according to OpenAI, anyways — this market is much stickier and reticent to change. Which makes sense: developers using a particular model’s API are seeking to make a good product, and while everyone talks about the importance of avoiding lock-in, most companies are going to see more gains from building on and expanding from what they already know, and for a lot of companies that is OpenAI. Winning business one app by one will be a lot harder for Google than simply making a spreadsheet presentation to the top of a company about upfront costs and total cost of ownership. Still, API costs will matter, and here Google almost certainly has a structural advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The biggest market of all, however, is consumer, Google’s bread-and-butter. What makes Google so dominant in search, impervious to both competition and regulation, is that billions of consumers choose to use Google every day — multiple times a day, in fact. Yes, Google helps this process along with its payments to its friends, but that’s downstream from its control of demand, not the driver.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is paradoxical to many about this reality is that the seeming fragility of Google’s position — competition really is a click away! — is in fact its source of strength. From United States v. Google:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Increased digitization leads to increased centralization (the opposite of what many originally assumed about the Internet). It also provides a lot of consumer benefit — again, Aggregators win by building ever better products for consumers — which is why Aggregators are broadly popular in a way that traditional monopolists are not. Unfortunately, too many antitrust-focused critiques of tech have missed this essential difference…&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There is certainly an argument to be made that Google, not only in Shopping but also in verticals like local search, is choking off the websites on which Search relies by increasingly offering its own results. At the same time, there is absolutely nothing stopping customers from visiting those websites directly, or downloading their apps, bypassing Google completely. That consumers choose not to is not because Google is somehow restricting them — that is impossible! — but because they don’t want to. Is it really the purview of regulators to correct consumer choices willingly made?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not only is that answer “no” for philosophical reasons, it should be “no” for pragmatic reasons, as the ongoing Google Shopping saga in Europe demonstrates. As I noted last December, the European Commission keeps changing its mind about remedies in that case, not because Google is being impertinent, but because seeking to undo an Aggregator by changing consumer preferences is like pushing on a string.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The CEO of a hyperscaler can issue a decree to work around CUDA; an app developer can decide that Google’s cost structure is worth the pain of changing the model undergirding their app; changing the habits of 800 million+ people who use ChatGPT every week, however, is a battle that can only be fought individual by individual. This is ChatGPT’s true difference from Nvidia in their fight against Google.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Moat Map and Advertising&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is, I think, a broader point: the naive approach to moats focuses on the cost of switching; in fact, however, the more important correlation to the strength of a moat is the number of unique purchasers/users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is certainly one of the simpler charts I’ve made, but it’s not the first in the moat genre; in 2018’s The Moat Map I argued that you could map large tech companies across two spectrums. First, the degree of supplier differentiation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, the extent to which a company’s network effects were externalized:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Putting this together gave you the Moat Map:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What you see in the upper right are platforms; the lower left are Aggregators. Platforms like the App Store enable differentiated suppliers, which lets them profitably take a cut of purchases driven by those differentiated suppliers; Aggregators, meanwhile, have totally commoditized their suppliers, but have done so in the service of maximizing attention, which they can monetize through advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s the bottom left that I’m describing with the simplistic graph above: the way to commoditize suppliers and internalize network effects is by having a huge number of unique users. And, by extension, the best way to monetize that user base — and to achieve a massive user base in the first place — is through advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s so obvious the bottom left is where ChatGPT sits. At one point it didn’t seem possible to commoditize content more than Google or Facebook did, but that’s exactly what LLMs do: the answers are a statistical synthesis of all of the knowledge the model makers can get their hands on, and are completely unique to every individual; at the same time, every individual user’s usage should, at least in theory, make the model better over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It follows, then, that ChatGPT should obviously have an advertising model. This isn’t just a function of needing to make money: advertising would make ChatGPT a better product. It would have more users using it more, providing more feedback; capturing purchase signals — not from affiliate links, but from personalized ads — would create a richer understanding of individual users, enabling better responses. And, as an added bonus — and one that is very pertinent to this Article — it would dramatically deepen OpenAI’s moat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Google’s Advantages&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not out of the question that Google can win the fight for consumer attention. The company has a clear lead in image and video generation, which is one reason why I wrote about The YouTube Tip of the Google Spear:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In short, while everyone immediately saw how AI could be disruptive to Search, AI is very much a sustaining innovation for YouTube: it increases the amount of compelling content in absolute terms, and it does so with better margins, at least in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;del&gt;million&lt;/del&gt;&lt;del&gt;billion&lt;/del&gt;trillion dollar question: what is going to matter more in the long run, text or video? Sure, Google would like to dominate everything, but if it had to choose, is it better to dominate video or dominate text? The history of social networking that I documented above suggests that video is, in the long run, much more compelling to many more people.&lt;p&gt;To put it another way, the things that people in tech and media are interested in has not historically been aligned with what actually makes for the largest service or makes the most money: people like me, or those reading me, care about text and ideas; the services that matter specialize in videos and entertainment, and to the extent that AI matters for the latter YouTube is primed to be the biggest winner, even as the same people who couldn’t understand why Twitter didn’t measure up to Facebook go ga-ga over text generation and coding capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google is also obviously capable of monetizing users, even if they haven’t turned on ads in Gemini yet (although they have in AI Overviews). It’s also worth pointing out, as Eric Seufert did in a recent Stratechery Interview, that Google started monetizing Search less than two years after its public launch; it is search revenue, far more than venture capital money, that has undergirded all of Google’s innovation over the years, and is what makes them a behemoth today. In that light OpenAI’s refusal to launch and iterate an ads product for ChatGPT — now three years old — is a dereliction of business duty, particularly as the company signs deals for over a trillion dollars of compute.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And, on the flip side, it means that Google has the resources to take on ChatGPT’s consumer lead with a World War I style war of attrition; OpenAI’s lead should be unassailable, but the company’s insistence on monetizing solely via subscriptions, with a degraded user experience for most users and price elasticity challenges in terms of revenue maximization, is very much opening up the door to a company that actually cares about making money.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To put it another way, the long-term threat to Nvidia from TPUs is margin dilution; the challenge of physical products is you do have to actually charge the people who buy them, which invites potentially unfavorable comparisons to cheaper alternatives, particularly as buyers get bigger and more price sensitive. The reason to be more optimistic about OpenAI is that an advertising model flips this on its head: because users don’t pay, there is no ceiling on how much you can make from them, which, by extension, means that the bigger you get the better your margins have the potential to be, and thus the total size of your investments. Again, however, the problem is that the advertising model doesn’t yet exist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;A Theory’s Journey&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started this Article recounting the hero’s journey, in part to make the easy leap to “The Empire Strikes Back”; however, there was a personal angle as well. The hero of this site has been Aggregation Theory and the belief that controlling demand trumps everything else; there Google was my ultimate protagonist. Moreover, I do believe in the innovation and velocity that comes from a founder-led company like Nvidia, and I do still worry about Google’s bureaucracy and disruption potential making the company less nimble and aggressive than OpenAI. More than anything, though, I believe in the market power and defensibility of 800 million users, which is why I think ChatGPT still has a meaningful moat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, I understand why the market is freaking out about Google: their structural advantages in everything from monetization to data to infrastructure to R&amp;amp;D is so substantial that you understand why OpenAI’s founding was motivated by the fear of Google winning AI. It’s very easy to imagine an outcome where Google’s inputs simply matter more than anything else, which is to say one of my most important theories is being put to the ultimate test (which, perhaps, is why I’m so frustrated at OpenAI’s avoidance of advertising). Google is now my antagonist!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google has already done this once: Search was the ultimate example of a company winning an open market with nothing more than a better product. Aggregators win new markets by being better; the open question now is whether one that has already reached scale can be dethroned by the overwhelming application of resources, especially when its inherent advantages are diminished by refusing to adopt an Aggregator’s optimal business model. I’m nervous — and excited — to see how far Aggregation Theory really goes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46108437</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 15:18:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google *Unkills* JPEG XL?</title><link>https://tonisagrista.com/blog/2025/google-unkills-jpegxl/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7a5300562852eb8c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Google unkills JPEG XL?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A quick summary of the format’s road to stardom&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve written about JPEG XL in the past. First, I noted Google’s move to kill the format in Chromium in favor of the homegrown and inferior AVIF.12 Then, I had a deeper look at the format, and visually compared JPEG XL with AVIF on a handful of images.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The latter post started with a quick support test:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“If you are browsing this page around 2023, chances are that your browser supports AVIF but does not support JPEG XL.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, here we are at the end of 2025, and this very sentence still holds true. Unless you are one of the 17% of users using Safari3, or are adventurous enough to use a niche browser like Thorium or LibreWolf, chances are you see the AVIF banner in green and the JPEG XL image in black/red.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The good news is, this will change soon. In a dramatic turn of events, the Chromium team has reversed its &lt;code&gt;Obsolete&lt;/code&gt; tag, and has decided to support the format in Blink (the engine behind Chrome/Chromium/Edge). Given Chrome’s position in the browser market share, I predict the format will become a de factor standard for images in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Let’s recap&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been following JPEG XL since its experimental support in Blink. What started as a promising feature was quickly axed by the team in a bizarre and ridiculous manner. First, they asked the community for feedback on the format. Then, the community responded very positively. And I don’t only mean a couple of guys in their basement. Meta, Intel, Cloudinary, Adobe, &lt;code&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;libvips&lt;/code&gt;, Krita, and many more. After that came the infamous comment:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;da...@chromium.orgda...@chromium.org&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;#85 Oct 31, 2022 12:34AM&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Thank you everyone for your comments and feedback regarding JPEG XL. We will be removing the JPEG XL code and flag from Chromium for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Experimental flags and code should not remain indefinitely&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There is not enough interest from the entire ecosystem to continue experimenting with JPEG XL&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The new image format does not bring sufficient incremental benefits over existing formats to warrant enabling it by default&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;By removing the flag and the code in M110, it reduces the maintenance burden and allows us to focus on improving existing formats in Chrome&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, right, “not enough interest from the entire ecosystem”. Sure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway, following this comment, a steady stream of messages pointed out how wrong that was, from all the organizations mentioned above and many more. People were noticing in blog posts, videos, and social media interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strangely, the following few years have been pretty calm for JPEG XL. However, a few notable events did take place. First, the Firefox team showed interest in a JPEG XL Rust decoder, after describing their stance on the matter as “neutral”. They were concerned about the increased attack surface resulting from including the current 100K+ lines C++ &lt;code&gt;libjxl&lt;/code&gt; reference decoder, even though most of those lines are testing code. In any case, they kind of requested a “memory-safe” decoder. This seems to have kick-started the Rust implementation, jxl-rs, from Google Research.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To top it off, a couple of weeks ago, the PDF Association announced their intent to adopt JPEG XL as a preferred image format in their PDF specification. The CTO of the PDF Association, Peter Wyatt, expressed their desire to include JPEG XL as the preferred format for HDR content in PDF files.4&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Chromium’s new stance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of this pressure exerted steadily over time made the Chromium team reconsider the format. They tried to kill it in favor of AVIF, but that hasn’t worked out. Rick Byers, on behalf of Chromium, made a comment in the Blink developers Google group about the team welcoming a performant and memory-safe JPEG XL decoder in Chromium. He stated that the change of stance was in light of the positive signs from the community we have exposed above (Safari support, Firefox updating their position, PDF, etc.). Quickly after that, the Chromium issue state was changed from &lt;code&gt;Obsolete&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;Assigned&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;About JPEG XL&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is great news for the format, and I believe it will give it the final push for mass adoption. The format is excellent for all kinds of purposes, and I’ll be adopting it pretty much instantly for this and the Gaia Sky website when support is shipped. Some of the features that make it superior to the competition are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lossless re-compression of JPEG images. This means you can re-compress your current JPEG library without losing information and benefit from a ~30% reduction in file size for free. This is a killer feature that no other format has.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Support for wide gamut and HDR.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Support for image sizes of up to 1,073,741,823x1,073,741,824. You won’t run out of image space anytime soon. AVIF is ridiculous in this aspect, capping at 8,193x4,320. WebP goes up to 16K2, while the original 1992 JPEG supports 64K2.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Maximum of 32 bits per channel. No other format (except for the defunct JPEG 2000) offers this.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Maximum of 4,099 channels. Most other formats support 4 or 5, with the exception of JPEG 2000, which supports 16,384.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;JXL is super resilient to generation loss.5&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;JXL supports progressive decoding, which is essential for web delivery, IMO. WebP or HEIC have no such feature. Progressive decoding in AVIF was added a few years back.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Support for animation.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Support for alpha transparency.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Depth map support.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a full codec feature breakdown, see Battle of the Codecs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JPEG XL is the future of image formats. It checks all the right boxes, and it checks them well. Support in the overwhelmingly most popular browser engine is probably going to be a crucial stepping stone in the format’s path to stardom. I’m happy that the Chromium team reconsidered their inclusion, but I am sad that it took so long and so much pressure from the community to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46108563</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 15:28:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ask HN: Who is hiring? (December 2025)</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46108941</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3741985a3402e664"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please state the location and include REMOTE for remote work, REMOTE (US) or similar if the country is restricted, and ONSITE when remote work is &lt;/p&gt;not&lt;p&gt; an option.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please only post if you personally are part of the hiring company—no recruiting firms or job boards. One post per company. If it isn't a household name, explain what your company does.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please only post if you are actively filling a position and are committed to responding to applicants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commenters: please don't reply to job posts to complain about something. It's off topic here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Readers: please only email if you are personally interested in the job.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Searchers: try https://dheerajck.github.io/hnwhoishiring/, http://nchelluri.github.io/hnjobs/, https://hnresumetojobs.com, https://hnhired.fly.dev, https://kennytilton.github.io/whoishiring/, https://hnjobs.emilburzo.com, or this (unofficial) Chrome extension: https://chromewebstore.google.com/detail/hn-hiring-pro/mpfal....&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don't miss this other fine thread: Who wants to be hired? https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46108940&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46108941</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 16:01:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ImAnim: Modern animation capabilities to ImGui applications</title><link>https://github.com/soufianekhiat/ImAnim</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5f2ad13529538d8a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Animation Engine for Dear ImGui&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ImAnim brings modern animation capabilities to ImGui applications. Write smooth, UI animations with minimal code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// Animate anything in one line
float alpha = iam_tween_float(id, channel, hovered ? 1.0f : 0.5f, 0.3f, ease, policy, dt);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Immediate-mode friendly - Works naturally with ImGui's paradigm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Zero dependencies - Only requires Dear ImGui&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Large easing collection - 30+ easing functions including spring physics&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Perceptual color blending - OKLAB and OKLCH&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Responsive layouts - Anchor-relative animations that survive window resizing&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Category&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Capabilities&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tweens&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Float, Vec2, Vec4, Int, Color with crossfade/cut/queue policies&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Clips&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Timeline keyframes, looping, callbacks, chaining, stagger&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Easing&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Quad to Bounce presets, cubic-bezier, steps, spring physics&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Paths&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bezier curves, Catmull-Rom splines, text along paths&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Procedural&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Oscillators, shake, wiggle, Perlin/Simplex noise&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Extras&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Style interpolation, scroll animation, debug inspector&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include "im_anim.h"

// Each frame
iam_update_begin_frame();
iam_clip_update(dt);

// Hover animation
bool hovered = ImGui::IsItemHovered();
float scale = iam_tween_float(
    ImGui::GetID("button"), ImHashStr("scale"),
    hovered ? 1.1f : 1.0f,
    0.15f,
    iam_ease_preset(iam_ease_out_back),
    iam_policy_crossfade,
    dt
);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add two files to your project:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;src/im_anim.h
src/im_anim.cpp
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's it. No build system changes, no external dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full documentation in the &lt;code&gt;docs/&lt;/code&gt; folder:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Quick Start - Get running in 5 minutes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tweens - Immediate-mode animation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clips - Timeline-based keyframe animation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Easing - All 30+ easing functions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Motion Paths - Animate along curves&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text Along Paths - Curved text rendering&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Stagger - Cascading element animations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Oscillators - Continuous periodic motion&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Shake &amp;amp; Wiggle - Feedback and organic motion&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Noise - Perlin/Simplex procedural animation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Text Stagger - Per-character text effects&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Style Interpolation - Animated theme transitions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anchors - Resize-aware animation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Debug - Inspector and debugging tools&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;demo/&lt;/code&gt; folder contains a comprehensive demo showcasing all features:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Interactive easing curve visualizer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cubic bezier editor&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Spring physics playground&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All animation types with live controls&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Performance benchmarks&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;List Stagger&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Grid Stagger&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Card Animation&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Color Blending&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Wave Color&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Gradient&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ImGui Integration&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Development is supported through Patreon:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT License - see LICENSE for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Made for the Dear ImGui community&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46109080</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 16:11:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A New AI Winter Is Coming</title><link>https://taranis.ie/llms-are-a-failure-a-new-ai-winter-is-coming/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="be51831122679e58"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;LLMs are a failure. A new AI winter is coming.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though LLMs had a lot of promise, this has not been demonstrated in practice. The technology is essentially a failure, and a new AI winter is coming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like many people, I got pretty excited when it was discovered that the transformer neural network architecture appeared to break through many years of stagnation in AI research. Chatbots suddenly had emergent capabilities, derived almost entirely from unstructured, unsupervised learning, far surpassing older technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My first experiences were with unreleased models, pre-ChatGPT, and I was seriously impressed. Though these early, small, models would often mess up, even generating streams of garbage text, when they worked they worked. Spookily well. I completely understand why some people at the time thought they were sentient – this is a whole other discussion for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People were saying that this meant that the AI winter was over, and a new era was beginning. I should explain for anyone who hasn't heard that term before, that way back in the day, when early AI research was seemingly yielding significant results, there was much hope, as there is now, but ultimately the technology stagnated. First time around, AI was largely symbolic – this basically means that attempts to model natural language understanding and reasoning were based essentially on hard-coded rules. This worked, up to a point, but it was soon clear that it was simply impractical to build a true AI that way. Human language is too messy for mechanised parsing to work in a general way. Reasoning required far too much world knowledge for it to be practical to write the code by hand, and nobody knew how to extract that knowledge without human intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other huge problem with traditional AI was that many of its algorithms were NP-complete, which meant that whilst a lot of the time you got a result, often you just didn't, with the algorithm taking an arbitrarily long time to terminate. I doubt anyone can prove this – I certainly wouldn't attempt it – but I strongly suspect that 'true AI', for useful definitions of that term, is at best NP-complete, possibly much worse. Though quantum computing in principle could give some leverage here, none of the technologies currently being built or that are being considered feasible are likely to be useful. Just not enough qubits to represent the kinds of data that would need to be processed – this is a way, way harder problem than trying to reverse encryption secured by the difficulty of prime factorization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So then came transformers. Seemingly capable of true AI, or, at least, scaling to being good enough to be called true AI, with astonishing capabilities. For the uninitiated, a transformer is basically a big pile of linear algebra that takes a sequence of tokens and computes the likeliest next token. More specifically, they are fed one token at a time, which builds an internal state that ultimately guides the generation of the next token. This sounds bizarre and probably impossible, but the huge research breakthrough was figuring out that, by starting with essentially random coefficients (weights and biases) in the linear algebra, and during training back-propagating errors, these weights and biases could eventually converge on something that worked. Exactly why this works is still somewhat mysterious, though progress has been made.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transformers aren't killed by the NP-completeness and scaling problems that caused the first AI winter. Technically, a single turn-of-the-handle, generating the next token from the previous token and some retained state, always takes the same amount of time. This inner loop isn't Turing-complete – a simple program with a while loop in it is computationally more powerful. If you allow a transformer to keep generating tokens indefinitely this is probably Turing-complete, though nobody actually does that because of the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transformers also solved scaling, because their training can be unsupervised (though, practically they do often need supervised training in order to create guardrails against dangerous behaviour). It is now standard practice to train new models on just about every book ever written and everything that can be scraped from the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's the good news. That was the good news. But we've gone past that point now, and we are now all up against the reality of widespread use of transformers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All transformers have a fundamental limitation, which can not be eliminated by scaling to larger models, more training data or better fine-tuning. It is fundamental to the way that they operate. On each turn of the handle, transformers emit one new token (a token is analogous to a word, but in practice may represest word parts or even complete commonly used small phrases – this is why chatbots don't know how to spell!). In practice, the transformer actually generates a number for every possible output token, with the highest number being chosen in order to determine the token. This token is then fed back, so that the model generates the next token in the sequence. The problem with this approach is that the model will always generate a token, regardless of whether the context has anything to do with its training data. Putting it another way, the model generates tokens on the basis of what 'looks most plausible' as a next token. If this is a bad choice, and gets fed back, the next token will be generated to match that bad choice. And as the handle keeps turning, the model will generate text that looks plausible. Models are very good at this, because this is what they are trained to do. Indeed, it's all they can do. This is the root of the hallucination problem in transformers, and is unsolveable because hallucinating is all that transformers can do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would conjecture that this is another manifestation of the NP-completeness wall that slammed symbolic AI, causing the first AI winter. It's always possible to turn an NP-complete algorithm into one that runs quickly, if you don't mind that it fails to generate any output if you hit a timeout. The transformer equivalent of this is generating plausible, wrong, hallucinated output in cases where it can't pattern match a good result based on its training. The problem, though, is that with traditional AI algorithms you typically know if you've hit a timeout, or if none of your knowledge rules match. With transformers, generating wrong output looks exactly like generating correct output, and there is no way to know which is which.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practically, this manifests as transformers generating bad output a percentage of the time. Depending on the context, and how picky you need to be about recognizing good or bad output, this might be anywhere from a 60% to a 95% success rate, with the remaining 5%-40% being bad results. This just isn't good enough for most practical purposes. More concerning is the fact that larger transformer models produce extremely plausible bad output, that can only be identified as bad by genuine experts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The rumour mill has it that about 95% of generative AI projects in the corporate world are failures. This isn't really surprising to anyone who was around for the dot com bubble, where corporate executives all seemed to assume that just being online would somehow transform their businesses, and that new ventures only really needed user count and that the financials would sort themselves out later. The same thing is happening again with generative AI, though the numbers are far larger. It is absolutely inevitable that the bubble will burst, and fairly soon. Expect OpenAI to crash, hard, with investors losing their shirts. Expect AI infra spends to be cancelled and/or clawed back. Expect small AI startups that aren't revenue positive to vanish overnight. Expect use cases based on unrealistic expectations of LLM capabilites to crash the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A good example is transformers used to assist in programming, or to generate code from scratch. This has convinced many non-programmers that they can program, but the results are consistently disastrous, because it still requires genuine expertise to spot the hallucinations. Plausible hallucinations in code often result in really horrible bugs, security holes, etc., and can be incredibly difficult to find and fix. My own suspicion is that this might get you close to what you think is finished, but actually getting over the line to real production code still requires real engineering, and it's a horrible liability to have to maintain a codebase that nobody on the team actually authored.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transformers must never be used for certain applications – their failure rate is unacceptable for anything that might directly or indirectly harm (or even significantly inconvenience) a human. This means that they should never be used in medicine, for evaluation in school or college, for law enforcement, for tax assessment, or a myriad of other similar cases. It is difficult to spot errors even when you are an expert, so nonexpert users have no chance whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The technology won't disappear – existing models, particularly in the open source domain, will still be available, and will still be used, but expect a few 'killer app' use cases to remain, with the rest falling away. We're probably stuck with spammy AI slop, and with high school kids using gen AI to skip their boring homework. We'll probably keep AI features in text editors, and a few other places.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know that this is a currently-unpopular opinion. It is based on solid science, however. For what it's worth, I founded a chatbot company back in the late 90s, based on symbolic AI technology, that went splat in the dot com crash. I've been around this block, and I've stayed up to date on the technology – I've built my own transformer from scratch, and have experimented quite a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My advice: unwind as much exposure as possible you might have to a forthcoming AI bubble crash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Winter is coming, and it's harsh on tulips.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46109534</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 16:42:15 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>