<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 10:10:45 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Amiga Unix (Amix)</title><link>https://www.amigaunix.com/doku.php/home</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a7a29c0e5929259e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Amiga Unix wiki!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amiga UNIX (also known as “Amix”) was Commodore's port of AT&amp;amp;T System V Release 4 Unix to the Amiga in 1990. Like many early Unix variants, Amiga Unix never became wildly popular, but it is an interesting sidestep in the history of the Amiga.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two “official” machines that could run Amix were the Amiga 2500UX and 3000UX models, however it can run on any Amiga that meets its hardware requirements. The awesome Amiga emulator WinUAE has been able to run it since 2013 (version 2.7.0 onwards).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This site is dedicated on preserving Amix's history and sharing information and instructions on what Amix is, how to install it (either on real hardware or in emulation) and what can you do with it. Mainly, it tries to cater to people who wish to run AMIX for whatever reason on their hardware. By documenting experiences with it, it is hoped that subsequent SVR4 junkies will find the way more smooth than it might have been without any guidance at all. For even a relatively experienced modern Unix or GNU/Linux administrator, System V UNIX is sufficiently different to present difficulty in installation and administration. Not so much in moving around between directories, and using common utilities that persist to this day - although many of those are hoary and somewhat forgetful in their retirement - but of doing more in depth tasks and understanding the differences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Table of contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; Amiga 3000UX Advert (thanks to 1000bit.it!) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;History and Documentation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Hardware&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Tutorials &amp;amp; How-to's&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Software&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;General topics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;STREAM: Commodore Had UNIX On Amiga?! by NCommander on YouTube (1.5.2022)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Abysmal AMIX Performance" and other blog posts about Amix and its disk performance in bdwheele's blog&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Article about Amix in “Virtually Fun” blog: AMIX (2013).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WinUAE and the beginnings of Amix support in EAB forums&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Great Amix site with re-done manuals and other useful files (in german): http://www.amigaunix.de&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Telefisk.org gopher site mirror to grab files: http://gopher.muffinlabs.com/telefisk.org/amiga/Amix/&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Not that active anymore, but still a good reading: Amiga UNIX Discussions in Amiga.org&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Old, and riddled with Spam, but there once was a thriving Newsgroup dedicated to Amiga Unix. Seeing the Internet “never forgets”, you can find the old discussions at Google Groups: https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/comp.unix.amiga&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Where to get help with Amix?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently the most active Amix-related forum seems to be support.Amix @ English Amiga Board. Ask there if you need any help!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wanted: content for this site! Do you have a piece of third-party software for Amix? Copy of an exotic hardware driver? Would you like to help write guides? Have copy of files from litamiga.epfl.ch or amiga.physik.unizh.ch? Please let us know!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why would you like to try Amix? The short answer is, you don't want it. Stay with me for just a minute here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amiga UNIX is really, really real UNIX. AT&amp;amp;T System V Release 4, ported by a team at Commodore that quit the day that 1.0 was released - at least, as legend has it. All the releases have their share of issues, and none of them have been updated in well over a decade. It runs on old hardware that was expensive when new and hard enough to find now that “RARE!” tags on eBay aren't hyperbole for once. You can cheat and get it installed without the tape drive, at least, but it's not for the faint of heart and has its own caveats such as a completely broken package system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think for a minute about your goals before embarking on this journey. If you're a die-hard Amiga user - and we all know they are still out there - interested in trying this UNIX thing, because you've heard about Mac OS X and that's based on UNIX, but before you swap out Kickstart for init you'd like to kick the tires on Amiga UNIX…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don't.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ten minutes with Amiga UNIX will have some Amiga users reaching for their 3.1 floppies. Actually, two minutes with the installer might have the same effect. That's just not fair to UNIX, whether it's GNU/Linux, Solaris, FreeBSD, or whatever. The environment has come a long way in the years and years since Amiga UNIX was shiny and new, rather than bitter and tarnished. Your average Ubuntu user will have set fire to their house trying to expunge any evidence of the unforgiving AMIX installation. Did I mention it hasn't been updated in a decade? Put your Amiga UNIX machine on the net with no firewall and you may see it rooted faster than a Win98SE box running IE5.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, and this is a biggie, there is no future for AMIX. Its kernel, libc, and much of its software is closed source, so when Commodore folded its story was over. It was put to pasture even as free UNIX environments began to be truly plausible contenders for commercial UNIX, and largely forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So this is quite the happy page, isn't it? Why would you want to install AMIX?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's really only one reason. Well, two, if you count being an idiot like us. That reason is simple curiosity. If you'd like to put yourself in the shoes of an aspiring systems programmer in the early nineties, go for it. If you find the legacy of the ever growing open source operating system revolution fascinating, AMIX could prove instructive. If you're trying to impress bearded UNIX gurus with arcane knowledge from the times when men were men, and 16MB was a ton of RAM, the dwindling lore of System V might be the key. These days, Amiga UNIX is all about history and learning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So if you have the requisite hardware and you have girded yourself for what is in store for you should you venture into the m68k-cbm-sysv4 dungeon, you might enjoy this site and the dusty treasures it contains. But seriously, if you just want to try UNIX or GNU/Linux out, the most expedient way to do it is on x86 or just something better supported on Amiga hardware. There are lots of choices for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good luck, and enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Folkert “Tahoe” de Gans for hosting the site!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Ville Laustela for images &amp;amp; scans and updating the Wiki.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Toni Wilen for maintaining the WinUAE emulator and making it possible to run Amix inside it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dedicated to Andrew “Failsure” Whitlock, the original creator and maintainer of this site. RIP, agw.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 8044 visitors since 1.8.2019 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To contact us, please use the contact form.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46845244</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 10:57:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Adventure Game Studio: OSS software for creating adventure games</title><link>https://www.adventuregamestudio.co.uk/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="8762b55fd9f7e9e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adventure Game Studio (AGS) is open-source software for creating graphical point-and-click adventure games. It is free, standalone, and requires no subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Windows-based IDE, streamlines game creation by integrating tools for importing graphics, writing scripts, and testing. Games created with AGS can be played on multiple platforms, including Linux, iOS, and Android.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Suitable for all skill levels, AGS features an active community for support and socialising.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Showcase your games by uploading them to this website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rot your brain by consuming AI slop and services in this classic arcade style game created for the MAGS January 2026 game jam in the AGS forums.Move […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You awaken alone on a cold, rocky shore beneath a moonless sky, dragged from the sea through a sewer pipe with no memory of who you are, how you […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A dead man's soul cries out against the force of a ferocious blizzard. He cries for help. He cries for answers. Then he screams as he is torn apart […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A madness for spiritualism has gripped London in 1907. Séances and theatrical shows where spirits make contact with their living families are all […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Beginners' Technical Questions&lt;lb/&gt; By: helloimtim (11 minutes ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: The Rumpus Room&lt;lb/&gt; By: Khris (27 minutes ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Critics' Lounge&lt;lb/&gt; By: Nine Toes (1 hour ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Adventure Related Talk &amp;amp; Chat&lt;lb/&gt; By: Rui "Giger Kitty" Pires (3 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Competitions &amp;amp; Activities&lt;lb/&gt; By: Rui "Giger Kitty" Pires (5 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Game Page Entry Reports&lt;lb/&gt; By: AGS Site Reports (5 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: AGS Games in Production&lt;lb/&gt; By: heltenjon (8 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In: Competitions &amp;amp; Activities&lt;lb/&gt; By: heltenjon (8 hours ago) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AGS has an active and friendly community, with many ways of keeping in touch and getting help with your project or games made with AGS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These include our local forums, Facebook page, Discord server, in-person meet-ups, and many more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The AGS community is run by a team of dedicated volunteers, who put their time and efforts into keeping it running as a welcoming, friendly and informative place to be. The AGS server and forums are paid for out of our own pockets, so in effect it costs us money to provide a free service to AGS users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you appreciate the work we do, and would like to give a little something back, please use the below link to donate via PayPal. Any profit made after covering server costs will be put back into hosting community events such as Mittens.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46846252</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 13:56:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple I Advertisement (1976)</title><link>http://apple1.chez.com/Apple1project/Gallery/Gallery.htm</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b45ed919010701fc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;row&gt;
      &lt;cell valign="TOP" width="210"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt; The Apple Computer. A truly complete microcomputer system on a single PC board. Based on the MOS Technology 6502 micro- processor, the Apple also has a built-in video terminal and sockets for 8K bytes of onboard RAM memory. With the addition of a keyboard and video monitor, you'll have an extremely powerful computer system that can be used for anything from developing programs to playing games or running BASIC.&lt;lb/&gt; Combining the computer, video terminal and dynamic memory on a single board has resulted in a large reduction in chip count, which means more reliability and lowered cost. Since the Apple comes fully assembled, tested &amp;amp; burned-in and has a complete power supply on-board, initial set-up is essentially "hassle-free" and you can be running within minutes. At $666.66 (including 4K bytes RAM!) it opens many new possibilities for users and systems manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;You Don't Need an Expensive Teletype.&lt;lb/&gt; Using the built-in video terminal and keyboard interface, you avoid all the expense, noise and mantenance associated with a teletype. And the Apple video terminal is six times faster than a teletype, which means more throughput and less waiting. The Apple connects directly to a video monitor (or home TV with an in- expensive RF modulator) and dis- plays 960 easy to read characters in 24 rows of 40 characters per line with automatic scrolling. The video display section contains its own 1K bytes of memory, so all the RAM memory is available for user programs. And the &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;cell valign="TOP" width="210"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Keyboard Interface lets you use almost any ASCII-encoded keyboard.&lt;lb/&gt; The Apple Computer makes it possible for many people with limited budgets to step up to a video terminal as an I/O device for their computer.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;No More Switches,&lt;lb/&gt; No MoreLights&lt;lb/&gt; Compared to switches and LED's, a video terminal can dis- play vast amounts of information simultaneously. The Apple video terminal can display the contents of 192 memory locations at once on the screen. And the fimrware in PROMS enables you to enter,display and debug programs (all in hex) from the keyboard, ren- dering a front panel unnecessary. The firmware also allows your programs to print characters on the display, and since you'll be looking at letters and numbers instead of just LED's, the door is open to all kinds of alphanumeric software (i.e., Games and BASIC).&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;8K Bytes RAM in 16 Chips!&lt;lb/&gt; The Apple Computer uses the new 16-pin 4K dynamic memory chips. They are faster and take 1/4 the space and power of even the low power 2102's (the memory chip that everyone else uses). That means 8K bytes in sixteen chips. It also means no more 28 amp power supplies. The system is fully expandable to 65K via an edge connector which carries both the address and data busses, power supplies and all timing signals. All dy- namic memory refreshing for both on and off-board memory is done automatically. Also, the Apple Computer can be upgraded to use the 16K chips when they become availa- &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;cell valign="TOP" width="210"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;ble. That's 32K bytes on-board RAM in 16 IC's --the equivalent of 256 2102's!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A little Cassette Board that Works!&lt;lb/&gt; Unlike many other cassette boards on the marketplace,ours works every timeIt plugs directly into the upright connector on the mainboard and stands only 2" tall.And since it is very fast (1500 bits per second), you can read or write 4 K bytes in about 20 seconds.All timing is done in software, witch results in crystal-controlled accuracy and uniformity from unit to unit.&lt;lb/&gt; unlike some other cassette interfaces witch requires an expensive tape recorder, the Apple Cassette Interface works reliably with almost any audio-grade cassette recorder.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Softwares&lt;lb/&gt; A tape of APPLE BASIC is inclued free with the Cassette Interface.Apple Basic features immediate error message and fast execution, and let's you program in a highter level language immediately and without added cost.Also avialable now are a dis-assembler and many games, with many software packages,(including a macro assembler) in the works.And since our philosophy is to provide software for our machines free or at minimal cost, you won't be continually paying for access to this growing software library.&lt;lb/&gt; The Apple Computer is in stock al almost all major computer stores.(if your local computer store doesn't carry our products, encourage them or write us direct).Dealer inquiries invited. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/cell&gt;
    &lt;/row&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46847780</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 17:36:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Crisis comes to Wordle: Reusing old words</title><link>https://forkingmad.blog/wordle-crisis/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2a1d83a66f285f21"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;A Crisis comes to Wordle: Reusing old words!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few days ago, The new York Times (owner of Wordle) announced that from 2 February it would start reusing some words from previous years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Their announcement started:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hey, Wordlers! We have some exciting news to share&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;and continued&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Starting on Monday, we will begin adding previously run words back into play. There are still many first-time answers to debut, but also more chances for Wordle in ones and those magical, serendipitous moments when Wordle overlaps with real life. Happy solving!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, whoever wrote this nonsense deserves an award for fake cheerfulness. There is absolutely no "exciting news" in that paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It has caused a bit of a stir in the Wordle Community. Many wondering why, and some suggesting they will now stop playing the dumbed down version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;It got me thinking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they running out of five-letter words? I've gathered the data and crunched the numbers, and here are my findings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, I started with a list of English words. I've actually had a list for some time, and I knew one day it would come in useful. It contains 466,547 words: from aahed 1 to zugzwang 2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I then narrowed that down to five-letter words (22,949) before excluding plurals, which are not used in Wordle, and Proper Nouns (such as Paris, or March -- anything with uppercase first letter, but leaving "march" for example). The list was down to 10,784 words.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, one more trip through the sausage machine. I put this list in a word processor and calculated how many spelling errors there were. This, roughly, would help me identify the more common five-letter words. I doubt many of us could use valew 3 in a sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We now have a more manageable potential Wordle list of 5,437 words.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The longevity of five-thousand words?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A word-a-day from that list would yield almost 15 years of daily challenges. Wordle has been running since October 2021. By my reckoning we have enough to run until 2036&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;NYT, Why?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So that does beg the question: New York Times - why start repeating?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Leave a Comment; Or copy this post id and search for it in your Fediverse client to reply; Or send a message. If you have replied with your own blog post and I will mention it here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://gofer.social/@daj/statuses/01KGCRW6RR3XWCYYHBKW7YHKRJ&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46847924</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 17:54:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Towards a science of scaling agent systems: When and why agent systems work</title><link>https://research.google/blog/towards-a-science-of-scaling-agent-systems-when-and-why-agent-systems-work/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3479c6dba9c380b3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Towards a science of scaling agent systems: When and why agent systems work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;January 28, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yubin Kim, Research Intern, and Xin Liu, Senior Research Scientist, Google Research&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through a controlled evaluation of 180 agent configurations, we derive the first quantitative scaling principles for AI agent systems, revealing that multi-agent coordination dramatically improves performance on parallelizable tasks but degrades it on sequential ones; we also introduce a predictive model that identifies the optimal architecture for 87% of unseen tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Quick links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI agents — systems capable of reasoning, planning, and acting — are becoming a common paradigm for real-world AI applications. From coding assistants to personal health coaches, the industry is shifting from single-shot question answering to sustained, multi-step interactions. While researchers have long utilized established metrics to optimize the accuracy of traditional machine learning models, agents introduce a new layer of complexity. Unlike isolated predictions, agents must navigate sustained, multi-step interactions where a single error can cascade throughout a workflow. This shift compels us to look beyond standard accuracy and ask: How do we actually design these systems for optimal performance?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Practitioners often rely on heuristics, such as the assumption that "more agents are better", believing that adding specialized agents will consistently improve results. For example, "More Agents Is All You Need" reported that LLM performance scales with agent count, while collaborative scaling research found that multi-agent collaboration "...often surpasses each individual through collective reasoning."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In our new paper, “Towards a Science of Scaling Agent Systems”, we challenge this assumption. Through a large-scale controlled evaluation of 180 agent configurations, we derive the first quantitative scaling principles for agent systems, revealing that the "more agents" approach often hits a ceiling, and can even degrade performance if not aligned with the specific properties of the task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Defining "agentic" evaluation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To understand how agents scale, we first defined what makes a task "agentic". Traditional static benchmarks measure a model's knowledge, but they don't capture the complexities of deployment. We argue that agentic tasks require three specific properties:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sustained multi-step interactions with an external environment.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Iterative information gathering under partial observability.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adaptive strategy refinement based on environmental feedback.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We evaluated five canonical architectures: one single-agent system (SAS) and four multi-agent variants (independent, centralized, decentralized, and hybrid) across four diverse benchmarks, including Finance-Agent (financial reasoning), BrowseComp-Plus (web navigation), PlanCraft (planning), and Workbench (tool use). The agent architectures are defined as follow:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Single-Agent (SAS): A solitary agent executing all reasoning and acting steps sequentially with a unified memory stream.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Independent: Multiple agents working in parallel on sub-tasks without communicating, aggregating results only at the end.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Centralized: A "hub-and-spoke" model where a central orchestrator delegates tasks to workers and synthesizes their outputs.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Decentralized: A peer-to-peer mesh where agents communicate directly with one another to share information and reach consensus.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hybrid: A combination of hierarchical oversight and peer-to-peer coordination to balance central control with flexible execution.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Results: The myth of "more agents"&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To quantify the impact of model capabilities on agent performance, we evaluated our architectures across three leading model families: OpenAI GPT, Google Gemini, and Anthropic Claude. The results reveal a complex relationship between model capabilities and coordination strategy. As shown in the figure below, while performance generally trends upward with more capable models, multi-agent systems are not a universal solution — they can either significantly boost or unexpectedly degrade performance depending on the specific configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The results below compare the performance of the five architectures across different domains, such as web browsing and financial analysis. The box plots represent the accuracy distribution for each approach, while the percentages indicate the relative improvement (or decline) of multi-agent teams compared to the single-agent baseline. This data highlights that while adding agents can drive massive gains in parallelizable tasks, it can often lead to diminishing returns — or even performance drops — in more sequential workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The alignment principle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On parallelizable tasks like financial reasoning (e.g., distinct agents can simultaneously analyze revenue trends, cost structures, and market comparisons), centralized coordination improved performance by 80.9% over a single agent. The ability to decompose complex problems into sub-tasks allowed agents to work more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The sequential penalty&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conversely, on tasks requiring strict sequential reasoning (like planning in PlanCraft), every multi-agent variant we tested degraded performance by 39-70%. In these scenarios, the overhead of communication fragmented the reasoning process, leaving insufficient "cognitive budget" for the actual task.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The tool-use bottleneck&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We identified a "tool-coordination trade-off". As tasks require more tools (e.g., a coding agent with access to 16+ tools), the "tax" of coordinating multiple agents increases disproportionately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Architecture as a safety feature&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps most important for real-world deployment, we found a relationship between architecture and reliability. We measured error amplification, the rate at which a mistake by one agent propagates to the final result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We found that independent multi-agent systems (agents working in parallel without talking) amplified errors by 17.2x. Without a mechanism to check each other's work, errors cascaded unchecked. Centralized systems (with an orchestrator) contained this amplification to just 4.4x. The orchestrator effectively acts as a "validation bottleneck", catching errors before they propagate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A predictive model for agent design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moving beyond retrospection, we developed a predictive model (R^2 = 0.513) that uses measurable task properties like tool count and decomposability to predict which architecture will perform best. This model correctly identifies the optimal coordination strategy for 87% of unseen task configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This suggests we are moving toward a new science of agent scaling. Instead of guessing whether to use a swarm of agents or a single powerful model, developers can now look at the properties of their task, specifically its sequential dependencies and tool density, to make principled engineering decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As foundational models like Gemini continue to advance, our research suggests that smarter models don't replace the need for multi-agent systems, they accelerate it, but only when the architecture is right. By moving from heuristics to quantitative principles, we can build the next generation of AI agents that are not just more numerous, but smarter, safer, and more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We would like to thank our co-authors and collaborators from Google Research, Google DeepMind, and academia for their contributions to this work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46847958</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 18:00:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ian's Shoelace Site</title><link>https://www.fieggen.com/shoelace/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f9d7e127c154339c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Ian's Shoelace Site&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fun, fashion &amp;amp; science in the Internet's #1 website about shoelaces – and home of the Ian Knot, the world's fastest shoelace knot. If you want to lace shoes, tie shoes or learn about shoelaces – this is the place!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Welcome!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;G'day everyone, Ian Fieggen here, also known as “Professor Shoelace”. I'm a real human living in Melbourne, Australia. This website has no “A.I.” content – it's all built with “H.I.” plus Human Effort over more than two decades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome to “Ian's Shoelace Site” – made by one human, for all humans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contains over 100 × step-by-step shoe lacing tutorials, over 2,700 × shoe lacing photos, plus the interactive “Create-a-Lace” for designing your own lacing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contains 25 × shoelace knots (including my world's fastest “Ian Knot”), plus info on tying correctly so that they sit straight and stay securely tied – yet can be untied without jamming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heaps of knowledge about shoelaces, including their construction, length calculations – even what the tips are called, as well as Ian's interviews, articles, Q&amp;amp;As and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Information about this website and the site's author, Ian Fieggen – including Ian's contact details. Also info on this site's sponsors plus ways that you, too, can support Ian.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contact Ian Fieggen via e-mail or connect with “Professor Shoelace” via YouTube, Instagram, Twitter, Facebook or RSS feed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking for something? This website has more than 300 pages – which can be daunting to wade through! Search the whole of Ian's Shoelace Site using Google Custom Search.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Latest Photo&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;02-Feb-2026&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today's shoe lacing photo was contributed by Guillaume R. in Feb-2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Black &amp;amp; white Umbro soccer cleats laced with white Ladder Lacing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neat lacing that should also provide good support for playing soccer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What's New?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;22-Jan-2025 – Added Ian's interview from 2018 about modern shoelace alternatives, plus an interview from 2020 about lacing, knots and my “Professor Shoelace” alias.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;04-Dec-2025 – During Australia's marriage equality debate, PUMA engaged me to create the “Equality Knot”, then sent a film crew to shoot this “content piece” video.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;02-Dec-2025 – Following a visitor request, I added diagrams for the inverted variation of Pentagram Lacing for 7, 6 and 5 pairs of eyelets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;28-Nov-2025 – Following a suggestion from a website visitor, I added buttons to filter by either “Shortening” or “Lengthening” methods.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;10-Nov-2025 – Added Ian's interview from Dec-2016 with The Stuph File about my Shoelace Site, from its humble beginnings through to the extensive and respected website that it is today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;06-Nov-2025 – Added Ian's interview from Sep-2015 with BBC Radio 4, which coincided with “back to school” in the UK, covered teaching kids to tie their shoes for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;29-Oct-2025 – This website has long included “Woven Lacing” for shoes with eyelets. A recent visitor-contributed photo prompted me to add Lug Woven Lacing for shoes with lugs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;14-Oct-2025 – Added an interactive Shoelace Weave Diagram, which allows you to experiment with creating shoelace weave patterns thread-by-thread.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Recent Visitor Feedback&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I just want to express my gratitude and appreciation for your website and the work you put into it. I look forward to learning all about tying knots I'm going to relish for years to come. Thank you again, sir.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Travis S., Virginia, USA, Feb-2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Can't believe that I've been tying my shoelaces wrongly for 50 years! Never too late to learn I guess... many thanks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Mike B., UK, Feb-2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lesson that will at least benefit Mike for the next 50-odd years – and which prompted a donation in gratitude. Thanks, Mike!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Ian Fieggen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tonight I was having a grand time looking through your shoe lacing tutorials for fun, and then I saw that you actually invented my favorite way to tie my shoes and show off a little bit!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I yelled “HE INVENTED THIS KNOT? I KNOW THAT KNOT!!!” (and scared my cat a little bit hahahaha)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyways just wanted to thank you for having a great website, I’m really enjoying it and can’t wait to try out some of the decorative lacing on my boots!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Selkie, Los Angeles, USA, Feb-2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the Canadian Forces' lacing instructions were at best a 2/10 I got referenced to this site and never looked back, thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Andres S., Canada, Jan-2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andres was also appreciative enough to send a donation – thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Ian Fieggen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Love the site! Been checking it on occasion for years, and I have been using the Ian [k]not for so long I don't remember how to tie the normal bow. Hadn't occurred to me I could donate until I saw Chris Person's article.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Baynard N., USA, Jan-2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kind comments plus acts of generosity like Baynard's are the catalyst that has kept me going all these years. Thanks, Baynard!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Ian Fieggen&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you'd also like to send feedback, please Contact Ian.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46848231</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 18:38:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Clearspace (YC W23) Is Hiring an Applied Researcher (ML)</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/clearspace/jobs/GOWiDwp-research-engineer-at-clearspace</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="14939967bc01edd1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eliminate compulsive phone usage&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Clearspace&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clearspace is building the intentionality layer of the internet. Our mission is to build technology as effective at protecting human attention as social media is at exploiting it (infinite scrolling, short-form feeds, manipulative notifications, etc). Our category defining mobile app has been featured on Huberman Lab, New York Times Wirecutter, NPR Marketplace, Forbes, TBPN.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People that want a better relationship with their devices have nowhere to turn except for willpower. We are building an agent that achieves this on all devices by processing and filtering network traffic based on natural language rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About The Role&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are looking for an ML-focused engineer that will be responsible for training and improving a model for classifying network traffic. You are great for this role if you are not only excited about the latest in AI and ML but are also a problem-solver in the data domain. You don’t just think about the model but “how can we get more data volume”; “how can we featurize the data intelligently”; “what are our data needs based on our task and desired model size”, and like building backwards from inference requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qualifications&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nice to Have&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At Clearspace we help people reduce compulsive phone usage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We exist to protect people's attention from the exploits of modern technology platforms and make space for the things that matter to them most.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe the technology to protect someones attention should be just as sophisticated and effective as the tech that is exploiting it and are building a world-class engineering team to arm the world with a comprehensive attention protection stack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46848260</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 18:41:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Building Your Own Efficient uint128 in C++</title><link>https://solidean.com/blog/2026/building-your-own-u128/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="172010af286e8a4b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Building Your Own Efficient uint128 in C++&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A practical walk-through of a fixed-width uint128 implementation in modern C++.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We build a minimal &lt;code&gt;u128&lt;/code&gt; as two &lt;code&gt;u64&lt;/code&gt; limbs and implement arithmetic using carry, borrow, and multiply intrinsics that map directly to x64 instructions.
The generated code is on par with builtin &lt;code&gt;__uint128_t&lt;/code&gt; for addition, subtraction, multiplication, and comparison.
This is unsigned-only, x64-focused, and intentionally narrow in scope.
The result is a solid foundation for exact, fixed-width arithmetic with a focus on good codegen and predictability, not abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Full code and compiler output: https://godbolt.org/z/K6dn3s91Y&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Scope&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We take the smallest reasonable definition of a 128-bit integer, two 64-bit words, and turn it into a usable arithmetic type whose generated code is indistinguishable from a builtin &lt;code&gt;__uint128_t&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post is explicitly not about dynamically-sized big integer arithmetic. It is about being explicit with range bounds and letting the compiler emit the exact instructions we want. The scope is deliberately limited: unsigned arithmetic, fixed width, modern x64, with Clang and GCC as the primary targets and notes for MSVC where it differs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why fixed-width big integers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In many domains, especially geometry and numerics, we do not need arbitrary precision. We need enough precision to be exact for known bounds, and we need the cost to be predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dynamic big integer libraries solve a different problem. They are flexible and general, but they pay for that generality in memory traffic, branches, and indirection. If your values fit into a fixed number of bits and you know that ahead of time, fixed-width arithmetic is usually the better trade. (In fact, our high-performance exact mesh booleans are completely built on this: Exact Arithmetic in Solidean)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A 128-bit integer is the gateway drug to fixed-width arithmetic. It is the smallest width that is no longer builtin, while still mapping cleanly to the underlying hardware. Once the carry and multiply patterns are explicit at 128 bits, extending them to 192 or 256 bits is straightforward. In production, we use 256-bit integers in our hot paths and go up to 564 bits for certain edge cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Representation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We represent a 128-bit unsigned integer as two 64-bit limbs. You can literally think of this as writing the &lt;code&gt;u128&lt;/code&gt; as a 2-digit number in base \(2^{64}\).
Because it's unsigned, we don't need to think about two's complement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#include &amp;lt;cstdint&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;immintrin.h&amp;gt; // _addcarry_u64, _subborrow_u64, _mulx_u64

// this is the type used in the intrinsics signature
// (and uint64_t is unsigned long, not unsigned long long...)
using u64 = unsigned long long;

struct u128
{
    u64 low = 0;
    u64 high = 0;
};
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Addition, with carry&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We start off easy. Addition is simply done using long addition on our base \(2^{64}\) digits. The intrinsic &lt;code&gt;_addcarry_u64&lt;/code&gt; corresponds to the x64 instruction &lt;code&gt;adc&lt;/code&gt; and is exactly what we need:
Given two &lt;code&gt;u64&lt;/code&gt; summands and an input carry (0 or 1), we get the &lt;code&gt;u64&lt;/code&gt; result (via a slightly cumbersome output parameter) and a new carry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;u128 operator+(u128 a, u128 b) 
{
    u128 r;
    unsigned char c = _addcarry_u64(0, a.low,  b.low,  &amp;amp;r.low);
    (void)_addcarry_u64(c, a.high, b.high, &amp;amp;r.high);
    return r;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The generated assembly is exactly what you would write by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;operator+(u128, u128):
        mov     rax, rdi
        add     rax, rdx
        adc     rsi, rcx
        mov     rdx, rsi
        ret
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The moves are just calling convention noise. The core is an &lt;code&gt;add&lt;/code&gt; (because the first addition has no input carry) followed by an &lt;code&gt;adc&lt;/code&gt;.
This is identical to what the compiler emits for &lt;code&gt;__uint128_t&lt;/code&gt; addition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A small but important point is that intrinsics are preferable to inline assembly here. They act like specialized IR operations. The compiler understands their semantics, can schedule around them, and can still optimize aggressively. Inline assembly is more of a black box and much easier to get wrong or inhibit optimizations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Subtraction: same story, inverted&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Subtraction mirrors addition almost perfectly. Instead of a carry, we track a borrow. On x64, this is &lt;code&gt;sbb&lt;/code&gt;, subtract with borrow.
The corresponding intrinsic is &lt;code&gt;_subborrow_u64&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;u128 operator-(u128 a, u128 b) 
{
    u128 r;
    unsigned char c = _subborrow_u64(0, a.low,  b.low,  &amp;amp;r.low);
    (void)_subborrow_u64(c, a.high, b.high, &amp;amp;r.high);
    return r;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And again, the assembly is exactly what we want.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;operator-(u128, u128):
        mov     rax, rdi
        sub     rax, rdx
        sbb     rsi, rcx
        mov     rdx, rsi
        ret
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, addition and subtraction are basically solved. There is no hidden cost and no abstraction penalty. It's also easy to see how this scales to larger integer types with one extra instruction per &lt;code&gt;u64&lt;/code&gt; "digit".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Multiplication: regrouping our &lt;code&gt;u64&lt;/code&gt; digits&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiplication is where things get more interesting. A 128-bit by 128-bit multiply produces a 256-bit result but we want only the lower 128 bit for our result. Same story with &lt;code&gt;u64 * u64&lt;/code&gt; really, which produces a 128 bit result in theory, but you usually only use the lower &lt;code&gt;u64&lt;/code&gt;.
Speaking of which, all modern 64-bit architectures give you access to fast &lt;code&gt;u64 * u64 -&amp;gt; u128&lt;/code&gt; instructions.
With BMI2, this is exposed as &lt;code&gt;_mulx_u64&lt;/code&gt;.
On MSVC, the equivalent is &lt;code&gt;_umul128&lt;/code&gt;.
This is our building block for large multiplication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can derive the code from writing the &lt;code&gt;u128 * u128&lt;/code&gt; as 2-digit long multiplication &lt;code&gt;(u64, u64) * (u64, u64)&lt;/code&gt; and then look sharply at what sums up to which digit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's how I do it on paper, but here we can also choose an algebraic route. Write the numbers as: $$ (a.\text{low} + 2^{64} \cdot a.\text{high}) \cdot (b.\text{low} + 2^{64} \cdot b.\text{high}) $$ Expanding this gives four terms. Of those, only three contribute to the low 128 bits:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;\(a_\text{low} \cdot b_\text{low}\) contributes both low and high parts&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;\(a_\text{low} \cdot b_\text{high}\) contributes to bits 64..127&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;\(a_\text{high} \cdot b_\text{low}\) contributes to bits 64..127&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;\(a_\text{high} \cdot b_\text{high}\) contributes only above bit 128 and can be discarded&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This works for larger integers as well, though summing up intermediate terms can produce carries for "higher digits".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;u128 operator*(u128 a, u128 b) 
{
    // we want the low 128 bits of:
    // (a.low + 2^64 a.high) * (b.low + 2^64 b.high)
    //
    // r.low  = lo64(a.low * b.low)
    // r.high = hi64(a.low * b.low)
    //        + lo64(a.low * b.high)
    //        + lo64(a.high * b.low)        (mod 2^64)

    // NOTE (MSVC): for multiply, you can use _umul128(a, b, &amp;amp;hi) instead of _mulx_u64.
    //              Clang/GCC: _mulx_u64 is BMI2 and needs -mbmi2.

    u128 r;

    u64 p0_hi;
    r.low = _mulx_u64(a.low, b.low, &amp;amp;p0_hi);

    // cross terms: only the low 64 bits contribute to r.high
    u64 t1_hi;
    u64 t1_lo = _mulx_u64(a.low,  b.high, &amp;amp;t1_hi);

    u64 t2_hi;
    u64 t2_lo = _mulx_u64(a.high, b.low,  &amp;amp;t2_hi);

    // simply add is sufficient: carries would land in bit 128 and are discarded
    r.high = p0_hi + t1_lo + t2_lo;

    return r;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that we do not need carry handling there. Any carry out of bit 127 would land in bit 128, which we are discarding anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The compiler output reflects this reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;operator*(u128, u128):
        mulx    r8, rax, rdi
        imul    rcx, rdi
        imul    rdx, rsi
        add     rdx, rcx
        add     rdx, r8
        ret
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The compiler chooses slightly different instructions and registers for the builtin &lt;code&gt;__uint128_t&lt;/code&gt; multiplication but is otherwise identical as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Equality&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now an easy one. &lt;code&gt;u128&lt;/code&gt; equality is simple structural equality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;bool operator==(u128 a, u128 b) 
{
    return a.low == b.low &amp;amp;&amp;amp; a.high == b.high;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The generated assembly is worth a quick look.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;operator==(u128, u128):
        xor     rdi, rdx
        xor     rsi, rcx
        or      rsi, rdi
        sete    al
        ret
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead of branching (as you might expect from the short-circuiting of &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt;), the compiler XORs the corresponding limbs.
XOR produces zero if and only if the inputs are equal.
ORing the results combines the checks.
If the final value is zero, both limbs were equal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pattern continues for larger integers, though we might see branching due to short-circuiting at some point. (We could of course just use the XOR approach in &lt;code&gt;operator==&lt;/code&gt; but it is distinctly less readable.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Comparison: borrow beats branching&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The straightforward way to compare two 128-bit integers is to compare the high parts first and then the low parts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;bool operator&amp;lt;(u128 a, u128 b)
{
    if (a.high != b.high) return a.high &amp;lt; b.high;
    return a.low &amp;lt; b.low;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is correct, but the codegen is not great:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;operator&amp;lt;(u128, u128):
        xor     r8d, r8d
        cmp     rdi, rdx
        setb    r8b
        xor     eax, eax
        cmp     rsi, rcx
        setb    al
        cmove   eax, r8d
        ret
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Works, but heavier than necessary. We can do better by leaning on the hardware borrow flag.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unsigned comparison &lt;code&gt;a &amp;lt; b&lt;/code&gt; is equivalent to checking whether &lt;code&gt;a - b&lt;/code&gt; produces a borrow:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;bool operator&amp;lt;(u128 a, u128 b) 
{
    u64 dont_care;

    // compute borrow from (a.low - b.low). If a.low &amp;lt; b.low =&amp;gt; borrow = 1.
    unsigned char borrow = _subborrow_u64(0, a.low, b.low, &amp;amp;dont_care);

    // now subtract highs with that borrow
    // final borrow tells us if a &amp;lt; b in 128-bit unsigned.
    borrow = _subborrow_u64(borrow, a.high, b.high, &amp;amp;dont_care);

    return borrow != 0;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The resulting assembly is minimal:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;operator&amp;lt;(u128, u128):
        cmp     rdi, rdx
        sbb     rsi, rcx
        setb    al
        ret
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One compare, one subtract with borrow, and a flag check. This is exactly the kind of codegen we want in hot code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A small use site&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make sure everything composes properly, let's build a slightly larger function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;u128 demo_u128(u128 a, u128 b) 
{
    u128 x = a + b;
    u128 y = a * b;
    return x &amp;lt; y
            ? y - x
            : x - y;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All operators inline cleanly:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;demo_u128(u128, u128):
        mov     r8, rdi
        add     r8, rdx
        mov     r9, rsi
        adc     r9, rcx
        mulx    rax, r10, rdi
        imul    rcx, rdi
        imul    rdx, rsi
        add     rdx, rcx
        add     rdx, rax
        mov     rax, r8
        sub     rax, r10
        mov     rcx, r9
        sbb     rcx, rdx
        jae     .LBB13_2
        sub     r10, r8
        sbb     rdx, r9
        mov     rax, r10
        mov     rcx, rdx
.LBB13_2:
        mov     rdx, rcx
        ret
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a branch for the ternary operator while the builtin version uses conditional moves instead. Which is better depends on data patterns but could go either way. I consider this basically as good as it gets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Platform notes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The examples shown are for x64 with Clang or GCC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On MSVC, &lt;code&gt;_addcarry_u64&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;_subborrow_u64&lt;/code&gt; work the same way.
For multiplication, &lt;code&gt;_umul128&lt;/code&gt; replaces &lt;code&gt;_mulx_u64&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On AArch64, the same approach applies using &lt;code&gt;adds&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;adcs&lt;/code&gt; instructions for addition, &lt;code&gt;subs&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sbcs&lt;/code&gt; for subtraction, and &lt;code&gt;mul + umulh&lt;/code&gt; for the low + high half of a 64-bit multiply.
The patterns carry over directly, even though the intrinsics differ slightly (and multiplication is split into two parts).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Outlook&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This &lt;code&gt;u128&lt;/code&gt; is the easiest large integer you can write.
Our goal is best performance, so we made sure that codegen is reasonably identical to the builtin &lt;code&gt;__uint128_t&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From here, the same patterns extend naturally to signed variants, widening multiplies such as u128 times u128 to u256, and chains of fixed-width integers like i192 or i256. More importantly, the same reasoning applies when you design predicate-specific arithmetic that only computes what is actually needed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lot of our performance really boils down to these types: No &lt;code&gt;BigInteger&lt;/code&gt; tax, no floating predicates (that need a few kB of stack space for the worst case).
Just a lot of straightline integer code and some light static branching.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Addendum 2026-01-24&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some notes based on reader feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On PowerPC: I don't know much about PowerPC or the availability of intrinsics, but the instructions you need are definitely there. For add/sub with carry, there's addc / adde for addition and subfc / subfe for subtraction with borrow. For wide multiplication, mulhdu gives you the high half of a 64-bit multiply (and mulhd for signed).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On GCC codegen with intrinsics: Someone pointed out that GCC doesn't always handle the intrinsic-based addition optimally. It sometimes moves the result through the stack before setting it in the final registers. This is related to writing directly to the result struct. If you write to "real" scalars first, the codegen is optimal again. A weird one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On division: There is no neat codegen for division. Even the builtin delegates to a library call. The naive but practical approach is binary long division, which finishes in up to 128 steps. Either branchless with fixed runtime or with a loop that searches for the next set bit. Either way it's a bit of work. Our exact predicates are always formulated in a division-free way simply because division would be expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On &lt;code&gt;_BitInt(N)&lt;/code&gt;:
The upcoming &lt;code&gt;_BitInt(N)&lt;/code&gt; type does work, but with caveats.
For B = 128, you get the normal codegen.
For B &amp;gt; 128, GCC calls into a function where the bit size is a runtime parameter.
So yes, they would work, but performance will be subpar for larger widths.
Clang generates properly inlined assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46849154</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 20:40:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>My iPhone 16 Pro Max produces garbage output when running MLX LLMs</title><link>https://journal.rafaelcosta.me/my-thousand-dollar-iphone-cant-do-math/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3402b8b4df265bde"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My iPhone 16 Pro Max produces garbage output when running MLX LLMs. An iPhone 15 Pro runs the same code perfectly. A MacBook Pro also runs the same code perfectly. The tensor outputs on the 16 show numerical values an order of magnitude wrong. I suspect it points to a hardware defect in the Neural Engine or some other ML-needed system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was a PITA to debug, but at least I got a blog post out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How did I get there?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was supposed to be a simple, unwinding-time project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the past few months I've been working on a &lt;del&gt;Clawdbot&lt;/del&gt; Moltbot clone that I've been calling Schmidt. It basically does the same kind of thing but with a custom chat UI instead of using Telegram, WhatsApp or other "I-can't-afford-to-be-banned-from" Service. This project has been consuming early days and late nights, so, to unwind, I decided that it may be a good idea to do something simpler. Since I recently subscribed to MiniMax M2.1, I thought I would do what many do and build a simple expense tracking app to test out the model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The core functionality is simple:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Automatically, upon each payment, add the expense to my app&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Update an Apple Watch complication with the % of my monthly budget spent&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Categorize the purchase for later analysis&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This all comes from being basically orphaned by Nubank's amazing native app (since replaced by a less-full-featured Flutter version).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Integrating with Shortcuts is manual, but reliable. Within 15 minutes I had a version of the app that could register purchases. The Apple Watch complication, the main goal, can come later. I'd rather get the classification feature, which should be easy, done quickly – so I figured.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Apple Intelligence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given the new LLM-bonanza we've been living through, it's no surprise that Apple has their own set of APIs developers such as me can use. Reading up on the documentation, it's a matter of checking for the availability of the feature and then asking the model to either reply to a textual query or, in my case, categorize a request.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MiniMax raced through it in a single prompt and then I ran it on my iPhone. First expense was a purchase at a shop called "Kasai Kitchin", classified as... &lt;code&gt;unknown&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;lb/&gt;Weird.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Checking the logs, it was clear: the model support was downloading. The feature hadn't been enabled. Again, weird. I should have it on. Anyway, I go into settings, do the weird dance of toggling it on and off – sadly, that's not surprising on Apple's services. Maybe my Settings.app got stuck in a weird state, who knows? – and wait for it to download.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After 4h I realized it was not going anywhere. Looking it up, it seems that many have the same issue (this thread shows 12 pages of frustrated users). Again, not a surprise for Apple's services recently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oh well, time to give up on the Apple Intelligence approach. Let's move on to the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;MLX LLM&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, the iOS framework engineers don't seem to be the only engineers at Apple capable of coming up with Machine Learning APIs in Swift. Apparently, there's a whole separate way of doing it – with models downloaded to your app. Not great for the user's storage, but great for me!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, MiniMax does it in a heartbeat, specially after being given documentation and one or two Medium posts. Time to run on my iPhone and... gibberish.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The CPU spins to 100% and the model starts generating. But it's all gibberish. And no "stop" token is generated, so this goes on for long.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, the only explanation is: I'm completely incompetent and can't even get a simple "ready made" framework to execute what I want. Or, rather, MiniMax is! The good thing about offloading your work to an LLM is that you can blame it for your shortcomings. Time to get my hands dirty and do it myself, typing code on my keyboard, like the ancient Mayan and Aztec programmers probably did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;My own MLX implementation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I went back to the documentation, to the Medium posts and, much to my surprise: MiniMax had followed it to the letter. Even went back to some deprecated methods of generation and it also was gibberish. And now there's no one to blame, but myself. I go to work everyday and this impostor-syndrome inducing problem silently consumes me. &lt;lb/&gt;After 3 days of trying to get it to work, I'm ready to give up...&lt;lb/&gt;...until, on a Tuesday morning, at 7-8 AM, I have an idea: let me, just in case, run this on my old iPhone 15 Pro. Up to this point, I was running it on my daily driver, an iPhone 16 Pro Max that was a replacement phone sent by Apple Care after a small clubbing mishap (in which my iPhone was irreparably crashed). I rush to get everything ready before it's time to go to work and: it works! Gemma, Qwen, and all other models generate coherent responses!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I stop and think: this cannot be a hardware issue, right? Of course not. The iPhone 15 is still running iOS 18. The iPhone 16 is running 26. It must be an OS issue. Well, time to be late for my work standup and update the old phone. The curiosity is too much. Many minutes later... same results, now on iOS 26. The plot is thickening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Finding the smoking gun: breakpoints in MLX's implementations of Gemma&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After that work day, and after many lunch and coffee discussions with coworkers about the sources of my troubles, I get home and immediately set myself on debugging MLX as it runs, if possible. The game plan is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use a known-to-be-reliable model, that fits in RAM (I went with quantized Gemma)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use a simple prompt, in my case "What is 2+2?"&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;To be really pedantic: the prompt was &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;start_of_turn&amp;gt;user\nWhat is 2+2?&amp;lt;end_of_turn&amp;gt;\n&amp;lt;start_of_turn&amp;gt;model&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;To be really pedantic: the prompt was &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Run everything with temperature set to &lt;code&gt;0.0&lt;/code&gt;– maybe that's enough to remove variability&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Find the model implementation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Find where the model iterates through the layers and&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Print out the MLXArray/Tensor with the values on each layer as the input goes through&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few moments later and I find where I need to be. Added the breakpoints, added the logs and off to the races.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I run it on my iPhone 16 Pro Max. The model loads and the prompt is "What is 2+2?". The tensors start printing out, line after line after line. For once, the logs aren't complete gibberish – they're numbers. Floating point values representing the model's internal state as it processes the input. I save the output to a file and do the same on my iPhone 15 Pro. Same model, same prompt, same code. Time to compare.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Welp, now it's definitely out of my expertise&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I grep for a pattern I know should be consistent – an array at log-line 58, right before the values get normalized/softmaxed. On a working device, I hypothesize this should be the same every time.&lt;lb/&gt;On the iPhone 15 Pro:&lt;code&gt;3: "[[[[53.875, 62.5625, -187.75, ..., 42.625, 6.25, -21.5625]]]]"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;On the iPhone 16 Pro Max:&lt;code&gt;3: "[[[[191.5, 23.625, 173.75, ..., 1298, -147.25, -162.5]]]]"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Huh. Not close. Not at all. These values are orders of magnitude off. I double check the start of the logs and both phones show the same:&lt;code&gt;1: "array([[[0.162842, -0.162842, -0.48877, ..., -0.176636, 0.0001297, 0.088501],\n [-0.348633, -2.78906, 0, ..., 0.84668, 0, -1.69336],\n [-1.30957, 1.57324, -1.30957, ..., -0.0010376, -0.0010376, 1.12305],\n ...,\n [-0.348633, -2.78906, 0, ..., 0.84668, 0, -1.69336],\n [0.296875, 0.59375, 0.890625, ..., -0.59375, 0.296875, -0.890137],\n [1.02734, -0.616211, -0.616211, ..., -0.275879, -0.551758, 0.275879]]], dtype=float16)"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OK, so the model receives the same thing as input, but at some point, the values start to go off. Like, way off. In order to make sure I'm not crazy, I do one last thing: run the same thing on my Mac. Make the app run on iPad compatibility mode and...&lt;code&gt;3: "[[[[53.875, 62.5625, -187.75, ..., 42.625, 6.25, -21.5625]]]]"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bingo! Same as iPhone 15!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The model isn't broken. The code isn't broken. Most importantly, I'm not broken*. My phone is broken.&lt;lb/&gt;*arguable, but besides the point here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;What's going on?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let me explain what I think it's going on here: the iPhone 16 Pro Max contains Apple's A18 chip with its Neural Engine—a specialized accelerator for machine learning operations. MLX uses Metal to compile tensor operations for this accelerator. Somewhere in that stack, the computations are going very wrong. I don't think it's a widespread issue but, I do get disappointed that a relatively newly replaced iPhone from Apple Care came with such an issue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, if my Apple Intelligence troubles are related – and they might as well be, I'd assume that code and MLX are not dissimilar in operations being done –, it could be that all the 12 pages of users are users in a similar dillema, but without the means of debugging it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What now?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I spent 3 days thinking I was incompetent. I blamed MiniMax. I blamed myself. The entire time, my $1,400 phone had a broken hardware. I could lose more time figuring out exactly what is wrong with it but it’s literally not worth my time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I guess I can at least take a lesson that, when debugging, I should always consider the physical layer. I spent three days assuming this was a software problem – my code, the library, the framework, my skills as a developer. The breakthrough was basically: "What if I'm not dumb and it's not my code?"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As for my phone: it'll probably go back to Apple, as a trade in for a new iPhone 17 Pro Max that hopefully 🤞 can do math.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Update on Feb. 1st:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, now it's Feb. 1st and I have an iPhone 17 Pro Max to test with and... everything works as expected. So it's pretty safe to say that THAT specific instance of iPhone 16 Pro Max was hardware-defective.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46849258</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 20:51:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Defeating a 40-year-old copy protection dongle</title><link>https://dmitrybrant.com/2026/02/01/defeating-a-40-year-old-copy-protection-dongle</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a99b5744e017df58"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s right — this little device is what stood between me and the ability to run an even older piece of software that I recently unearthed during an expedition of software archaeology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a bit more background, I was recently involved in helping a friend’s accounting firm to move away from using an extremely legacy software package that they had locked themselves into using for the last four decades.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This software was built using a programming language called RPG (“Report Program Generator”), which is older than COBOL (!), and was used with IBM’s midrange computers such as the System/3, System/32, and all the way up to the AS/400. Apparently, RPG was subsequently ported to MS-DOS, so that the same software tools built with RPG could run on personal computers, which is how we ended up here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This accounting firm was actually using a Windows 98 computer (yep, in 2026), and running the RPG software inside a DOS console window. And it turned out that, in order to run this software, it requires a special hardware copy-protection dongle to be attached to the computer’s parallel port! This was a relatively common practice in those days, particularly with “enterprise” software vendors who wanted to protect their very important™ software from unauthorized use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sadly, most of the text and markings on the dongle’s label has been worn or scratched off, but we can make out several clues:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The words “Stamford, CT”, and what’s very likely the logo of a company called “Software Security Inc”. The only evidence for the existence of this company is this record of them exhibiting their wares at SIGGRAPH conferences in the early 1990s, as well as several patents issued to them, relating to software protection.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A word that seems to say “RUNTIME”, which will become clear in a bit.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My first course of action was to take a disk image of the Windows 98 PC that was running this software, and get it running in an emulator, so that we could see what the software actually does, and perhaps export the data from this software into a more modern format, to be used with modern accounting tools. But of course all of this requires the hardware dongle; none of the accounting tools seem to work without it plugged in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before doing anything, I looked through the disk image for any additional interesting clues, and found plenty of fascinating (and archaeologically significant?) stuff:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We’ve got a compiler for the RPG II language (excellent!), made by a company called Software West Inc.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Even better, there are two versions of the RPG II compiler, released on various dates in the 1990s by Software West.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We’ve got the complete source code of the accounting software, written in RPG. It looks like the full accounting package consists of numerous RPG modules, with a gnarly combination of DOS batch files for orchestrating them, all set up as a “menu” system for the user to navigate using number combinations. Clearly the author of this accounting system was originally an IBM mainframe programmer, and insisted on bringing those skills over to DOS, with mixed results.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I began by playing around with the RPG compiler in isolation, and I learned very quickly that it’s the RPG compiler itself that requires the hardware dongle, and then the compiler automatically injects the same copy-protection logic into any executables it generates. This explains the text that seems to say “RUNTIME” on the dongle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The compiler consists of a few executable files, notably &lt;code&gt;RPGC.EXE&lt;/code&gt;, which is the compiler, and &lt;code&gt;SEU.EXE&lt;/code&gt;, which is a source editor (“Source Entry Utility”). Here’s what we get when we launch SEU without the dongle, after a couple of seconds:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A bit rude, but this gives us an important clue: this program must be trying to communicate over the parallel port over the course of a few seconds (which could give us an opportunity to pause it for debugging, and see what it’s doing during that time), and then exits with a message (which we can now find in a disassembly of the program, and trace how it gets there).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A great tool for disassembling executables of this vintage is Reko. It understands 16-bit real mode executables, and even attempts to decompile them into readable C code that corresponds to the disassembly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so, looking at the decompiled/disassembled code in Reko, I expected to find &lt;code&gt;in&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;out&lt;/code&gt; instructions, which would be the telltale sign of the program trying to communicate with the parallel port through the PC’s I/O ports. However… I didn’t see an &lt;code&gt;in&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;out&lt;/code&gt; instruction anywhere! But then I noticed something: Reko disassembled the executable into two “segments”: &lt;code&gt;0800&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;0809&lt;/code&gt;, and I was only looking at segment &lt;code&gt;0809&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we look at segment &lt;code&gt;0800&lt;/code&gt;, we see the smoking gun: &lt;code&gt;in&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;out&lt;/code&gt; instructions, meaning that the copy-protection routine is definitely here, and best of all, the entire code segment is a mere 0x90 bytes, which suggests that the entire routine should be pretty easy to unravel and understand. For some reason, Reko was not able to decompile this code into a C representation, but it still produced a disassembly, which will work just fine for our purposes. Maybe this was a primitive form of obfuscation from those early days, which is now confusing Reko and preventing it from associating this chunk of code with the rest of the program… who knows.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a GitHub Gist with the disassembly of this code, along with my annotations and notes. My x86 assembly knowledge is a little rusty, but here is the gist of what this code does:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It’s definitely a single self-contained routine, intended to be called using a “far” &lt;code&gt;CALL&lt;/code&gt;instruction, since it returns with a&lt;code&gt;RETF&lt;/code&gt;instruction.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It begins by detecting the address of the parallel port, by reading the BIOS data area. If the computer has more than one parallel port, the dongle must be connected to the first parallel port (LPT1).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It performs a loop where it writes values to the data register of the parallel port, and then reads the status register, and accumulates responses in the &lt;code&gt;BH&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;BL&lt;/code&gt;registers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;At the end of the routine, the “result” of the whole procedure is stored in the &lt;code&gt;BX&lt;/code&gt;register (&lt;code&gt;BH&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;BL&lt;/code&gt;together), which will presumably be “verified” by the caller of the routine.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Very importantly, there doesn’t seem to be any “input” into this routine. It doesn’t pop anything from the stack, nor does it care about any register values passed into it. Which can only mean that the result of this routine is completely constant! No matter what complicated back-and-forth it does with the dongle, the result of this routine should always be the same.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the knowledge that this routine must exit with some magic value stored in &lt;code&gt;BX&lt;/code&gt;, we can now patch the first few bytes of the routine to do just that! Not yet knowing which value to put in &lt;code&gt;BX&lt;/code&gt;, let’s start with 1234:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BB 34 12       MOV BX, 1234h
CB             RETF
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only the first four bytes need patching — set &lt;code&gt;BX&lt;/code&gt; to our desired value, and get out of there (&lt;code&gt;RETF&lt;/code&gt;). Running the patched executable with these new bytes still fails (expectedly) with the same message of “No dongle, no edit”, but it fails immediately, instead of after several seconds of talking to the parallel port. Progress!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stepping through the disassembly more closely, we get another major clue: The only value that &lt;code&gt;BH&lt;/code&gt; can be at the end of the routine is 76h (this is hard-coded into the routine). So, our total value for the magic number in &lt;code&gt;BX&lt;/code&gt; must be of the form 76xx. In other words, only the &lt;code&gt;BL&lt;/code&gt; value remains unknown:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BB __ 76       MOV BX, 76__h
CB             RETF
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since &lt;code&gt;BL&lt;/code&gt; is an 8-bit register, it can only have 256 possible values. And what do we do when we have 256 combinations to try? Brute force it! I whipped up a script that plugs a value into that particular byte (from 0 to 255) and programmatically launches the executable in DosBox, and observes the output. Lo and behold, it worked! The brute forcing didn’t take long at all, because the correct number turned out to be… 6. Meaning that the total magic number in &lt;code&gt;BX&lt;/code&gt; should be 7606h:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BB 06 76       MOV BX, 7606h
CB             RETF
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bingo!&lt;lb/&gt; And then, proceeding to examine the other executable files in the compiler suite, the parallel port routine turns out to be exactly the same. All of the executables have the exact same copy protection logic, as if it was rubber-stamped onto them. In fact, when the compiler (&lt;code&gt;RPGC.EXE&lt;/code&gt;) compiles some RPG source code, it seems to copy the parallel port routine from itself into the compiled program. That’s right: the patched version of the compiler will produce executables with the same patched copy protection routine! Very convenient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I must say, this copy protection mechanism seems a bit… simplistic? A hardware dongle that just passes back a constant number? Defeatable with a four-byte patch? Is this really worthy of a patent? But who am I to pass judgment. It’s possible that I haven’t fully understood the logic, and the copy protection will somehow re-surface in another way. It’s also possible that the creators of the RPG compiler (Software West, Inc) didn’t take proper advantage of the hardware dongle, and used it in a way that is so easily bypassed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In any case, Software West’s RPG II compiler is now free from the constraint of the parallel port dongle! And at some point soon, I’ll work on purging any PII from the compiler directories, and make this compiler available as an artifact of computing history. It doesn’t seem to be available anywhere else on the web. If anyone reading this was associated with Software West Inc, feel free to get in touch — I have many questions!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46849567</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 21:30:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Treasures found on HS2 route stored in secret warehouse</title><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c93v21q5xdvo</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bffb9117a88385da"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Treasures found on HS2 route stored in secret warehouse&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Treasures unearthed by hundreds of archaeologists during the ongoing construction of the controversial HS2 train line have been shown exclusively to the BBC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 450,000 objects, which are being held in a secret warehouse, include a possible Roman gladiator's tag, a hand axe that may be more than 40,000 years old and 19th Century gold dentures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is an "unprecedented" amount and array of items, which will yield new insights into Britain's past, says the Centre for British Archaeology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Major building developments in the UK need land to be assessed by archaeologists as part of the planning process, to protect heritage sites.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since 2018 around 1,000 archaeologists have been involved in 60 digs along the route HS2 is set to take between London to Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the route is not currently scheduled to open until after 2033 due to delays, archaeologists say their fieldwork is largely complete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The warehouse's location is a closely guarded secret for security purposes. All we can say is that it is in Yorkshire. Inside are shelves and shelves of pallets, loaded with around 7,300 boxes of historic items destined for further research.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The future of many objects, including whether they will stay in storage or be displayed, is still undecided, along with their ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Historic England commended the team for revealing "new and exciting sites spanning over 10,000 years of our past".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But building HS2 has changed the landscape along its route, cutting into fields and communities, and dividing opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Critics, such as Greg Smith, MP for Mid Buckinghamshire, say soaring costs, delays, abandoned villages and damage to the natural and historic environment mean that it is not worth building.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It should not have cost the taxpayer tens of billions of pounds to build a railway that no-one wants and brings so much destruction," Smith says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;HS2 said in response: "Chief Executive Mark Wild has been clear that overall delivery of HS2 has been unacceptable and he's committed to ending the project's cycle of cost increases and delays."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Our specialist archaeology team and contractors have carefully excavated numerous sites and have shown care and respect throughout this work."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Whether HS2 is a good or bad thing is debatable, but I tell you what, if they built the railway and they didn't do the archaeology that would be more tragic," said historian Graham Evans, who chairs the Northamptonshire Battlefields Society.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The store holds showstoppers such as Roman statue heads and a gold 'three lions' pendant from the 13th-14th Century.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the ground in one area is a bubble-wrapped empty coffin dating to 1799, with a smaller one next to it wrapped in masking tape - sobering reminders that this store is a snapshot of real lives once lived.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the objects discovered have already been shown to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have picked out six that have never been on display. You can see where they were found on the HS2 route map below - then scroll further down to see the objects and read about their history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Palaeolithic hand axe&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experts think this is more than 40,000 years old and was made by Neanderthals or an earlier species of human.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Found in the Edgcote area in Northamptonshire, it has a sharp edge likely designed for butchering animals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hand axes were held in the palm rather than attached to a wooden handle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"There is something tactile about it when you hold it," said Dr Sara Machin, the finds lead for Access +, the consortium of archaeologists in charge of this project. "Even now it fits snugly in my hand."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Roman gladiator tag&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The small piece of carved thin bone bears an inscription. Experts would expect it to read if complete: "DOMINE VICTOR VINCAS FELIX" or "Lord Victor, may you win and be lucky."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Discovered in Northamptonshire, Machin says it could have belonged to an active or former Roman gladiator, or even be a spectator's souvenir, even though there is no evidence of an arena or circus space in that part of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was recovered from a large pottery vessel containing cremated human remains, with an X on the lid.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dr John Pearce Reader in Archaeology at Kings College University said that a link to a gladiator was possible, but added that "with more forensic analysis of the burial, a different story may come to light".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Anglo-Saxon spindle whorl&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thought to be made from a cattle femur, this decorated Anglo-Saxon spindle whorl, used to provide weight while spinning yarn, was unearthed from farmland near Bishopstone, Buckinghamshire.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"It's a very interesting piece of evidence of textile advancements in the Anglo-Saxon period," said Willow Major, a post-excavation assistant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Its polished surface leads her to believe it got a lot of use and was very dear to someone, she said, adding that interestingly, the ring and dot motif had been found on spinning tools from the much earlier Iron age.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Medieval die&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A tiny polished die recovered from a deserted medieval village in Lower Radbourne, Warwickshire, resembles modern ones, but with a different numbering format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Its imperfections, with one side longer than the others, stand it in contrast with today's mass-produced dice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pug found in a grave&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This complete figurine of a seated pug dog in plain white-glazed porcelain with black details was found in the grave of an unnamed female at St James' Gardens in Euston.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is thought to have been made in the Derby porcelain factory around 1770-1800.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;19th Century gold dentures&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Every box has a surprise," Machin said as she unwrapped perhaps the most bizarre item here, thought to be from the 19th Century: a set of lower gold dentures found at St Mary's Old Church in Stoke Mandeville.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It contains six teeth and has a number stamped on the inside.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"These are objects, but they all relate to people," Machin said. "It's all about the people who lived in these areas going back thousands of years and we can start writing the stories about their lives and what they can tell us."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;'Extraordinary' scale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The scale is what makes it so extraordinary," Neil Redfern from the Council for British Archaeology says comparing HS2 to other big development projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"But it is the length of the scheme and the landscapes and places that HS2 passed through that make the collection of sites and material so interesting. The research potential from this material is remarkable."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He believes that the finds could help people understand wider landscape change now and in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To dig deeper into these stories, archaeologists are now entering the second phase of works, including further condition, cleaning and conservation checks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More plans are afoot to show the objects. Artefacts from the Wendover Saxon cemetery, where 122 graves were unearthed, will soon go on display for the first time at a Discover Bucks Museum exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the future of other items is less clear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A spokesperson for HS2 explained that under English property law, archaeological and historical objects found during the works will either belong to the government or landowners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Occasionally landowners may wish to retain title to objects, in which case they will be returned to their care," said the spokesperson.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Charlotte Self, archive manager for the project said she and her team were asking landowners to donate them where possible, so people around the route could enjoy them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"I would love to see the majority of these items deposited with the local museums from near where they were found," she said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get our flagship newsletter with all the headlines you need to start the day. Sign up here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46849926</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 22:14:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: NanoClaw – “Clawdbot” in 500 lines of TS with Apple container isolation</title><link>https://github.com/gavrielc/nanoclaw</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="1f0c5d761f97c4e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My personal Claude assistant that runs securely in Apple containers. Lightweight and built to be understood and customized for your own needs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenClaw is an impressive project with a great vision. But I can't sleep well running software I don't understand with access to my life. OpenClaw has 52+ modules, 8 config management files, 45+ dependencies, and abstractions for 15 channel providers. Security is application-level (allowlists, pairing codes) rather than OS isolation. Everything runs in one Node process with shared memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NanoClaw gives you the same core functionality in a codebase you can understand in 8 minutes. One process. A handful of files. Agents run in actual Linux containers with filesystem isolation, not behind permission checks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/gavrielc/nanoclaw.git
cd nanoclaw
claude&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then run &lt;code&gt;/setup&lt;/code&gt;. Claude Code handles everything: dependencies, authentication, container setup, service configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Small enough to understand. One process, a few source files. No microservices, no message queues, no abstraction layers. Have Claude Code walk you through it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Secure by isolation. Agents run in Linux containers (Apple Container). They can only see what's explicitly mounted. Bash access is safe because commands run inside the container, not on your Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Built for one user. This isn't a framework. It's working software that fits my exact needs. You fork it and have Claude Code make it match your exact needs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Customization = code changes. No configuration sprawl. Want different behavior? Modify the code. The codebase is small enough that this is safe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI-native. No installation wizard; Claude Code guides setup. No monitoring dashboard; ask Claude what's happening. No debugging tools; describe the problem, Claude fixes it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Skills over features. Contributors shouldn't add features (e.g. support for Telegram) to the codebase. Instead, they contribute claude code skills like &lt;code&gt;/add-telegram&lt;/code&gt; that transform your fork. You end up with clean code that does exactly what you need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Best harness, best model. This runs on Claude Agent SDK, which means you're running Claude Code directly. The harness matters. A bad harness makes even smart models seem dumb, a good harness gives them superpowers. Claude Code is (IMO) the best harness available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No ToS gray areas. Because it uses Claude Agent SDK natively with no hacks or workarounds, using your subscription with your auth token is completely legitimate (I think). No risk of being shut down for terms of service violations (I am not a lawyer).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;WhatsApp I/O - Message Claude from your phone&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Isolated group context - Each group has its own &lt;code&gt;CLAUDE.md&lt;/code&gt;memory, isolated filesystem, and runs in its own container sandbox with only that filesystem mounted&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Main channel - Your private channel (self-chat) for admin control; every other group is completely isolated&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Scheduled tasks - Recurring jobs that run Claude and can message you back&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Web access - Search and fetch content&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Container isolation - Agents sandboxed in Apple containers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Optional integrations - Add Gmail (&lt;code&gt;/add-gmail&lt;/code&gt;) and more via skills&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Talk to your assistant with the trigger word (default: &lt;code&gt;@Andy&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@Andy send an overview of the sales pipeline every weekday morning at 9am (has access to my Obsidian vault folder)
@Andy review the git history for the past week each Friday and update the README if there's drift
@Andy every Monday at 8am, compile news on AI developments from Hacker News and TechCrunch and message me a briefing
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the main channel (your self-chat), you can manage groups and tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@Andy list all scheduled tasks across groups
@Andy pause the Monday briefing task
@Andy join the Family Chat group
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are no configuration files to learn. Just tell Claude Code what you want:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Change the trigger word to @Bob"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Remember in the future to make responses shorter and more direct"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Add a custom greeting when I say good morning"&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;"Store conversation summaries weekly"&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or run &lt;code&gt;/customize&lt;/code&gt; for guided changes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The codebase is small enough that Claude can safely modify it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don't add features. Add skills.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to add Telegram support, don't create a PR that adds Telegram alongside WhatsApp. Instead, contribute a skill file (&lt;code&gt;.claude/skills/add-telegram/SKILL.md&lt;/code&gt;) that teaches Claude Code how to transform a NanoClaw installation to use Telegram.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users then run &lt;code&gt;/add-telegram&lt;/code&gt; on their fork and get clean code that does exactly what they need, not a bloated system trying to support every use case.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Skills we'd love to see:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Communication Channels&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/add-telegram&lt;/code&gt;- Add Telegram as channel. Should give the user option to replace WhatsApp or add as additional channel. Also should be possible to add it as a control channel (where it can trigger actions) or just a channel that can be used in actions triggered elsewhere&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/add-slack&lt;/code&gt;- Add Slack&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/add-discord&lt;/code&gt;- Add Discord&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Platform Support&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/setup-windows&lt;/code&gt;- Windows via WSL2 + Docker&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Session Management&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/add-clear&lt;/code&gt;- Add a&lt;code&gt;/clear&lt;/code&gt;command that compacts the conversation (summarizes context while preserving critical information in the same session). Requires figuring out how to trigger compaction programmatically via the Claude Agent SDK.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;macOS Tahoe (26) or later - runs great on Mac Mini&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Node.js 20+&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Claude Code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Apple Container&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;WhatsApp (baileys) --&amp;gt; SQLite --&amp;gt; Polling loop --&amp;gt; Container (Claude Agent SDK) --&amp;gt; Response
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Single Node.js process. Agents execute in isolated Linux containers with mounted directories. IPC via filesystem. No daemons, no queues, no complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key files:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;src/index.ts&lt;/code&gt;- Main app: WhatsApp connection, routing, IPC&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;src/container-runner.ts&lt;/code&gt;- Spawns agent containers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;src/task-scheduler.ts&lt;/code&gt;- Runs scheduled tasks&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;src/db.ts&lt;/code&gt;- SQLite operations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;groups/*/CLAUDE.md&lt;/code&gt;- Per-group memory&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why WhatsApp and not Telegram/Signal/etc?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because I use WhatsApp. Fork it and run a skill to change it. That's the whole point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why Apple Container instead of Docker?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lightweight, fast, and built into macOS. Requires macOS Tahoe and runs great on a Mac Mini. Contribute a skill to convert to Docker if you want Docker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Can I run this on Linux?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes. Run Claude Code and say "make this run on Linux." ~30 min of back-and-forth and it'll work. When you're done, ask Claude to create a skill explaining how to make it work on Linux, then contribute the skill back to the project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is this secure?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Agents run in containers, not behind application-level permission checks. They can only access explicitly mounted directories. You should still review what you're running, but the codebase is small enough that you actually can. See docs/SECURITY.md for the full security model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why no configuration files?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We don't want configuration sprawl. Every user should customize it to so that the code matches exactly what they want rather than configuring a generic system. If you like having config files, tell Claude to add them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How do I debug issues?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ask Claude Code. "Why isn't the scheduler running?" "What's in the recent logs?" "Why did this message not get a response?" That's the AI-native approach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why isn't the setup working for me?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't know. Run &lt;code&gt;claude&lt;/code&gt;, then run &lt;code&gt;/debug&lt;/code&gt;. If claude finds an issue that is likely affecting other users, open a PR to modify the setup SKILL.md.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What changes will be accepted into the codebase?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security fixes, bug fixes, and clear improvements to the base configuration. That's it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everything else (new capabilities, OS compatibility, hardware support, enhancements) should be contributed as skills.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This keeps the base system minimal and lets every user customize their installation without inheriting features they don't want.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46850205</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 22:49:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Two kinds of AI users are emerging</title><link>https://martinalderson.com/posts/two-kinds-of-ai-users-are-emerging/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="24210a181cb681fe"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Two kinds of AI users are emerging. The gap between them is astonishing.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It still shocks me how much difference there is between AI users. I think it explains a lot about the often confusing (to me) coverage in the media about AI and its productivity impact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think it's clear there are two types of users to me now, and by extension, the organisations they work for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, you have the "power users", who are all in on adopting new AI technology - Claude Code, MCPs, skills, etc. Surprisingly, these people are often not very technical. I've seen far more non-technical people than I'd expect using Claude Code in terminal, using it for dozens of non-SWE tasks. Finance roles seem to be getting enormous value out of it (unsurprisingly, as Excel on the finance side is remarkably limiting when you start getting used to the power of a full programming ecosystem like Python).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Secondly, you have the people who are generally only chatting to ChatGPT or similar. So many people I wouldn't expect are still in this camp.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;M365 Copilot has a lot to answer for&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One extremely jarring realisation was just how poor Microsoft Copilot is. It has enormous market share in enterprise as it is bundled in with various Office 365 subscriptions, yet feels like a poorly cloned version of the (already not great) ChatGPT interface. The "agent" feature is absolutely laughable compared to what a CLI coding agent (including Microsoft's own GitHub confusingly-named-Copilot CLI).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To really underline this, Microsoft itself is rolling out Claude Code to internal teams[1], despite (obviously) having access to Copilot at near zero cost, and significant ownership of OpenAI. I think this sums up quite how far behind they are&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem is that in enterprise Copilot is often the only allowed AI tool, so that's all you can use without either potentially losing your job or spending a lot of effort trying to procure and use another AI tool. It's slow, the code execution tool in it doesn't work properly and fails horribly with large(ish) files, seemingly due to very very aggressive memory and CPU limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is becoming an existential risk for many enterprises. Senior decision makers are no doubt using these tools with such poor results and are therefore writing off AI, and/or spending a fortune with various large consulting and management consultancy outfits to get not very far.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why enterprise is so at risk&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enterprise corporate IT policy results in a completely disastrous combination of limitations that basically ensure that people cannot successfully use more 'cutting edge' AI tooling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, they tend to have extremely locked down environments, with no ability to run even a basic script interpreter locally (VBA if you are lucky, but even that may be limited by various Group Policies). Secondly, they're locked into legacy software with no real "internal facing" APIs on their core workflows, which means agents have nothing to connect to even if you could run them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, they tend to have extremely siloed engineering departments (which may be completely outsourced), so there's nobody internally who could build the infrastructure to run safely sandboxed agents even if they wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The security concerns are real. You definitely do not want people YOLOing coding agents over production databases with no control, and as I've covered, sandboxing agents is difficult[2].&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, this does cause a real problem in so much that you don't have an engineering team that can help build the infrastructure to run safely sandboxed agents against your datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The gap&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've also spoken to many smaller companies that don't have all this baggage and are absolutely flying with AI. The gap is so obvious when you can see both sides of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On one hand, you have Microsoft's (awful) Copilot integration for Excel (in fairness, the Gemini integration in Google Sheets is also bad). So you can imagine financial directors trying to use it and it making a complete mess of the most simple tasks and never touching it again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other you have a non-technical executive who's got his head round Claude Code and can run e.g. Python locally. I helped one recently almost one-shot[3] converting a 30 sheet mind numbingly complicated Excel financial model to Python with Claude Code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the model is in Python, you effectively have a data science team in your pocket with Claude Code. You can easily run Monte Carlo simulations, pull external data sources as inputs, build web dashboards and have Claude Code work with you to really integrate weaknesses in your model (or business). It's a pretty magical experience watching someone realise they have so much power at their fingertips, without having to grind away for hours/days in Excel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This effectively leads to a situation where smaller company employees are able to be so much more productive than the equivalent at an enterprise. It often used to be that people at small companies really envied the resources &amp;amp; teams that their larger competitors had access to - but increasingly I think the pendulum is swinging the other way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The future&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm starting to get a feel for what the future of work looks like. The first observation is that (often) the real leaps are being made organically by employees, not from a top down AI strategy. Where I see the real productivity gains are small teams deciding to try and build an AI assisted workflow for a process, and as they are the ones that know that process inside out they can get very good results - unlike an often outsourced software engineering team who have absolutely zero experience doing the process that they are helping automate. I think this is the opposite of what most 'digital transformation' projects looked like in enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Secondly, companies that have some sort of APIs for internal systems are going to be able to do far more than those that don't. This might be as simple as a readonly data warehouse employees can connect to and run queries on behalf of users, or it could be as far as many complex core business processes being completely APId.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thirdly, this all needs to be wrapped up in some sort of secure mechanism, but I actually think a hosted VM running some sort of code agent with well thought through network restrictions would work well, at least for read only reporting. For creating and editing data I don't think we quite have the model for non technical users (especially) to be able to use agents safely (yet).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, legacy enterprise SaaS players either have enormous lock in, or are extremely vulnerable depending on how you look at it. Most are not "API-first" products, and the APIs they have tend to be really for developer usage - not optimised for thousands of employees to ping in weird and wonderful inefficient ways. But if they are the source of truth for the company, they are going to be very difficult to migrate away from and bottleneck a lot of productivity gains.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, smaller companies tend to use newer products which have far better thought through APIs (simply because they weren't often originally created many decades ago with various interfaces grafted on over time).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The user prompts, the agent synthesises - connecting to APIs and producing outputs on demand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I've come to realise is that the power of having a bash sandbox with a programming language and API access to systems, combined with an agentic harness, results in outrageously good results for non technical users. It can effectively replace nearly every standard productivity app out there - both classic Microsoft Office style ones - and also web apps. It can build any report you ask for - and export it however you like. To me this seems like the future of knowledge work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bifurcation is real and seems to be, if anything, speeding up dramatically. I don't think there's ever been a time in history where a tiny team can outcompete a company one thousand times its size so easily.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Microsoft is using Claude Code internally while selling you Copilot ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Let's keep in mind that users already have access to these systems. CISOs need to figure out how to enable these kind of secure VMs en masse. There's already precedent for this with Codespaces - it just requires a similar approach scaled up to the entire organisation. ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Two or three prompts got it there, using plan mode to figure out the structure of the Excel sheet, then prompting to implement it. It even added unit tests to the Python model itself, which I was impressed with! ↩︎&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46850588</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 23:45:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Time Machine-style Backups with rsync (2018)</title><link>https://samuelhewitt.com/blog/2018-06-05-time-machine-style-backups-with-rsync</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="be0e885544af93ba"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Data Hoarding 101&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have digital backups of data, especially of my photos, going back almost a decade (Iâm not that old) but itâs only recently that I got into creating time-snapshots of my backups, after I mistakenly deleted a bunch of (non-crucial) personal files with a stray &lt;code&gt;rsync --delete&lt;/code&gt; on a directory I had not backed-up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My home server used be compatible with macOSâs Time Machine and when I kept most things on my Mac that was useful, but I changed my data hoarding habits and that solution started to not be the optimal one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Time Based Snapshots Using rsync&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt; has got to be one of my favourite and most used utilities. I use it constantly to transfer files between machine on my local network (and remote ones) but Iâve discovered itâs very useful as a backup tool. The following is a short script that uses &lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt; to create snapshots of the my data directory to another directory (they are mount points on two different drives):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh

TIMESTAMP=`date "+%Y-%m-%dT%H-%M-%S"`
USER=user
SOURCEDIR=/var/data/backups
TARGETDIR=/var/redundancy

# Create new backup using rsync and output to log
rsync -avPh --delete --link-dest=$TARGETDIR/current $SOURCEDIR/$USER/ $TARGETDIR/$USER-$TIMESTAMP &amp;gt; /var/log/rsync/$TIMESTAMP.log 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1

# check exit status to see if backup failed
if [ "$?" = 0 ]; then
    # Remove link to current backup
    rm -f $TARGETDIR/current
    # Create link to the newest backup
    ln -s $TARGETDIR/$USER-$TIMESTAMP $TARGETDIR/current
else
    # Rename directory if failed
    mv $TARGETDIR/$USER-$TIMESTAMP $TARGETDIR/failed-$USER-$TIMESTAMP
fi
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Essentially this script creates incremental copies of backups for a given user on the system by comparing any changes to that userâs data directory (&lt;code&gt;$SOURCEDIR&lt;/code&gt;) with the current backup (&lt;code&gt;$TARGETDIR&lt;/code&gt;) and making a new snapshot of any changes with the date.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now all that remains is to save this script somewhere and create a &lt;code&gt;cron&lt;/code&gt; job to run it on an automatic interval:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# daily at 5am
0 5 * * * bash /usr/local/bin/rsync-time-machine
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Hard Links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This method uses rsyncâs &lt;code&gt;--link-dest&lt;/code&gt; option to create hard-links so that isnât duplicative of file data (the contents are only stored once, so you donât use twice as much) and you can delete snapshots at will. (The links do still take up some space but itâs relatively insignificant.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Be careful when deleting old snapshots. A new full backup of should be made before further incremental ones. I have to give a shoutout to Mike Rubel whose post was helpful in coming up with this solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46850709</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Wikipedia as a doomscrollable social media feed</title><link>https://xikipedia.org</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d4d05bb2748febb3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Loading...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Xikipedia is a pseudo social media feed that algorithmically shows you content from Simple Wikipedia. It is made as a demonstration of how even a basic non-ML algorithm with no data from other users can quickly learn what you engage with to suggest you more similar content. No data is collected or shared here, the algorithm runs locally and the data disappears once you refresh or close the tab.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source code on GitHub, discuss on fedi, bluesky, or twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pick some categories to get started (optional)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or add your own&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the content and images shown is from random Wikipedia articles, you will likely see NSFW content. Please only continue if you're an adult.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46850803</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:12:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Actors: A Model of Concurrent Computation [pdf] (1985)</title><link>https://apps.dtic.mil/sti/tr/pdf/ADA157917.pdf</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46851192</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 01:11:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Building a Telegram Bot with Cloudflare Workers, Durable Objects and Grammy</title><link>https://flashblaze.xyz/posts/cloudflare-workers-durable-objects-telegram-bot/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a7110b530835dec2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last month I visited my friend for a week or so who mentioned I drink way less water and he showed me the reading on his water purifier. On average, I drank like 1L of water.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I then started keeping track of how much water I drank, but then I used to miss a couple of days. So I thought, why not create an app to track this and also remind myself to drink water.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I present to you Drinky which does just that. If you’re interested, the GitHub repo is here. This blog post will go into why I went via the bot route, the tech stack I chose and the things I learned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Has to be a new tech stack and low friction to use&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I didn’t want to develop another web app in which I had to log in to. I thought of creating an Android app and to store the data locally but it would have been overkill and it would also be a hassle if I wanted to share it with somebody. I had already built a Telegram bot to notify when your Blender render is completed (Render Notifier) and I knew the Telegram API was also pretty nice to work with. This would also allow me to share the bot with anyone. So there it was. Telegram bot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was tired of using D1 due to its cold start time and drizzle not supporting its sessions API. Since I wanted to deploy everything to Cloudflare, I thought why not use Durable Objects? I had used it a while back to write a blog post, but not in a product as such and each user gets their own DB and since there won’t be any external DB calls as such, the latency between data fetching, updating, etc would be close to 0ms. So I chose DO for my database.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last remaining part was which TS library to use to interact with Telegram API. I had read about telegraf.js somewhere so I checked it out, but it was not actively maintained. After searching for a bit, I went with grammY due to extensive documentation and it being actively maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Some more new things&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some more new libs which I have used are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;oxc - for linting and formatting&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vitest - for testing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AGENTS.md - for Gemini CLI&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;drizzle (beta version) - for ORM&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Things I learned&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Setting webhook URL&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seemed pretty basic in hindsight, but no matter what, I was unable to listen to the messages sent to the bot. Added to the fact that I was using wrangler to develop locally (since I would be deploying to Cloudflare Workers), I was not sure what I was doing wrong. I eventually found out I had to set the webhook like so &lt;code&gt;https://api.telegram.org/bot/&amp;lt;BOT_ID&amp;gt;setWebhook?url=&amp;lt;WEBHOOK_URL&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. This would tell the bot to forward the messages to the webhook URL. To expose my localhost to the public internet, I used Cloudflare Tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Bot not responding to messages&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was now able to see the messages, but I was not able to respond to them. I regrettably had to ask Cursor to fix this to which it spat out below code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;app.post("/webhook", async (c) =&amp;gt; {
    const update = await c.req.json();

    const bot = await setupBot({
        token: c.env.BOT_TOKEN,
        env: c.env,
        commands,
        callbacks,
    });

    await bot.handleUpdate(update);

    return c.json({ ok: true });
});&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;await bot.handleUpdate(update);&lt;/code&gt; is used to pass the updates to the bot instance. Apparently, this is needed in a serverless env where everything is stateless. Adding this fixed the issue&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Commands can be registered dynamically&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially I was under the impression that BotFather has to be used to update any commands which the bot can show to the user. But turns out you can set them via the API as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;app.post("/webhook", async (c) =&amp;gt; {
    const update = await c.req.json();

    const bot = await setupBot({
      token: c.env.BOT_TOKEN,
      env: c.env,
      commands,
      callbacks,
    });

    await bot.api.setMyCommands(
      commands.map((command) =&amp;gt; ({
        command: command.name,
        description: command.description,
      })),
    );

    // This is required for grammy to work in Cloudflare Workers. Also, this has to go after the commands are registered.
    await bot.handleUpdate(update);

    return c.json({ ok: true });
});&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As you can see, the &lt;code&gt;handleUpdate&lt;/code&gt; method needs to be called after the commands are set. Otherwise, the data is not passed along.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Not everything has to be AI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There came a point where I had to have timezone identification in the bot. My first thought was to ask user where they’re located, send it to an LLM and then get the timezone in IANA format. Instead, I now ask the user for their location via Telegram’s API, send their &lt;code&gt;lat&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;long&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;tz-lookup&lt;/code&gt; and get the timezone. I’m glad I did not go via the AI route and I’m ashamed I did not think of the &lt;code&gt;tz-lookup&lt;/code&gt; solution first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All in all, it was a lot of fun building this bot. I learned a lot and also solved my problem rather elegantly if I say so myself.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46851922</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 03:02:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple's MacBook Pro DFU port documentation is wrong</title><link>https://lapcatsoftware.com/articles/2026/2/1.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="362448954b27b1fd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to the Apple support document How to identify the DFU port on Mac, the DFU (device firmware update) port location for MacBook Pro models with Apple silicon is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;14-inch MacBook Pro with M4 or M5 chip: The rightmost USB-C port when youâre facing the left side of the Mac&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;All other models: The leftmost USB-C port when youâre facing the left side of the Mac&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is wrong, a discovery that took me about a half dozen attempts to update macOS on an external disk. I have a 16-inch MacBook Pro with an M4 chip, specifically an M4 Pro chip, and the DFU port seems to be the USB-C port on the right side of the Mac, not on the left side.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For some damn reason, it matters which port your external disk is plugged into when you install or update macOS, as described by the Apple support document How to use an external storage device as a Mac startup disk:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Make sure that your storage device is plugged into the appropriate port on your Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you're using a Mac with Apple silicon, plug your storage device into any compatible port except the DFU port. Learn how to identify the DFU port. After macOS installation is complete, you can connect your storage device to any compatible port, including the DFU port.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If youâre using any other Mac, plug your storage device into any compatible port.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mac disk management was so much easier in the days of Intel and PowerPC!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On an external SSD I had installed a macOS Sequoia boot volume (among others), which Iâve used to take Mac App Store screenshots for my apps and which Iâd now like to use to take a screen recording. The installed version was still macOS 15.2, because I donât often boot into the disk to take new screenshots, and going through the software update process would occupy my MacBook Pro for annoyingly long. However, it appears that Safari 26 requires a version of macOS 15 higher than .2, so I needed to update macOS in order to update Safari from version 18.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past few days, every attempt I made to update the disk volume to macOS 15.7.3 failed inexplicably. I tried both Software Update in System Settings and the &lt;code&gt;softwareupdate&lt;/code&gt; command-line tool in Terminal. They went through all the motions, downloading the entire update, rebooting, etc., but afterwards I always ended up right where I started, at macOS 15.2. The &lt;code&gt;softwareupdate&lt;/code&gt; tool gave no error message. I did eventually see the following (truncated) notification:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the so-called âDetailsâ button presented no actual details, simply opening Software Update again in System Settings. At no point did it ever say, hey, plug your disk into a different port!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While searching for a solution to my problem, I found an article by Michael Tsai, Failed Software Update on the External Drive of an Apple Silicon Mac. It described something that I also saw in my testing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;I happened to boot into macOS Recovery and look in the Startup Security Utility, and I saw that it did not have access to change the security policy for the external drive. In order to do that, it said I had to set the drive as the startup disk. This kind of didnât make sense because donât the security options get set when booted from Recovery?&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I followed Tsaiâs instructions, which did allow me to change the security policy for the external drive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;I donât know why software update couldnât tell me this or why there is seemingly no direct GUI command to view or edit the authorized users. But restarting from within Startup Disk is apparently the way to get macOS to offer to fix the LocalPolicy. Once I added the user, I was able to do a normal boot from the external drive and software update normally.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also thought this would solve my macOS update problem, but it didnât. In retrospect, though, perhaps I needed both solutions, to fix the LocalPolicy and to change the ports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was about to surrender to despair when I discovered a second article by Michael Tsai, Failing to Finish Updating macOS on an External Disk, published soon after the first article:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;With the final release of macOS 15.5, the problem got worse, and the Startup Disk workaround no longer helps.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tsai ultimately hits on the solution:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;The problem ended up being that I had plugged the external drive into the wrong USB-C port (the DFU port).&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sure enough, after plugging my disk into a port on the left side of my MacBook Pro, software update succeeded on the first attempt. Every previous, failed attempt used the port on the right side, which was physically more convenient on the desk. So after all that, the external disk is finally updated to macOS 15.7.3 now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tsai offers the same complaint about this absurd situation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;I donât know why macOS canât just report an error when you use the wrong port instead of proceeding to install for an hour and then not report an error but not work, either.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the way, Software Update in System Settings allowed my Mac to go to sleep during the âPreparingâ phase, despite the fact that the battery was charged to 99%, so when I returned home from a workout I unhappily found 30 minutes remaining. Sigh. Whatever happened to âit just worksâ?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46852096</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 03:29:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Leaked Chats Expose the Daily Life of a Scam Compound's Enslaved Workforce</title><link>https://www.wired.com/story/the-red-bull-leaks/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7e05985b3d2382ed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just before 8am one day last April, an office manager who went by the name Amani sent out a motivational message to his colleagues and subordinates. “Every day brings a new opportunity—a chance to connect, to inspire, and to make a difference,” he wrote in his 500-word post to an office-wide WhatsApp group. “Talk to that next customer like you're bringing them something valuable—because you are.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amani wasn’t rallying a typical corporate sales team. He and his underlings worked inside a “pig butchering” compound, a criminal operation built to carry out scams—promising romance and riches from crypto investments—that often defraud victims out of hundreds of thousands or even millions of dollars at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The workers Amani was addressing were eight hours into their 15-hour night shift in a high-rise building in the Golden Triangle special economic zone in Northern Laos. Like their marks, most of them were victims, too: forced laborers trapped in the compound, held in debt bondage with no passports. They struggled to meet scam revenue quotas to avoid fines that deepened their debt. Anyone who broke rules or attempted to escape faced far worse consequences: beatings, torture, even death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bizarre reality of daily life in a Southeast Asian scam compound—the tactics, the tone, the mix of cruelty and upbeat corporate prattle—is revealed at an unprecedented level of resolution in a leak of documents to WIRED from a whistleblower inside one such sprawling fraud operation. The facility, known as the Boshang compound, is one of dozens of scam operations across Southeast Asia that have enslaved hundreds of thousands of people. Often lured from the poorest regions of Asia and Africa with fake job offers, these conscripts have become engines of the most lucrative form of cybercrime in the world, coerced into stealing tens of billions of dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last June, one of those forced laborers, an Indian man named Mohammad Muzahir, contacted WIRED while he was still captive inside the scam compound that had trapped him. Over the following weeks, Muzahir, who initially identified himself only as “Red Bull,” shared with WIRED a trove of information about the scam operation. His leaks included internal documents, scam scripts, training guides, operational flowcharts, and photographs and videos from inside the compound.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of all Muzahir’s leaks, the most revealing is a collection of screen recordings in which he scrolled through three months’ worth of the compound’s internal WhatsApp group chats. Those videos, which WIRED converted into 4,200 pages of screenshots, capture hour-by-hour conversations between the compound’s workers and their bosses—and the nightmare workplace culture of a pig butchering organization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s a slave colony that’s trying to pretend it’s a company,” says Erin West, a former Santa Clara County, California, prosecutor who leads an anti-scam organization called Operation Shamrock and who reviewed the chat logs obtained by WIRED. Another researcher who reviewed the leaked chat logs, Jacob Sims of Harvard University’s Asia Center, also remarked on their “Orwellian veneer of legitimacy.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s terrifying, because it’s manipulation and coercion,” says Sims, who studies Southeast Asian scam compounds. “Combining those two things together motivates people the most. And it’s one of the key reasons why these compounds are so profitable.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In another chat message, sent within hours of Amani’s saccharine pep talk, a higher-level boss weighed in: “Don't resist the company's rules and regulations,” he wrote. “Otherwise you can't survive here.” The staffers responded with 26 emoji reactions, all thumbs-ups and salutes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fined Into Slavery&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, according to WIRED’s analysis of the group chat, more than 30 of the compound’s workers successfully defrauded at least one victim in the 11 weeks of records available, totaling to around $2.2 million in stolen funds. Yet the bosses in the chat frequently voiced their disappointment in the group’s performance, berated the staff for lack of effort, and imposed fine after fine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rather than explicit imprisonment, the compound relied on a system of indentured servitude and debt to control its workers. As Muzahir described it, he was paid a base salary of 3,500 Chinese yuan a month (about $500), which in theory entailed 75 hours a week of night shifts including breaks to eat. Although his passport had been taken from him, he was told that if he could pay off his “contract” with a $5,400 payment, it would be returned to him and he would be allowed to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In reality, the WhatsApp chats reveal how even that meager salary was almost entirely chipped away with fines. One message warns that anyone who fails to start a “first chat”—an introductory conversation with a scam victim—on any given day will be fined 50 yuan, and the failure will be announced to the group. Filing a false progress report results in a fine of 1,000 yuan. Falling asleep in the office, or “watching unrelated video, chatting with friends, and any activity that is not related to the job” are each punishable with a 200 yuan fine, as is any “disturbance” in the dormitory, where workers sleep five or six to a room in bunk beds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One message notes a fine of 500 yuan for a worker who slept late, and another fined 200 yuan for not being in the dorm at “check-in time” following his shift. Resist a fine by not signing a form that admits to the misbehavior, and the fine is doubled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Muzahir himself described being fined so much that he was virtually broke. The food in the office cafeteria was also frequently denied as a punishment, the messages showed, with workers’ ID badges that granted access to the canteen sometimes being taken away for seven days for small infractions like tardiness. Even the freedom to bring in snacks and drinks—other than betel nuts, a stimulant—could be rescinded if staff underperformed. Time off was also withheld, with staff sometimes forced to work seven nights a week, Muzahir says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet those punishments could be avoided, the bosses frequently promised, if they successfully scammed someone—or “opened a customer,” as the bosses euphemistically described scamming a new victim. (Scamming the same victim multiple times was called a “recharge.”) In theory, workers were entitled to a commission, over and above their salary, for any scams they pulled off. Muzahir says he successfully perpetrated two scams during his months in the compound—both of which left him racked with regret, he says—and he was never paid after either of them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bosses nonetheless used workers’ illusory hope of paying off their debt—or even going home rich—as a motivator. “I understand—when penalties or fines come your way, it's easy to feel disheartened. But I urge you not to see it as a punishment, but as a lesson and an investment in your own growth,” wrote Amani. “Don't fear the fine. Let it fuel your fire.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The more senior boss, who went by the name Da Hai, spelled out the carrot-and-stick approach more clearly. “The company's incentives are much higher than the fines, so as long as you work hard to open new customers you will receive a generous reward!” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the bosses’ tactics was to play teams off one another, reprimanding underperforming workers while pointing to the success of other scammers in the compound. Each room of the office appears to have had a Chinese ceremonial drum, played when a worker successfully scammed a victim for a six-figure sum. “Do you know why the next office is beating drums?” wrote a higher-level boss called Alang.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A victim had paid “480k,” a boss who goes by the name Libo answers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It doesn't matter, because he belongs to others,” Alang responds. “The important thing is, which one of you can play the drum?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Under the Pretense, a Brutal Reality&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beyond these manipulative tactics, the messages occasionally offer glimpses of a far harsher reality—as does the personal experience and testimony of Muzahir himself. Muzahir describes hearing stories of people who were tortured and says he was himself threatened by Amani with beating and electrocution if he didn’t find new “clients.” Sometimes coworkers disappeared without explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eventually Muzahir came up with a plan to trick his captors into letting him leave. When the bosses caught on, he was held in a room, beaten, slapped and kicked, denied food and water, and made to drink a solution with a white powder dissolved in it, which seems to have been intended to make him more cooperative with their interrogation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Occasional messages in the chat logs hint that these cruel punishments lurked underneath the compound’s motivational messages. At one point, the boss Alang mentions a girl who “sneaked away from the company and went to work in a brothel,” and another person in the group mentions that the “company” still holds her passport. Among the captive workers, Muzahir says, rumor had it that the girl was in fact sold into prostitution, a practice documented in other accounts from scam compound survivors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At another point, while chastising the group for underperformance, the boss Da Hai hints at the large sum of money workers needed to produce if they ever hoped to leave the compound. “You continue to violate the company's regulations,” he writes to the group. “If you continue like this, please prepare your compensation and get out of here.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Such references to paying “compensation” for release are in fact “coded words for ransom and debt bondage,” says Harvard’s Sims. The nation of Laos, Sims points out, is a signatory to the Palermo Protocol, which classifies anyone held in debt and forced to work without freedom of movement a victim of human trafficking. “There is no gray area here.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Day in the Life of a Scammer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The leaked WhatsApp chats include a message from a boss who went by the name Terry laying out a strict work schedule for those under his supervision. “Obey and respect the working time,” the message says. Each shift would start at around 11:30 pm Beijing time—10:30 pm in Laos—with people told to arrive a few minutes early. Before the day ended at 2 pm Beijing time, there would be two break periods, one of which was set aside for meals. By 5 pm everyone was required to be back in their dormitories and “sleep or keep silence, no disturbing the others.” If the rules weren’t followed, fines would be issued and ID badges could be taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reason for this nocturnal schedule was to sync with the waking hours of victims in the US—almost entirely Indian-American men. (It’s a common practice to pair scammers with victims of their own ethnicity, to avoid language and culture barriers.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In grim contrast to their actual lives, all staffers were required to post an imaginary daily schedule for their fake personas—the wealthy, attractive women they’d pretend to be during scams. In hour-by-hour breakdowns, they describe mornings spent meditating, practicing yoga, taking walks, and “setting positive intentions” for the day. Other activities include a “relaxed” lunch with their team, dinner with loved ones, and time at the gym—when in reality they were spending entire nights in front of a screen in a fluorescent-lit office space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many of the staffers writing the schedules were nonetheless admonished for not sticking to the script while scamming. “The purpose of editing a daily plan is to let everyone know clearly what you are going to share with your clients today when you start working,” one boss complained. “I find that many people just do it to get the job done and don't apply your plan to your clients.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During each day’s work, the forced scammers were also required—under the threat of more fines—to report their scamming efforts back to the bosses in detail. The WhatsApp logs are filled with lengthy messages from every team member that offer those reports in identical message templates, listing their “team,” their name, and their recent online activity with the fake profiles. They would report how many active social media accounts they were operating, if any of their accounts were suspended, how many chats they’d started, how many were ongoing, any successful scams, and their target for the month. The internal chats also show scammers sharing with bosses and colleagues screenshots of their victim chats on Facebook Messenger, Instagram, Snapchat, and other chat apps, while asking questions about potential victims.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bosses frequently gave pointed feedback about how workers were managing the meta-narrative of their scams. “When sharing travel topics, you need to know how to share details,” one chat says. Another message from a boss admonishes workers not to mention the car their persona drives if they can’t provide a convincing photo of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Managers would keep a close eye on the activity. On multiple occasions, bosses ask the forced workers to connect their WhatsApp accounts to the managers’ computers so they could monitor the conversations themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Anatomy of a Scam&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 25 scripts and guides Muzahir shared with WIRED, too, offer a window into the tactics and training of the compound’s workers. Many of the guidance documents pertain to the nitty gritty of carrying out cryptocurrency investment scams, including how to build a friendship that can segue into an investment proposition, how to explain what cryptocurrency is, and what to do once a target agrees to make an investment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One document lists “100 chat topics,” geared toward building the emotional intimacy required for a romance scam (“What was your dream when you were little?” “What was the last time I cried for?”). Another suggests providing an update about having gotten into a car accident. “On my way to work in the morning, my car was hit by a car following at a traffic light, which almost delayed my meeting in the morning. Thank you for your concern. I am fine.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiple documents guide scammers to pretend they are currently making an investment, then introduce the idea that banks are resistant to letting their customers convert their money into cryptocurrency. “If we transfer or withdraw funds, they will have one less customer,” one proposed scam script says. “If everyone does this, then the bank will be in crisis and there will be a situation of capital rupture. I can understand their motives, but as a bank customer, I should not be hindered from transferring assets reasonably and legally. This is what makes me angry.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The documents also display a technique that researchers say is often used in Southeast Asian investment and romance scams: Attackers intentionally mention the concept of scams—even directly talking about the threat of investment scams—as a way of inoculating themselves against suspicion. The idea is that if a person is willing to talk openly about scams and isn’t avoiding the subject or acting strange about it, then they couldn’t be a scammer themself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That strategy goes so far as to include mentally preparing a victim for the anti-fraud warnings from their bank or even law enforcement that they may have to ignore in order to transfer large amounts of fiat currency into cryptocurrency. “I was going to transfer funds to my coinbase today, but I was deliberately delayed and obstructed by the bank staff,” one script reads, referring to the popular crypto wallet service Coinbase. “I also received an anti-fraud call from the FBI today, which wasted a lot of my time.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The materials Muzahir provided from the Boshang compound also document the key role generative AI tools play in its deceptions. Muzahir described to WIRED how the compound workers are trained in using tools like ChatGPT and Deepseek to come up with responses in chats with victims and craft natural-sounding turns of phrase. But even more crucial was the compound’s use of deepfake AI software to allow scammers to convincingly video chat with victims at their request using an AI-generated face, impersonating an individual whose photos they’ve stolen for a fake persona.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The internal chat logs Muzahir captured describe a dedicated “AI room” where a female model conducts face-swapped calls on request with an endless parade of victims. One WhatsApp message from a boss to the group chat notes that “Sana (our model who helps us to call) is not available tonight. she is not feeling well. Therefore, don't promise your customers to call them. Maybe she will come at work in the morning. Plan your work accordin[g]ly.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other chats about the AI room relate to scheduling challenges given demand for face-swapped calls and the fact that a single model can only do one deepfake call at a time. One chat, for example, notes: “If there is a ‘busy’ sign on her door, change it to ‘free’ when you come out, so as to avoid crowding and frequent door openings.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scripts Muzahir shared also include tips for delaying a video chat with a victim—perhaps until the scammer is prepared to use deepfake tools. “When we meet, it will not be awkward but rather we will look forward to it,” says one script about what to say when a victim asks to video chat. It continues, “We are strengthening our relationship every day. You have also seen my photos. When we meet, can you recognize me?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Beyond the Golden Triangle&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As dystopian as the Golden Triangle compound described in the leaked documents may be, its work environment appears to have been relatively lax compared to other compounds in countries like Cambodia or Myanmar. In those facilities, Operation Shamrock’s Erin West says, she has heard firsthand stories of workers being beaten simply for missing their quota of scams or being forced to work 18-hour shifts while standing, with none of the pretense of voluntary work in a corporate environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The relative leniency of Muzahir’s compound, says Harvard’s Sims, likely stems from scam operations’ sense of total control in Laos’ Golden Triangle region—a zone of the country controlled largely by Chinese business interests that has become a host to crimes ranging from narcotics and organ sales to illegal wildlife trafficking. Even human trafficking victims who escape from a compound there, Sims points out, can be tracked down relatively easily thanks to Chinese organized crime’s influence over local law enforcement. “These guys don’t have to be held in a cell,” Sims says. “The whole place is a closed circuit.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the Boshang compound that held Muzahir appears to have moved in November from the Golden Triangle to Cambodia, a country that’s become by some measures an even safer base for scammers to operate from. Based on messages from his former coworkers, Muzahir says he’s determined that the operation and its captive workers are now based in the town of Chrey Thom, what Sims and West both describe as a growing hot spot for scam operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The move may have been precipitated, Sims speculates, by police raids on compounds across the region around that time. Many of those raids appear to have been part of a “performative crackdown,” as Sims puts it. (One such raid in June targeted the building where Muzahir’s compound had previously been located, but Muzahir says the workers who were rounded up by police were quickly released again and returned to work.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the nuisance of even those superficial disruptions may have persuaded the operation’s bosses to relocate to Cambodia. In that country, even the family of the country’s prime minister, Hun Manet, has been linked to a corporate conglomerate that oversees a subsidiary with documented ties to the burgeoning scam industry. “It’s been a very hospitable environment to do this work,” West says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of Muzahir’s old bosses also confirmed to him in a private text exchange that the compound is still “recruiting” new workers—victims trapped in a system of modern slavery hidden under a thin facade of a willing workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This is a place to work, not to enjoy,” that same boss had written in the group chat during Muzahir’s time in the compound, in a rare moment when the mask of a normal office environment seemed to slip. “You can only enjoy life when you leave here.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional reporting by Sophia Takla, Maddy Varner, and Zeyi Yang.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let us know what you think about this article. Submit a letter to the editor at mail@wired.com.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46852660</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 05:10:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Most People Miss About Getting Promoted – By Yue Zhao</title><link>https://news.theuncommonexecutive.com/p/what-most-people-miss-about-getting</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f4fad35d0a7ed5ad"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;What Most People Miss About Getting Promoted&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Make the business case for why now. Pitch your promotion broadly on why invest in expanding your scope, and not fund someone else's promotion.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Client: I was passed over for promotion 6 months ago. This time, I am working closely with my manager and my skip level on my promotion package. We’ve documented my impact and accomplishments for the case and have received support from my cross-functional partners. What am I missing? What else can I do to increase my chances?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As an executive coach who helps women and minorities move up the career ladder, one mistake I notice often is that people narrowly focus their promotion pitch on their past accomplishments. Here’s what I’ve done, and here’s the impact it had. They falsely believe that because they did a great job, they deserve the promotion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, past performance is necessary but insufficient. Past performance can indicate capability. However, what is missing is timing and the potential to deliver at the next level. A great promotion case requires these two additional components.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Timing: Why should we promote you now? Why not in 6 months? What do we gain by paying you more now?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Potential: Will you succeed at the next level? What does that mean for business impact? How critical is the success of your next role or project to the business?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Businesses don’t do promotions at senior levels because you “deserve” it. They promote those who have the highest potential to deliver outsized impact and value. While past performance is an indicator of future success, it’s important to make the case that yours is the most impactful promotion to the business to make happen now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Make Your Case For Timing = Now&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ve done great work (and will likely keep doing great work). So why promote you now?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key here is to articulate what the business will additionally gain from your promotion compared with if you continued at your current level. Ironically, this is where people who work harder after missing out on a promotion shoot themselves in the foot. By showing you can do the work without the promotion, you are giving the business less incentive to promote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When making the case for “why now”, consider these aspects:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;How does your success necessitate a more senior role? Consider this from the perspective of writing a job description for your replacement. What would be the mandatory requirements? Some common factors that up-level a role include:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Hire and lead more senior team members&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Peer leveling and default invitations to small-group leadership forums&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Need to represent the company externally at conferences and workshops with a higher title. For those VP-level roles, building an external brand can help make the case for internal promotions.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Do you have attractive alternatives? Whether you think it’s fair or not, promotion as a tool for retention is the business reality. Intentionally or not, managers sometimes delay promotions until it is essential to retain you. In some ways, if they give the promotion, you may be more likely to leave if you are not fully satisfied. Make it clear you don’t plan to leave, but that there are attractive alternatives should the company not allow you to operate at your highest potential.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Address the Why Your Role? &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In any company with more than 50 people, there are multiple people up for promotion in a review cycle. Unless you’re at a high-flying AI-native startup, the promotion budget is likely capped. With the on margins and profitability, VPs and executives are more frequently fighting to get their people promoted. In addition to addressing your past accomplishments and timing, it is important to articulate why your specific promotion is essential for business success.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This process looks a bit like writing your future performance review for the new role:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Articulate the criticality of the new role: How does it connect with critical business metrics? How does it impact the success of other core teams? What might be at risk if you’re slowed down by unnecessary politics?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Show the business gain: How does the promotion accelerate your impact? How does it free up your capacity through increased delegation? How does it increase your effectiveness and speed up your work?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Compared to other roles, why is your promotion potentially more critical? Is your role more closely tied to revenue and top-line growth? To a higher priority company goal? This is one of the primary reasons high-visibility projects create faster promotion paths. Or why certain functions see faster promotions than others.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The three components of a great promotion story will include past performance to demonstrate capability and potential, timing criticality, and relative importance to other roles. Having strong arguments on all three fronts will help your leadership pound the table for your promotion to go through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s all folks! See you next week at 3:14 pm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yue&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Yue’s Coaching Corner&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;High-stakes meetings break down because we misunderstand incentives, pressures, and fears. On Feb 11, I’m teaching a free lesson on how to use simple AI workflows to anticipate conflicts and communicate with confidence. Register here.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Wondering what might be stopping you from that next promotion? Check out my The Uncommon Executive Leadership Accelerator made for mid-career leaders looking to transition from a do-er to a lead-er. Over 8 weeks, we cover the core leadership skills you need to become a top 1% leader.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46853983</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 09:18:09 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>