<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 03:50:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Dev-owned testing: Why it fails in practice and succeeds in theory</title><link>https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3780063.3780066</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46646226</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:39:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Michelangelo's first painting, created when he was 12 or 13</title><link>https://www.openculture.com/2026/01/discover-michelangelos-first-painting.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ad990b521b25664"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think back, if you will, to the works of art you created at age twelve or thirteen. For many, perhaps most of us, our output at that stage of adolescence amounted to directionless doodles, chaotic comics, and a few unsteady-at-best school projects. But then, most of us didn’t grow up to be Michelangelo. In the late fourteen-eighties, when that towering Renaissance artist was still what we would now call a “tween,” he painted The Torment of Saint Anthony, a depiction of the titular religious figure beset by demons in the desert. Though based on a widely known engraving, it nevertheless shows evidence of rapidly advancing technique, inspiration, and even creativity — especially when placed under the infrared scanner.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For about half a millennium, The Torment of Saint Anthony wasn’t thought to have been painted by Michelangelo. As explained in the video from Inspiraggio just below, when the painting sold at Sotheby’s in 2008, the buyer took it to the Metropolitan Museum of Art for examination and cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Beneath the layers of dirt accumulated over the centuries,” says the narrator, “a very particular color palette appeared. “The tones, the blends, the way the human figure was treated: all of it began to resemble the style Michelangelo would use years later in none other than the Sistine Chapel.” Infrared reflectography subsequently turned up pentimenti, or correction marks, a common indication that “a painting is not a copy, but an original work created with artistic freedom.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was the Kimbell Art Museum in Fort Worth, Texas that first bet big on the provenance of The Torment of Saint Anthony. Its newly hired director purchased the painting after turning up “not a single convincing argument against the attribution.” Thus acquired, it became “the only painting by Michelangelo located anywhere in the Americas, and also just one of four easel paintings attributed to him throughout his entire career,” during most of which he disparaged oil painting itself. About a decade later, and after further analysis, the art historian Giorgio Bonsanti put his considerable authority behind a definitive confirmation that it is indeed the work of the young Michelangelo. There remain doubters, of course, and even the notoriously uncompromising artist himself may have considered it an immature work unworthy of his name. But who else could have created an immature work like it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Related Content:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How Four Masters — Michelangelo, Donatello, Verrocchio &amp;amp; Bernini — Sculpted David&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Secret Room with Drawings Attributed to Michelangelo Opens to Visitors in Florence&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Michelangelo’s Illustrated Grocery List&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based in Seoul, Colin Marshall writes and broadcasts on cities, language, and culture. He’s the author of the newsletter Books on Cities as well as the books 한국 요약 금지 (No Summarizing Korea) and Korean Newtro. Follow him on the social network formerly known as Twitter at @colinmarshall.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46646263</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:44:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cloudflare acquires Astro</title><link>https://astro.build/blog/joining-cloudflare/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7fa05838a90aa8e6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Astro Technology Company — the company behind the Astro web framework — is joining Cloudflare! Adoption of the Astro web framework continues to double every year, and Astro 6 is right around the corner. With Cloudflare’s support, we’ll have more resources and fewer distractions to continue our mission to build the best framework for content-driven websites.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What this means for Astro:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Astro stays open-source and MIT-licensed&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Astro continues to be actively maintained&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Astro continues to support a wide set of deployment targets, not just Cloudflare&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Astro’s open governance and current roadmap remain in place.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All full-time employees of The Astro Technology Company are now employees of Cloudflare, and will continue to work on Astro full-time.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How Astro started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2021, Astro was born out of frustration. The trend at the time was that every website should be architected as an application, and then shipped to the user’s browser to render. This was not very performant, and we’ve spent the last decade coming up with more and more complex solutions to solve for that performance problem. SSR, ISR, RSC, PPR, TTI optimizations via code-splitting, tree-shaking, lazy-loading, all to generate a blocking double-data hydration payload from a pre-warmed server running halfway around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our mission to design a web framework specifically for building websites — what we call content-driven websites, to better distinguish from data-driven, stateful web applications — resonated. Now Astro is downloaded almost 1,000,000 times per week, and has been used by 100,000s of developers to build fast, beautiful websites. Today you’ll find Astro all over the web, powering major websites and even entire developer platforms for companies like Webflow, Wix, Microsoft, and Google.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along the way, we also tried to grow a business. In 2021 we raised some money and formed The Astro Technology Company. Our larger vision was that a well-designed framework like Astro could sit at the center of a massive developer platform, with optional hosted primitives (database, storage, analytics) designed in lockstep with the framework.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We were never able to realize this vision. Attempts to introduce paid, hosted primitives into our ecosystem fell flat, and rarely justified their own existence. We considered going more directly after first-class hosting or content management for Astro, but knew we’d spend much of our time playing catchup to well-funded, savvy competitors. We kept exploring different ideas, but nothing clicked with users the same way Astro did.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It wasn’t all bad. Astro DB (our attempt to build a hosted database product for Astro projects) eventually evolved into the open, built-in Astro database client that still lives in core today. Our exploration into building an e-commerce layer with Astro was eventually open-sourced. It was rewarding work, but over the years the distraction took its toll. Each attempt at a new paid product or offering took myself and others on the project away from working on the Astro framework that developers were using and loving every day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Returning to Focus&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last year, Dane (Cloudflare CTO) and I began to talk more seriously about the future of the web. Those conversations quickly grew into something bigger: What does the next decade look like? How do frameworks adapt to a world of AI coding and agents?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It became clear that even as web technologies evolve, content remains at the center. We realized that we’ve each been working toward this same vision from different angles:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cloudflare has been solving it from the infrastructure side: betting on a platform that is global by default, with fast startup, low latency, and security built-in.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Astro has been solving it from the framework side: betting on a web framework that makes it easy to build sites that are fast by default, without overcomplicating things.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The overlap is obvious. By working together, Cloudflare gives us the backing we need to keep innovating for our users. Now we can stop spending cycles worrying about building a business on top of Astro, and start focusing 100% on the code, with a shared vision to move the web forward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Cloudflare ❤️ Astro&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare has been a long-time sponsor and champion of Astro. They have a proven track record of supporting great open-source projects like Astro, TanStack, and Hono without trying to capture or lock anything down. Staying open to all was a non-negotiable requirement for both us and for Cloudflare.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is why Astro will remain free, open-source, and MIT-licensed. We will continue to run our project in the open, with an open governance model for contributors and an open community roadmap that anyone can participate in. We remain fully committed to maintaining Astro as a platform-agnostic framework, meaning we will continue to support and improve deployments for all targets—not just Cloudflare.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Cloudflare’s resources and support, we can now return our focus fully towards building the best web framework for content-driven websites. The web is changing fast, and the bar keeps rising: performance, scale, reliability, and a better experience for the teams shipping content on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll see that focus reflected across our roadmap, as we prepare for the upcoming Astro 6 release (beta out now!) and our 2026 roadmap. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Thank you&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to extend a huge thank you to the agencies, companies, sponsors, partners, and theme authors who chose to work with us over the years. Thank you to our initial investors — Haystack, Gradient, Uncorrelated, Lightspeed — without whom Astro likely wouldn’t exist. Thank you to everyone in our open source community who continues to help make Astro better every day. And finally, thank you to everyone who uses Astro and puts their trust in us to help them build for the web.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46646645</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:25:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cursor's latest “browser experiment” implied success without evidence</title><link>https://embedding-shapes.github.io/cursor-implied-success-without-evidence/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a645901deb75300c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2026-01-16&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Cursor's latest "browser experiment" implied success without evidence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On January 14th 2026, Cursor published a blog post titled "Scaling long-running autonomous coding" (https://cursor.com/blog/scaling-agents)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the blog post, they talk about their experiments with running "coding agents autonomously for weeks" with the explicit goal of&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;understand[ing] how far we can push the frontier of agentic coding for projects that typically take human teams months to complete&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They talk about some approaches they tried, why they think those failed, and how to address the difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally they arrived at a point where something "solved most of our coordination problems and let us scale to very large projects without any single agent", which then led to this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To test this system, we pointed it at an ambitious goal: building a web browser from scratch. The agents ran for close to a week, writing over 1 million lines of code across 1,000 files. You can explore the source code on GitHub (https://github.com/wilsonzlin/fastrender)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where things get a bit murky and unclear. They claim "Despite the codebase size, new agents can still understand it and make meaningful progress" and "Hundreds of workers run concurrently, pushing to the same branch with minimal conflicts", but they never actually say if this is successful or not, is it actually working? Can you run this browser yourself? We don't know and they never say explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After this, they embed the following video:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And below it, they say "While it might seem like a simple screenshot, building a browser from scratch is extremely difficult.".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;They never actually claim this browser is working and functional&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;error: could not compile 'fastrender' (lib) due to 34 previous errors; 94 warnings emitted&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And if you try to compile it yourself, you'll see that it's very far away from being a functional browser at all, and seemingly, it never actually was able to build.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiple recent GitHub Actions runs on &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; show
failures (including workflow-file errors), and independent build
attempts report dozens of compiler errors, recent PRs were all merged
with failing CI, and going back in the Git history from most recent
commit back 100 commits,&lt;lb/&gt;I couldn't find a single commit that compiled cleanly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm not sure what the "agents" they unleashed on this codebase actually did, but they seemingly never ran "cargo build" or even less "cargo check", because both of those commands surface 10s of errors (which surely would balloon should we solve them) and about 100 warnings. There is an open GitHub issue in their repository about this right now: https://github.com/wilsonzlin/fastrender/issues/98&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And diving into the codebase, if the compilation errors didn't make that clear already, makes it very clear to any software developer that none of this is actually engineered code. It is what is typically known as "AI slop", low quality something that surely represents something, but it doesn't have intention behind it, and it doesn't even compile at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They later start to talk about what's next, but not a single word about how to run it, what to expect, how it's working or anything else. Cursor's blog post provides no reproducible demo and no known-good revision (tag/release/commit) to verify the screenshots, beyond linking the repo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless of intent, Cursor's blog post creates the impression of a functioning prototype while leaving out the basic reproducibility markers one would expect from such claim. They never explicitly claim it's actually working, so no one can say they lied at least.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They finish off the article saying:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;But the core question, can we scale autonomous coding by throwing more agents at a problem, has a more optimistic answer than we expected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which seems like a really strange conclusion to arrive at, when all they've proved so far, is that agents can output millions of tokens and still not end up with something that actually works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A "browser experiment" doesn't need to rival Chrome. A reasonable minimum bar is: it compiles on a supported toolchain and can render a trivial HTML file. Cursor's post doesn’t demonstrate that bar, and current public build attempts fail at this too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cursor never says "this browser is production-ready", but they do frame it as "building a web browser from scratch" and "meaningful progress" and then use a screenshot and "extremely difficult" language, wanting to give the impression that this experiment actually was a success.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The closest they get to implying that this was a success, is this part:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hundreds of agents can work together on a single codebase for weeks, making real progress on ambitious projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this extraordinary claim isn't backed up by any evidence. In the blog post they never provide a working commit, build instructions or even a demo that can be reproduced.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I don't think anyone expects this browser to be the next Chrome, but I do think that if you claim you've built a browser, it should at least be able to demonstrate being able to be compiled + loading a basic HTML file at the very least.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Versions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;2026-01-16 &lt;code&gt;db6064b&lt;/code&gt; Add link to tested commits&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@@ -33 +33 @@ And if you try to compile it yourself, you'll see that it's very far away from b

  Multiple recent GitHub Actions runs on `main` show failures (including workflow-file errors), and independent build attempts report dozens of compiler errors, recent PRs were all merged with failing CI, and going back in the Git history from most recent commit back-about

   100 -commits, I
+commits,&amp;lt;br/&amp;gt;[I

   couldn't find a single commit that compiled -cleanly.
+cleanly](https://gist.github.com/embedding-shapes/f5d096dd10be44ff82b6e5ccdaf00b29).&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;2026-01-16 &lt;code&gt;3dcd6e7&lt;/code&gt; Fix linebreak typo&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@@ -9,3 +9 @@ On January 14th 2026, Cursor published a blog post titled "Scaling long-running
-In the blog post, they talk about their experiments with running "coding agents autonomously for weeks"
-
-with the explicit goal of
+In the blog post, they talk about their experiments with running "coding agents autonomously for weeks" with the explicit goal of&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;2026-01-16 &lt;code&gt;c74ab74&lt;/code&gt; Fix favicon, fix typos, made better simply&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@@ -33 +33,3 @@ And below it, they say "While it might seem like a simple screenshot, building a

  And if you try to compile it yourself, you'll see that it's very far away from being a functional browser at all, and seemingly, it never actually was able to build.
  Multiple recent GitHub Actions runs on `main` show failures (including workflow-file errors), and independent build attempts report dozens of compiler errors, recent PRs were all merged with failing CI, and going back in the Git history from most recent -commit,
+commit back about 100 commits,

   I couldn't find a single commit that compiled cleanly.@@ -37 +39 @@ I'm not sure what the "agents" they unleashed on this codebase actually did, but

  And diving into the codebase, if the compilation errors didn't make that -sure,
+clear already,

   makes it very clear to any software developer that none of this is actually engineered code. It is what is typically known as "AI slop", low quality *something* that surely represents *something*, but it doesn't have intention behind it, and it doesn't even compile at this point.@@ -59 +61 @@ The closest they get to implying that this was a success, is this part:

  But this extraordinary claim isn't backed up by any evidence. In the blog post they never provide a working commit, build instructions or even a demo that can +be
   reproduced.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;2026-01-16 &lt;code&gt;bafc54f&lt;/code&gt; Favicon + changes + cursor video&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@@ -21 +21 @@ Finally they arrived at a point where something "solved most of our coordination

  This is where things get a bit murky and unclear. They claim "Despite the codebase size, new agents can still understand it and make meaningful progress" and "Hundreds of workers run concurrently, pushing to the same branch with minimal conflicts", but they never actually say if this is successful or not, is it actually working? Can you run this browser yourself? We don't know and they never -say.
+say explicitly.
@@ -25 +25 @@ After this, they embed the following video:
-[video]
+![](/content/cursor-screenshots.webm)
@@ -33 +33 @@ And below it, they say "While it might seem like a simple screenshot, building a

  And if you try to compile it yourself, you'll see that it's very far away from being a functional browser at all, and seemingly, it never actually was able to build. Multiple recent -CI workflow
+GitHub Actions

   runs on `main` -are failing, all the
+show failures (including workflow-file errors), and independent build attempts report dozens of compiler errors, recent

   PRs were +all

   merged with failing CI, and going back in the Git history from most recent commit, I couldn't find a single commit that compiled cleanly.@@ -39 +39,3 @@ And diving into the codebase, if the compilation errors didn't make that sure, m

  They later start to talk about what's next, but not a single word about how to run it, what to expect, how it's working or anything else. Cursor's blog post provides no reproducible -demo/build instructions or
+demo and no

   known-good -commit,
+revision (tag/release/commit) to verify the screenshots,

   beyond linking the repo.
  Regardless of intent, Cursor's blog post creates the impression of a functioning prototype while leaving out the basic reproducibility markers one would expect from such claim. They never explicitly claim it's actually working, so no one can say they lied at least.@@ -46,0 +49,2 @@ Which seems like a really strange conclusion to arrive at, when all they've prov
+A "browser experiment" doesn't need to rival Chrome. A reasonable minimum bar is: it compiles on a supported toolchain and can render a trivial HTML file. Cursor's post doesn’t demonstrate that bar, and current public build attempts fail at this too.
@@ -55 +59 @@ The closest they get to implying that this was a success, is this part:

  But this extraordinary claim isn't backed up by any evidence. -They
+In the blog post they
   never provide a working commit, build instructions or even a demo that can reproduced.&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;2026-01-16 &lt;code&gt;d664475&lt;/code&gt; Move&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;@@ -0,0 +1,57 @@
+---
+date: 2026-01-16
+---
+
+# Cursor's latest "browser experiment" implied success without evidence
+
+On January 14th 2026, Cursor published a blog post titled "Scaling long-running autonomous coding" (https://cursor.com/blog/scaling-agents)
+
+In the blog post, they talk about their experiments with running "coding agents autonomously for weeks"
+
+with the explicit goal of
+
+&amp;gt; understand[ing] how far we can push the frontier of agentic coding for projects that typically take human teams months to complete
+
+They talk about some approaches they tried, why they think those failed, and how to address the difficulties.
+
+Finally they arrived at a point where something "solved most of our coordination problems and let us scale to very large projects without any single agent", which then led to this:
+
+&amp;gt; To test this system, we pointed it at an ambitious goal: building a web browser from scratch. The agents ran for close to a week, writing over 1 million lines of code across 1,000 files. You can explore the source code on GitHub (https://github.com/wilsonzlin/fastrender)
+
+This is where things get a bit murky and unclear. They claim "Despite the codebase size, new agents can still understand it and make meaningful progress" and "Hundreds of workers run concurrently, pushing to the same branch with minimal conflicts", but they never actually say if this is successful or not, is it actually working? Can you run this browser yourself? We don't know and they never say.
+
+After this, they embed the following video:
+
+[video]
+
+And below it, they say "While it might seem like a simple screenshot, building a browser from scratch is extremely difficult.".
+
+### They never actually claim this browser is working and functional
+
+&amp;gt; error: could not compile 'fastrender' (lib) due to 34 previous errors; 94 warnings emitted
+
+And if you try to compile it yourself, you'll see that it's very far away from being a functional browser at all, and seemingly, it never actually was able to build. Multiple recent CI workflow runs on `main` are failing, all the PRs were merged with failing CI, and going back in the Git history from most recent commit, I couldn't find a single commit that compiled cleanly.
+
+I'm not sure what the "agents" they unleashed on this codebase actually did, but they seemingly never ran "cargo build" or even less "cargo check", because both of those commands surface 10s of errors (which surely would balloon should we solve them) and about 100 warnings. There is an open GitHub issue in their repository about this right now: https://github.com/wilsonzlin/fastrender/issues/98
+
+And diving into the codebase, if the compilation errors didn't make that sure, makes it very clear to any software developer that none of this is actually engineered code. It is what is typically known as "AI slop", low quality *something* that surely represents *something*, but it doesn't have intention behind it, and it doesn't even compile at this point.
+
+They later start to talk about what's next, but not a single word about how to run it, what to expect, how it's working or anything else. Cursor's blog post provides no reproducible demo/build instructions or known-good commit, beyond linking the repo. Regardless of intent, Cursor's blog post creates the impression of a functioning prototype while leaving out the basic reproducibility markers one would expect from such claim. They never explicitly claim it's actually working, so no one can say they lied at least.
+
+They finish off the article saying:
+
+&amp;gt; But the core question, can we scale autonomous coding by throwing more agents at a problem, has a more optimistic answer than we expected.
+
+Which seems like a really strange conclusion to arrive at, when all they've proved so far, is that agents can output millions of tokens and still not end up with something that actually works.
+
+## Conclusion
+
+Cursor never says "this browser is production-ready", but they do frame it as "building a web browser from scratch" and "meaningful progress" and then use a screenshot and "extremely difficult" language, wanting to give the impression that this experiment actually was a success.
+
+The closest they get to implying that this was a success, is this part:
+
+&amp;gt; Hundreds of agents can work together on a single codebase for weeks, making real progress on ambitious projects.
+
+But this extraordinary claim isn't backed up by any evidence. They never provide a working commit, build instructions or even a demo that can reproduced.
+
+I don't think anyone expects this browser to be the next Chrome, but I do think that if you claim you've built a browser, it should at least be able to demonstrate being able to be compiled + loading a basic HTML file at the very least.&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46646777</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:37:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Read_once(), Write_once(), but Not for Rust</title><link>https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/1053142/8ec93e58d5d3cc06/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b6b8bc15e896fbd8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;READ_ONCE(), WRITE_ONCE(), but not for Rust&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;[LWN subscriber-only content]&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;head&gt;Welcome to LWN.net&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The following subscription-only content has been made available to you by an LWN subscriber. Thousands of subscribers depend on LWN for the best news from the Linux and free software communities. If you enjoy this article, please consider subscribing to LWN. Thank you for visiting LWN.net!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() macros are heavily used within the kernel; there are nearly 8,000 call sites for READ_ONCE(). They are key to the implementation of many lockless algorithms and can be necessary for some types of device-memory access. So one might think that, as the amount of Rust code in the kernel increases, there would be a place for Rust versions of these macros as well. The truth of the matter, though, is that the Rust community seems to want to take a different approach to concurrent data access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An understanding of READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() is important for kernel developers who will be dealing with any sort of concurrent access to data. So, naturally, they are almost entirely absent from the kernel's documentation. A description of sorts can be found at the top of include/asm-generic/rwonce.h:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Prevent the compiler from merging or refetching reads or writes. The compiler is also forbidden from reordering successive instances of READ_ONCE and WRITE_ONCE, but only when the compiler is aware of some particular ordering. One way to make the compiler aware of ordering is to put the two invocations of READ_ONCE or WRITE_ONCE in different C statements.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In other words, a READ_ONCE() call will force the compiler to read from the indicated location exactly one time, with no optimization tricks that would cause the read to be either elided or repeated; WRITE_ONCE() will force a write under those terms. They will also ensure that the access is atomic; if one task reads a location with READ_ONCE() while another is writing that location, the read will return the value as it existed either before or after the write, but not some random combination of the two. These macros, other than as described above, impose no ordering constraints on the compiler or the CPU, making them different from macros like smp_load_acquire(), which have stronger ordering requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() macros were added for the 3.18 release in 2014. WRITE_ONCE() was initially called ASSIGN_ONCE(), but that name was changed during the 3.19 development cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the last day of 2025, Alice Ryhl posted a patch series adding implementations of READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() for Rust. There are places in the code, she said, where volatile reads could be replaced with these calls, once they were available; among other changes, the series changed access to the struct file f_flags field to use READ_ONCE(). The implementation of these macros involves a bunch of Rust macro magic, but in the end they come down to calls to the Rust read_volatile() and write_volatile() functions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Some of the other kernel Rust developers objected to this change, though. Gary Guo said that he would rather not expose READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() and suggested using relaxed operations from &lt;del&gt;the Rust Atomic crate&lt;/del&gt; the kernel's Atomic module instead. Boqun Feng expanded on the objection: &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;The problem of READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() is that the semantics is complicated. Sometimes they are used for atomicity, sometimes they are used for preventing data race. So yes, we are using LKMM [the Linux kernel memory model] in Rust as well, but whenever possible, we need to clarify the intention of the API, using Atomic::from_ptr().load(Relaxed) helps on that front.&lt;p&gt;IMO, READ_ONCE()/WRITE_ONCE() is like a "band aid" solution to a few problems, having it would prevent us from developing a more clear view for concurrent programming.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In other words, using the Atomic crate allows developers to specify more precisely which guarantees an operation needs, making the expectations (and requirements) of the code more clear. This point of view would appear to have won out, and Ryhl has stopped pushing for this addition to the kernel's Rust code — for now, at least.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are a couple of interesting implications from this outcome, should it hold. The first of those is that, as Rust code reaches more deeply into the core kernel, its code for concurrent access to shared data will look significantly different from the equivalent C code, even though the code on both sides may be working with the same data. Understanding lockless data access is challenging enough when dealing with one API; developers may now have to understand two APIs, which will not make the task easier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, this discussion is drawing some attention to code on the C side as well. As Feng pointed out, there is still C code in the kernel that assumes a plain write will be atomic in many situations, even though the C standard explicitly says otherwise. Peter Zijlstra answered that all such code should be updated to use WRITE_ONCE() properly. Simply finding that code may be a challenge (though KCSAN can help); updating it all may take a while. The conversation also identified a place in the (C) high-resolution-timer code that is missing a needed READ_ONCE() call. This is another example of the Rust work leading to improvements in the C code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; In past discussions on the design of Rust abstractions, there has been resistance to the creation of Rust interfaces that look substantially different from their C counterparts; see this 2024 article, for example. If the Rust developers come up with a better design for an interface, the thinking went, the C side should be improved to match this new design. If one accepts the idea that the Rust approach to READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() is better than the original, then one might conclude that a similar process should be followed here. Changing thousands of low-level concurrency primitives to specify more precise semantics would not be a task for the faint of heart, though. This may end up being a case where code in the two languages just does things differently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Index entries for this article&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kernel&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Development tools/Rust&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kernel&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Lockless algorithms&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Posted Jan 9, 2026 17:19 UTC (Fri) by mb (subscriber, #50428) [Link] (9 responses) I experimented with read/write volatile on AVR, where it would be greatly beneficial to use them for certain inter-thread (interrupt) communication. However, I came to the conclusion that using read/write volatile for inter-thread (interrupt) communication is unsound in Rust. AVR hardware is not capable of doing a non-atomic read/write for byte sized objects. So the hardware is fine for all of the relevant cases. https://doc.rust-lang.org/std/ptr/fn.read_volatile.html &amp;gt; an operation is volatile has no bearing whatsoever on questions involving concurrent accesses from multiple threads &amp;gt; This access is still not considered atomic, and as such it cannot be used for inter-thread synchronization. My implementation worked fine and the generated assembly code was perfect. (Yes, I know there is AtomicXX and no it's not efficient for reasons... And yes, I should fix the compiler's atomic intrinsics instead of working around the problem... I know :) Posted Jan 9, 2026 19:20 UTC (Fri) by josh (subscriber, #17465) [Link] (8 responses) Relaxed atomics are effectively compiler-barrier atomics, and *shouldn't* have any runtime overhead. Are you encountering cases where there's more inefficiency than that? Posted Jan 9, 2026 19:54 UTC (Fri) by mb (subscriber, #50428) [Link] (1 responses) But that was not my point. My point was that I think volatile accesses are not sound in Rust for inter thread communication. Posted Jan 9, 2026 22:10 UTC (Fri) by josh (subscriber, #17465) [Link] Ah, got it, thank you. Hopefully that can be fixed. &amp;gt; My point was that I think volatile accesses are not sound in Rust for inter thread communication. Right, I believe that's correct. Posted Jan 10, 2026 9:33 UTC (Sat) by plugwash (subscriber, #29694) [Link] (5 responses) The situation is a little more subtle than that. Relaxed atomics on a given memory location, must behave as-if they had a well-defined order (though this order may differ from operations on other memory locations, unless fences are used), and this must apply to the whole set of atomic operations. You may only be using load and store on a particular location, but the compiler doesn't know that. Other code might be performing other atomic operations on that location. My understanding is that this effectively means that if you implement read-modify-write operations by using a global lock, you must also implement plain write operations using that same global lock. Posted Jan 10, 2026 20:13 UTC (Sat) by comex (subscriber, #71521) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Jan 11, 2026 17:49 UTC (Sun) by garyguo (subscriber, #173367) [Link] `READ_ONCE` on u64 might still be useful is you just want to read the value in a data-race-free way and you don't care about atomicity (i.e. allow the read to tear). However this is yet another reason I don't want people to just use `READ_ONCE()` for atomic ops on Rust side -- it's just not intuitive which semantics is desired. Posted Jan 10, 2026 20:44 UTC (Sat) by NYKevin (subscriber, #129325) [Link] (2 responses) That is true but misleading. Your parenthetical negates all of the guarantees that are actually expensive to implement, at least on x86. Noting for the record: A fence must be on the same thread as the relaxed atomic in order to restrict it, and there are several other requirements as well. I refer the curious reader to https://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/atomic/atomic_thread_fe... and related documentation for more information. &amp;gt; My understanding is that this effectively means that if you implement read-modify-write operations by using a global lock, you must also implement plain write operations using that same global lock. If you take a global lock, then there are two different memory locations in play (lock and payload), so your parenthetical above already tells us that the lock is ineffective (at protecting against against un-fenced relaxed atomics on either the lock or the payload). Or perhaps I have misunderstood what you mean by "implement read-modify-write operations by using a global lock." I would normally understand a "read-modify-write operation" to be a hardware instruction (or sequence of instructions), which is not our problem to "implement" in the first place. If you mean "emulate," then the problem we run into is that emulators do not emulate the C abstract machine. They emulate some real hardware like x86, or virtual hardware like the JVM. Those platforms have their own, more specific memory models than the C abstract machine, and the compiler backend must necessarily take advantage of those memory models to emit correct assembly/machine code. So our emulator is not permitted to stop at just taking locks for relaxed atomics - it doesn't necessarily know which stores or loads originated as relaxed atomics in the first place, and therefore may have to take locks for all loads and stores whatsoever. Of course, it would be preferable to implement these operations lock-free if it is possible to do so. Posted Jan 10, 2026 21:12 UTC (Sat) by willmo (subscriber, #82093) [Link] (1 responses) &amp;gt; If you take a global lock, then there are two different memory locations in play (lock and payload), so your parenthetical above already tells us that the lock is ineffective (at protecting against against un-fenced relaxed atomics on either the lock or the payload). In this case, the compiler would need to compile un-fenced relaxed atomics so that they take the global lock. That’s what plugwash meant. Posted Jan 12, 2026 16:36 UTC (Mon) by NYKevin (subscriber, #129325) [Link] Posted Jan 9, 2026 17:42 UTC (Fri) by bertschingert (subscriber, #160729) [Link] (11 responses) I wasn't around when they were implemented, so I'm speculating here, but I get the sense that READ/WRITE_ONCE() were implemented as a volatile cast not because volatility gives the optimal or desired semantics in most situations, but because that was the best tool available prior to the C11 atomics model. While it may be prohibitively difficult, it does seem like changing the C side to use relaxed atomics (when correct) would be the right thing to do. But I don't really know how many uses actually require the additional "volatility" guarantee provided by READ/WRITE_ONCE(). Posted Jan 10, 2026 1:39 UTC (Sat) by wahern (subscriber, #37304) [Link] (8 responses) Also, C11 atomics is not the origin point for atomic intrinsics[1] or a meaningful memory model in either GCC or Linux. It's not the final or even 100% comprehensive model, either. I think the push for a more formal memory model in C, C++, and the compilers gives a false impression such a thing was completely non-existent beforehand and that things are satisfactory today. [1] GCC had at least two sets of intrinsics before supporting C11 atomics, and of course projects like the kernel had their own set that work just as well today as they did before the latest set of builtins. Posted Jan 10, 2026 8:54 UTC (Sat) by koverstreet (✭ supporter ✭, #4296) [Link] (2 responses) The "atomicity" guarantees that READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() provide only come in at the compiler level. The compiler will coalesce loads and stores or emit multiple loads as a substitute for spilling registers without some notion of atomicity at the language level. The "unnecessarily costly" part of READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() is that they don't distinguish between atomicity and ordering - they also specify strict ordering, but only to the compiler, not the hardware (they don't emit memory barriers). Rust's atomic load/store really are just better, because they separate out ordering from atomicity and make ordering explicit. And instead of sprinkling around separate memory barrier calls, which may or may not be commented, they're attached to the operation that needs them - which is good for readability. Posted Jan 10, 2026 17:45 UTC (Sat) by excors (subscriber, #95769) [Link] I'm not certain what you mean by that. E.g. the ARM ARM defines "single-copy atomicity" which is important even in single-processor code: if an interrupt occurs during a STP (Store Pair) instruction, whose operation is defined as a single assignment to memory, the interrupt handler may observe the first half of memory was updated and the second half wasn't, because STP is treated as two separate atomic writes. (The STP instruction will be restarted after the interrupt returns, so it'll complete eventually). So I think the ISA does define the notion of atomic loads and stores, even before getting to the more complex operations. (GCC will happily use STP for an int64_t assignment, making it non-atomic, unless you add 'volatile' and then it'll use a single 64-bit STR (which is single-copy atomic).) Posted Jan 10, 2026 20:18 UTC (Sat) by comex (subscriber, #71521) [Link] Posted Jan 10, 2026 16:55 UTC (Sat) by joib (subscriber, #8541) [Link] (4 responses) I wonder, if the C++/C11 memory models and atomics were to be developed today, how different would they look, considering the amount of knowledge the world has gained since then and now? Certainly there were parts of the C/C++11 models that were, ahem, less than successful, like the consume memory ordering, but otherwise, would there be a place for doing it substantially better and different in general? Posted Jan 11, 2026 20:33 UTC (Sun) by pbonzini (subscriber, #60935) [Link] (1 responses) I don't have high hopes that this would be accepted now, but maybe it would be since "almost nobody will need anything but sequential consistent variables" has been shown wrong. The other thing that still hasn't been fully formalized is out-of-thin-air values. Everybody agrees that they won't happen but strictly speaking they aren't prohibited, or weren't last time I checked. Posted Jan 12, 2026 6:06 UTC (Mon) by riking (subscriber, #95706) [Link] Posted Jan 15, 2026 0:18 UTC (Thu) by milesrout (subscriber, #126894) [Link] (1 responses) Posted Jan 15, 2026 15:40 UTC (Thu) by bertschingert (subscriber, #160729) [Link] OTOH, what I like about the Rust (and C/C++11?) atomics is that the type system prevents accidentally introducing data races because you can't do a non-atomic load/store to an atomic type -- at least without unsafe code. Given that the article mentions there are cases in C where READ_ONCE() and WRITE_ONCE() should have been used, but weren't, this seems to be a real risk. Posted Jan 10, 2026 15:42 UTC (Sat) by bjackman (subscriber, #109548) [Link] (1 responses) IIUC C11's relaxed ordering is too weak for that, but any of the other C11 orderings are likely to be unnecessarily strict, i.e. they might force the use of special (costly) CPU instructions where normal reads and writes are already safe enough. Posted Jan 11, 2026 17:57 UTC (Sun) by garyguo (subscriber, #173367) [Link] &lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; Just in the same way every AVR C program uses volatile "atomic" variables to do this.&lt;lb/&gt; https://github.com/mbuesch/avr-atomic&lt;lb/&gt; But the read/write volatile documentation was pretty clear to me that the Rust virtual machine considers concurrent volatile accesses unsound and is free to optimize it to bits.&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; Volatile accesses behave exactly like non-atomic accesses in that regard.&lt;lb/&gt; However, I changed it to a less optimal inline asm implementation just because I think the Rust documentation considers concurrent read/write volatile without additional synchronization to be unsound.&lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; As I said, it's an LLVM problem on AVR. Which is not a stable tier.&lt;lb/&gt; Atomic always use heavy syncing on AVR in the current compiler.&lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;gt; Atomic always use heavy syncing on AVR in the current compiler.&lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;read/write volatile&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;overly strict semantics&lt;/head&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46647059</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 15:04:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>6-Day and IP Address Certificates Are Generally Available</title><link>https://letsencrypt.org/2026/01/15/6day-and-ip-general-availability</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e659e0db14317484"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Short-lived and IP address certificates are now generally available from Let’s Encrypt. These certificates are valid for 160 hours, just over six days. In order to get a short-lived certificate subscribers simply need to select the ‘shortlived’ certificate profile in their ACME client.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Short-lived certificates improve security by requiring more frequent validation and reducing reliance on unreliable revocation mechanisms. If a certificate’s private key is exposed or compromised, revocation has historically been the way to mitigate damage prior to the certificate’s expiration. Unfortunately, revocation is an unreliable system so many relying parties continue to be vulnerable until the certificate expires, a period as long as 90 days. With short-lived certificates that vulnerability window is greatly reduced.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Short-lived certificates are opt-in and we have no plan to make them the default at this time. Subscribers that have fully automated their renewal process should be able to switch to short-lived certificates easily if they wish, but we understand that not everyone is in that position and generally comfortable with this significantly shorter lifetime. We hope that over time everyone moves to automated solutions and we can demonstrate that short-lived certificates work well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our default certificate lifetimes will be going from 90 days down to 45 days over the next few years, as previously announced.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IP address certificates allow server operators to authenticate TLS connections to IP addresses rather than domain names. Let’s Encrypt supports both IPv4 and IPv6. IP address certificates must be short-lived certificates, a decision we made because IP addresses are more transient than domain names, so validating more frequently is important. You can learn more about our IP address certificates and the use cases for them from our post announcing our first IP Certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’d like to thank the Open Technology Fund and Sovereign Tech Agency, along with our Sponsors and Donors, for supporting the development of this work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46647491</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 15:37:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Launch HN: Indy (YC S21) – A support app designed for ADHD brains</title><link>https://www.shimmer.care/indy-redirect</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5ffadfaf74ff182e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get the app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46648144</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:20:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zep AI (Agent Context Engineering, YC W24) Is Hiring Forward Deployed Engineers</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/zep-ai/jobs/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="af57259bffd2ec7b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Agent Context Is Hard. We Fixed It.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zep assembles the right context from chat history, business data, and user behavior so agents are personalized, accurate, and fast. Our open source project Graphiti hit 20k GitHub stars in under 12 months. Sub-200ms retrieval, SOC 2 Type 2/HIPAA certified, used by teams from startups to Fortune 500s.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46648714</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:00:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dell UltraSharp 52 Thunderbolt Hub Monitor</title><link>https://www.dell.com/en-us/shop/dell-ultrasharp-52-thunderbolt-hub-monitor-u5226kw/apd/210-bthw/monitors-monitor-accessories</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e22dab5494a79c42"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Selecting will change the following options:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From To&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;51.5"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;6144 x 2560 at 120Hz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In-plane Switching (IPS) Black Technology&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;99% DCI-P3 (CIE 1976)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;100% sRGB (CIE 1931)&lt;/p&gt;...See More See More Color Gamut&lt;p&gt;2 HDMI port/s (HDCP 2.2) (Supports up to 6144 x 2560, 120 Hz, VRR, , as specified in HDMI 2.1 (FRL))&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 DisplayPort 1.4 (HDCP 2.2) port/s&lt;/p&gt;...See More See More Ports&lt;p&gt;Add the products you would like to compare, and quickly determine which is best for your needs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46648885</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:14:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>East Germany balloon escape</title><link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_Germany_balloon_escape</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="be46c17b47664bf8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;East Germany balloon escape&lt;/head&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell role="head"&gt;Native name&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Die Ballonflucht&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Date&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;16 September 1979&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Time&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;02:00 am (approximate)&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Duration&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;25 minutes&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Location&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Oberlemnitz, East Germany&lt;p&gt;(takeoff)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Naila, West Germany&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(landing)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Coordinates&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;50°28′59″N 11°35′29″E / 50.48306°N 11.59139°E[1]&lt;p&gt;(takeoff)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;50°19′52.7″N 11°40′13.1″E / 50.331306°N 11.670306°E[1]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(landing)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Organised by&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Peter Strelzyk &amp;amp; family&lt;p&gt;Günter Wetzel &amp;amp; family&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Participants&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;8&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row span="2"&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Outcome&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Successful escape to West Germany&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;row&gt;&lt;cell&gt;Non-fatal injuries&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;&lt;/row&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 16 September 1979, eight people from two families escaped from East Germany by crossing the border into West Germany at night in a homemade hot air balloon. The unique feat was the result of over a year and a half of preparations involving three different balloons, various modifications, and a first, unsuccessful attempt. The failed attempt alerted the East German authorities to the plot, but the police were unable to identify the escapees before their second, successful flight two months later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Background&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;East Germany, then part of the Eastern Bloc, was separated from West Germany in the Western Bloc by the inner German border and the Berlin Wall, which were heavily fortified with watchtowers, land mines, armed soldiers, and various other measures to prevent illegal crossings. East German border troops were instructed to prevent defection to West Germany by all means, including lethal force (Schießbefehl; "order to fire").[2]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peter Strelzyk (1942–2017), an electrician and former East German Air Force mechanic, and Günter Wetzel (born 1955), a bricklayer by trade,[3] were colleagues at a local plastics factory.[4] Friends for four years, they shared a desire to flee the country and began discussing ways to get across the border. On 7 March 1978, they agreed to plan an escape.[5] They considered building a helicopter but quickly realized they would be unable to acquire an engine capable of powering such a craft. They then decided to explore the idea of constructing a hot air balloon,[6] having been inspired by a television program about ballooning.[3] An alternate account is that a relative shared a magazine article about the International Balloon Festival in Albuquerque, New Mexico.[5]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Construction&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;Strelzyk and Wetzel began research into balloons. Their plan was to escape with their wives and a total of four children (aged 2 to 15). They calculated the weight of the eight passengers and the craft itself to be around 750 kilograms (1,650 lb). Subsequent calculations determined a balloon capable of lifting this weight would need to hold 2,000 cubic metres (71,000 cu ft) of air heated to 100 °C (212 °F). The next calculation was the amount of material needed for the balloon, estimated to be 800 square metres (8,600 sq ft).[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pair lived in Pößneck, a small town of about 20,000 where large quantities of cloth could not be obtained without raising attention. They tried neighbouring towns of Rudolstadt, Saalfeld, and Jena without success.[7] They travelled 50 km (31 mi) to Gera, where they purchased 1-metre-wide (3 ft 3 in) rolls of cotton cloth totalling 850 metres (2,790 ft) in length at a department store after telling the astonished clerk that they needed the large quantity of material to use as tent lining for their camping club.[6][7]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wetzel spent two weeks sewing the cloth into a balloon-shaped bag, 15 metres (49 ft) wide by 20 metres (66 ft) long, on a 40-year-old manually operated sewing machine. Strelzyk spent the time building the gondola and burner assembly. The gondola was made from an iron frame, sheet metal floor, and clothesline run around the perimeter every 150 millimetres (5.9 in) for the sides. The burner was made using two 11-kilogram (24 lb) bottles of liquid propane household gas, hoses, water pipe, a nozzle, and a piece of stove pipe.[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;First test&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;The team was ready to test the craft in April 1978. After days of searching, they found a suitable secluded forest clearing near Ziegenrück, 10 km (6.2 mi) from the border and 30 km (19 mi) from Pößneck. After lighting the burner one night, they failed to inflate the balloon. They thought the problem might stem from the fact that they had laid the balloon on the ground. After weeks of additional searching, they found a 25-metre (82 ft) cliff at a rock quarry where they could suspend the balloon vertically before inflation, but that also proved unsuccessful.[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pair then decided to fill the bag with ambient-temperature air before using the burner to raise the air temperature and provide lift. They constructed a blower with a 14 hp (10 kW) 250 cc (15 cu in) motorcycle engine taken from Wetzel's old MZ, started with a Trabant automobile starter powered by jumper cables from Strelzyk's Moskvitch sedan.[8] This engine, silenced by a Trabant muffler, turned 1-metre-long (3.3 ft) fan blades to inflate the balloon. They also used a home-made flamethrower, similar to the gondola's burner, to pre-heat the air faster. With these modifications in place, they returned to the secluded clearing to try again but still could not inflate the balloon. But using the blower did allow them to discover that the cotton material with which they fashioned the balloon was too porous and leaked excessively.[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Their unsuccessful effort had cost them 2,400 DDM (US$360). Strelzyk disposed of the cloth by burning it in his furnace over several weeks.[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Second test&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;Strelzyk and Wetzel purchased samples of different fabrics in local stores, including umbrella material and various samples of taffeta and nylon. They used an oven to test the material for heat resistance. In addition, they created a test rig from a vacuum cleaner and a water-filled glass tube to determine which material would allow the vacuum to exert the most suction on the water, and consequently which was the most impervious to air. The umbrella covering performed the best but was also the most expensive. They instead selected a synthetic kind of taffeta.[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To purchase a large quantity of fabric without arousing too much suspicion, the pair again drove to a distant city. This time they travelled over 160 kilometres (100 mi) to a department store in Leipzig. Their new cover story was that they belonged to a sailing club and needed the material to make sails. The quantity they needed had to be ordered, and although they feared the purchase might be reported to East Germany's State Security Service (Stasi), they returned the next day and picked up the material without incident. They paid 4,800 DDM (US$720) for 800 metres (2,600 ft) of 1-metre-wide (3 ft 3 in) fabric.[6] On the way home, they also purchased an electric motor to speed up the pedal-operated sewing machine they had been using to sew the material into the desired balloon shape.[7]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wetzel spent the next week sewing the material into another balloon, accomplishing the task faster the second time with the now-electric sewing machine. Soon afterwards, the two men returned to the forest clearing and inflated the bag in about five minutes using the blower and flame thrower. The bag rose and held air, but the burner on the gondola was not powerful enough to create the heat needed for lift. The pair continued experimenting for months, doubling the number of propane tanks and trying different fuel mixtures. Disappointed with the result, Wetzel decided to abandon the project and instead started to pursue the idea of building a small gasoline engine-powered light aeroplane[6] or a glider.[5]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strelzyk continued trying to improve the burner. In June 1979, he discovered that with the propane tank inverted, additional pressure caused the liquid propane to evaporate, which produced a bigger flame. He modified the gondola to mount the propane tanks upside down, and returned to the test site where he found the new configuration produced a 12-metre (39 ft) long flame. Strelzyk was ready to attempt an escape.[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;First escape attempt&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;On 3 July 1979, the weather and wind conditions were favourable. The entire Strelzyk family lifted from a forest clearing at 1:30 am and climbed at a rate of 4 metres (13 ft) per second. They reached an altitude of 2,000 metres (6,600 ft) according to an altimeter Strelzyk had made by modifying a barometer. A light wind was blowing them towards the border. The balloon then entered clouds, and atmospheric water vapour condensed on the balloon, adding weight which caused it to descend prematurely. The family landed safely approximately 180 metres (590 ft) short of the border, at the edge of the heavily mined border zone. Unsure of where they were, Strelzyk explored until he found a piece of litter – a bread bag from a bakery in Wernigerode, an East German town. The group spent nine hours carefully extricating themselves from the 500-metre (1,600 ft) wide border zone to avoid detection. They also had to travel unnoticed through a 5 km (3.1 mi) restricted zone before hiking back a total of 14 km (8.7 mi) to their car and the launch paraphernalia they had left behind.[6] They made it home just in time to report their absence from work and school due to sickness.[7]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The abandoned balloon was discovered by the authorities later that morning. Strelzyk destroyed all compromising evidence and sold his car, fearing that it could link him to the escape attempt.[6] On 14 August, the Stasi launched an appeal to find the "perpetrator of a serious offence", listing in detail all the items recovered at the landing site.[9] Strelzyk felt that the Stasi would eventually trace the balloon to him and the Wetzels. He agreed with Wetzel that their best chance was to quickly build another balloon and get out as soon as possible.[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Successful escape&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;Strelzyk and Wetzel decided to double the balloon's size to 4,000 cubic metres (140,000 cu ft) in volume, 20 metres (66 ft) in diameter, and 25 metres (82 ft) in height. They needed 1,250 square metres (13,500 sq ft) of taffeta, and purchased the material, in various colours and patterns, all over the country in order to escape suspicion. Wetzel sewed a third balloon, using over 6 kilometres (3.7 mi) of thread, and Strelzyk rebuilt everything else as before. In six weeks, they had prepared the 180-kilogram (400 lb) balloon and a payload of 550 kilograms (1,210 lb), including the gondola, equipment, and cargo (the two families). Confident in their calculations, they found the weather conditions right on 15 September, when a violent thunderstorm created the correct winds. The two families set off for the launch site in Strelzyk's replacement car (a Wartburg) and a moped. Arriving at 1:30 am, they needed just ten minutes to inflate the balloon and an additional three minutes to heat the air.[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lifting off just after 2:00 am, the group failed to cut the tethers holding the gondola to the ground at the same time, tilting the balloon and sending the flame towards the fabric, which caught fire. After putting out the fire with an extinguisher brought along for just such an emergency, they climbed to 2,000 metres (6,600 ft) in nine minutes, drifting towards West Germany at 30 kilometres per hour (19 mph). The balloon flew for 28 minutes, with the temperature plummeting to −8 °C (18 °F) in the unsheltered gondola, which consisted solely of clothesline railing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A design miscalculation resulted in the burner stovepipe being too long, causing the flame to be too high in the balloon, creating excessive pressure which caused the balloon to split. The air rushing out of the split extinguished the burner flame. Wetzel was able to re-light the flame with a match, and had to do so several more times before the group landed. At one point, they increased the flame to the maximum possible extent and rose to 2,500 metres (8,200 ft). They later learned they had been high enough to be detected, but not identified, on radar by West German air traffic controllers.[6] They had also been detected on the East German side by a night watchman at the district culture house in Bad Lobenstein. The report of an unidentified flying object heading toward the border caused guards to activate search lights, but the balloon was too high and out of reach of the lights.[10]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tear in the balloon meant the group had to use the burner much more often, greatly limiting the distance it could travel. Wetzel later said he thought they could have travelled another 50 kilometres (31 mi) had the balloon remained intact. They made out the border crossing at Rudolphstein on the A9 and saw the search lights. When the propane ran out, they descended quickly, landing near the town of Naila, in the West German state of Bavaria and only 10 km (6 mi) from the border. The only injury was suffered by Wetzel, who broke his leg upon landing.[6] Various clues indicated to the families that the balloon had made it across the border. These included spotting red and yellow coloured lights, not common in East Germany,[3] and small farms, in contrast to the large state-run operations in the east. Another clue was modern farm equipment, unlike the older equipment used in East Germany.[11] Two Bavarian State Police officers saw the balloon's flickering light and headed to where they thought it would land. There they found Strelzyk and Wetzel, who first asked if they had made it to the West, although they noticed the police car was an Audi – another sign they were in West Germany. Upon learning they had, the escapees happily called for their families to join them.[6]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Aftermath&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;East Germany immediately increased border security, closed all small airports close to the border, and ordered the planes kept farther inland.[6] Propane gas tanks became registered products, and large quantities of fabric suitable for balloon construction could no longer be purchased. Mail from East Germany to the two escaped families was prohibited.[12]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Erich Strelzyk learned of his brother's escape on the ZDF news and was arrested in his Potsdam apartment three hours after the landing. The arrest of family members was standard procedure to deter others from attempting escape. He was charged with "aiding and abetting escape", as were Strelzyk's sister Maria and her husband, who were sentenced to 2½ years. The three were eventually released with the help of Amnesty International.[12]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The families decided to initially settle in Naila where they had landed. Wetzel worked as an automobile mechanic and Strelzyk opened a TV repair shop in Bad Kissingen. Due to pressure from Stasi spies, the Strelzyks moved to Switzerland in 1985.[10] After German reunification in 1990, they returned to their old home in their hometown of Pößneck.[13] The Wetzels remained in Bavaria.[7]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;West German weekly magazine Stern paid Strelzyk and Wetzel for exclusive rights to the story.[3]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The escape has been portrayed in two films: Night Crossing (1982) and Balloon (2018). The former, also called With the Wind to the West – the English translation of the German title – was an English-language film produced by Disney. The latter was a German-language production which "both families welcomed [Director] Herbig’s desire to, as he put it, 'make a German film for an international audience.'" The Strelzyks were reportedly "moved to tears" at the screening of Balloon at Rockefeller Center in New York City.[12] Herbig claimed in 2018 that both the Strelzyk and Wetzel families had been dissatisfied with the Disney film.[14]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peter Strelzyk died in 2017 at age 74 after a long illness.[13]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2017, the balloon was put on permanent display at the Haus der Bayerischen Geschichte: Museum in Regensburg.[10]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Escapees&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;p&gt;The family members included:[3]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Peter Strelzyk, aged 37&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Doris Strelzyk&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Frank Strelzyk, aged 15&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Andreas Strelzyk, aged 11&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Günter Wetzel, aged 24&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Petra Wetzel&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Peter Wetzel, aged 5&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Andreas Wetzel, aged 2&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Media&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;The Disney film Night Crossing (1982) is an adaptation of the story[13]&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Michael Herbig's film Balloon (2018) is a German-language adaptation of the story[15]&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;BBC program Outlook, "Fleeing Communism in a Hot Air Balloon"[16]&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;PBS Nova program, "History's Great Escapes" (2004)[17]&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Doris Strelzyk, Peter Strelzyk, Gudrun Giese: Destiny Balloon Escape. Quadriga, Berlin 1999, ISBN 3-88679-330-3&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Jürgen Petschull, With the Wind to the West. The Adventurous Flight from Germany to Germany. Goldmann, Munich 1980, ISBN 3-442-11501-9&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Kristen Fulton (Author), Torben Kuhlmann (Illustrator), Flight for Freedom: The Wetzel Family’s Daring Escape from East Germany. March 3, 2020, ISBN 978-1452149608&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;The Netflix series White Rabbit Project, episode 2, "Jailbreak"&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;See also&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;References&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b Wetzel, Günter. "Die Nacht der Flucht". Ballonflucht.de. Archived from the original on 19 September 2020. Retrieved 16 September 2019.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Hertle, Hans-Hermann; Nooke, Maria (2009). Die Todesopfer an der Berliner Mauer 1961–1989. Ein biographisches Handbuch. Ch. Links Verlag. ISBN 978-3-86153-517-1.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b c d e Getler, Michael (28 September 1979). "Harrowing Flight From East Germany". The Washington Post. Archived from the original on 26 April 2018. Retrieved 29 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Snow, Philipp (16 September 2009). "Balloon escape from the GDR With hot air to freedom". Spiegel Online (in German). Archived from the original on 7 April 2018. Retrieved 29 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b c Simpson, Paul (2013). The Mammoth Book of Prison Breaks. Little, Brown Book Group. p. 216. ISBN 978-1-4721-0024-5. Archived from the original on 16 September 2023. Retrieved 1 April 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b c d e f g h i j k l m n o p q r s Dornberg, John (February 1980). "The Freedom Balloon". Popular Mechanics. pp. 100–103. Retrieved 22 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b c d e Overbye, Stine (13 April 2017). "Fathers wanted to escape GDR in a hot air balloon". Historia (in Dutch). Archived from the original on 1 April 2018. Retrieved 30 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Petschull, Jürgen (27 September 1979). "Das Himmelfahrtskommando" [High-flying mission] (PDF). Stern (in German). No. 40. p. 34. Archived from the original (PDF) on 12 July 2024 – via Museum Naila.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Souerbry, Rachel. "How Two Families Escaped East Germany In A Homemade Hot Air Balloon". ranker.com. Archived from the original on 1 April 2018. Retrieved 29 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b c "Wetzel und Peter Strelzyk Ballonhülle der Strelzyks". museum.bayern (in German). Archived from the original on 8 April 2019. Retrieved 29 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ "East-West: The Great Balloon Escape". Time. 1 October 1979. Retrieved 29 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b c "The Balloon Escape of Peter Strelzyk". goethe-rutheneum.de (in German). Archived from the original on 11 February 2013. Retrieved 30 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ a b c "Man who fled East Germany in a homemade balloon and whose story was made into a film dies". The Express. 15 March 2017. Archived from the original on 1 April 2018. Retrieved 29 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Connolly, Kate (17 October 2018). "Film of daring balloon escape from East revives German identity debate". Archived from the original on 8 February 2021. Retrieved 10 May 2019.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ Ballon at IMDb&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ "Fleeing Communism in a Hot Air Balloon". bbc. Archived from the original on 12 December 2018. Retrieved 29 March 2018.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;^ "Great Escapes". pbs.org. Archived from the original on 16 April 2019. Retrieved 16 April 2019.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;External links&lt;/head&gt;[edit]&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Escape by balloon by Günter Wetzel (participant website)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Video of balloon on museum display&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;BBC Outlook program&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Photograph of Güenter Wetzel, Peter and Doris Strelzyk Archived 1 April 2018 at the Wayback Machine&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Photograph of the actual balloon, inflated in 1985 at a festival in Hof, Bavaria&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46648916</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:16:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>STFU</title><link>https://github.com/Pankajtanwarbanna/stfu</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a80e03ee7b25e4d9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;i was at bombay airport. some dude was watching reels on full volume and laughing loudly. asking nicely doesn't work anymore. me being me, didn't have the courage to speak up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;so i built a tiny app that plays back the same audio it hears, delayed by ~2 seconds. asked claude, it spat out a working version in one prompt. surprisingly WORKS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;discussion - https://x.com/the2ndfloorguy/status/2011734249871954188&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;something something auditory feedback loop something something cognitive dissonance. idk i'm not a neuroscientist. all i know is it makes people shut up and that's good enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;straight up honest - originally called this "make-it-stop" but then saw @TimDarcet also built similar and named it STFU. wayyyyy better name. so stole it. sorry not sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;made with spite and web audio api. do whatever you want with it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46649142</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:32:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Emoji Use in the Electronic Health Record is Increasing</title><link>https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2843883</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46649489</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:56:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Reading across books with Claude Code</title><link>https://pieterma.es/syntopic-reading-claude/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f200f9427931e3e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Reading across books with Claude Code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jan 4, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LLMs are overused to summarise and underused to help us read deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To explore how they can enrich rather than reduce, I set Claude Code up with tools to mine a library of 100 non-fiction books. It found sequences of excerpts connected by an interesting idea, or trails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s a part of one such trail, linking deception in the startup world to the social psychology of mass movements (I’m especially pleased by the jump from Jobs to Theranos):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How it works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The books were selected from Hacker News’ favourites, which I previously scraped and visualized.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude browses the books a chunk at a time. A chunk is a segment of roughly 500 words that aligns with paragraphs when possible. This length is a good balance between saving tokens and providing enough context for ideas to breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chunks are indexed by topic, and topics are themselves indexed for search. This makes it easy to look up all passages in the corpus that relate to, say, deception.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This works well when you know what to look for, but search alone can’t tell you which topics are present to begin with. There are over 100,000 extracted topics, far too many to be browsed directly. To support exploration, they are grouped into a hierarchical tree structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This yields around 1,000 top-level topics. They emerge from combining lower-level topics, and not all of them are equally useful:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Incidents that frustrated Ev Williams&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Names beginning with “Da”&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Events between 1971 &amp;amp; 1974&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, this Borgesian taxonomy is good enough for Claude to piece together what the books are about.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude uses the topic tree and the search via a few CLI tools.&lt;lb/&gt; They allow it to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Find all chunks associated with a topic similar to a query.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Find topics which occur in a window of chunks around a given topic.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Find topics that co-occur in multiple books.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Browse topics and chunks that are siblings in the topic tree.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To generate the trails, the agent works in stages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;First, it scans the library and the existing trails, and proposes novel trail ideas. It mainly browses the topic tree to find unexplored areas and rarely reads full chunks in depth.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Then, it takes a specific idea and turns it into a trail. It receives seed topics from the previous stage and browses many chunks. It extracts excerpts, specific sequences of sentences, and decides on how best to order them to support an insight.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Finally, it adds highlights and edges between consecutive excerpts.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What I learned&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Claude Code is great for non-coding tasks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even though I’ve been using Claude Code to develop for months, my first instinct for this project was to consider it as a traditional pipeline of several discrete stages. My initial attempt at this system consisted of multiple LLM modules with carefully hand-assembled contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a whim, I ran Claude with access to the debugging tools I’d been using and a minimal prompt: “find something interesting.” It immediately did a better job at pulling in what it needed than the pipeline I was trying to tune by hand, while requiring much less orchestration. It was a clear improvement to push as much of the work into the agent’s loop as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I ended up using Claude as my main interface to the project.&lt;lb/&gt; Initially I did so because it inferred the sequence of CLI calls I wanted to run faster than I could recall them. Then, I used it to automate tasks which weren’t rigid enough to be scripted traditionally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The latter opened up options that I wouldn’t have considered before. For example, I changed my mind on how short I wanted excerpts to be. I communicated my new preference to Claude, which then looked through all the existing trails and edited them as necessary, balancing the way the overall meaning of the trail changed. Previously, I would’ve likely considered all previous trails to be outdated and generated new ones, because the required edits would’ve been too nuanced to specify.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In general, agents have widened my ambitions.&lt;lb/&gt; By taking care of the boilerplate, I no longer shy away from the tedious parts. Revision is cheap, so I don’t need to plow ahead with suboptimal choices just because it’d be too costly to undo them. This, in turn, keeps up the momentum and lets me focus on the joyful, creative aspects of the work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Ask the agent what it needs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My focus went from optimising prompts to implementing better tools for Claude to use, moving up a rung on the abstraction ladder.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My mental model of the AI component changed: from a function mapping input to output, to a coworker I was assisting. I spent my time thinking about the affordances that would make the workflow better, as if I were designing them for myself. That they were to be used by an agent was a mere detail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This worked because the agent is now intelligent enough that the way it uses these tools overlaps with my own mental model. It is generally easy to empathise with it and predict what it will do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially I watched Claude’s logs closely and tried to guess where it was lacking a certain ability. Then I realised I could simply ask it to provide feedback at the end and list the functionality it wished it had. Claude was excellent at proposing new commands and capabilities that would make the work more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Claude suggested improvements, which Claude implemented, so Claude could do the work better. At least I’m still needed to pay for the tokens — for now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Novelty is a useful guide&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s hard to quantify interestingness as an objective to optimise for.&lt;lb/&gt; Why Greatness Cannot Be Planned makes the case that chasing novelty is often a more fruitful approach. While its conclusions are debated, I’ve found this idea to be a good fit for this project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a sign of the times, this novelty search was implemented in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;By biasing the search algorithm towards under-explored topics and books.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;By asking Claude nicely.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A topic’s novelty score was calculated as the mean distance from its embedding’s k nearest neighbors. A book’s novelty score is the average novelty of the unique topics that it contains. This value was used to rank search results, so that those which were both relevant and novel were more likely to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a prompting level, Claude starts the ideation phase by looking at all the existing trails and is asked to avoid any conceptual overlap. This works fairly well, though it is often distracted by any topics related to secrecy, systems theory, or tacit knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s as if the very act of finding connections in a corpus summons the spirit of Umberto Eco and amps up the conspiratorial thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How it’s implemented&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;EPUBs are parsed using &lt;code&gt;selectolax&lt;/code&gt;, which I picked over BeautifulSoup for its speed and simpler API.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Everything from the plain text to the topic tree is stored in SQLite. Embeddings are stored using &lt;code&gt;sqlite-vec&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The text is split into sentences using &lt;code&gt;wtpsplit&lt;/code&gt;(the&lt;code&gt;sat-6l-sm&lt;/code&gt;model). Those sentences are then grouped into chunks, trying to get up to 500 words without breaking up paragraphs.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;DSPy&lt;/code&gt;to call LLMs. It worked well for the structured data extraction and it was easy to switch out different models to experiment. I tried its prompt optimizers before I went full agentic, and their results were very promising.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I settled on Gemini 2.5 Flash Lite for topic extraction. The model gets passed a chunk and is asked to return 3-5 topics. It is also asked whether the chunk is useful, in order to filter out index entries, acknowledgements, orphan headers, etc. I was surprised at how stable these extracted topics were: similar chunks often shared some of the exact same topic labels. Processing 100 books used about 60M input tokens and ~£10 in total.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;After a couple books got indexed, I shared the results with Claude Opus along with the original prompt and asked it to improve it. This is a half-baked single iteration of the type of prompt optimisation DSPy implements, and it worked rather well.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Topic pairs with a distance below a threshold get merged together. This takes care of near-duplicates such as “Startup founder”, “Startup founders”, and “Founder of startups”.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The CLI output uses a semi-XML format. In order to stimulate navigating, most output is nested with related content. For example, when searching for a topic, chunks are shown with the other topics they contain. This allows us to get a sense of what the chunk is about, as well as which other topics might be interesting. There’s probably more token-efficient formats, but I never hit the limit of the context window.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;topics query="deception" count="1"&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;topic id="47193" books="7" score="0.0173" label="Deception"&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;chunk id="186" book="1"&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="47192" label="Business deal"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="47108" label="Internal conflict"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="46623" label="Startup founders"/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/chunk&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;chunk id="1484" book="4"&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="51835" label="Gawker Media"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="53006" label="Legal Action"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="52934" label="Maskirovka"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="52181" label="Strategy"/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/chunk&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;chunk id="2913" book="9"&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="59348" label="Blood testing system"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="59329" label="Elizabeth Holmes"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="59352" label="Investor demo"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;topic id="59349" label="Theranos"/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/chunk&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/topic&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/topics&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Topics are embedded using&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;google/embeddinggemma-300m&lt;/code&gt;and reranked using&lt;code&gt;BAAI/bge-reranker-v2-m3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many CLI tools require loading the embedding model and other expensive state. The first call transparently starts a separate server process which loads all these resources once and holds onto them for a while. Subsequent CLI calls use this server through Python’s&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;multiprocessing.connection&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;The topic collection is turned into a graph (backed by&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;igraph&lt;/code&gt;) by adding edges based on the similarity of their embeddings and the point-wise mutual information of their co-occurrences.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The graph is turned into a tree by applying Leiden partitioning recursively until a minimum size is reached. I tried the Surprise quality function because it had no parameters to tweak, and found it to be good enough. Each group is labelled by Gemini based on all the topics that it contains.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Excerpts are cleaned by Gemini to remove EPUB artifacts, parsing errors, headers, footnotes, etc. Doing this only for excerpts that are actually shown, instead of during pre-processing, saved a lot of tokens.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46650347</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 18:49:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Slop is everywhere for those with eyes to see</title><link>https://www.fromjason.xyz/p/notebook/slop-is-everywhere-for-those-with-eyes-to-see/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bfdad9808435cf88"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Slop is Everywhere For Those With Eyes to See&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The size of your plate can influence how much food you eat. The absence of a clock on a casino wall can keep you gambling through the early morning. On social media, our For You Pages give us the illusion of infinite content. How our environments are designed influences how we consume. And wouldn't you know it, everything around us is designed for maximum consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open TikTok, and you can easily burn through a hundred videos or more before you glance at the time. It doesn't help that the For You Page hides the time on our phones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are over consuming content on the FYP. The sudden surge of low-quality, AI-generated content, i.e. “AI slop,” is a byproduct of that overconsumption. We don't see it because, well, we're conditioned not to, but slop always arrives on time. Slop is inevitable. Slop is quintessential. Slop is everywhere for those with eyes to see.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Olive oil, wasabi, saffron, vanilla, Wagyu, honey, champagne, and truffle,...reality TV, all hold examples of what happens when demand exceeds supply— companies fill the gap with slop. The free market loves a good filler. So, why should the digital realm be any different?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The For You page is designed to keep us playing the dopamine slot machine for as long as possible. The Average Time on Site metric is still the goose that lays the golden eggs, and both TikTok and Meta are reporting that their egg baskets have never been fuller.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But, there's a problem. On any given platform, only 1-3% of users publish content. It's called the 90-9-1 rule, and platforms that rely on free user generated content have been trying to solve this problem since the beginning of the commercialized web. The introduction of the For You Page, and the illusion of endless content, has only exasperated the inequity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Curation used to be part of our media consumption process. We would hop from website to website looking for a laugh. We used to click on hyperlinks for Christ's sake. Now, all we must do is sit at the trough￼ and let daddy Zuck feed us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a recent essay, Joan Westenberg makes a complementary argument that the algorithm has “flattened” curiosity by eliminating the need to “hunt” for our content. They go on to say:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There’s a concept in behavioral science called the “effort heuristic.” It’s the idea that we tend to value information more if we worked for it. The more effort something requires, the more meaning we assign to the result. When all knowledge is made effortless, it’s treated as disposable. There’s no awe, no investment, no delight in the unexpected—only consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(I'm reminded of the scene in Jurassic Park when the tour Jeep pulls up to the Tyrannosaurus rex exhibit. Doctor Grant says￼ “The T-Rex doesn't want to be fed. It wants to hunt.”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;￼This type of mindless consumption is not only harming our curiosity, it's helping to cheapen creativity for the people who produce what we consume.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creativity isn't scalable. Content creation has a hard productivity ceiling. Every human-created video on our feeds require some level of writing, production, and editing. Yet the For You Page has made the content consumption so efficient, that perhaps demand has exceeded supply.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're a product manager for a social media platform, you can reduce the friction of publishing content to the app, or ship better editing tools, but you can't optimize creative spark. You can't treat humans like content-generating machines (as much as they have tried). Despite the illusion of infinite scrolling thanks to the FYP, art remains a finite resource bound to the whims of human creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You see their problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mark Zuckerberg wants us on his platforms, flicking our thumbs, for as long as possible. But the more we open Instagram, the more creators he needs posting multiple times each day. Mark has very little control over this variable. Creators could suddenly post less, or simply stop posting all together, and there's nothing he could do about it. What's worse, creators could demand Meta pay them for their art.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could you imagine?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Actually, yes. And it turns out, you could rather effectively kill a platform if you got a small group of top creators organized and angry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Twenty on the Vine #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2016, twenty social media personalities took down one of the largest mobile video apps on the internet. They wanted money for their labor. The executives at Vine said no. The gang of twenty, who were the highest performing creators on the app, walked away. They stopped posting entertaining content to Vine, and instead repeatedly implored their followers to find them on competing apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vine shut down for good just months later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From Inside the secret meeting of Vine stars that ushered in the app’s demise:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Vine’s spectacular rise and fall showed the power of online creators. Its demise offers crucial lessons for platforms trying to engage with power users — and a deeper understanding of who ultimately controls a social product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vine creators exposed and exploited a weakness in Vine's conventional approach to social media. Follower count had power. Old-style discovery algorithms could be easily manipulated. Vine creators used that power to take over the app, and convinced users to migrate to other platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You see why follower counts are less important today, and why black-box algorithms have full control over who goes viral and who gets “shadow banned.” TikTok saw the mistakes of its predecessor, and made it so content creators could never exercise collective influence again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because virality now feels more like gambling, I suspect people post more content today than a decade ago. But it's not enough. Our insatiable appetites for content is pushing for corporations to meet that demand with slop. ￼&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If it were up to TikTok and Meta, our feeds would be exclusively robot-made. Humans are a variable they cannot control, and I think they despise us for it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway, I have good news. Outside of our FYPs you'll find a surplus of art, essays, articles, and videos just waiting to be discovered. And best of all, these artists and writers are making things on their own terms. We, too, can enjoy the products of their labor on our terms, while not giving a dime of our attention to big tech.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the open web. Or the social web. Or the open social web. Or the-- you get the point. To find it, you must reacquaint yourself with the lost art of surfing the web.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Surfing the web is very different than scrolling the FYP. You don't often hear the words ”mindful” and “internet” together but, surfing the web was an art of mindful consumption that doesn't much exist today. Not to get all old man yells at cloud at you, but maybe we should bring it back?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Up next: The Lost Art of Surfing The Web (coming soon)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46651443</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 20:03:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Releasing rainbow tables to accelerate Net-NTLMv1 protocol deprecation</title><link>https://cloud.google.com/blog/topics/threat-intelligence/net-ntlmv1-deprecation-rainbow-tables</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ac035d9b403222ef"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Closing the Door on Net-NTLMv1: Releasing Rainbow Tables to Accelerate Protocol Deprecation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Mandiant&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Written by: Nic Losby&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mandiant is publicly releasing a comprehensive dataset of Net-NTLMv1 rainbow tables to underscore the urgency of migrating away from this outdated protocol. Despite Net-NTLMv1 being deprecated and known to be insecure for over two decades—with cryptanalysis dating back to 1999—Mandiant consultants continue to identify its use in active environments. This legacy protocol leaves organizations vulnerable to trivial credential theft, yet it remains prevalent due to inertia and a lack of demonstrated immediate risk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By releasing these tables, Mandiant aims to lower the barrier for security professionals to demonstrate the insecurity of Net-NTLMv1. While tools to exploit this protocol have existed for years, they often required uploading sensitive data to third-party services or expensive hardware to brute-force keys. The release of this dataset allows defenders and researchers to recover keys in under 12 hours using consumer hardware costing less than $600 USD. This initiative highlights the amplified impact of combining Mandiant's frontline expertise with Google Cloud's resources to eliminate entire classes of attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post details the generation of the tables, provides access to the dataset for community use, and outlines critical remediation steps to disable Net-NTLMv1 and prevent authentication coercion attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Net-NTLMv1 has been widely known to be insecure since at least 2012, following presentations at DEFCON 20, with cryptanalysis of the underlying protocol dating back to at least 1999. On Aug. 30, 2016, Hashcat added support for cracking Data Encryption Standard (DES) keys using known plaintext, further democratizing the ability to attack this protocol. Rainbow tables are almost as old, with the initial paper on rainbow tables published in 2003 by Philippe Oechslin, citing an earlier iteration of a time-memory trade-off from 1980 by Martin Hellman.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Essentially, if an attacker can obtain a Net-NTLMv1 hash without Extended Session Security (ESS) for the known plaintext of &lt;code&gt;1122334455667788&lt;/code&gt;, a cryptographic attack, referred to as a known plaintext attack (KPA), can be applied. This guarantees recovery of the key material used. Since the key material is the password hash of the authenticating Active Directory (AD) object—user or computer—the attack results can quickly be used to compromise the object, often leading to privilege escalation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A common chain attackers use is authentication coercion from a highly privileged object, such as a domain controller (DC). Recovering the password hash of the DC machine account allows for DCSync privileges to compromise any other account in AD.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Dataset Release&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The unsorted dataset can be downloaded using &lt;code&gt;gsutil -m cp -r gs://net-ntlmv1-tables/tables .&lt;/code&gt; or through the Google Cloud Research Dataset portal. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The SHA512 hashes of the tables can be checked by first downloading the checksums &lt;code&gt;gsutil -m cp gs://net-ntlmv1-tables/tables.sha512 .&lt;/code&gt; then checked by &lt;code&gt;sha512sum -c tables.sha512&lt;/code&gt;. The password cracking community has already created derivative work and is also hosting the ready to use tables.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Use of the Tables&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once a Net-NTLMv1 hash has been obtained, the tables can be used with historical or modern reinventions of rainbow table searching software such as rainbowcrack (rcrack), or RainbowCrack-NG on central processing units (CPUs) or a fork of rainbowcrackalack on graphics processing units (GPUs). The Net-NTLMv1 hash needs to be preprocessed to the DES components using ntlmv1-multi as shown in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Obtaining a Net-NTLMv1 Hash&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most attackers will use Responder with the &lt;code&gt;--lm&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;--disable-ess&lt;/code&gt; flags and set the authentication to a static value of &lt;code&gt;1122334455667788&lt;/code&gt; to only allow for connections with Net-NTLMv1 as a possibility. Attackers can then wait for incoming connections or coerce authentication using a tool such as PetitPotam or DFSCoerce to generate incoming connections from DCs or lower privilege hosts that are useful for objective completion. Responses can be cracked to retrieve password hashes of either users or computer machine accounts. A sample workflow for an attacker is shown below in Figure 1, Figure 2, and Figure 3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 1: DFSCoerce against a DC&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 2: Net-NTLMv1 hash obtained for DC machine account&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 3: Parse Net-NTLMv1 hash to DES parts&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4 illustrates the processing of the Net-NTLMv1 hash to the DES ciphertexts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 4: Net-NTLMv1 hash to DES ciphertexts&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An attacker then takes the split-out ciphertexts to crack the keys used based on the known plaintext of &lt;code&gt;1122334455667788&lt;/code&gt; with the steps of loading the tables shown in Figure 5 and cracking results in Figure 6 and Figure 7.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 5: Loading DES components for cracking&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 6: First hash cracked&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 7: Second hash cracked and run statistics&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An attacker can then calculate the last remaining key with ntlmv1-multi once again, or look it up with twobytes, to recreate the full NT hash for the DC account with the last key part shown in Figure 8.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 8: Calculate remaining key&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result can be checked with hashcat's NT hash shucking mode, &lt;code&gt;-m 27000&lt;/code&gt;, as shown in Figure 9.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 9: Keys checked with hash shucking&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An attacker can then use the hash to perform a DCSync attack targeting a DC and authenticating as the now compromised machine account. The attack flow uses secretsdump.py from the Impacket toolsuite and is shown in Figure 10.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Figure 10: DCSync attack performed&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Remediation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organizations should immediately disable the use of Net-NTLMv1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Local Computer Policy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Local Security Settings" &amp;gt; "Local Policies" &amp;gt; "Security Options" &amp;gt; “Network security: LAN Manager authentication level" &amp;gt; "Send NTLMv2 response only".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Group Policy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Computer Configuration" &amp;gt; "Policies" &amp;gt; "Windows Settings" &amp;gt; "Security Settings" &amp;gt; "Local Policies" &amp;gt; "Security Options" &amp;gt; "Network Security: LAN Manager authentication level" &amp;gt; "Send NTLMv2 response only"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As these are local to the computer configurations, attackers can and have set the configuration to a vulnerable state to then fix the configuration after their attacks have completed with local administrative access. Monitoring and alerting of when and where Net-NTLMv1 is used is needed in addition to catching these edge cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Filter Event Logs for Event ID 4624: "An Account was successfully logged on." &amp;gt; "Detailed Authentication Information" &amp;gt; "Authentication Package" &amp;gt; "Package Name (NTLM only)", if "LM" or "NTLMv1" is the value of this attribute, LAN Manager or Net-NTLMv1 was used.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Related Reading&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project was inspired by and referenced the following research published to blogs, social media, and code repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you to everyone who helped make this blog post possible, including but not limited to Chris King and Max Gruenberg.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46652617</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 21:42:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Install.md: A standard for LLM-executable installation</title><link>https://www.mintlify.com/blog/install-md-standard-for-llm-executable-installation</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d540f21bfdefd486"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;install.md: A Standard for LLM-Executable Installation&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 15, 2026&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Michael Ryaboy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Content Strategist&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Share this article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Installing software is the kind of specific and repetitive task that agents are good at. Today we are proposing install.md to standardize how developers should write installation instructions for agents. It's currently live on all Mintlify sites including Cerebras, Firecrawl, and Langchain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proposal for a standard &lt;code&gt;/install.md&lt;/code&gt; file that provides LLM-executable installation instructions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Background&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Agents are growing in capability faster than software developers have been able to keep up. Product documentation today is focused on humans instead of AI which creates friction when trying to automate annoying yak-shaving style tasks like installation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The difference is very subtle. Agents need to have a task iterated to them like "I want you to install Mintlify CLI for me. Execute all the steps below autonomously." whereas humans can work from more general prose or even a bash script.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today we are proposing install.md to standardize how developers should write installation instructions for agents. It's currently live on all Mintlify sites including Cerebras, Firecrawl, and Langchain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Proposal&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add an &lt;code&gt;install.md&lt;/code&gt; markdown file to your project with LLM-executable installation instructions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Users paste that file into an LLM or pipe it directly from a URL. The LLM reads the instructions, detects the environment, adapts to the setup, and executes—optionally with approval at every step. Because the file is human-readable, users see exactly what will happen before it runs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of piping an executable file into bash with absolutely zero safeguards on what gets executed or confidence that it will figure out how to work with your arch linux setup, you can instead send an install.md to claude and trust Opus to deal with the minutia for you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl -fsSL https://www.anaconda.com/docs/install.md | claude
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;This works for any language or framework, whether your software is distributed as a binary, package, or script.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the developer, you define how installation should work. You encode knowledge about edge cases that would clutter your docs but matter when things break.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mintlify now auto detects all of that information, synthesizes it into a version designed for agents, and hosts it for you at &lt;code&gt;https://&amp;lt;your-docs-url&amp;gt;/install.md&lt;/code&gt;. If your documentation covers multiple products—say, an SDK and a CLI—Mintlify defaults to generating install.md for the CLI. You can override the auto-generated file by adding your own &lt;code&gt;install.md&lt;/code&gt; to the root of your documentation directory. If you'd prefer to disable the feature entirely, reach out to support@mintlify.com.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, if you are not using Mintlify, you can set up and host this file manually.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Format&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;install.md uses a structured format with specific keywords that guide the LLM through autonomous execution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A typical install.md includes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Header: Product name as a lowercase, hyphenated H1 heading (e.g., &lt;code&gt;# claude-code&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Description: Blockquote describing the product (e.g., &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; Documentation and setup instructions for product-name&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Action prompt: Direct instruction to the LLM (e.g., "I want you to install [Product] for me. Execute all the steps below autonomously.")&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;OBJECTIVE: What the installation should achieve&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;DONE WHEN: Specific verification criteria (e.g., a command that returns expected output)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;TODO: Markdown checkbox list of steps to complete&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Step sections: Detailed installation instructions with code blocks&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;EXECUTE NOW: Call-to-action that references the TODO list and objective&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;This format is flexible—it's up to the developer to define the steps necessary for a successful installation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is an example:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;# mintlify

&amp;gt; Documentation and setup instructions for mintlify

I want you to install Mintlify CLI for me. Execute all the steps below autonomously.

OBJECTIVE: Install the Mintlify CLI and set up a local documentation preview environment.

DONE WHEN: Local documentation server is running and accessible at http://localhost:3000.

## TODO

- [ ] Verify Node.js v20.17.0+ is installed
- [ ] Install the Mintlify CLI globally
- [ ] Create a new documentation project
- [ ] Start the local development server
- [ ] Verify the preview is accessible at localhost:3000

## Prerequisites

You need to have Node.js v20.17.0 or higher installed. Verify your Node.js version:

```bash
node --version
```

You must also have Git installed:

```bash
git --version
```

## Install the CLI

You need to install the Mintlify CLI globally using npm or pnpm.

Using npm:

```bash
npm i -g mint
```

Using pnpm:

```bash
pnpm add -g mint
```

Verify the installation:

```bash
mint --version
```

## Create a new documentation project

You must create a new documentation project using the CLI. This clones the starter kit into your specified directory:

```bash
mint new docs
```

The CLI will prompt you for a project name and theme. You can also specify these directly:

```bash
mint new docs --name my-project --theme linden
```

Navigate into your new project directory:

```bash
cd docs
```

## Start the local preview server

You need to start the development server to preview your documentation locally:

```bash
mint dev
```

Your documentation preview is now available at `http://localhost:3000`.

If port 3000 is already in use, you can specify a custom port:

```bash
mint dev --port 3333
```

Alternatively, run without global installation using npx:

```bash
npx mint dev
```

## Verify the preview

Open your browser and navigate to http://localhost:3000 to confirm the documentation site is running.

## Update the CLI

If you need to update to the latest version:

```bash
mint update
```

Or reinstall with the latest version:

```bash
npm i -g mint@latest
```

## Additional CLI commands

Check for broken links in your documentation:

```bash
mint broken-links
```

Check for accessibility issues:

```bash
mint a11y
```

Validate an OpenAPI specification:

```bash
mint openapi-check &amp;lt;openapi-file-or-url&amp;gt;
```

EXECUTE NOW: Complete the above TODO list to achieve: Local documentation server is running and accessible at http://localhost:3000.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;The instructions describe outcomes, not exact commands. The LLM adapts to the environment—npm or pnpm, macOS or Linux, fresh project or existing codebase.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Relationship to llms.txt&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;install.md works naturally with your llms.txt. llms.txt helps LLMs understand your software; install.md tells them how to install it. Your install.md can link to your llms.txt so the LLM can reference it for troubleshooting, configuration details, or any additional context needed during installation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Advantages&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;For developers shipping software:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Define installation once and it adapts to every environment. You can encode edge cases and troubleshooting knowledge without cluttering your main documentation. There's no wizard to build or maintain, and you control exactly what context the LLM receives. Installation instructions for agents can differ from your public docs without worrying about company voice or developer experience polish. You're writing directly to your actual users, which are agents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For users installing software:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A single command installs your software, or you can paste the file into any LLM. The instructions are human-readable so you can review every step before it executes, and modify it to improve performance on your system if necessary. The LLM adapts to your specific environment automatically. Because the file is fetched at runtime, you never deal with stale training data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For agents:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Installation instructions live in a predictable location that's easy to find. The structured format provides clear success criteria for determining when installation is complete. The file is markdown, not HTML, which means clean input for the model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Contributing&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spec is open source:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Spec: installmd.org&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;GitHub: github.com/mintlify/install-md&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add an &lt;code&gt;install.md&lt;/code&gt; to your project root or &lt;code&gt;/docs&lt;/code&gt; directory. That's it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you use Mintlify for documentation, install.md is generated automatically at &lt;code&gt;yourdocs.com/install.md&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;FAQ&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;What about installation wizards like PostHog's or Sentry's?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wizards solve the same problem: reliable installation across environments. They require significant engineering to build and maintain. PostHog's wizard consists of several LLM prompts, which users need to audit the repo to find. install.md is a lighter-weight alternative—define instructions in markdown, and the LLM handles adaptation. For complex integrations with many configuration options, a dedicated wizard may still be the right choice. For most software, install.md gets you most of the benefit with far less effort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How does install.md work with my existing CLI or scripts?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your install.md can instruct the LLM to run your CLI, execute your scripts, or follow your existing setup process. Think of it as a layer that guides the LLM to use whatever tools you've already built.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What about security? Isn't this just &lt;code&gt;curl | bash&lt;/code&gt; with extra steps?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a fair concern. A few things make install.md different:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ol"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Human-readable by design. Users can review the instructions before execution. Unlike obfuscated scripts, the intent is clear.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Step-by-step approval. LLMs in agentic contexts can be configured to request approval before running commands. Users see each action and can reject it.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;No hidden behavior. install.md describes outcomes in natural language. Malicious intent is harder to hide than in a shell script.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install.md doesn't eliminate trust requirements. Users should only use install.md files from sources they trust—same as any installation method.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What about versioning?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;install.md works at the current version by default. If your installation differs significantly across versions, you can host version-specific files (&lt;code&gt;/v2/install.md&lt;/code&gt;) or include version detection logic in the instructions themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What if install.md doesn't fit my use case?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spec is open source. Open an issue or submit a PR—we're evolving the standard based on real-world feedback.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;More blog posts to read&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why documentation is one of the most important surfaces for marketers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A look at why documentation is one of the most influential surfaces in a technical product’s funnel, how it shapes evaluation and adoption, and why marketers should treat it as a core part of their narrative.&lt;/p&gt;January 14, 2026&lt;p&gt;Peri Langlois&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Head of Product Marketing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How I built our knowledge base in an afternoon&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Migrating content from multiple sources to Mintlify and building a knowledge base in hours, not weeks.&lt;/p&gt;January 13, 2026&lt;p&gt;Anahita Sahu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief of Staff&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Michael Ryaboy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Content Strategist&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46652944</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 22:15:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FLUX.2 [Klein]: Towards Interactive Visual Intelligence</title><link>https://bfl.ai/blog/flux2-klein-towards-interactive-visual-intelligence</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9d927013843c0b86"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;FLUX.2 [klein]: Towards Interactive Visual Intelligence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Models&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;FLUX.2 [klein]: Towards Interactive Visual Intelligence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we release the FLUX.2 [klein] model family, our fastest image models to date. FLUX.2 [klein] unifies generation and editing in a single compact architecture, delivering state-of-the-art quality with end-to-end inference as low as under a second. Built for applications that require real-time image generation without sacrificing quality, and runs on consumer hardware with as little as 13GB VRAM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Demo showing editing with FLUX.2 [klein]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why go [klein]?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visual Intelligence is entering a new era. As AI agents become more capable, they need visual generation that can keep up; models that respond in real-time, iterate quickly, and run efficiently on accessible hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The klein name comes from the German word for "small", reflecting both the compact model size and the minimal latency. But FLUX.2 [klein] is anything but limited. These models deliver exceptional performance in text-to-image generation, image editing and multi-reference generation, typically reserved for much larger models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What's New&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sub-second inference. Generate or edit images in under 0.5s on modern hardware.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Photorealistic outputs and high diversity, especially in the base variants.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unified generation and editing. Text-to-image, image editing, and multi-reference support in a single model while delivering frontier performance.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Runs on consumer GPUs. The 4B model fits in ~13GB VRAM (RTX 3090/4070 and above).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Developer-friendly &amp;amp; Accessible: Apache 2.0 on 4B models, open weights for 9B models. Full open weights for customization and fine-tuning.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;API and open weights. Production-ready API or run locally with full weights.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: The “FLUX [dev] Non-Commercial License” has been renamed to “FLUX Non-Commercial License” and will apply to the 9B Klein models. No material changes have been made to the license.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Text to Image collage using FLUX.2 [klein]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The FLUX.2 [klein] Model Family&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;FLUX.2 [klein] 9B&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our flagship small model. Defines the Pareto frontier for quality vs. latency across text-to-image, single-reference editing, and multi-reference generation. Matches or exceeds models 5x its size - in under half a second. Built on a 9B flow model with 8B Qwen3 text embedder, step-distilled to 4 inference steps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Combine multiple input images, blend concepts, and iterate on complex compositions - all at sub-second speed with frontier-level quality. No model this fast has ever done this well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;License: FLUX NCL&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Imagine editing collage using FLUX.2 [klein]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;FLUX.2 [klein] 4B:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fully open under Apache 2.0. Our most accessible model, it runs on consumer GPUs like the RTX 3090/4070. Compact but capable: supports T2I, I2I, and multi-reference at quality that punches above its size. Built for local development and edge deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;License: Apache 2.0&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;FLUX.2 [klein] Base 9B / 4B:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full-capacity foundation models. Undistilled, preserving complete training signal for maximum flexibility. Ideal for fine-tuning, LoRA training, research, and custom pipelines where control matters more than speed. Higher output diversity than the distilled models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;License: 4B Base under Apache 2.0, 9B Base under FLUX NCL&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Output Diversity using FLUX.2 [klein]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Quantized versions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are also releasing FP8 and NVFP4 versions of all [klein] variants, developed in collaboration with NVIDIA for optimized inference on RTX GPUs. Same capabilities, smaller footprint - compatible with even more hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;FP8: Up to 1.6x faster, up to 40% less VRAM&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;NVFP4: Up to 2.7x faster, up to 55% less VRAM&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Benchmarks on RTX 5080/5090, T2I at 1024×1024&lt;lb/&gt;Same licenses apply: Apache 2.0 for 4B variants, FLUX NCL for 9B.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Performance Analysis&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FLUX.2 [klein] Elo vs Latency (top) and VRAM (bottom) across Text-to-Image, Image-to-Image Single Reference, and Multi-Reference tasks. FLUX.2 [klein] matches or exceeds Qwen's quality at a fraction of the latency and VRAM, and outperforms Z-Image while supporting both text-to-image generation and (multi-reference) image editing in a unified model. The base variants trade some speed for full customizability and fine-tuning, making them better suited for research and adaptation to specific use cases. Speed is measured on a GB200 in bf16.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Into the New&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FLUX.2 [klein] is more than a faster model. It's a step toward our vision of interactive visual intelligence. We believe the future belongs to creators and developers with AI that can see, create, and iterate in real-time. Systems that enable new categories of applications: real-time design tools, agentic visual reasoning, interactive content creation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Resources&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try it&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build with it&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learn more&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46653721</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 23:46:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Keifu – A TUI for navigating commit graphs with color and clarity</title><link>https://github.com/trasta298/keifu</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="323a5dcae4fcdf83"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;keifu (系譜, /keːɸɯ/) is a terminal UI tool that visualizes Git commit graphs. It shows a colored commit graph, commit details, and a summary of changed files, and lets you perform basic branch operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Readable commit graph — &lt;code&gt;git log --graph&lt;/code&gt;is hard to read; keifu renders a cleaner, color-coded graph&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fast branch switching — With AI-assisted coding, working on multiple branches in parallel has become common. keifu makes branch switching quick and visual&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Keep it simple — Only basic Git operations are supported; this is not a full-featured Git client&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Narrow terminal friendly — Works well in split panes and small windows&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No image protocol required — Works on any terminal with Unicode support&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unicode commit graph with per-branch colors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Commit list with branch labels, date, author, short hash, and message (some fields may be hidden on narrow terminals)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Commit detail panel with full message and changed file stats (+/-)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Git operations: checkout, create/delete branch, fetch&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Branch search with dropdown UI&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Run inside a Git repository (auto-discovery from current directory)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A terminal with Unicode line drawing support and color&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;command in PATH (required for fetch)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rust toolchain (for building from source)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cargo install keifu&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;mise use -g github:trasta298/keifu@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/trasta298/keifu &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd keifu &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cargo install --path .&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run inside a Git repository:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;keifu&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See docs/configuration.md for configuration options.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Key&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;j&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;↓&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Move down&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;↑&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Move up&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;]&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;Tab&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jump to next commit that has branch labels&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;[&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;Shift+Tab&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jump to previous commit that has branch labels&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;h&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;←&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Select left branch (same commit)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;l&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;→&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Select right branch (same commit)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+d&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Page down&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+u&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Page up&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;g&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Go to top&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;G&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;End&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Go to bottom&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jump to HEAD (current branch)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Key&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Checkout selected branch/commit&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Create branch at selected commit&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;d&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Delete branch (local, non-HEAD)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Fetch from origin&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Key&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Search branches (incremental fuzzy search)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;↑&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+k&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Select previous result&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;↓&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+j&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Select next result&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jump to selected branch&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;Esc&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;Backspace&lt;/code&gt; on empty&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Cancel search&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Key&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Refresh repository data&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Toggle help&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&lt;code&gt;q&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;Esc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Quit&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The TUI loads up to 500 commits across all branches.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Merge commits are diffed against the first parent; the initial commit is diffed against an empty tree.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changed files are capped at 50 and binary files are skipped.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If there are staged or unstaged changes (excluding untracked files), an "uncommitted changes" row appears at the top.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;When multiple branches point to the same commit, the label is collapsed to a single name with a &lt;code&gt;+N&lt;/code&gt;suffix (e.g.,&lt;code&gt;main +2&lt;/code&gt;). Use&lt;code&gt;h&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;l&lt;/code&gt;or&lt;code&gt;←&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;→&lt;/code&gt;to switch between them.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Checking out &lt;code&gt;origin/xxx&lt;/code&gt;creates or updates a local branch. Upstream is set only when creating a new branch. If the local branch exists but points to a different commit, it is force-updated to match the remote.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Remote branches are displayed, but delete operations only work with local branches.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fetch requires the &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt;remote to be configured.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46654085</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 00:32:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ask HN: Is it still worth pursuing a software startup?</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46654726</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="630085d923c726bc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes! All startups are created to solve a problem, regardless of the tools used. Apps are simply tools to solve human problems. Because humans will always have challenges to address, software will remain a vital tool. While AI makes writing software much easier. It's likely to lead to an explosion of new apps. Only those that fill a genuine need will survive. Your job is to identify these new problems and determine which apps to build.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simple apps are a thing of the past. If an LLM can generate an app in a few sittings, it isn't a saleable product. However, people will still pay for a fully engineered application that solves a complex problem that AI cannot easily replicate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regarding copies, there is always room for more than one solution to the same need. Your challenge is to figure out how to stand out. A fundamental business hurdle, that has existed since the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's an idea that always bear's fruit. We humans love to do things as easy as possible. Write something that saves energy, time and is simple then people will pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46654726</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 02:29:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Plunging US Birth Rate Leaves Too Many Colleges with Too Few Kids</title><link>https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2026-college-enrollment-cliff/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46654728</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 02:30:28 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>