<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 22:08:04 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>MapSCII – World map in terminal</title><link>https://github.com/rastapasta/mapscii</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ecc3b87ab9807886"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A node.js based Vector Tile to Braille and ASCII renderer for xterm-compatible terminals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ telnet mapscii.me&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're on Windows, use the open source telnet client PuTTY to connect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use your mouse to drag and zoom in and out!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Discover Point-of-Interests around any given location&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Highly customizable layer styling with Mapbox Styles support&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Connect to any public or private vector tile server&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Or just use the supplied and optimized OSM2VectorTiles based one&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Work offline and discover local VectorTile/MBTiles&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compatible with most Linux and OSX terminals&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Highly optimized algorithms for a smooth experience&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;100% pure JavaScript! 😎&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With a modern node installation available, just start it with&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npx mapscii
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you haven't already got Node.js &amp;gt;= version 10, then go get it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install -g mapscii
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're on OSX, or get an error about file permissions, you may need to do &lt;code&gt;sudo npm install -g mapscii&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In any of the supported Linux distros:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo snap install mapscii
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(This snap is maintained by @nathanhaines)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is pretty simple too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;mapscii
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Arrows up, down, left, right to scroll around&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Press a or z to zoom in and out&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Press c to switch to block character mode&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Press q to quit&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your terminal supports mouse events you can drag the map and use your scroll wheel to zoom in and out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;x256&lt;/code&gt;for converting RGB values to closest xterm-256 color code&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;term-mouse&lt;/code&gt;for mouse handling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;keypress&lt;/code&gt;for input handling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;string-width&lt;/code&gt;to determine visual string lengths&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;vector-tile&lt;/code&gt;for VectorTile parsing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;pbf&lt;/code&gt;for Protobuf decoding&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;mbtiles&lt;/code&gt;for MBTiles parsing&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;earcut&lt;/code&gt;for polygon triangulation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;rbush&lt;/code&gt;for 2D spatial indexing of geo and label data&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;bresenham&lt;/code&gt;for line point calculations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;simplify-js&lt;/code&gt;for polyline simplifications&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;node-fetch&lt;/code&gt;for HTTP requests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;env-paths&lt;/code&gt;to determine where to persist downloaded tiles&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;MapSCII&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;GeoJSON support via geojson-vt&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;CLI support&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
              &lt;item&gt;[-] startup parameters &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;TileSource&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Style&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;center position&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;zoom&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;demo mode?&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
            &lt;/list&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;[-] startup parameters &lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;mouse control&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
              &lt;item&gt;hover POIs/labels&lt;/item&gt;
              &lt;item&gt;hover maybe even polygons/-lines?&lt;/item&gt;
            &lt;/list&gt;
          &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Styler&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;respect zoom based style ranges&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Renderer&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;TileSource&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;implement single vector-tile handling&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;lukasmartinelli &amp;amp; manuelroth for all their work on OSM2VectorTiles (global vector tiles from OSM Planet)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;mourner for all his work on mindblowing GIS algorithms (like the used earcut, rbush, simplify-js, ..)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenStreetMap is open data, licensed under the Open Data Commons Open Database License (ODbL) by the OpenStreetMap Foundation (OSMF).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are free to copy, distribute, transmit and adapt our data, as long as you credit OpenStreetMap and its contributors. If you alter or build upon our data, you may distribute the result only under the same licence. The full legal code explains your rights and responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cartography in our map tiles, and our documentation, are licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 2.0 licence (CC BY-SA).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45293012</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 18:12:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PYREX vs. pyrex: What's the difference?</title><link>https://www.corning.com/worldwide/en/products/life-sciences/resources/stories/in-the-field/pyrex-vs-pyrex-whats-the-difference.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bc309c5290c9256b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;PYREX vs pyrex Construction Differences&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Corning used borosilicate to produce all Pyrex products. However, the company that purchased the cookware products switched to soda-lime glass, adopting the name pyrex (spelled with all lowercase letters).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Corning continued to make its lab tools with borosilicate, dubbing these products to be PYREX (spelled with all uppercase letters). Borosilicate glassware can sustain the large, sudden temperature changes that frequently occur in labs without shattering. These products are also less likely to react to chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Corning sold the consumer products or cookware business in 1998. The new owner, known as Borden at the time, later rebranding to World Kitchen in 2000, recognized that the cookware didn't need to be quite as strong, and — to make it accessible to the average customer — it needed to be more affordable. With this in mind, they switched the cookware to soda-lime glass, a less expensive component. Soda-lime glass, now called pyrex, isn't as resistant to thermal shock, but it is durable enough for everyday cooking.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Benefits of PYREX Labware&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;PYREX labware is designed to meet the rigorous demands of scientific experimentation. In fact, these scientific glassware products were integral in developing penicillin during World War II and the polio vaccine during the 1950s.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Corning laboratory glassware products have long been manufactured to meet the quality and reliability standards created by the American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM). Corning advanced its quality control for accuracy and precision further by testing its volumetric glassware in an ISO/IEC 17025 accredited laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;PYREX glass is well-suited for lab work because Corning uses borosilicate to produce beakers, flasks, test tubes, and other lab glassware. PYREX lab glassware made with borosilicate can withstand harsh, corrosive chemicals, handle extremely low and high temperatures, and it can survive rapid temperature changes without sustaining damage. PYREX beakers, Erlenmeyer flasks, and round- and flat-bottom boiling flasks can be repeatedly heated up to 230ºC. PYREX volumetric laboratory ware can be brought to 150ºC. Overall, PYREX laboratory glassware has a temperature shock limit — or allowable difference between the temperature of the glass and any medium in contact with the glass (air, liquid, or solid) — of 160ºC.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Always check laboratory glassware for any cracks, scratches, chips, or hazing — these damages can cause the product to break while in use. If properly cleaned and not damaged, PYREX laboratory glassware is reusable.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Unique Cleaning Procedures for PYREX Lab Glassware&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Despite being made of a strong, durable material, PYREX lab glassware requires specific care and maintenance. Ignoring the specific cleaning differences of PYREX labware can undermine the glassware's integrity and stability. If handled improperly, these products could shatter when exposed to high temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Always clean PYREX products with a non-abrasive glassware detergent either by hand or in a dishwasher. Do not exceed temperatures above 110°C during the cleaning process. Do not use abrasive brushes or scrubbing pads that can scratch the glass or its coating. In addition, limit exposure to any aldehydes, ketones, chlorinated solvents, or concentrated acids, because they can damage the glassware.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For over 100 years, Corning has been a trailblazer in creating innovative glassware products that can reliably and repeatedly meet users' needs. These products have accelerated scientific discoveries and enhanced human health.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45310995</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 06:37:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FLX1s phone is launched</title><link>https://furilabs.com/flx1s-is-launched/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="dfe351495ea32377"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is with great excitement that we can now release the FLX1s. Pre-sales are open and the phone is in production which is due to complete end of October 2025. Following that we can start shipping. Existing orders will be opted into the FLX1s or refunded.&lt;lb/&gt;To all our amazing FLX1 owners and those waiting patiently for their order, you have been the most wonderful and supportive community that we could ever have imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Thank-you from the FuriLabs Team.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45312326</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 11:20:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Images over DNS</title><link>https://dgl.cx/2025/09/images-over-dns</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="fec80dd7a0729493"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What's the limit of what can be in a TXT record?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some places say 255 bytes. They are wrong. Within a TXT record there are multiple character-strings (RFC 1035 section 3.3.14) and those are limited in length (because a single byte is used for their length), however there can be many of them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The actual limit is limited by the size of the DNS payload, which for UDP is these days around 1232 bytes. That is obviously quite low. However if we use TCP, which doesn't require anything special, other than the normal fallback to TCP that DNS does, then we can serve up to 64KB.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I set out to demonstrate exactly that, by using Google Public DNS's JSON API and then serving large TXT responses over TCP, from a custom server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This mostly just works, the main issue is not with the length, but with binary data, because JSON isn't really designed to handle binary data. Therefore there is some slightly custom JSON parsing. Using raw binary data in a TXT record avoids the overhead of Base64 or another encoding, meaning more data can be packed in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👉 See it in action. For more read the comments in image.html.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Non-browser&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is possible to query this via dig. Although turning it back into binary output is a bit tricky, as the presentation form of DNS responses is escaped for output.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can retrieve the data with dig and a little Perl to unescape and combine the character sequences:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ dig +short dog.log.battery.st TXT | perl -pe'chomp; s/" "//g; s/^"//; s/"$//; s/\\(\d{3})/chr $1/eg; s/\\([\\"])/$1/g' &amp;gt; dog.avif
$ sha256sum dog.avif
7058fbd20ef2af84d5efb0ae7d91f87ce7a912380636c468b32f2c759cbb9130  dog.avif
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(This is actually just a modified version of the Perl one liner from my Wikipedia over DNS from 2008, nothing changes.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because the web version uses Google's JSON resolver we know it doesn't have problems querying very large TXT records, however your local recursor may not support this. If it doesn't work you can add &lt;code&gt;@dns.google&lt;/code&gt; to the dig command
line to send the query to Google's Public DNS servers (or any other open
recursor, &lt;code&gt;@9.9.9.9&lt;/code&gt; seems to work too).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought it was a cute hack when I realised it was possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For those interested in security there is a consideration here, attackers have long tunnelled over DNS, but tunnelling large payloads to a browser is potentially something new. Because Google Public DNS has a certificate that includes &lt;code&gt;8.8.8.8&lt;/code&gt; and so on, HTTPS
traffic can go directly from a browser without a DNS lookup. This may be
unexpected in environments that use DNS filtering. This is something that will
become more common once Lets Encrypt fully rolls out IP address
certificates,
the difference here is piggybacking on an existing IP address certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This deliberately uses a low TTL (10 seconds) to avoid filling DNS recursor's caches with useless content. It would be possible to increase this and therefore get caching from the recursors, a bit like a free distributed CDN (although I suspect if someone actually did this they would adaptively limit TTLs, if something like that isn't already done).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Server side&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The server is a custom Go DNS server. To be honest it was written by ChatGPT because it's not that clever, the idea is what matters. (Although ChatGPT did get some details like truncation wrong so I fixed the code myself.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the code is here. AI was only used for the server component, this blog post and the client HTML code is my own work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45312515</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 11:50:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Vapor chamber tech keeps iPhone 17 Pro cool</title><link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/iphone-17-pro-vapor-chamber</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9533a64f32e316ed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On 9 September, Apple introduced its newest lineup, including the iPhone 17 series. Much of the attention went to a new ultrathin model and a bright orange color option (a shade not dissimilar to that of the IEEE Spectrum logo). The new smartphones will also ship with the latest operating system and its “Liquid Glass” software design—but the liquid in these phones goes beyond software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The iPhone 17 Pro and iPhone 17 Pro Max contain thin, hermetically sealed chambers with a drop of water inside that cycles between liquid and gas to help dissipate heat. Known as vapor chambers, the cooling system is becoming more common in smartphones built for sustained high performance. Some high-end Samsung Galaxy and Google Pixel models, among others, have introduced vapor-chamber cooling in the past few years. Now, Apple is following their lead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Cooling of smaller portables like phones must focus on spreading heat as widely as possible to the surface of the device, with particular attention to heat-generating components, like the chip,” says Kenneth Goodson, a professor of mechanical engineering at Stanford who specializes in heat transfer and energy conversion. To cool down those hot spots, the industry seems to be moving toward vapor chambers and other phase-change technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How vapor chambers keep phones cool&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The standard approach to cooling smartphones uses a solid, highly conductive plate made from a material like copper to spread heat. This approach relies on having a surface where heat can spread. Sometimes, fins are added to extend that surface, but this can lead to a thicker device. Most companies, however, are intent on making thinner and thinner phones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Phase-change technology—which has been used in laptops for decades, Goodson notes—achieves the same goal more effectively with fluid that boils and condenses to dissipate heat. These two-phase solutions include vapor chambers, like those used in the new iPhone, as well as narrow, fingerlike structures called heat pipes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Phones have limited volume to work with, and “performance per volume is critical,” says Victor Chiriac, the CEO and cofounder of Global Cooling Technology Group, based in Phoenix. Thin and wide vapor chambers have a high heat-removal capacity and offer an effective solution. The cycle between liquid and vapor is “a powerful mechanism for absorbing heat,” he says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple’s vapor chamber efficiently spreads heat across the phone’s body.Apple&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Apple’s version, a small amount of deionized water is sealed in the chamber. The water evaporates when near heat sources, then condenses back into a liquid when the heat dissipates into the phone’s surrounding aluminum body. Water is often used in vapor chambers, though sometimes other materials are mixed in to prevent it from freezing and cracking the seal, Chiriac says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Vapor-chamber manufacturing faces challenges&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Apple, Samsung, and others push the boundaries of how thin phones can get, manufacturing vapor chambers may become a challenge. While solid materials can easily be shaved down, these chambers need to have enough space for coolant to travel through channels. The chambers have to be perfectly sealed in order to work properly, and “the thinner you make it, the less space you have for that secret sauce to do its thing,” Chiriac says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It comes down to physics: “A big challenge in small devices like phones is that as you scale down the thickness of a vapor chamber, the fluid physics aggressively scale back their performance relative to copper and other solid heat conductors,” Goodson explains. (This is a problem that researchers, including his students, are working to address with new microstructures.) Plus, vapor chambers tend to be expensive to manufacture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still, Apple and other companies have decided to invest in this technology for their most powerful phone models. Goodson suspects part of that decision is to leverage the “wow” factor. But, he says, “with time this approach will likely become an industry standard.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All-Silicon “Fan-on-a-Chip” Keeps Thin Devices Cool ›&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Superslim Liquid Loop Will Keep Future Smartphones Cool ›&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gwendolyn Rak is an assistant editor at IEEE Spectrum covering consumer electronics and careers. She holds a master’s degree in science journalism from New York University and a bachelor’s degree in astrophysics and history from Swarthmore College.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45313415</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 13:50:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Living microbial cement supercapacitors with reactivatable energy storage</title><link>https://www.cell.com/cell-reports-physical-science/fulltext/S2666-3864(25)00409-6</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45313418</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 13:51:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cormac McCarthy's tips on how to write a science paper (2019) [pdf]</title><link>https://gwern.net/doc/science/2019-savage.pdf</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45313557</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 14:08:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Is Zig's new writer unsafe?</title><link>https://www.openmymind.net/Is-Zigs-New-Io-Unsafe/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a4c2da7bf824bab0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Is Zig's New Writer Unsafe?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sep 20, 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we wanted to write a function that takes one of Zig's new &lt;code&gt;*std.Io.Reader&lt;/code&gt; and write it to stdout, we might start with something like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;fn output(r: *std.Io.Reader) !void {
    const stdout = std.fs.File.stdout();
    var buffer: [???]u8 = undefined;
    var writer = stdout.writer(&amp;amp;buffer);
    _ = try r.stream(&amp;amp;writer.interface, .unlimited);
    try writer.interface.flush();
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what should the size of &lt;code&gt;buffer&lt;/code&gt; be? If this was a one-and-done, maybe we'd leave it empty or put some seemingly sensible default, like 1K or 4K. If it was a mission critical piece of code, maybe we'd benchmark it or make it platform dependent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But unless I'm missing something, whatever size we use, this function's behavior is undefined. You see, the issue is that readers can require a specific buffer sizes on a writer (and writers can require a specific buffer size on a reader). For example, this code, with a small buffer of 64, fails an assertion in debug mode, and falls into an endless loop in release mode:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;const std = @import("std");

pub fn main() !void {
    var fixed = std.Io.Reader.fixed(&amp;amp;.{
        40, 181, 47, 253, 36, 110, 149, 0, 0, 88, 111, 118, 101, 114, 32, 57,
        48, 48, 48, 33, 10, 1, 0, 192, 105, 241, 2, 170, 69, 248, 150
    });

    var decompressor = std.compress.zstd.Decompress.init(&amp;amp;fixed, &amp;amp;.{}, .{});
    try output(&amp;amp;decompressor.reader);
}

fn output(r: *std.Io.Reader) !void {
    const stdout = std.fs.File.stdout();
    var buffer: [64]u8 = undefined;
    var writer = stdout.writer(&amp;amp;buffer);
    _ = try r.stream(&amp;amp;writer.interface, .unlimited);
    try writer.interface.flush();
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some might argue that this is a documentation challenge. It's true that the documentation for &lt;code&gt;zstd.Decompress&lt;/code&gt; mentions what a &lt;code&gt;Writer&lt;/code&gt;'s buffer must be. But this is not a documentation problem. There are legitimate scenarios where the nature of a &lt;code&gt;Reader&lt;/code&gt; is unknown (or, at least, difficult to figure out). A type of a reader could be conditional, say based on an HTTP response header. A library developer might take a &lt;code&gt;Reader&lt;/code&gt; as an input and present their own &lt;code&gt;Reader&lt;/code&gt; as an output - what buffer requirement should they document?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Worse is that the failure can be conditional on the input. For example, if we change our source to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;var fixed = std.Io.Reader.fixed(&amp;amp;.{
    40, 181, 47, 253, 36, 11, 89, 0, 0, 111, 118, 101, 114, 32, 57,
    48, 48, 48, 33, 10, 112, 149, 178, 212,
});&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everything works, making this misconfiguration particularly hard to catch early.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To me this seems almost impossible - like, I must be doing something wrong. And if I am, I'm sorry. But, if I'm not, this is a problem right?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45313597</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 14:12:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Systemd can be a cause of restrictions on daemons</title><link>https://utcc.utoronto.ca/~cks/space/blog/linux/SystemdCanBeRestrictionCause</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f732f94725c702d9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;These days, systemd can be a cause of restrictions on daemons&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the traditional rites of passage for Linux system administrators is having a daemon not work in the normal system configuration (eg, when you boot the system) but work when you manually run it as root. The classical cause of this on Unix was that $PATH wasn't fully set in the environment the daemon was running in but was in your root shell. On Linux, another traditional cause of this sort of thing has been SELinux and a more modern source (on Ubuntu) has sometimes been AppArmor. All of these create hard to see differences between your root shell (where the daemon works when run by hand) and the normal system environment (where the daemon doesn't work). These days, we can add another cause, an increasingly common one, and that is systemd service unit restrictions, many of which are covered in systemd.exec.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(One pernicious aspect of systemd as a cause of these restrictions is that they can appear in new releases of the same distribution. If a daemon has been running happily in an older release and now has surprise issues in a new Ubuntu LTS, I don't always remember to look at its .service file.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of systemd's protective directives simply cause failures to do things, like access user home directories if ProtectHome= is set to something appropriate. Hopefully your daemon complains loudly here, reporting mysterious 'permission denied' or 'file not found' errors. Some systemd settings can have additional, confusing effects, like PrivateTmp=. A standard thing I do when troubleshooting a chain of programs executing programs executing programs is to shim in diagnostics that dump information to /tmp, but with PrivateTmp= on, my debugging dump files are mysteriously not there in the system-wide /tmp.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(On the other hand, a daemon may not complain about missing files if it's expected that the files aren't always there. A mailer usually can't really tell the difference between 'no one has .forward files' and 'I'm mysteriously not able to see people's home directories to find .forward files in them'.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes you don't get explicit errors, just mysterious failures to do some things. For example, you might set IP address access restrictions with the intention of blocking inbound connections but wind up also blocking DNS queries (and this will also depend on whether or not you use systemd-resolved). The good news is that you're mostly not going to find standard systemd .service files for normal daemons shipped by your Linux distribution with IP address restrictions. The bad news is that at some point .service files may start showing up that impose IP address restrictions with the assumption that DNS resolution is being done via systemd-resolved as opposed to direct DNS queries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(I expect some Linux distributions to resist this, for example Debian, but others may declare that using systemd-resolved is now mandatory in order to simplify things and let them harden service configurations.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right now, you can usually test if this is the problem by creating a version of the daemon's .service file with any systemd restrictions stripped out of it and then seeing if using that version makes life happy. In the future it's possible that some daemons will assume and require some systemd restrictions (for instance, assuming that they have a /tmp all of their own), making things harder to test.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45314157</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 15:26:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Are touchscreens in cars dangerous?</title><link>https://www.economist.com/science-and-technology/2025/09/19/are-touchscreens-in-cars-dangerous</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45314432</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 15:57:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ultrasonic Chef's Knife</title><link>https://seattleultrasonics.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="c4ae7ddc24d05992"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The World's First&lt;/head&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;Ultrasonic Chef's Knife&lt;lb/&gt;For Home Cooks&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Switch on the ultrasonics and feel the blade glide effortlessly through food. Clean cuts, minimal force, less sticking.&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regular price $399.00 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Regular price &lt;del class="price-item price-item--regular" data-product-id="7320581177440" rend="overstrike"&gt; $399.00 &lt;/del&gt; Sale price $399.00 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-Order now for estimated shipping by January, 2026 (Batch 1). Cancel anytime before your order ships. What is a Pre-Order?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regular price $499.00 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Regular price &lt;del class="price-item price-item--regular" data-product-id="7497201942624" rend="overstrike"&gt; $548.00 &lt;/del&gt; Sale price $499.00 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-Order now for estimated shipping by January 2026 (Batch 1). Cancel anytime before your order ships. What is a Pre-Order?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45314592</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 16:12:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Designing NotebookLM</title><link>https://jasonspielman.com/notebooklm</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf50da1b9d312eaa"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User Journey â¢ Annotated Overview&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Home&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design Lead&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UX + Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2024&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I led design for NotebookLM, shaping the productâs core user experience, brand identity, and visual system from experiment to launch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This remains one of my proudest projects, and Iâm incredibly grateful for the opportunity to design something entirely new from the ground up. It was a chance to explore fresh paradigms, invent new patterns, and bring a product to life that hadnât existed before. None of it wouldâve been possible without the tight-knit, cross-functional team I was fortunate to collaborate with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Podcast â¢ Sequoia&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raiza and I discuss the journey building NotebookLM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NotebookLM â¢ Winner!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recognized as one of TIMEâs Best Inventions of 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visual Assets&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UI Evolution&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early Prototype&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what the UI looked like when I first joined the early project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notes driven UI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exploratory chat UI introduced as an overlay on the note canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3-Panel Structure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synthesizes learnings into a scalable and adaptive layout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the core problems we set out to solve with NotebookLM was âtab overwhelmâ the scattered, fractured experience of jumping between tools while trying to synthesize ideas. We wanted to create a space where every part of the creation journey could happen in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â Inputs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outputs â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Citations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Multiple entry points&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This visual shows how the core building blocks came together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The structure you see now may seem obvious but it took After what felt like 1000 iterations to get there. Trying to put these blocks together in a way that allowed for a clear mental model and digstible UI. These early sketches are from a plane. I ran out of paper and ultimately found the final solution when drawing on a napkin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mental model of NotebookLM was built around the creation journey: starting with inputs, moving through conversation, and ending with outputs. Users bring in their sources (documents, notes, references), then interact with them through chat by asking questions, clarifying, and synthesizing before transforming those insights into structured outputs like notes, study guides, and Audio Overviews.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By grounding the design in this linear but flexible flow (Inputs â Chat â Outputs) we gave users a clear sense of place within the product while keeping the complexity of new AI interactions digestible and intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs rare to find a product that brings reading, writing, and creation together in a truly integrated way largely because juggling all three can be overwhelming. But with AI reducing friction, the opportunity emerged to design a space where every part of the creative process could coexist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make that possible, I designed a responsive panel system that adapts to the userâs needs, scaling fluidly while preserving quick access to key elements like sources and notes, even at the smallest sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default layout, offering a balanced view of sources, chat, and notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Optimized for referencing sources and generating responses with citations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A popular request, designed for users focused on drafting and iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ideal for composing while keeping source material in view.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To optimize spatial utility, I created a set of responsive panels that scale based on user needs, retaining essential icons for sources and notes even at minimal widths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scalability was a core principle. While the content within these panels can shift and evolve, the underlying system is built to support growth, accommodating new tools, modes, and workflows without breaking the structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Studio Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See how the team has continued to scale this system with the newest launch of flashcards, quizzes, professional reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hereâs what that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User Journey â¢ Annotated Overview&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read the full story&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Defining the brand identity was a fast-paced effort, made possible by close collaboration with Google Labs and the central brand team. Shoutout Feel Hwang, Nick Mcginnis, Jennifer Leartanasan and team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Home&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design Lead&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UX + Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2024&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I led design for NotebookLM, shaping the productâs core user experience, brand identity, and visual system from experiment to launch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This remains one of my proudest projects, and Iâm incredibly grateful for the opportunity to design something entirely new from the ground up. It was a chance to explore fresh paradigms, invent new patterns, and bring a product to life that hadnât existed before. None of it wouldâve been possible without the tight-knit, cross-functional team I was fortunate to collaborate with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brand Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visual Assets&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Takeaways&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UI Evolution&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early Prototype&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what the UI looked like when I first joined the early project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notes driven UI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exploratory chat UI introduced as an overlay on the note canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3-Panel Structure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synthesizes learnings into a scalable and adaptive layout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the core problems we set out to solve with NotebookLM was âtab overwhelmâ the scattered, fractured experience of jumping between tools while trying to synthesize ideas. We wanted to create a space where every part of the creation journey could happen in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â Inputs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outputs â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Citations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Multiple entry points&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This visual shows how the core building blocks came together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The structure you see now may seem obvious but it took After what felt like 1000 iterations to get there. Trying to put these blocks together in a way that allowed for a clear mental model and digstible UI. These early sketches are from a plane. I ran out of paper and ultimately found the final solution when drawing on a napkin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mental model of NotebookLM was built around the creation journey: starting with inputs, moving through conversation, and ending with outputs. Users bring in their sources (documents, notes, references), then interact with them through chat by asking questions, clarifying, and synthesizing before transforming those insights into structured outputs like notes, study guides, and Audio Overviews.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By grounding the design in this linear but flexible flow (Inputs â Chat â Outputs) we gave users a clear sense of place within the product while keeping the complexity of new AI interactions digestible and intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs rare to find a product that brings reading, writing, and creation together in a truly integrated way largely because juggling all three can be overwhelming. But with AI reducing friction, the opportunity emerged to design a space where every part of the creative process could coexist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make that possible, I designed a responsive panel system that adapts to the userâs needs, scaling fluidly while preserving quick access to key elements like sources and notes, even at the smallest sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default layout, offering a balanced view of sources, chat, and notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading + Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Optimized for referencing sources and generating responses with citations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To optimize spatial utility, I created a set of responsive panels that scale based on user needs, retaining essential icons for sources and notes even at minimal widths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scalability was a core principle. While the content within these panels can shift and evolve, the underlying system is built to support growth, accommodating new tools, modes, and workflows without breaking the structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Studio Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See how the team has continued to scale this system with the newest launch of flashcards, quizzes, professional reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hereâs what that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User Journey â¢ Annotated Overview&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read the full story&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Defining the brand identity was a fast-paced effort, made possible by close collaboration with Google Labs and the central brand team. Shoutout Feel Hwang, Nick Mcginnis, Jennifer Leartanasan and team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wanda Wingleton&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Home&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design Lead&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UX + Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2024&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I led design for NotebookLM, shaping the productâs core user experience, brand identity, and visual system from experiment to launch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This remains one of my proudest projects, and Iâm incredibly grateful for the opportunity to design something entirely new from the ground up. It was a chance to explore fresh paradigms, invent new patterns, and bring a product to life that hadnât existed before. None of it wouldâve been possible without the tight-knit, cross-functional team I was fortunate to collaborate with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Podcast â¢ Seqouia Training Data&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Raiza and I discuss the journey building NotebookLM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NotebookLM â¢ Winner!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recognized as one of TIMEâs Best Inventions of 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brand Identity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Visual Assets&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Takeaways&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design Evolution&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early Prototype&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what the UI looked like when I first joined the early project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notes driven UI&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exploratory chat UI introduced as an overlay on the note canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3-Panel Structure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Synthesizes learnings into a scalable and adaptive layout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the core problems we set out to solve with NotebookLM was âtab overwhelmâ the scattered, fractured experience of jumping between tools while trying to synthesize ideas. We wanted to create a space where every part of the creation journey could happen in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â Inputs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outputs â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Citations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¢ Multiple entry points&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This visual shows how the core building blocks came together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The structure you see now may look obvious but it took what felt like a thousand iterations to get there. I was trying to arrange these blocks in a way that supported a clear mental model and a UI that felt intuitive and digestible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These sketches were done on a plane. I ran out of paper and ended up sketching the final solution across a few napkins.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mental model of NotebookLM was built around the creation journey: starting with inputs, moving through conversation, and ending with outputs. Users bring in their sources (documents, notes, references), then interact with them through chat by asking questions, clarifying, and synthesizing before transforming those insights into structured outputs like notes, study guides, and Audio Overviews.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By grounding the design in this linear but flexible flow (Inputs â Chat â Outputs) we gave users a clear sense of place within the product while keeping the complexity of new AI interactions digestible and intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Itâs rare to find a product that brings reading, writing, and creation together in a truly integrated way largely because juggling all three can be overwhelming. But with AI reducing friction, the opportunity emerged to design a space where every part of the creative process could coexist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make that possible, I designed a responsive panel system that adapts to the userâs needs, scaling fluidly while preserving quick access to key elements like sources and notes, even at the smallest sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Standard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The default layout, offering a balanced view of sources, chat, and notes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading + Chat&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Optimized for referencing sources and generating responses with citations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat + Writing&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A popular request, designed for users focused on drafting and iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reading + Writing&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ideal for composing while keeping source material in view.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To optimize spatial utility, I created a set of responsive panels that scale based on user needs, retaining essential icons for sources and notes even at minimal widths.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scalability was a core principle. While the content within these panels can shift and evolve, the underlying system is built to support growth, accommodating new tools, modes, and workflows without breaking the structure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Studio Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See how the team has continued to scale this system with the newest launch of flashcards, quizzes, professional reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chat Panel&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hereâs what that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read the full story&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Defining the brand identity was a fast-paced effort, made possible by close collaboration with Google Labs and the central brand team. Shoutout Feel Hwang, Nick Mcginnis, Jennifer Leartanasan and team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jason Spielman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Linkedin â&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45315312</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 17:25:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TV Time Machine: A Raspberry Pi That Plays Random 90s TV</title><link>https://quarters.captaintouch.com/blog/posts/2025-09-20-tv-time-machine-a-raspberry-pi-that-plays-random-90s-tv.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="aac6b06d71c2c067"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Growing up in the 90s, television was a different experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You turned on the TV, and whatever was playing at that moment would become your entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nowadays you yourself are in control, you choose what you want to see, whenever you want.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strangely enough, I miss that feeling of having something selected for me, something I cannot influence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's just my nostalgic musings, but why not create an afternoon project out of it and actually find out if there's something more to this nostalgic feeling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Take a Raspberry Pi (I used a cheap tiny Raspberry Pi 3A+)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Fill the SD card with all your favorite shows from your childhood&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Add a script that starts playing those shows in a random order at startup&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The idea is to have it plugged into a television or monitor and I can just turn it on whenever I feel like watching some random 90's tv.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's what's currently playing on my device:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Star Trek: The Next Generation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- StarGate SG-1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Saved by the Bell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Friends&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Dinosaurs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Family Matters&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- The Simpsons&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- X-Files&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Home Improvement&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Sliders&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- 3rd Rock from the Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- The Wonder Years&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Married with Children&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- ALF&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- MacGyver&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Xena: Warrior Princess&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is just a list to get started with, if you have any more 90's tips, let me know! (Mastodon details at the bottom)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This really only took an afternoon, it's that simple.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take an SD card and install Raspberry Pi OS Lite (64-bit) on it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can use Raspberry Pi's imaging software, make sure to preconfigure it so it connects to the wifi and that you have your authentication details set (I made a user account called 'retro')&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once the image is made, boot it up with your raspberry pi and ensure that you can log in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When logged in, create a video folder to store your files&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;mkdir video&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then take the SD card, plug it back into your computer (you might need a linux pc for this) and dump all your videos into a newly created 'video' folder in the root of your home directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the above is too much of a hassle for you, you can just as well just keep these videos on an attached USB stick, just make sure to update the path in the script.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install the software needed to play the videos:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo apt-get update sudo apt-get install vlc pulseaudio&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Save the following script in the root of your home directory as startVideo.sh (nano startVideo.sh):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;#!/bin/bash VIDEO_DIR=&amp;amp;quot/home/retro/video&amp;amp;quot pulseaudio --start pactl set-default-sink 1 mapfile -t video_files &amp;amp;lt &amp;amp;lt(find &amp;amp;quot$VIDEO_DIR&amp;amp;quot -type f | shuf) for video in &amp;amp;quot${video_files[@]}" do cvlc --fullscreen --play-and-exit &amp;amp;quot$video&amp;amp;quot done&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This just makes a list of all your videos, shuffles them and feeds them to VLC for playing. (use cvlc instead of vlc when you don't need an interface)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pactl command was needed in my case to ensure the audio also outputs over hdmi, if you are using the headphone jack, just leave out this line, note that this might differ on other Raspberry Pi devices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make sure to adjust the VIDEO_DIR path to wherever you are storing the videos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To ensure it's always playing, we'll make a systemd service so it auto starts playing at startup:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Save the following file as /etc/systemd/system/videoplayer.service (you can use sudo nano followed by the file location)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;[Unit] Description=Video Player Service After=multi-user.target [Service] User=retro Group=retro ExecStart=/home/retro/startVideo.sh Restart=always [Install] WantedBy=multi-user.target&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And then register it as a service:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo systemctl enable videoplayer&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reboot and cross your fingers!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right now I just have this plugged into a spare monitor (that has speakers built-in), but I'm looking for a small CRT to put in the corner of my office.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That would involve finding a HDMI to SCART, HDMI to s-video or similar convertor though.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TV, Nostalgia, HomeLab&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can get in touch through Mastodon:&lt;/p&gt;@rxpz@social.linux.pizza&lt;p&gt;TV Time Machine: A Raspberry Pi That Plays Random 90s TV was published on 2025-09-20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45316244</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 18:59:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bringing restartable sequences out of the niche</title><link>https://lwn.net/Articles/1033955/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f41a91ffbea2bfbc"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bringing restartable sequences out of the niche&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;LWN.net needs you!The restartable sequences feature, which was added to the 4.18 kernel in 2018, exists to enable better performance in certain types of threaded applications. While there are users for restartable sequences, they tend to be relatively specialized code; this is not a tool that most application developers reach for. Over time, though, the use of restartable sequences has grown, and it looks to grow further as the feature is tied to new capabilities provided by the kernel. As restartable sequences become less of a niche feature, though, some problems have turned up; fixing one of them may involve an ABI change visible in user space.&lt;p&gt;Without subscribers, LWN would simply not exist. Please consider signing up for a subscription and helping to keep LWN publishing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;A restartable sequences overview&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the number of CPUs in a system grows, so does the desire to write and run highly parallel programs. In user space, as well as in the kernel, concurrent code using locks eventually runs into scalability problems, leading to an interest in the use of lockless algorithms instead. The kernel has a distinct advantage when it comes to lockless concurrent access, though, in that code running in kernel space can prevent interruptions from interrupts, preemption, or migration to another CPU during critical sections; user space has no such guarantees. So any user-space lockless algorithm must work correctly in an environment where code execution can be interrupted at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Restartable sequences are one solution to this problem. To use this feature, an application must designate a critical section that does some work, culminating in a single atomic instruction that commits whatever change is being made. One of the earliest uses of restartable sequences was a memory allocator that would, within its critical section, identify an object to allocate from a per-CPU list, then remove it from that list with an atomic compare-and-exchange operation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It would obviously be problematic if this critical section were to be interrupted between the identification of the object to allocate and the final step committing the change. To work around this problem, the application informs the kernel of the critical section by filling a structure (struct rseq_cs) describing the address range of the instructions within that section, along with a special abort address. If the kernel interrupts the execution of the relevant thread, to preempt it, move it to another CPU, or to deliver a signal, it will, on return to user space check for the existence of this structure. If the current instruction pointer lies within the critical section, the kernel will cause execution to jump to the abort address. The thread can then clean up after its aborted attempt and restart the operation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The hope, of course, is that most runs through the critical section will complete without interruption, accomplishing their job in about the fastest way possible. The extra overhead of dealing with aborts only enters the picture in cases where the critical section is interrupted for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using restartable sequences requires setting up a shared memory area using the rseq() system call. The actual critical section almost certainly must be written in assembly. Until relatively recently, there was no support for restartable sequences in the GNU C Library (glibc), though that has been changing. Given the effort that is required to use this feature properly, and given that it is a Linux-only feature, it is not surprising that relatively few application developers have made use of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Not so niche anymore&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The shared-memory area set up by rseq() allows a thread to tell the kernel when it is executing in a critical section, but the communication through that area goes both ways. Whenever the kernel runs a thread, it will update this area to reflect which CPU and NUMA node the thread ended up on. That information is used by glibc to accelerate functions like sched_getcpu(), which can obtain the needed information directly without calling into the kernel. Other uses of restartable sequences within glibc are under consideration; Mathieu Desnoyers (the creator of this feature) has been advocating for increased use of it within glibc to improve scalability for some time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently, there has been interest in another feature intended to help user space write efficient critical sections: time-slice extension. The idea here is that a thread running in a critical section (perhaps holding a lock) could indicate that fact to the kernel as a way of politely asking to not be preempted, even if its time slice runs out. The kernel could, if it is in a good mood, respond by giving the thread a little bit more time to finish its work and release the lock, so that other threads can proceed. It makes obvious sense to tie a feature like this to restartable sequences, so the time-slice-extension patch set added the "please can I run a little longer" bit to the shared area.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time-slice extension is a feature that affects the core CPU scheduler, and it is likely to see wider use, so it is not surprising that it has brought more attention to restartable sequences. Thomas Gleixner dug into the patches and, not entirely liking what he saw, put together a proposal for an improved interface for time-slice extension. His changes are likely to be the way this work proceeds in the future, and may merit an article on its own, but Gleixner also found a few things to improve in the restartable-sequences code as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The trouble with restartable sequences&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; His observations in this area led to the posting of a separate patch set aimed at addressing the problems he found with restartable sequences. The end result is significantly improved performance, which is a good thing given that the performance cost of restartable sequences has been starting to attract attention. Jens Axboe, for example, responded to the series saying: "&lt;quote&gt;I'd see rseq at 2-3% of overall CPU time last I tested&lt;/quote&gt;". Kernel developers will work long and hard to eliminate a performance hit much smaller than that. A couple of the things that Gleixner fixed are good examples of how the combination of history and oversights can slow things down. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are a number of ways in which a user-space thread might lose access to the CPU. The restartable-sequences code in current kernels maintains a field, rseq_event_mask, in each thread's task_struct structure to track those ways; there are separate bits for preemption, the delivery of a signal, and migration to a different CPU. So, for example, if the kernel ends up delivering a signal to a task, it will set the RSEQ_EVENT_SIGNAL bit in rseq_event_mask. When the time comes to return to user space after whatever has happened, rseq_need_restart() will be called to see if a critical section was interrupted; in that case, rseq_event_mask will be consulted to see whether the critical section should be continued, or whether the thread should instead be diverted to the abort address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gleixner noticed a couple of interesting problems with this code. One is that the kernel is constantly setting the bits in rseq_event_mask, but those bits are only cleared in rseq_need_restart(), and only when the thread happens to be executing within a critical section at the time. Otherwise those bits just pile up there. That is likely to result in a spurious restart the next time an interrupt occurs while the thread is executing within a critical section, taking away some of the performance advantage that the restartable sequences feature was added to provide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps more tellingly, though, those bits exist to allow a thread to specify when its critical section should be aborted. Given the nature of any given section, some sorts of events do not risk breaking the algorithm; a thread might be able to handle a signal without risking concurrent access to data needed by its critical sections, for example. But that feature was deprecated for the 6.0 release in 2022; it added complexity without bringing a lot of value. That deprecation was of a relatively severe variety; any process trying to use that feature would be immediately killed with a SIGSEGV signal. So the chances are pretty good that there are no actual users of the feature in the wild now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gleixner replaced all of that machinery with a single "an event happened" boolean value. This elimination also allowed the removal of some accesses to user-space memory, which speeds things up. User-space access from the kernel is never entirely cheap, and the need for Spectre mitigations has made it even slower. As a separate optimization, the series changes the remaining user-space access to the masked user-space-access primitives (added in 6.12) that carry a lower mitigation cost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two ways that a thread running in user space can end up switching to kernel mode: an interrupt happens, or the thread makes a system call. All of the cases that restartable sequences are meant to handle will be the result of an interrupt of some type or another. Threads in critical sections are not supposed to make system calls at all. When running on a kernel built with the DEBUG_RSEQ configuration option, making a system call while in a critical section will result in the immediate termination of the offending process — a gentle hint that the restartable sequences feature is not being used correctly. Without that option (as will be the case in production systems), though, the kernel will handle a system-call return in the same way as an interrupt return: if the thread is running in a critical section and an event has occurred, control will be redirected to the abort handler.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gleixner's work separates the handling of the interrupt and system-call case, since the time-slice-extension feature will only apply for the former. As an optimization, he removed the restartable-sequences handling for system-call returns; the relevant patch notes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;This changes the current behaviour, which just blindly fixes up the critical section unconditionally in the syscall case. But that's a user space problem when it invokes a syscall from within a critical section and expects it to work. That code was clearly never tested on a debug kernel and user space can keep the pieces.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If there are users that behave in this way, and the code has worked so far, they may be in for an unpleasant surprise once this change goes in. That would likely become the cause of an interesting conversation; "user space was always broken" is not normally considered an acceptable argument for causing a working program to break. There is a good chance that this change will have to be reverted if trouble appears. Given the relatively limited use of restartable sequences so far, though, there is reason to hope that no such user exists.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; It may be a little while until we find out, anyway. This work will need review, including, presumably, a look at how it interacts with the time-slice extension work. For extra fun, Gleixner has let it be known that he has found more things to fix, so further patches will be forthcoming. But, at their core, the current changes appear to make sense, addressing problems that have managed to sneak into the code over the years. Almost any body of code can benefit from restarted development involving a fresh set of eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Index entries for this article&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kernel&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Restartable sequences&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kernel&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Scheduler/Time-slice extension&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Posted Aug 21, 2025 16:43 UTC (Thu) by davecb (subscriber, #1574) [Link] (4 responses) Ask them how to support an abi change by versioning the interface that changed, using linker symbols. High-level (and oversimplified!) view in https://leaflessca.wordpress.com/2018/05/31/an-alternativ..., and the real details in David J Brown's proposal, https://www.usenix.org/legacy/publications/library/procee... Posted Aug 22, 2025 0:17 UTC (Fri) by quotemstr (subscriber, #45331) [Link] (3 responses) What happens if you call dlsym? What happens if you try to build a program on a new system targeting an old one and pick up the new symbol without realizing it? (glibc refuses to provide a preprocessor macro for targeting older systems.) Much better to give new functions new names. Don't add a symbol version my_api@2. Just define a my_api2(). It looks uglier in the short term, sure, but saves everyone trouble in the end. Posted Aug 22, 2025 0:29 UTC (Fri) by intelfx (subscriber, #130118) [Link] (2 responses) Perhaps this is a glibc problem rather than a symbol versioning problem? Posted Aug 22, 2025 0:43 UTC (Fri) by quotemstr (subscriber, #45331) [Link] (1 responses) How do you solve the problem of shipping bugfixes that might break older versions e.g. the infamous memcpy direction problem? Use what macOS, Windows, and Android do: compatibility versions embedded in the binary manifest. Posted Aug 23, 2025 1:42 UTC (Sat) by comex (subscriber, #71521) [Link] There's a compiler flag to specify the minimum OS version you need to run on. Meanwhile, every declaration in every system header is marked with a minimum OS version, so you get an error if you accidentally use a newer function (this can be disabled for functionality you want to use conditionally). In more subtle cases, header files can manually check the target version with #if and change their behavior, though this is rarely done. The goal is that you can always use the latest SDK, even if you are targeting an old OS version (though there is a limit to how far back you can go). I think glibc would be well-served if it adopted a similar scheme. Posted Aug 22, 2025 3:02 UTC (Fri) by PengZheng (subscriber, #108006) [Link] I would once again propose the buggy rwlock([1]), which is a complicated mess, as a rewrite candidate. Posted Aug 23, 2025 18:42 UTC (Sat) by corbet (editor, #1) [Link] Posted Aug 24, 2025 17:57 UTC (Sun) by ssmith32 (subscriber, #72404) [Link] (2 responses) "the kernel will handle a system-call return in the same way as an interrupt return: if the thread is running in a critical section and an event has occurred, control will be redirected to the abort handler. " And this: " If the current instruction pointer lies within the critical section, the kernel will cause execution to jump to the abort address. The thread can then clean up after its aborted attempt and restart the operation. " What's "if an event occurred"? I read this as saying invoking a system call in a critical section results in the abort handler being called.. which restart the sequence, which would seem to be a bit (infinite) loopy. But the rest of the article seems to imply the current (pre-tglx) code inadvertently works on non-debug kernels. So I missed something, probably obvious.. but I can't sort out what. Posted Aug 24, 2025 18:02 UTC (Sun) by ssmith32 (subscriber, #72404) [Link] (1 responses) I assume the answer is "possibly", in which case the code loops infinitely. But wondering if I'm misunderstanding. Posted Aug 24, 2025 18:42 UTC (Sun) by corbet (editor, #1) [Link] &lt;head&gt;If this threatens a userspace (meaning glibc in particular) change ...&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;If this threatens a userspace (meaning glibc in particular) change ...&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;If this threatens a userspace (meaning glibc in particular) change ...&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;If this threatens a userspace (meaning glibc in particular) change ...&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;If this threatens a userspace (meaning glibc in particular) change ...&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;Please Rewrite Glibc RWlock or Revert to Drepper's Good Old Implementation.&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head/&gt; For the curious: Thomas Gleixner has posted a followup series fixing another set of problems and offering some strong commentary on the situation as a whole. &lt;head&gt;Followup series&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;I missed something about abort&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head&gt;I missed something about abort&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head/&gt; Yes, a system call can result in those things. As an extreme example, think of a read() call that has to wait for data to be brought in from disk; that will result in the calling thread losing access to the CPU indefinitely. But almost any system call can result in preemption and/or migration of the calling thread. &lt;head&gt;I missed something about abort&lt;/head&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45316266</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 19:01:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A revolution in English bell ringing</title><link>https://harpers.org/archive/2025/10/a-change-of-tune-veronique-greenwood-bell-ringing/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f108bd6b5cc6fc83"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;October 2025 Issue [Annotation] A Change of Tune Download PDF Adjust Share A revolution in English bell ringing by Veronique Greenwood, Veronique Greenwood is a writer and bell ringer who lives in England. Tags Bell ringing England Adjust Share&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45316744</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 19:51:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Philips announces digital pathology scanner with native DICOM JPEG XL output</title><link>https://www.philips.com/a-w/about/news/archive/standard/news/articles/2025/philips-announces-digital-pathology-scanner-with-native-configurable-dicom-jpeg-and-jpeg-xl-output-in-world-first.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="1758be5a88b6ac93"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sep 08, 2025 | 2 minute read&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Pathology plays a crucial role in the diagnosis of a variety of diseases, particularly cancer, through examination of patient tissue samples. With an estimated 70% of important medical decisions involving laboratory or pathology tests [2], the availability of digitally stored pathology images is especially important as it has a significant impact on patient care. The digital transformation of pathology also means there is a growing need for scalable storage to meet new data volumes and computing resources, which also allows full AI adoption in clinical and research environments. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; DICOM (Digital Imaging and Communications in Medicine) is the international standard for medical images and related patient information. Because digital pathology is a relatively new imaging modality compared to radiology and others, there was no established DICOM standard in place. As a result, vendors created their own proprietary formats.&lt;lb/&gt; Today, Philips announced that it is expanding its SG300 and SG60 scanner offering with the Pathology Scanner SGi with configurable DICOM JPEG and DICOM JPEG XL output. As a result, it is the first in the world to offer native DICOM JPEG XL output. DICOM JPEG XL output files are up to 50% smaller while still providing the same high image quality [3], enabling pathology labs to store, manage, and analyze growing volumes of digital pathology data and enable more productive workflows in the cloud and on premise.&lt;lb/&gt; “The adoption of DICOM in pathology marks an important shift toward achieving scalable, interoperable imaging workflows, said Imogen Fitt, Principal Analyst at Signify Research. “As pathology labs face mounting data volumes and storage demands, the move to standardized formats helps reduce infrastructure costs and enables integration with a wider range of AI tools. Philips’ support for DICOM JPEG and DICOM JPEG XL as a native output from its scanners illustrates how vendors are aligning with these trends, intending to support capabilities such as centralized archiving, cross-modality diagnostics, and remote collaboration for customers.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Sources [1] Pathology Scanner SGi is under development and is not CE marked and is not yet available for sale. [2] Report of the Second Phase of the Review of NHS Pathology Services in England, Lord Carter of Coles (2008). Results are specific to the institution where they were obtained and may not reflect the results achievable at other institutions. [3] Based on preliminary test data on diverse slide types. Data representative of a typical clinical mix is not yet available.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45316833</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 20:00:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Homegrown digital road maps turn into lifelines for West Bank’s Palestinians</title><link>https://restofworld.org/2025/palestinians-digital-maps-west-bank-israel/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ab513a9b89b0fce3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Palestinians living in the West Bank, stepping onto the roads of the territory occupied by Israel is a daily journey of resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With movement shackled by a complex web of Israeli checkpoints and barriers, homegrown mapping solutions have become their lifelines. These digital networks help Palestinians reach work, schools, and hospitals as blockades have continued to increase since the latest Israel-Gaza war started in October 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apps such as Doroob Navigator and Azmeh, which crowdsource traffic data and information about road closures, guide them through the numerous obstacles they face in their commutes. The situation has worsened dramatically in recent months. Simple trips that once took 45 minutes now stretch beyond three hours, with some routes completely sealed, commuters say.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Before the war, the UN counted about 565 obstacles across the West Bank. Today, the app Azmeh, Arabic for traffic jams, tracks more than 800 checkpoints and barriers based on updates from its 60,000-plus users, one of the developers of the app told Rest of World on condition of anonymity, fearing Israeli reprisal. In October and November of 2023, 8,000 Palestinians installed the Azmeh app every single day, the person said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Started in 2015, Azmeh was paused after its creators received threats from the Israeli military, which perceived tracking checkpoints as a security threat. Back online since March 2023, it now has 70,000 users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We are stranded for hours, sometimes from sunrise to sunset,” Rakan Said, a minibus driver with 20 years of experience, told Rest of World. “Passengers can’t reach jobs, and drivers lose their entire day’s wages waiting at checkpoints.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The West Bank’s fragmented road system imposes severe movement restrictions on Palestinians. Approximately 79 kilometers of roads connecting Israeli settlements to each other and to Israel are designated exclusively for Israeli citizens. Palestinians are banned from these roads, and unauthorized entry risks arrest, expensive fines, or violence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I use Waze for external roads to check if there’s traffic or the presence of Israeli police,” Abu Ahmad, a minibus driver in Ramallah, told Rest of World. “Waze treats us as Israelis, and as soon as we enter the West Bank, it starts sending warnings that we are in dangerous areas. So, we turn to WhatsApp groups instead.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doroob Navigator, which has more than 200,000 active users, was created by Palestinian tech entrepreneur Mohammad Abdel Haleem when a drive using Google Maps between the West Bank cities of Bethlehem and Ramallah left him lost in a remote valley.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The app is intended to help drivers by using widely recognized street and place names, offering an alternative to typical mapping tools,” Haleem told Rest of World.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What makes Palestinian navigation networks different from regular GPS systems is that they’re built on community support rather than business interests. While normal navigation apps try to find the fastest route, Palestinian digital networks focus on avoiding risks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This is a collective effort to save lives,” Mohamed Atiyat, a minibus driver who participates in and manages WhatsApp groups where thousands share real-time road updates, told Rest of World. “We share minute-by-minute updates on road conditions through videos, voice notes, and text messages so we can help each other stay safe.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Atiyat’s experience shows what’s at stake — he once spent 36 hours trying to find a route to the hospital for a young cancer patient after the town of Al-Auja was sealed off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenStreetMap (OSM), a collaborative, open-source mapping platform, allows communities to document and update local geographical situations. It allows Palestinians to accurately represent their villages, roads, and barriers that might otherwise be misrepresented or entirely absent on regular navigation tools such as Google Maps and Waze.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Palestinians have a long tradition of building community support systems. During the Intifadas — mass Palestinian uprisings against Israeli occupation during 1987–1993 and 2000–2005 — neighborhoods organized committees to distribute food, run schools, and provide healthcare when normal life was disrupted. Today’s tech solutions serve a similar purpose, Atiyat said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2018, Palestinian digital rights group 7amleh started a campaign calling for Google to recognize Palestine on its maps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We had been talking with Google’s human rights unit about their responsibilities,” Nadim Nashif, 7amleh’s director, told Rest of World. “Unfortunately, their policies have only gotten worse.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The navigation efforts face other technical challenges, Maysa Monayer, director general at the Palestinian Ministry of Telecommunications, told Rest of World.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the region, 3G service is patchy, and frequent GPS jamming disrupts navigation apps, vehicle tracking, and emergency services. The combination of inadequate infrastructure and surveillance makes locally developed alternatives the natural choice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clashes with Israeli settlers, who built communities on land captured by Israel during the 1967 war, pose additional risks. UN monitors counted 1,700 settler attacks in the West Bank between October 2023 and December 2024 — about four incidents a day. To avoid the risk, drivers, including Atiyat, have started traveling in groups.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“When we’re just one car on the road, we’re more vulnerable,” Atiyat said. “But with three cars or more, settlers are afraid to attack.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45317337</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 20:46:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A brief history of threads and threading</title><link>https://eclecticlight.co/2025/09/20/a-brief-history-of-threads-and-threading/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="66748c770736d00a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The original 128K Mac from 1984 came with a single Motorola 68000 processor running at 8 MHz that could only run one app at a time. Yet today’s Macs come with multiple CPU cores that can comfortably run several substantial apps simultaneously, while running a Time Machine backup and other tasks in the background. This brief history outlines the journey between them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A processor with a single core and no support for multi-tasking runs one sequence of instructions at a time. When those call for an operating system function to be performed, the running app is interrupted to hand control over to the system, and once that has completed, control is passed back to the app. That’s what the first Macs did until Andy Hertzfeld wrote Switcher, released by Apple in April 1985. This allowed the user to switch between running more than one app, but was still limited to running just one of them at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Multitasking&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the next couple of years, some third-party utilities were produced to go further than Switcher, but it wasn’t until 1987 that MultiFinder replaced Switcher, and was integrated into System 7 in 1991. Developed by Erich Ringewald and Phil Goldman, this brought cooperative multitasking, which was to become the mainstay of classic Mac OS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In computers with a single processor core, multitasking is a way of cheating to give the impression that the processor is doing several things at once, when in fact all it’s doing is switching rapidly between two or more different programs. There are two fundamental models for doing that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;cooperative multitasking, in which individual tasks yield to give others processing time;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;preemptive multitasking, in which a scheduler switches between tasks at regular intervals.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a processor switches from one task to the next, the current task state must be saved so it can be resumed later. Once that’s complete, the next task is loaded to complete the context switch. That incurs overhead, both in terms of processing and in memory storage, which are less when switching between lightweight tasks. Different strategies have been adopted to determine the optimum size of tasks and overhead imposed by context switching, and terminology differs between them, variously using words such as processes, threads and even fibres, which can prove thoroughly confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Classic Mac OS thus has a Process Manager that launches apps in cooperative multitasking. This works well much of the time, but lets badly behaved tasks hog the processor and block other tasks from getting their fair share. It’s greatly aided by the main event loop at the heart of Mac apps that waits for control input to direct the app to perform work for the user. But when an app charges off to spend many seconds tackling a demanding task without polling its main event loop, that app could lock the user out for what seems like an age.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In February 1988 Apple released the first Unix for Macintosh, A/UX, which came with preemptive multitasking. That was added to Mac OS in 1996 in System 7.5.3, in Multiprocessing Services, and further enhanced in Mac OS 8.6 three years later. Cooperative multitasking was also supported by the Thread Manager.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Threads&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2000 Apple’s hardware and software changed radically. Its first Macs with dual processors came in PowerPC 7400 (G4) chips in Power Mac G4 desktop systems, and Mac OS X brought several types of thread that could be used to manage processing on multiple processors or CPU cores, together with preemptive multitasking. Thread types include low-level Mach threads, higher-level POSIX threads or Pthreads that replaced Multiprocessing Services, Java Threads, Cocoa’s NSThreads, and cooperatively scheduled threads using the Carbon Thread Manager. The following diagram summarises Apple’s current terminology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In most cases, we’re considering applications with a GUI, normally run from a bundle structure. These can in turn run their own code, such as privileged helper apps used to perform work that requires elevated privileges. In recent years, there has been a proliferation of additional executable code associated with many apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When that app is run, there’s a single runtime instance created from its single executable code, and given its own virtual memory and access to system resources that it needs. This is a process, and listed as such in Activity Monitor, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each process has a main thread, a single flow of code execution, and may create additional threads, perhaps to run in the background. Threads don’t get their own virtual memory, but share that allocated to the process, although they have their own stack. On Apple silicon Macs they’re easy to tell apart as they can only run on a single core, although they may be moved between cores, sometimes rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Within each thread are individual tasks, each a quantity of work to be performed. These can be brief sections of code and are more interdependent than threads. They’re often divided into synchronous and asynchronous tasks, depending on whether they need to be run as part of a strict sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2005 the Power Mac G5 was the first Mac to use dual-core PowerPC G5 processors, then the iMac 17-inch of the following year used Apple’s first Intel Core Duo processor with two cores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Grand Central Dispatch&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2009 Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard introduced a new dispatcher, named Grand Central Dispatch (GCD) after Grand Central Terminal in New York City, and that was enhanced in macOS Sierra a decade later. More recently it has been referred to simply as Dispatch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At its heart, GCD is a dispatcher managing queues of tasks, activating those that need most to be run, and leaving the less pressing to wait a bit longer. It has its own queues, as well as those assembled by apps. Some are run as simple queues with a first in first out rule, others using sophisticated heuristics to determine relative priorities. There’s a detailed account of GCD internals in Jonathan Levin’s book *OS Internals volume 1, and Apple’s current developer documentation is here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GCD was introduced for Macs with multiple identical cores, to support their symmetric multiprocessing (SMP), and with the release of the first Apple silicon Macs in November 2020 it has managed queues of threads to be dispatched for execution on two CPU core types, Performance and Efficiency. Core allocation is now managed according to the Quality of Service (QoS) assigned to each thread. When used on SMP processors with no contention for core availability, QoS has limited effects on thread performance, but performance on P and E cores may differ by a factor of 10.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the last 41 years, macOS has gained thorough support for getting the best performance from multiple tasks, threads, and processes in chips that contain up to 32 CPU cores of two types – a far cry from that single 68000 processor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45317526</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 21:04:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>$2 WeAct Display FS adds a 0.96-inch USB information display to your computer</title><link>https://www.cnx-software.com/2025/09/18/2-weact-display-fs-adds-a-0-96-inch-usb-information-display-to-your-computer/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="aa305d1c39dee0f3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WeAct Display FS is an inexpensive 0.96-inch USB display dongle designed to add an information display or a tiny secondary display to your computer or SBC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve seen this type of information display with products such as the Turing Smart Screen, a larger 3.5-inch color display, or small OLEDs integrated into cases such as the Pironman 5 Max to disable text. The WeAct Display FS V1 may be tiny, but it’s also a full-color 160×80 resolution display that can be customized with software provided by WeAct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WeAct Display FS V1 specifications:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Display – 0.96-inch RGB565 display with 160×80 resolution&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Host interface – “Reversible” USB 2.0 Type-A Full Speed (FS) port showing as a CDC device&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dimensions – 43 x 14.5 mm&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since you wouldn’t want to get a display only for it to face the wrong direction, for instance, the desk or the wall, the company made the USB-A port reversible, and the user only needs to install one of the two provided pads on the unused side of the port to avoid short circuits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WeAct provides two programs for it. The first one is the WeAct Studio System Monitor based on a fork of Matthieu Houdebine’s Turing Smart Screen Python project. This allows users to create UIs/themes with text, images, weather, and other features… WeAct says the little device only works on Windows, but the open-source project is supposed to also work on macOS, Linux (including Raspberry Pi OS), and essentially any operating system with support for Python 3.9+.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second program is called WeAct Studio Screen Projection, and as I understand it, it emulates an actual display, so you could move any window/program to the USB display. I’m just not sure how a desktop OS like Windows will handle a tiny 160×80 “monitor”… I suppose it could be used to play a full-screen YouTube video or display photos for whatever reason. That one only works on Windows, and there’s no source code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ll find the WeAct Display FS V1 (0.96-inch) on AliExpress for about $2 plus shipping, but while looking for information, I also noticed a 3.5-inch variant with 480×320 resolution for about $11.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jean-Luc started CNX Software in 2010 as a part-time endeavor, before quitting his job as a software engineering manager, and starting to write daily news, and reviews full time later in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support CNX Software! Donate via cryptocurrencies, become a Patron on Patreon, or purchase goods on Amazon or Aliexpress. We also use affiliate links in articles to earn commissions if you make a purchase after clicking on those links.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45317527</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 21:04:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why do some gamers invert their controls?</title><link>https://www.theguardian.com/games/2025/sep/18/why-do-some-gamers-invert-their-controls-scientists-now-have-answers-but-theyre-not-what-you-think</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a63b909429620de9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Five years ago, on the verge of the first Covid lockdown, I wrote an article asking what seemed to be an extremely niche question: why do some people invert their controls when playing 3D games? A majority of players push down on the controller to make their onscreen character look down, and up to make them look up. But there is a sizeable minority who do the opposite, controlling their avatars like a pilot controls a plane, pulling back to go up. For most modern games, this requires going into the settings and reconfiguring the default controls. Why do they still persist?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought a few hardcore gamers would be interested in the question. Instead, more than one million people read the article, and the ensuing debate caught the attention of Dr Jennifer Corbett (quoted in the original piece) and Dr Jaap Munneke, then based at the Visual Perception and Attention Lab at Brunel University London.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the time, the two were conducting research into vision science and cognitive neuroscience, but when the country locked down, they were no longer able to test volunteers in their laboratory. The question of controller inversion provided the perfect opportunity to study the neuroscience of human-computer interactions using remote subjects. They put out a call for gamers willing to help research the reasons behind controller inversion and received many hundreds of replies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it wasn’t just gamers who were interested. “Machinists, equipment operators, pilots, designers, surgeons – people from so many different backgrounds reached out,” says Corbett. “Because there were so many different answers, we realised we had a lot of scientific literature to review to design the best possible study. Readers’ responses turned this study into the first of its kind to try to figure out what actually are those factors that shape how users configure their controllers. Personal experiences, favourite games, different genres, age, consoles, which way you scroll with a mouse … all of these things could potentially be involved.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This month the duo published their findings in a paper entitled “Why axis inversion? Optimising interactions between users, interfaces, and visual displays in 3D environments”. And the reason why some people invert their controls? It’s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The process started with participants completing a survey about their backgrounds and gaming experiences. “Many people told us that playing a flight simulator, using a certain type of console, or the first game they played were the reasons they preferred to invert or not,” says Corbett. “Many also said they switched preferences over time. We added a whole new section to the study based on all this feedback.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Corbett and Munneke, now based at MIT and Northeastern University respectively, were certain that there would also be important cognitive components to the inversion question that could be measured only through behavioural responses. So they devised a questionnaire and a series of four experiments that participants would take part in while being instructed and observed via Zoom. As Corbett explains: “They had to mentally rotate random shapes, take on the perspective of an ‘avatar’ object in a picture, determine which way something was tilted in differently tilted backgrounds, and overcome the typical ‘Simon effect’ where it’s harder to respond when a target is on the opposite v the same side of the screen as the response button. Then we used some machine-learning algorithms to help us sort through all this survey and experiment data and pick out what combination of all of these things best explained whether someone inverted.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What they discovered through the cognitive testing was that a lot of assumptions being made around controller preferences were wrong. “None of the reasons people gave us [for inverting controls] had anything to do with whether they actually inverted,” says Corbett. “It turns out the most predictive out of all the factors we measured was how quickly gamers could mentally rotate things and overcome the Simon effect. The faster they were, the less likely they were to invert. People who said they sometimes inverted were by far the slowest on these tasks.” So does this mean non-inverters are better gamers? No, says Corbett. “Though they tended to be faster, they didn’t get the correct answer more than inverters who were actually slightly more accurate.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In short, gamers think they are an inverter or a non-inverter because of how they were first exposed to game controls. Someone who played a lot of flight sims in the 1980s may have unconsciously taught themselves to invert and now they consider that their innate preference; alternatively a gamer who grew up in the 2000s, when non-inverted controls became prevalent may think they are naturally a non-inverter. However, cognitive tests suggest otherwise. It’s much more likely that you invert or don’t invert due to how your brain perceives objects in 3D space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consequently, Corbett says that it may improve you as a gamer to try the controller setup you are currently not using. “Non-inverters should give inversion a try – and inverters should give non-inversion another shot,” she says. “You might even want to force yourself to stick with it for a few hours. People have learned one way. That doesn’t mean they won’t learn another way even better. A good example is being left-handed. Until the mid-20th century, left-handed children were forced to write with their right hand, causing some people to have lifelong handwriting difficulties and learning problems. Many older adults still don’t realise they’re naturally left-handed and could write/draw much better if they switched back.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through this research, Corbett and Munneke have established that there are complex and often unconscious cognitive processes involved in how individuals use controllers, and that these may have important ramifications for not just game hardware but for any human-computer interfaces, from aircraft controls to surgical devices. They were able to design a framework for assessing how to best configure controls for any given individual and have now made that available via their research paper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This work opened our eyes to the huge potential that optimising inversion settings has for advancing human-machine teaming,” says Corbett. “So many technologies are pairing humans with AI and other machines to augment what we can do alone. Understanding how a given individual best performs with a certain setup (controller configuration, screen placement, whether they are trying to hit a target or avoid an obstacle) can allow for much smoother interactions between humans and machines in lots of scenarios from partnering with an AI player to defeat a boss, to preventing damage to delicate internal tissue while performing a complicated laparoscopic surgery.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what started as an idle, slightly nerdy question has now become a published cognitive research paper. One scientific publication has already cited it and interview requests are pouring in from podcasts and Youtubers. As for my takeaway? “The most surprising finding for gamers [who don’t invert] is that they might perform better if they practised with an inverted control scheme,” says Corbett. “Maybe not, but given our findings, it’s definitely worth a shot because it could dramatically improve competitive game play!”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45317870</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 21:46:11 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>