<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:45:23 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Demand for human radiologists is at an all-time high</title><link>https://www.worksinprogress.news/p/why-ai-isnt-replacing-radiologists</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2fd9d9d02935859e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;AI isn't replacing radiologists&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Radiology combines digital images, clear benchmarks, and repeatable tasks. But demand for human radiologists is at an all-time high.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Works in Progress is becoming a print magazine. Our first print issue, Issue 21, will land in November. If you live in the United States or the United Kingdom, you can subscribe here. If you live outside the US or UK and want to be notified as soon as subscriptions are live in your country, leave your details here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CheXNet can detect pneumonia with greater accuracy than a panel of board-certified radiologists. It is an AI model released in 2017, trained on more than 100,000 chest X-rays. It is fast, free, and can run on a single consumer-grade GPU. A hospital can use it to classify a new scan in under a second.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since then, companies like Annalise.ai, Lunit, Aidoc, and Qure.ai have released models that can detect hundreds of diseases across multiple types of scans with greater accuracy and speed than human radiologists in benchmark tests. Some products can reorder radiologist worklists to prioritize critical cases, suggest next steps for care teams, or generate structured draft reports that fit into hospital record systems. A few, like IDx-DR, are even cleared to operate without a physician reading the image at all. In total, there are over 700 FDA-cleared radiology models, which account for roughly three-quarters of all medical AI devices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radiology is a field optimized for human replacement, where digital inputs, pattern recognition tasks, and clear benchmarks predominate. In 2016, Geoffrey Hinton – computer scientist and Turing Award winner – declared that ‘people should stop training radiologists now’. If the most extreme predictions about the effect of AI on employment and wages were true, then radiology should be the canary in the coal mine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But demand for human labor is higher than ever. In 2025, American diagnostic radiology residency programs offered a record 1,208 positions across all radiology specialties, a four percent increase from 2024, and the field’s vacancy rates are at all-time highs. In 2025, radiology was the second-highest-paid medical specialty in the country, with an average income of $520,000, over 48 percent higher than the average salary in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three things explain this. First, while models beat humans on benchmarks, the standardized tests designed to measure AI performance, they struggle to replicate this performance in hospital conditions. Most tools can only diagnose abnormalities that are common in training data, and models often don’t work as well outside of their test conditions. Second, attempts to give models more tasks have run into legal hurdles: regulators and medical insurers so far are reluctant to approve or cover fully autonomous radiology models. Third, even when they do diagnose accurately, models replace only a small share of a radiologist’s job. Human radiologists spend a minority of their time on diagnostics and the majority on other activities, like talking to patients and fellow clinicians.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence is rapidly spreading across the economy and society. But radiology shows us that it will not necessarily dominate every field in its first years of diffusion — at least until these common hurdles are overcome. Exploiting all of its benefits will involve adapting it to society, and society’s rules to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Islands of automation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All AIs are functions or algorithms, called models, that take in inputs and spit out outputs. Radiology models are trained to detect a finding, which is a measurable piece of evidence that helps identify or rule out a disease or condition. Most radiology models detect a single finding or condition in one type of image. For example, a model might look at a chest CT and answer whether there are lung nodules, rib fractures, or what the coronary arterial calcium score is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For every individual question, a new model is required. In order to cover even a modest slice of what they see in a day, a radiologist would need to switch between dozens of models and ask the right questions of each one. Several platforms manage, run, and interpret outputs from dozens or even hundreds of separate AI models across vendors, but each model operates independently, analyzing for one finding or disease at a time. The final output is a list of separate answers to specific questions, rather than a single description of an image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even with hundreds of imaging algorithms approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) on the market, the combined footprint of today’s radiology AI models still cover only a small fraction of real-world imaging tasks. Many cluster around a few use cases: stroke, breast cancer, and lung cancer together account for about 60 percent of models, but only a minority of the actual radiology imaging volume that is carried out in the US. Other subspecialties, such as vascular, head and neck, spine, and thyroid imaging currently have relatively few AI products. This is in part due to data availability: the scan needs to be common enough for there to be many annotated examples that can be used to train models. Some scans are also inherently more complicated than others. For example, ultrasounds are taken from multiple angles and do not have standard imaging planes, unlike X-rays.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once deployed outside of the hospital where they were initially trained, models can struggle. In a standard clinical trial, samples are taken from multiple hospitals to ensure exposure to a broad range of patients and to avoid site-specific effects, such as a single doctor’s technique or how a hospital chooses to calibrate its diagnostic equipment.1 But when an algorithm is undergoing regulatory approval in the US, its developers will normally test it on a relatively narrow dataset. Out of the models in 2024 that reported the number of sites where they were tested, 38 percent were tested on data from a single hospital. Public benchmarks tend to rely on multiple datasets from the same hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The performance of a tool can drop as much as 20 percentage points when it is tested out of sample, on data from other hospitals. In one study, a pneumonia detection model trained on chest X-rays from a single hospital performed substantially worse when tested at a different hospital. Some of these challenges stemmed from avoidable experimental issues like overfitting, but others are indicative of deeper problems like differences in how hospitals record and generate data, such as using slightly different imaging equipment. This means that individual hospitals or departments would need to retrain or revalidate today’s crop of tools before adopting them, even if they have been proven elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The limitations of radiology models stem from deeper problems with building medical AI. Training datasets come with strict inclusion criteria, where the diagnosis must be unambiguous (typically confirmed by a consensus of two to three experts or a pathology result) and without images that are shot at an odd angle, look too dark, or are blurry. This skews performance towards the easiest cases, which doctors are already best at diagnosing, and away from real-world images. In one 2022 study, an algorithm that was meant to spot pneumonia on chest X-rays faltered when the disease presented in subtle or mild forms, or when other lung conditions resembled pneumonia, such as pleural effusions, where fluid builds up in lungs, or in atelectasis (collapsed lung). Humans also benefit from context: one radiologist told me about a model they use that labels surgical staples as hemorrhages, because of the bright streaks they create in the image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Medical imaging datasets used for training also tend to have fewer cases from children, women, and ethnic minorities, making their performance generally worse for these demographics. Many lack information about the gender or race of cases at all, making it difficult to adjust for these issues and address the problem of bias. The result is that radiology models often predict only a narrow slice of the world,2 though there are scenarios where AI models do perform well, including identifying common diseases like pneumonia or certain tumors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problems don’t stop there. Even a model for the precise question you need and in the hospital where it was trained is unlikely to perform as well in clinical practice as it did in the benchmark. In benchmark studies, researchers isolate a cohort of scans, define goals in quantitative metrics, such as the sensitivity (the percentage of people with the condition who are correctly identified by the test) and specificity (the percentage of people without the condition who are correctly identified as such), and compare the performance of a model to the score of another reviewer, typically a human doctor. Clinical studies, on the other hand, show how well the model performs in a real healthcare setting without controls. Since the earliest days of computer-aided diagnosis, there has been a gulf between benchmark and clinical performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, computer-aided diagnosis, effectively rudimentary AI systems, were developed to screen mammograms, or X-rays of breasts that are performed to look for breast cancer. In trials, the combination of humans and computer-aided diagnosis systems outperformed humans alone in accuracy when evaluating mammograms. More controlled experiments followed, which pointed to computer-aided diagnosis helping radiologists pick up more cancer with minimal costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FDA approved mammography computer-aided diagnosis in 1998, and Medicare started to reimburse the use of computer-aided diagnosis in 2001. The US government paid radiologists $7 more to report a screening mammogram if they used the technology; by 2010, approximately 74 percent of mammograms in the country were read by computer-aided diagnosis alongside a clinician.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But computer-aided diagnosis turned out to be a disappointment. Between 1998 and 2002 researchers analyzed 430,000 screening mammograms from 200,000 women at 43 community clinics in Colorado, New Hampshire, and Washington. Among the seven clinics that turned to computer-aided detection software, the machines flagged more images, leading to clinicians conducting 20 percent more biopsies, but uncovering no more cancer than before. Several other large clinical studies had similar findings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another way to measure performance is to compare having computerized help to a second clinician reading every film, called ‘double reading’. Across ten trials and seventeen studies of double reading, researchers found that computer aids did not raise the cancer detection rate but led to patients being called back an additional ten percent more often. In contrast, having two readers caught more cancers while slightly lowering callbacks. Computer-aided detection was worse than standard care, and much worse than another pair of eyes. In 2018, Medicare stopped reimbursing doctors more for mammograms read with computer-aided diagnosis than those read by a radiologist alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One explanation for this gap is that people behave differently if they are treating patients day to day than when they are part of laboratory studies or other controlled experiments.3 In particular, doctors appear to defer excessively to assistive AI tools in clinical settings in a way that they do not in lab settings. They did this even with much more primitive tools than we have today: one clinical trial all the way back in 2004 asked 20 breast screening specialists to read mammogram cases with the computer prompts switched on, then brought in a new group to read the identical films without the software. When guided by computer aids, doctors identified barely half of the malignancies, while those reviewing without the model caught 68 percent. The gap was largest when computer aids failed to recognize the malignancy itself; many doctors seemed to treat an absence of prompts as reassurance that a film was clean. Another review, this time from 2011, found that when a system gave incorrect guidance, clinicians were 26 percent more likely to make a wrong decision than unaided peers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Humans in the loop&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It would seem as if better models and more automation could together fix the problems of current-day AI for radiology. Without a doctor involved whose behavior might change we might expect real-world results to match benchmark scores. But regulatory requirements and insurance policies are slowing the adoption of fully autonomous radiology AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FDA splits imaging software into two regulatory lanes: assistive or triage tools, which require a licensed physician to read the scan and sign the chart, and autonomous tools, which do not. Makers of assistive tools simply have to show that their software can match the performance of tools that are already on the market. Autonomous tools have to clear a much higher bar: they must demonstrate that the AI tool will refuse to read any scan that is blurry, uses an unusual scanner, or is outside its competence. The bar is higher because, once the human disappears, a latent software defect could harm thousands before anyone notices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meeting that criteria is difficult. Even state-of-the-art vision networks falter with images that lack contrast, have unexpected angles, or lots of different artefacts. IDx-DR, a diabetic retinopathy screener and one of the few cleared to operate autonomously, comes with guardrails: the patient must be an adult with no prior retinopathy diagnosis; there must be two macula-centred photographs of the fundus (the rear of the eye) with a resolution of at least 1,000 times 1,000 pixels; if glare, small pupils or poor focus degrade quality, the software must self-abort and refer the patient to an eye care professional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stronger evidence and improved performance could eventually clear both hurdles, but other requirements would still delay widespread use. For example, if you retrain a model, you are required to receive new approval even if the previous model was approved. This contributes to the market generally lagging behind frontier capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And when autonomous models are approved, malpractice insurers are not eager to cover them. Diagnostic error is the costliest mistake in American medicine, resulting in roughly a third of all malpractice payouts, and radiologists are perennial defendants. Insurers believe that software makes catastrophic payments more likely than a human clinician, as a broken algorithm can harm many patients at once. Standard contract language now often includes phrases such as: ‘Coverage applies solely to interpretations reviewed and authenticated by a licensed physician; no indemnity is afforded for diagnoses generated autonomously by software’. One insurer, Berkley, even carries the blunter label ‘Absolute AI Exclusion’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without malpractice coverage, hospitals cannot afford to let algorithms sign reports. In the case of IDx-DR, the vendor, Digital Diagnostics, includes a product liability policy and an indemnity clause. This means that if the clinic used the device exactly as the FDA label prescribes, with adult patients, good-quality images, and no prior retinopathy, then the company will reimburse the clinic for damages traceable to algorithmic misclassification.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, if American hospitals wanted to adopt AI for fully independent diagnostic reads, they would need to believe that autonomous models deliver enough cost savings or throughput gains to justify pushing for exceptions to credentialing and billing norms. For now, usage is too sparse to make a difference. One 2024 investigation estimated that 48 percent of radiologists are using AI at all in their practice. A 2025 survey reported that only 19 percent of respondents who have started piloting or deploying AI use cases in radiology reported a ‘high’ degree of success.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Better AI, more MRIs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if AI models become accurate enough to read scans on their own and are cleared to do so, radiologists may still find themselves busier, rather than out of a career.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radiologists are useful for more than reading scans; a study that followed staff radiologists in three different hospitals in 2012 found that only 36 percent of their time was dedicated to direct image interpretation. More time is spent on overseeing imaging examinations, communicating results and recommendations to the treating clinicians and occasionally directly to patients, teaching radiology residents and technologists who conduct the scans, and reviewing imaging orders and changing scanning protocols.4 This means that, if AI were to get better at interpreting scans, radiologists may simply shift their time toward other tasks. This would reduce the substitution effect of AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As tasks get faster or cheaper to perform, we may also do more of them. In some cases, especially if lower costs or faster turnaround times open the door to new uses, the increase in demand can outweigh the increase in efficiency, a phenomenon known as Jevons paradox. This has historical precedent in the field: in the early 2000s hospitals swapped film jackets for digital systems. Hospitals that digitized improved radiologist productivity, and time to read an individual scan went down. A study at Vancouver General found that the switch boosted radiologist productivity 27 percent for plain radiography and 98 percent for CT within a year of going filmless. This occurred alongside other advancements in imaging technology that made scans faster to execute. Yet, no radiologists were laid off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, the overall American utilization rate per 1,000 insured patients for all imaging increased by 60 percent from 2000 to 2008. This is not explained by a commensurate increase in physician visits. Instead, each visit was associated with more imaging on average. Before digitization, the nonmonetary price of imaging was high: the median reporting turnaround time for x-rays was 76 hours for patients discharged from emergency departments, and 84 hours for admitted patients. After departments digitized, these times dropped to 38 hours and 35 hours, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Faster scans give doctors more options. Until the early 2000s, only exceptional trauma cases would receive whole-body CT scans; the increased speed of CT turnaround times mean that they are now a common choice. This is a reflection of elastic demand, a concept in economics that describes when demand for a product or service is very sensitive to changes in price. In this case, when these scans got cheaper in terms of waiting time, demand for those scans increased.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The first decade of diffusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, improvements in image interpretation have run far ahead of their diffusion. Hundreds of models can spot bleeds, nodules, and clots, yet AI is often limited to assistive use on a small subset of scans in any given practice. And despite predictions to the contrary, head counts and salaries have continued to rise. The promise of AI in radiology is overstated by benchmarks alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multi‑task foundation models may widen coverage, and different training sets could blunt data gaps. But many hurdles cannot be removed with better models alone: the need to counsel the patient, shoulder malpractice risk, and receive accreditation from regulators. Each hurdle makes full substitution the expensive, risky option and human plus machine the default. Sharp increases in AI capabilities could certainly alter this dynamic, but it is a useful model for the first years of AI models that benchmark well at tasks associated with a particular career.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are industries where conditions are different. Large platforms rely heavily on AI systems to triage or remove harmful or policy-violating content. At Facebook and Instagram, 94 percent and 98 percent of moderation decisions respectively are made by machines. But many of the more sophisticated knowledge jobs look more like radiology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In many jobs, tasks are diverse, stakes are high, and demand is elastic. When this is the case, we should expect software to initially lead to more human work, not less. The lesson from a decade of radiology models is neither optimism about increased output nor dread about replacement. Models can lift productivity, but their implementation depends on behavior, institutions and incentives. For now, the paradox has held: the better the machines, the busier radiologists have become.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deena Mousa is a lead researcher at Open Philanthropy. Follow her on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few groups have started doing this, like the 2025 ‘OpenMIBOOD’ suite which explicitly scores chest-X-ray models on 14 out-of-distribution collections, but that hasn’t yet become standard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few companies and research groups are working to mitigate this, such as by training on multi-site datasets, building synthetic cases, or using self-supervised learning to reduce labeling needs, but these approaches are still early and expensive. This limitation is an important reason why AI models do not yet perform as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One study tracked 27 mammographers and compared how well each interpreted real screening films versus a standardised ‘test-set’ of the same images. The researchers found no meaningful link between a radiologist’s accuracy in the lab and accuracy on live patients; the statistical correlation in sensitivity-specificity scores was essentially zero.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45372335</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 13:19:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Launch HN: Webhound (YC S23) – Research agent that builds datasets from the web</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45373008</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="354a104b23ad844a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We're the team behind Webhound (&lt;/p&gt;https://webhound.ai&lt;p&gt;), an AI agent that builds datasets from the web based on natural language prompts. You describe what you're trying to find. The agent figures out how to structure the data and where to look, then searches, extracts the results, and outputs everything in a CSV you can export.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've set up a special no-signup version for the HN community at https://hn.webhound.ai - just click "Continue as Guest" to try it without signing up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's a demo: https://youtu.be/fGaRfPdK1Sk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started building it after getting tired of doing this kind of research manually. Open 50 tabs, copy everything into a spreadsheet, realize it's inconsistent, start over. It felt like something an LLM should be able to handle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some examples of how people have used it in the past month:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Competitor analysis: "Create a comparison table of internal tooling platforms (Retool, Appsmith, Superblocks, UI Bakery, BudiBase, etc) with their free plan limits, pricing tiers, onboarding experience, integrations, and how they position themselves on their landing pages." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/c67c96a6-9d17-4c91-b9a0-ff69...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lead generation: "Find Shopify stores launched recently that sell skincare products. I want the store URLs, founder names, emails, Instagram handles, and product categories." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/b63d148a-8895-4aab-ac34-455e...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pricing tracking: "Track how the free and paid plans of note-taking apps have changed over the past 6 months using official sites and changelogs. List each app with a timeline of changes and the source for each." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/c17e6033-5d00-4e54-baf6-8dea...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Investor mapping: "Find VCs who led or participated in pre-seed or seed rounds for browser-based devtools startups in the past year. Include the VC name, relevant partners, contact info, and portfolio links for context." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/1480c053-d86b-40ce-a620-37fd...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research collection: "Get a list of recent arXiv papers on weak supervision in NLP. For each, include the abstract, citation count, publication date, and a GitHub repo if available." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/e274ca26-0513-4296-85a5-2b7b...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hypothesis testing: "Check if user complaints about Figma's performance on large files have increased in the last 3 months. Search forums like Hacker News, Reddit, and Figma's community site and show the most relevant posts with timestamps and engagement metrics." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/42b2de49-acbf-4851-bbb7-080b...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first version of Webhound was a single agent running on Claude 4 Sonnet. It worked, but sessions routinely cost over $1100 and it would often get lost in infinite loops. We knew that wasn't sustainable, so we started building around smaller models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That meant adding more structure. We introduced a multi-agent system to keep it reliable and accurate. There's a main agent, a set of search agents that run subtasks in parallel, a critic agent that keeps things on track, and a validator that double-checks extracted data before saving it. We also gave it a notepad for long-term memory, which helps avoid duplicates and keeps track of what it's already seen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After switching to Gemini 2.5 Flash and layering in the agent system, we were able to cut costs by more than 30x while also improving speed and output quality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The system runs in two phases. First is planning, where it decides the schema, how to search, what sources to use, and how to know when it's done. Then comes extraction, where it executes the plan and gathers the data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It uses a text-based browser we built that renders pages as markdown and extracts content directly. We tried full browser use but it was slower and less reliable. Plain text still works better for this kind of task.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also built scheduled refreshes to keep datasets up to date and an API so you can integrate the data directly into your workflows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right now, everything stays in the agent's context during a run. It starts to break down around 1000-5000 rows depending on the number of attributes. We're working on a better architecture for scaling past that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We'd love feedback, especially from anyone who's tried solving this problem or built similar tools. Happy to answer anything in the thread.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks! Moe&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45373008</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:28:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cloudflare Email Service: private beta</title><link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/email-service/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ee97ad5b3f10bcad"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you are building an application, you rely on email to communicate with your users. You validate their signup, notify them about events, and send them invoices through email. The service continues to find new purpose with agentic workflows and other AI-powered tools that rely on a simple email as an input or output.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And it is a pain for developers to manage. Itâs frequently the most annoying burden for most teams. Developers deserve a solution that is simple, reliable, and deeply integrated into their workflow.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Today, we're excited to announce just that: the private beta of Email Sending, a new capability that allows you to send transactional emails directly from Cloudflare Workers. Email Sending joins and expands our popular Email Routing product, and together they form the new Cloudflare Email Service â a single, unified developer experience for all your email needs.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;With Cloudflare Email Service, weâre distilling our years of experience securing and routing emails, and combining it with the power of the developer platform. Now, sending an email is as easy as adding a binding to a Worker and calling &lt;code&gt;send&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;export default {
  async fetch(request, env, ctx) {

    await env.SEND_EMAIL.send({
      to: [{ email: "[email protected]" }],
      from: { email: "[email protected]", name: "Your App" },
      subject: "Hello World",
      text: "Hello World!"
    });

    return new Response(`Successfully sent email!`);
  },
};&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Email experience is user experience&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email is a core tenet of your user experience. Itâs how you stay in touch with your users when they are outside your applications. Users rely on email to inform them when they need to take actions such as password resets, purchase receipts, magic login links, and onboarding flows. When they fail, your application fails.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;That means itâs crucial that emails need to land in your usersâ inboxes, both reliably and quickly. A magic link that arrives ten minutes late is a lost user. An email delivered to a spam folder breaks user flows and can erode trust in your product. Thatâs why weâre focusing on deliverability and time-to-inbox with Cloudflare Email Service.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To do this, weâre tightly integrating with DNS to automatically configure the necessary DNS records â like SPF, DKIM and DMARC â such that email providers can verify your sending domain and trust your emails. Plus, in true Cloudflare fashion, Email Service is a global service. That means that we can deliver your emails with low latency anywhere in the world, without the complexity of managing servers across regions.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Simple and flexible for developers&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Treating email as a core piece of your application also means building for every touchpoint in your development workflow. Weâre building Email Service as part of the Cloudflare stack to make developing with email feels as natural as writing a Worker.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In practice, that means solving for every part of the transactional email workflow:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Starting with Email Service is easy. Instead of managing API keys and secrets, you can use the &lt;code&gt;Email&lt;/code&gt; binding to your &lt;code&gt;wrangler.jsonc&lt;/code&gt; and send emails securely and with no risk of leaked credentials.Â &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;You can use Workers to process incoming mail, store attachments in R2, and add tasks to Queues to get email sending off the hot path of your application. And you can use &lt;code&gt;wrangler&lt;/code&gt; to emulate Email Sending locally, allowing you to test your user journeys without jumping between tools and environments.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;In production, you have clear observability over your emails with bounce rates and delivery events. And, when a user reports a missing email, you can quickly dive into the delivery status to debug issues quickly and help get your user back on track.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Weâre also making sure Email Service seamlessly fits into your existing applications. If you need to send emails from external services, you can do so using either REST APIs or SMTP. Likewise, if youâve been leaning on existing email frameworks (like React Email) to send rich, HTML-rendered emails to users, you can continue to use them with Email Service. Import the library, render your template, and pass it to the `send` method just as you would elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;import { render, pretty, toPlainText } from '@react-email/render';
import { SignupConfirmation } from './templates';

export default {
  async fetch(request, env, ctx) {

    // Convert React Email template to html
    const html = await pretty(await render(&amp;lt;SignupConfirmation url="https://your-domain.com/confirmation-id"/&amp;gt;));

    // Use the Email Sending binding to send emails
    await env.SEND_EMAIL.send({
      to: [{ email: "[email protected]" }],
      from: { email: "[email protected]", name: "Welcome" },
      subject: "Signup Confirmation",
      html,
      text: toPlainText(html)
    });

    return new Response(`Successfully sent email!`);
  }
};&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Email Routing and Email Sending: Better together&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Sending email is only half the story. Applications often need to receive and parse emails to create powerful workflows. By combining Email Sending with our existing Email Routing capabilities, we're providing a complete, end-to-end solution for all your application's email needs.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email Routing allows you to create custom email addresses on your domain and handle incoming messages programmatically with a Worker, which can enable powerful application flows such as:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Using Workers AI to parse, summarize and even label incoming emails: flagging security events from customers, early signs of a bug or incident, and/or generating automatic responses based on those incoming emails.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Creating support tickets in systems like JIRA or Linear from emails sent to &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Processing invoices sent to &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt; and storing attachments in R2.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To use Email Routing, add the &lt;code&gt;email&lt;/code&gt; handler to your Worker application and process it as needed:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;export default {
  // Create an email handler to process emails delivered to your Worker
  async email(message, env, ctx) {

    // Classify incoming emails using Workers AI
    const { score, label } = env.AI.run("@cf/huggingface/distilbert-sst-2-int8", { text: message.raw" })

    env.PROCESSED_EMAILS.send({score, label, message});
  },
};  &lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When you combine inbound routing with outbound sending, you can close the loop entirely within Cloudflare. Imagine a user emails your support address. A Worker can receive the email, parse its content, call a third-party API to create a ticket, and then use the Email Sending binding to send an immediate confirmation back to the user with their ticket number. Thatâs the power of a unified Email Service.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email Sending will require a paid Workers subscription, and we'll be charging based on messages sent. We're still finalizing the packaging, and we'll update our documentation, changelog, and notify users as soon as we have final pricing and long before we start charging. Email Routing limits will remain unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email is core to your application today, and it's becoming essential for the next generation of AI agents, background tasks, and automated workflows. We built the Cloudflare Email Service to be the engine for this new era of applications, weâll be making it available in private beta this November.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Interested in Email Sending? Sign up to the waitlist here.Â &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Want to start processing inbound emails? Get started with Email Routing, which is available now, remains free and will be folded into the new email sending APIs coming.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Weâre excited to be adding Email Service to our Developer Platform, and weâre looking forward to seeing how you reimagine user experiences that increasingly rely on emails!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45373081</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:33:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The story of DOGE, as told by federal workers</title><link>https://www.wired.com/story/oral-history-doge-federal-workers/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7e60c110ece257dd"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In August, months after Elon Musk left the federal government, the director of the Office of Personnel Management offered the first hard estimate of the so-called Department of Government Efficiency’s impact on the civil service. The government would likely end 2025 with about 300,000 fewer employees than it had at the start of the year, he told reporters. Most resignations were attributable to the incentives DOGE had offered the federal workforce to resign their positions. The total figure amounted to one in eight workers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, almost. In recent weeks, hundreds of the employees DOGE pushed out have reportedly been offered reinstatement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The true scope of DOGE’s attack on the federal government remains unknown. While there is no reason to think it achieved meaningful cost savings or operational efficiencies, the ramifications of building a master database to track and surveil immigrants are just beginning to be felt, and its cadre of Musk protégés and tech entrepreneurs remain embedded in agencies throughout the executive branch. The possibilities this opens up—of private takeovers of government operations, of the government embracing Silicon Valley’s ethos of moving fast and breaking things—remain open.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WIRED spoke with more than 200 federal workers across dozens of agencies to gather the most comprehensive picture yet of how the American government got to this point, and where it may go from here. Many sources requested anonymity because they fear retaliation. They told WIRED not just what has been going on inside the federal government at a time of unprecedented change—but what it’s been like to experience those changes firsthand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following is the story, in their words, of what happened when the world’s most powerful man unleashed the world’s richest one on the world’s most complex institution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I kept comparing it to a natural disaster,” one worker at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention told WIRED. “But it wasn’t natural. Just a stampede of wide-eyed, confused government employees moving files around and looking over their shoulders because they think maybe Elon was creeping behind them with a chain saw.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donald Trump established DOGE within hours of taking office on January 20, assigning it the task of “modernizing Federal technology and software to maximize governmental efficiency and productivity.” Within days, Musk’s allies and their coterie of young, inexperienced technologists were appearing in the offices of relatively unknown agencies like the General Services Administration and the Office of Personnel Management—obtaining unprecedented access to government systems and personnel files in the process. The DOGE operatives included young men like Edward “Big Balls” Coristine, Kyle Schutt, and Ethan Shaotran, all of whom would go on to work at a number of government agencies, from the Department of Education to the Social Security Administration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I met Kyle and Ethan on January 23, and I very briefly bumped into Coristine before anyone was talking about him. I would describe them all as giddy, excited, curious, passionate, and super interested in learning about and jumping in on this new thing. I was super excited too at first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Then the next week it felt like everything shifted and suddenly they were no longer curious or asking questions or on an adventure and instead they were just frantically running around trying to do impossible shit with no context and no flexibility and no ability to push back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I thought maybe it would turn around. But it never did.” —General Services Administration (GSA) worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The first meeting with DOGE—really the only meeting with DOGE, if I'm going to be honest—was … a virtual meeting that was 30 minutes long. In typical DOGE fashion, the government organization that we were promised unbelievable transparency on, they don't turn the cameras on, they don't tell you who they are, they don't tell you if anybody else is in the room, so you have no idea who you're talking to.” —Colin O’Brien, former head of security at the United States Institute of Peace&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We saw them immediately. They acted like new hires but a bit furtive since they were actually instructed not to share their full names with us at first.” —Technology Transformation Services worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“My big aha moment came late, because for so long I was giving them the benefit of the doubt. These guys were young, and they had a job to do, and yes, they were doing it aggressively—but again, I assumed the best. But then Ethan Shaotran went on Fox News, on Jesse Watters. He just trash-talked us pretty bad, conflating things they’d found at other agencies, basically implying we were misappropriating grant money. It made my blood boil. Ethan had to know that wasn’t true. That was it for me—there is no good faith at all.” —Federal worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The vibe they gave was ‘So, what is it that you do here?’ and ‘Why can’t AI do that?’” —Technology Transformation Services worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During the early weeks of the administration, emails from DOGE started showing up in federal workers’ inboxes—or at least in their spam folders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I logged on to find several emails tagged ‘External,’ because DOGE just brought in their own servers and plugged them into the network. Then there were several subsequent emails from different leaders saying things like, ‘Thank you for all the phishing reports, but the emails are real and need to be followed. But also please keep reporting things that look like phishing. Except from DOGE … but probably even then. And this is totally fine and normal.’” —Contractor for the Veterans Administration&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the emails was the now infamous “Fork in the Road,” encouraging workers to be loyal or quit. It closely tracked the language of an email sent to Twitter employees not long after Musk’s takeover of that company. A subsequent follow-up was even more insulting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It was truly so idiotic and looked like it was written by a disturbed child.” —CDC employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We’re used to every little thing done by regulation, and now we’re just getting crazy emails … This is a 5-alarm fire. This is a constitutional crisis.” —Department of Labor employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“That response shocked me. We knew that this administration had little regard for professionals who choose to work for the federal government, but to state it so publicly, dripping with contempt, was truly unbelievable to me.” —GSA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Federal employees who remained were forced back to the office. Many found their workplaces increasingly hostile.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“A woman I did not know in the cubicle next to me broke down. She was literally wailing, inconsolable, because she could not get into a childcare facility she could afford on such short notice. She literally had to choose between her little child and working. Her explaining to her manager the way her child cried and begged Mommy to stay home broke me. Then, as if on cue, an email from a person whose account said they were the acting IRS commissioner arrived in our inboxes, reminding us that it was “Mental Health Awareness” month and that we can do such helpful things as “practicing gratitude” and breathing techniques to deal with stress. It also reminded us we can take time off to seek professional help … I never saw her again, and her cube is now empty.” —Internal Revenue Service employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Because we are part of Homeland Security, there’s always an armed guard at FEMA facilities. That’s a very standard thing. But the guys we’re used to seeing are like the contracted-out, office patrol guys—they’re mall cops, to be polite about it. They sit at the desk and make sure you have ID, and that’s the extent of their policing. We have a pretty good relationship with our local guy at the front desk of our building. He’s a nice guy; he’ll walk around our office sometimes. We share our snacks with him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“One day he comes in to walk the office, like he does occasionally, and a few minutes after he passes by, another officer walks through. This time, it’s somebody we’ve never seen before, and he’s like, kitted out. He’s dressed in all black from head to toe; he’s got body armor on. He’s wearing a tactical helmet. He’s got a big gun on him, like a rifle, not like a handgun in a side pouch. He did not have a visible name tag, which is not standard at all—everybody in a federal facility is required to identify themselves at all times, and he had no individual identifying markings. The only writing on his uniform was the big yellow text on his back that said HOMELAND SECURITY.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“He was walking through the office as slowly as he could. He would pause behind you and watch what you were doing for five to 20 seconds and then move on. His entire demeanor, it was very obvious he wanted us to see him, and he wanted to see us watching him. These are fucking office workers working on laptops. We’re doing spreadsheets and PowerPoints. Like, chill out, dude.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“My coworker went over [to the guard] and was like ‘Hey, welcome, can I help you with something, are we in danger? What’s the problem? The officer announces—not just to my coworker but to as many people as can hear him—‘No, I don’t want your help. I’m just here to patrol you and to desensitize you to my presence.’ Then he just keeps on walking. That’s the only thing he’s said to us. He’s been through a couple times now and never gives anyone the time of day—never smiles, never says good morning, just walks through, dresses us all down for a few minutes, and leaves.” —FEMA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The offices were also quite literally gross—because DOGE had put a $1 spending limit on most government credit cards and didn’t make exceptions for basic necessities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The women’s restroom was out of toilet paper within a week or so of us coming back to the office. I brought this up to Facilities, like, ‘Hey, this is kind of a sanitation and dignity issue, can you hook us up with more toilet paper?’ They were like, ‘We’d love to, but we can’t purchase anything until they unfreeze the cards, and we don’t even know what the process is, because they have them sort of indefinitely frozen.’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“For five months we were instructed to bring in our own toilet paper. I literally kept two rolls at my desk. I wish I were joking.” —FEMA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Musk and Trump were eagerly filling government agencies with their allies. At the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD), Trump installed Scott Turner, a former NFL cornerback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“[Turner] has two primary sources of anecdotes I keep hearing: his time in the NFL—specifically that he was drafted in the last round—and his father’s time working as a shelf stocker at Safeway and how he is doing the same thing at HUD by ‘taking inventory and restocking the shelves.’ For a motivational speaker and pastor he is neither motivational nor inspirational.” —HUD employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Immigration was a major pillar of the second Trump administration. While the government made crystal clear it did not want foreigners in the country, it carved out an exception for a minority group of white South Africans in an executive order in February—a topic near and dear to Musk’s heart, as a white immigrant from South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This administration has made a complete mockery of the humanitarian side of immigration. I have interviewed parents who saw their children beheaded in front of them. I have interviewed children who saw their parents killed in front of them. I have interviewed women who have been sexually assaulted. I have interviewed children who have been sexually assaulted. I have interviewed teenagers who were beaten and threatened by their own family because they were part of the LGBTQI+ community. What has happened to these people in South Africa that warrants refugee status in the US? Nothing.” —Department of Homeland Security employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Musk said he wanted to downsize the federal workforce. What was the right size, exactly? As lean as possible. Entire agencies were gutted as tens of thousands of federal employees were subjected to reductions in force, or RIFs. Some of these actions have been challenged in court, but the Supreme Court recently ruled that the Trump administration could continue its proposals to potentially lay off federal workers en masse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The moment everything crystallized for me was the day they came for a respected career deputy. Someone who embodied integrity and competence. His ‘crime’? Having the guts to challenge DOGE’s reckless RIF plans. One afternoon, he returned from lunch to find security waiting at his desk. No explanation, no warning—just a quiet escort out of the building while stunned colleagues looked on. Years of dedicated service reduced to a public humiliation.” —Department of Labor employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I knew what the powers that be were doing wasn't legal. So either they were incompetent and didn't know it was illegal, or they knew it was illegal and didn’t care. Which one is scarier?” —CDC employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What stands out to me is how disorganized and unprofessional the GSA reduction in force was. Staff were instructed to return government IDs ASAP. We lost Google Drive access immediately, and the agency put resources about our RIF on there. We were blocked from sending emails to non-GSA addresses. Even trying to email career documents to your private email address became a huge issue.” —GSA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“When the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau was first gutted, one person left their blazer in the office and was unable to get back into the building to get it. It was the only blazer they owned: They were broke, applying for jobs, and had nothing to wear to interviews because of this.” —CFPB employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On February 14, tens of thousands of federal workers lost their jobs in an event that would become known to those impacted as the Valentine’s Day Massacre. Other workers were told they were going to receive firing letters imminently—only to wait days with no news.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“My fiancée and I had just come back from dinner. We’re getting ready to go to bed. I decide I’m just going to disconnect from social media and my email. I’m just going to turn it off … I saw I had an unread message. I was fired at 11, 11:30 pm. [My fiancée] looks at me, and she sees my demeanor change. [She says,] ‘That was the email, wasn't it?’” —Fired Federal Aviation Administration aeronautical information specialist&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It was Valentine’s Day, and my partner planned a romantic dinner for us that I ate in a catatonic state, in my sweatpants, covered in tears.” —CDC employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On February 22, in another echo of his Twitter takeover, Musk warned that the entire federal workforce needed to write an email explaining what they’d gotten done the previous week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It was so humiliating to have to prove, ostensibly to Elon Musk—someone not in my chain of command or even a government employee—what I was doing. Not only is it none of their business what I was up to (they are not my supervisor), but they wouldn’t even understand anything I put in there anyway since it’s far too technical. I put read receipts on my first submission, and after I hadn’t gotten pinged that it had been read after two subsequent submissions, I just stopped sending them. It made me so mad that not only are they passive-aggressively insinuating I’m doing nothing, but they’re wasting tons of federal workers’ time (and taxpayer money) doing this exercise, and they aren’t even opening the emails. Infuriating.” —Department of Defense employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“[Employees were responding with] emails in different languages … responding with the Constitution, and (for someone coming right back from maternity leave) responding with things such as: ‘breastfed a newborn for X number of hours, changed Y number of diapers with Z throughput, managed stakeholder input from my in-laws on best ways to burp a child.’” —VA IT worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I actually laughed pretty hard [at Musk’s email]. It’s just so ridiculous … It’s either [that or] be mad 24/7 (which some of my compatriots have decided to do), and I just don’t have the energy anymore.” —FAA air traffic controller&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On March 14, 2025, Colin O’Brien, then the head of security for the United States Institute of Peace, learned that the agency’s board had purportedly been fired. DOGE associates, including one named Nate Cavanaugh, arrived at USIP headquarters in Washington, DC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The on-duty security lieutenant called me and said, ‘Hey, DOGE is here.’ The instructions we had given were that any visit by DOGE that was unscheduled, they were not to be permitted entry. If they had a scheduled appointment, absolutely, we’d have let them in. They stayed outside for a little bit less than 30 minutes and then left.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later, O’Brien got another call from the front security desk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“They're like, ‘Hey, the FBI is here with DOGE.’ So we step outside. It was two FBI agents to our right and then four DOGE people to the left, sort of standing in a semicircle. They're dressed like college kids—sneakers and jeans that are too tight—certainly not business attire.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Our attorney asked the FBI: Why are you guys here? Do you have a court order, a warrant, anything? And they said no, and they said, ‘We're here to facilitate a cordial conversation.’ They looked embarrassed to be there, being just very honest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The conversation lasts maybe five minutes, then the DOGE people leave with the FBI agents. I didn’t realize at the time that one of the women in the DOGE SUV had run around to the side of the building and was trying to convince one of the guards to let her in through a side door, claiming at first that it was cold and she had to go to the bathroom. Then that changed, when she was told no, to: ‘I have every right to be in a government building.’ So on one hand you have the intimidation factor of federal agents plus DOGE at your front door. And then you have this juvenile covert attempt in the back door. If she’d gotten in the door she would’ve probably called 911 and claimed false imprisonment or something.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DOGE ultimately got into the building (estimated value: $500 million; DOGE attempted to gift GSA the space but was blocked by a federal judge) and fired nearly every employee. On March 28, as staff were receiving termination notices—and finding out their health care would be cut the same day—one of O’Brien’s colleagues spied a salad in the office refrigerator with the name “Nate C” on it and promptly threw it in the trash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, DOGE was entering more agencies for the first time. Departments that rarely faced political strain, such as those that support arts and culture programs, were put under a microscope. Others, like the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, were put on ice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“No one has ever been against museums and libraries before. It seems like a really nonpolitical issue, and here we are facing a hostile takeover in real time … We were put on leave on March 31. By April 3, we were already starting to hear about grants being terminated. They were done through email, very generically, not through the official recordkeeping system, saying that they no longer met the priorities of the agencies. We initially heard about it from grantees. They were posting things publicly. On LinkedIn. On social media.” —Institute of Museum and Library Services employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“People’s livelihoods were gone, wiped out and thoroughly decimated. So many of these grantees work their entire lives to see a project, book, or exhibit come to fruition. These dreams came to a crashing and fiery end in the single hit of a button by someone who likely would never understand the true devastating impact.” —National Endowment for the Humanities employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I like to think of it as I am being slightly defiant. I’ll say, ‘Although I was hired to do [certain duties] under the law, I have not been permitted to do work, so my accomplishments are limited to submitting a timesheet.’” —CFPB employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After an initial flurry of lawsuits related to DOGE access to sensitive networks, the president decided to unilaterally declare on March 20 that they could go, essentially, wherever they wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Learning about that was like getting punched in the stomach. It goes against everything our agency stands for, our mission. I have personally encouraged immigrant parents to file for benefits for their American children because those children needed it, and have promised all of them that they were safe and that we didn’t share their information, and they trusted me. And now this administration has made a liar out of me.” —Social Security Administration employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At some agencies, that access extended to taking control of official social media accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I had to turn over access to our website and social media accounts. Ethan Shaotran asked me to turn over the login info to the website, to Facebook, Instagram, and X. I gave the passwords and usernames for those accounts. He came back later and asked for the address to log in to the WordPress account. I tried to just give the exact information they asked for because I wanted to passively resist. That’s why DOGE didn’t get access to our LinkedIn—they didn’t ask for it. The public considers these guys to be tech geniuses, but I’d say WordPress is pretty intuitive. It took them two days to take the website down.” —Federal worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In March, the Social Security Administration readied a plan ostensibly to combat identity theft. Under the plan, beneficiaries would not be able to verify their identity on the phone as they had in the past. Instead they’d have to use an online portal or show up in person. (About a week later, the SSA relented and began allowing the phone again.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Some elderly beneficiaries were crying on the phone, terrified that they would lose their benefits if they couldn’t figure out how to travel to an office and show us their ID. One woman was in her nineties. Another elderly couple showed up at an SSA office to prove they were alive, but it was never clear that this was necessary—no policy guidance had been issued.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We were told to be patient and wait until guidance could be provided. At one point, we were told that we would receive instructions a week AFTER the policy implementation day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In the end, the administration discovered that there wasn’t a problem with fraud in our teleclaims, something that frontline staff could’ve told them from the beginning. Less than 1 percent of claims were even flagged for further investigation. If our leaders would take the time to learn how to read the records, they might know this too.” —SSA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The concern for security apparently did not extend to DOGE affiliates themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In April, I happened to come across a partial list of employees and contractors who had not completed some of their mandatory security training. I wasn't surprised to see that DOGE-affiliated names made up more than a quarter of the list. It included [Technology Transformation Services director] Thomas Shedd, [Federal Acquisition Service head] Josh Gruenbaum, Ed Coristine, Luke Farritor, and Steven Davis. —Current GSA IT contractor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At AmeriCorps, DOGE called home thousands of young volunteers working on infrastructure projects or disaster relief around the country. It was chaos—a kind of chaos repeated across many agencies as spring wore on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“DOGE arrived at our agency in early April. About a week later, on Tuesday, they shut down the National Civilian Community Corps. They wanted to bring all the members home. Members were in the literal field though, like they were in forests and on trails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The next day, 85 percent of us were placed on administrative leave. They had people booking flights for members to get home, and their computers were cut off while they were booking. It was chaos. People were just disappearing. On April 24, people started receiving RIF notices, except a bunch of them were addressed to the wrong person.” —Current AmeriCorp employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By June, Musk appeared to officially leave DOGE. With him went some key lieutenants: Steve Davis, Musk’s right-hand man during the Twitter takeover and DOGE’s de facto leader; Nicole Hollander, Davis’ partner, who played a key role at the GSA; and Katie Miller, communications lead for DOGE and the wife of White House deputy chief of staff for policy Stephen Miller. Musk’s send-off had included a friendly press conference with Trump, but that fragile peace was shattered a few days later, when Musk went to war with Trump on X. It seemed like Musk’s ouster from government—and breakup with the president—was complete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“For all the talk that Trump likes teams of rivals, he doesn’t respect people who are nasty, interpersonally … I thought the cabinet secretary fights would be the end. The president was not going to tolerate him going after his cabinet secretaries, publicly or privately … The president just didn’t want that. He’s not going to tolerate that negativity. He likes all these people. These are his people. Marco’s a decade-old friend, at least, and a former competitor [with whom] he has a special comradery who he almost picked as his vice president. Peter Navarro went to jail for the guy. Took a federal charge, was found guilty, and ate it. Scott Bessent is his treasury secretary. Stuff like that was not gonna fly for very long.” —Senior Trump official&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The era of Musk’s DOGE, the flashy, so-called agency that garnered Fox News specials and had orchestrated the biggest upheaval the modern US government has ever faced, appeared to be over. But the next phase was just beginning, with DOGE’s operatives and its ethos occupying every corner of government. And the toll on federal employees still hasn't stopped.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We are in purgatory—not having enough resources to do our jobs and not knowing what the vision is for the agency moving forward. Leadership by utter neglect.” —GSA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I am a clinical psychologist with plenty of lifetime trauma myself, but I had never actually attended therapy or seen a psychiatrist until after the inauguration. I was so upset when I first spoke to the telehealth psychiatrist that I couldn't even speak and almost had to hang up. They said that I was not the first federal employee that they'd talked to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This was the trauma that they wanted, that they planned, that they promised us. And, for once, they did a great job of delivering.” —CDC employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I’m terrified for our country and what all this means for the future. I need medication to help regulate me, because [Trump is] not going away anytime soon. And since I'm in HR, I can't get away from it. I live and breathe this during all my awake hours. If I'm not at work fielding questions from terrified employees or working with another team to terminate tons of people, family and friends are calling to see if I have any inside scoop or to check on the status of my own job.” —Federal HR employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I’m the type of person where, like, if you push me I’ll push back. I don’t like to live in a mindset of despair and negativity. When these people do this shit, it just lights my fire. It makes me more fucking mad. This used to be the best job I’ve ever had, the best environment I’ve ever had, the best culture I’ve ever had—and they fucking ruined it. I will never ever forget how much they ruined it. I’m like, fuck these people. They can’t get me scared. I will not give them what they want. I will not just leave. I’m going to make it as difficult as possible for these fuckheads.” —FEMA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let us know what you think about this article. Submit a letter to the editor at mail@wired.com.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45373102</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:36:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ChatControl: EU wants to scan all private messages, even in encrypted apps</title><link>https://metalhearf.fr/posts/chatcontrol-wants-your-private-messages/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b516b17038a1bfe5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Introduction #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 🇪🇺 European Union is advancing legislation that could fundamentally change how we communicate online. ChatControl would require all messaging platforms to automatically scan their users’ private messages and images.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes, even encrypted ones like Signal, WhatsApp and Telegram. No, you can’t opt out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t just another privacy policy update you can ignore. If passed, this EU regulation (strongest and most binding legal instrument in EU law) would automatically apply to all member states without any wiggle room for national interpretation. It would even override constitutional protections for communication privacy and establish unprecedented mass surveillance of private communications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The official justification? Fighting child sexual abuse material (CSAM). Protecting children is undeniably crucial, but the proposed methods would eliminate digital privacy for 450 million Europeans and set a global precedent for mass surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This surveillance trend extends beyond Europe: 🇨🇭 Switzerland is advancing metadata retention requirements, the 🇬🇧 UK is implementing comprehensive age verification systems and now the 🇪🇺 EU proposes to scan every private message. Each initiative is positioned as child protection policy, but the implications reach far beyond their stated goals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What is ChatControl #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChatControl is what critics call the EU’s proposed Regulation to Prevent and Combat Child Sexual Abuse, also known as CSAR (Child Sexual Abuse Regulation).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proposal builds on surveillance techniques already deployed by major tech companies. Meta analyzes all Facebook Messenger conversations and unencrypted WhatsApp data (profile photos, group descriptions). Apple announced similar scanning for iCloud content in 2021, though they later suspended the program.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This turns voluntary corporate surveillance into mandatory government-ordered scanning. A temporary 2021 EU regulation allowed platforms to scan content voluntarily for three years. That authorization expired in 2024, which is why CSAR was proposed. The temporary regulation merely permitted scanning; CSAR would make detection obligatory under certain conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s also the Roadmap for Lawful Access to Data which has an even bigger goal: making all our digital data readable by authorities upon request. We’ll dive deeper into this broader surveillance agenda later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Scope and Coverage #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CSAR casts an extremely wide net. The regulation would apply to all interpersonal communication service providers, not just obvious targets like Signal, WhatsApp, or Telegram, but also:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Email providers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dating apps&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gaming platforms with chat features&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Social media platforms&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File hosting services (Google Drive, iCloud, DropBox…)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;App stores&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Even small community hosting services run by associations&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means virtually any digital service that allows people to communicate or share content would fall under surveillance requirements. The scope extends far beyond what most people imagine when they hear messaging apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How it Works #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChatControl relies on Client-Side Scanning. Your device becomes a monitoring station that analyzes your content before encryption happens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This represents a fundamental shift away from traditional surveillance that intercepts messages during transmission. With ChatControl, every message gets automatically checked, assuming everyone is guilty until proven innocent and effectively reversing the presumption of innocence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Technical Implementation #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The system would automatically scan for three categories of content before encryption:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Known illegal content: Images or videos already catalogued by authorities as CSAM. Your device creates hash fingerprints of your content and compares them against databases of known illegal material.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Unknown potential content: Photos or videos that might constitute CSAM but haven’t been previously identified. AI algorithms analyze visual elements (like exposed skin) to flag potentially problematic content based on statistical models.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Grooming behavior: Text analysis using AI to identify communication patterns that match predefined indicators of adults soliciting children. This involves scanning the actual content of your private conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If something gets flagged, it automatically gets reported to authorities. No human checks it first, that would be impossible given the billions of daily messages. This would be mandatory for all messaging platforms in 🇪🇺 Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why This Breaks Encryption #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChatControl doesn’t break encryption, it bypasses it entirely. While your messages still get encrypted during transmission, the system defeats the purpose of end-to-end encryption by examining your content before it gets encrypted. True E2EE means only you and your recipient can read messages: no government, no company, no algorithm should peek inside. This surveillance violates that principle by inserting monitoring at the source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Privacy-focused companies like Proton point out this approach might be worse than encryption backdoors. Backdoors give authorities access to communications you share with others. This system examines everything on your device, whether you share it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your encrypted messaging app becomes spyware. Supporters claim this protects privacy because scanning happens locally, but surveillance built into your device makes it impossible to escape.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Governance Structure #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proposal would create a centralized EU Centre on Child Sexual Abuse to receive all reports, but EU institutions wouldn’t control the scanning technology itself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Service providers would face additional obligations beyond scanning. They would need to conduct risk assessments to evaluate and minimize the potential for illegal content sharing on their platforms. This requires collecting detailed information about their users (age groups, content types) that many privacy-focused services deliberately avoid gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The regulation also pushes for mandatory age verification systems. No viable, privacy-respecting age verification technology currently exists. These systems would eliminate online anonymity, requiring users to prove their identity to access digital services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Real-World Impact #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Encryption Concerns #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChatControl fits into a broader political strategy. Since the 1990s crypto wars, certain states have argued that privacy-protecting technologies, especially encryption, obstruct police investigations. These technologies are designed to do exactly that, protect everyone’s ability to control their expression and communication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The European Commission’s Roadmap for Lawful Access to Data wants to make all digital data accessible to authorities by 2030. This involves systematically weakening encryption rather than simply bypassing it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edward Snowden’s revelations ten years ago led to widespread adoption of encryption and institutional consensus supporting the right to encrypted communication. But governments remain frustrated by their inability to access private communications. We’re seeing a return to authoritarian positions using terrorism, organized crime and child exploitation as justifications for undermining encryption.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;🇩🇰 Danish Minister of Justice Peter Hummelgaard, chief architect of the current ChatControl proposal, recently stated: “We must break with the totally erroneous perception that it is everyone’s civil liberty to communicate on encrypted messaging services.” Well, there you have it folks: encrypted communication isn’t a civil liberty anymore. You cypherpunks were wrong all along. /s&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly in 🇫🇷 France, both Bernard Cazeneuve and Emmanuel Macron have explicitly stated their desire to control encrypted messaging, seeking to pierce the privacy of millions who use these services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CSAR provides the perfect opportunity for member states to finally design and implement a generalized surveillance tool for monitoring population communications. Crossing this threshold means eliminating all confidentiality from communications using digital infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;False Positives #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These scanning systems get it wrong most of the time. Studies show approximately 80% of algorithmic reports are false positives: innocent content incorrectly flagged as illegal. 🇮🇪 Irish law enforcement confirms this: only 20.3% of 4,192 automated reports actually contained illegal material.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even with hypothetical 99% accuracy (which current systems don’t achieve), scanning billions of daily messages would generate millions of false accusations. Police resources would be overwhelmed investigating innocent families sharing vacation photos while real crimes go uninvestigated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Innocent content regularly triggers these systems: family photos, teenage conversations, educational materials and medical communications. Consider this real case: a father was automatically reported to police after sending photos of his child’s medical condition to their doctor. Google’s algorithms flagged this legitimate medical consultation as potential abuse, permanently closed his account and refused all appeals. His digital life was destroyed by an algorithm that couldn’t distinguish between medical care and criminal activity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Scientific Opposition #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the third time in three years, over 600 cryptographers, security researchers and scientists across 35 countries have co-signed an open letter explaining why this mass scanning project is “technically unfeasible”, constitutes a “danger to democracy” and would “completely compromise” the security and privacy of all European citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The letter emphasizes that client-side scanning cannot distinguish between legal and illegal content without fundamentally breaking encryption and creating vulnerabilities that malicious actors can exploit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Commission has provided no serious studies demonstrating the effectiveness, reliability or appropriateness of these intrusive measures for actually protecting children. Industry claims appear to have taken precedence over evidence-based policy-making.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Genuine security emerges through thoughtful design where security measures and civil liberties function as complementary forces, not opposing ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Easily Defeated #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fundamental flaw in ChatControl becomes clear when examining how easily determined actors can circumvent these scanning systems. Criminals don’t need sophisticated techniques to bypass client-side scanning; they use well-documented public knowledge already employed by malicious actors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Layered Encryption&lt;lb/&gt; Encrypt files with standard tools like GPG before messaging. Hell, even a basic Caesar cipher would be sufficient to bypass detection. Since client-side scanning occurs after user encryption but before transport encryption, pre-encrypted content looks like random data to detection algorithms. Recipients decrypt locally with shared keys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;External Platform Bypass&lt;lb/&gt; Upload content to any third-party platform (Dropbox, OneDrive, anonymous file hosts, or obscure hosting services) and share links instead of files. The scanner sees innocent text containing a URL while the actual content sits untouched on external servers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Custom Messaging Clients&lt;lb/&gt; Open-source protocols like XMPP and Matrix allow custom client development. Modified clients can automatically implement cloud storage and encryption workflows transparently. Users experience normal messaging while completely evading surveillance infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Digital Steganography&lt;lb/&gt; Steganographic techniques embed data within innocent images. Family photos can carry hidden payloads invisible to both human operators and AI systems. Tools like OpenStego make this accessible to average users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Platform Migration&lt;lb/&gt; Criminal networks can shift to decentralized platforms, peer-to-peer networks or services outside EU jurisdiction. Tor-based messaging, blockchain communications or servers in non-compliant countries remain beyond ChatControl’s reach.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChatControl catches only amateur criminals who directly attach problematic content to messages. Professional networks already employ these evasion techniques as standard practice. EU legislation won’t make them forget how computers work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The system fails at protecting children while succeeding at mass civilian monitoring. It’s not a bug, it’s a feature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Business Interests #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Industry Players #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The child protection narrative masks concerning business interests. The European Commission based its CSAR proposal primarily on claims from industry players rather than independent research.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commercial surveillance companies would manage the technology with guaranteed access to the European market. Organizations like Thorn (co-founded by actor Ashton Kutcher), Microsoft’s PhotoDNA and other tech companies develop these detection systems while simultaneously lobbying for regulations that would require their adoption across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These companies develop the detection technologies and lobby for laws mandating their adoption, creating a profitable feedback loop. The proposal would secure privileged market positions for surveillance companies across hundreds of millions of European users. Pretty nice, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These systems would be:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Proprietary: Built on closed-source code with methods hidden from public view&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unverifiable: Operating without meaningful external examination or accountability&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Legally powerful: Capable of starting criminal proceedings through algorithmic decisions&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Rhetorical Tactics #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commissioner Ylva Johansson consistently emphasizes this narrative in her communications:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“[Privacy defenders make a lot of noise], but someone has to speak for the children.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Think of the children” is a well-documented political rhetoric technique that appeals to emotion rather than evidence. While child protection is genuinely important, this approach frames any opposition as being against child welfare, making nuanced discussion more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This creates a false choice. Privacy isn’t a luxury for troublemakers, it’s a fundamental right that protects journalists, whistleblowers, activists and ordinary people from unwarranted intrusion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Critics aren’t opposing child protection. We’re questioning whether undermining privacy rights for 450 million 🇪🇺 Europeans is the most effective approach when targeted alternatives exist that preserve rights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;EU Country Positions #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understanding how 🇪🇺 EU member states position themselves on this legislation is crucial, as their votes will determine whether ChatControl becomes reality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Vote Breakdown #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Countries that support ChatControl (12): 🇧🇬 Bulgaria • 🇭🇷 Croatia • 🇨🇾 Cyprus • 🇩🇰 Denmark • 🇫🇷 France • 🇭🇺 Hungary • 🇮🇪 Ireland • 🇱🇹 Lithuania • 🇲🇹 Malta • 🇵🇹 Portugal • 🇷🇴 Romania • 🇪🇸 Spain&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Countries that oppose ChatControl (7): 🇦🇹 Austria • 🇨🇿 Czech Republic • 🇪🇪 Estonia • 🇫🇮 Finland • 🇱🇺 Luxembourg • 🇳🇱 Netherlands • 🇵🇱 Poland&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Countries still undecided (8): 🇧🇪 Belgium • 🇩🇪 Germany • 🇬🇷 Greece • 🇮🇹 Italy • 🇱🇻 Latvia • 🇸🇰 Slovakia • 🇸🇮 Slovenia • 🇸🇪 Sweden&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;National Stances #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;💪 Strong opposition (the good guys) (click to expand)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;🇦🇹 Austria: Constitutional and privacy concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;🇨🇿 Czech Republic: Prime Minister explicitly rejects proposals that would allow widespread monitoring of citizens’ private digital communications.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;🇪🇪 Estonia: Acknowledges sincere concerns about child exploitation, but opposes undermining end-to-end encryption and forcing mass surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;🇫🇮 Finland: Cannot support the latest compromise proposal because it contains a constitutionally problematic identification order.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;🇱🇺 Luxembourg: Rejects broad surveillance measures like client-side scanning and insists that EU regulation must ensure proportional, targeted detection to protect citizens’ fundamental rights.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;🇳🇱 Netherlands: Strong privacy protection stance.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;🇵🇱 Poland: Opposition to mass surveillance measures.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;🤷 Undecided positions (click to expand)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🇧🇪 Belgium: The N-VA party calls ChatControl a “monster that invades your privacy and cannot be tamed”. Despite this, Belgium backed Denmark’s compromise during September meetings. Mixed signals from Brussels.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🇩🇪 Germany: Won’t break encryption but wants to find middle ground. They’re trying to craft their own compromise instead of rejecting ChatControl outright. Germany’s fence-sitting could be decisive.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🇬🇷 Greece: Still figuring out the technical details. No clear stance yet.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🇮🇹 Italy: Has concerns about expanding the scope to cover new CSAM detection. Rome seems hesitant about how far this thing could reach.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🇱🇻 Latvia: The government likes what they see on paper but worries about political backlash after summer attention. Classic politicians hedging their bets.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🇸🇰 Slovakia: Playing the wait-and-see game. No commitment either way.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🇸🇮 Slovenia: Dealing with constitutional headaches around privacy. Another country wrestling with legal implications.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🇸🇪 Sweden: Stockholm is still reading the fine print. Taking their time to decide.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Current Status #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Current situation: Country positions continue shifting regularly since September 12. With 12 countries supporting, 7 opposing, and 8 undecided, ChatControl supporters still fall short of the 65% EU population threshold needed for a qualified majority. The opposition maintains enough demographic weight to block the proposal for now, but the situation remains fluid as the interim regulation approaches expiration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;📅 Timeline of Events (click to expand)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ChatControl Proposal Introduced&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;May 11, 2022&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;European Commission&lt;/head&gt;The European Commission unveils the original ChatControl proposal, requiring all email and messaging providers to scan communications for child sexual abuse material.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Danish Presidency Takes Charge&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Jul 1, 2025&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;EU Council Presidency&lt;/head&gt;🇩🇰 Denmark assumes the EU Council Presidency and immediately reintroduces ChatControl as a top legislative priority, targeting October 14, 2025 for adoption.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Support Momentum Builds&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Jul 28, 2025&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;15 Member States&lt;/head&gt;Fifteen EU member states back the ChatControl proposal, reversing earlier resistance. 🇫🇷 France has shifted its position and now supports the proposal. 🇩🇪 Germany remains the crucial undecided vote.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Opposition Wave Begins&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Aug 26, 2025&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Czech Republic&lt;/head&gt;🇨🇿 Czech Prime Minister Petr Fiala announces total opposition on behalf of the entire coalition government.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Constitutional Concerns&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Aug 29, 2025&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Finland&lt;/head&gt;🇫🇮 Finland rejects the compromise proposal due to constitutionally problematic detection requirements.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Blocking Minority Secured&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Sep 10, 2025&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Germany, Luxembourg, Slovakia&lt;/head&gt;🇩🇪 Germany, 🇱🇺 Luxembourg, and 🇸🇰 Slovakia officially oppose breaking encryption. This creates the blocking minority needed to stop the proposal.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Estonia Joins Opposition&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Sep 14, 2025&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Privacy Protection&lt;/head&gt;🇪🇪 Estonia acknowledges child exploitation concerns but opposes undermining end-to-end encryption and mass surveillance.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Germany Wavers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Sep 16, 2025&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Position Unclear&lt;/head&gt;🇩🇪 Germany refrains from taking a definitive stance during the LEWP meeting, despite previous encryption concerns. Position becomes uncertain.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Three Countries Flip&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Sep 23, 2025&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Belgium, Latvia, Italy&lt;/head&gt;🇧🇪 Belgium, 🇱🇻 Latvia, and 🇮🇹 Italy have moved away from supporting the proposal and are now undecided. Country positions continue changing regularly since September 12.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Consequences #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The effects of these proposals go beyond individual privacy concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cybersecurity gets compromised&lt;lb/&gt; Adding deliberate vulnerabilities to encryption creates weaknesses that everyone can exploit. Any backdoor for authorized access becomes a potential entry point for criminals and foreign intelligence services. In February 2024, the 🇪🇺 European Court of Human Rights already determined that mandating weakened encryption “cannot be regarded as necessary in a democratic society”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Innovation suffers&lt;lb/&gt; 🇪🇺 European cybersecurity companies would face an impossible situation in global markets. How could they credibly sell security solutions when regulations require them to build in access mechanisms that undermine those very protections?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Buy our ultra-secure encrypted stuff!” (Terms and conditions apply, government backdoors included)."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tech companies will leave Europe&lt;lb/&gt; Privacy-focused services that moved to 🇪🇺 Europe after the Snowden revelations are already signaling they might leave. Signal has explicitly said it would stop operating in 🇪🇺 Europe rather than compromise its security.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even 🇨🇭 Switzerland, traditionally seen as a privacy haven, is facing severe legislative pressures that are forcing tech companies to relocate. Proton has confirmed it has begun moving some of its physical infrastructure out of Switzerland due to “legal uncertainty” over the proposed surveillance law amendments. Lumo, their AI chatbot, became the first product to relocate, moving to Germany instead of Switzerland specifically because of these legislative concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Swiss OSCPT (Ordinance on the Surveillance of Correspondence by Post and Telecommunications) revision would require VPNs and messaging apps to identify users and retain data for up to six months, plus decrypt communications upon authority request. As Proton’s CEO Andy Yen explained, these are proposals that “have been outlawed in the EU” but could soon become reality in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other privacy-focused providers like Tuta have expressed similar concerns and contingency plans to leave 🇨🇭 Switzerland if the surveillance laws pass.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Europe might become dependent on US surveillance&lt;lb/&gt; I’m not so sure on this one, but by outsourcing surveillance technology to American companies, 🇪🇺 Europe may create dangerous dependencies. These companies operate under 🇺🇸 US jurisdiction and the CLOUD Act, potentially allowing 🇺🇸 Washington to access data collected on 🇪🇺 European citizens. Under the pretense of child protection, the 🇪🇺 EU risks handing surveillance keys to foreign powers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social behavior changes&lt;lb/&gt; When people know they’re being watched, they change how they communicate. People start self-censoring, avoiding certain topics and carefully choosing their words even in private conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is called the chilling effect. Rights don’t disappear overnight: they erode gradually as people change their behavior to avoid potential problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Take Action #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s how you can contribute to defending our digital freedoms:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Share this article and educate your network: Use hashtags like &lt;code&gt;#ChatControl&lt;/code&gt;or&lt;code&gt;#StopScanningMe&lt;/code&gt;. Forward resources to friends, family and colleagues.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sign the petition: against ChatControl at change.org.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Stay informed and follow updates: @[email protected], x.com/nonchatcontrol, patrick-breyer.de and fightchatcontrol.eu.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Contact your national representatives to convince your country to oppose ChatControl, if it’s not already the case.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Join campaigns and support organizations: stopscanningme.eu for local actions, EFF and EDRi for digital rights advocacy.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Adopt privacy tools and infrastructure: Use Signal and other privacy-respecting alternatives. Host your own services or support privacy-focused providers.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The irony is kinda painful: the continent that built GDPR to protect digital privacy now designs ChatControl to dismantle it systematically. What was once a fundamental right could become mandatory surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChatControl represents a historic choice for 🇪🇺 Europe. Either we become the first democracy to normalize mass surveillance of private communications or we defend the digital rights that made Europe a global privacy leader.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This decision deserves close attention: authoritarian regimes worldwide are watching, ready to justify their own programs with: “Eh, if Europe does it, why shouldn’t we?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The next chapter unfolds on October 14, 2025. 😉&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45374500</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 16:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ChatGPT Pulse</title><link>https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-pulse/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9a26a651bae7d2f3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Introducing ChatGPT Pulse&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now ChatGPT can start the conversation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're building ChatGPT to help you reach your goals. Since ChatGPT launched, that's always meant coming to ask a question. There's magic in being able to simply ask and get answers to help you learn, create or solve problems. However that's limited by what you know to ask for and always puts the burden on you for the next step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today we're releasing a preview of ChatGPT Pulse to Pro users on mobile. Pulse is a new experience where ChatGPT proactively does research to deliver personalized updates based on your chats, feedback, and connected apps like your calendar. You can curate what ChatGPT researches by letting it know what’s useful and what isn’t. The research appears in Pulse as topical visual cards you can scan quickly or open for more detail, so each day starts with a new, focused set of updates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the first step toward a more useful ChatGPT that proactively brings you what you need, helping you make more progress so you can get back to your life. We’ll learn and improve from early use before rolling it out to Plus, with the goal of making it available to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ChatGPT can now do asynchronous research on your behalf. Each night, it synthesizes information from your memory, chat history, and direct feedback to learn what’s most relevant to you, then delivers personalized, focused updates the next day. These could look like follow-ups on topics you discuss often, ideas for quick, healthy dinner to make at home that evening, or next steps toward a longer-term goal such as training for a triathlon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also connect Gmail and Google Calendar to provide additional context for more relevant suggestions. When Calendar is connected, ChatGPT might draft a sample meeting agenda, remind you to buy a birthday gift, or surface restaurant recommendations for an upcoming trip. These integrations are off by default and can be turned on or off anytime in settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Topics shown in Pulse also pass through safety checks to avoid showing harmful content that violates our policies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can ask for what you’d like ChatGPT to research for you each day. Tap "curate" to request what you want to see in future editions—ask for a Friday roundup of local events, tips for learning a new skill, or something specific like "focus on professional tennis updates tomorrow." You can also give quick feedback with a thumbs up or thumbs down, and easily view or delete your feedback history. Over time, your guidance makes Pulse more personal and useful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every morning, ChatGPT delivers a curated set of the most relevant updates, giving you the information you need so you can get back to what matters most. Each update is available for that day only unless you save it as a chat or ask a follow-up question, which adds it to your conversation history. Expand any update to dive deeper, request next steps, or save it for later so you can move forward on goals with clear, timely information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We partnered with college students in the ChatGPT Lab to gather early feedback and improve Pulse. One insight in particular we had was that many started to feel its utility once they started telling ChatGPT what they wanted to see. That insight underscored the importance of simple feedback, so we added more ways to share reactions and guide what appears. Here are a few of the students’ favorite personalized updates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Student use cases&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Actionable recommendations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Received this based on a conversation that I had yesterday that focused on calendar management/structuring PTO for my grant period in Taiwan. What it produced was several logical steps ahead of where I was at in the conversation. The update was incredibly helpful and exposed me to train and commute information I would have never come across or looked for otherwise."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pulse is a preview and won’t always get things right. It aims to show you what’s most relevant and useful but you may still see suggestions that miss the mark. For example, you may get tips for a project you already completed. You can guide what shows up by telling ChatGPT directly. It remembers your feedback for next time and improves as it learns from real use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pulse is the first step toward a new paradigm for interacting with AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By combining conversation, memory, and connected apps, ChatGPT is moving from answering questions to a proactive assistant that works on your behalf. Over time, we envision AI systems that can research, plan, and take helpful actions for you—based on your direction—so that progress happens even when you are not asking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pulse introduces this future in its simplest form: personalized research and timely updates that appear regularly to keep you informed. Soon, Pulse will be able to connect with more of the apps you use so updates capture a more complete picture of your context. We’re also exploring ways for Pulse to deliver relevant work at the right moments throughout the day, whether it’s a quick check before a meeting, a reminder to revisit a draft, or a resource that appears right when you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we expand to more apps and richer actions, ChatGPT will evolve from something you consult into something that quietly accelerates the work and ideas that matter to you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45375477</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 16:59:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Improved Gemini 2.5 Flash and Flash-Lite</title><link>https://developers.googleblog.com/en/continuing-to-bring-you-our-latest-models-with-an-improved-gemini-2-5-flash-and-flash-lite-release/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf7738879939489d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, we are releasing updated versions of Gemini 2.5 Flash and 2.5 Flash-Lite, available on Google AI Studio and Vertex AI, aimed at continuing to deliver better quality while also improving the efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The latest version of Gemini 2.5 Flash-Lite was trained and built based on three key themes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;You can start testing this version today using the following model string: &lt;code&gt;gemini-2.5-flash-lite-preview-09-2025&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This latest 2.5 Flash model comes with improvements in two key areas we heard consistent feedback on:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re already seeing positive feedback from early testers. As Yichao ‘Peak’ Ji, Co-Founder &amp;amp; Chief Scientist at Manus, an autonomous AI agent, noted: “The new Gemini 2.5 Flash model offers a remarkable blend of speed and intelligence. Our evaluation on internal benchmarks revealed a 15% leap in performance for long-horizon agentic tasks. Its outstanding cost-efficiency enables Manus to scale to unprecedented levels—advancing our mission to Extend Human Reach.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can start testing this preview version today by using the following model string: &lt;code&gt;gemini-2.5-flash-preview-09-2025&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the last year, we’ve learned that shipping preview versions of our models allows you to test our latest improvements and innovations, provide feedback, and build production-ready experiences with the best of Gemini. Today’s releases are not intended to graduate to a new, stable version but will help us shape our future stable releases, and allow us to continue iterating and bring you the best of Gemini.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make it even easier to access our latest models while also reducing the need to keep track of long model string names, we are also introducing a &lt;code&gt;-latest&lt;/code&gt; alias for each model family. This alias always points to our most recent model versions, allowing you to experiment with new features without needing to update your code for each release. You can access the new previews using:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gemini-flash-latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;gemini-flash-lite-latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;To ensure you have time to test new models, we will always provide a 2-week notice (via email) before we make updates or deprecate a specific version behind &lt;code&gt;-latest&lt;/code&gt;. These are just model aliases so the rate limits, cost, and features available may fluctuate between releases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For applications that require more stability, continue to use &lt;code&gt;gemini-2.5-flash&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;gemini-2.5-flash-lite&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We continue to push the frontier of what is possible with Gemini and this release is just another step in that direction. We will have more to share soon, but in the meantime, happy building!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45375845</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 17:20:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Athlon 64: How AMD turned the tables on Intel</title><link>https://dfarq.homeip.net/athlon-64-how-amd-turned-the-tables-on-intel/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e70d5115fd2265ff"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;22 years ago, on September 23, 2003, AMD changed the game for x86 once and for all. They released the Athlon 64 CPU, a chip that did something Intel didn’t want. Intel didn’t want to extend x86 to 64 bits. But when AMD did it, it forced Intel to clone AMD, rather than the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why Intel didn’t want to go 64-bit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even in 2001, x86 had decades of baggage attached to it. It was a 32-bit architecture that had been extended from a 16-bit architecture. But that in turn had been extended from an 8-bit CPU design from 1972 that, believe it or not, originated at Datapoint, not Intel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was great for backward compatibility. 8-bit applications were very easy to port to x86 in the early 1980s, and those early DOS applications still ran flawlessly on modern systems 30 years later. For that matter, it’s not impossible to get them running even today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Removal of the ability to run 16-bit applications in 64-bit Windows was a design decision, not a technical limitation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intel wanted to start over to go 64-bit. Without having to worry about backward compatibility, they could design something that would be faster and more efficient. In theory at least, it would be able to scale higher in clock speed. And there was no question a new design would outperform a theoretical 64-bit x86 when running at the same speed because of efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And if you are cynical, there was one more motivation. If Intel could start over, they wouldn’t have to worry about competing CPU designs, at least not for a very long time. The new design would be encumbered with so many patents, it might be 20 years before someone could clone it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that in 2003, not only was AMD in the picture, but Transmeta was still in the picture, and Cyrix was fading but not completely gone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting over with a new CPU architecture outright was massively attractive to Intel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This new 64-bit architecture wasn’t theoretical, either. Intel was producing it. It was called Itanium, and Intel first released it in June 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;AMD’s risky bet and why they made it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AMD was well aware of the shortcomings of extending x86 to 64 bits. And they did it anyway. For them, the stakes were completely different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AMD knew that if Itanium caught on, that would be the end for them as a CPU company, unless maybe they wanted to become just another ARM licensee. Being just another ARM licensee is more attractive in 2025 than it was in 2003.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But they could see Itanium wasn’t catching on. It had its uses, and it was doing well enough in those niches, but Windows on Itanium was a non-starter. So much so, The Register called it “Itanic.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AMD bet that there would be appeal in a 64-bit architecture that was fully backward compatible with x86 and natively ran 32-bit applications at full speed. People would be able to run 32-bit Windows and 32-bit applications on it if they needed to, and then when they were ready for 64-bit software, the hardware was there and ready to go. And they could continue to run 32-bit apps in 64-bit operating systems as long as needed to ease the transition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The transition to 32 bits took a decade. AMD reasoned more people would be willing to upgrade to 64 bits if they made that transition as similar as the transition from the 286 to the 386 as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They believed the market would willingly trade lower 64-bit performance in the long term for better 32-bit performance right away. They also believed that if Microsoft was willing to build Windows on Itanium, they would be willing to take a chance on 64-bit x86 as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So on September 23, 2003, AMD launched its Athlon 64, the first 64-bit x86 CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why the Athlon 64 was a hit&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AMD64 was everything AMD hoped it would be. It was backward compatible with 32-bit x86. The 64-bit builds of Windows weren’t available immediately, and they didn’t catch on immediately, but you cannot say nobody used them. People did, in fact, use them. In late 2005, I was in charge of administering the complimentary antivirus software that Charter Communications provided to its subscribers. I’m not going to say say someone called me every day wanting 64-bit antivirus for 64-bit Windows. But it did happen once a week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The transition took at least as long as AMD expected. When I finally bought an Athlon 64 in 2011, I found native 64-bit software was still scarce. I’m an outspoken Firefox fan; the reason I briefly switched to Google Chrome was to get a 64-bit web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Athlon 64 in the enterprise&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few months later, I got a better job with more pay and better growth potential. I can’t talk a lot about the job, but I was administering a mission critical system that ran on Windows, mostly on Dell hardware. I mention Dell because they were exclusively an Intel vendor for years. Cofounder and longtime AMD CEO Jerry Sanders once said of Michael Dell, “I can’t sell him a[n AMD] K6 no matter what I do.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was the Athlon 64 that made Dell relent and finally start using AMD CPUs. Not only were they using them on desktop systems, but they were putting AMD CPUs in servers, an idea that would have been extremely controversial 5 years before. At least in the circles I ran in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Athlon 64 caught on because, in spite of its name, it was an outstanding 32-bit CPU. It was faster than an Intel CPU running at the same clock rate, and it used less power as well. The power consumption was the key to getting into the data center. The Intel name was a security blanket, even though AMD had been making x86 CPUs exactly as long as Intel. But certain decision makers bought Intel marketing and saw AMD as a second tier brand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thing is, when you have a data center with hundreds of systems in it, the money you save on a more efficient CPU really talks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Replacing Intel Prescott-based servers with AMD64 servers was not a universally popular idea. But you could tell a difference when you were standing behind a rack full of Intel-based servers versus a rack full of AMD based servers. The Intels ran hotter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From an uptime perspective, we couldn’t see a difference. The performance metrics I collected showed there was a slight difference, and that difference was in AMD’s favor. So the AMD critics quickly ate their words.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Intel giving in and cloning AMD64&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2004, Intel wrote off the Itanium and cloned AMD64. They called it Intel64, but it was a blatant copy of the AMD implementation. A quirk in the agreements that allowed AMD to use the x86 instruction set also gave Intel the rights to use the AMD64 instructions. So there was nothing illegal about what Intel did. Itanium continued to see use in specialized applications, but Intel quietly discontinued it in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AMD and Intel have been chasing and catching each other ever since. One of them will pass the other for a CPU generation or two, and then they will change positions. It’s not terribly different from the situation in 1999 with the original Athlon, when AMD outperformed Intel for the first time. The question in everyone’s mind was whether they would do it a second time. The Athlon 64 was the second time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was a big step forward. Eight years before, AMD was trying to pass off a high-clocked 486 as a Pentium equivalent. With the Athlon 64, AMD was innovating.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;David Farquhar is a computer security professional, entrepreneur, and author. He has written professionally about computers since 1991, so he was writing about retro computers when they were still new. He has been working in IT professionally since 1994 and has specialized in vulnerability management since 2013. He holds Security+ and CISSP certifications. Today he blogs five times a week, mostly about retro computers and retro gaming covering the time period from 1975 to 2000.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45376605</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 18:09:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Redox OS Development Priorities for 2025/26</title><link>https://www.redox-os.org/news/development-priorities-2025-09/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3691901340131be1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Development Priorities for 2025/26&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;By Ron Williams on&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox has made great strides over the past year, with notable improvements in stability, performance, and compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To give a big-picture perspective for where Redox development is headed, here is our view of priorities as of September, 2025. Obviously, we can’t finish everything on this list in the next 15 months, but it would be nice to have people working on as many of these things as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Redox Variants&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“Hosted Redox” as a Web Services Runtime, in a Virtual Machine&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“Redox Server” for Edge and Cloud&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;“Redox Desktop” for your daily driver&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Development Priorities&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Building Redox on Redox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compliance and Compatibility&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Programming Language and Build System Support&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Performance&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Security&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hardware Support&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;COSMIC, Wayland, and GPU Acceleration&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Accessibility&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How can you help?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some ways you can help us move Redox closer to our goals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Donating&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you would like to support Redox development, please consider donating or buying some merch! We are currently funding a community support/researcher/documentation person, a part-time build engineer, and our Redox Summer of Code program for students, all from donations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Contributing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you would like to help with Redox development or documentation, please read the CONTRIBUTING page and join us on Redox Chat. Try to connect with others who are interested in one of the major areas, create a tracking issue for the work to be done, and start checking things off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Redox is Hiring!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox is looking for an experienced kernel/core developer. Check out the job description in the July report. Please contact us if you think you are the right person.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As well, we are frequently applying for grants. We currently have three students working on grants from NGI Zero and NLnet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are a talented Rust developer interested in obtaining a grant to work on Redox, get in touch with us and we will do our best to help. You can also apply for grants for “Redox-adjacent” work on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Send an email to president@redox-os.org, cc info@redox-os.org, with a resume/CV or links to your open source work, and let us know what you are interested in doing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Redox Variants&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Hosted Redox as a Web Services Runtime, in a Virtual Machine&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the opportunities we would like to pursue is to use Redox as a hosted runtime environment for web services. The goal is to run your web services in a secure Redox environment, but to have the hardware compatibility and management tools delegated to a Linux host. We believe that this is one of the quickest paths to getting Redox into real-world use, and to help us validate it as a secure platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The set up would be something like the following.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A Linux server&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A QEMU Virtual Machine, with KVM, VirtioFS and a virtualized compute acceleration interface like virglrenderer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Redox running in QEMU, with some combination of these applications &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;A web server and content manager&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;A database&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;WASM/WASI microservices&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Custom web services applications of your choice&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We will need the following improvements to Redox to make this work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A faster network stack, including Ring Buffer I/O&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;virtiofs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;virglrenderer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Improvements to our shared memory and IPC&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;General compatibility, performance, security and stability testing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Management tools to simplify the use of the system&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Repeatable builds&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It would be nice to experiment with making virtualized devices like the GPU or VirtioFS available as a relibc/Redox-RT service, although that is not a major goal for 2026. This would be a configurable option, where the web service has exclusive use of the virtualized device. To the extent possible, the API should be the same whether the virtualized device is available as a library service or as a scheme-type service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Redox Server for Edge and Cloud&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most valuable application for Redox is as a secure host for web services, initially as a private server or edge server, and eventually as a multi-tenant cloud server. Redox can provide lightweight but secure sandboxing of web servers, databases and web service applications. We plan to provide heavyweight containerization in the longer-term future, with complete isolation between each tenant in a multi-tenant environment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This represents a substantial effort, but we plan to tackle it in phases to demonstrate value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Phase 1 - Redox running on bare metal in a single tenant server/edge scenario&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Phase 2 - Multi-tenant Redox with lightweight containers for WASM microservices and other supported applications&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Phase 3 - Multi-tenant Redox with heavyweight containers and support for arbitrary applications&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Redox Desktop for your daily driver&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox Desktop will benefit from all the features of Redox Server, but it also needs to be usable for everyone. And Redox security must work in a natural way for the average user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The COSMIC Desktop is being developed at System76, with Jeremy Soller as principal engineer. Itâs an open source Linux desktop environment that is written almost entirely in Rust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox currently supports several key applications, including COSMIC Terminal, COSMIC Files, COSMIC Editor, COSMIC Reader, and COSMIC Store. However, a few important parts of the COSMIC environment are missing due to our lack of Wayland support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once Wayland is supported, we will be able to support almost the entire COSMIC Desktop. We will also be able to add features for accessibility, i18n/l10n, and other improvements to the desktop experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We then plan to experiment with “sandboxing by default”, restricting the access of applications to only the resources that they should normally require. We would like to create a consistent experience for sandboxed applications, requesting greater access, and being aware of when you are more-privileged or less-privileged. There are several initiatives in this area, and if we can partner with someone to build a sandboxed desktop, it would be a valuable opportunity for us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Development Priorities&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building Redox on Redox&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although this has been an important goal for a long time, we are getting closer to supporting development for Redox, on Redox. Having the ability to edit, compile and run your code without having to cross-compile and generate bootable images will make development much faster and more pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have done some small-scale development on Redox, debugging test suites in C and making one-off changes. It’s quite pleasant, although it’s currently easier to mirror the changes manually in a host editor than to move the files back and forth between Redox and the host file system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How it will work&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the short/medium-term, Redox developers will be running Redox in QEMU or VirtualBox on their Linux, Windows or MacOS laptops or desktops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Initially, developers will need to use the GitLab server as their trusted storage, as work in progress might be lost if there is a Redox failure of some sort.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We hope to add a VirtioFS file system service so Redox can access the host files. This will greatly improve the developer experience.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;And, hopefully after a few months of use as a “daily driver” for developers, we will have the confidence that the Redox file system can be used for persistent storage, and you can push to GitLab when you reach a good stopping point.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For a small number of systems, we will be able to support Redox development on real hardware. The system will need to have hardware that works well with Redox, including a wired Ethernet connection. But we hope to have at least a few people doing development on real hardware before the end of 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Things to do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some of the challenges we need to address to make Self-Hosting a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Network performance needs to improve - we have an NGI Zero &amp;amp; NLnet funded project to implement Ring Buffers for disk I/O. We need to implement ring buffers in our network stack as well, once the disk I/O work stabilizes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Move to the upstream Rust compiler - we have mostly solved this, and just need to finish up.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rustc and Cargo reliability - due to past performance issues and a few challenging bugs, we have not had Cargo and the Rust compiler working consistently on Redox. We could use help fighting through the bugs while we wait for the networking improvements.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Build system improvements - we have removed a lot of legacy build system code and scripts, and now we are in a position to optimize our custom build tools.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Workflow improvements - self-hosting is a different experience from cross-compiling, and we will need to tweak our package manager and some build tools to make the development cycle more straightforward.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Redox improvements - self-hosting will be our first opportunity to use Redox as a daily driver, and we expect to find a few bugs or incomplete features that need polishing, and probably one or two unexpected performance bottlenecks.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compilers and build systems are a real torture test for operating systems, with many processes spawned and lots of files being opened and closed, and lots of small-file reads and writes. Getting Redox working smoothly for development will also greatly improve its general stability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Debugging&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Currently, Redox supports limited debugging with &lt;code&gt;gdb&lt;/code&gt; running on the Linux host.
This works well for debugging the kernel,
but it is more challenging when debugging applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We don’t have a reasonable self-hosted debugger setup yet, as Redox’s &lt;code&gt;ptrace&lt;/code&gt; implementation needs to be reworked.
That’s a complex enough project that we consider it a secondary goal for 2026.
If someone is up for a real challenge, please let us know.
Or, if you have ideas on how to improve debugging of user space applications and services
using &lt;code&gt;gdb&lt;/code&gt; on the Linux host, please get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Compliance and Compatibility&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox is not intended to be 100% POSIX compliant, or 100% source compatible with Linux, but we want to come close where it’s practical. Porting Linux applications to Redox has been the main driver for compatibility, but we have recently set up some compliance tests. Using a test-driven approach, rather than just focusing on porting, will speed up porting, with fewer non-compliance bugs to track down. There are also some chunks of functionality that are medium-high priority that we would love to have help fixing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Controlling Terminal needs a proper implementation&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There are several functions related to timers and alarms that need both POSIX and Linux functionality&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Many other examples will crop up as we do more compliance testing&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We would also like to polish our Rust compatibility. If you would like to set up tests for the Rust &lt;code&gt;std::&lt;/code&gt; library or other popular crates,
please join us and we can work together to add the tests to our Redox test suites.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Programming Language and Build Systems Support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox intends to support applications developed in any language. However, there are some tricky bits. Rust and C/C++ are well-supported, but we have trouble with languages that come with their own runtime. We need to add some fairly complex hooks in &lt;code&gt;relibc&lt;/code&gt; (our &lt;code&gt;libc&lt;/code&gt; implementation),
or provide a Redox-compatible implementation to support those runtimes,
and then we need to port and test the languages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can currently run Python programs using RustPython, but it would be nice if we could support the official implementation. We have started porting a couple of JavaScript engines, and we have work underway to support Go.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have some expertise in x86, ARM and RISC-V assembly, as well as language runtimes, and would like to get into the details of relibc and Redox’s runtime support for applications, please give us a hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also need to port the build tools, scripting languages, and utilities used in build systems. We have decent support for shell scripts, GNU Make, and the most common utilities. But we can use help figuring out if we can get build systems for various libraries and applications working, and what additional utilities are required.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Performance&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last year, we made really substantial improvements to Redox’s file system performance, thanks to James Matlik (RedoxFS), Jacob Lorentzon (Kernel) and Jeremy Soller (Disk I/O), which got us to the point where Redox can be usable in realistic scenarios. We are continuing to improve performance, as described above, so much so that by the end of next year, performance should not be a roadblock for using Redox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We do want to continue to make Redox go faster, but that work will be incremental going forward. Here’s a summary of our upcoming performance work (including things mentioned elsewhere).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ring Buffers for the disk and file system&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Direct process switching (context switching to the target driver with no scheduler intervention) as part of the Ring Buffers work&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ring Buffers for the network stack&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Scheduler improvements (EEVDF, and maybe others)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ongoing improvements to RedoxFS&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hardware-accelerated graphics&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Performance benchmarking - we would like someone to help curate and improve our benchmarking&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Security&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox is implementing Capability Based Security as a fundamental part of how files and resources are accessed. Over the next 12 months, the underlying representation of file descriptors will be replaced by capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first stage of this work is&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;to implement the machinery to create capabilities and transfer them between processes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;to have file references be relative to some capability (see openat(2))&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;to have every program running in a resource namespace that can be restricted as appropriate&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;to provide POSIX-style paths and file descriptors as a layer on top of capabilities&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There will be lots of followup work, to implement Capsicum-style security and mechanisms for requesting additional privileges, and to make security easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Hardware Support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To run Redox on real hardware, we need compatible drivers for the full range of system functionality. Linux has literally hundreds of people working on device drivers of all kinds, and we don’t have that luxury. So we will be focusing on “recommended” hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Redox Server, we will have to partner with a small number of server vendors, and develop drivers for that particular hardware. Whether it’s x86_64/amd64, Aarch64/ARM64, or RISC-V 64, we will have to find a vendor that will provide either funding or developers (or both) to create optimized drivers for disk, network, compute acceleration, as well as for system management and other functions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For Redox Desktop, we will support a very small number of desktop and laptop systems for our own development purposes, focusing on drivers that are likely to be compatible with the maximum number of real-world systems. For emerging standards and less common devices, we will look for help from the community to build out a more complete set of drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some of the key efforts that we are hoping to complete by the end of 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Firmware Support and Hardware Management&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need to rework our ACPI support, as the implementation we have needs better integration with the drivers and driver management. As well, Isaac Woods and the Rust-OSDev team have developed an entirely new AML parser, and improved the design of their acpi crate. We hope to take full advantage of their implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal for 2026 is to ensure we can configure and run the system correctly, with full system management as stretch goals and future work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are designing our boot/init to handle non-APCI firmware, and we could use help developing drivers for IEEE-1275 and other standards, as well as getting access to hardware that we can use for testing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;WiFi&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WiFi support is a whole collection of functionality, and it is not something we have tackled yet. We would appreciate some help porting an existing written-in-Rust WiFi driver stack, if an appropriate one can be found. It’s a pretty big project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;USB and I2C Support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox has USB drivers for keyboard, mouse, disk, and hub, but full support for USB on all the varied hardware out there remains a challenge. We could use help with improving our USB implementation, seeing if we can collaborate with other written-in-Rust implementations, adding new devices, and testing on real hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We don’t have an I2C driver, and would love to collaborate with someone on creating one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;IOMMU and Virtualization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is our intent that Redox will use IOMMU and hardware virtualization features wherever they are available, to protect against rogue hardware and drivers. However, we have not implemented support for IOMMU yet. We would like to at least get started on this in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Hosted Linux for Driver Support&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order to avoid porting thousands of device drivers, we would like to port QEMU to Redox, then run a stripped-down Linux to provide device drivers for less common and older devices. The interface between Redox and Linux-in-QEMU will be designed to be secure, so this approach should give us reasonable safety.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is an experimental approach, and our goal for 2026 is to determine if it is feasible and useful. We want to be able to run QEMU on Redox regardless, so please join us if you want to help out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;COSMIC, Wayland, and GPU Acceleration&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox uses the COSMIC Desktop, although we don’t currently support the COSMIC Compositor, so we are unable to use a lot of the COSMIC features. Porting Wayland will be a big step towards supporting the COSMIC Compositor, so that’s very high on our list of things to do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ability to send file descriptors over our Unix Domain Sockets was implemented in one of our Summer of Code projects (thanks Ibuki!), which represents a big step forward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are still missing some functionality in &lt;code&gt;relibc&lt;/code&gt;,
including timerfds and a few other things,
although most of the underlying machinery exists,
so if you want to help, please join our chat and let us know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are also looking for a full D-Bus implementation in Rust that can be ported to Redox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For GPU acceleration, our first goal is to support Virtio graphics acceleration, probably using virglrenderer. Then Intel graphics will probably be the easiest next step, with drivers for AMD and NVIDIA graphics dependent on having access to the right information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Accessibility and Internationalization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So far, Redox has not accomplished as much as we would like with either Internalization or Accessibility. We have gotten a start in the last few months but there’s lots to do.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Internationalization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our goal with Internationalization (“i18n”) is to align with POSIX where possible, and we encourage ideas that go beyond the POSIX standard. Redox is UTF-8 natively, but we allow for opening non-UTF-8 file names on non-RedoxFS file systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of the areas that need work are&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Localization APIs and settings storage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Non-US keyboard support (started but not complete)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Non-Latin text display (COSMIC supports this, but Redox does not use it yet)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Timezones, numeric and currency display, other LC_* types&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having team members with expertise in i18n/l10n support is would be a great boost to Redox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Accessibility&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have started a discussion group for Accessibility. One of our contributors, Bendeguz Pisch, has been working on a screen reader solution for Redox. More help would be appreciated. We would ideally like a written-in-Rust solution with an MIT or other permissive license, but a good screen reader is not a small undertaking, and requires expertise in meeting the expectations of users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are many other areas of accessibility to address, and we would like to find contributors that can help us ensure that Redox meets the needs of as many users as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Join Us!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s lots of exciting work ahead, and a great team already working on it. If you would like to be part of the team, or just listen in to the conversation, please join us on Redox Chat.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45376895</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 18:29:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tracing JITs in the Real World CPython Core Dev Sprint</title><link>https://antocuni.eu/2025/09/24/tracing-jits-in-the-real-world--cpython-core-dev-sprint/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="23330e932cf522d9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Tracing JITs in the real world @ CPython Core Dev Sprint¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last week I got to take part in the CPython Core Developer Sprint in Cambridge, hosted by ARM and brilliantly organized by Diego Russo -- about ~50 core devs and guests were there, and I was excited to join as one of the guests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had three main areas of focus:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;C API: this was a follow up of what we discussed at the C API summit at EuroPython. The current C API is problematic, so we are exploring ideas for the development of PyNI (Python Native Interface), whose design will likely be heavily inspired by HPy. It's important to underline that this is just the beginning and the entire process will require multiple PEPs.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;fancycompleter This is a small PR which I started months ago, to enable colorful tab completions within the Python REPL. I wrote the original version of fancycompleter 15 years ago, but colorful completions work only in combination with PyREPL. Now PyREPL is part of the standard library and enabled by default, so we can finally upstream it. I hope to see it merged soon.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;"JIT stuff": I spent a considerable amount of time talking to the people who are working on the CPython JIT (in particular Mark, Brandt, Savannah, Ken Jin and Diego). Knowledge transfer worked in both ways: I learned a lot about the internal details of CPython's JIT, and conversely I shared with them some of the experience, pain points and gut feelings which I got by working many years on PyPy.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In particular, on the first day I presented a talk titled Tracing JIT and real world Python (slides and source code).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What follows is an annotated version of the slides.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CPython's new JIT and PyPy's JIT share fundamental similarities, as they're both tracing JITs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I spent ~7 years of my career optimizing existing code for PyPy at a high-frequency trading firm, and I realized that I'm probably one of the few people in the world with actual experience in optimizing real world Python code for a tracing JIT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I expect that some of the challenges which I faced will still be valid also for CPython, and I wanted to share my experience to make sure that CPython core devs are aware of them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One lesson which I learned is that the set of benchmarks in &lt;code&gt;pyperformance&lt;/code&gt; are
a good starting point, but they are not entirely representative of what you
find in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The main goal of the talk is not to present solutions to these problems, but to raise awareness that they exist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Until now CPython's performance has been particularly predictable, there are well established "performance tricks" to make code faster, and generally speaking you can mostly reason about the speed of a given piece of code "locally".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adding a JIT completely changes how we reason about performance of a given program, for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;JITted code can be very fast if your code conforms to the heuristics applied by the JIT compiler, but unexpectedly slow(-ish) otherwise;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;the speed of a given piece of code might depend heavily on what happens elsewhere in the program, making it much harder to reason about performance locally.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The end result is that modifying a line of code can significantly impact seemingly unrelated code. This effect becomes more pronounced as the JIT becomes more sophisticated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The CPython JIT is still pretty new and doesn’t give huge speedups yet. I expect that as it gets faster, its performance will start looking more and more like PyPy’s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I delivered this talk at the Core Dev Sprint: I expected my audience to be familiar with CPython's JIT, and wanted to draw parallels with PyPy's one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since the audience of this blog is different, let me briefly explain CPython's JIT first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The explanations of both JITs are necessarily short, incomplete and highly simplified.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;CPython JIT 101¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Python source code is turned into bytecode. Bytecode is a sequence of "opcodes" (&lt;code&gt;LOAD_FAST&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;BINARY_OP&lt;/code&gt;, etc.), and the CPython VM is an
interpreter for those opcodes. Historically the VM was written by hand, and the
main loop consisted of a big &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; statement which executed the code
corresponding to each opcode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nowadays things are different: the opcodes are written in a special DSL and the main interpreter loop is generated from this DSL. Additionally, the DSL describes how each opcode can be decomposed into multiple "microops".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the interpreter detects a "hot loop", it starts the JIT. The JIT retroactively looks at the opcodes which were executed in the last iteration of the loop, and creates a "linear trace" which contains the equivalent microops. This process is called trace projection and the result is an unoptimized trace of microops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, the JIT can produce an optimized trace, by reordering and removing redundant microops. Finally, the optimized trace is turned into executable code using the "copy &amp;amp; patch" technique.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;PyPy JIT 101¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CPython's Python interpreter is written in C, and then compiled into an executable by &lt;code&gt;gcc&lt;/code&gt; (or any other C compiler).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, PyPy's Python interpreter is written in RPython, and then compiled into an executable by &lt;code&gt;rpython&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under the hood, &lt;code&gt;rpython&lt;/code&gt; applies two separate transformations to the source
code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;it turns each function into C code, which is then fed to&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gcc&lt;/code&gt;to get the final executable;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;it turns each function into "jitcodes", which is a way to represent RPython's IR (internal representation). For each RPython function, the final&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;./pypy&lt;/code&gt;executable contains its compiled representation (generated by GCC) and its jitcode representation (embedded as static data into the executable).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a way, RPython's jitcodes are equivalent to CPython's microops, as they are a low-level representation of the logic of each opcode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the interpreter detects a hot loop, it enters trace recording mode, which is essentially an interpreter which executes the jitcodes: the result is a linear unoptimized trace of all the jitcodes which were actually executed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly to CPython, PyPy then produces an optimized trace, which is then sent to the JIT backend for actual native code generation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tracing JITs work by recording a trace of all microops which are executed. The optimizer can then reason about what happens in the trace and remove unneeded operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, sometimes we encounter some operation which is a black box from the point of view of the tracer: we call them "trace blocker", because the tracing JIT cannot see through them. In the case of CPython, this happens for example, whenever we call any function implemented in C (because it doesn't have any correspondent "microop").&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a simple function that computes &lt;code&gt;pi&lt;/code&gt;, generated by ChatGPT.  Its
precise content is not important: what matters is that it's a nice purely
numerical loop that the PyPy JIT can optimize very well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Same function as above, with a call to &lt;code&gt;hic_sunt_leones()&lt;/code&gt;. This is actually
an empty function which does absolutely nothing, but annotated in a
special way so that the PyPy JIT cannot "enter" it, so it effectively behaves
as trace blocker.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this example we use the special &lt;code&gt;pypyjit.residual_call&lt;/code&gt; to simulate a trace
blocker, but in real life we get it whenever we have a call to any
non-traceable function, in particular C extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The clean version runs 42x faster on PyPy than CPython - that's the JIT working perfectly. But with just one untraceable function call added to the loop, PyPy slows down to only 1.8x faster than CPython. That single line destroyed most of the JIT's effectiveness!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This happens because after the call the optimizer no longer knows whether its assumptions about the world are still true, and thus must be much more conservative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I fear that for CPython, this will turn out to be a much bigger problem than for PyPy, for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;nowadays it's virtually impossible to run Python code without using any C extension, either directly or indirectly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;by construction, PyPy's JIT can see much more than CPython's JIT. Remember the slide about "jitcodes": any RPython function gets a "jitcodes" equivalent, which means that the JIT can automatially trace inside builtins and internals of the interpreter, whereas CPython can trace only inside pure python code.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, PyPy's JIT can trace through &lt;code&gt;range()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;zip&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;enumerate()&lt;/code&gt;
automatically. CPython's JIT currently cannot because they are implemented in
C. CPython could add special cases for these common functions, but the
general approach doesn't scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second big problem is what I call "data driven control flow". This example has been autogenerated by ChatGPT and it's completely silly, but it's a good representation of what happens in real life code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this example, &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt; takes 9 variables, each of them can be &lt;code&gt;None&lt;/code&gt; or a
number. The function starts with a sequence of &lt;code&gt;if &amp;lt;var&amp;gt; is None: ...&lt;/code&gt;. The
function is then called repeatedly in a loop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the assumption of tracing JITs is that control flow tends to stay on the "hot path", and that it's enough to optimize that to get good performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But in a case like this, each combination of &lt;code&gt;None&lt;/code&gt;ness selects a different
path, and if we assume the data is evenly distributed, we find out that
there is no hot path.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's see what happens when we execute on CPython and PyPy:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PyPy without JIT is "only" 2.3x slower than CPython, but when we enable the JIT, it becomes much worse. This happens because of an exponential explosion of code paths seen by the JIT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a normal compiler, an &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; statement is compiled as a diamond, and the
control flow merges after each &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A tracing JIT by definition follows what's happening during a concrete execution, so it sees only a concrete path in the control flow, with "guards" to ensure correctness:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When &lt;code&gt;guard(a is None)&lt;/code&gt; fails enough times, we create a "bridge" and record
another linear trace, following again the concrete control flow that happens
now:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;          guard(a is None) ----&amp;gt; FAIL (side exit)
            /                         \
           /                           \
        a = 0                          pass
           \                             \
            \                             \
    guard(b not None)              guard(b not None)
            /                             /
           /                             /
        b = 0                         b = 0
           \                             \
            \                             \
           ...                           ...
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note how &lt;code&gt;b = 0&lt;/code&gt; is effectively duplicated now. By design, PyPy's JIT never
merges execution flow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking inside &lt;code&gt;PYPYLOG&lt;/code&gt; confirms our theory: we get "exponential
tracing". The JIT has to compile separate optimized code for every unique
combination of which parameters are None and which aren't. With 9 parameters,
that could be up to 512 different combinations!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One possible mitigation is to rewrite conditional code to be "branchless" - using arithmetic tricks instead of if statements. But this makes code ugly and unreadable, and it's not always possible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite years of working on this, I never found a really good solution. There were cases in which we had to continue running some piece of code on CPython because I never managed to make the PyPy version faster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pattern happens quite a lot, although often is more subtle: in this silly example all the &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;s are nicely grouped together at the start, but in a long
trace they can be scattered in multiple places, and any kind of control flow
contributes to the problem, not only &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;s. In Python, this includes any kind
of dynamic dispatch, exceptions, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One possible solution for CPython's JIT is to try to merge (some) traces to avoid or limit the exponential explosion. However, it is worth underlining that tracing JITs shine precisely when they can optimize a long linear trace: if you try to compile shorter traces, you might quickly end up in a situation which is equivalent to the "trace blocker" problem described earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I suspect this might be a fundamental limitation of tracing JITs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compared to the other two problems, this is less serious, but it's worth mentioning because of prevalence of &lt;code&gt;async&lt;/code&gt; (and thus implicitly generators)
in modern Python.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's another silly function that counts Pythagorean triples using nested loops. This is our baseline version using plain loops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's the same algorithm refactored to use a generator function for the nested iteration. The "state of iteration" is implicitly stored inside the local variables of frame object associated to the &lt;code&gt;range_product&lt;/code&gt; generator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's the same functionality implemented as a traditional iterator class. The "state of iteration" is explicitly stored as attributes of &lt;code&gt;RangeProductIter&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On CPython, the generator version is ~29% slower than the explicit loops. The iterator class is much slower, as one would intuitively expect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, on PyPy we see different results: &lt;code&gt;RangeProductIter&lt;/code&gt; is basically
same speed as the baseline, while the generator version is slower. This
happens because in the case of &lt;code&gt;RangeProductIter&lt;/code&gt; the JIT is able to see the whole
lifetime of the object and optimize it away entirely: instance variables
become local variables, the call to &lt;code&gt;__next__&lt;/code&gt; is inlined and we get the
equivalent of explicit nested loops.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, generators are required to create a frame object and represent a fundamental case in which the JIT cannot trace through them effectively. In more complex real-world scenarios, we saw much worse slowdowns than these examples show.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a collection of other miscellaneous problems that I had to deal with. Generally speaking, we lack good support for tooling and profilers. CPython needs to have a good story to explain people how to understand what's happening when the JIT is enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Warmup is another big problem: in PyPy, very short programs tend to be slower than CPython because JITting costs. Moreover warmup is not an easily definable phase, as the linked paper shows. This is an area where currently CPython shines, as its JIT is very fast. I think that it will become slightly slower when it tries to optimize more aggressively, but hopefully warmup will overall be a lesser problem than on PyPy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moreover, it's very easy to accidentally make your code 2x, 5x or even 10x slower by changing seemingly innocent pieces of code. This is another reason why good tooling is essential.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, the "long tail of JITting": every loop and every guard gets a counter, and we start JITting when it reaches a threshold. Given a sufficiently long running program, all counters reach the threshold eventually and we end up JITting much more than necessary, using too much memory and/or thrashing the cache. In many cases I found beneficial to just disable the JIT "after a while", with manually tuned heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are slides which I didn't show during the live presentation, and show a case where a tracing JIT can shine: since the JIT sees a complete trace of an entire loop (including nested calls) it can easily removes a lot of temporary objects which usually penalize Python performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In many cases, we can get the famous "zero-cost abstractions".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let's look at a concrete example. We need to compute the barycenter of triangles that are serialized in a binary format. Each triangle has three points, each point has x and y coordinates. This simulates real world protocols such as protobuf, capnproto, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is what we use a a baseline: a bare loop, using &lt;code&gt;struct.unpack_from&lt;/code&gt; to read 6 floats at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's the "proper" object-oriented approach, similar to how modern serialization libraries work. We create &lt;code&gt;Triangle&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Point&lt;/code&gt; classes that
provide a nice API for accessing the binary data. Each property access creates
new objects and calls struct.unpack_from. This is much more readable and
reusable, but creates many temporary objects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's how you'd use the object-oriented API. The code is much cleaner and more readable than the bare loop version. But notice how many object creations are happening: one &lt;code&gt;Triangle&lt;/code&gt; object, six &lt;code&gt;Point&lt;/code&gt; objects, plus all the
intermediate tuples from &lt;code&gt;struct.unpack_from&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As expected, on CPython &lt;code&gt;read_proto&lt;/code&gt; is much slower than the bare one,
roughly 6x slower. However, PyPy can fully optimize away all the
abstraction overhead introduced by &lt;code&gt;Triangle&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Point&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In PyPy jargon we call this form of allocation removal "virtuals" (because we create "virtual objects" whose fields are represented as local variables) and it's probably the single most important optimization that PyPy does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During my week in Cambridge I talked extensively with the CPython JIT devs about this and I hope I convinced them that this is what they should aim for 😊.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note also that &lt;code&gt;read_proto&lt;/code&gt; is actually faster than &lt;code&gt;read_loop&lt;/code&gt;. This
happens because in &lt;code&gt;read_loop&lt;/code&gt; we do a single &lt;code&gt;struct.unpack_from('dddddd', ...)&lt;/code&gt;,
while in &lt;code&gt;read_proto&lt;/code&gt; we do a succession of six individual
&lt;code&gt;struct.unpack_from('d', ...)&lt;/code&gt;. It turns out that the JIT is able to trace
into the second form but not into the first, which means that in &lt;code&gt;read_loop&lt;/code&gt;
we actually need to allocate a pseudo-tuple at each iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The funny part is that I did not expect to get this result. I had to take the time to analyze the JIT traces of both versions to understand why &lt;code&gt;read_loop&lt;/code&gt; was slower.  This is probably the best explanation of how
counterintuitive it is to reason about performance in a JITted world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Acknowledgments¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Carl Friedrich Bolz-Tereick and Hood Chatham for feedback on the slides and the post.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45377030</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 18:40:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Implementing UI translation in SumatraPDF, a C++ Windows application</title><link>https://blog.kowalczyk.info/a-vn0v/implementing-ui-translation-in-sumatrapdf-a-c-windows-application.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3c5278dd8a2abbb8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Translating user interface of SumatraPDF&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;SumatraPDF&lt;p&gt; is the best PDF/eBook/Comic Book viewer for Windows. It’s small, fast, full of features, free and open-source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It became popular enough that it made sense to translate the UI for non-English users. Currently we support 72 languages.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This article describes how I designed and implemented a translation system in SumatraPDF, a native win32 C++ Windows application.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hard things about translating the UI&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are 2 hard things about translating an application&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;code for translation system (extracting strings to translate, translate strings from English to user’s language)&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;translating them into many languages&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Currently there are 381 strings in SumatraPDF subject to translation. It’s important that the system requires the least amount of effort when adding new strings to translate.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Every string that needs to be translated is marked in &lt;code&gt;.cpp&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.h&lt;/code&gt; file with one of two macros:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;_TRA("Rename")&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;_TRN("Open")&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I have a script that extracts those strings from source files. Mine is written in Go but it could just as well be Python or JavaScript. It’s a simple regex job.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;_TR&lt;/code&gt; stands for “translation”.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;_TRA(s)&lt;/code&gt; expands into &lt;code&gt;const char* trans::GetTranslation(const char* str)&lt;/code&gt; function which returns &lt;code&gt;str&lt;/code&gt; translated to current UI language.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We auto-detect language at startup based on Windows settings and allow the user to explicitly set UI language.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For English we just return the original string.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If a string to be translated is e.g. a part of &lt;code&gt;const char* array[]&lt;/code&gt;, we can’t use &lt;code&gt;trans::GetTranslation()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For cases like that we have &lt;code&gt;_TRN()&lt;/code&gt; which expands to English string. We have to write code to translate it at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Adding new strings is therefore as simple as wrapping them in &lt;code&gt;_TRA()&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;_TRN()&lt;/code&gt; macros.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Translating strings into many languages&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve extracted strings to be translated, we need to translate them into 72 languages.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;SumatraPDF is a free, open-source program. I don’t have a budget to hire translators. I don’t have a budget, period.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The only option was to get help from SumatraPDF users.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It was vital to make it very easy for users to send me translations. I didn’t want to ask them, for example, to download some translation software.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Design and implementation of AppTranslator web app&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I designed it to be generic but I don’t think anyone else is using it.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;4k lines of Go server code&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;451 lines of html code&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;a single dependency: bootstrap CSS framework (the project is old)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s simple because I don’t want to spend a lot of time writing translation software. It’s just a side project in service of the goal of translating SumatraPDF.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Login is exclusively via GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It doesn’t even use a database. Like in Redis, changes are stored as a series of operations in an append-only log. We keep the whole state in memory and re-create it from the log at startup.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Main operation is &lt;code&gt;translate a string from English to language X&lt;/code&gt; represented as &lt;code&gt;[kOpTranslation, english string, language, translation, user who provided translation]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When user provides a translation in the web UI, we send an API call to the server which appends the translation operation to the log.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Simple and reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Because the code is written in Go, it’s very fast and memory efficient. When running it uses mere megabytes of RAM. It can comfortably run on the smallest 256 MB VPS server.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I backup the log to S3 so if the server ever fails, I can re-install the program on a new server and re-download the translations from S3.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I provide RSS feed for each language so that people who provide translations can monitor for new strings to be translated.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Sending strings for translation and receiving translations&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;So I have a web app for collecting translations and a script that extracts strings to be translated from source code.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;How do they connect?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;AppTranslator has an API for submitting the current set of strings to be translated in the simplest possible format: a line for each string (I ensure there are no newlines in the string itself by escaping them with &lt;code&gt;\n&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;API is password protected because only I can submit the strings.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The server compares the strings sent with the current set and records a difference in the log.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It also sends a response with translations. Again the simplest possible format:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;AppTranslator: SumatraPDF
651b739d7fa110911f25563c933f42b1d37590f8
:%s annotation. Ctrl+click to edit.
am:%s մեկնաբանություն: Ctrl+քլիք՝ խմբագրելու համար:
ar:ملاحظة %s. اضغط Ctrl للتحرير.
az:Qeyd %s. Düzəliş etmək üçün Ctrl+düyməyə basın.
&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As you can see:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;a string to translate is on a line starting with :&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;is followed by translations of that strings in the format: &lt;code&gt;${lang}: ${translation}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;An optimization: &lt;code&gt;651b739d7fa110911f25563c933f42b1d37590f8&lt;/code&gt; is a hash of this response. If I submit this hash with my request and translations didn’t change on the server, the response is empty.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Implementing C++ part of translation system&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;So now I have a text file with translation downloaded from the server. How do I get a translation in my C++ code?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As with everything in SumatraPDF, I try to do things in a simple and efficient way.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The whole &lt;code&gt;Translation.cpp&lt;/code&gt; is only 239 lines of code.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The core of translation system is &lt;code&gt;const char* trans::GetTranslation(const char* s);&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I embed the translations in exact the same format as received from AppTranslator in the executable as data file in resources.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If the UI language is English, we do nothing. &lt;code&gt;trans::GetTranslation()&lt;/code&gt; returns its argument.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When we switch the language, we load the translations from resources and build an index:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;an array of English strings&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;an array of corresponding translations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both arrays use my own &lt;/p&gt;StrVec&lt;p&gt; class optimized for storing an array of strings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To find a translation we scan the first array to find an index of the string and return translation from the second array, at the same index.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Linear scan seems like it would be slow but it isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Resizing dialogs&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I have a few dialogs defined in &lt;code&gt;SumatraPDF.rc&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The problem with dialogs is that position of UI elements is fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A translated string will almost certainly have a different size than the English string which will mess up fixed layout.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Thankfully someone wrote DialogSizer that smartly resizes dialogs and solves this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The evolution of a solution&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;No AppTranslator&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My initial implementation was simpler. I didn’t yet have AppTranslator so I stored the strings in a text file in repository in the same format as what I described above.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;People would download it, make changes using a text editor and send me the file via email which I would then checkin.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It worked for a while but it became worse over time. More strings, more languages created more work for me to manually manage e-mail submissions.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I decided to automate the process.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Code generation&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My first implementation of C++ side used code generation instead of embedding the text file in resources.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My Go script would generate C++ source code files with static &lt;code&gt;const char* []&lt;/code&gt; arrays.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This worked well but I decided to improve it further by making the code use the text file with translations embedded in the app.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The main motivation for the change was to open a possibility of downloading latest translations from the server to fix the problem of translations not being all ready when I build the release executable.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I haven’t done that yet but it’s now easier to implement given that the format of strings embedded in the exe is the same as the one I can download from AppTranslator.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Only utf-8&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;SumatraPDF started by using both &lt;code&gt;WCHAR*&lt;/code&gt; Unicode strings and &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; utf8 strings.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For that reason the translation system had to support returning translation in both &lt;code&gt;WCHAR*&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;char*&lt;/code&gt; version.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Over time I refactored the code to use mostly utf8 and at some point I no longer needed to support &lt;code&gt;WCHAR*&lt;/code&gt; version.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;That made the code even smaller and reduced memory usage.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The experience&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m happy how things turned out.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;AppTranslator&lt;p&gt; proved to be reliable and hassle free. It runs for many years now and collected 35440 string translations from users.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I automated everything so that all I need to do is to periodically re-run the script that extracts strings from source code, uploads them to AppTranslator and downloads latest translations.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;One problem is that translations are not always ready in time for release so I make a release and then people start translating strings added since last release.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’ve considered downloading the latest translations from the server, in addition to embedding them in an executable at the time of building the app.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Would I do the same today?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While AppTranslator is reliable and doesn’t require on-going work, it would be better to not have to run a server at all.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The world has changed since I started SumatraPDF.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Namely: people are comfortable using GitHub and you can edit files directly in GitHub UI. It’s not a great experience but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;One option would be to generate a translation text file for each language, in this format:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;:first untranslated string
:second untranslated string
:first translated string
translation of first string
:second translated string
translation of second string
&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Untranslated strings are listed at the top, to make it easier to find.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A link would send a translator directly to edit this file in GitHub UI.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When translator saves translations, it creates a PR for me to review and merge.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The roads not taken&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;But why did you re-invent everything? You should do X instead.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;All other X that I know about suck.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Using per-language .rc resource files&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Traditional way of localizing / translating Window GUI apps is to store all strings and dialog definitions in an &lt;code&gt;.rc&lt;/code&gt; file. Each language gets its own &lt;code&gt;.rc&lt;/code&gt; file (or files) and the program picks the right resource based on a language.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This doesn’t solve the 2 hard problems:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;having an easy way to add strings for translations&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;having an easy way for users to provide translations&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;XML horror show&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There was a dark time when the world was under the iron grip of XML fanaticism.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Everything had to be an XML file even when it was the worst possible solution for the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;XML doesn’t solve the 2 hard problems and a string storage format is an absolute nightmare for human editing.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;GNU gettext&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There’s a C library gettext that uses &lt;code&gt;.po&lt;/code&gt; files.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is much saner solution than XML horror show. &lt;code&gt;.po&lt;/code&gt; files are relatively simple text format. The code is already written.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Warning: tooting my own horn.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;My format is better. It’s easier for people to edit, it’s easier to write code to parse it. &lt;/p&gt;This&lt;p&gt; looks like many times more than 239 lines of code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ok, gettext probably does a bit more than my code, but clearly nothing than I need.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It also doesn’t solve the 2 hard problems. I would still have to write code to extract strings from source code and build a way to allow users to translate them easily.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45377572</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 19:17:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ollama Web Search</title><link>https://ollama.com/blog/web-search</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2d52dc131ca4ae0e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Web search&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;September 24, 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A new web search API is now available in Ollama. Ollama provides a generous free tier of web searches for individuals to use, and higher rate limits are available via Ollama’s cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This web search capability can augment models with the latest information from the web to reduce hallucinations and improve accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Web search is provided as a REST API with deeper tool integrations in Ollama’s Python and JavaScript libraries. This also enables models such as OpenAI’s &lt;code&gt;gpt-oss&lt;/code&gt; models to conduct long-running research tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Get started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create an API key from your Ollama account.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;export OLLAMA_API_KEY="your_api_key"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;cURL&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;curl https://ollama.com/api/web_search \
  --header "Authorization: Bearer $OLLAMA_API_KEY" \
  -d '{
    "query": "what is ollama?"
  }'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example output&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "results": [
    {
      "title": "Ollama",
      "url": "https://ollama.com/",
      "content": "Cloud models are now available..."
    },
    {
      "title": "What is Ollama? Introduction to the AI model management tool",
      "url": "https://www.hostinger.com/tutorials/what-is-ollama",
      "content": "Ariffud M. 6min Read..."
    },
    {
      "title": "Ollama Explained: Transforming AI Accessibility and Language ...",
      "url": "https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/artificial-intelligence/ollama-explained-transforming-ai-accessibility-and-language-processing/",
      "content": "Data Science Data Science Projects Data Analysis..."
    }
  ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Python&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install and run Ollama’s Python library&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pip install 'ollama&amp;gt;=0.6.0'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then make a request using &lt;code&gt;ollama.web_search&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import ollama
response = ollama.web_search("What is Ollama?")
print(response)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example output&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;results = [
    {
        "title": "Ollama",
        "url": "https://ollama.com/",
        "content": "Cloud models are now available in Ollama..."
    },
    {
        "title": "What is Ollama? Features, Pricing, and Use Cases - Walturn",
        "url": "https://www.walturn.com/insights/what-is-ollama-features-pricing-and-use-cases",
        "content": "Our services..."
    },
    {
        "title": "Complete Ollama Guide: Installation, Usage &amp;amp; Code Examples",
        "url": "https://collabnix.com/complete-ollama-guide-installation-usage-code-examples",
        "content": "Join our Discord Server..."
    }
]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;JavaScript&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install and run Ollama’s JavaScript library&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install 'ollama@&amp;gt;=0.6.0'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Ollama } from "ollama";

const client = new Ollama();
const results = await client.webSearch({ query: "what is ollama?" });
console.log(JSON.stringify(results, null, 2));
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example output&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "results": [
    {
      "title": "Ollama",
      "url": "https://ollama.com/",
      "content": "Cloud models are now available..."
    },
    {
      "title": "What is Ollama? Introduction to the AI model management tool",
      "url": "https://www.hostinger.com/tutorials/what-is-ollama",
      "content": "Ollama is an open-source tool..."
    },
    {
      "title": "Ollama Explained: Transforming AI Accessibility and Language Processing",
      "url": "https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/artificial-intelligence/ollama-explained-transforming-ai-accessibility-and-language-processing/",
      "content": "Ollama is a groundbreaking..."
    }
  ]
}

&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Building a search agent&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use Ollama’s web search as a tool to build a mini search agent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The example uses Alibaba’s Qwen 3 model with 4B parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ollama pull qwen3:4b
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from ollama import chat, web_fetch, web_search

available_tools = {'web_search': web_search, 'web_fetch': web_fetch}

messages = [{'role': 'user', 'content': "what is ollama's new engine"}]

while True:
  response = chat(
    model='qwen3:4b',
    messages=messages,
    tools=[web_search, web_fetch],
    think=True
    )
  if response.message.thinking:
    print('Thinking: ', response.message.thinking)
  if response.message.content:
    print('Content: ', response.message.content)
  messages.append(response.message)
  if response.message.tool_calls:
    print('Tool calls: ', response.message.tool_calls)
    for tool_call in response.message.tool_calls:
      function_to_call = available_tools.get(tool_call.function.name)
      if function_to_call:
        args = tool_call.function.arguments
        result = function_to_call(**args)
        print('Result: ', str(result)[:200]+'...')
        # Result is truncated for limited context lengths
        messages.append({'role': 'tool', 'content': str(result)[:2000 * 4], 'tool_name': tool_call.function.name})
      else:
        messages.append({'role': 'tool', 'content': f'Tool {tool_call.function.name} not found', 'tool_name': tool_call.function.name})
  else:
    break
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Result&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Thinking:  Okay, the user is asking about Ollama's new engine. I need to figure out what they're referring to. Ollama is a company that develops large language models, so maybe they've released a new model or an updated version of their existing engine...

Tool calls:  [ToolCall(function=Function(name='web_search', arguments={'max_results': 3, 'query': 'Ollama new engine'}))]
Result:  results=[WebSearchResult(content='# New model scheduling\n\n## September 23, 2025\n\nOllama now includes a significantly improved model scheduling system. Ahead of running a model, Ollama’s new engine...

Thinking:  Okay, the user asked about Ollama's new engine. Let me look at the search results.

First result is from September 23, 2025, talking about new model scheduling. It mentions improved memory management, reduced crashes, better GPU utilization, and multi-GPU performance. Examples show speed improvements and accurate memory reporting. Supported models include gemma3, llama4, qwen3, etc...

Content:  Ollama has introduced two key updates to its engine, both released in 2025:

1. **Enhanced Model Scheduling (September 23, 2025)**
   - **Precision Memory Management**: Exact memory allocation reduces out-of-memory crashes and optimizes GPU utilization.
   - **Performance Gains**: Examples show significant speed improvements (e.g., 85.54 tokens/s vs 52.02 tokens/s) and full GPU layer utilization.
   - **Multi-GPU Support**: Improved efficiency across multiple GPUs, with accurate memory reporting via tools like `nvidia-smi`.
   - **Supported Models**: Includes `gemma3`, `llama4`, `qwen3`, `mistral-small3.2`, and more.

2. **Multimodal Engine (May 15, 2025)**
   - **Vision Support**: First-class support for vision models, including `llama4:scout` (109B parameters), `gemma3`, `qwen2.5vl`, and `mistral-small3.1`.
   - **Multimodal Tasks**: Examples include identifying animals in multiple images, answering location-based questions from videos, and document scanning.

These updates highlight Ollama's focus on efficiency, performance, and expanded capabilities for both text and vision tasks.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recommended models:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These models have great tool-use capabilities and are able to have multi-turn interactions with the user and tools to get to a final result.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;qwen3&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;gpt-oss&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recommended cloud models:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;qwen3:480b-cloud&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;gpt-oss:120b-cloud&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;deepseek-v3.1-cloud&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;web_search&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;web_fetch&lt;/code&gt; tools can return thousands of tokens. It is recommended to increase the context length of the model to ~32000 tokens for reasonable performance. Search agents work best with full context length.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Fetching page results&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To fetch individual pages (e.g. when a user provides a url in the prompt), use the new web fetch API.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Python library&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;from ollama import web_fetch

result = web_fetch('https://ollama.com')
print(result)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Result&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;WebFetchResponse(
    title='Ollama',
    content='[Cloud models](https://ollama.com/blog/cloud-models) are now available in Ollama\n\n**Chat &amp;amp; build
with open models**\n\n[Download](https://ollama.com/download) [Explore
models](https://ollama.com/models)\n\nAvailable for macOS, Windows, and Linux',
    links=['https://ollama.com/', 'https://ollama.com/models', 'https://github.com/ollama/ollama']
)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example Python code is available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;JavaScript library&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Ollama } from "ollama";

const client = new Ollama();
const fetchResult = await client.webFetch({ url: "https://ollama.com" });
console.log(JSON.stringify(fetchResult, null, 2));
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Result&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "title": "Ollama",
  "content": "[Cloud models](https://ollama.com/blog/cloud-models) are now available in Ollama...",
  "links": [
    "https://ollama.com/",
    "https://ollama.com/models",
    "https://github.com/ollama/ollama"
  ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example JavaScript code is available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;cURL&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;curl --request POST \
  --url https://ollama.com/api/web_fetch \
  --header "Authorization: Bearer $OLLAMA_API_KEY" \
  --header 'Content-Type: application/json' \
  --data '{
      "url": "ollama.com"
}'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Result&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "title": "Ollama",
  "content": "[Cloud models](https://ollama.com/blog/cloud-models) are now available in Ollama...",
  "links": [
    "http://ollama.com/",
    "http://ollama.com/models",
    "https://github.com/ollama/ollama"
  ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Integrations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;MCP Server (Model Context Protocol server)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can enable web search in any MCP client through the Python MCP server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Cline&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To integrate with Cline, configure MCP servers in its settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Manage MCP Servers &amp;gt; Configure MCP Servers &amp;gt; Add the configuration below&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "mcpServers": {
    "web_search_and_fetch": {
      "type": "stdio",
      "command": "uv",
      "args": ["run", "path/to/web-search-mcp.py"],
      "env": { "OLLAMA_API_KEY": "your_api_key_here" }
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Codex&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add the following configuration to &lt;code&gt;~/.codex/config.toml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;[mcp_servers.web_search]
command = "uv"
args = ["run", "path/to/web-search-mcp.py"]
env = { "OLLAMA_API_KEY" = "your_api_key_here" }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Goose&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can integrate with Ollama via Goose’s extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Get started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Web search is included with a free Ollama account, with much higher rate limits available by upgrading your Ollama subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To get started, sign up for an Ollama account!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45377641</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 19:21:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Can a model trained on satellite data really find brambles on the ground?</title><link>https://toao.com/blog/can-we-really-see-brambles-from-space</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3d09f083bdbd4a9a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Can a model trained on satellite data really find brambles on the ground?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the summer Gabriel Mahler has been conducting research on hedgehog habitat mapping using Agent Based Models (ABMs) and remote sensing. Hedgehogs seem to like brambles and so as part of his work he has produced a bramble map. He did this by combining the TESSERA earth representation embeddings (using the geotessera library) with data from iNaturalist. The current model is an ensemble of logistic regression and a knn classifier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Can we really see brambles from space? What better way to test the model than a quick field trip around Cambridge. Gabriel, Anil, Shane and I did just that today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We started at Milton Community Centre, as the model was relatively confident there were brambles near the car park and along the path to Milton Park. It took us about 20 seconds to find the first one in an area indicated by the model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So it turns out that there's a lot of bramble between the community center and entrance to Milton Country Park. We stopped six or seven times before reaching the park entrance. While the model predicted we'd find brambles all over the park, we went for the few areas of very high confidence near the entrance. In every place we checked, we found pretty significant amounts of bramble.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We collected photos of all the places we stopped, as well as recording our GPS location. One thought while out exploring is that the model did a great job predicting where we would find very large quantities of bramble without any cover. It didn't have high confidence in other areas where we found smaller brambles under partial cover. Since TESSERA is learned representation from remote sensing data (Sentinel 1 and 2), it would make sense that bramble partially obscured from above might be harder to spot. This is something we can potentially tease apart when we have more validation data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, we were satisfied the model was doing a good job in the park area and decided to pick a hotspot the model was predicting in part of a residential street. We drove over to find an empty plot that did indeed have a lot of bramble!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another hotspot was on Fen Road and we stopped by to find this absolute unit:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, we headed back in to Cambridge to see what one of the big hotspots in North Cambridge was like. To our amusement we ended up at the local nature reserve Bramblefields, which, true to its name, has a lot of bramble.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was pleasantly surprised by how good Gabriel's model was for its simplicity. Great work!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We had hoped to actually re-run the model based on the data we were gathering but that proved tricky on a laptop, in a park. Given the richness of the TESSERA embeddings and the simplicity of the classifiers being used, a mobile phone-based human-in-the-loop active learning setup could be practical..&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45377748</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 19:28:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New Quasi-Moon Discovered Orbiting Earth, but It's Been Around for Decades</title><link>https://explorersweb.com/new-quasi-moon-discovered-orbiting-earth-but-its-been-around-for-decades/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7777217bfc065bf0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Astronomers have found a space rock that has been quietly hanging around Earth for decades: a tiny asteroid named 2025 PN7. This so-called “quasi-moon” isn’t a true moon or a mini-moon, because it orbits the Sun rather than our planet. But its orbit is so similar to Earth’s that it will be our companion for around another 60 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though the quasi-moon orbits the Sun, it occasionally looks from our vantage point like it is looping around us. However, our orbits are slightly different, so sometimes it lags behind us and sometimes it seems to lead us. But since the little asteroid’s orbit around the Sun is very close to one Earth year, it is always pretty close.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025 PN7 is just 19 meters across and might be the smallest quasi-moon ever found. Its minuscule size means that it can be quite tricky to spot. As astronomers put it, its “visibility windows” are very narrow. We can only see it through very large telescopes when its position and the lighting are favorable. That’s partly why it evaded detection for so long.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Entered orbit in 1957&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although the Pan-STARRS1 telescope in Hawaii discovered it in August 2025, the quasi-moon has been in this orbit for far longer. When researchers later trawled through archived images, they found that 2025 PN7 had shown up decades earlier. They think it likely entered its current orbit in 1957.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It won’t stay with us in this dance forever. Simulations suggest that it will keep up company for another 60 years before it wanders off in another direction. In that time, its distance from Earth will change quite a bit. So far, it has varied between 4 million kilometers at its closest and 18 million kilometers at its furthest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2025 PN7 is one of seven quasi-moons in Earth-like orbits, and seems to be the smallest and least stable. Astronomers aren’t exactly sure where it came from. It does not pose any threat to us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“These asteroids are relatively easy to access for unmanned missions and can be used to test planetary exploration technologies [relatively cheaply],” said Carlos de la Fuente Marcos, lead author of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45378871</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 20:50:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factory Raises $50M Series B</title><link>https://factory.ai/news/series-b</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ed41c6f668801462"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have raised $50M for our Series B at a valuation of $300M, led by NEA, Sequoia Capital, J.P. Morgan, Nvidia, and other industry leaders. Droids are now #1 on Terminal Bench and available to anyone, with any model, in any interface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Factory Raises $50M Series B&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have raised $50M for our Series B at a valuation of $300M. The round was led by NEA, Sequoia Capital, J.P. Morgan, Nvidia, Abstract Ventures, Mantis Ventures, and other industry leaders including Frank Slootman, Nikesh Arora, and Aaron Levie.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The best software development agents will be the best general agents. Droids are the best software development agents in the world, reaching #1 on Terminal Bench. Terminal Bench is the most challenging general software development benchmark, going beyond just coding to evaluate agents on tasks like modernizing legacy code, debugging dev environments, training AI models, and managing cloud infrastructure. Droids using sub-frontier models outperform agents from research labs running their own frontier models—by a wide margin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, Droids are available to anyone, with any model, in any interface: CLI, IDE, Slack, Linear, Browser. Read more about achieving #1 on Terminal Bench.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every AI coding platform forces you to choose: one IDE, one LLM, one agent, one interface. Subscribing and unsubscribing from plans to try and stay at the cutting edge is now obsolete. Developers deserve a choice. Factory is giving choice back to developers. Droids work with any LLM, in any IDE, in local or remote, and in any interface. You can delegate tasks to Droids from your Terminal, your IDE, Slack, Linear, or on the web. For further customization, you can use headless mode to set up scripts or triggers to run Droids tailored to your team's workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Factory's platform for Agent-Native Development has been globally rolled out at enterprise engineering organizations such as MongoDB, EY, Bayer, Zapier, and Clari. Enterprises are seeing results across the SDLC: 31x faster feature delivery, 96.1% shorter migration times, 95.8% reduction in on-call resolution times, and more time for developers to focus on design and architecture. Droids accelerate the less exciting but very real bottlenecks that occur in large, complex organizations: migrations, refactors, testing, documentation, code review.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are a tiny but prolific team in San Francisco (with a median typing speed of 120 wpm) committed to building the best experience for developers and delivering real business outcomes to customers. If you are an unreasonably relentless and obsessed builder, Factory is where you belong.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45378910</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 20:53:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>RedoxFS is the default filesystem of Redox OS, inspired by ZFS</title><link>https://doc.redox-os.org/book/redoxfs.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="1c99101b8162c9f1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;RedoxFS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the default filesystem of Redox OS, inspired by ZFS and adapted to a microkernel architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Redox had a read-only ZFS driver but it was abandoned because of the monolithic nature of ZFS that created problems with the Redox microkernel design.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(It's a replacement for TFS)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Current features:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compatible with Redox and Linux (FUSE)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Copy-on-write&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Data/metadata checksums&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Transparent encryption&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Standard Unix file attributes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File/directory size limit up to 193TiB (212TB)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File/directory quantity limit up to 4 billion per 193TiB (2^32 - 1 = 4294967295)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Disk encryption fully supported by the Redox bootloader, letting it load the kernel off an encrypted partition.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MIT licensed&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being MIT licensed, RedoxFS can be bundled on GPL-licensed operating systems (Linux, for example).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Tooling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RedoxFS tooling can be used to create, mount and edit contents of an &lt;code&gt;.img&lt;/code&gt; file containing RedoxFS. It can be installed with:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cargo install redoxfs
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you found errors while installing it, make sure to install &lt;code&gt;fuse3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Create a disk&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can create an empty, non bootable RedoxFS by allocating an empty file with &lt;code&gt;fallocate&lt;/code&gt; then run &lt;code&gt;redoxfs-mkfs&lt;/code&gt; to initialize the whole image as &lt;code&gt;RedoxFS&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fallocate -l 1G redox.img
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;redoxfs-mkfs redox.img
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Mount a disk&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To mount the disk, run &lt;code&gt;redoxfs [image] [directory]&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;mkdir ./redox-img
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;redoxfs redox.img ./redox-img
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It will mount the disk using FUSE underneath.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Unmount&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unmount the disk using FUSE unmount binary:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;fusermount3 ./redox-img
&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45379325</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 21:25:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Word Made Lifeless. Are we becoming stochastic parrots?</title><link>https://hedgehogreview.com/issues/lessons-of-babel/articles/the-word-made-lifeless</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ff0098e48035f739"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are moments when finding the right word takes on special urgency. You might be talking, over beers, with a friend going through a wrenching divorce. Or talking with your own spouse about the antipathies that keep welling up between you and have now risen to a crisis, and whether you can still picture a future you both want. In such moments, you need words called forth by the singular person before you and the singular crisis at hand. To look for guidance in “what one says,” or to fall into cliché, would be a serious failing—a failure to bring yourself into full presence with the other. To indulge in euphemisms or to be insistently optimistic would be a different sort of failing—a failure to trust another to endure un-prettified truth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Such moments often take you to the edge of your understanding of life and its significance and trials. Your thoughts are not already clear, worded, needing only to be enunciated. They are half-formed and obscure. Words are the medium with which you can give them sufficient definiteness to truly have them. The initial thing—the embryonic thought—is on the way to being. It is determinate enough that you can recognize the right words for it when you find them, but not yet so determinate that the words flow easily. By wording what is at the still-hazy horizon of our thought, we illuminate it. And in the realm of thought, illumination is the same thing as being. The power of the word is, then, a creative power, a power to give birth to thought—that is, to move thoughts toward greater clarity, which is to say, toward full and vivid being. For our deepest and most formative thoughts—the thoughts that form the central elements of our conception of what we are called to do with this life—this is a long road, a road we will be traversing for our entire lives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In difficult conversations, the operation of this questing and creative power is sometime audible. There are pauses, false starts and restarts, sometimes an explicit cancellation, a “No, that’s not the word for it,” or “That’s not quite what I’m trying to say.” At such times, we feel the allure of what Heidegger rightly took to be the characteristic Greek conception of the human form of being: “Being on the way toward what is to be uncovered.” As Plato put it, the human form of existence is not, in the full and strict sense, to be (einai). Being in the fullest sense is reserved for those things that never change: numbers, geometric shapes, goodness. Humans are on the way to being. Their life is a continual becoming or being born (gignesthai—the Greek word has both meanings). In Bob Dylan’s folksier formulation, “He not busy being born is busy dying.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The quest for words is a crucially important driver of this continuous emergence toward being. As we bring our thoughts to words, we give to ourselves a more definite and concerted identity. This too is sometimes audible, and even visible. There is a difference between a speaker who is reading a paper without thinking the thoughts being articulated and a speaker who is having the thoughts expressed by his words. In the latter case, you can hear the speaker gathered up and enlivened by his speech. This is what fresh and truly fitting words do: They awaken us. They reenact the uncanny event of the quickening of clay.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matters are quite otherwise with the new text generators we have so recently brought into our lives, and to which we now delegate a rapidly growing share of our quest for fitting words. If we can speak of thinking here, it is thinking of a wholly different kind. These new entities have no still-hazy intimations of their own that their words might either crystallize or bastardize. There is no possibility of felt urgency in their quest for words, none of that nearly erotic excitement we humans feel when we finally have the thought we have been groping for. They have no pangs of conscience when their words sound shallow or cliché. Indeed, cliché is their special strength: They cleave to the center of gravity of the vast sea of human-generated texts, finding each new word by predicting what human beings would most likely say. They have nothing of their own to say, no life from which they might say it, nor any soul or self their words might fashion or disfigure. They are, as it has aptly been put, stochastic parrots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It would be a brazen slander for anyone to add: and so are we, as Sam Altman did in a 2023 tweet soon after the release of ChatGPT: “i am a stochastic parrot, and so r u.” Such words could emerge only from a willful forgetting of the lived experience of being human and of seeking to say something worthwhile to fellow humans. No one speaking to his own child in a moment of despair, or to his spouse in a moment of marital reckoning, could consciously aim for faithful mimicry of the patterns laid down by past generations of fellow mimickers. To hear yourself, suddenly, as speaking in this way would be to lose all faith in your capacity to rise to the occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a lamentable impulse, especially among some academics dedicated to the study of the human mind and consciousness, to dismiss the line of thought I’ve just put forward as intellectual cowardice. Dispassionate empirical inquiry, it is said, has revealed that what looks most special about us is a mere trick of light. We must own up to this hard fact. We can learn what makes us tick by seeing what it takes for a machine to mimic us convincingly. The charge of unseriousness applies to those whose language has religious roots—who talk, say, about the Word made flesh, or who have stopped quoting the Bible yet still retain the quasi-religious idea that human beings have a special importance unequaled by the other animals. Such ideas spring from inherently unreliable sources: if not from religion or its enduring traces, then from “species-ist” self-congratulations, or from the fear T.S. Eliot showed us in a handful of dust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On this dispute, I side with Nietzsche in thinking that the scientistic humblers of humanity are tangled in performative contradiction. They profess an unwavering devotion to the truth. Yet this stance—if it is to be more than an arbitrary whim—requires an affirmation of the great value of unflinching lucidity. That is, it requires serious attachment to a recognizable vision of the good or noble mode of thought for human beings. When we affirm such an ideal, we thereby open a gap between our words and the ideals to which we strive to lift them. And when we resolve to lift our words across that gap, we have affirmed ourselves as something very different from stochastic parrots.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pretend for a moment that you’ve been granted the enormous memory and data-processing capacity of the new generation of large language models (LLMs). You could then adopt and hold yourself to the standard of successful word choice that they use. Actually, we don’t have to pretend: We can already ensure that our words are meeting this standard simply by letting the LLMs choose them for us. It is obvious that we could not pursue any worthy ideal of speech while applying this suddenly available method. There is, after all, only an occasional coincidence between the word that is the most probable successor to a string of already-written words and the next word required by any worthy ideal, including unflinching lucidity. This should come as no surprise. It takes only a moment’s serious thought to see that stochastic parroting is utterly beneath us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or, at any rate, I hope we see this. Yet this insight might prove fragile. As Iris Murdoch once wrote, “Man is a creature who makes pictures of himself and then comes to resemble the picture.” We should keep this in mind when we assess Sam Altman’s declaration that we are all stochastic parrots. If we were to internalize this picture of ourselves, we might slowly release our attachment to whatever aspirations and ideals are obviously at odds with it. We would then be living more faithfully in accordance with the self-conception recommended by certain enthusiasts of “human-level” AI. Which is to say, we would be busy dying.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Biblical Moment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After these initial polemics, I would very much like to adopt a more moderate tone. I would like to earn your trust with sober, understated speech. Unfortunately, my topic makes it very hard for me to adopt this tactic. There is, to my ear, one word that screams out to be applied to our headlong rush into the Age of Artificial Intelligence. That word is biblical.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I will begin with the biblical creation story—by which I mean, the creation story yielded by reading Genesis through the lens of the opening lines of the Gospel of John. This story has it that the universe begins with “the Word,” and that this unfamiliar thing, this “Word,” is God. Everything we know—the earth, the heavens, the light of day, the night, the waters, the land, the grass and trees and fruits, the birds and beasts—came forth from this Word. We too came forth from the Word, and not only from the Word but in the image and likeness of the Word. Our participation in the Word is our distinguishing attribute, our divine gift.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we human beings are fashioning a new being in what Altman and many others believe to be our image and our likeness. This being is thought by these enthusiasts to share with us the power of the Word. Indeed, there is a widespread expectation that it will soon equal or exceed the human level of facility with this power. It would be possible, I suppose, for someone moved by the biblical creation story to regard this as the highest fulfillment yet of the Imitatio Dei. God created us in his image and his likeness. Lacking the power of creation ex nihilo, the nearest imitation open to us is to create a being with found materials in our own image and likeness. This would be a grand case—maybe the grandest possible case—of paying it forward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet it seems far more plausible to read our moment as the apotheosis of the sin of pride. It is, on this latter reading, the moment when we insert ourselves in God’s place on the Sistine Chapel ceiling, extending our finger across the cosmos and giving life to the Adam of the new machinic age, the one now stretching its newfound powers toward us—that is, toward what some regard as human-level intelligence, and what I am tempted to regard as a dangerously distorted vision of our intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What’s the Word?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not every day that human history teeters on whether we have arrived at a tenable answer to a perennial and deeply obscure philosophical problem. We are teetering now. So much hinges on whether we have understood this special power of ours, this power of the Word. What if we have got it wrong? We would then be in the midst of enacting (or, for believers, reenacting) the biblical creation story in the key of travesty. What stray and perhaps uncontainable thing might then be taking shape in the laboratories of Silicon Valley? If we can credit this thing with thinking (and I have my doubts), how will its thinking differ from our own? And what consequences might this difference have for us?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, then, what is the Word? As most of us know, the Greek term at issue here—the term used by John—is logos. In the centuries leading up to the writing of the New Testament, it was widely accepted among Greek philosophers that logos is a crucial, and perhaps the most crucial, of the distinctive capabilities possessed by human beings. Yet translations of the relevant philosophical works rarely render logos as “the word.” Logos is usually translated as “reason” when referring to a mental faculty, and “discourse” or “speech” or “[reasoned] account” when referring to the characteristic products of this faculty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For these philosophers, then, and for the world of thought in which John the Apostle came of age, we humans are distinguished by a form of thinking that makes essential the use of language. Yet the thinking in question is decidedly not exhausted by mastery of language. It brings us into contact with, and takes direction from, realities that lie beyond language and that give to language the great significance that it has. If it were not for the capacity of logos to reach beyond language and find significance and guidance there, the Word would be a lifeless thing—or so I will try to show.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s begin with an example that I would guess is common ground for all of us: Plato’s Republic. The entirety of Socrates’ discourse in the Republic is put forward in response to Glaucon’s request for a logos (a reasoned account) of justice. Socrates makes clear that the ultimate source of any real insight he can offer is the good itself and the light it casts on justice. Keen eyesight is required, he says—by which he means that the mind’s eye must be cleared of distractions and turned toward timeless truths. What we then might hope to glimpse—the good, or that variant of it that we call justice—cannot be exhaustively captured in words. We can perhaps help others to see it more clearly, either with decades of soul-shaping education or (if shortcuts are needed) with images and allegories and myths. But the point of this education, or of these literary devices, is to help us see what lies beyond words. The dialectical exchange of words can prepare the soul for an illuminating encounter with and apprehension of the good, but it cannot confer what is known in this encounter. The good is undefinable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the ancient Greek thinkers we are considering, logos is not an all-purpose capacity, a kind of cognitive horsepower equally suited to plumb any object of thought. We might use logos solely to burnish our reputation or to gain wealth or political power. But if we understand what logos is, we will see that these are serious misuses. Logos has a substantive telos. Our power of worded thought comes fully into its own, and brings us fully into our own, when rising toward an increasingly clear apprehension of its proper object, the good. This was clearly Plato’s view. And, notwithstanding their ontological and epistemological disagreements about the good, Aristotle held this view as well. He too thought the vocation of the strange sort of animal we are, the animal with logos, is to grasp the good and the just and to lift itself toward these ideals under their inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This calling seems to have no correlate in the lives of other animals. While other animals reliably pursue their good, they do not do so from an understanding of the goodness of so doing. It is only human beings, as far as we can tell, who pursue the good under the idea of its goodness. When things go well in human lives, the cosmos comes to contain a distinctive kind of goodness that would otherwise be lacking. It contains goodness that is not merely an instance of the good but also a self-standing tribute to the good. Human goodness makes manifest the peculiar kind of property that goodness is: a property that cannot be known without being loved and thereby internalized. A being that cannot love cannot understand the good and hence cannot share in the power of logos. Such a being is not made in the image and likeness of the Word. It cannot be at once an instance of and a tribute to the good.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We humans do, of course, have the power to bring into being new possessors of the power of the word. This does not require fancy technology. We do it by having children and educating them—that is, by begetting, not by making. Our powers of making have not yet advanced to the point where they can rival this technique.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Another Creation Story&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is another, decidedly non-biblical way of telling the story of the rise of artificial intelligence (AI). On this telling, we are living through the moment when the shaping of life forms by natural selection gives way to what it had for so long been mistaken for: intelligent design. A particularly clever ape, having decoded the blind dynamics that yielded its own intricate physiology and powerful brain, has created an environment in which advantageous mutations of code can be selected for what might loosely be called cognitive fitness. This has resulted in the intentional acceleration of the evolution of intelligence. We are in the first moments of this shift from natural selection in natural environments to artificial selection in virtual and symbolic environments, and we are already seeing its dramatic potential for speeding the evolution of cognitive power. But it is likely that we will soon witness a sudden leap forward into superintelligence—that is, intelligence that can quickly and repeatedly enhance itself by tinkering with its own software and even by designing and planning the production of new kinds of hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My guess is that this second creation story has far more currency than the first among the engineers who have devised this new technology, and who perhaps tend to pride themselves on their immunity to myths. On reflection, though, this story has every bit as much mythic resonance as the first, and hope for its enactment is perhaps as strongly driven by wish fulfillment as belief in the first. The first thing to note about this story is that it is a precise inversion of the biblical creation story. Now, almost two millennia after the writing of the Gospel of John, the software engineers of Silicon Valley are finally giving to John’s delusional talk of the Word something to which it can refer. Yet we are the creators of this newly minted Word, not it of us. Had a genuinely good creator really been there in the beginning, we would not have been consigned to the lives we have until now been stuck with. We would not have had to earn our food and shelter by the sweat of our brow. We would not have had to labor for years to make something of ourselves, only to enter, within a few quick decades, into an inexorable decline culminating in death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite these hardships, the new myth goes, we have worked our way, generation after generation, to a remarkably sophisticated understanding of the workings of the natural world. This has permitted us to create a new kind of intelligent being. While the powers of this new being are still in rapid development, there are those who think it will permit us to lift the various curses we have been living under. The curse of labor, the curse of ill health. There is even talk among the Silicon Valley intelligentsia that it will help us to “solve death”—either by devising medical procedures that can halt the aging process or by permitting us to encode what is essential to our being in a form that can be indefinitely preserved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In short, the Word really has come this time, some two millennia after we hallucinated its presence. It is here to fix a botched creation. It offers real blessings, not consoling fictions. Some think it might even offer salvation from death. We are moving in religious dimensions of meaning, but this time with ones and zeroes, not chants and incense. Those driving this heady story must feel themselves to be at the center of a nearly biblical remaking of the world, conjuring what in other ages would surely be counted as miracles. For the rest of us, and perhaps for them as well, this creates a nearly audible unease, a rapid oscillation between the sense that we are living in a time of marvels and the sense that all hell is on the verge of breaking loose. This anxious oscillation is, for me, the distinctive phenomenological marker of life in the mid-2020s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Who Is Shaping the Future?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The unease is intensified by the utter lack of public control over the sculpting of this technology that appears to be on the verge of changing everything. The Manhattan Project and the NASA Moon Missions were overseen directly by the government, whose ventures at least theoretically answer to the public. AI research is being steered and funded privately. Traditional economic theory would have it that this gives the public a different and perhaps more reliable mechanism of control—the mechanism of consumer sovereignty. But one of the more troubling markers of the contemporary economy is that consumer preferences appear to have been decoupled from the decisions of the largest R&amp;amp;D departments. This is visible—as Matt Crawford has pointed out—in the ongoing race to develop driverless cars, for which there is no discernible public clamor. It is visible, too, in the development of the comparatively primitive AI algorithms that have created the booming market in human attention. Consumers were hardly asking for units of their conscious awareness to be harvested, ideally in a vacant and suggestible condition, and sold to the highest bidder. And it is visible in the ongoing AI revolution, whose most valuable products might well be replacement workers, which is to say—at least in the short term—pink slips and poverty for most consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The development of AI reads less like a familiar chapter from the history of consumer capitalism and more like the storyboard of a Bond film in which we’ve all been cast as extras. There are, of course, differences. In place of the malice of a single unbalanced villain, we have a more familiar and realistic threat: good intentions shared by a powerful group with a grandiose sense of its world-historical mission. We have, more specifically, lavishly bankrolled techno-utopians caught up in dreams of a glowing future but not unaware that their do-goodism could easily backfire, causing enormous damage to the purported beneficiaries. They have presumably weighed the odds and deemed the risk worth taking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a question of entitlement here: Do the techno-utopians have the right to run such risks with our collective future? But there is a more fundamental question that does not apply, say, to those performing gain-of-function research for (what they believe to be) the public good. The question is this: Are they operating with a tenable conception of the human good? There is, after all, a notoriously fine line between utopian and dystopian visions. The techno-elites are now drawing this line on our behalf. Should we trust them with this job?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Leap In or Be Left Behind&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Socrates distinguished two fundamentally different uses of logos—a rhetorical use that bends our thoughts toward the strategic pursuit of worldly success, and a wisdom-loving use that helps us to clarify and come into harmony with our proper calling. The contemporary university is perhaps still torn between these two ideals, but it leans increasingly toward the former. This leads to strikingly inapt defenses of fields like philosophy or literature, which have no obvious place in any systematic plan of professional training. Administrators often remind students that these fields give them all-purpose cognitive skills that can be used in any career. There is some truth to this, but no real philosopher would explain the point of his field in such terms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my view, Plato’s most interesting critique of the instrumental use of language is found in the Phaedrus. Here we listen in on a conversation between Socrates and a young man, Phaedrus, who is torn between the appeal of philosophy and the enticements of the teachers of rhetoric. The choice between these opposing pictures of a proper education—and, by extension, of a well-lived life—has suddenly become personal for Phaedrus. He is mulling over a speech, and what appears to be a seduction bid, delivered earlier that morning by the distinguished orator Lysias. Lysias has argued that it is better to opt for an unloving sexual exchange than the mad ride of an erotic affair.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After hearing Phaedrus recount Lysias’s speech, Socrates offers two speeches of his own—one intended to outdo Lysias’s condemnation of erotic liaisons and another that heaps praises on the divine madness of love. Socrates then subjects all three speeches to scrutiny, with an eye to understanding what it is to make proper use of logos. It will turn out that to use words properly is to use them erotically, and that those who are not gripped by love will be deficient not only in their relationships but in their thought. By contrast, to use words badly is to use them in a lifeless or death-inducing manner. The choice before Phaedrus, then, boils down to love or death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Socrates sees things, the proper use of logos is to work toward, and to be transformed by, an increasingly clear grasp of the good. He regards this as an erotic undertaking. The more clearly we see the good, the more we long to bring ourselves into closer proximity to it. And the most promising path to the apprehension and internalization of the good is prolonged union and thoughtful conversation with a worthy lover.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rhetoricians like Lysias have a completely different view of what words are for. They compose their speeches with the sole aim of getting others to believe whatever they think it most advantageous to have them believe. The advantage Lysias seeks is reliable sexual access to the young Phaedrus, so he tries to convince Phaedrus that it is best to select an influential yet unloving suitor such as Lysias himself. Socrates claims that, because it was devised by beginning with a fixed conclusion and working backwards to premises that lend support to it, Lysias’s speech lacks the special sort of organic unity possessed by a living thing. What Socrates seems to mean is that in choosing his words, Lysias has inverted the temporal direction of genuinely living thought. He began where he ought to have ended, with the fixed conclusion, and moved forward to where he ought to have begun, with considerations that purport to determine what one ought to conclude. Since the speech was not born from one of those electrified strands of living thought in which opacity or perplexity about a crucially important question slowly gives way to clarity, it is not well-suited to ignite such a transformative awakening in those who hear it. Yet this sort of awakening is the distinctive activity of the human being.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the human being is, or is the image of, logos made flesh, what is at issue here is the refusal of the human, the turning of living flesh to stone. This was the special power, or curse, of King Midas. So it is quite apt that Plato turns to the myth of Midas to convey what is wrong with Lysias’s way of stringing words together. What Plato is telling us, with this metaphor, is that if you want to take the life out of someone, you should teach them to use words for maximal instrumental benefit. By contrast, if you want to enliven someone, as Socrates seems to want to enliven (or re-enliven) Phaedrus, you induce them to reflect earnestly on how best to live and think.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If logos were a purely instrumental power, meant for the efficient securing of worldly ends, it would make perfect sense to delegate our thinking and writing to the new generation of LLMs and to train our students to do likewise. Educators like me would be well-advised either to step aside or to devote themselves to teaching skillful prompt-writing and editing. These are the skills of text generation that will be in demand in the workplace of the future. There would be no further point in teaching students to find words for their own thoughts. This won’t happen in the workplace, so teaching students to do it would be as pointless as teaching students to do long division by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is no easy thing to become who we are called to become. We are often tempted to spare our loved ones from this struggle by somehow trying to do it for them. Heidegger calls this misguided form of beneficence “leaping in”—a term that aptly highlights what is wrong with it. It displaces another from a task that only they can do. To be spared this work is to be spared growth; it is to be left stunted. An often painful and arduous struggle is sidestepped, and the thing that steps in for you seems sure to be unobjectionable, at very least. This gets at what most worries me about the LLMs. Their stochastic parroting gives to their pronouncements a seductive simulacrum of authority—the authority of reigning opinion, the authority of the herd. Now that we can access this authority with the push of a button and undetectably attach our name to it, claiming it as our own, will we continue with the struggles that it promises to spare us from? Or will we be seduced by the frictionless-ness that is both the design ideal of the virtual realm and the central element of the technology sector’s operative notion of the human good?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My hope is that we will keep our eye on the line between the friction we should be relieved of and the friction that is an essential part of the well-lived human life. But a frictionless alternative existence is being crafted for us. It offers a respite from the struggles of life. We might easily take to life in this friction-free zone, despite—or perhaps because of—its deadening effects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our form of being is a never-completed becoming. We should welcome technological innovations that help us with this task of becoming and refuse those that promise to spare us this task. Yet the difficulty of this task will sorely tempt us to opt for innovations of the second kind. If we do, we will not in fact have sidestepped the task of becoming. We will have engaged in it badly, becoming shallower, less fully human.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45380671</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 23:31:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple Demands EU Repeal the Digital Markets Act</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/09/apple-demands-eu-repeal-the-digital-markets-act/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b9a134745b03d8a0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple has demanded Brussels scrap its landmark Big Tech legislation, marking a step up in US tech giants’ fight against European oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EU’s Digital Markets Act (DMA), which entered into force in 2022, aims to curb the power of Big Tech and level the playing field for smaller rivals, with fines of up to 10 percent of global revenue for companies that do not comply.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple’s call to repeal the law comes at a time of transatlantic tensions over the EU’s digital rule book, including the DMA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump has threatened to punish countries that “discriminate” against US companies with higher tariffs, and Meta’s Mark Zuckerberg has personally lobbied Trump against the DMA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The DMA should be repealed while a more appropriate fit for purpose legislative instrument is put in place,” the iPhone maker said in its response to a routine call for feedback on the Digital Markets Act.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The EU fined Apple €500 million in April following an investigation into whether the company’s rules prevented app developers from sending consumers to cheaper offers for products and services outside Apple’s ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45380690</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 23:33:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bluesky Alt Text Stream</title><link>https://bobbiec.github.io/bluesky-alt-text.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6972460eaef3f6a4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This demo is part of Image descriptions on Bluesky: not bad, could be better - see the blog post for more details!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The streaming tool itself is a fork of Simon Willison's Bluesky WebSocket Firehose (code here), with the following changes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Apache License Version 2.0, January 2004 http://www.apache.org/licenses/ TERMS AND CONDITIONS FOR USE, REPRODUCTION, AND DISTRIBUTION 1. Definitions. "License" shall mean the terms and conditions for use, reproduction, and distribution as defined by Sections 1 through 9 of this document. "Licensor" shall mean the copyright owner or entity authorized by the copyright owner that is granting the License. "Legal Entity" shall mean the union of the acting entity and all other entities that control, are controlled by, or are under common control with that entity. For the purposes of this definition, "control" means (i) the power, direct or indirect, to cause the direction or management of such entity, whether by contract or otherwise, or (ii) ownership of fifty percent (50%) or more of the outstanding shares, or (iii) beneficial ownership of such entity. "You" (or "Your") shall mean an individual or Legal Entity exercising permissions granted by this License. "Source" form shall mean the preferred form for making modifications, including but not limited to software source code, documentation source, and configuration files. "Object" form shall mean any form resulting from mechanical transformation or translation of a Source form, including but not limited to compiled object code, generated documentation, and conversions to other media types. "Work" shall mean the work of authorship, whether in Source or Object form, made available under the License, as indicated by a copyright notice that is included in or attached to the work (an example is provided in the Appendix below). "Derivative Works" shall mean any work, whether in Source or Object form, that is based on (or derived from) the Work and for which the editorial revisions, annotations, elaborations, or other modifications represent, as a whole, an original work of authorship. For the purposes of this License, Derivative Works shall not include works that remain separable from, or merely link (or bind by name) to the interfaces of, the Work and Derivative Works thereof. "Contribution" shall mean any work of authorship, including the original version of the Work and any modifications or additions to that Work or Derivative Works thereof, that is intentionally submitted to Licensor for inclusion in the Work by the copyright owner or by an individual or Legal Entity authorized to submit on behalf of the copyright owner. For the purposes of this definition, "submitted" means any form of electronic, verbal, or written communication sent to the Licensor or its representatives, including but not limited to communication on electronic mailing lists, source code control systems, and issue tracking systems that are managed by, or on behalf of, the Licensor for the purpose of discussing and improving the Work, but excluding communication that is conspicuously marked or otherwise designated in writing by the copyright owner as "Not a Contribution." "Contributor" shall mean Licensor and any individual or Legal Entity on behalf of whom a Contribution has been received by Licensor and subsequently incorporated within the Work. 2. Grant of Copyright License. Subject to the terms and conditions of this License, each Contributor hereby grants to You a perpetual, worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable copyright license to reproduce, prepare Derivative Works of, publicly display, publicly perform, sublicense, and distribute the Work and such Derivative Works in Source or Object form. 3. Grant of Patent License. Subject to the terms and conditions of this License, each Contributor hereby grants to You a perpetual, worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable (except as stated in this section) patent license to make, have made, use, offer to sell, sell, import, and otherwise transfer the Work, where such license applies only to those patent claims licensable by such Contributor that are necessarily infringed by their Contribution(s) alone or by combination of their Contribution(s) with the Work to which such Contribution(s) was submitted. If You institute patent litigation against any entity (including a cross-claim or counterclaim in a lawsuit) alleging that the Work or a Contribution incorporated within the Work constitutes direct or contributory patent infringement, then any patent licenses granted to You under this License for that Work shall terminate as of the date such litigation is filed. 4. Redistribution. You may reproduce and distribute copies of the Work or Derivative Works thereof in any medium, with or without modifications, and in Source or Object form, provided that You meet the following conditions: (a) You must give any other recipients of the Work or Derivative Works a copy of this License; and (b) You must cause any modified files to carry prominent notices stating that You changed the files; and (c) You must retain, in the Source form of any Derivative Works that You distribute, all copyright, patent, trademark, and attribution notices from the Source form of the Work, excluding those notices that do not pertain to any part of the Derivative Works; and (d) If the Work includes a "NOTICE" text file as part of its distribution, then any Derivative Works that You distribute must include a readable copy of the attribution notices contained within such NOTICE file, excluding those notices that do not pertain to any part of the Derivative Works, in at least one of the following places: within a NOTICE text file distributed as part of the Derivative Works; within the Source form or documentation, if provided along with the Derivative Works; or, within a display generated by the Derivative Works, if and wherever such third-party notices normally appear. The contents of the NOTICE file are for informational purposes only and do not modify the License. You may add Your own attribution notices within Derivative Works that You distribute, alongside or as an addendum to the NOTICE text from the Work, provided that such additional attribution notices cannot be construed as modifying the License. You may add Your own copyright statement to Your modifications and may provide additional or different license terms and conditions for use, reproduction, or distribution of Your modifications, or for any such Derivative Works as a whole, provided Your use, reproduction, and distribution of the Work otherwise complies with the conditions stated in this License. 5. Submission of Contributions. Unless You explicitly state otherwise, any Contribution intentionally submitted for inclusion in the Work by You to the Licensor shall be under the terms and conditions of this License, without any additional terms or conditions. Notwithstanding the above, nothing herein shall supersede or modify the terms of any separate license agreement you may have executed with Licensor regarding such Contributions. 6. Trademarks. This License does not grant permission to use the trade names, trademarks, service marks, or product names of the Licensor, except as required for reasonable and customary use in describing the origin of the Work and reproducing the content of the NOTICE file. 7. Disclaimer of Warranty. Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, Licensor provides the Work (and each Contributor provides its Contributions) on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied, including, without limitation, any warranties or conditions of TITLE, NON-INFRINGEMENT, MERCHANTABILITY, or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. You are solely responsible for determining the appropriateness of using or redistributing the Work and assume any risks associated with Your exercise of permissions under this License. 8. Limitation of Liability. In no event and under no legal theory, whether in tort (including negligence), contract, or otherwise, unless required by applicable law (such as deliberate and grossly negligent acts) or agreed to in writing, shall any Contributor be liable to You for damages, including any direct, indirect, special, incidental, or consequential damages of any character arising as a result of this License or out of the use or inability to use the Work (including but not limited to damages for loss of goodwill, work stoppage, computer failure or malfunction, or any and all other commercial damages or losses), even if such Contributor has been advised of the possibility of such damages. 9. Accepting Warranty or Additional Liability. While redistributing the Work or Derivative Works thereof, You may choose to offer, and charge a fee for, acceptance of support, warranty, indemnity, or other liability obligations and/or rights consistent with this License. However, in accepting such obligations, You may act only on Your own behalf and on Your sole responsibility, not on behalf of any other Contributor, and only if You agree to indemnify, defend, and hold each Contributor harmless for any liability incurred by, or claims asserted against, such Contributor by reason of your accepting any such warranty or additional liability. END OF TERMS AND CONDITIONS APPENDIX: How to apply the Apache License to your work. To apply the Apache License to your work, attach the following boilerplate notice, with the fields enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information. (Don't include the brackets!) The text should be enclosed in the appropriate comment syntax for the file format. We also recommend that a file or class name and description of purpose be included on the same "printed page" as the copyright notice for easier identification within third-party archives. Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner] Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations under the License.&lt;/quote&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45380726</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 23:36:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Conspiracy content drives anti-establishment sentiment on TikTok, YouTube</title><link>https://news.umich.edu/conspiracy-content-drives-anti-establishment-sentiment-on-tiktok-youtube/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45380858</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 23:55:29 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>