<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 22:08:31 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Why is Zig so cool?</title><link>https://nilostolte.github.io/tech/articles/ZigCool.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2e0298192ea533d8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;I can’t think of any other language in my 45 years long career that surprised more than Zig. I can easily say that Zig is not only a new programming language, but it’s a totally new way to write programs, in my opinion. To say it’s merely a language to replace C or C++, it’s a huge understatement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will present the features that I found to be most seductive in the language, and I will also present a brief overview about it. The goal is to present simple features for programmers to quick start in the language. Be aware, though, that many more features are affecting its acceptability in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably the most incredible virtue of Zig compiler is its ability to compile C code. This associated with the ability to cross-compile code to be run in another architecture, different than the machine where it is was originally compiled, is already something quite different and unique. These features alone, completely out-of-the-box, are causing an incredible impact in the industry already. In spite of that what we want to concentrate on is how to program in Zig and why should one choose Zig instead of any other language.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Installing the compiler is quite simple. In Zinglang’s download page one finds the compiler in several formats, depending on the processor or OS:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Windows 10, for example, one chooses the x86_64 zip file and copy its decompressed content in the desired directory. For example, in “Program Files”. I modified the root directory name to “zig-windows-x86_64” because in this way I can just copy another version of the compiler with no need to modify the path in Path environment variable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next, one adds this root directory path to the Path environment variable using Advanced System Properties (clicking on 1-4, pasting path on 5, and clicking “OK” on 6-8):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice that after setting the path to Zig’s root directory one can already use the compiler in CLI mode. That’s the recommended way to use it for the sake of simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s recommended to build a “Hello World!” program using the instructions in the “Getting Started” section in this site. An alternative installation procedure is also presented there, including for MacOS and Linux (“Installing manually” is highly recommended). It’s also recommended to check the “Language” Basis section, for a deeper insight of Zig language.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following sections will give a bird’s eye view of Zig language. Their goal is to instruct the programmer how to quickly start programming in Zig by just knowing a few basic concepts and commands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, a compact view on how to build programs and test modules is given.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, a deeper view on how low level programming can be done in Zig. A more detailed explanation on the examples used is also given.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Normally, variable declarations in Zig have potentially three parts. The first part contains the accessibility (&lt;code&gt;pub&lt;/code&gt; or nothing),
followed by the word &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;, followed by
the variable name. The second part, separated of the first part by a
colon, contains the variable type declaration. The third part is the
initialization of the variable. Only the first and third part are
compulsory in Zig, which is kind of puzzling, coming from Java or C. One
may wonder how the compiler discovers the variable type. The type in
this case is inferred by the initialization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;var sum : usize = 0;         // variable declaration with 3 parts&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Variables that don’t have their accessibility explicitly &lt;code&gt;pub&lt;/code&gt; are local to the module, that is, they aren’t
accessible outside the source file it was declared (just like
&lt;code&gt;static&lt;/code&gt; variables in C). It’s not recommended to have
variables declared &lt;code&gt;pub&lt;/code&gt; and it’s recommended to have just
few functions declared &lt;code&gt;pub&lt;/code&gt; in a module to discourage
coupling and encourage cohesion. The &lt;code&gt;pub&lt;/code&gt; functions behave
as the module’s API.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Zig, a &lt;code&gt;.{&lt;/code&gt; closed with a &lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt; is an
“anonymous struct literal” - an anonymous struct mostly used to
initialize the elements of another structure or to create a new
structure with its elements initialized. A &lt;code&gt;.{ }&lt;/code&gt; is an an
empty anonymous struct literal. The word &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt; followed by
a &lt;code&gt;{&lt;/code&gt; and closed with a &lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt; is a struct
declaration. One can initialize a variable with a type, which functions
as an alias to the type. Notice the “test block” allowing to
compile and execute tests without the need of an executable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bitfields are declared fields with types having specific sizes in a &lt;code&gt;packed struct&lt;/code&gt;. Pointers can point to a specific bit field
as shown here:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zig syntax is clearer than C’s, except that one would think it should be &lt;code&gt;[0..8]&lt;/code&gt;, but in reality it’s an open interval:
&lt;code&gt;[0..9)&lt;/code&gt;. Advantage in Zig: the type
declaration of &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt;, its initialization, test, and
incrementation are automatic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;[_]&lt;/code&gt; defines an array with unknown size. It must be followed
by the type of its elements (here &lt;code&gt;u8&lt;/code&gt;, unsigned
byte) and its initialization between &lt;code&gt;{&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt;. In this example below, the initialization is saying that
this is an array of unknown size (&lt;code&gt;[_]&lt;/code&gt;) where each element
is of type &lt;code&gt;u8&lt;/code&gt; (unsigned byte) and each element initialized
with zeros (&lt;code&gt;{0} ** 81&lt;/code&gt;). Notice that the size is also
inferred by the repetition factor (&lt;code&gt;81&lt;/code&gt;) of the
initialization (&lt;code&gt;{0}&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;var grid = [_]u8{0} ** 81;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;We see in the figure below a test environment with a loop interacting over the array and adding its elements. The &lt;code&gt;try expect&lt;/code&gt;
statement verifies that &lt;code&gt;sum&lt;/code&gt; is correct.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;code&gt;byte&lt;/code&gt; is not a type or reserved word in Zig.
Here, it’s a variable to hold each of the array’s elements on each step
of the loop. Notice that a variable declared between two &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;
with an array between the parenthesis of a for loop is always assumed of
the same type as the array elements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice also, that &lt;code&gt;usize&lt;/code&gt; is the natural unsigned integer
for the platform. That means on 64 bits machines it’s an
&lt;code&gt;u64&lt;/code&gt;, and in 32 bits machines it’s an &lt;code&gt;u32&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pointers to arrays can use pointer arithmetic only if the pointer is explicitly declared as a many-item pointer, here &lt;code&gt;[*]const i32&lt;/code&gt;. Notice that the array below is
&lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt;, can’t be changed, but that the pointer is
&lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When attributed the address of an individual array position, a pointer cannot be updated with pointer arithmetic. In this case, &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; only prevents its value to be changed with another
direct address attribution. To dereference pointers in Zig one uses the
&lt;code&gt;ptr.*&lt;/code&gt; as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zig can do many things in compilation time. Let’s initialize an array, for example. Here, a labelled break is used. The block is labelled with an &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; after its name &lt;code&gt;init&lt;/code&gt; and
then a value is returned from the block with &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This syntax may look overwhelming. &lt;code&gt;0..&lt;/code&gt; means an infinite
range starting with zero. In the &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt;, variables &lt;code&gt;pt&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; are respectively initialized with the address of
&lt;code&gt;initial_value&lt;/code&gt; array and zero. During the loop both are
incremented automatically and the loop stops right after dealing with
the array’s last position. Also notice how to dereference the
&lt;code&gt;pt&lt;/code&gt; pointer: &lt;code&gt;pt.*&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also interesting it’s how the array is declared in the labelled block. The array is called &lt;code&gt;initial_value&lt;/code&gt; and has 10
positions of the type &lt;code&gt;Point&lt;/code&gt; (declared afterwards).
Variables must be initialized in Zig. The way to explicitly not
initialize is with the reserved word &lt;code&gt;undefined&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Functions in Zig are declared with &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt; and are static by
default (cannot be imported in other files) in the file they are
declared, except when &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt; is preceded by &lt;code&gt;pub&lt;/code&gt;. A
function can be “inlined.” Function pointers are preceded by
&lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; and followed by the function prototype.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Structs can have functions. Here, a simple stack is implemented. This stack is declared and used only inside the module it is defined, and it accesses and modifies other data structures in the module that are irrelevant in this example. The stack can have at maximum 81 elements (as seen in &lt;code&gt;stk&lt;/code&gt; declaration), each one of type
&lt;code&gt;StkNode&lt;/code&gt;. Notice that ++ and –– operators don’t exist in Zig.
The equivalent += and –= should be used instead. The stack pointer is
just an integer used as an index in the &lt;code&gt;stk&lt;/code&gt; array.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice that the pointer &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; is not a
reserved word, but it’s just a convention) is not passed explicitly as a
parameter as one would normally expect. It is indirectly assumed that it
is a pointer to the instance of the stack the function is been called
from. In the example below, a stack pop would be called with
&lt;code&gt;stack.pop();&lt;/code&gt;. In this case the pointer &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt;
corresponds to a pointer to &lt;code&gt;stack&lt;/code&gt;. This pointer is then
somewhat equivalent to &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; in Java or C++.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Function &lt;code&gt;init()&lt;/code&gt; is the stack constructor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice as well that functions &lt;code&gt;pop&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;push&lt;/code&gt;
are “inlined.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To build an executable program one needs a &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt;
function, which indicates the program entry point as in Java or C
programs. When this function exists the set of modules can be compiled
to an executable code. A simple program can have a &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt;
function in the same file as the rest of the program. In many cases one
can also insert a main function at the end of a module to create an
executable in order to debug the module independently. Once debugged
this function can be commented out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In these situations one can use the following command line to compile &lt;code&gt;program.zig&lt;/code&gt; and to generate an executable program (on
Windows, a &lt;code&gt;program.exe&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;zig build-exe -O ReleaseFast program.zig&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;This can be put inside a batch file to prevent typos.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is probably the best feature of Zig as a programming language. This environment is normally used for testing, but it can also be used for prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A block in Zig is similar to a block in C or Java, that is, some code between &lt;code&gt;{&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt;. A test block is a
block that starts with &lt;code&gt;test "message" {&lt;/code&gt; and finishes with
&lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt;, where &lt;code&gt;"message"&lt;/code&gt; is a string containing the
message to be displayed when the test is executed (in this case only the
word message).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Test blocks are executed independently from an executable file. The final executable file does not execute the tests. The test blocks in a given &lt;code&gt;module.zig&lt;/code&gt; are compiled together with the entire code
in that file and executed by the following command:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;zig test module.zig&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a real life example, the test block from module example.zig is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;test " =&amp;gt; testing set and print functions" {
    set(
      "800000000003600000070090200" ++
      "050007000000045700000100030" ++
      "001000068008500010090000400"
    );
    std.debug.print("\n" ++
      "===================\n" ++
      "Input Grid\n" ++
      "===================\n",
      .{}
    );
    print();
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice that &lt;code&gt;example.zig&lt;/code&gt; alone has no main
function and, therefore, cannot generate an executable, but its test
block can be executed by using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;zig test example.zig&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the message says, the test block above tests the functions &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt;. As the code shows,
&lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; passes a string of decimal digits as a parameter,
followed by a print statement (which prints a header saying “Input Grid”
), followed itself by a call of the &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The real display in a command tool is the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s focus now on the &lt;code&gt;std.debug.print&lt;/code&gt; statement. This
statement is in fact a call to the function &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; in
&lt;code&gt;debug.zig&lt;/code&gt; in the standard Zig library &lt;code&gt;std&lt;/code&gt;. The
first parameter is a format string, and the second is an anonymous
struct (preceded by a dot) containing a list of variables to be
displayed using the format string. Since there is no formatting in the
format string, the struct is empty. This is how formatted prints are
done. This one will display in the stderr by default, as shown
above.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This all looks just like in C language, but there is a fundamental difference here. In C, the printf function dynamically interprets the format string in execution time, whereas in Zig it’s possible to deal with the literal string and the list of variables in compilation time. This is a difficult principle to grasp at the start. Many things can be executed in compilation time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using a debugger is not usually a straightforward task, except in IDEs that already integrate a debugger (as in Java IDEs such as Eclipse or Intellij IDEA) or in integrated development kits (such as w64devkit for C/C++).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A huge inconvenient in using debuggers in this way is that one must integrate the symbols, which not only bloats the code with information that is not useful to the program, but also requires compiling in Debug mode, which generates executable code that’s notoriously less efficient. Someone with practice in complex systems knows that it can be a very time consuming task.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zig offers a quite convenient hack in order to avoid these headaches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This built-in stops a program at the point where a &lt;code&gt;@breakpoint();&lt;/code&gt; is inserted in the source code when its
executable is run in a debugger. This is actually an useful feature to
debug optimized Zig code without the need of symbols.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All it’s needed is to trace the variables one wants to watch using &lt;code&gt;std.debug.print&lt;/code&gt; right before &lt;code&gt;@breakpoint();&lt;/code&gt; In
this way one can know what are the values of the variables at that exact
moment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a real life example, one generates an executable for module debug_example.zig which has the has the following &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pub fn main() !void {
    set(
      "800000000003600000070090200" ++
      "050007000000045700000100030" ++
      "001000068008500010090000400"
    );
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be able to double check with the results from example.zig, the parameter passed to &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; function in this
&lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; is the same string as the one passed to
&lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; in the test block in example.zig,
but this time one inserts the following code inside &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;
function:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;        if (c != 0) {
           print();
           std.debug.print(
              "Current digit {}\nposition in string {}\n" ++
              "line {}\ncolumn {}\ncode {b}\n", 
              .{c, k, i, j, code}
           );
           @breakpoint();
        }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;One can then generate the &lt;code&gt;debug_example.exe&lt;/code&gt; executable
with the following build command:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;zig build-exe debug_example.zig&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next, one uses a debugger to call &lt;code&gt;debug_example.exe&lt;/code&gt;. In
this case I used &lt;code&gt;gdb&lt;/code&gt;, a debugger for C/C++ included in
w64devkit, but it could be any debugger for executable programs. Once
inside &lt;code&gt;gdb&lt;/code&gt;, one needs to run the program using an
&lt;code&gt;r&lt;/code&gt; command and typing &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt; right after as
shown below. Notice that the program printed the grid with its contents
so far as well as the variables, stopping
at the point expected. Then, by typing &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; command followed
by an &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt; one continues tracing the grid contents and 
the variables. After that, one can continue by just typing 
&lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt; (it repeats the last command - &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt;, in this 
case). By continuing typing &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt; until the program finishes, 
the values found in the grid correspond to the values shown by the test 
block in &lt;code&gt;example.zig&lt;/code&gt; above, since both examples have the same
parameter passed to &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the introduction and the examples given in the previous sections, one can already start programming Zig for writing generic applications. For more advanced programmers, what follows is a more in-depth analysis of some interesting low-level features already used in the examples, but not yet explicitly commented.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The idea of the examples shown is to construct a module that sets (initializes) and displays a 9x9 matrix. This matrix will hold a Sudoku grid, that is, it will only contain elements with decimal digits. The initialization of the grid should guarantee that the grid satisfies the rules of Sudoku game, so it will contain no errors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time it would be also an excellent opportunity to demonstrate Zig’s low level capabilities, at least the most noticeable ones, and these examples fit this goal quite well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The whole hypothesis behind these examples is the representation of a grid digit as a bit in the position given by its value. This representation is quite convenient to detect if a digit is already present in the grid or not (these are basic rules of Sudoku grids). In spite of that, this is so encrypted it is only used internally in the module.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the purpose of having values that are easily understood by humans, the digits are actually stored in the matrix as standard &lt;code&gt;u8&lt;/code&gt; integers. Even though the input grid in the examples is
given in string format, the ASCII characters are internally converted to
&lt;code&gt;u8&lt;/code&gt; integers. The digits’ storage in the grid is organized
linearly, line by line, in an array with 81 positions, called
&lt;code&gt;grid&lt;/code&gt; in the examples:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;var grid = [_]u8{0} ** 81;        // Sudoku grid stored linearly&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;To verify grid correctness, one needs to access the elements by its respective line and column. In other words, one needs to access the elements as in a matrix. The strategy is to create an array of pointers with 9 positions, each one pointing to the start of each line. Blocks of code cannot in principle return a value, but in Zig they can with labeled breaks:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;const matrix = fill9x9: {         // matrix array to allow access  
   var m : [9][*]u8 = undefined;  // to grid element as a matrix, 
   var pt : [*]u8 = &amp;amp;grid;        // thus: element = matrix[i][j]
   for (0..9) |i| {               //
      m[i] = pt;                  // stores pointers of each line
      pt += 9;                    // at each position of matrix
   }                              //
   break :fill9x9 m;              // initializes matrix with m
};&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the loop, &lt;code&gt;m&lt;/code&gt; is returned outside the block
using a &lt;code&gt;break :fill9x9 m;&lt;/code&gt; command. Notice that
&lt;code&gt;fill9x9&lt;/code&gt; corresponds to the name of a label placed right
before the beginning of the block.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supposing &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;j&lt;/code&gt;, respectively an
element’s line and column, any element of the grid can be accessed using
this notation:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;element = matrix[i][j]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key concept used here is the replacement of an integer decimal digit &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; by an integer &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; such as:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;      i ∈ [1,9]  →  code = 2ⁱ⁻¹
      i = 0      →  code = 0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other words, the only bit of &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; that is set to
&lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; is the bit at the position &lt;code&gt;i-1&lt;/code&gt; if
&lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; is between &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;9&lt;/code&gt;, otherwise
all bits of &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; are zero.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; for
each digit&lt;p&gt;The table below shows the correspondence between digits and their binary representation:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; in
Zig&lt;p&gt;The value of &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; is calculated in the function
&lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; using a left shift operator only if &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; is
not zero:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;code = @as(u9,1) &amp;lt;&amp;lt; (c-1);&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Zig, constants must have a proper size in order to allow an operation to be compiled and to attribute the the result of an operation to a given variable. In this case, &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; is declared of type
&lt;code&gt;u9&lt;/code&gt;. That’s another fundamental quality of Zig, to be able
to have variables with arbitrary bit size. As can be
seen in the table above, the maximum value that &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; can have is 256,
which requires at least 9 bits to represent. The built-in
&lt;code&gt;@as&lt;/code&gt; allows to cast the &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; constant to type
&lt;code&gt;u9&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By representing digits as bits one can mirror the entire grid in much simpler ways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The array &lt;code&gt;lines&lt;/code&gt; mirrors the entire grid by representing
each line with a &lt;code&gt;9&lt;/code&gt; bits integer, each bit representing a
decimal digit that might be present in the a line:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;var   lines   = [_]u9{0} ** 9; &lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, by just accessing this array with the line &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; of an element in the 9x9 grid one can know if a given
digit is already present in that line, by just performing a bitwise
and ( &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; ) with the digit’s
&lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt;, in this way:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;lines[i] &amp;amp; code&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the result of the operation above is zero, this means the digit is not yet present in the line &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt;. Otherwise we have a
duplicate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The array &lt;code&gt;columns&lt;/code&gt; mirrors the entire grid by
representing each column with a &lt;code&gt;9&lt;/code&gt; bits integer:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;var   columns = [_]u9{0} ** 9;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, by just accessing this array with the column &lt;code&gt;j&lt;/code&gt; of an element in the 9x9 grid one can know if a given
digit is already present in that column, by just performing a bitwise
and ( &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; ) with the digit’s
&lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt;, in this way:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;columns[i] &amp;amp; code&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the result of the operation above is zero, this means the digit is not yet present in the column &lt;code&gt;j&lt;/code&gt; . Otherwise it’s a
duplicate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s suppose an empty Sudoku grid, as it is the case when one is populating the grid with the input string as done in the examples. A new digit inserted at any empty element, must not already exist in the entire line, column or cell containing the new element.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s suppose now this grid, already initialized:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A cell is each one of the nine 3x3 grids delimited by the thick lines. The key knowledge to understand at this point is that each specific element in the 9x9 grid has a unique line, column and cell that contains this element.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, the first cell of the grid contains the values: 3, 5, 6, 8, and 9. Therefore, the values: 1, 2, 4 and 7 are missing. Let’s suppose one is willing to place the value 7 in one of the empty places in the first cell. Obviously, one cannot place it in the only empty element of the first line, because 7 is already present in that line. One cannot place it in the only empty place in the first column either since 7 is already in that column. One can only place the 7 in one of the two empty elements of the second line. But one can’t know for sure which one is the good one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine now the second cell, which contains the values: 1, 5, 7, and 9. One can see that the only possible element in this cell where an 8 can be placed is in the first line at the empty position on the right of the value 7.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arrays &lt;code&gt;lines&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;columns&lt;/code&gt; take care of
checking duplicates in lines and in columns. A new array is then needed
to check duplicates in cells.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The array &lt;code&gt;cells&lt;/code&gt; mirrors the entire grid by representing
each cell with a &lt;code&gt;9&lt;/code&gt; bits integer:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;var   cells   = [_]u9{0} ** 9;    // all elements at each cell&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is where things get more complicated. One cannot access &lt;code&gt;cells&lt;/code&gt; directly using the line or the column. It would be
easier if one could access &lt;code&gt;cells&lt;/code&gt; as a 3x3 matrix. This can
be done mimicking what has been done for the 9x9 matrix, that is,
filling the array &lt;code&gt;cell&lt;/code&gt; as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;const cell = fill3x3: {           // cell array to allows access
   var m : [3][*]u9 = undefined;  // cell elements as a matrix,
   var pt : [*]u9 = &amp;amp;cells;       // cell[cindx[i]][cindx[j]]
   for (0..3) |i| {               // 
      m[i] = pt;                  // stores pointers of each line
      pt += 3;                    // at each position of cell
   }                              //
   break :fill3x3 m;              // initializes cell with m
};                                //&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now one needs to determine the line and column in &lt;code&gt;cell&lt;/code&gt; matrix from the line and column of the element in the
original 9x9 grid. One could use integer divisions to divide the line
and column by 3 to obtain the proper indexes, but a division operation
is notoriously slow. Two divisions makes it even worse. One can use the
following array to give the result of the division as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;const cindx   = [_]usize{ 0,0,0, 1,1,1, 2,2,2 };&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, by just accessing this matrix with the line &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; and column &lt;code&gt;j&lt;/code&gt; of an element in the 9x9 grid,
one can know if a given digit is already present in this element’s cell
by just performing a bitwise and ( &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; )
with the digit’s &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt;, in this way:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cell[cindx[i]][cindx[j]] &amp;amp; code&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the result of the operation above is zero, this means the digit is not yet present in the cell. Otherwise it’s a duplicate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The complete test to verify if an element is duplicated can be done by composing with a bitwise or ( &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt; )
all the previous elements in the same line, column and cell, and then
performing a bitwise and ( &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; ) with
the element’s &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt;, in this way:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;if (((lines[i]|columns[j]|cell[cindx[i]][cindx[j]])&amp;amp;code) !=  0) {
    unreachable;
}&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the result is zero it’s because the element doesn’t exist yet in its line, column or cell. If the result is not zero the program stops because it tries to run the instruction &lt;code&gt;unreacheable&lt;/code&gt;. This
is the simplest way to explicitly indicate an execution error in Zig.
Notice that the actual code in &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; function also prints the
details where the error occurs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, replacing the &lt;code&gt;'0'&lt;/code&gt; right after the first
&lt;code&gt;'8'&lt;/code&gt; by a &lt;code&gt;'5'&lt;/code&gt; in the string passed to
&lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; gives the following error while testing example.zig:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is because in column 1 there was already a 5 in line 3 as the error message says. The error is due to a panic caused by reaching an unreachable code at function &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; as indicated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In function &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;, a double &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loop
interacts line by line to copy each new element from the input string
&lt;code&gt;s&lt;/code&gt; into the grid as indicated below (variable &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt;
keeps the index of the new input character in the string
&lt;code&gt;s&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;   for ( 0..9 ) |i| {
      line = matrix[i];
      for ( 0..9 ) |j| {
        c = @intCast(s[k]-'0');
        if (c != 0) {
          code = @as(u9,1) &amp;lt;&amp;lt; (c-1);
          ⋮  // rest of the code
        }
        line[j] = c;
        k+= 1;  
      }
   }&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The character is converted to an &lt;code&gt;u4&lt;/code&gt; (variable
&lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt;) by subtracting &lt;code&gt;'0'&lt;/code&gt; from it. If the new
element to be inserted in the grid is not equal to zero (
&lt;code&gt;c != 0&lt;/code&gt; ), &lt;code&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; (calculated with a left shift
instruction as indicated) is copied in each of the mirror grids, by
doing a bitwise or ( &lt;code&gt;|=&lt;/code&gt; ) with the
corresponding mirror grid, that is:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;    lines[i] |= code;
    columns[j] |= code;
    cell[cindx[i]][cindx[j]] |= code;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No test is required to explicitly test if the value of &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt;
is between &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;9&lt;/code&gt; because an overflow will
occur at execution time when the shift operation is executed. For
example, replacing the &lt;code&gt;'0'&lt;/code&gt; right after the first
&lt;code&gt;'8'&lt;/code&gt; of the input string by a &lt;code&gt;':'&lt;/code&gt; in the string
passed to &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; gives the following error while testing example.zig:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By substituting the same &lt;code&gt;'0'&lt;/code&gt; by a &lt;code&gt;'/'&lt;/code&gt; a
similar execution error will issued. The program will work only if the
values are between &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;9&lt;/code&gt;, that is, if the
input grid contains only decimal digits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many Sudoku grids on the web also represent &lt;code&gt;'0'&lt;/code&gt; as a
&lt;code&gt;'.'&lt;/code&gt;. That’s the reason the following line exists in
&lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;if (s[k] == '.') c = 0;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will conveniently bypass the shift operation because the value of &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; is zero.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The forced errors shown in the two sections above demonstrate important features of Zig that might have passed inconspicuously. One is Zig’s robustness. In the case of the shift operation no wrong behavior is allowed and the situation is caught at execution time, as has been shown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One might think that all the efforts in Zig are towards efficiency, but here it’s a typical case where performance was traded for robustness. One can have mixed feelings about this decision, when performance was the ultimate goal. In C, for example, it’s the programmer’s problem if a shift operation loses a bit and this translates in better performance for this specific Assembler instruction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another feature demonstrated in the two sections above is the possibility of using the test blocks for prototyping as suggested at the beginning of the article. The possibilities are numerous, even though the application shown was only to debug certain situations in cases of error.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These features alone demonstrate an awesome power, very rare in programming languages, particularly in compiled programing languages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is all quite surprising and let one think that many advantages previously found only in interpreted languages are gradually migrating to compiled languages in order to offer more performance. [A reference to Mojo here looks appropriate].&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zig resemblance to interpreted languages is quite striking, particularly with its concept of compile time execution, unfortunately not stressed enough in this article. This is an aspect of Zig that on one hand makes it particularly different and powerful but on the other hand difficult to grasp.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I concentrated more in instructing how to have a quick and easy start with the language, and in simple aspects that make Zig language cool, although there are many other aspects not mentioned here that are also quite impressive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The examples shown here are simplified versions of a more involved program to solve Sudoku grids, which was also developed in Java and in C. The documentation in this repository explains in detail most of the structures and algorithms used to accomplish that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45852328</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 23:04:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Valdi – A cross-platform UI framework that delivers native performance</title><link>https://github.com/Snapchat/Valdi</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="777bc13e072966c6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Beta Status: Valdi has been widely used in Snap's production apps for the last 8 years. We're calling this a beta because our tools and documentation need more battle testing in the open source world. Valdi will exit beta when we're happy with the developer experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valdi is a cross-platform UI framework that delivers native performance without sacrificing developer velocity. Write your UI once in declarative TypeScript, and it compiles directly to native views on iOS, Android, and macOS—no web views, no JavaScript bridges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A basic Valdi component:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Component } from 'valdi_core/src/Component';

class HelloWorld extends Component {
  onRender() {
    const message = 'Hello World! 👻';
    &amp;lt;view backgroundColor='#FFFC00' padding={30}&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;label color='black' value={message} /&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/view&amp;gt;;
  }
}&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valdi is a cross-platform UI framework designed to solve the fundamental problem of cross-platform development: velocity vs. runtime performance. For 8 years, it has powered a large portion of Snap's production apps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike frameworks that rely on web views or JavaScript bridges, Valdi compiles declaratively rendered TypeScript components into platform-native views. Valdi also includes several other performance advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Automatic view recycling - Global view pooling system reuses native views across all screens, dramatically reducing inflation latency&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Optimized component rendering - Components re-render independently without triggering parent re-renders, enabling fast incremental updates&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Optimized layout engine - C++ layout engine runs on the main thread with minimal marshalling overhead&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Viewport-aware rendering - Only visible views are inflated, making infinite scrolling performant by default&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learn more in our Performance Optimization Guide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valdi eliminates the traditional compile-test-debug cycle that slows native development:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Instant hot reload - See changes in milliseconds on iOS, Android, or desktop without recompiling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Full VSCode debugging - Set breakpoints, inspect variables, profile performance, and capture heap dumps directly in VSCode&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Familiar syntax - TSX components with TypeScript for type safety&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valdi integrates easily into existing apps - start small and scale as needed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Embed Valdi in native - Drop Valdi components into existing UIKit or Android view hierarchies&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Embed native in Valdi - Use platform-specific views within Valdi layouts via &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;custom-view&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Polyglot modules - Write performance-critical code in C++, Swift, Kotlin, or Objective-C with type-safe bindings to TypeScript&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Full-stack architecture - Build entire features in Valdi with worker threads for background processing, eliminating platform-specific bridge code&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valdi generates type-safe bindings between TypeScript and native platforms:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Automatic code generation - TypeScript interfaces compile to Kotlin, Objective-C, and Swift bindings&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Native API access - Direct access to platform APIs and third-party native libraries through polyglot modules&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bidirectional communication - Pass complex data structures and callbacks between TypeScript and native code safely&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Native protobuf support - Seamless integration with protobuf for efficient data serialization&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Powers critical features in production Snap apps.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Supports advanced animations, real-time rendering, and complex gesture systems&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Flexbox layout system with automatic RTL support&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Worker threads for multi-threaded JavaScript execution&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Native animations for native look and feel&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Advanced gesture recognition with platform-native handling&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Built-in testing framework with component-level unit tests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bazel integration for reproducible, incremental builds&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Join our Discord for support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please follow the contributing guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valdi is made available under the MIT License.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45852854</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:14:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Immutable Software Deploys Using ZFS Jails on FreeBSD</title><link>https://conradresearch.com/articles/immutable-software-deploy-zfs-jails</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="eab8fd53f56d28e5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Immutable Software Deploys Using ZFS Jails on FreeBSD&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FreeBSD’s native support for ZFS snapshots and jails provides a powerful foundation for immutable deployments. By creating a new jail from a ZFS snapshot for every release, we get instant roll‑backs, zero‑downtime upgrades, and a clean, reproducible environment. This article walks through the (very opinionated) flow that we use. From jails setup through running Caddy as a health‑checked reverse proxy in front of the jails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;1. Prerequisites&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FreeBSD 14+ (or the latest stable release) offers the necessary ZFS and jail primitives. Enabling ZFS with a zpool installed allows cheap, instant cloning. The Caddy v2 binary handles TLS, reverse-proxying, and health checks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;2. Architecture Overview&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;+--------------------+      +------------------------+      +-------------------+
|                    |      |                        |      |                   |
|   Caddy (reverse   | &amp;lt;-&amp;gt;  |  Immutable Jails       | &amp;lt;-&amp;gt;  |  Application      |
|   proxy &amp;amp; health-  |      |  (ZFS snapshot/clone)  |      |  inside each jail |
|   check)           |      |                        |      |                   |
|                    |      |                        |      |                   |
+--------------------+      +------------------------+      +-------------------+
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Caddy routes to the currently healthy jail.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Each deployment clones a ZFS snapshot → new jail.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;After passing health‑checks, Caddy reconfigures to the new jail.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;3. Configure the Jails Host Server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a new loopback network interface for the jails. We'll use 172.16.0.0/12 which means jails can use any IP address within the range 172.16.0.1 – 172.31.255.254. Then create a new service to manage the loopback interface via a file at '/usr/local/etc/rc.d/lo1' with the following content:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh
# PROVIDE: lo1
# REQUIRE: NETWORKING
# BEFORE:  jail
# KEYWORD: shutdown

. /etc/rc.subr

name="lo1"
command="ifconfig"

start_cmd="${command} ${name} create &amp;amp;&amp;amp; ${command} ${name} inet 172.16.0.1 netmask 255.240.0.0 up"
stop_cmd="${command} ${name} down"

run_rc_command "$1"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then make the service start at boot and enable it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;chmod +x /usr/local/etc/rc.d/lo1
sysrc lo1_enable="YES"
service lo1 start
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now we can go onwards to enabling jails:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sysrc jail_enable="YES"
sysrc jail_parallel_start="YES"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a /etc/jail.conf file with the below configurations so that it includes the configurations for each jail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;NOTE: Each jail configuration should be placed in a separate file in '/etc/jail.conf.d/'.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt;NOTE: The leading '.' before include is required.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;.include "/etc/jail.conf.d/*.conf";
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a ZFS dataset mount point and paths for the jails:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;zfs create -o mountpoint=/usr/local/jails zroot/jails
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create child datasets for the jails:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Contains the compressed files of the downloaded userlands.
zfs create zroot/jails/media
# Will contain the templates.
zfs create zroot/jails/templates
# Will contain the containers.
zfs create zroot/jails/containers
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;4. Build the Base Image Template&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download the base FreeBSD image and unpack it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Set environment variable for the FreeBSD version. Note that the cut is to remove the patch level.
export FREEBSD_VERSION=$(freebsd-version | cut -d- -f1-2)
zfs create -p zroot/jails/templates/$FREEBSD_VERSION
fetch https://download.freebsd.org/ftp/releases/$(uname -m)/$FREEBSD_VERSION/base.txz -o /usr/local/jails/media/$FREEBSD_VERSION-base.txz
tar -xf /usr/local/jails/media/$FREEBSD_VERSION-base.txz -C /usr/local/jails/templates/$FREEBSD_VERSION --unlink
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Copy critical files to the image template:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cp /etc/resolv.conf /usr/local/jails/templates/$FREEBSD_VERSION/etc/resolv.conf
cp /etc/localtime /usr/local/jails/templates/$FREEBSD_VERSION/etc/localtime
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update the image template to the latest patch level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;freebsd-update -b /usr/local/jails/templates/$FREEBSD_VERSION fetch install
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, create a ZFS snapshot of the base image template. From this snapshot we we'll use ZFS clones to create new jails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;zfs snapshot zroot/jails/templates/$FREEBSD_VERSION@base
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;5. Create a New Jail&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check which ip addresses on the 'lo1' loopback interface are in use so that we can assign an available ip address to the new jail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ifconfig lo1 | grep 'inet ' | awk '{print $2}'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lookup the git repo commit hash for the latest commit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git ls-remote https://github.com/yourusername/mygitrepo.git | head
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clone the base image template to create a new jail. We'll be creating a new jail within our git repo path.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;export FREEBSD_VERSION=$(freebsd-version | cut -d- -f1-2)
export JAIL_NAME=mygitrepo_gitSHA
zfs clone zroot/jails/templates/$FREEBSD_VERSION@base zroot/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a config file for the jail to be located at '/etc/jail.conf.d/$JAIL_NAME.conf'.&lt;lb/&gt; We name the jail using the SHA of the git commit that we're deploying.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;mygitrepo_gitSHA {
	# STARTUP/LOGGING
	exec.start = "/bin/sh /etc/rc";
	exec.stop = "/bin/sh /etc/rc.shutdown";
	exec.consolelog = "/var/log/jail_console_${name}.log";

	# PERMISSIONS
	allow.raw_sockets;
	exec.clean;
	mount.devfs;

	# HOSTNAME/PATH
	host.hostname = "${name}";
	path = "/usr/local/jails/containers/${name}";

	# NETWORK. We're using the lo1 loopback interface that we created for jails to use.
	interface = lo1;
	ip4.addr = 172.16.0.2; # Use an available ip address within the range of the lo1 interface. You can find available ip addresses by running "ifconfig lo1 | grep 'inet ' | awk '{print $2}'"
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start the jail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;service jail start $JAIL_NAME
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confirm that the jail's ipaddress is within the range of the lo1 interface:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;jexec $JAIL_NAME ifconfig lo1 | awk '/inet /{print $2}'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confirm that the jail is up and what it's running:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;jls
jexec $JAIL_NAME ps aux
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;6 Create a Proof of Concept Service Within Our Newly Created Jail&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the proof of concept Go hello world binary that we'll run as a service within the jail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// main.go
package main

import (
	"fmt"
	"log"
	"net/http"
)

func main() {
	http.HandleFunc("/", func(w http.ResponseWriter, r *http.Request) {
		fmt.Fprintf(w, "Hello World!")
	})
	http.HandleFunc("/up", func(w http.ResponseWriter, r *http.Request) {
		w.WriteHeader(http.StatusOK)
	})
	log.Fatal(http.ListenAndServe(":8080", nil))
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build the binary and place it in the jail's bin directory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;go build main.go
mkdir -p /usr/local/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME/usr/local/bin
cp main /usr/local/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME/usr/local/bin/main
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a service file for the binary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh
#
# PROVIDE: main
# REQUIRE: LOGIN
# KEYWORD: shutdown

. /etc/rc.subr

name="main"
rcvar="main_enable"

# Path to your Go binary
command="/usr/local/bin/main"
pidfile="/var/run/${name}.pid"

# Redirect output to a log file
logfile="/var/log/${name}.log"

# How to start the process
start_cmd="${name}_start"
stop_cmd="${name}_stop"

main_start() {
	echo "Starting ${name}..."
	daemon -p "${pidfile}" -f -o "${logfile}" "${command}"
}

main_stop() {
	echo "Stopping ${name}..."
	if [ -f "${pidfile}" ]; then
		kill "$(cat ${pidfile})" &amp;amp;&amp;amp; rm -f "${pidfile}"
	else
		echo "No pidfile found; process may not be running."
	fi
}

load_rc_config $name
: ${main_enable:="NO"}

run_rc_command "$1"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Copy the service file to the jail's /etc/rc.d directory and enable it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;mkdir -p /usr/local/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME/usr/local/etc/rc.d
cp /usr/local/etc/rc.d/main /usr/local/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME/usr/local/etc/rc.d/main
jexec $JAIL_NAME chmod +x /usr/local/etc/rc.d/main
jexec $JAIL_NAME sysrc main_enable=YES
jexec $JAIL_NAME service main start
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setup log rotation so they don't fill up the disk, and do the initial rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;jexec $JAIL_NAME sh -c "echo '/var/log/main.log  root:wheel  644  5  100  *  Z  /var/run/main.pid' &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/newsyslog.conf.d/main.conf"
jexec $JAIL_NAME newsyslog -vF
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confirm the service is running.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;jexec $JAIL_NAME service main status
curl 172.16.0.2:8080 # Use the ip address of the jail.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;7 Setup Caddy (reverse proxy)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a 'service', or similar, group to the system if it doesn't already exist. This group should have permissions to write to the pid and log files. Make sure to use the same group in the next step when we create a user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pw groupadd service
chown root:service /var/run
chown root:service /var/log
chmod 770 /var/run
chmod 770 /var/log
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a user and assign permissions. Make sure to add the user without login capabilities and assign to the 'service' group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pw useradd caddy -d /nonexistent -s /sbin/nologin -c "Caddy Service Account" -g service
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note: We're running Caddy behind a Cloudflare Tunnel on port 8080. If you're not and using a port below 1024 then you'll need to setup security/portacl-rc to enable privileged port binding, and configure for user 'caddy'. This will allow the caddy user to bind to ports below 1024.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;pkg install security/portacl-rc sysrc portacl_users+=caddy sysrc portacl_user_caddy_tcp="http https" sysrc portacl_user_caddy_udp="https" service portacl enable service portacl start&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install Caddy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cd /usr/ports/www/caddy
make install clean
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Change the ownership of the caddy binary and required files to the caddy user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;chown caddy:service /usr/local/bin/caddy
chmod 740 /usr/local/bin/caddy
chown -R caddy:service /var/log/caddy
chown -R caddy:service /usr/local/etc/caddy
chown -R caddy:service /var/db/caddy
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Setup log rotation so they don't fill up the disk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;echo '/var/log/caddy.log  root:wheel  644  5  100  *  Z  /var/run/caddy.pid' &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/newsyslog.conf.d/caddy.conf
newsyslog -vF
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add the caddy service to the system startup and make sure it runs as the caddy user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sysrc -f /etc/rc.conf caddy_enable="YES"
sysrc -f /etc/rc.conf caddy_user="caddy"
sysrc -f /etc/rc.conf caddy_group="service"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Caddy reads the configuration file at '/usr/local/etc/caddy/Caddyfile'.&lt;lb/&gt; Inside the jail, '/up' returns '200 OK' when healthy.&lt;lb/&gt; Caddy polls the specified health‑check endpoint using the healthcheck directive, routing traffic exclusively to backends that return a successful health check.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Important: We're only disabling automatic HTTPS because we're running behind a Cloudflare Tunnel. If that's not the case, you should enable automatic HTTPS by removing the 'auto_https off' line.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# /usr/local/etc/caddy/Caddyfile
{
	auto_https off # Note: Disable automatic HTTPS since we're running behind a Cloudflare Tunnel.
}

:8080 {

	# Matcher and reverse proxy for serviceA.null.live.
	@serviceA host serviceA.null.live # Change the hostname to your actual hostname.
	reverse_proxy @serviceA 172.16.0.2:8080 {
		health_uri /up
		health_interval 10s
		health_timeout 5s
	}

	# Matcher and reverse proxy for serviceB.null.live.
	@serviceB host serviceB.null.live # Change the hostname to your actual hostname.
	reverse_proxy @serviceB 172.16.0.3:8080 {
		health_uri /up
		health_interval 10s
		health_timeout 5s
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;8. Deploy a New Jail and Switch Caddy to the New Jail&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a config file for the jail to be located at '/etc/jail.conf.d/$JAIL_NAME.conf'.&lt;lb/&gt; Make sure to replace the ip4.addr variable value with the next available ip address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;ifconfig lo1 | grep 'inet ' | awk '{print $2}'
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;mygitrepo_gitSHA {
	# STARTUP/LOGGING
	exec.start = "/bin/sh /etc/rc";
	exec.stop = "/bin/sh /etc/rc.shutdown";
	exec.consolelog = "/var/log/jail_console_${name}.log";

	# PERMISSIONS
	allow.raw_sockets;
	exec.clean;
	mount.devfs;

	# HOSTNAME/PATH
	host.hostname = "${name}";
	path = "/usr/local/jails/containers/${name}";

	# NETWORK. We're using the lo1 loopback interface that we created for jails to use.
	interface = lo1;
	ip4.addr = 172.16.0.3; # Use the ip address we found in the previous step.
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a new jail. We name our jail using the format: mygitrepo_gitSHA. For the repo of the application being deployed. This makes it easy to track which version of the application is running in each jail. The last line is used to confirm the jail is running.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git ls-remote https://github.com/yourusername/mygitrepo.git | head
export FREEBSD_VERSION=$(freebsd-version | cut -d- -f1-2)
export JAIL_NAME=mygitrepo_gitSHA
export SERVICE_NAME=conradresearchcom # Note: '-' are not allowed in service names.
zfs clone zroot/jails/templates/$FREEBSD_VERSION@base zroot/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME

# Copy the binary of the application to the jail. We'll use our 'main' demo app from previous steps.
go build main.go
mkdir -p /usr/local/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME/usr/local/bin
cp $SERVICE_NAME /usr/local/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME/usr/local/bin/$SERVICE_NAME

# Copy the rc.d script to the jail.
mkdir -p /usr/local/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME/usr/local/etc/rc.d
cp $SERVICE_NAME /usr/local/jails/containers/$JAIL_NAME/usr/local/etc/rc.d/$SERVICE_NAME

# Start the jail.
service jail start $JAIL_NAME
jexec $JAIL_NAME chmod +x /usr/local/etc/rc.d/$SERVICE_NAME
jexec $JAIL_NAME sysrc ${SERVICE_NAME}_enable=YES
jexec $JAIL_NAME service $SERVICE_NAME start
while ! curl -s -o /dev/null -w "%{http_code}" http://172.16.0.3:8080/up; do sleep 1; done
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using your favorite text editor, update the Caddy configuration at '/usr/local/etc/caddy/Caddyfile' to point to the new jail via updating the jail's IP address to the new jail's IP address. Then run the following command to reload Caddy:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;service caddy reload
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;9. Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By combining ZFS snapshots, FreeBSD jails, and a Caddy reverse‑proxy, you get:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Zero‑downtime upgrades.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Instant rollbacks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A predictable environment that can be reproduced at any time.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Give it a try, tweak the scripts for your own stack, and enjoy the peace of mind that comes with immutable infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cheers 🥂&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45852895</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:21:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mullvad: Shutting down our search proxy Leta</title><link>https://mullvad.net/en/blog/shutting-down-our-search-proxy-leta</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9e42cf9623e0a788"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Shutting down our search proxy Leta&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NewsÂ&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On November 27, 2025, we will shut down our search proxy, Leta.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Leta's primary benefit was that it acted as a privacy proxy for search. Pooling and caching requests on behalf of a great number of users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The search industry continues to undergo big changes. Leta will not be able to follow and will likely become less useful over time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similar privacy can be achieved through the combination of a VPN and a privacy-focused browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have therefore decided to discontinue Leta and continue to advance the development of state-of-the-art of VPNs and browser privacy - through our own work and research and in collaboration with our partners.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45852974</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:37:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Making Democracy Work: Fixing and Simplifying Egalitarian Paxos</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02743</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e09cf502047156ab"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Distributed, Parallel, and Cluster Computing&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 4 Nov 2025]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:Making Democracy Work: Fixing and Simplifying Egalitarian Paxos (Extended Version)&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:Classical state-machine replication protocols, such as Paxos, rely on a distinguished leader process to order commands. Unfortunately, this approach makes the leader a single point of failure and increases the latency for clients that are not co-located with it. As a response to these drawbacks, Egalitarian Paxos introduced an alternative, leaderless approach, that allows replicas to order commands collaboratively. Not relying on a single leader allows the protocol to maintain non-zero throughput with up to $f$ crashes of any processes out of a total of $n = 2f+1$. The protocol furthermore allows any process to execute a command $c$ fast, in $2$ message delays, provided no more than $e = \lceil\frac{f+1}{2}\rceil$ other processes fail, and all concurrently submitted commands commute with $c$; the latter condition is often satisfied in practical systems.&lt;lb/&gt;Egalitarian Paxos has served as a foundation for many other replication protocols. But unfortunately, the protocol is very complex, ambiguously specified and suffers from nontrivial bugs. In this paper, we present EPaxos* -- a simpler and correct variant of Egalitarian Paxos. Our key technical contribution is a simpler failure-recovery algorithm, which we have rigorously proved correct. Our protocol also generalizes Egalitarian Paxos to cover the whole spectrum of failure thresholds $f$ and $e$ such that $n \ge \max\{2e+f-1, 2f+1\}$ -- the number of processes that we show to be optimal.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45854862</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 07:29:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>My friends and I accidentally faked the Ryzen 7 9700X3D leaks</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/pcmasterrace/comments/1orc6jl/my_friends_and_i_accidentally_faked_the_ryzen_7/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45855933</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 11:27:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cekura (YC F24) Is Hiring</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45856069</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b9ee1a7b5dbe270d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cekura is growing fast, and we’re now building our Customer Success vertical from the ground up. If you love owning outcomes, turning customers into champions, and shaping 0→1 playbooks, this is for you.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You will be joining at that perfect moment where what we’ve built works and our customers are challenging us everyday.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We grew as much in the first week of November as in all of October - equal parts scary and exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We have openings in both our offices at San Francisco and Bengaluru. Come work with us to build the future of how agents are getting shipped!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://lnkd.in/eRU9RFQW https://lnkd.in/ewQvhcm3&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45856069</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 12:00:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Study identifies weaknesses in how AI systems are evaluated</title><link>https://www.oii.ox.ac.uk/news-events/study-identifies-weaknesses-in-how-ai-systems-are-evaluated/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7dc8d0970fb3495b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A new study led by the Oxford Internet Institute (OII) at the University of Oxford and involving a team of 42 researchers from leading global institutions including EPFL, Stanford University, the Technical University of Munich, UC Berkeley, the UK AI Security Institute, the Weizenbaum Institute, and Yale University, has found that many of the tests used to measure the capabilities and safety of large language models (LLMs) lack scientific rigour. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In Measuring What Matters: Construct Validity in Large Language Model Benchmarks, accepted for publication in the upcoming NeurIPS conference proceedings, researchers review 445 AI benchmarks – the standardised evaluations used to compare and rank AI systems. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The researchers found that many of these benchmarks are built on unclear definitions or weak analytical methods, making it difficult to draw reliable conclusions about AI progress, capabilities or safety. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Benchmarks underpin nearly all claims about advances in AI,” says Andrew Bean, lead author of the study. “But without shared definitions and sound measurement, it becomes hard to know whether models are genuinely improving or just appearing to.” &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Benchmarks play a central role in how AI systems are designed, deployed, and regulated. They guide research priorities, shape competition between models, and are increasingly referenced in policy and regulatory frameworks, including the EU AI Act, which calls for risk assessments based on “appropriate technical tools and benchmarks.” &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The study warns that if benchmarks are not scientifically sound, they may give developers and regulators a misleading picture of how capable or safe AI systems really are. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“This work reflects the kind of large-scale collaboration the field needs,” adds Dr. Adam Mahdi. “By bringing together leading AI labs, we’re starting to tackle one of the most fundamental gaps in current AI evaluation.” &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Key findings &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt; Lack of statistical rigour&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Only 16% of the reviewed studies used statistical methods when comparing model performance. This means that reported differences between systems or claims of superiority could be due to chance rather than genuine improvement. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list start="2" rend="ol"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt; Vague or contested definitions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Around half of the benchmarks aimed to measure abstract ideas such as reasoning or harmlessness without clearly defining what those terms mean. Without a shared understanding of these concepts, it is difficult to ensure that benchmarks are testing what they intend to.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Examples &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="1" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="1" data-aria-level="1"&gt;Confounding formatting rules – A test might ask a model to solve a simple logic puzzle but also require it to present the answer in a very specific, complicated format. If the model gets the puzzle right but fails the formatting, it looks worse than it really is. &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="1" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="1" data-aria-level="1"&gt;Brittle performance – A model might do well on short, primary school-style maths questions, but if you change the numbers or wording slightly, it suddenly fails. This shows it may be memorising patterns rather than truly understanding the problem&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="1" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="1" data-aria-level="1"&gt;Unsupported claims – If a model scores well on multiple-choice questions from medical exams, people might claim it has doctor-level expertise. But passing an exam is only one small part of what doctors do, so the result can be misleading.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Recommendations for better benchmarking &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The authors stress that these problems are fixable. Drawing on established methods from fields such as psychometrics and medicine, they propose eight recommendations to improve the validity of AI benchmarks. These include: &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="2" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="1" data-aria-level="1"&gt;Define and isolate: Provide a precise, operational definition for the concept being measured and control for unrelated factors. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="2" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="2" data-aria-level="1"&gt;Build representative evaluations: Ensure test items represent real-world conditions and cover the full scope of the target skill or behaviour. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="2" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="3" data-aria-level="1"&gt;Strengthen analysis and justification: Use statistical methods to report uncertainty and enable robust comparisons; conduct detailed error analysis to understand why a model fails; and justify why the benchmark is a valid measure for its intended purpose. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The team also provides a Construct Validity Checklist, a practical tool researchers, developers, and regulators can use to assess whether an AI benchmark follows sound design principles before relying on its results. The checklist is available at https://oxrml.com/measuring-what-matters/ &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The paper, Measuring What Matters: Construct Validity in Large Language Model Benchmarks, will be published as part of the NeurIPS 2025 peer-reviewed conference proceedings in San Diego from 2-7 December. The peer-reviewed paper is available on request. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Media spokespeople &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lead author: Andrew Bean, Doctoral Student, Oxford Internet Institute, University of Oxford &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Senior authors: Adam Mahdi, Associate Professor, and Luc Rocher, Associate Professor, Oxford Internet Institute, University of Oxford &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Contact &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For more information and briefings, please contact: &lt;lb/&gt; Anthea Milnes, Head of Communications &lt;lb/&gt; Sara Spinks / Veena McCoole, Media and Communications Manager &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;T: +44 (0)1865 280527 &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;M: +44 (0)7551 345493 &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;E: press@oii.ox.ac.uk &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;About the Oxford Internet Institute (OII) &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Oxford Internet Institute (OII) has been at the forefront of exploring the human impact of emerging technologies for 25 years. As a multidisciplinary research and teaching department, we bring together scholars and students from diverse fields to examine the opportunities and challenges posed by transformative innovations such as artificial intelligence, large language models, machine learning, digital platforms, and autonomous agents. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;About the University of Oxford &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oxford University was placed number one in the Times Higher Education World University Rankings for the tenth year running in 2025. At the heart of this success are the twin-pillars of our ground-breaking research and innovation and our distinctive educational offer. Oxford is world-famous for research and teaching excellence and home to some of the most talented people from across the globe. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Funding information &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="1" data-aria-level="1"&gt;A.M.B. is supported in part by the Clarendon Scholarships and the Oxford Internet Institute’s Research Programme on AI &amp;amp; Work. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="2" data-aria-level="1"&gt;A.M. is supported by the Oxford Internet Institute’s Research Programme on AI &amp;amp; Work. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="3" data-aria-level="1"&gt;R.O.K. is supported by a Fellowship from the Cosmos Institute. H.M. is supported by ESRC [ES/P000649/1] and would like to acknowledge the London Initiative for Safe AI. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="4" data-aria-level="1"&gt;C.E. is supported by the EPSRC Centre for Doctoral Training in Health Data Science (EP/S02428X/1) and the AXA Research Fund. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="5" data-aria-level="1"&gt;F.L. is supported by Clarendon and Jason Hu studentships. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="6" data-aria-level="1"&gt;H.R.K.’s PhD is supported by the Economic and Social Research Council grant ES/P000649/1. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="7" data-aria-level="1"&gt;M.G. was supported by the SMARTY (PCI2024-153434) project funded by the Agencia Estatal de Investigación (doi:10.13039/501100011033) and by the European Commission through the Chips Act Joint Undertaking project SMARTY (Grant 101140087). This material is based in part upon work supported by the National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship Program under Grant No. DGE-2139841. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="8" data-aria-level="1"&gt;O.D. is supported by the UKRI’s EPSRC AIMS CDT grant (EP/S024050/1). &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="9" data-aria-level="1"&gt;J.R is supported by the Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="10" data-aria-level="1"&gt;J.B. would like to acknowledge funding by the Federal Ministry of Education and Research of Germany (BMBF) under grant no. 16DII131. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="11" data-aria-level="1"&gt;A. Bibi would like to acknowledge the UK AISI systemic safety grant. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item data-leveltext="" data-font="Symbol" data-listid="3" data-list-defn-props="{&amp;quot;335552541&amp;quot;:1,&amp;quot;335559685&amp;quot;:720,&amp;quot;335559991&amp;quot;:360,&amp;quot;469769226&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Symbol&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469769242&amp;quot;:[8226],&amp;quot;469777803&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;left&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777804&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;469777815&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;hybridMultilevel&amp;quot;}" data-aria-posinset="12" data-aria-level="1"&gt;A. Bosselut gratefully acknowledges the support of the Swiss National Science Foundation (No. 215390), Innosuisse (PFFS-21-29), the EPFL Center for Imaging, Sony Group Corporation, and a Meta LLM Evaluation Research Grant. &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45856804</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 14:18:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Btop: A better modern alternative of htop with a gamified interface</title><link>https://github.com/aristocratos/btop</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7e8db9181da4b5e0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;News&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Documents&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Description&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Features&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Themes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Support and funding&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Prerequisites (Read this if you are having issues!)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Screenshots&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Keybindings&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Installation Linux/macOS&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compilation Linux&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compilation macOS&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compilation FreeBSD&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compilation NetBSD&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compilation OpenBSD&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Testing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GPU compatibility&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Installing the snap&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Configurability&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;License&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Btop release v1.4.0&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intel GPU support added, note that only GPU utilization, power usage and clock speed available to monitor. Thanks to @bjia56 for contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NetBSD support added. Thanks to @fraggerfox for contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See CHANGELOG.md and latest release for detailed list of new features, bug fixes and new themes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Btop release v1.3.0&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Big release with GPU support added for Linux and platform support for OpenBSD. Big thanks to @romner-set (GPU support) and @joske (OpenBSD support) for contributions. And a multitude of bugfixes and small changes, see CHANGELOG.md and latest release for detailed list and attributions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See news entry below for more information regarding GPU support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPU monitoring added for Linux!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compile from git main to try it out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use keys &lt;code&gt;5&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;6&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;7&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; to show/hide the gpu monitoring boxes. &lt;code&gt;5&lt;/code&gt; = Gpu 1, &lt;code&gt;6&lt;/code&gt; = Gpu 2, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gpu stats/graphs can also be displayed in the "Cpu box" (not as verbose), see the cpu options menu for info and configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that the binaries provided on the release page (when released) and the continuous builds will not have gpu support enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because the GPU support relies on loading of dynamic gpu libraries, gpu support will not work when also static linking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See Compilation Linux for more info on how to compile with gpu monitoring support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many thanks to @romner-set who wrote the vast majority of the implementation for GPU support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Big update with version bump to 1.3 coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First release of btop4win available at https://github.com/aristocratos/btop4win&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;More...&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Release v1.2.0 with FreeBSD support. No release binaries for FreeBSD provided as of yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again a big thanks to @joske for his porting efforts!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since compatibility with Linux, macOS and FreeBSD are done, the focus going forward will be on new features like GPU monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Release v1.1.0 with macOS support. Binaries in continuous-build-macos are only x86 for now. macOS binaries + installer are included for both x86 and ARM64 (Apple Silicon) in the releases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Big thank you to @joske who wrote the vast majority of the implementation!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work on the OSX [macOS] and FreeBSD branches, both initiated and mostly worked on by @joske, will likely be completed in the coming weeks. The OSX [macOS] branch has some memory leaks that needs to be sorted out and both have some issues with the processes cpu usage calculation and other smaller issues that needs fixing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to help out, test for bugs/fix bugs or just try out the branches:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;macOS / OSX&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Install and use Homebrew or MacPorts package managers for easy dependency installation
brew install coreutils make gcc@11 lowdown
git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git
cd btop
git checkout OSX
gmake&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FreeBSD&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo pkg install gmake gcc11 coreutils git lowdown
git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git
cd btop
git checkout freebsd
gmake&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that GNU make (&lt;code&gt;gmake&lt;/code&gt;) is recommended but not required for macOS/OSX but it is required on FreeBSD.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;macOS development have been started by @joske, big thanks :) See branch OSX for current progress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Linux version of btop++ is complete. Released as version 1.0.0&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will be providing statically compiled binaries for a range of architectures in every release for those having problems compiling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For compilation GCC 11 is required.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please report any bugs to the Issues page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The development plan right now:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1.1.0 macOS [OSX] support&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1.2.0 FreeBSD support&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1.3.0 Support for GPU monitoring&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1.X.0 Other platforms and features...&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Windows support is not in the plans as of now, but if anyone else wants to take it on, I will try to help.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is gonna take some time until it has complete feature parity with bpytop, since all system information gathering will have to be written from scratch without any external libraries. And will need some help in the form of code contributions to get complete support for BSD and macOS/OSX.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Resource monitor that shows usage and stats for processor, memory, disks, network and processes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;C++ version and continuation of bashtop and bpytop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Easy to use, with a game inspired menu system.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Full mouse support: all buttons with a highlighted key are clickable and mouse scrolling works in process list and menu boxes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fast and responsive UI with UP, DOWN key process selection.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Function for showing detailed stats for selected process.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ability to filter processes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Easy switching between sorting options.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tree view of processes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Send any signal to selected process.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pause the process list.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UI menu for changing all config file options.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Auto scaling graph for network usage.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Shows IO activity and speeds for disks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Battery meter&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Selectable symbols for the graphs.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Custom presets&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;And more...&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Btop++ uses the same theme files as bpytop and bashtop (some color values missing in bashtop themes).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See themes folder for available themes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Btop searches the following directories for system themes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;../share/btop/themes&lt;/code&gt;(this path is relative to the btop executable)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/share/btop/themes&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;/usr/share/btop/themes&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first directory that exists and isn't empty is used as the system themes directory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The user themes directory depends on which environment variables are set:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If &lt;code&gt;$XDG_CONFIG_HOME&lt;/code&gt;is set, the user themes directory is&lt;code&gt;$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/btop/themes&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Otherwise, if &lt;code&gt;$HOME&lt;/code&gt;is set, the user themes directory is&lt;code&gt;$HOME/.config/btop/themes&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Otherwise, the user themes directory is &lt;code&gt;~/.config/btop/themes&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;make install&lt;/code&gt; command places the default themes in &lt;code&gt;[$PREFIX or /usr/local]/share/btop/themes&lt;/code&gt;.
User created themes should be placed in the user themes directory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let me know if you want to contribute with new themes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can sponsor this project through GitHub. See my sponsors page for options.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or donate through PayPal or ko-fi.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any support is greatly appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the best experience run within a terminal with support for:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;24-bit truecolor (See list of terminals with truecolor support)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;256-color terminals are supported through 24-bit to 256-color conversion when setting "truecolor" to False in the options or with "-lc/--low-color" arguments.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;16 color TTY mode will be activated if a real tty device is detected. Can be forced with "-t/--tty" arguments.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Wide characters (Are sometimes problematic in web-based terminals)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also necessary is a UTF8 locale and a font that includes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unicode Block “Braille Patterns” U+2800 - U+28FF (Not needed in TTY mode or with graphs set to type: block or tty.)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unicode Block “Geometric Shapes” U+25A0 - U+25FF&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Unicode Block "Box Drawing" and "Block Elements" U+2500 - U+259F&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GPU monitoring also requires a btop binary built with GPU support (&lt;code&gt;GPU_SUPPORT=true&lt;/code&gt; flag).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See GPU compatibility section for more about compiling with GPU support.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;NVIDIA&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you have an NVIDIA GPU you must use an official NVIDIA driver, both the closed-source and open-source ones have been verified to work.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In addition to that you must also have the nvidia-ml dynamic library installed, which should be included with the driver package of your distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;AMD&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have an AMD GPU&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rocm_smi_lib&lt;/code&gt;is required, which may or may not be packaged for your distribution.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;INTEL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Requires a working C compiler if compiling from source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also requires the user to have permission to read from SYSFS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can be set with&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;make setcap&lt;/code&gt;(preferred) or&lt;code&gt;make setuid&lt;/code&gt;or by running btop with&lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;or equivalent.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you are having problems with the characters in the graphs not looking like they do in the screenshots, it's likely a problem with your systems configured fallback font not having support for braille characters.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;See Terminess Powerline for an example of a font that includes the braille symbols.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;See comments by @sgleizes link and @XenHat link in issue #100 for possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If text is misaligned and you use Konsole or Yakuake, turning off "Bi-Directional text rendering" is a possible fix.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Characters clipping into each other or text/border misalignments are not bugs caused by btop, but most likely a fontconfig or terminal problem where the braille characters making up the graphs aren't rendered correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Look to the creators of the terminal emulator you use to fix these issues if the previously mentioned fixes don't work for you.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Binaries for Linux are statically compiled with musl and work on kernel releases 2.6.39 and newer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Download btop-(VERSION)-(ARCH)-(PLATFORM).tbz from latest release and unpack to a new folder&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Notice! Use x86_64 for 64-bit x86 systems, i486 and i686 are 32-bit!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install (from created folder)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Run:&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;# use "make install PREFIX=/target/dir" to set target, default: /usr/local # only use "sudo" when installing to a NON user owned directory sudo make install&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Optional/Required for Intel GPU and CPU wattage) Set extended capabilities or suid bit to btop&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enables signal sending to any process without starting with&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;and can prevent /proc read permissions problems on some systems.&lt;p&gt;Is required for Intel GPU support and CPU wattage monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Run:&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;code&gt;# run after make install and use same PREFIX if any was used at install sudo make setcap&lt;/code&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;or&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;quote&gt;# run after make install and use same PREFIX if any was used at install # set SU_USER and SU_GROUP to select user and group, default is root:root sudo make setuid&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Run:&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo make uninstall&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Show help&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;make help&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Binary release (from native os repo)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;openSUSE &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Tumbleweed: &lt;code&gt;sudo zypper in btop&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;For all other versions, see openSUSE Software: btop&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tumbleweed: &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fedora &lt;quote&gt;sudo dnf install btop&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;RHEL/Rocky/AlmaLinux 8+ &lt;quote&gt;sudo dnf install epel-release sudo dnf install btop&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;FreeBSD &lt;quote&gt;pkg install btop&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;NetBSD &lt;quote&gt;pkg_add btop&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Binary release on Homebrew (macOS (x86_64 &amp;amp; ARM64) / Linux (x86_64))&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Homebrew &lt;quote&gt;brew install btop&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Requires at least GCC 14 or Clang 19.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Makefile also needs GNU &lt;code&gt;coreutils&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; (should already be installed on any modern distribution).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Btop++ supports Nvidia and AMD GPUs and Intel IGPUs out of the box on Linux x86_64, provided you have the correct drivers and libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gpu support for Nvidia or AMD will not work when static linking glibc (or musl, etc.)!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For x86_64 Linux the flag &lt;code&gt;GPU_SUPPORT&lt;/code&gt; is automatically set to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;, to manually disable gpu support set the flag to false, like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;make GPU_SUPPORT=false&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;cmake -DBTOP_GPU=false&lt;/code&gt; with CMake)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;NVIDIA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must use an official NVIDIA driver, both the closed-source and open-source ones have been verified to work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to that you must also have the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;nvidia-ml&lt;/code&gt;dynamic library installed, which should be included with the driver package of your distribution.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;AMD&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AMDGPU data is queried using the ROCm SMI library, which may or may not be packaged for your distribution. If your distribution doesn't provide a package, btop++ is statically linked to ROCm SMI with the&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;RSMI_STATIC=true&lt;/code&gt;make flag.&lt;p&gt;This flag expects the ROCm SMI source code in&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;lib/rocm_smi_lib&lt;/code&gt;, and compilation will fail if it's not there. The latest tested version is 5.6.x, which can be obtained with the following command:&lt;quote&gt;git clone https://github.com/rocm/rocm_smi_lib.git --depth 1 -b rocm-5.6.x lib/rocm_smi_lib&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install dependencies (example for Ubuntu 24.04 Noble)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo apt install coreutils sed git build-essential lowdown&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git cd btop&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;make&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Options for make:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;th&gt;Flag&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&lt;code&gt;VERBOSE=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To display full compiler/linker commands&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATIC=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For static compilation&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;QUIET=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For less verbose output&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STRIP=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To force stripping of debug symbols (adds&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s&lt;/code&gt;linker flag)&lt;code&gt;DEBUG=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sets OPTFLAGS to&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-O0 -g&lt;/code&gt;and enables more verbose debug logging&lt;code&gt;ARCH=&amp;lt;architecture&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To manually set the target architecture&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;GPU_SUPPORT=&amp;lt;true|false&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Enable/disable GPU support (Enabled by default on X86_64 Linux)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;RSMI_STATIC=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To statically link the ROCm SMI library used for querying AMDGPU&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;ADDFLAGS=&amp;lt;flags&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For appending flags to both compiler and linker&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Manually set which compiler to use&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;make ADDFLAGS=-march=native&lt;/code&gt;might give a performance boost if compiling only for your own system.&lt;p&gt;Notice! If using LDAP Authentication, usernames will show as UID number for LDAP users if compiling statically with glibc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo make install&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Append&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;PREFIX=/target/dir&lt;/code&gt;to set target, default:&lt;code&gt;/usr/local&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice! Only use "sudo" when installing to a NON user owned directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Optional/Required for Intel GPU support and CPU wattage) Set extended capabilities or suid bit to btop&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No need for&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;to enable signal sending to any process and to prevent /proc read permissions problems on some systems.&lt;p&gt;Also required for Intel GPU monitoring and CPU wattage monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run after make install and use same PREFIX if any was used at install.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo make setcap&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;SU_USER&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;SU_GROUP&lt;/code&gt;to select user and group, default is&lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo make setuid&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo make uninstall&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove any object files from source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;make clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove all object files, binaries and created directories in source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;make distclean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Show help&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;make help&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install build dependencies&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Requires Clang / GCC, CMake, Ninja, Lowdown and Git&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;For example, with Debian Bookworm:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo apt install cmake git g++ ninja-build lowdown&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone the repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd btop&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;# Configure cmake -B build -G Ninja # Build cmake --build build&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will automatically build a release version of btop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some useful options to pass to the configure step:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;th&gt;Configure flag&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DBTOP_STATIC=&amp;lt;ON|OFF&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Enables static linking (OFF by default)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DBTOP_LTO=&amp;lt;ON|OFF&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Enables link time optimization (ON by default)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DBTOP_GPU=&amp;lt;ON\|OFF&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;| Enable GPU support (ON by default) | |&lt;code&gt;-DBTOP_RSMI_STATIC=&amp;lt;ON\|OFF&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;| Build and link the ROCm SMI library statically (OFF by default) | |&lt;code&gt;-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;| The installation prefix ('/usr/local' by default) |&lt;p&gt;To force any other compiler, run&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt; cmake -B build -G Ninja&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --install build&lt;/quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;May require root privileges&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CMake doesn't generate an uninstall target by default. To remove installed files, run&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cat build/install_manifest.txt | xargs rm -irv&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Cleanup build directory&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --build build -t clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Requires at least GCC 14 or Clang 19.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Makefile also needs GNU coreutils and &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install and use Homebrew or MacPorts package managers for easy dependency installation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install dependencies (example for Homebrew)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;brew install coreutils make gcc@15 lowdown&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git cd btop&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;gmake&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Options for make:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;th&gt;Flag&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&lt;code&gt;VERBOSE=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To display full compiler/linker commands&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATIC=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For static compilation (only libgcc and libstdc++)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;QUIET=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For less verbose output&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STRIP=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To force stripping of debug symbols (adds&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s&lt;/code&gt;linker flag)&lt;code&gt;DEBUG=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sets OPTFLAGS to&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-O0 -g&lt;/code&gt;and enables more verbose debug logging&lt;code&gt;ARCH=&amp;lt;architecture&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To manually set the target architecture&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;ADDFLAGS=&amp;lt;flags&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For appending flags to both compiler and linker&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Manually set which compiler to use&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gmake ADDFLAGS=-march=native&lt;/code&gt;might give a performance boost if compiling only for your own system.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake install&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Append&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;PREFIX=/target/dir&lt;/code&gt;to set target, default:&lt;code&gt;/usr/local&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice! Only use "sudo" when installing to a NON user owned directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Recommended) Set suid bit to make btop always run as root (or other user)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake setuid&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;No need for&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;to see information for non user owned processes and to enable signal sending to any process.&lt;p&gt;Run after make install and use same PREFIX if any was used at install.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;SU_USER&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;SU_GROUP&lt;/code&gt;to select user and group, default is&lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;wheel&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake uninstall&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove any object files from source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;gmake clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove all object files, binaries and created directories in source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;gmake distclean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Show help&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;gmake help&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install build dependencies&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Requires Clang, CMake, Ninja, Lowdown and Git&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;brew update --quiet brew install cmake git llvm ninja lowdown&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone the repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd btop&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;# Configure export LLVM_PREFIX="$(brew --prefix llvm)" export CXX="$LLVM_PREFIX/bin/clang++" export CPPFLAGS="-I$LLVM_PREFIX/include" export LDFLAGS="-L$LLVM_PREFIX/lib -L$LLVM_PREFIX/lib/c++ -Wl,-rpath,$LLVM_PREFIX/lib/c++ -fuse-ld=$LLVM_PREFIX/bin/ld64.lld" cmake -B build -G Ninja # Build cmake --build build&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will automatically build a release version of btop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some useful options to pass to the configure step:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;th&gt;Configure flag&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DBTOP_LTO=&amp;lt;ON|OFF&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Enables link time optimization (ON by default)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;| The installation prefix ('/usr/local' by default) |&lt;p&gt;To force any specific compiler, run&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt; cmake -B build -G Ninja&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --install build&lt;/quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;May require root privileges&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CMake doesn't generate an uninstall target by default. To remove installed files, run&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cat build/install_manifest.txt | xargs rm -irv&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Cleanup build directory&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --build build -t clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Requires at least Clang 19 (default) or GCC 14.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that GNU make (&lt;code&gt;gmake&lt;/code&gt;) is required to compile on FreeBSD.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install dependencies&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo pkg install gmake coreutils git lowdown&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git cd btop&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;gmake&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Options for make:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;th&gt;Flag&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&lt;code&gt;VERBOSE=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To display full compiler/linker commands&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATIC=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For static compilation (only libgcc and libstdc++)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;QUIET=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For less verbose output&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STRIP=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To force stripping of debug symbols (adds&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s&lt;/code&gt;linker flag)&lt;code&gt;DEBUG=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sets OPTFLAGS to&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-O0 -g&lt;/code&gt;and enables more verbose debug logging&lt;code&gt;ARCH=&amp;lt;architecture&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To manually set the target architecture&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;ADDFLAGS=&amp;lt;flags&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For appending flags to both compiler and linker&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Manually set which compiler to use&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gmake ADDFLAGS=-march=native&lt;/code&gt;might give a performance boost if compiling only for your own system.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake install&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Append&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;PREFIX=/target/dir&lt;/code&gt;to set target, default:&lt;code&gt;/usr/local&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice! Only use "sudo" when installing to a NON user owned directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Recommended) Set suid bit to make btop always run as root (or other user)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake setuid&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;No need for&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;to see information for non user owned processes and to enable signal sending to any process.&lt;p&gt;Run after make install and use same PREFIX if any was used at install.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;SU_USER&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;SU_GROUP&lt;/code&gt;to select user and group, default is&lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;wheel&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake uninstall&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove any object files from source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;gmake clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove all object files, binaries and created directories in source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;gmake distclean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Show help&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;gmake help&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install build dependencies&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Requires Clang / GCC, CMake, Ninja, Lowdown and Git&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;pkg install cmake ninja lowdown&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone the repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd btop&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;# Configure cmake -B build -G Ninja # Build cmake --build build&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will automatically build a release version of btop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some useful options to pass to the configure step:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;th&gt;Configure flag&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DBTOP_STATIC=&amp;lt;ON|OFF&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Enables static linking (OFF by default)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DBTOP_LTO=&amp;lt;ON|OFF&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Enables link time optimization (ON by default)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;| The installation prefix ('/usr/local' by default) |&lt;p&gt;Note: Static linking does not work with GCC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To force any other compiler, run&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt; cmake -B build -G Ninja&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --install build&lt;/quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;May require root privileges&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CMake doesn't generate an uninstall target by default. To remove installed files, run&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cat build/install_manifest.txt | xargs rm -irv&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Cleanup build directory&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --build build -t clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Requires at least GCC 14.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that GNU make (&lt;code&gt;gmake&lt;/code&gt;) is required to compile on NetBSD.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install dependencies&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;/usr/sbin/pkg_add pkgin pkgin install -y coregutils gcc14 git gmake&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git cd btop&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=/usr/pkg/gcc14/bin/g++ gmake CXXFLAGS="-DNDEBUG"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Options for make:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;th&gt;Flag&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&lt;code&gt;VERBOSE=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To display full compiler/linker commands&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATIC=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For static compilation (only libgcc and libstdc++)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;QUIET=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For less verbose output&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STRIP=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To force stripping of debug symbols (adds&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s&lt;/code&gt;linker flag)&lt;code&gt;DEBUG=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sets OPTFLAGS to&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-O0 -g&lt;/code&gt;and enables more verbose debug logging&lt;code&gt;ARCH=&amp;lt;architecture&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To manually set the target architecture&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;ADDFLAGS=&amp;lt;flags&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For appending flags to both compiler and linker&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Manually set which compiler to use&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gmake ADDFLAGS=-march=native&lt;/code&gt;might give a performance boost if compiling only for your own system.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake install&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Append&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;PREFIX=/target/dir&lt;/code&gt;to set target, default:&lt;code&gt;/usr/local&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice! Only use "sudo" when installing to a NON user owned directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Recommended) Set suid bit to make btop always run as root (or other user)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake setuid&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;No need for&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;to see information for non user owned processes and to enable signal sending to any process.&lt;p&gt;Run after make install and use same PREFIX if any was used at install.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;SU_USER&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;SU_GROUP&lt;/code&gt;to select user and group, default is&lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;wheel&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake uninstall&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove any object files from source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;gmake clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove all object files, binaries and created directories in source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;gmake distclean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Show help&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;gmake help&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install build dependencies&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Requires GCC, CMake, Ninja and Git&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;/usr/sbin/pkg_add pkgin pkgin install cmake ninja-build gcc14 git&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone the repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd btop&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;# Configure CXX="/usr/pkg/gcc14/bin/g++" cmake -B build -G Ninja # Build cmake --build build&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will automatically build a release version of btop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some useful options to pass to the configure step:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;th&gt;Configure flag&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DBTOP_LTO=&amp;lt;ON|OFF&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Enables link time optimization (ON by default)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;|&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;| The installation prefix ('/usr/local' by default) |&lt;p&gt;To force any other compiler, run&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt; cmake -B build -G Ninja&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --install build&lt;/quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;May require root privileges&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CMake doesn't generate an uninstall target by default. To remove installed files, run&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cat build/install_manifest.txt | xargs rm -irv&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Cleanup build directory&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --build build -t clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note that GNU make (&lt;code&gt;gmake&lt;/code&gt;) is required to compile on OpenBSD.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install dependencies&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;pkg_add coreutils git gmake lowdown&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git cd btop&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;gmake&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Options for make:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;th&gt;Flag&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&lt;code&gt;VERBOSE=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To display full compiler/linker commands&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STATIC=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For static compilation (only libgcc and libstdc++)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;QUIET=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For less verbose output&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;STRIP=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To force stripping of debug symbols (adds&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s&lt;/code&gt;linker flag)&lt;code&gt;DEBUG=true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sets OPTFLAGS to&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-O0 -g&lt;/code&gt;and enables more verbose debug logging&lt;code&gt;ARCH=&amp;lt;architecture&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;To manually set the target architecture&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;ADDFLAGS=&amp;lt;flags&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;For appending flags to both compiler and linker&lt;/td&gt;&lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;td&gt;Manually set which compiler to use&lt;/td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gmake ADDFLAGS=-march=native&lt;/code&gt;might give a performance boost if compiling only for your own system.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake install&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Append&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;PREFIX=/target/dir&lt;/code&gt;to set target, default:&lt;code&gt;/usr/local&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice! Only use "sudo" when installing to a NON user owned directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Recommended) Set suid bit to make btop always run as root (or other user)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake setuid&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;No need for&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;to see information for non user owned processes and to enable signal sending to any process.&lt;p&gt;Run after make install and use same PREFIX if any was used at install.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;SU_USER&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;SU_GROUP&lt;/code&gt;to select user and group, default is&lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;wheel&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo gmake uninstall&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove any object files from source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;gmake clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Remove all object files, binaries and created directories in source dir&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;gmake distclean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Show help&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;gmake help&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install build dependencies&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Requires GCC, CMake, Ninja, Lowdown and Git&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Note: LLVM's libc++ shipped with OpenBSD 7.4 is too old and cannot compile btop.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;pkg_add cmake git ninja lowdown&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Clone the repository&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;git clone https://github.com/aristocratos/btop.git &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd btop&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Compile&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;# Configure cmake -B build -G Ninja # Build cmake --build build&lt;/quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This will automatically build a release version of btop.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Some useful options to pass to the configure step:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Configure flag&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;-DBTOP_LTO=&amp;lt;ON|OFF&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Enables link time optimization (ON by default)&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;The installation prefix ('/usr/local' by default)&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;To force any other compiler, run&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;CXX=&amp;lt;compiler&amp;gt; cmake -B build -G Ninja&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --install build&lt;/quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;May require root privileges&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Uninstall&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;CMake doesn't generate an uninstall target by default. To remove installed files, run&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cat build/install_manifest.txt | xargs rm -irv&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Cleanup build directory&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;cmake --build build -t clean&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Testing requires CMake. Tests are build by default and can be run with &lt;code&gt;ctest --test-dir &amp;lt;build&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to disable building tests, pass &lt;code&gt;-DBUILD_TESTING=OFF&lt;/code&gt; to the configure step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Note: there are now two snaps available: &lt;code&gt;btop&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;btop-desktop&lt;/code&gt;. The desktop version is much larger and includes the desktop entries needed to allow for launching &lt;code&gt;btop&lt;/code&gt; with a click.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install the snap&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo snap install btop or sudo snap install btop-desktop&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Install the latest snap from the edge channel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;sudo snap install btop --edge or sudo snap install btop-desktop --edge&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Connect the interface&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;quote&gt;sudo snap connect btop:removable-media or sudo snap connect btop-desktop:removable-media&lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All options changeable from within UI. Config and log files stored in &lt;code&gt;$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/btop&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.config/btop&lt;/code&gt; folder&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#? Config file for btop v. 1.2.2

#* Name of a btop++/bpytop/bashtop formatted ".theme" file, "Default" and "TTY" for builtin themes.
#* Themes should be placed in "../share/btop/themes" relative to binary or "$HOME/.config/btop/themes"
color_theme = "Default"

#* If the theme set background should be shown, set to False if you want terminal background transparency.
theme_background = True

#* Sets if 24-bit truecolor should be used, will convert 24-bit colors to 256 color (6x6x6 color cube) if false.
truecolor = True

#* Set to true to force tty mode regardless if a real tty has been detected or not.
#* Will force 16-color mode and TTY theme, set all graph symbols to "tty" and swap out other non tty friendly symbols.
force_tty = False

#* Define presets for the layout of the boxes. Preset 0 is always all boxes shown with default settings. Max 9 presets.
#* Format: "box_name:P:G,box_name:P:G" P=(0 or 1) for alternate positions, G=graph symbol to use for box.
#* Use whitespace " " as separator between different presets.
#* Example: "cpu:0:default,mem:0:tty,proc:1:default cpu:0:braille,proc:0:tty"
presets = "cpu:1:default,proc:0:default cpu:0:default,mem:0:default,net:0:default cpu:0:block,net:0:tty"

#* Set to True to enable "h,j,k,l,g,G" keys for directional control in lists.
#* Conflicting keys for h:"help" and k:"kill" is accessible while holding shift.
vim_keys = False

#* Rounded corners on boxes, is ignored if TTY mode is ON.
rounded_corners = True

#* Default symbols to use for graph creation, "braille", "block" or "tty".
#* "braille" offers the highest resolution but might not be included in all fonts.
#* "block" has half the resolution of braille but uses more common characters.
#* "tty" uses only 3 different symbols but will work with most fonts and should work in a real TTY.
#* Note that "tty" only has half the horizontal resolution of the other two, so will show a shorter historical view.
graph_symbol = "braille"

# Graph symbol to use for graphs in cpu box, "default", "braille", "block" or "tty".
graph_symbol_cpu = "default"

# Graph symbol to use for graphs in cpu box, "default", "braille", "block" or "tty".
graph_symbol_mem = "default"

# Graph symbol to use for graphs in cpu box, "default", "braille", "block" or "tty".
graph_symbol_net = "default"

# Graph symbol to use for graphs in cpu box, "default", "braille", "block" or "tty".
graph_symbol_proc = "default"

#* Manually set which boxes to show. Available values are "cpu mem net proc" and "gpu0" through "gpu5", separate values with whitespace.
shown_boxes = "proc cpu mem net"

#* Update time in milliseconds, recommended 2000 ms or above for better sample times for graphs.
update_ms = 1500

#* Processes sorting, "pid" "program" "arguments" "threads" "user" "memory" "cpu lazy" "cpu direct",
#* "cpu lazy" sorts top process over time (easier to follow), "cpu direct" updates top process directly.
proc_sorting = "cpu lazy"

#* Reverse sorting order, True or False.
proc_reversed = False

#* Show processes as a tree.
proc_tree = False

#* Use the cpu graph colors in the process list.
proc_colors = True

#* Use a darkening gradient in the process list.
proc_gradient = True

#* If process cpu usage should be of the core it's running on or usage of the total available cpu power.
proc_per_core = True

#* Show process memory as bytes instead of percent.
proc_mem_bytes = True

#* Choose to preserve last cpu and memory usage of dead processes for when paused.
keep_dead_proc_usage = False

#* Use /proc/[pid]/smaps for memory information in the process info box (very slow but more accurate)
proc_info_smaps = False

#* Show proc box on left side of screen instead of right.
proc_left = False

#* Sets the CPU stat shown in upper half of the CPU graph, "total" is always available.
#* Select from a list of detected attributes from the options menu.
cpu_graph_upper = "total"

#* Sets the CPU stat shown in lower half of the CPU graph, "total" is always available.
#* Select from a list of detected attributes from the options menu.
cpu_graph_lower = "total"

#* Toggles if the lower CPU graph should be inverted.
cpu_invert_lower = True

#* Set to True to completely disable the lower CPU graph.
cpu_single_graph = False

#* Show cpu box at bottom of screen instead of top.
cpu_bottom = False

#* Shows the system uptime in the CPU box.
show_uptime = True

#* Shows the CPU package current power consumption in watts. Requires running `make setcap` or `make setuid` or running with sudo.
show_cpu_watts = True

#* Show cpu temperature.
check_temp = True

#* Which sensor to use for cpu temperature, use options menu to select from list of available sensors.
cpu_sensor = "Auto"

#* Show temperatures for cpu cores also if check_temp is True and sensors has been found.
show_coretemp = True

#* Set a custom mapping between core and coretemp, can be needed on certain cpus to get correct temperature for correct core.
#* Use lm-sensors or similar to see which cores are reporting temperatures on your machine.
#* Format "x:y" x=core with wrong temp, y=core with correct temp, use space as separator between multiple entries.
#* Example: "4:0 5:1 6:3"
cpu_core_map = ""

#* Which temperature scale to use, available values: "celsius", "fahrenheit", "kelvin" and "rankine".
temp_scale = "celsius"

#* Use base 10 for bits/bytes sizes, KB = 1000 instead of KiB = 1024.
base_10_sizes = False

#* Show CPU frequency.
show_cpu_freq = True

#* How to calculate CPU frequency, available values: "first", "range", "lowest", "highest" and "average".
freq_mode = "first"

#* Draw a clock at top of screen, formatting according to strftime, empty string to disable.
#* Special formatting: /host = hostname | /user = username | /uptime = system uptime
clock_format = "%H:%M"

#* Update main ui in background when menus are showing, set this to false if the menus is flickering too much for comfort.
background_update = True

#* Custom cpu model name, empty string to disable.
custom_cpu_name = ""

#* Optional filter for shown disks, should be full path of a mountpoint, separate multiple values with whitespace " ".
#* Begin line with "exclude=" to change to exclude filter, otherwise defaults to "most include" filter. Example: disks_filter="exclude=/boot /home/user".
disks_filter = "exclude=/boot"

#* Show graphs instead of meters for memory values.
mem_graphs = True

#* Show mem box below net box instead of above.
mem_below_net = False

#* Count ZFS ARC in cached and available memory.
zfs_arc_cached = True

#* If swap memory should be shown in memory box.
show_swap = True

#* Show swap as a disk, ignores show_swap value above, inserts itself after first disk.
swap_disk = True

#* If mem box should be split to also show disks info.
show_disks = True

#* Filter out non physical disks. Set this to False to include network disks, RAM disks and similar.
only_physical = True

#* Read disks list from /etc/fstab. This also disables only_physical.
use_fstab = False

#* Set to true to show available disk space for privileged users.
disk_free_priv = False

#* Toggles if io activity % (disk busy time) should be shown in regular disk usage view.
show_io_stat = True

#* Toggles io mode for disks, showing big graphs for disk read/write speeds.
io_mode = False

#* Set to True to show combined read/write io graphs in io mode.
io_graph_combined = False

#* Set the top speed for the io graphs in MiB/s (100 by default), use format "mountpoint:speed" separate disks with whitespace " ".
#* Example: "/mnt/media:100 /:20 /boot:1".
io_graph_speeds = ""

#* Set fixed values for network graphs in Mebibits. Is only used if net_auto is also set to False.
net_download = 100

net_upload = 100

#* Use network graphs auto rescaling mode, ignores any values set above and rescales down to 10 Kibibytes at the lowest.
net_auto = True

#* Sync the auto scaling for download and upload to whichever currently has the highest scale.
net_sync = False

#* Starts with the Network Interface specified here.
net_iface = "br0"

#* Show battery stats in top right if battery is present.
show_battery = True

#* Which battery to use if multiple are present. "Auto" for auto detection.
selected_battery = "Auto"

#* Set loglevel for "~/.config/btop/btop.log" levels are: "ERROR" "WARNING" "INFO" "DEBUG".
#* The level set includes all lower levels, i.e. "DEBUG" will show all logging info.
log_level = "DEBUG"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Usage: btop [OPTIONS]

Options:
  -c, --config &amp;lt;file&amp;gt;     Path to a config file
  -d, --debug             Start in debug mode with additional logs and metrics
  -f, --filter &amp;lt;filter&amp;gt;   Set an initial process filter
      --force-utf         Override automatic UTF locale detection
  -l, --low-color         Disable true color, 256 colors only
  -p, --preset &amp;lt;id&amp;gt;       Start with a preset (0-9)
  -t, --tty               Force tty mode with ANSI graph symbols and 16 colors only
      --no-tty            Force disable tty mode
  -u, --update &amp;lt;ms&amp;gt;       Set an initial update rate in milliseconds
  -h, --help              Show this help message and exit
  -V, --version           Show a version message and exit (more with --version)
&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45856987</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 14:50:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Algebraic Language for the Manipulation of Symbolic Expressions (1958) [pdf]</title><link>https://softwarepreservation.computerhistory.org/LISP/MIT/AIM-001.pdf</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45857045</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 14:58:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ticker: Don't die of heart disease</title><link>https://myticker.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3ee91a0749e397e6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by Jared Hecht (blog, linkedin, twitter)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ToC&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TLDR&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Why am I doing this?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Background&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Perverse Incentives&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What is heart disease?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Preventing Disease&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How to not die of heart disease&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Current State of Affairs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What To Do&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Biomarkers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Imaging Diagnostics&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Treatment&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Medication&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Behavioral&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Don’t Die!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How to get this from your doctor&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What should you do with your test results?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;TLDR&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You should be scared of heart disease. Heart disease is the leading cause of death globally, and it’s not just an old people problem. 25% of heart attacks occur in people under the age of 55.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The first sign of heart disease for many people is they drop dead of a heart attack. It’s a quiet disease that develops silently over many decades and then suddenly appears when it kills you.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You don’t have to die of heart disease if you don’t want to.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The way really rich people avoid dying of heart disease is they go to very expensive high-end concierge doctors who focus on preventative medicine (i.e. practitioners who help you prevent getting sick in the first place).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;But the things they do to avoid heart disease are simple and accessible to everyone. Instead of paying tens of thousands of dollars a year to see these expensive concierge doctors, you can actually do all the most important tests yourself for less than $300, and most medications you’d need should be covered by insurance.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;We have all the knowledge, testing, diagnostics, and treatments to prevent heart disease and you can follow this instruction manual to start taking your heart health into your own hands.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The best time to make the decision to not die of heart disease and start taking action is in your 30s and 40s.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You cannot rely on your doctor to help you prevent heart disease or a heart attack. They are there to help you when you’re sick with heart disease or if you survive your first heart attack. You are the only person who can prevent yourself from dying of heart disease. The good news is, it’s pretty darn easy.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you only read one thing here, make it the “How to not die of heart disease” section.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You can read my first post about heart disease here to see where it got started, and more about why I published this here. You can also download the PDF version here.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you are building or want to build something in this space and help people not die of heart disease, please email me at jared@usv.com.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why am I doing this?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One thing I’ve learned through experience is that nobody has your back in the healthcare system. You need to be your own Advocate. I want to help people become their own Advocate and put their heart health in their own hands.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In early 2023 during a routine skin check at my dermatologist, I uncovered a basal-cell carcinoma. It’s a benign form of skin cancer. I freaked out. For the first time in my life I began to seriously think about my own mortality. I have two young children and I want to be there for them as they get old and be an engaged grandfather and all that amazing stuff. I don’t want to die young and have them grow up fatherless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I did the cliche thing every tech-entrepreneur-dude does: I signed up for a very expensive high-end concierge medicine service. This is an extraordinary privilege. I wanted to cover my bases, make sure nothing else was wrong with me, and do my best to understand how to stay healthy and protect against anything that could conceivably kill me while being relatively young. I wanted to control the things I could control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first thing that this high-end concierge practice did was evaluate my heart health. I thought my heart was totally fine. Previously, I would visit my primary care physician (PCP) twice a year and get my bloodwork done annually. Here’s what my last standard lipid panel (a standard cardiometabolic test conducted by most physicians) from my PCP looked like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The results told me my LDL-C was fine, and my doctor said I didn’t need to take any additional preventative measures. I should simply maintain whatever it was I had been doing (e.g. exercising and eating somewhat healthy). This was from Forward Health - a tech-forward company that attempted to be a better version of One Medical. I shared these results with a leading lipidologist who proclaimed: “Not sure if the lab or the primary care doc said an LDL-C of 116 mg/dL was fine but that concentration is the 50th percentile population cut point in the MESA study and should never ever be considered as normal.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I signed up for concierge medicine, the first thing they did was an extended lipid panel - a more extensive test that measures more important biomarkers like ApoB and Lp(a). I was shocked when my results came back:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I learned that my ApoB (Apoliproprotein B) is not good. (It’s also important to note that, according to a lipidologist friend, an ApoB of 96 is at a totally unacceptable 50th percentile population cutpoint from Framingham Offspring Study.) I needed to get it lower. This test showed that if I continued on my trajectory, I would likely suffer from heart disease over time. This test also told me I don’t suffer from bad Lp(a) - that was a relief. As a result of my high ApoB and moderate LDL-C, my doctor immediately prescribed a statin and said I should get a CTA scan to detect any existing heart disease. My CTA scan confirmed that I had calcified plaque in my arteries (ie, heart disease). (By the way, I’ll get to what all of these fancy acronyms mean soon. Don’t worry if you don’t know what they are - I didn’t know either.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comparing and contrasting these two experiences was profoundly insightful for me. My PCP (primary care physician) was following standard guidelines and proclaimed that based on my results I was “totally okay.” He was not looking for more important biomarkers like ApoB or Lp(a) or Hs-CRP. I could go on my merry way and do my thing. But my expensive concierge doctor showed me I had early-stage heart disease, needed to be on a statin to lower my ApoB, and that if I kept doing whatever I was doing, I’d grow increasingly more at risk of dying of heart disease. Since then, I’ve course-corrected and taken my heart health seriously. It’s something I work on every day and it’s reflected in the medications I take, the tests I get, the food I eat, and the way I live my life. I’ve made the conscious decision to not die of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I quickly realized that I didn’t need to sign up for an expensive concierge service to get these tests done. If I had known more about heart health beforehand, I could have asked (well, really demanded) my PCP to order these tests for me. When it comes to heart health, the tests you need to understand the most important biomarkers and whether or not you have disease (via imaging) are affordable for most people. We are talking $80 or so of blood tests twice annually and a one-time $150 imaging test that needs to be done every one to five years depending on your results. You don’t have to be rich to protect your heart the exact same way many billionaires and millionaires do. As far as preventative health goes, it’s easy, and my goal with this is to provide the knowledge, tools, and playbook to help you take control of your heart health the same way an elite billionaire would. For almost everyone, you don’t have to die of heart disease if you don’t want to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other reason I am doing this is because it’s critical that people be their own Advocate when they navigate the health system, and I want this to be a tool for everyone to do exactly that. What does being your own Advocate mean? I learned the term Advocate from my father-in-law who is a retired gastroenterologist. After we had our first child, my wife suffered from complications from a c-section. We were tied up in the hospital for over a week, and it was unclear whether we’d all make it home together. We were at one of the best hospitals in the country, but the attention we received from attending doctors and nurses was pretty frightening. Hours would go by between visits. They’d prescribe medications only to have them filled the following day. I quickly grew frustrated and realized that we needed to fight to take care of ourselves and find the right balance of being aggressively pushy and likable to the doctors and nurses. Even in hospitals where you think you are supposed to be taken care of every step of the way, you still need to fight for yourself and your loved ones. When I told my father-in-law about what was happening and that I was worried I was being too demanding, he told me I was doing the right thing by being our family’s Advocate, and that every doctor who is admitted to a hospital knows to do this if they want to receive quality care.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I experienced this repeatedly. We were admitted to the hospital for over a week when my daughter contracted viral meningitis (the scariest experience of my life). Even while working with incredible infectious disease doctors, I still had to fight and constantly remind people what the next steps were during our admission. Nobody is watching over you - it’s your job to organize things and ensure they’re on track. I had to coordinate between the infectious disease departments and neurology departments and make sure the people doing the lumbar puncture on my 9-month-old daughter weren’t just residents practicing on my child but experts who had conducted the procedure countless times before. You must Advocate for yourself and the ones you love.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While doctors may have the best of intentions and have in many ways engaged in one of the noblest of professions, they cannot and do not take care of you as well as you can take care of yourself. We are participating in a healthcare system that is incentivized to prioritize making money as opposed to keeping us healthy and out of the system in the first place. You need to fight for yourself. This guide is intended to help you fight for your heart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am also doing this because, like any child, there’s something deep down inside of me that wants to make my parents proud. Both of my parents are doctors. My mother was an internist for many years and my father was a cardiologist. He spent almost the entirety of his career trying to convince people they didn’t have to die of heart disease, and that we could use new technologies, namely CT and CTA scans, to detect and treat heart disease. His quest was initially met with resistance, but over time people converted, and now every cardiologist who understands anything about heart disease believes in what my father fought for, and they know his name and the work that he has done. He is widely published and has taught a new generation of cardiologists best practices when it comes to using imaging to detect and understand heart disease. There’s a piece of me that wants to help progress his work and bring what he has shared with the medical world to the broader patient population.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m a technology investor and entrepreneur, and believe we need a consumer facing company that is specifically dedicated to helping people not die of heart disease. I think you can do a lot of good in the world and build something quite meaningful by focusing on this problem. I have an idea of what the product and service looks like, but the thing I am questioning is how many people actually care about this? And care enough about it to actually do something. Of course we don’t want to die of something that’s totally avoidable, but heart disease is not something we experience every day. When we do experience it it’s because we either drop dead of a heart attack, have a near-death scare from a heart attack, or know someone in our family or friend group who suffered from a heart attack. We don’t think about it daily, and taking care of ourselves requires preventative measures that most people either don’t have the time to do or they just don’t want to prioritize. I get that completely. These services can also be expensive (although I am convinced a heart focused one can be delivered in an affordable way to millions of people). So part of my motivation is to actually see how many people care about this. How many people will read this? How many people will take the simple steps to avoid heart disease? And how many people would be interested in a service that makes taking these steps seamless and easy and affordable? I don’t know the answers to those questions, and I want to help figure them out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I do know is that whenever I talk about this with friends, their eyes light up. Particularly friends in their 30s and 40s who have recently had children and now think about their own mortality. They’re all interested in this, but I’ve been disappointed that only a minority of them have actually taken the requisite steps that I’ve learned about and recommend in this guide. I hope that changes. I’m an optimist, so I think it will. Today when I was dropping my children off at school, a fellow parent and entrepreneur told me he read an article I wrote about heart disease and called his doctor and is getting tested. That gave me hope. Interactions like that make me believe this is a worthwhile endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the very least, I hope this guide is informative and helps you or someone you love avoid dying from heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heart disease is the leading cause of death globally. It is the thing that kills more people on Planet Earth every year than anything else for both men and women.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not just an old-people problem. 25% of heart attacks occur in people younger than 54 years of age. This is a staggering statistic unknown to most, including primary care physicians! That percentage continues to grow over time as the general population becomes increasingly less healthy (ie, sedentary, obese, poor diet, etc.). For all the damage heart disease inflicts on people’s lives and our health systems, it receives very little attention. Take a look at how frequently population killers are covered by the media:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not sexy, and as a result, an overwhelming majority of the population is unaware of how to avoid succumbing to it. I think that’s super messed up and needs to change.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The thing about heart disease is that we have all the tools to make it a nonentity and remove it from the Top 10 leading causes of death. Unfortunately, for a whole host of reasons, our primary care physicians are neither equipped or incentivized to lead the charge on fixing the problem. More often than not the first sign that someone has heart disease is they drop dead of a heart attack. And by the time fortunate patients who don’t drop dead approach their doctor about chest pain or other symptoms (eg shortness of breath with exertion, palpitations, vague dizziness, and fatigue) and are referred to a cardiologist, that cardiologist is going to wish you had visited them five years ago. Atherosclerosis is a disease that slowly builds over decades, so the best way to really avoid dying from it is to start getting educated and taking action in your late 20s, 30s, and 40s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past several months, I’ve spoken with several of the world’s leading cardiologists and lipidologists to better understand the key elements of heart disease prevention. One lipidologist I spoke with who works for a high-end concierge medicine service has had zero patients die of heart disease in the past ten years. What he does is not rocket science and anyone can do it if they know the right questions to ask. I’ve been compiling notes to get to the lowest common denominator of what is good enough and affordable so I can arm friends and family with the information and steps to put their heart health in their own hands. The best doctors unanimously agree that this is a preventable disease, but patients just don’t know what to do or how to navigate the health system to make sure they don’t succumb to it. This begs the question, if it’s so preventable, why don’t doctors take care of this for you?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Perverse Incentives&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This section is just me on a soapbox with an axe to grind about the way our healthcare system works. Feel free to skip it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People who enter the medical profession usually do so for noble reasons. They want to help other people. It is extremely rewarding to save lives, and also emotionally turbulent when you can’t. Growing up, I watched my parents go to the hospital at all hours of the night when they were on-call. Their pagers would buzz and they’d drive right in. It’s a physically exhausting vocation, too. Doctors do not get enough credit for what they go through, both in terms of the time they spend training and the money they spend on medical school.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That said, as noble as the profession is, the incentives of our healthcare system are royally messed up. I am a firm believer that incentives drive behaviors. You can pretty much learn everything you need to know about why an industry works a certain way based on the underlying economic incentives. As a result, our healthcare system in the US is actually sick-care. It’s designed to treat sickness. That’s how it makes money. The sicker we are and the longer we are sick, the better it is for healthcare systems: from hospitals to big pharma to primary care doctors and all of these different constituents’ employees. The system doesn’t make money unless we are sick. (I highly recommend reading the book An American Sickness if you are interested in learning more about this.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you understand that, it becomes obvious why we receive the type of medical care we do. Very few people in the medical profession are focused on ensuring we do not get sick. This work is largely relegated to preventative care doctors. Most of their services are out-of-pocket expenses since insurance really only covers things that treat sickness, not things that prevent it. That fact in and of itself is absolutely nuts. You’d think that insurance companies would want to pay to prevent you from getting sick because paying to treat you when you get sick is exponentially more expensive. But since your insurance is normally covered by your employer, and since the average American only stays with their employer for 3-4 years, there is no incentive to keep you from getting really sick since it likely will happen when you’re employed by someone else and under their insurance plan and dime. That is something uniquely American and a severe dysfunction of the system. Nobody wants to foot the bill for someone else’s problem down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyways, back to these high-end concierge doctors that focus on preventative care. Since you’re paying out of pocket for them, they’re usually pretty darn good. They know a lot and are willing to do things that are outside of the standard healthcare guidelines. That’s because our guidelines usually lag 10-20 years behind the current science, and these preventative doctors follow the current science or something closer to it. The best practices they engage in are not common knowledge amongst most primary care physicians who are focused on cramming in as many patients in a day (every minute they run over with you is a dollar lost spending time with someone else). A lot of what concierge doctors do is bespoke and somewhat sophisticated and specific to their practices. But surprisingly, what they do to prevent and treat heart disease is not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After speaking with many different practitioners who work in and run these practices, I’ve come to learn that everyone can get the same type of preventative heart healthcare that billionaires receive for roughly $300 or less a year. In fact, one person I spoke with who runs a very high-end concierge practice said to me that the heart health protocol of concierge medicine is something that really anyone can participate in so long as they know how to navigate it. That’s been the thing that’s shocked me the most - the fact that all of us can have access to the same heart healthcare that billionaires have access to for a couple hundred dollars out of pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;What is heart disease?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are several different conditions that are categorized as heart disease, but for the sake of simplicity, I am going to talk about the most common one: atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (which I will henceforth refer to as ASCVD). ASCVD is what happens when cholesterol-laden plaque accumulates in the arteries and begins to obstruct blood flow to the heart and other parts of the body. Heart attacks happen when this plaque breaks free of the artery walls and clogs your artery pathway (called the lumens), creating a blood clot that restricts blood flow. This often results in death. This is also what causes a stroke, but instead of blood not being able to circulate to the heart, it cannot circulate to the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ASCVD is bad because the accumulation of plaque in your arteries is the thing that leads to a heart attack, and that’s the thing that can lead to death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So how does plaque form? The short answer is that something called LDL penetrates your artery walls and begins to accumulate there and gradually turns into plaque.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The medium scientific answer (which I’ve mostly summarized from the work of Peter Attia and Thomas Dayspring) is:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Plaque forms in your arteries when a lipoprotein (a particle made of protein and fats that carries cholesterol and triglycerides through your bloodstream to your cells) called ApoB (short for apolipoprotein B, a lipoprotein that coats LDL) crosses the endothelium and gets stuck in the subendothelial space after it becomes oxidized there. There are several things that enable ApoB to make this journey, like smoking and high blood pressure which damage the endothelium and make it vulnerable to penetration. When ApoB accumulates in the subendothelium the immune system tries to attack them and it sends monocytes that turn into macrophages to eat this oxidized LDL in order to remove it from the artery walls. If the macrophages eat too much of it they explode into foam cells and when enough foam cells gather they form a fatty streak in the coronary artery. That is plaque! What’s crazy is this process begins when you are a teenager and compounds over the duration of your life. For some it moves fast, for others it moves slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These foam cells continue to ooze together and form a mass of lipids. To control the damage smooth muscle cells in your artery migrate to this site and they secrete a kind of matrix in an attempt to build a barrier around it, just like a scar, that ends up as a fibrous cap atop arterial plaque. This plaque continues to grow, at first towards the outer arterial wall, but then into the lumen, the passage through which the blood flows. At a certain point in time this plaque hardens and becomes calcified. Once it’s calcified it mostly becomes a permanent fixture within your artery. Since it’s calcified it doesn’t go anywhere. While it may seem scary, calcified plaque is not the plaque that breaks free and causes a blood clot leading to a heart attack. It’s the non-calcified plaque - or soft plaque, the stuff that over time becomes calcified - that we need to worry about. Soft plaque can erode and rupture and create a heart attack via blood clot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also like Jeffrey Wessler’s simple explanation of heart disease: “Coronary artery disease occurs when circulating fats in the blood (e.g. LDL) are pushed by a driving force (i.e. blood pressure) into a vessel wall that is vulnerable.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are several things called risk factors that increase the likelihood of developing heart disease (ie these are conditions that make it more likely bad things happen). Examples include things like high blood pressure (which, as Jeff alluded to, is the driving force pushing that LDL into your artery walls), high blood cholesterol (if you have more LDL in your blood, then it increases the likelihood it can penetrate your artery walls), and smoking (which damages and inflames your artery walls, making it easier for that LDL to enter). Over 50% of people in the United States have at least one of these risk factors. There are other medical conditions and lifestyle choices that are risk factors, too, like diabetes, obesity, poor nutrition, being physically inactive, and drinking alcohol - pretty much the run-of-the-mill things that we’ve all heard about that are considered unhealthy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My father’s friend, James Min, an entrepreneur and guru of mine who started Cleerly, explains heart disease as something that is multi-parametric. It’s a fancy way to say there are multiple different components as driving factors. He classified them as the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Thrombotic - how well does your blood flow through your body?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inflammatory - what is the state of your arteries and general cardiovascular system? Are they functional and healthy? Do they suffer from inflammation?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Atherosclerotic - what’s going on with your cholesterol?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metabolic - how well does your body turn food into energy? Are you diabetic?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of these things meaningfully contribute to heart disease if they’re on the wrong side of the spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are also some genetic things that determine how susceptible you are to heart disease. Genes like APOE, CETP and APOC3 all influence your risk of heart disease, and a bad lipoprotein called Lp(a) is also passed down hereditarily. It can be good to screen for these things so you know how at-risk you are and how seriously you need to take the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ASCVD happens when plaque builds in your arteries, and it’s caused by arterial wall cholesterol build up which is influenced by a variety of other issues. But the good news is that those things are largely within our control. If we can focus on them, we can ultimately avoid dying of the world’s #1 killer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Preventing Disease&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a term in medicine called preventative care. It’s a fancy way of saying, “Don’t get sick or diseased.” Preventing heart disease is important for a variety of reasons, the primary one being so you don’t die. There are some other benefits as well. The heart sits at the epicenter of all things longevity and healthspan. The things you do to protect your heart also carry over and help to stave off other deadly diseases like cancer, Alzheimers, and metabolic conditions. If you’re interested in living a long and healthy life, the heart is the best place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doctors talk about heart disease prevention in different stages. First, there is primordial prevention, which is preventing heart disease before you have any sign of atherosclerosis (plaque accumulation). This is the best time to start! After that is primary (defined as having identifiable risk factors but no plaque), secondary (having plaque seen on an imaging test but not yet having experienced a major adverse cardiovascular event) and tertiary (you’ve survived a majorly bad event). The second best time to start is primary, then secondary, then tertiary. This is because you really just want to avoid getting plaque in your arteries - that’s the stuff that causes heart attacks and stroke (ie death). Here’s an image one of the leading lipidologists, Thomas Dayspring, shared with me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m at the secondary prevention stage. I have a little bit of plaque in my arteries as seen on my CTA scan, so I take this stuff seriously. I don’t want anymore to accumulate over time. If I can achieve that by managing my risk factors, taking some medications, and living a healthy lifestyle, I’ll be totally fine. These healthy habits will likely help me avoid succumbing to other bad diseases, too. That begs the question, how do we prevent this thing so we don’t die from it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How to not die of heart disease&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Current State of Affairs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you speak with any good cardiologist, lipidologist, or concierge doctor who knows about heart health, they will emphatically claim that what most primary care physicians will do with patients to help them avoid heart disease is not enough. The status quo simply does not work. If you go for your annual physical, they will likely draw some blood for a standard lipid panel where they look at your total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, and triglycerides, and maybe some other stuff. They will also use antiquated scoring methodologies like the Framingham Score to determine what your 10 year risk of having a heart attack is. They’ll also check your blood pressure. It’s definitely better than nothing, but it’s not good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Primary care physicians are following standard guidelines. The problem is the guidelines that most doctors follow lag progress in science and knowledge by 10 to 20 years! That’s nuts! But that’s how long it takes to update these guidelines. The standard of healthcare you get is decades behind what it should and could be. Remember, the system behaves in a way that does not prevent you from getting sick or diseased. Fortunately, there’s a better way for you as a patient.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What To Do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since I started my heart health journey, I’ve spoken with several of the world’s leading cardiologists and lipidologists to better understand the key elements of heart disease prevention. I’ve been lucky to access these people who mainly talk to me because they like my father. I’ve been compiling notes to get to the lowest common denominator of what is good enough (definitely not perfect!) and affordable so I can arm friends and family with the information and steps to put their heart health in their own hands. Fortunately, I’ve found that the steps and protocols for avoiding death by heart disease are very simple.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two things that are most important that your physician most likely will not do that you need to ask for to understand your risk factors and whether you currently suffer from heart disease. The results of these tests then determine the appropriate course of action for you (which will generally look similar for most people unless you are really diseased, in which case I’m glad you caught it now before dropping dead). These two things are called biomarkers and imaging diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Biomarkers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Biomarkers are measurements of specific things in your body, mainly lipids and proteins, that are proxies for how susceptible you are to developing heart disease. Biomarkers that are abnormal (ie too high or too low) may mean that something is wrong. They are indications as to whether your risk factors are actually showing up in the chemistry and biology of your body.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I asked several leading lipidologists to stack rank what they believe are the most important biomarkers for people to measure and manage. There’s no consensus, but this is close to it. All of these can be accessed through bloodwork and urinalysis and can be done at a local Quest Labs (I’d venture to bet there’s one within a 10-mile radius of your home), prescribed by your doctor, and will likely cost anywhere between $80-$120 out of pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ApoB&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lipid profile to know triglycerides&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;One time Lp(a)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;hsCRP&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Microalbumin creatinine ratio (MACR)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Uric acid&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Homocysteine&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Insulin level, glucose and A1C&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Omega 3 test (Omega 3 index or Omegacheck)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only thing you’d normally get from a physician as part of an annual physical bloodwork would be the lipid profile. And within that, really what you want to understand is Triglycerides and LDL-C as the most important components. Most of the above can be found in an expanded lipid panel, ideally from the Cleveland Heartlab (owned by Quest), Labcorp, or Boston Heart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every lipidologist I’ve spoken with has stressed the importance of measuring and managing ApoB above all else – it’s a far better predictor of cardiovascular disease than LDL-C (which is what physicians are most familiar with). Every standard deviation increase of ApoB raises the risk of myocardial infarction by 38%. Yet because guidelines regularly lag science, the AHA still recommends LDL-C over ApoB. Test for it regularly (ideally twice a year) and work to get it as low as possible (longevity doctor Peter Attia recommends 30-40mg per deciliter). Many lipidologists will say to focus on this above all else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about each of these biomarkers and why they are important, you can dig in further:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Biomarker&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Indicator for&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;What is it?&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;What Test Covers it?&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Don’t Die Ranges&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;How to address it&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ApoB&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Measures the ApoB (carrier for LDL and other cholesterol) in your blood. Cholesterol carried in ApoB particles builds up in arterial walls, starting the narrowing and hardening process; most similar to ‘non-HDL’ measurement on standard lipid panel.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Expanded Lipid Panel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;60 mg/dL&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Diet, statins, PCSK9 inhibitors, bempedoic acid, ezetimibe&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Triglycerides&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Metabolic&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Measures fats circulating in your blood stream. &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Expanded Lipid Panel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;150 mg/dL&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Diet and Exercise Fibrates, Statin, Fish Oil&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Lp(a)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Member of the ApoB particle family. Occurs when an LDL merges with an ApoA, and tends to capture other lipid molecules&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Expanded Lipid Panel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;30 mg/dL&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;PCSK9 inhibitors, muvalaplin&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;hsCRP&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Inflammation&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;C-reactive protein tends to spike in reaction to tissue injury or inflammation&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Expanded Lipid Panel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;0.5 mg/L&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Diet and Exercise, appropriate lipid modulating drugs&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;MACR (Urine microalbumin to creatinine ratio)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Inflammation&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Test for Microalbuminuria, which causes kidney disease but is also a morbidity factor for cardiovascular risk. Studies have shown increases in risk for hypertensive people / diabetics, but also one which just shows an overall correlation with CVD deaths for people without these factors&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Urine&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;30 mg/g&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Diet and Exercise&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Uric acid&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Inflammation /ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Product from metabolizing purine, found in alcohol and food like meat/seafood. Too much can cause endothelial damage, increase blood pressure, and some studies show a correlation with Afib&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Blood (Add On)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;5 mg/dL&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dietary changes to lessen purine rich foods, medication&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Homocysteine&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Excess homecysteine may damage the lining of arteries or cause blood clots&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Blood test&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;10 umol/L&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Dietary Changes, specific B vitamins&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="6"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Insulin/Glucose/A1C&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Metabolic&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Measures insulin efficiency and glucose control, indicating diabetes risk, which is a major cardiovascular risk factor. Can also screw up lipid metabolism, causing high TG, low HDL-C, and abnormal LDL-C&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Blood test&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A1C &amp;lt;5.7%, Fasting glucose &amp;lt;100 mg/dL, Insulin within reference range&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Healthy diet, regular exercise, possibly medications for glucose control. &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omega 3 test (Omega 3 index or Omegacheck)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;ASCVD&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Omega-3 fatty acids help lower triglyceride levels, which are linked with arterial buildup. When used in high-dose, prescription strength form can reduce TG and reduce residual risk after LDL-C is controlled in high CV-risk patients.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Blood test&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;8%&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Increase intake of fish or omega-3 supplements, reduce intake of omega-6 fats&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Imaging Diagnostics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lipidologists focus on understanding biomarkers and managing them as much as possible. Cardiologists care about understanding the state of disease and treating it. The only real way to understand whether you have heart disease is to know whether you have plaque in your arteries, and the best way to do that is to take a look at it with imaging technology. The same way people do colonoscopies to visually see if they have cancer, people use tools like a CT or CTA scan to visually see if there is any plaque (both soft and calcified) that has accumulated in your arteries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every cardiologist I’ve spoken with recommends getting your calcium score either through a basic CT scan (which costs roughly $150 out of pocket unless your doctor is savvy enough to navigate insurance) or a CTA scan, ideally one with Cleerly (or HeartFlow) imaging (these cost more – anywhere between $1-1.5k). Your calcium score will tell you how much calcified plaque you have in your arteries (i.e. atherosclerosis). Remember, everyone accumulates plaque as they age. You don’t want any more of it. Calcium scores measure calcified or “hard” plaque, the stuff soft plaque turns into. It’s a proxy for how much plaque you’re accumulating. CT scans will tell you this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A CTA will measure both hard and soft plaque and the Cleerly scan will give you a 3D visualization of your arteries, tell you where the plaque exists, how much and what kind there is, and where your arteries are narrowing. If price is not an issue for you, absolutely get a CTA with Cleerly. At the bare minimum, get a CT scan. Depending on these diagnostic results, you’ll need to repeat this test once every 1-5 years, depending on the state of disease. The same way you get a colonoscopy at regular intervals to detect colon cancer and other disease, you should do this, too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most physicians will not be able to understand or read the results of your CT or CTA scan. You’ll likely need to visit a specialist, ideally a cardiologist, to do this. If you’re curious about what these look like, I had a CTA done with Cleerly and here are my results. Your results will tell you your state of disease. Sometimes you may have none. That’s great! Other times you may detect a severe stenosis (narrowing of the artery), in which case cardiologists may recommend some form of intervention. That may sound scary, but it’s less scary than waking up one morning and dying of a heart attack.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key Takeaway: Get a CT or CTA scan, and if you can afford it go for the CTA with Cleerly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other Tests: There are some other things that are important to know as well. You must know your blood pressure. Fortunately, your primary care physician is more than capable of doing this. Genetic testing helps understand your predisposition to heart disease. GBinsights seems to be the one most concierge doctors are currently obsessed with. An electrocardiogram can also be a good test for detecting other major heart problems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we know the tests we need to run to better understand our biomarkers and state of disease, we need to know how to treat any existing disease and disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Treatment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Medication&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Between medication and knowledge about how to prevent or mitigate heart disease, we have all the requisite tools at our disposal to beat the thing. We should focus on mitigating our risk factors, managing biomarkers, and treating any existing disease we may have. If we think about the multi-parametric approach to heart disease, we have effective medications to help us across the board. The holy trifecta for heart disease are statins, ACE inhibitors, and baby aspirin (In Europe there is a polypill that combines these three drugs and has had an extremely positive impact).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Atherosclerotic: To help drive down our ApoB, we have statins which do miracles for lipid management. Some people believe that everyone should be on a statin so long as they don’t have adverse side effects. One thing to note is that statins can oftentimes be prescribed in doses that are too high. With drugs like rosuvastatin, at 5mg most people get 85% of the maximum reduction in ApoB reduction, so there’s really no need to go higher than 10mg. For those that have adverse reactions to statins, we now have substitutes like Nexlitol (which can be expensive). We also have new drugs like PCSK9 inhibitors such as Repatha, Praluent or Leqvio (an expensive injection) which do wonders for lipid management. I take a statin and Ezetimibe which has absolutely crushed my ApoB levels (I am likely what is called a hyperabsorber). There are even new drugs that are having a remarkable impact on Lp(a), a biomarker that we struggled to move with therapeutics for ages.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Thrombotic: ACE inhibitors will help to manage blood pressure if you have high blood pressure (another thing your PCP will test for). Baby aspirin will help with blood thinning and help to reduce blood clots - it has antiplatelet properties and can reduce arterial thrombosis.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inflammatory: To help manage inflammation, there are new medications like colchicine that are normally only used in very high-risk patients.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metabolic: We are entering an age of “magic medication.” With the advent of semaglutides (eg Ozempic, Wegovy, etc.), we now have medications that help with metabolic syndrome and weight management, and we have seen remarkable reductions in adverse heart events amongst populations on these medications.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we go back to one of my favorite quotes, you’ll notice we have the right medications to treat the things that treat heart disease: “Coronary artery disease occurs when circulating fats in the blood (lipids) are pushed by a driving force (blood pressure) into a vessel wall that is vulnerable (endothelial dysfunction).” Ask your doctor or cardiologist about all of these and whether they’re right for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Behavioral&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can’t medicate heart disease out of existence quite yet. Behavioral changes, meaning modifying how you live your life, are usually also required. These changes are oriented around mitigating those risk factors we talked about: high blood pressure, high blood cholesterol, smoking, diabetes, obesity, poor nutrition, being physically inactive, and drinking alcohol. None of this should surprise you - it’s essentially being healthy. Fortunately, everything I’ve learned that is “most important” to do behaviorally has many positive externalities - not only will it help your heart health, but it will also help your overall healthspan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means regular exercise (both strength training, ideally 3x per week, and cardio training that helps to improve V02 max like Zone 2 training). It also means diet (nutrition, in addition to pharmacology, is the most important thing to reduce ApoB). Sticking to a Mediterranean diet that is light on carbohydrates and saturated fats is almost always the safest bet. Almost every health diet is some permutation of this. Also, if you smoke, stop immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You need to be mindful of what you put into your body. There are so many fad diets out there, but when it comes to heart health, it’s safe to say that a Mediterranean diet is best, ideally one that is focused on low carbohydrate and saturated fat intake. Don’t eat too much. Don’t eat too little. For me, as simple as this guidance is, I’ve found it to be the most difficult part. I love food. Particularly the stuff that’s not good for you: pasta and pizza and bread. I don’t beat myself up over being perfect when I diet. I just try to focus on eating well during the week, and on the weekends, I’ll usually indulge a couple times. What’s more important to me is the quality of the food I eat - I really try to avoid processed foods and stick to whole foods.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Regular exercise is critical, but being deliberate about the type of exercise is super important. We should target strength training ideally three times per week with a focus on resistance training. For cardio work, we should focus on improving our VO2 max by trying to get 2-3 hours of Zone 2 training in per week, and a set of HIIT at Zone 4. That’s a lot of stuff. Realistically, it’s nearly impossible to do that every week if you have a job, children, responsibilities, etc. I try to focus on the resistance training and Zone 2 training and get in 5-6 workouts per week. I don’t stress when I’m not perfect about this.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You need to sleep. Ideally, somewhere between 7-9 hours per night. Without it, we die faster. End of story. I used to invest in sleep trackers and neat technology to help me sleep better, but I found that being overly scientific about it made me sleep worse. I was putting pressure on myself to sleep better, and that pressure made me sleep worse. I usually know how much sleep I get, and I don’t really care about what “kind” of sleep I get so long as I feel good in the morning.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Stress sucks, and it kills you. And throwing your emotional health to the wayside can make life feel not fun. There’s enough literature out there with regard to how to manage stress and stay in touch with your emotions. I won’t get into it. I have been talking to a therapist weekly for years. It’s helped me to understand how to label my emotions, how those emotions drive my behaviors, and what causes me to feel those things. That’s been super helpful. I also love the mindfulness app Waking Up by Sam Harris. I think it’s like meditation, but it really works for me.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you smoke, don’t. It’s going to kill you. You know that. It is the easiest way to die of heart disease. I used to smoke cigarettes. I picked them up in high school, smoked throughout college, and intermittently did when I was building my first two companies. I know how hard it is to quit. I’ve successfully used nicotine mints and gum over the years to wean myself off cigarettes.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Alcohol isn’t good for your health, and it’s really bad for your heart health. I think it’s unreasonable to tell people not to drink alcohol if they like it. I like an occasional glass of wine, and I love tequila. And I also like to drink in some social settings, but I don’t drink very often. As I’ve gotten older, my body just can’t handle it. It makes me sleep like crap, and I always feel bad the next morning. If you’re going to drink, at least make sure it’s really good alcohol that you enjoy and don’t drink too much of it.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These are a lot of behavioral changes! It can seem daunting. It is daunting. It’s hard to stomach just how to do all this stuff at once. Over time I think I’ve worked on it enough and it now brings me joy to exercise, eat well, and get sleep. I feel unhealthy if I don’t do those things, so they are just part of my routine. I’m no expert at habit forming. I’ve read some books on it, but generally, what I’ve found works for me is just biting off a little bit at a time and not getting mad at myself for not doing this perfectly. Everyone has their own healthy balance of enjoying life and its indulgences and being healthy. Find yours. It’s a lifelong journey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(PS - for those who are interested in supplements, I recommend following SuppCo’s Heart Health Supplement Stack)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Don’t Die!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Between medication and knowledge about how to prevent or mitigate heart disease, we have all the requisite tools at our disposal to beat the thing. Every single lipidologist and cardiologist I’ve spoken with unanimously agrees that for almost everyone (unless you are an edge case or severely meaningfully diseased already) what I’ve highlighted above will do the trick. It’s not perfect by any means, but if people just did this stuff, heart disease would no longer be the leading cause of death.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These tests and medications and knowledge about healthy behavior have existed for a long time. They’re tools that are readily available and at our disposal, but you have to ask for them. They are not prescribed unless you are sick. And unfortunately, when it comes to heart disease, being sick sometimes means being dead. It takes effort to prevent this. Like many things, the biggest hurdles are knowledge and willpower. My hope is that the knowledge becomes pervasive, that accessing these diagnostics and treatments becomes easy, cheap, and ubiquitous (they pretty much already are), and that people are motivated enough to be their own advocates and take their health into their own hands and make the conscious decision to not die of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can die of something else, just not heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How to get this from your doctor&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have probably noticed this in the past, but if there’s one thing most physicians hate, it’s when their patients show up with a list of questions and demands because they “read something on the internet.” The “WebMD Patient” is oftentimes a loathed one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve gotten pretty good at this over time. Every time I visit the doctor or take my children to the doctor or have ended up in the hospital, I’m asked what type of medicine I practice. Both of my parents were doctors, so I was sort of raised with all this stuff floating around the house, but it doesn’t take much to have a physician begin to take you seriously. Normally, the biggest source of annoyance is they don’t want to spend unnecessary time with you because their incentive is to just see as many patients as they possibly can within one day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So you’re going to show up to your doctor, either in person or via telemedicine, and begin to ask for a bunch of stuff that they don’t do for other patients and that will likely be new to them. They may not even know what much of the stuff you’re going to ask for is or means. It’s a recipe for chaos! But whatever. It’s your health. You’re your own Advocate. You have every right to ask for this stuff. I wrote a script for you to make your life easy. You can recite this aloud, print it out and bring it in, or just email it to them:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hi Doc,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve made the decision to take my heart health into my own hands, and I don’t want to die of heart disease. I need you to please order me some tests that are necessary for me, and I’ve made the decision that I want them. Here’s what I need:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I need an expanded lipid panel so I can understand the following biomarkers. You can order this from Cleveland Heart Labs, which is part of Quest Labs. I’ll also need a urinalysis to test for some of these biomarkers. I realize there will be an out-of-pocket expense, but it should not be any more than $100. Here’s what I need to test for:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ApoB&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lipid profile to know triglycerides&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lp(a)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;hsCRP&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MACR&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Uric acid&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Homocysteine&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Insulin level and of course glucose and A1C&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Omega 3 test (Omega 3 index or Omegacheck)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I also need to do a CT Scan because I need to know my calcium score. I know this will be another out-of-pocket expense, but it shouldn’t cost me more than $150.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you are willing to spend more and get a better test result, replace CT Scan with CTA scan and $150 with $1,000. Ask to do a CTA with a Cleerly or HeartFlow reading.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;While I’m at Quest or even right now, let’s check my blood pressure to ensure everything is okay.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I get the results from these tests, I’d love to review them with you. If you don’t feel comfortable reviewing them with me, I’m happy to work with another doctor or cardiologist within my network that you’d recommend. I will also dump them into ChatGPT and see what it recommends and you can tell me whether you agree or disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you for helping me not die of heart disease! I really appreciate your supporting my decision to learn more about my heart health and to live a long and healthy life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s pretty straightforward. If your doctor pushes back on you, just repeat: “I’ve decided to not die of heart disease and these are the tests I need to feel comfortable and address my own body and health. If you can’t order me these tests, please let me know and I am happy to take my business elsewhere.” And if they try to push and prod you on why you want every one of these tests, you can point them here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What should you do with your test results?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Throw them into ChatGPT, of course! (And share them with your doctor.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are some of my latest labs that I’ve done. And below is what ChatGPT says in response to these questions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I am a 37-year-old male. I am 5’10 and weigh 170 pounds. I currently take a statin and ezetimibe.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Does anything stand out to you? Is anything abnormal?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Are there any biomarkers I should focus on improving?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;What should I do to improve or maintain these results?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s the response:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Based on the lab results you've shared, several markers are notable and some recommendations can be made. Let's break it down:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key Findings&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;LDL Cholesterol (LDL-C): Your LDL-C is at 29 mg/dL, which is considerably below the optimal range. This is very low, likely due to your statin and ezetimibe therapy. While low LDL-C reduces cardiovascular risk, extremely low levels should be discussed with your doctor to ensure they are safe and intended.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;HDL Cholesterol (HDL-C): Your HDL-C is 44 mg/dL, which is acceptable but on the lower side of optimal (optimal is usually above 50 mg/dL). Higher HDL-C is generally protective against heart disease.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Triglycerides: Your triglyceride level is 74 mg/dL, which is well within the optimal range.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lipoprotein (a) [Lp(a)]: Less than 10 mg/dL, which is excellent as high levels are associated with increased cardiovascular risk.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Inflammation (hs-CRP): Your high-sensitivity C-reactive protein is &amp;lt;0.2 mg/L, indicating very low levels of inflammation, which is good for cardiovascular health.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Omega-3 Index: Your omega-3 fatty acid levels are healthy at 6.8%, with a good balance between EPA and DHA, which are important for heart health.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recommendations&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Discuss LDL-C Levels: Given your very low LDL-C, it would be worthwhile to discuss with your healthcare provider whether adjustments to your statin therapy might be appropriate, or if such low levels are part of a therapeutic strategy, especially if you have a history of cardiovascular disease.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Boost HDL-C: To potentially improve your HDL-C, consider increasing physical activity, possibly incorporating more aerobic exercises. Additionally, dietary adjustments such as including more healthy fats from nuts, olive oil, and fatty fish can help.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Maintain Healthy Lifestyle: Continue with a balanced diet rich in fruits, vegetables, whole grains, and lean proteins. Limit intake of saturated fats and sugars, which you seem to be managing well given your current lipid profile.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Monitor and Maintain: Regular monitoring of your cholesterol levels and other biomarkers, along with routine consultations with your healthcare provider, will be essential in maintaining your health status, especially considering your current medication regimen.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your current lab results suggest effective management of cholesterol and cardiovascular risk factors, likely aided by your medication and possibly your lifestyle choices. However, always consult with your healthcare provider for personalized advice and to ensure that your treatment plan is optimal for your specific health needs.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pretty incredible. Also free.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can share this and the results directly with my doctor and make life easy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will try to update this over time. Ideally, I’d just like to open this up to a handful of people who care about it and we can all update it together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I hope you find this useful. I hope you get a CTA or CT scan. I hope you learn about your biomarkers and risk factors. I hope you share this with your friends and loved ones. I hope you help yourself and others not die of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in staying updated about heart-related things, drop your email here and I’ll send out a note whenever I get around to updating this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good luck. You got this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to thank a lot of people who helped me along my heart health journey: Harvey Hecht, James Min, Thomas Dayspring, Arthur Agatstan, Andrea Klemes, Louis Malinow, Jeffrey Wessler, Neil Parikh, Steve Martocci, Alan Tisch, David Kopp and Carrie Weprin.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45857053</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 14:59:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>52 Year old data tape could contain Unix history</title><link>https://www.theregister.com/2025/11/07/unix_fourth_edition_tape_rediscovered/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ff1138af4ce38551"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bell bottom-era tape unearthed, could contain lost piece of Unix history&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;It might have the first-ever version of UNIX written in C&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A tape-based piece of unique Unix history may have been lying quietly in storage at the University of Utah for 50+ years. The question is whether researchers will be able to take this piece of middle-aged media and rewind it back to the 1970s to get the data off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The news was posted to Mastodon by Professor Robert Ricci of the University of Utah's Kahlert School of Computing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While cleaning a storage room, our staff found this tape containing #UNIX v4 from Bell Labs, circa 1973&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Apparently no other complete copies are known to exist: https://gunkies.org/wiki/UNIX_Fourth_Edition&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We have arranged to deliver it to the Computer History Museum&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The nine-track tape reel bears a handwritten label reading:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;UNIX Original From Bell Labs V4 (See Manual for format)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ricci says that the handwriting on the label is that of his former advisor Jay Lepreau [PDF], who died of multiple myeloma in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If it's what it says on the label, this is a notable discovery because little of UNIX V4 remains. That's unfortunate as this specific version is especially interesting: it's the first version of UNIX in which the kernel and some of the core utilities were rewritten in the new C programming language. Until now, the only surviving parts known were the source code to a slightly older version of the kernel and a few &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt; pages – plus the Programmer's Manual [PDF], from November 1973.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More was to follow – some hours later, he continued:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We have some more information on this! One of @regehr's grad students did some excellent sleuthing and figured out that this was received by Martin Newell: https://archive.org/details/unix_news_july-30-1975/page/n9/mode/2up&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If that name sounds familiar to you, it's probably because his teapot is ubiquitous in computer graphics: https://graphics.cs.utah.edu/teapot/&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, this is the original copy of UNIX Fourth Edition received from AT&amp;amp;T by the inventor of the Utah Teapot – as seen in the original Windows NT OpenGL screensaver.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The elusive goal of Unix – or Linux – simplicity&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Forgetting the history of Unix is coding us into a corner&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Beta of Unix version 2 restored to life&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Unix Epochalypse might be sooner than you think&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ricci said:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The staff member who found it is planning to drive it to the CHM, rather than ship it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That being the Computer History Museum in Mountain View, California – which Google Maps tells us is a mere 771 miles away, a modest 12 hours' drive. The software librarian at the CHM is the redoubtable Al Kossow of Bitsavers, who commented in the thread that he is on the case. On the TUHS mailing list, he explained how he plans to do it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;taping off the head read amplifier, using a multi-channel high speed analog to digital converter which dumps into 100-ish gigabytes of RAM, then an analysis program Len Shustek wrote: https://github.com/LenShustek/readtape&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It is a '70s 1200ft 3M tape, likely 9 track, which has a pretty good chance of being recoverable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He also noted:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is rare enough that I'm pushing the recovery of it up near the top of my project queue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Reg FOSS desk has occasionally corresponded with Kossow, and we feel sure that this precious find could be in no better hands. ®&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45857695</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 16:12:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cloudflare scrubs Aisuru botnet from top domains list</title><link>https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/11/cloudflare-scrubs-aisuru-botnet-from-top-domains-list/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a380bbd25c1024c3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the past week, domains associated with the massive Aisuru botnet have repeatedly usurped Amazon, Apple, Google and Microsoft in Cloudflare’s public ranking of the most frequently requested websites. Cloudflare responded by redacting Aisuru domain names from their top websites list. The chief executive at Cloudflare says Aisuru’s overlords are using the botnet to boost their malicious domain rankings, while simultaneously attacking the company’s domain name system (DNS) service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aisuru is a rapidly growing botnet comprising hundreds of thousands of hacked Internet of Things (IoT) devices, such as poorly secured Internet routers and security cameras. The botnet has increased in size and firepower significantly since its debut in 2024, demonstrating the ability to launch record distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attacks nearing 30 terabits of data per second.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Until recently, Aisuru’s malicious code instructed all infected systems to use DNS servers from Google — specifically, the servers at 8.8.8.8. But in early October, Aisuru switched to invoking Cloudflare’s main DNS server — 1.1.1.1 — and over the past week domains used by Aisuru to control infected systems started populating Cloudflare’s top domain rankings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As screenshots of Aisuru domains claiming two of the Top 10 positions ping-ponged across social media, many feared this was yet another sign that an already untamable botnet was running completely amok. One Aisuru botnet domain that sat prominently for days at #1 on the list was someone’s street address in Massachusetts followed by “.com”. Other Aisuru domains mimicked those belonging to major cloud providers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare tried to address these security, brand confusion and privacy concerns by partially redacting the malicious domains, and adding a warning at the top of its rankings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Note that the top 100 domains and trending domains lists include domains with organic activity as well as domains with emerging malicious behavior.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare CEO Matthew Prince told KrebsOnSecurity the company’s domain ranking system is fairly simplistic, and that it merely measures the volume of DNS queries to 1.1.1.1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The attacker is just generating a ton of requests, maybe to influence the ranking but also to attack our DNS service,” Prince said, adding that Cloudflare has heard reports of other large public DNS services seeing similar uptick in attacks. “We’re fixing the ranking to make it smarter. And, in the meantime, redacting any sites we classify as malware.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Renee Burton, vice president of threat intel at the DNS security firm Infoblox, said many people erroneously assumed that the skewed Cloudflare domain rankings meant there were more bot-infected devices than there were regular devices querying sites like Google and Apple and Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Cloudflare’s documentation is clear — they know that when it comes to ranking domains you have to make choices on how to normalize things,” Burton wrote on LinkedIn. “There are many aspects that are simply out of your control. Why is it hard? Because reasons. TTL values, caching, prefetching, architecture, load balancing. Things that have shared control between the domain owner and everything in between.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alex Greenland is CEO of the anti-phishing and security firm Epi. Greenland said he understands the technical reason why Aisuru botnet domains are showing up in Cloudflare’s rankings (those rankings are based on DNS query volume, not actual web visits). But he said they’re still not meant to be there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s a failure on Cloudflare’s part, and reveals a compromise of the trust and integrity of their rankings,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Greenland said Cloudflare planned for its Domain Rankings to list the most popular domains as used by human users, and it was never meant to be a raw calculation of query frequency or traffic volume going through their 1.1.1.1 DNS resolver.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“They spelled out how their popularity algorithm is designed to reflect real human use and exclude automated traffic (they said they’re good at this),” Greenland wrote on LinkedIn. “So something has evidently gone wrong internally. We should have two rankings: one representing trust and real human use, and another derived from raw DNS volume.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why might it be a good idea to wholly separate malicious domains from the list? Greenland notes that Cloudflare Domain Rankings see widespread use for trust and safety determination, by browsers, DNS resolvers, safe browsing APIs and things like TRANCO.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“TRANCO is a respected open source list of the top million domains, and Cloudflare Radar is one of their five data providers,” he continued. “So there can be serious knock-on effects when a malicious domain features in Cloudflare’s top 10/100/1000/million. To many people and systems, the top 10 and 100 are naively considered safe and trusted, even though algorithmically-defined top-N lists will always be somewhat crude.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over this past week, Cloudflare started redacting portions of the malicious Aisuru domains from its Top Domains list, leaving only their domain suffix visible. Sometime in the past 24 hours, Cloudflare appears to have begun hiding the malicious Aisuru domains entirely from the web version of that list. However, downloading a spreadsheet of the current Top 200 domains from Cloudflare Radar shows an Aisuru domain still at the very top.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to Cloudflare’s website, the majority of DNS queries to the top Aisuru domains — nearly 52 percent — originated from the United States. This tracks with my reporting from early October, which found Aisuru was drawing most of its firepower from IoT devices hosted on U.S. Internet providers like AT&amp;amp;T, Comcast and Verizon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experts tracking Aisuru say the botnet relies on well more than a hundred control servers, and that for the moment at least most of those domains are registered in the .su top-level domain (TLD). Dot-su is the TLD assigned to the former Soviet Union (.su’s Wikipedia page says the TLD was created just 15 months before the fall of the Berlin wall).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Cloudflare blog post from October 27 found that .su had the highest “DNS magnitude” of any TLD, referring to a metric estimating the popularity of a TLD based on the number of unique networks querying Cloudflare’s 1.1.1.1 resolver. The report concluded that the top .su hostnames were associated with a popular online world-building game, and that more than half of the queries for that TLD came from the United States, Brazil and Germany [it’s worth noting that servers for the world-building game Minecraft were some of Aisuru’s most frequent targets].&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A simple and crude way to detect Aisuru bot activity on a network may be to set an alert on any systems attempting to contact domains ending in .su. This TLD is frequently abused for cybercrime and by cybercrime forums and services, and blocking access to it entirely is unlikely to raise any legitimate complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45857836</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 16:25:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Marko – A declarative, HTML‑based language that makes building web apps fun</title><link>https://markojs.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a876cc8c70be3ce3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Trusted&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Powering high-traffic, production-grade websites like eBay.com&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Powering high-traffic, production-grade websites like eBay.com&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you know HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, you know Marko&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Streaming, resumable, optimizing compiler, and a tiny runtime&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From simple HTML templates to powerful components as needed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marko is HTML re‑imagined as a language for building dynamic and reactive user interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just about any valid HTML is valid Marko, but Marko extends the HTML language to allow building modern applications in a declarative way.&lt;/p&gt;Check it out!&lt;p&gt;Marko streams content to your users as soon as it's ready. No waiting for client side JavaScript bundles or data requests to start rendering.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;HTML, assets, and images are loaded as soon as possible with asynchronous content loading in as it completes.&lt;/p&gt;Learn How&lt;p&gt;Browsers and servers are built differently, shouldn't your code be too? Marko compiles your templates to perform their best with optimized, environment-specific output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faster loads. Smaller bundles. One seamless language.&lt;/p&gt;Learn How&lt;p&gt;Marko has built-in TypeScript support , with strong type inference that works across templates and components. Editors get full language features like autocompletion, jump-to-definition, syntax highlighting, and clean formatting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build confidently. Catch errors early. Write better code, faster.&lt;/p&gt;Explore&lt;p&gt;Need help? Want to Contribute?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get involved in the Marko Community!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45858905</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 18:43:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>WriterdeckOS</title><link>https://writerdeckos.com</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5e878a1b412da7b6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Requirements:&lt;lb/&gt; - 64bit processor (Intel/AMD)&lt;lb/&gt; - Will not work on an ARM processorThe installation ISO is hosted at The Internet Archive:&lt;lb/&gt; https://archive.org/details/tinkerWD-1.0Donate to the Internet Archive here: Donate&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;writerdeckOS is an operating system used to convert laptops and many Chromebooks (with 64-bit Intel/AMD processors) into a "Writer Deck".A Writer Deck is a device that is used solely for writing text.It minimizes distractions. No internet browsing, no apps, no games, no social media, no notifications. Not even major formatting!Just Writing.writerdeckOS is very light weight and specifically seeks to lower the barrier of entry to creating writer decks. It converts older, reused, refurbished, or inexpensive laptops into a dedicated writing machine.writerdeckOS sits on top of a "headless" Debian Linux image and boots directly into a console based text editor. We're using the Tilde Text Editor because it is simple text editor, has an intuitive User Interface, and allows for customized color schemes for light and dark modes.More information:&lt;lb/&gt; - General Info about Writer Decks: writerDeck.org&lt;lb/&gt; - Reddit: writerdeckOS Subreddit&lt;lb/&gt; - writerdeckOS: Github Repo | Archive Org ISO Page&lt;lb/&gt; - Tilde Text Editor: Github Repo | Website&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DISCLAIMER: writerdeckOS comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY, to the extent permitted by applicable law.WARNING: You are engaging in a DIY endeavor. You may break your machine. The installation may not work. You may erase the old operating system and not be able to start your device up ever again. This OS has only been tested on a couple of machines and is not guaranteed to work on every laptop. Only try this if you're willing to accept the consequences.WARNING: This will erase everything on the laptop you install it on. Please make backups before beginning.1. With the downloaded ISO, Create a bootable USB: Tutorial&lt;lb/&gt; 2. Plug the USB into your designated laptop and boot from USB: (Depending on your laptop, either press F12, Escape, or F2 during the boot up sequence. Check your laptop manual for specific instructions. Note: You may have to turn "Secure Boot" off within your BIOS.)&lt;lb/&gt; 3. Installation will proceed automatically. The hard drive and all previous contents will be erased and the writer deck will be installed.&lt;lb/&gt; 4. Once finished, press Enter when prompted. Between when the device shuts off and just as it starts up, remove the Installation USB.&lt;lb/&gt; 5. For First Boot you will enter&lt;lb/&gt; - Username: author&lt;lb/&gt; - Password: password&lt;lb/&gt; 6. After start up, shut down by pressing your laptops power button (this will take a short while but will be quicker on subsequent poweroffs).&lt;lb/&gt; 7. Restart laptop and it will boot directly into Tilde word processor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Always remember to Save (Ctrl+S). There is NO autosaving!!!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn On: Press your laptop's power button.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn Off: Press your laptop's power button.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn Off (alternate): From Tilde, Press Ctrl+Q to quit. From the command line, type: shutdown (press enter)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To use Tilde: Press Alt+F to bring up the menu system and use arrow keys to navigate around. More info: Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To change color scheme: (Light Mode / Dark Mode) - Press Alt+O, arrow key down to "Interface" and press Enter, then select "Text Area Attributes", then "Text". Change Foreground and Background Color to desired colors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Enable Word Wrap: Press Alt+O, arrow key down and select "Buffer Defaults". Press spacebar on "Wrap text", choose OK, and then restart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;USBs: Access plugged in USBs in the "USBs" folder in the home directory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Access File System: Press Ctrl+Q to quit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Navigate File System, Move Files, &amp;amp; Delete Files: Use common Bash commands: Tutorial&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¦ Photo of a writerdeckOS in Light Mode&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developer Mode: Press Ctrl+Q to quit Tilde. Underlying file system and command prompt is running Bash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To restart Tilde from the Command Line: Type tilde and press enter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To change keyboard layout: From the initial command line, run: exit to drop to a lower command line, then run sudo dpkg-reconfigure keyboard-configuration then run: sudo service keyboard-setup restart&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To use a different text editor besides Tilde: Edit the /home/author/.profile file. The Tinker WriterDeck comes preinstalled with several text editors. Use apt to install more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To connect to the internet: (For syncing and app installation purposes) Use: nmcli (from the command prompt).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To sync folders to cloud services: Follow service specific instructions. Examples: Nextcloud | Dropbox | Google Drive&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To Encrypt Harddrive &amp;amp; Require Password to Log in: Install a headless version of Debian 12.10 "Bookworm" and select Full Disk Encryption using LUKS upon installation. Then run configuration script found: Here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;â¦ Photo of a writerdeckOS in Dark Mode&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For questions or assistance, you're welcome to reach out directly to the developer via the Fediverse: @[email protected]For group discussion and questions, you're welcome to join the Reddit /r/writerdeckOS subreddit here: Reddit Discussion ThreadFor technical issues and bug discussions, please open an Issue Ticket on Github here: Github Issue Tracker&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45858945</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 18:49:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Facebook enables gender discrimination in job ads, European human rights rules</title><link>https://www.cnn.com/2025/02/28/tech/facebook-gender-discrimination-europe-ruling-asequals-intl</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="fc94b23912823b33"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Editor’s Note: This story, originally published in February 2025, is part of ‘Systems Error,’ a series by CNN’s As Equals, investigating how your gender shapes your life online. For information about how CNN As Equals is funded and more, check out our FAQs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update: In a separate ruling, in October 2025, the French equalities regulator said Meta’s Facebook algorithm breached France’s anti-discrimination law by displaying different job advertisements to men and women. The independent watchdog said Meta must ensure its ads are non-discriminatory and report back within three months. Meta has said it disagrees with the ruling and is assessing its options.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A European human rights body has ruled that Facebook’s algorithm shows gender bias when promoting job advertisements, marking what activists say is a crucial step in holding big tech companies accountable for the design of their platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Netherlands Institute for Human Rights said in a February 18 decision that Facebook’s algorithm reinforced gender stereotypes by mainly showing “typically female professions” to female Facebook users in the Netherlands and that Meta (META), the social platform’s owner, should have monitored and adjusted its algorithm to prevent that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Institute’s decision follows CNN As Equals reporting revealing that Facebook users in Europe were missing out on job opportunities due to gender bias.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 2023 article was based on findings shared with CNN by international non-profit Global Witness, which investigated Facebook’s job ads and found that ads in the Netherlands and five other countries often targeted users based on historical gender stereotypes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, ads for mechanic positions were predominantly shown to men, while those for preschool teacher roles were primarily directed to women. Global Witness said its experiments in the Netherlands, France, India, Ireland, the United Kingdom and South Africa demonstrated that the algorithm perpetuated similar biases around the world. The non-profit’s investigation led to four complaints from the Dutch human rights group Bureau Clara Wichmann and the French organization Fondation des Femmes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Netherlands Institute for Human Rights said in its February ruling that Meta Platforms Ireland Ltd., which manages Facebook ads in Europe, failed to demonstrate that its advertising algorithm does not engage in prohibited gender discrimination. The Dutch body said Facebook must revise its advertising algorithm to prevent further discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The European Union has several directives that prohibit discrimination based on gender, including in online advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Institute’s ruling added that “Meta Ireland has acknowledged that the gender data point can be part of the algorithm. Meta Ireland has not refuted that this data point can promote stereotyping via the algorithm.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Meta spokesperson told CNN that it would not be commenting on the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta spokesperson Ashley Settle previously told CNN that the company applies “targeting restrictions to advertisers when setting up campaigns for employment, as well as housing and credit ads.” Those audience targeting restrictions are in place in the United States, Canada and more than 40 European countries and territories, including France and the Netherlands, according to Meta.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We do not allow advertisers to target these ads based on gender,” Settle said in a 2023 statement. “We continue to work with stakeholders and experts across academia, human rights groups and other disciplines on the best ways to study and address algorithmic fairness.” Meta did not respond to questions from CNN at the time about how the algorithm that runs its ad system is trained. In a 2020 blog post about its ad delivery system, Facebook said ads are shown to users based on a variety of factors, including “behavior on and off” the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Berty Bannor of Bureau Clara Wichmann celebrated the Dutch institute’s decision, telling CNN that the ruling was significant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Today is a great day for Dutch Facebook users, who have an accessible mechanism to hold multinational tech companies such as Meta accountable and ensure the rights they enjoy offline are upheld in the digital space,” Bannor said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I see this as a first step in showing that anti-discrimination laws apply just as much to big tech companies as they do to the offline world,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rosie Sharpe, Senior Campaigner on Digital Threats at Global Witness, said the ruling “marks an important step towards holding Big Tech accountable for how they design their services and the discriminatory impact their algorithms can have on people.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We hope this ruling can be used as a springboard for further action, in Europe and beyond,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the decision by the Netherlands Institute for Human Rights is not legally binding, experts say that, if the case is further escalated, a court will be required to consider the Institute’s findings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dutch lawyer Anton Ekker, who specializes in artificial intelligence and digital rights, told CNN that the Institute’s ruling could lead to fines by the Dutch data protection regulator or orders to modify specific algorithms, specifically those that reinforce inequalities and disproportionately harm marginalized groups based on gender, race, ethnicity or religion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If Meta does not take action on the job ads algorithm, NGOs might choose to pursue further legal action to stop the discriminatory use of its algorithms, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Dutch ruling comes as protection of digital rights has been severely undermined, particularly for women and marginalized groups, Bannor said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Last month, Meta said it would end its diversity, equity and inclusion programs, change its policies on hateful conduct on its platforms and drop its third-party fact-checking programs in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Users are now allowed to, for example, refer to “women as household objects or property” or “transgender or non-binary people as ‘it,’” according to a section of the policy prohibiting such speech that was removed. A new section of the policy notes Meta will allow “allegations of mental illness or abnormality when based on gender or sexual orientation, given political and religious discourse about transgenderism and homosexuality.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Previously, such comments would have been subject to removal by Meta’s moderators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meta has faced various allegations of discrimination over the past decade, including lawsuits in the US regarding housing, employment and credit ads. As a result, the company has modified its algorithm for these ads in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sharpe at Global Witness told CNN that it’s “outrageous” the same changes were not applied globally, arguing that algorithms and AI are increasingly impacting everyday life and posing significant risks to social justice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CNN’s Kara Fox contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45859160</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 19:18:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Near mid-air collision at LAX between American Airlines and ITA [video]</title><link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-j76cp7bETw</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7055905545553646"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Press Copyright Contact us Creators Advertise Developers Terms Privacy Policy &amp;amp; Safety How YouTube works Test new features NFL Sunday Ticket © 2025 Google LLC&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45859216</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 19:26:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Avería: The Average Font (2011)</title><link>http://iotic.com/averia/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="367d013713a223d1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;am not a type designer. This is the story of the creation of a new font, Avería: the average of all the fonts on my computer. The field of typography has long fascinated me, and I love playing with creative programming ideas, so it was perhaps inevitable that the idea came to me one day of “generative typography”. A Google on the subject brought up little, and I put the idea to the back of my mind until it occurred to me that perhaps the process of averaging, or interpolating, existing fonts might bring up interesting results. Luckily at this point I didn't do any more web searching – instead I grabbed my laptop and came up with an initial idea for finding what the average of all my fonts might look like – by overlaying each letter at low opacity. The results can be seen in the below image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was done by printing each letter of each font, at the same point size, to lots of separate images, and then averaging them – using ImageMagick and PHP. The letters were aligned to the same centre point. I later realised that each font has a ‘baseline’ defined, and an origin on that baseline which each glyph is drawn relative to. The same process, repeated with equal origins, gives slightly different results (see below) – here you can see the baseline is very well-defined, with the glyphs becoming more blurred towards the top right of each.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was quite pleased with the results. It was only later that I discovered this had already been done – though it appeared that my end results (whilst not as beautifully animated) had a little more clarity, so I'm glad I tried for myself. But this didn't seem like the end of the journey. Whilst this was an interesting experiment, and showed an lot of correlation between a sample of common fonts (as well as a couple of oddities – notably the lower case ‘g’ which clearly exists in two distinct common forms), what I really wanted was an average which somehow preserved the well-defined edges of existing fonts. So I started considering ways to produce a smoother, sharper average of letter forms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One idea which seemed obvious was to simply take the blurry results of the first experiment, and use a threshold to create monochrome images. A few experiments in this direction (I first tried with a lower-case ‘f’, which I later found was never likely to give good results due to the variance in height of the middle cross-stroke) convinced me that I needed to look into cleverer ways to achieve this. Surely there must be a simple way to average shapes, while keeping the result as a shape?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It turns out not to be straightforward. There are many possible ways to ‘morph’ between two shapes – and what might seem the most natural generally depends on our perception of ‘features’ in the shapes. Consider the average of a capital I with serifs, and one without: the natural thing to do would be something like, make the serifs half as big, and use a horizontal stem width about half-way between the two glyphs. That's two feature concepts being applied to the abstract forms¹. To take a simpler example, what is the average of a square with the same square rotated 45˚? There are a few possibilities …&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, this stumped me for a while. I decided I needed to get to know fonts better, so I built a simple web app to view the lines, curves and control points present in the fonts I had. On this basis, I started to consider the ways the features (vertices, curves, stems, serifs etc) might be matched up between fonts. However, this was a rabbit hole I might never get to the bottom of - particularly when considering some of the more unusual varieties of font. Perhaps there was a simpler idea that was evading me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then it occurred to me: since my aim was to average a large number of fonts, perhaps it would be best to use a very simple process, and hope the results averaged out well over a large number of fonts. So, how about splitting each letter perimeter into lots of (say, 500) equally-spaced points, and just average between the corresponding positions of each, on each letter? It would be necessary to match up the points so they were about the same location in each letter, and then the process would be fairly simple².&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having found a simple process to use, I was ready to start. And after about a month of part-time slaving away (sheer fun! Better than any computer game) – in the process of which I learned lots about bezier curves and font metrics – I had a result. I call it Avería – which is a Spanish word related to the root of the word ‘average’. It actually means mechanical breakdown or damage. This seemed curiously fitting, and I was assured by a Spanish friend-of-a-friend that “Avería is an incredibly beautiful word regardless of its meaning”. So that's nice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along the way I naturally called on the counsel of the best designers I know – my brother Nick Sayers, Lloyd Thomas, Tom Muller and Chris McGrail, for advice. In the end, I decided to release the font using the SIL Open Font License – which means anyone can use it pretty much however they like – and to include within the family Regular, Bold and Light variants with Italics. Each is made from the corresponding subsets of the fonts on my machine. Also included is a “Gruesa” version made from all my fonts (725 in total).&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Family (ZIP, 369kB) [Updated 9 Nov 2011]&lt;lb/&gt; Avería at The Open Font Library&lt;lb/&gt; *NEW* by popular demand:&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Serif Family (ZIP, 323kB) OFLB&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Sans Family (ZIP, 320kB) OFLB&lt;lb/&gt; *NEW* Avería, Serif and Sans packaged as TTC TrueType collections (so you can install each family in one go, rather than one variant at a time). Thanks Ludwig:&lt;lb/&gt; Avería TTC Files (ZIP, 946kB)&lt;lb/&gt; *NEW* versions of Avería, based on OFL fonts from the Google Web Fonts directory - now available through GWF as Avería Libre:&lt;lb/&gt; Avería GWF Family (ZIP, 488kB)&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Serif GWF Family (ZIP, 432kB)&lt;lb/&gt; Avería Sans GWF Family (ZIP, 426kB)&lt;lb/&gt; Preview all&lt;lb/&gt; Feel free to email me if you have any questions – or use the comments box below.&lt;lb/&gt; N.B. I've had a number of emails from people asking if they can use Avería in various commercial / non-commercial projects. I'd love to hear if you do something with these fonts – but there's no need to ask permission. You are absolutely free to use them however you like. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45859243</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 19:29:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I Want You to Understand Chicago</title><link>https://aphyr.com/posts/397-i-want-you-to-understand-chicago</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9d28de95408392d3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want you to understand what it is like to live in Chicago during this time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every day my phone buzzes. It is a neighborhood group: four people were kidnapped at the corner drugstore. A friend a mile away sends a Slack message: she was at the scene when masked men assaulted and abducted two people on the street. A plumber working on my pipes is distraught, and I find out that two of his employees were kidnapped that morning. A week later it happens again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An email arrives. Agents with guns have chased a teacher into the school where she works. They did not have a warrant. They dragged her away, ignoring her and her colleagues’ pleas to show proof of her documentation. That evening I stand a few feet from the parents of Rayito de Sol and listen to them describe, with anguish, how good Ms. Diana was to their children. What it is like to have strangers with guns traumatize your kids. For a teacher to hide a three-year-old child for fear they might be killed. How their relatives will no longer leave the house. I hear the pain and fury in their voices, and I wonder who will be next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand what it is to pray in Chicago. On September 19th, Reverend David Black, lead pastor at First Presbyterian Church of Chicago, was praying outside the ICE detention center in Broadview when a DHS agent shot him in the head with pepper balls. Pepper balls are never supposed to be fired at the head because they can seriously injure, or even kill. “We could hear them laughing as they were shooting us from the roof,” Black recalled. He is not the only member of the clergy ICE has assaulted. Methodist pastor Hannah Kardon was violently arrested on October 17th, and Baptist pastor Michael Woolf was shot with pepper balls on November 1st.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand what it is to sleep in Chicago. On the night of September 30th, federal agents rappelled from a Black Hawk helicopter to execute a raid on an apartment building on the South Shore. Roughly three hundred agents deployed flashbangs, busted down doors, and took people indiscriminately. US citizens, including women and children, were grabbed from their beds, marched outside without even a chance to dress, zip-tied, and loaded into vans. Residents returned to find their windows and doors broken and their belongings stolen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand what it is to lead Chicago. On October 3rd, Alderperson Jesse Fuentes asked federal agents to produce a judicial warrant and allow an injured man at the hospital access to an attorney. The plainclothes agents grabbed Fuentes, handcuffed her, and took her outside the building. Her lawsuit is ongoing. On October 21st, Representative Hoan Huynh was going door-to-door to inform businesses of their immigration rights when he was attacked by six armed CBP agents, who boxed in his vehicle and pointed a gun at his face. Huynh says the agents tried to bash open his car window.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand what it is to live in Chicago. On October 9th, Judge Ellis issued a temporary restraining order requiring that federal agents refrain from deploying tear gas or shooting civilians without an imminent threat, and requiring two audible warnings. ICE and CBP have flaunted these court orders. On October 12th, federal agents shoved an attorney to the ground who tried to help a man being detained in Albany Park. Agents refused to identify themselves or produce a warrant, then deployed tear gas without warning. On October 14th, agents rammed a car on the East Side, then tear-gassed neighbors and police.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On October 23rd, federal agents detained seven people, including two U.S. citizens and an asylum seeker, in Little Village. Two worked for Alderperson Michael Rodriguez: his chief of staff Elianne Bahena, and police district council member Jacqueline Lopez. Again in Little Village, agents tear-gassed and pepper-sprayed protestors, seizing two high school students and a security guard, among others. Alderperson Byron Sigcho-Lopez reported that agents assaulted one of the students, who had blood on his face. On October 24th, agents in Lakeview emerged from unmarked cars, climbed a locked fence to enter a private yard, and kidnapped a construction worker. As neighbors gathered, they deployed four tear gas canisters. That same day, a few blocks away, men with rifles jumped out of SUVs and assaulted a man standing at a bus stop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“They were beating him,” said neighbor Hannah Safter. “His face was bleeding”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They returned minutes later and attacked again. A man from the Laugh Factory, a local comedy club, had come outside with his mother and sister. “His mom put her body in between them, and one of the agents kicked her in the face”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand what it is to be a family in Chicago. The next day, October 25th, federal agents tear-gassed children in Old Irving Park. Again, no warnings were heard. On October 26th, agents arrested a 70-year-old man and threw a 67-year old woman to the ground in Old Irving Park, then tear-gassed neighbors in Avondale. That same day, federal agents deployed tear gas at a children’s Halloween parade in Old Irving Park.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Kids dressed in Halloween costumes walking to a parade do not pose an immediate threat to the safety of a law enforcement officer. They just don’t. And you can’t use riot control weapons against them,” Judge Ellis said to Border Patrol chief Gregory Bovino.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand how the government speaks about Chicago. On November 3rd, paralegal Dayanne Figueroa, a US citizen, was driving to work when federal agents crashed into her car, drew their guns, and dragged her from the vehicle. Her car was left behind, coffee still in the cup holder, keys still in the car. The Department of Homeland Security blamed her, claiming she “violently resisted arrest, injuring two officers.” You can watch the video for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“All uses of force have been more than exemplary,” Bovino stated in a recent deposition. He is, as Judge Ellis put it, lying. Bovino personally threw a tear gas canister in Little Village. He claimed in a sworn deposition that he was struck in the head by a rock before throwing the canister, and when videos showed no rock, admitted that he lied about the event. When shown video of himself tackling peaceful protestor Scott Blackburn, Bovino refused to acknowledge that he tackled the man. Instead, he claimed, “That’s not a reportable use of force. The use of force was against me.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I find the government’s evidence to be simply not credible,” said Judge Ellis in her November 6th ruling. “The use of force shocks the conscience.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand what it is to be Chicago. To carry a whistle and have the ICIRR hotline in your phone. To wake up from nightmares of shouting militiamen and guns in your face. To rehearse every day how to calmly refuse entry, how to identify a judicial warrant, how to film and narrate an assault. To wake to helicopters buzzing your home, to feel your heart rate spike at the car horns your neighbors use to alert each other to ICE and CBP enforcement. To know that perhaps three thousand of your fellow Chicagoans have been disappeared by the government, but no one really knows for sure. To know that many of those seized were imprisoned a few miles away, as many as a hundred and fifty people in a cell, denied access to food, water, sanitation, and legal representation. To know that many of these agents—masked, without badge numbers or body cams, and refusing to identify themselves—will never face justice. To wonder what they tell their children.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The masked thugs who attack my neighbors, who point guns at elected officials and shoot pastors with pepper balls, who tear-gas neighborhoods, terrify children, and drag teachers and alderpeople away in handcuffs are not unprecedented. We knew this was coming a year ago, when Trump promised mass deportations. We knew it was coming, and seventy-seven million of us voted for it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This weight presses upon me every day. I am flooded with stories. There are so many I cannot remember them all; cannot keep straight who was gassed, beaten, abducted, or shot. I write to leave a record, to stare at the track of the tornado which tears through our city. I write to leave a warning. I write to call for help.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want you to understand, regardless of your politics, the historical danger of a secret police. What happens when a militia is deployed in our neighborhoods and against our own people. Left unchecked their mandate will grow; the boundaries of acceptable identity and speech will shrink. I want you to think about elections in this future. I want you to understand that every issue you care about—any hope of participatory democracy—is downstream of this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want you to understand what it is to love Chicago. To see your neighbors make the heartbreaking choice between showing up for work or staying safe. To march two miles long, calling out: “This is what Chicago sounds like!” To see your representatives put their bodies on the line and their voices in the fight. To form patrols to walk kids safely to school. To join rapid-response networks to document and alert your neighbors to immigration attacks. For mutual aid networks to deliver groceries and buy out street vendors so they can go home safe. To see your local journalists take the federal government to court. To talk to neighbor after neighbor, friend after friend, and hear yes, yes, it’s all hands on deck.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want you to understand Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45859402</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 19:47:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Humans have remote touch 'seventh sense' like sandpipers</title><link>https://techxplore.com/news/2025-11-humans-remote-seventh-sandpipers.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="96e4511ebbb1b911"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Humans have remote touch 'seventh sense' like sandpipers, research shows&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Gaby Clark&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;scientific editor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Andrew Zinin&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;lead editor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A study by researchers at Queen Mary University of London and University College London has found that humans have a form of remote touch, or the ability to sense objects without direct contact, a sense that some animals have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Human touch is typically understood as a proximal sense, limited to what we physically touch. However, recent findings in animal sensory systems have challenged this view. Certain shorebirds, such as sandpipers and plovers, use a form of "remote touch" to detect prey hidden beneath the sand. Remote touch allows the detection of objects buried under granular materials through subtle mechanical cues transmitted through the medium, when a moving pressure is applied nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study in IEEE International Conference on Development and Learning (ICDL) investigated whether humans share a similar capability. Participants moved their fingers gently through sand to locate a hidden cube before physically touching it. Remarkably, the results revealed a comparable ability to that seen in shorebirds, despite humans lacking the specialized beak structures that enable this sense in birds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Results show human hands have more sensitivity than expected&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By modeling the physical aspects of the phenomenon, the study found that human hands are remarkably sensitive, detecting the presence of buried objects by perceiving minute displacements in the sand surrounding them. This sensitivity approaches the theoretical physical threshold of what can be detected from mechanical "reflections" in granular material, when there is a sand movement that is "reflected" on a stable surface (the hidden object).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Do humans or robots perform better on remote touch?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When comparing a human's performance with a robotic tactile sensor trained using a Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) algorithm, humans achieved an impressive 70.7% precision within the expected detectable range. Interestingly, the robot could sense objects from slightly farther distances on average but often produced false positives, yielding only 40% overall precision.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These findings confirm that people can genuinely sense an object before physical contact, a surprising capacity for a sense that is usually concerned with objects that enter in direct contact with us. Both humans and robots performed very close to the maximum sensitivity predicted with physical models and displacement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why is the study important?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This research reveals that humans can detect objects buried in sand before actual contact, expanding our understanding of how far the sense of touch can reach. It provides quantitative evidence for a tactile skill not previously documented in humans. The findings also offer valuable benchmarks for improving assistive technology and robotic tactile sensing. By using human perception as a model, engineers can design robotic systems that integrate natural-like touch sensitivity for real-world applications such as probing, excavation, or search tasks where vision is limited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What are the wider implications?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elisabetta Versace, Senior Lecturer in Psychology and lead of the Prepared Minds Lab at Queen Mary University of London who conceived the human experiments said, "It's the first time that remote touch has been studied in humans and it changes our conception of the perceptual world (what is called the "receptive field") in living beings, including humans."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zhengqi Chen, Ph.D. student of Advanced Robotics Lab at Queen Mary University of London, said, "The discovery opens possibilities for designing tools and assistive technologies that extend human tactile perception. These insights could inform the development of advanced robots capable of delicate operations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"For example, locating archaeological artifacts without damage, or exploring sandy or granular terrains such as Martian soil or ocean floors. More broadly, this research paves the way for touch-based systems that make hidden or hazardous exploration safer, smarter, and more effective."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lorenzo Jamone, Associate Professor in Robotics &amp;amp; AI at University College London, said, "What makes this research especially exciting is how the human and robotic studies informed each other. The human experiments guided the robot's learning approach, and the robot's performance provided new perspectives for interpreting the human data. It's a great example of how psychology, robotics, and artificial intelligence can come together, showing that multidisciplinary collaboration can spark both fundamental discoveries and technological innovation."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers carried out two studies: the first, a human study assessing fingertip sensitivity to tactile cues from buried objects; the second, a robotic experiment using a tactile-equipped robotic arm and a Long Short-Term Memory model to detect object presence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The authors are Zhengqi Chen, Ph.D. student of Advanced Robotics Lab, Dr. Laura Crucianelli Lecturer in Psychology, Dr. Elisabetta Versace, Senior Lecturer in Psychology, all from Queen Mary University of London and Lorenzo Jamone, Associate Professor in Robotics and AI at University College London.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More information: Zhengqi Chen et al, Exploring Tactile Perception for Object Localization in Granular Media: A Human and Robotic Study, 2025 IEEE International Conference on Development and Learning (ICDL) (2025). DOI: 10.1109/icdl63968.2025.11204359&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45859928</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 21:00:45 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>