<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 15:10:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Python on the Edge: Fast, sandboxed, and powered by WebAssembly</title><link>https://wasmer.io/posts/python-on-the-edge-powered-by-webassembly</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="87ab2dfdccf438d4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Python on the Edge: Fast, sandboxed, and powered by WebAssembly&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are excited to announce full Python support in Wasmer Edge (Beta)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Founder &amp;amp; CEO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With AI workloads on the rise, the demand for Python support on WebAssembly on the Edge has grown rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, bringing Python to WebAssembly isn't trivial as it means supporting native modules like &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;pydantic&lt;/code&gt;.&amp;#13;
While projects like &lt;code&gt;pyodide&lt;/code&gt; made strides in running Python in the browser via WebAssembly, their trade-offs don't fully fit server-side needs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After months of hard work, today we're thrilled to announce full Python support in Wasmer Edge (Beta) powered by WebAssembly and WASIX.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now you can run FastAPI, Streamlit, Django, LangChain, MCP servers and more directly on Wasmer and Wasmer Edge! To accomplish it we had to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add support for dynamic linking (&lt;code&gt;dlopen&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;dlsym&lt;/code&gt;) into WASIX&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;libffi&lt;/code&gt;support (so Python libraries using&lt;code&gt;ctypes&lt;/code&gt;could be supported)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Polish Sockets and threading support in WASIX&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Release our own Python Package Index with many of the most popular Python Native libraries compiled to WASIX&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create our own alternative to Heroku Buildpacks / Nixpacks / Railpack / Devbox to automatically detect a project type from its source code and deploy it (including running with Wasmer or deploying to Wasmer Edge!). Updates will be shared soon!&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How fast is it?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This Python release is much faster than any of the other Python releases we did in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is fast. Insa…natively fast (it's even faster than our py2wasm project!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ wasmer run python/python@=0.2.0 --dir=. -- pystone.py&amp;#13;
Pystone(1.1) time for 50000 passes = 0.562538&amp;#13;
This machine benchmarks at 88882.9 pystones/second&amp;#13;
$ wasmer run python/python --dir=. -- pystone.py # Note: first run may take time&amp;#13;
Pystone(1.1) time for 50000 passes = 0.093556&amp;#13;
This machine benchmarks at 534439 pystones/second&amp;#13;
$ python3 pystone.py&amp;#13;
Pystone(1.1) time for 50000 passes = 0.0827736&amp;#13;
This machine benchmarks at 604057 pystones/second
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's 6x faster, and nearly indistinguishable from native Python performance… quite good, considering that your Python apps can now run fully sandboxed anywhere!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: the first time you run Python, it will take a few minutes to compile. We are working to improve this so no time will be spent on compilation locally.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;🚀 Even faster performance coming soon: we are trialing an optimization technique that will boost Python performance in Wasm to 95% of native Python speed. This is already powering our PHP server in production. Result: Near-native Python performance, fully sandboxed. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What it can run&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, you can run any kind of Python API server, powered by &lt;code&gt;fastapi&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;django&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;flask&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;starlette&lt;/code&gt;, connected to a MySQL database automatically when needed (FastAPI template, Django template).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can run &lt;code&gt;fastapi&lt;/code&gt; with websockets (example repo, demo).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can run &lt;code&gt;mcp&lt;/code&gt; servers (deploy using our MCP template, demo).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can run image processors like &lt;code&gt;pillow&lt;/code&gt;  (example repo, demo).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can run &lt;code&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt; inside Python (example repo, demo).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can run &lt;code&gt;streamlit&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;langchain&lt;/code&gt; (deploy using our LangChain template, demo).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can even run &lt;code&gt;pypandoc&lt;/code&gt;!  (example repo, demo).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Soon, we'll have full support for:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;curl_cffi&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;polars&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;gevent&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;greenlet&lt;/code&gt;(more on this soon!)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;Pytorch&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Wasmer VS alternatives&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Python on Wasmer Edge is just launching, but it's already worth asking: how does it stack up existing solutions?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Quick Comparison&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Feature / Platform&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Wasmer Edge&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Cloudflare&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;AWS Lambda&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Native modules (&lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt;, etc.)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Supported*&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;❌ Limited (no &lt;code&gt;libcurl&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Full support&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Multithreading &amp;amp; multiprocessing (&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;pandoc&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Yes&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;❌ No&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Yes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ASGI / WSGI frameworks (&lt;code&gt;uvicorn&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;daphne&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Supported&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;❌ Patched / limited&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;⚠️ Needs wrappers&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;WebSockets (&lt;code&gt;streamlit&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Yes&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;❌ No&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;❌ No&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Raw sockets (&lt;code&gt;libcurl&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Supported&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;❌ JS &lt;code&gt;fetch&lt;/code&gt; only&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Supported&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Multiple Python versions&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ In Roadmap (3.12, 3.14…)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;❌ Tied to bundled runtime&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ Supported&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Cold starts&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;⚡ Extremely fast&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;⏳ Medium (V8 isolates)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;⏳ Slow&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Code changes required&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;✅ None&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;⚠️ Some&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;⚠️ Wrappers&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pricing&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;💰 Affordable&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;💰 Higher&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;💰 Higher&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Cloudflare Workers (Python) / Pyodide&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ Most of the demos that we showcased on this article, are not runnable inside of Cloudflare:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;streamlit&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;pypandoc&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare launched Python support ~18 months ago, by using Pyodide inside workerd, their JavaScript-based Workers runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While great for browser-like environments, Pyodide has trade-offs that make it less suitable server-side. Here are the limitations when running Python in Cloudflare:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;❌ No support for &lt;code&gt;uvloop&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;uvicorn&lt;/code&gt;, or similar event-native frameworks (JS event loop patches break compatibility with native).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;❌ No pthreads or multiprocessing support, you can't call subprocesses like &lt;code&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt;or&lt;code&gt;pypandoc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;❌ No raw HTTP client sockets (HTTP clients are patched to use JS &lt;code&gt;fetch&lt;/code&gt;, no&lt;code&gt;libcurl&lt;/code&gt;available).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;❌ Limited to a bundled Python version and package set.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;⏳ Cold starts slower due to V8 isolate warmup.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why the limitations? Cloudflare relies on Pyodide: great in-browser execution, but server-side it implies no sockets, threads, or multiprocessing. The result: convenient for lightweight browser use, but might not be the best fit for real Python workloads on the server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In contrast, Wasmer Edge runs real Python on WASIX unmodified, so everything "just works", with near-native speed and fast cold starts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Amazon Lambda&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AWS Lambda doesn't natively run unmodified Python apps:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;❌ You need adapters (such as https://github.com/slank/awsgi or https://github.com/Kludex/mangum) for running your WSGI sites.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;❌ WebSockets are unsupported.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;⚠️ Setup is complex, adapters are often unmaintained.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why the limits? AWS Lambda requires you to use their HTTP lambda handler, which can cause incompatibility into your own HTTP servers. Also, because their lambda handlers are HTTP-based, there's no easy support for WebSockets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In contrast, Wasmer Edge supports any Python HTTP servers without requiring any code adaptation from your side.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Why Wasmer Edge Stands Out&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Closer to native Python than Pyodide (no JS involvement at all).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Faster cold starts and more compatibility than Cloudflare's Workers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;More compatible than AWS Lambda (no wrappers/adapters).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;More affordable across the board.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;🐍 It's Showtime!&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Python support in Wasmer and Wasmer Edge is already available and ready to use. We have set up many Python templates to help you get started in no time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;https://wasmer.io/templates?language=python&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To make things even better, we are working on a MCP server for Wasmer, so you will be able to plug Wasmer into ChatGPT or Anthropic and have your websites deploying from your vibe-coded projects. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;⚠️ Python in Wasmer Edge is still in Beta, so expect some rough edges if your project doesn't work out of the box… if you encounter any issues, please report them so we can work on enabling your workloads on Wasmer Edge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Create your first MCP Server in Wasmer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Go to https://wasmer.io/templates/mcp-chatgpt-starter?intent=at_vRxJIdtPCbKe&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Connect your Github account&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create a git repo from the template&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Deploy and enjoy!&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: source code available here: https://github.com/wasmer-examples/python-mcp-chatgpt-starter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Create your first Django app&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have set up a template for using Django + Uvicorn in Wasmer Edge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can start using it very easily, just click Deploy: https://wasmer.io/templates/django-starter?intent=at_WK0DIkt3CeKX&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deploying a Django app will create a MySQL DB for you in Wasmer Edge (Postgres support is coming soon), run migrations and prepare everything to run your website seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: source code available here: https://github.com/wasmer-examples/django-wasmer-starter&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ready to deploy your first Python app on Wasmer Edge?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are the best places to begin:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🚀 Starter Templates → Browse Python templates&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📖 Docs &amp;amp; Examples → Wasmer GitHub&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;💬 Community Support → Join our Discord&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👉 Deploy your first Python app now&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With WebAssembly and Wasmer, Python is now portable, sandboxed, and running at near-native speeds. Ready for AI workloads, APIs, and anything you can imagine at the edge.&lt;lb/&gt; The sky is the limit ❤️.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;About the Author&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Syrus Akbary is an enterpreneur and programmer. Specifically known for his contributions to the field of WebAssembly. He is the Founder and CEO of Wasmer, an innovative company that focuses on creating developer tools and infrastructure for running Wasm&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Founder &amp;amp; CEO&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How fast is it?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What it can run&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wasmer VS alternatives&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quick Comparison&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare Workers (Python) / Pyodide&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazon Lambda&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why Wasmer Edge Stands Out&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;🐍 It's Showtime!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create your first MCP Server in Wasmer&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create your first Django app&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deploy your first Python site in seconds with our managed cloud solution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h5"&gt;Read more&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;wasmerwasmer edgerustprojectsedgeweb scraper&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h6"&gt;Build a Web Scraper in Rust and Deploy to Wasmer Edge&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RudraAugust 14, 2023&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45362023</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 15:48:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Snapdragon X2 Elite ARM Laptop CPU</title><link>https://www.qualcomm.com/products/mobile/snapdragon/laptops-and-tablets/snapdragon-x2-elite</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e10fcdab2cdf53e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You need to enable JavaScript to run this app.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45366474</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 22:01:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Helium Browser</title><link>https://helium.computer/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="170e82509195b1e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Internet without interruptions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Best privacy and unbiased ad-blocking by default. Handy features like native !bangs and split view. No adware, no bloat, no noise. People-first and fully open source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Best privacy by default, not as a hidden option&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helium blocks ads, trackers, fingerprinting, third-party cookies, cryptominers, and phishing websites by default thanks to preinstalled uBlock Origin. No extra steps are needed, and there are no biased exceptions â unlike other browsers. &lt;lb/&gt; The browser itself doesn't have any ads, trackers, or analytics. Helium also doesn't make any web requests without your explicit consent, it makes zero web requests on first launch. &lt;lb/&gt; Not enough? Increase privacy even further with ungoogled-chromium flags or uBlock Origin filters. You're finally at the steering wheel of your privacy on the Internet â not in a toy car, but in a real race car. &lt;lb/&gt; We will always stand by our promise of the best privacy and will never prioritize profit over people, unlike big corporations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Respectful by design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helium doesn't annoy you with anything and never will. It doesn't do anything without your consent: no unprovoked tabs about updates or sponsors, no persistent popups telling you about features you don't care about, no weird restarts. &lt;lb/&gt; Nothing interrupts you, jumps in your face, or breaks your flow. Everything just makes sense. You're in full control.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Fast, efficient, and light&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helium is based on Chromium, the fastest and most optimized browser yet. Helium builds on this base to improve performance and save even more energy. You will notice a difference after using Helium for a day. It doesn't slow down over time. &lt;lb/&gt; All bloat is removed: Helium is one of the lightest modern browsers available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Powerful when you need it&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open pages side-by-side with split view to get even more things done at once. Quickly copy page links with â+Shift+C and share your discoveries with ease. Install any web apps and use them as standalone desktop apps without duplicating Chromium.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Designed to get out of your way&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helium's interface is compact and minimalistic, but it doesn't compromise on beauty or functionality. More web content fits on the screen at once, and the browser interface doesn't get in your way. You can hide everything extra from the toolbar if it annoys you. &lt;lb/&gt; Helium is built with attention to detail. Nothing jiggles or flickers abnormally. Your actions aren't throttled or stopped by lag. Everything's fast, smooth, and simple. Comfort and simplicity are among our top priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Works with all Chromium extensions, privately&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All Chromium extensions are supported and work right away, by default, including all MV2 extensions. We'll keep support for MV2 extensions for as long as possible. &lt;lb/&gt; Helium anonymizes all internal requests to the Chrome Web Store via Helium services. Thanks to this, Google can't track your extension downloads or target ads using this data. No other browser does this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Free and fully open-source&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All parts of the Helium browser are open source, including online services. You can self-host Helium services and use your own instance in your browser. &lt;lb/&gt; Everything is available on GitHub. No exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Always safe and sound&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We release new Chromium updates (such as security patches) as soon as possible. Your browser will always be safe and up to date. &lt;lb/&gt; Helium updates itself automatically on macOS, with auto-updating options available on Linux and Windows. &lt;lb/&gt; All builds are available on GitHub, and you can even make one yourself. The choice is yours!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Best security practices for everyone, by default&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helium enforces HTTPS on all websites and warns you when a website doesn't support it. Passkeys just work. &lt;lb/&gt; There's no built-in password manager. Passwords should be separate from a web browser to be truly secure and immutable. &lt;lb/&gt; There's also no cloud-based history/data sync. You should be the only one with access to your browsing data, not some conglomerate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Browse the Internet faster with !bangs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Skip the search engine and go directly to the website you want. Choose from over 13,000 bangs that make the Internet a breeze to browse, such as !w for Wikipedia, !gh for GitHub, and !wa for Wolfram Alpha. &lt;lb/&gt; Want to chat with AI? Just add !chatgpt or any other AI provider name at the start of your query. Helium will start a new chat for you without sending your prompt anywhere else. &lt;lb/&gt; Helium bangs are the fastest and most private implementation of bangs yet. They work offline, directly in your browser. &lt;lb/&gt; Not sure which bang to use? Check out the full list of bangs!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The web browser made for people, with love&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're making a web browser that we enjoy using ourselves. Helium's main goal is to provide an honest, comfortable, privacy-respecting, and non-invasive browsing experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Perfect for developers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helium is based on Chromium and doesn't break any web APIs or standards, despite the focus on privacy. DevTools have been cleaned up and no longer nag you with anything. There's nothing that gets in your way of creating the Internet of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Perfect for everyone on the go&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Helium's efficiency makes it handy for everyone with their laptop on the go. Split view and quick link copying make it easier than ever to get things done faster. Helium loads pages faster and saves data by blocking ads and other crap.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Ready to try Helium?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's never too late to get your internet life back on the right track. Helium can transfer your most important stuff from other browsers in one click. We hope you'll love it!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45366867</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 22:51:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Do YC after you graduate: Early decision for students</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/early-decision</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b61d01d108cf1634"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apply now, do YC after you graduate. For students who want to finish school before doing YC. Get funded the moment you're accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sneha and Anushka, founders of Spur (S24), applied in Fall 2023 for the S24 batch using Early Decision. This allowed them to graduate in May 2024 and then do YC. They've since raised $4.5M from top investors for their AI-powered QA testing tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early Decision lets you apply to YC while you're still in school and reserve your spot in a future batch. For example, you apply in Fall of this year, for a spot in the summer batch of the following year. You submit the same YC application as if you were applying for the upcoming batch. If you're accepted, we'll fund you immediately and hold your place for after you graduate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This program is designed for students who want to finish their degree before starting a company. If you're considering working on your own startup after graduation, Early Decision makes it easy to lock in your spot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if you're not completely sure yet if you want to do a startup, you should still apply. There is no downside.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, if you're not in your final year, you can still apply for Early Decision. You'll be able to finish the school year you're currently in, and then either join a later batch or decide to drop out and start sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most common path is students applying in the fall of their final year and joining the summer batch after graduating in Spring. But you can apply for any batch in the future within reason. The application and interview process is the same as if you were applying for the upcoming batch. Once you're accepted, YC funds you right away and confirms your future batch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you fill out your YC application, you'll see a question asking which batch you want to apply for. Simply select "A batch after Winter 2026" to indicate you're applying for Early Decision, and tell us which batch you'd like to be considered for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The batch preference question in the YC application&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many students want to finish their degree or complete more of their education before starting a company. Also we know that many students spend a lot of time in Fall or during their final year applying for jobs or internships. Early Decision gives students another option: apply to YC and bet on yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45367046</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 23:12:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Knotty: A domain-specific language for knitting patterns</title><link>https://t0mpr1c3.github.io/knotty/index.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a5ebd7a76a7f3314"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;▼ Knotty 1 Introduction 2 How to Make a New Pattern 3 Input and Output 4 Code Examples 5 Reference On this page: Knotty 8.11 contents ← prev up next → Knotty Tom Price &amp;lt; t0mpr1c3@gmail.com &amp;gt; ( require knotty ) package: knotty-lib A domain-specific language for knitting patterns. contents ← prev up next →&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45369768</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 06:13:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Some interesting stuff I found on IX LANs</title><link>https://blog.benjojo.co.uk/post/ixp-bad-broadcast-packets-interesting</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f78b85556837a9c2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These days the internet as a whole is mostly constructed out of point to point ethernet circuits, meaning an ethernet interface (mostly optical) attached directly from one routing device to another routing device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However that is not always the case, as the humble “internet exchange” (IX) still exists, and while the relevancy of IXs are progressively being diminished by the internet increasingly being concentrated into a small handful of content networks and IXs not keeping up with the lowering price of transit or private fiber connections to the largest networks, there are still a large number of networks that’s attached to at least one IX fabric.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IXs are a little bit strange, as they are at their core practically identical to a simple ethernet switch you may find in your home or office (except your home switch is unlikely to be doing terabits per second of traffic). As IXs depend on the ethernet switches interest in only being the MAC addresses of traffic and not the Layer 3 IP addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However home and small and medium business (SMB) routers often come with defaults that make life a lot easier for networks way of desktop computers and common office equipment on them, these same defaults are at the very least annoying and at the very worst actively exploitable if put on a IX LAN with many untrusted participants.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company that I run and operate has a large number of ports at internet exchanges (at a rough estimate I am the top 13 of all networks on the internet in this metric!), and alongside the route collecting that bgp.tools does on these IX ports, it also listens in on the broadcast and multicast traffic that happens on these exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t that magical, at its core it works by running tcpdump on each IX port, and picking up the BUM traffic, parsing what it is looking at (and throwing away the unknown unicast, since that is a separate common problem that I don’t want to get involved with), and reporting that data back up the chain to bgp.tools’s website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This creates little warning icons (or alerts if they use the monitoring product) on their IX membership rows to let them and others know that something is not configured correctly&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I first started off developing this feature I was basically going off the top of my head on what the obvious mistakes that were likely to happen on misconfigured IX ports. However at the same time I developed a “miscellaneous packets” feed that collected packets that I didn’t have code to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Checking that miscellaneous packet feed every week has been a lot of fun and deeply terrifying on what networks have been sending into exchanges. Here are some of the things that bgp.tools finds on a regular basis&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With large deployments of routers and switches it is often very difficult to actually locate where each device is plugged into at either end. For this exact reason, many vendors ship protocols that emit various identifier packets that are designed to help operations teams identify the “far side” of each port&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Low&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: Low&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Information Disclosure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Link Layer Discovery Protocol is a pretty common cross vendor protocol for doing exactly this, it is also sometimes used to automatically configure capabilities like higher wattage power over ethernet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of a LLDP packet (and what information it discloses) from my own network:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;root@blah:~# lldpctl 
------------------------------------------------------------------
LLDP neighbors:
------------------------------------------------------------------
Interface:    ens1f0, via: LLDP, RID: 3, Time: 146 days, 02:13:47
  Chassis:     
    ChassisID:    mac 1c:34:da:90:90:01
    SysName:      bgptools-switch
    SysDescr:     Debian GNU/Linux 12 (bookworm) Linux [...]
    MgmtIP:       10.xxx.xxx.2
    MgmtIface:    3
    MgmtIP:       fdd2:xxx::1
    MgmtIface:    3
    Capability:   Bridge, on
    Capability:   Router, on
    Capability:   Wlan, off
    Capability:   Station, off
  Port:        
    PortID:       mac 1c:34:da:90:90:26
    PortDescr:    swp8
    TTL:          120
    PMD autoneg:  supported: yes, enabled: yes
      Adv:          1000Base-X, HD: no, FD: yes
      MAU oper type: 10GigBaseCX4 - X copper over 8 pair 100-Ohm balanced cable
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: High&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Information Disclosure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cisco Discovery Protocol is a older and proprietary to Cisco (although that does not stop many vendors from having copied it) version of LLDP&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: High&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Information Disclosure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The popular budget network equipment vendor Mikrotik ships by default with a feature called “Mikrotik Neighbor Discovery Protocol” enabled by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is an example decoded MNDP packet from a network on FranceIX&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;    Seq: 134398
    MAC Address: 08:55:31:1b:9c:aa
    Identity: DC2.A23.CCR02
    Version: 6.49.6 (stable)
    Platform: MikroTik
    Uptime: 2239h52m39s
    SoftwareID: HBWH-7QHV
    Board: CCR1009-7G-1C-1S+
    IPv6Address: 2001:7f8:54::1:85
    InterfaceName: FRANCE_IX
    IPv4Address: 37.49.237.85
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can see what they named the device , what type of device it is, the interface name (FRANCE_IX), and the device uptime.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most consumer devices when they come on the network do not know what IP address/gateway they are supposed to be using, This is because in most environments you do not want to have machines that have statically configured addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However IX’s are not these kinds of environments, as they are environments where all participants have been assigned a very specific IP address to use on the LAN. This does not stop these automatic IP address assignment protocols from attempting to grab IP addresses with some configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Medium&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: High&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Targeted traffic redirection&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the exact same protocol that your mobile phone or laptop is using, just being blasted out to terabit/s per second switching fabrics. When a IX participant is asking for addresses with DHCP on the exchange, any one of the entities connected (some of which may be considered adversaries of your state) could reply to their request and assign them an IP address and default gateway, the latter possibly redirecting large amounts of traffic through them!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: High&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: People using your network for free&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Low&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IPv6 Router Advertisement is a protocol where routers periodically announced onto the LAN but they are capable of acting as a gateway (and optionally include instructions for clients to generate IPv6 addresses automatically), this is useful for IPv6 deployment, but this behavior is absolutely not desirable on internet exchanges as you do not want to have people use you as a gateway for the entire internet over peering LANs, as effectively giving them free internet transit, which is typically bad for business.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately this feature is enabled by default on Cisco and Arista, meaning it is so common that bgp.tools has a dedicated icon for it on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On exchanges there is generally only one accepted routing protocol that is allowed to be used between members and that is BGP. However that does not seem to stop other networks from accidentally enabling other protocols, some of which automatically “flood” messages to broadcast so they can look for peers to automatically establish relationships with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Low&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: You will import other peoples internal routes&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: People can insert routes into your network&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OSPF and IS-IS are the classic internal routing protocols that a lot of networks use to manage their internal routing table. This internal routing table is where the more specific routes for individual customers or subscriber pools exist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While OSPF and IS-IS offer an ability to restrict sessions that are automatically started without a given password in configuration, a decent number of networks do not use this feature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result of this is if these networks without a password configured meet each other on the internet exchange with OSPF/IS-IS configured they will automatically exchange internal routing tables of each other, the effects of this could range between a security risk because an attacker could inject routes into their internet routing table, all the way to a full blown outage as there would be overlap in internal network routes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Rare&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: You will import other peoples internal routes&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: People can insert routes into your network&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Routing Information Protocol is a very old way of doing what OSPF and IS-IS does on most modern networks today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RIP and RIPv2 have similar automatic peer configuration features, meaning that if two or more members on an internet exchange have this configured they will almost certainly automatically merge their internal routing tables.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Rare&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: People can manipulate MPLS labels&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: People can manipulate MPLS labels&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MultiProtocol Label Switching Label Distribution Protocol is a different type of internal routing protocol that rather than dealing with IP prefixes, handles the exchange of MPLS Labels. Given that a lot of networks deploy MPLS as the core way of moving data around in their network, exposing this to another untrusted party is pretty bad.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Low&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Quite a lot of vendors have their own form of proprietary ethernet loop detection, which often involve sending out probing packets into the LAN and seeing if they arrive back on any other interface (which would indicate a loop)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, here is a loop testing packet from a Huawei device&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Medium&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: Local disruption&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spanning Tree Protocol is a very common default that is enabled across most ethernet switches to combat ethernet loops. However accepting STP packets and sending them to other members of the exchange could result in disruption to the peer, as both sides try to agree a hierarchy with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SONiC is an open source network operating system (NOS) developed mostly by Microsoft, this is notable because almost all network operating systems are proprietary with no source code available. There are many reasons for this but one of the primary ones is that while there are many networking equipment vendors out there, the actual fundamental ASIC/Chips suppliers that are used to build high end equipment are limited down to around 3, with the majority of the market share being Broadcom. SONiC has in recent years become the most well known by name open source NOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately SONiC is also just not a very good pick for almost all users, and mortally let down by its software quality. An example of this is a script called arp_update that transmits a “Ping all IPv6 devices” packet to all connected LANs so that it can work around a potential limitation in the hardware that it supports. This is a nuisance on internet exchanges because once there are more than a handful of these devices on the exchange, every one is spending a non zero amount of resources responding to pointless pings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s hard for me to understate how crap of a workaround this is, and how much more crap this is for devices with internet exchange ports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a final category for things that are kind of just bizarre to see. They are just things that should not actually appear at all on any internet exchange port, and suggest something strange has happened. Either with unexpected devices being connected into the exchange fabric entirely, or very inadvisable configurations being used for public “network edge” ports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Low&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While Network Time Protocol is very common, most of the time it is configured in a unicast way (meaning that a device deliberately queries a NTP peer), however there is a lesser used broadcast mode where a server broadcasts the time into the LAN on regular intervals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately some networks have decided to enable this on their internet exchange ports, meaning that all members are receiving (but are unlikely using) these packets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It doesn’t help that almost every single time I have seen one of these situations, the time being broadcast itself is wrong by at least a few days implying that a device itself does not actually have a good source of time, and it’s just drifting from it’s original set up&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Medium&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Exposure of a remote configuration interface to untrusted networks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once again our friend MikroTik comes back with some interesting defaults, In this case the RoMON protocol that allows their GUI management interface (WinBox), and the ability to “telnet” into a neighboring device with just its MAC address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The logic behind the telnet feature is that it is useful for when you need to go to recover a device that you may have accidentally set a bad firewall or IP address/routing configuration on. However that does also mean that bgp.tools has traces of people using this telnet feature (which often broadcasts keystrokes and outputs) to all members. Implying that some networks are using the IX LAN (presumably by borrowing another member’s router) as a recovery mechanism for their misconfigurations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Medium&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Exposure of a legacy protocol to untrusted networks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Digital Equipment Corporation (Yes, the PDP-11 company) developed a series of network protocols called DECnet. While it is unlikely that you will ever encounter a device that needs DECNet support, Cisco by default enables this protocol on all interfaces (unless explicitly configured otherwise) on all enterprise software versions for IOS/IOS-XE.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Rare&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Allowing untrusted networks to configure your device&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simple Service Discovery Protocol and its’s most common implementation use case Universal Plug and Play is a protocol normally only ever found in the home/residential networking space. It allows for simple configuration for things like port forwarding. Since no one should be connecting such hardware to IX LANs, this is generally a sign of a serious misconfiguration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Rare&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Information Disclosure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multicast DNS and Link-Local Multicast Name Resolution are protocols used mostly by desktop computers to locate other things on the network (typically home or small biz networks) by name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MDNS is also very common in the automatic discovery of network printers, it also happens to be what I discovered the most on various exchanges&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While this is obviously ridiculous that a printer would be attached to an IX, what is likely actually happening here is that linux distributions like Debian will/would offer a “print server” role enabled by default. Since Linux “software routers” based on Debian are common in some regions, it doesn’t necessarily surprise me that these routers were installed with the print server role left enabled by mistake when they the operating system was installed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Rare&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: The exposure of Windows or SMB to untrusted networks&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NETBIOS is often used to power SMB/Samba, the Windows file and printer sharing protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I first encountered this packet I assumed that this was going to be a windows server configuration that had been let onto the exchanged by mistake, as encountering windows servers acting as edge routers is unheard of (although windows does actually have a bgp implementation, it is not designed for edge peering and so would make an extremely poor edge router)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upon further inspection of the packets it appears that what has actually happened here (at least 6 different times) is desktops/laptops have been let into the exchange instead. I can tell this because windows will automatically generate host names like &lt;code&gt;SERVER-ABCD1234&lt;/code&gt; for windows server installations, and &lt;code&gt;DESKTOP-ABCD1234&lt;/code&gt; for desktop/laptop ones, and NETBIOS packets often include the hostname of the system that is querying.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I can only assume this has happened due to incorrect physical cable patching or VLAN translation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Low&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: Untrusted networks could trigger failover of your routers&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: None&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol and Hot Standby Router Protocol are protocols that are designed to allow two routers to automatically take over from another if they fail. To do this the protocol sends packets on a regular interval into the LAN that has the gateway ip address that is being protected from downtime.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While redundancy is obviously desired on exchanges, this is typically done by actually attaching two discrete routers to the exchange with different LAN IP addresses, so VRRP and similar protocols are not appreciated configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Commonness: Medium&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Operational Danger: Embarrassment&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Security Danger: Information disclosure&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Cisco devices are unable to find a working DNS resolver, they resort to broadcasting the DNS query on all interfaces, Most of the time this just means that the Cisco licensing server (the “cslu-local”) is queried for, with an added bonus of the owners DNS search domain (if they have configured one)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So filtering for these packets is quite easy, and results in pretty much exactly what you would think.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ tcpdump -nr dns.pcap |&amp;amp; pcregrep -o1 '\] A{1,4}\? ([^\)]+)' | awk '{print $1}' | sort | uniq -c | sort -n | tail -n 15
    875 cslu-local.{CORP-F}
    998 cslu-local.{CORP-F}
   1162 tools.cisco.com.{Military-A}.
   1648 cslu-local.{CORP-G}
   1659 cslu-local.{CORP-F}
   1880 cslu-local.{CORP-E}
   2088 tools.cisco.com.{CORP-A}.
   2910 cslu-local.{CORP-D}
   4213 cslu-local.{Military-A}.
   5125 cslu-local.{CORP-C}.com.
   5515 cslu-local.{CORP-B}.fr.
   7367 cslu-local.{CORP-A}.com.
   7675 tools.cisco.com.
   9934 cslu-local.{Military-A}
  10838 cslu-local.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Except Cisco also has another interesting default back from the days when Cisco sold dedicated terminal servers where you would dial into the device (over the phone), and then type the device name you were looking to connect to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In practice everybody should be disabling this function in 2025, however by default it is enabled, so if you log into the Cisco CLI and make a typo (let’s say for this example you forgot the you’re on a cisco rather than a huawei), this happens:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The CLI just hangs, as it broadcasts your typo onto all interfaces…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway with a little bit of careful processing we can see all of these typos and sometimes the search domain from where they came from:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ tcpdump -nr dns.pcap |&amp;amp; pcregrep -o1 '\] A{1,4}\? ([^\)]+)' | awk '{print $1}' | sort | uniq -c | sort -n | egrep -v  'cslu|tools.cisco.com'

      1 cls.basetelco.com.
      1 configre.jato3.com.
      1 conft.asn28176.com.br.
      1 conft.powernet.net.br.
      1 cont.wanfiber.net.br.
      1 cpnf.cd.net.za.
      1 end.3cta.eb.mil.br.
      1 end.as37497.net.
      1 end.cd.net.za.
      1 end.spnet.com.br.
      1 exiexit.cd.net.za.
      1 exit-address-family.
      1 exitr.jfsc.local.
      1 expression.jato3.com.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve collected favorite most common typos below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;$ tcpdump -nr dns.pcap |&amp;amp; pcregrep -o1 '\] A{1,4}\? ([^\)]+)' | awk '{print $1}' |&amp;amp; pcregrep -o1 '^([^.]+)' | sort | uniq -c | sort -n 
...

      1 access-list
      1 configre
      1 cont
      1 cpnf
      1 exiexit
      1 exit-address-family
      1 exitr
      1 exti
      1 extit
      1 ifconfig
      1 int
      1 interface
      1 qconft
      1 qqq
      1 reboot
      1 uptime
      2 coinf
      2 Please
      2 shorun
      2 top
      4 ip
      4 ping
      6 save
      9 conft
     87 y
     92 quit
    134 q
    289 summary
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is of course an added danger while having this enabled that you could actually answer these queries and then trick an operator into typing into a terminal that you control. But I suspect that almost all operators would notice something like that happening, making such a trick difficult to pull off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While pretty much all exchanges have rules that define the kind of traffic that you are allowed to be sent into the internet exchange fabric that would forbid almost all of these types of packets from being sent ( For example, here is AMS-IX’s list of rules ), enforcement of these rules is nonexistent in most exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which is a shame really because a lot of this can be automatically done with simple access control lists (ACLs) that target just mac addresses alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DEC-MOP, RoMON, STP, CDP, IS-IS, ES-IS, LLDP, VRRP, OSPF, IPv6 RA are remarkably common, and yet they use specific MAC address destinations that could just be filtered out on all ports, preventing them from being seen by other IX participants.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While [LLMNR, NetBIOS, PIM, LDP, MDNS, DHCPv4 /DHCPv6, SSDP, DNS-Broadcast, Broadcast NTP, MikroTik Discovery] do require the IX device to be able to inspect Layer 3 headers like UDP port numbers in ACLs, this feature is very common among deployed hardware in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if exchanges are not able to automatically enforce policy using ACLs, there are open source projects like IXP-Watch and systems like bgp.tools that will monitor this for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There shouldn’t really be an excuse for things to be this way!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to stay up to date with the blog you can use the RSS feed or you can follow me on Fediverse @benjojo@benjojo.co.uk&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Related Posts:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Appreciation of automated IX Quarantine LAN testing (2024)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Better IX network quality monitoring (2024)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Random Post:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45370882</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 09:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bundler Belongs to the Ruby Community</title><link>https://andre.arko.net/2025/09/25/bundler-belongs-to-the-ruby-community/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e91a20914debb5e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;25 Sep 2025&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Bundler belongs to the Ruby community&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve spent 15 years of my life working on Bundler. When I introduce myself, people say “oh, the Bundler guy?”, and I am forced to agree.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I didn’t come up with the original idea for Bundler (that was Yehuda). I also didn’t work on the first six months worth of prototypes. That was all Carl and Yehuda together, back when “Carlhuda” was a super-prolific author of Ruby libraries, including most of the work to modularize Rails for version 3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I joined the team at a pivotal moment, in February 2010, as the 0.9 prototype was starting to be re-written yet another time into the shape that would finally be released as 1.0. By the time Carl, Yehuda, and I released version 1.0 together in August 2010, we had fully established the structure and commands that Bundler 2.7.2 still uses today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I gave my first conference talk about Bundler at Red Dirt Ruby in May 2010. Because they would be too busy with Rails 3 talks, Yehuda and Carl asked me to give the first RailsConf talk about Bundler, in June 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Carl and Yehuda drifted off to other projects, in 2011 and 2012 respectively, I took on a larger role, co-maintaining the project with Terence Lee, then on the Ruby platform team at Heroku. We shipped (and, embarrassingly, broke) many versions of Bundler on our way to the 1.1 release and its major speed improvements. We also gave several conference talks together, sharing what we had learned about Bundler, about gems, and about maintaining open source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2013, I managed to convince the owner of &lt;code&gt;bundler.io&lt;/code&gt; to sell me his domain, and rebuilt the website to host a separate copy of the documentation for every version of Bundler, ensuring even users on old versions could still access accurate documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the end of 2013, Terence had drifted away from the project as well, and I realized that everyone using Ruby was now one bus (or one lottery ticket) away from Bundler having no significant maintainers. During 2014, I made sure to settle any remaining ownership issues, including purchasing the rights to the Bundler logo, and began investigating various funding ideas. I tried specialized consulting, corporate sponsorships, and asking Ruby Central about sponsoring Bundler and RubyGems development work. Ruby Central declined, citing their desire to stay focused on conferences, but suggested that if I wanted to pursue something myself they would be happy to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2015, I founded Ruby Together specifically to raise funds to pay the existing maintainers team of Bundler, RubyGems, and RubyGems.org. Over time, we were able to raise enough money to quietly but scrappily keep the entire RubyGems ecosystem maintained and functional. Ruby Together did not ever, at any point, demand any form of governance or control over the existing open source projects. Maintainers did their thing in the RubyGems and Bundler GitHub orgs, while Ruby Together staff and board members did their thing in the rubytogether GitHub org.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By 2021, when Ruby Central and Ruby Together were both interested in merging together, funds were harder to find. Ruby Together had a membership program. Ruby Central wanted a to have a membership program. The confusing split between “Ruby Central owns the AWS account, but Ruby Together pays all the devs” continued to be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We prepared a merger agreement (which you can read in full at the link), stating that Ruby Central’s new goal after the merger would be “paying maintainers to do the programming”. The agreement also states that Ruby Central will follow Ruby Together’s Vision, Mission, and Values, a document that is hosted in the rubycentral GitHub organization today. That document includes a very specific list of goals, including:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Project users and maintainers are empowered to decide what’s best for their projects&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ruby open source developers are paid for their work&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Give control to the community&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Be accountable and transparent to the community&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Establish a collaborative, positive space for projects&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Have a clear and transparent funding process&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can read much more in both the merger agreement and in the Mission, Vision, and Values document, but the fundamental goal for both the non-profit and the open source projects is clear: this is all for the Ruby community. Without the community, there is no point to this work, and there is no way it could ever have been done in the first place. Without the 354 individuals who contributed to Bundler and to RubyGems, I could never have become “the Bundler guy” in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the last few weeks, Ruby Central has suddenly asserted that they alone own Bundler. That simply isn’t true. In order to defend the reputation of the team of maintainers who have given so much time and energy to the project, I have registered my existing trademark on the Bundler project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trademarks do not affect copyright, which stays with the original contributors unchanged. Trademarks do not affect license terms, which stay MIT and unchanged. Trademarks only impact one thing: who is allowed say that what they make is named “Bundler”. Ruby Central is welcome to the code, just like everyone else. They are not welcome to the project name that the Bundler maintainers have painstakingly created over the last 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the trademark has been registered under my name as an individual, I will not keep it for myself, because the idea of Bundler belongs to the Ruby community. Once there is a Ruby organization that is accountable to the maintainers, and accountable to the community, with openly and democratically elected board members, I commit to transfer my trademark to that organization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will not license the trademark, and will instead transfer ownership entirely. Bundler should belong to the community, and I want to make sure that is true for as long as Bundler exists.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45371061</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 10:05:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Theatre of Pull Requests and Code Review</title><link>https://meks.quest/blogs/the-theatre-of-pull-requests-and-code-review</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3754740beb3d5f9b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can't find the internet&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attempting to reconnect&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something went wrong!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hang in there while we get back on track&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Theatre of Pull Requests and Code Review&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Meks McClure · September 23, 2025&lt;/head&gt;Photo Credit to Petter Boström&lt;p&gt;I recently attended the Goatmire Elixir Conf and one of the standout talks for me was Saša Jurić's "Tell Me a Story". It was an incredible presentation that combined theatrical storytelling with practical technical advice. Saša performed parts of his talk in character, turning technical topics into a compelling narrative that was part comedy, part tragedy, and fully packed with useful insights I've started implementing myself. The recording will eventually be released online for viewing. I highly recommend that people watch it, and I'll endeavor to add a link to it here when it becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;Photo Credit to Petter Boström&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Code Review Challenge&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talk focused on Code Review and Pull Requests (PRs). Saša laid out common problems most software engineers face. Too often, engineers dread code reviews even though they're a significant part of team collaboration. We avoid them because PRs tend to be too large, too complex, too difficult to comprehend, and too painful to test. So we end up commenting "Looks Good To Me" and suggesting a few minor styling improvements to give the appearance of a thorough review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is how security leaks happen and codebases become progressively unmaintainable. Since git blame only points to the original author, it's easy to think "if something goes wrong, it's not on me". But we're all responsible for the whole system, regardless of who wrote the individual lines of code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Makes a PR Reviewable?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;So how do we review something that feels unreviewable? Saša advocates for normalizing the practice of returning difficult-to-understand PRs to the author. This makes logical sense, but it's challenging to implement because it can feel like admitting we're not smart enough to understand the code. However, saying "I don't understand this enough to approve it" is far more valuable than pretending with an empty "LGTM".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we commit to only reviewing truly reviewable PRs, what does that look like? According to Saša, it should take the average reviewer 5-10 minutes. By 'average reviewer,' he means mid-to-senior developers who understand the domain, business, and tech stack well—not newcomers still learning the system or mythical 10x engineers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How do you create a PR that can be reviewed in 5-10 minutes? By reducing the scope. A full feature should often be multiple PRs. A good rule of thumb is 300 lines of code changes - once you get above 500 lines, you're entering unreviewable territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Telling a Story with Commits&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A key part of having a reviewable PR is writing commits that tell a story. Present your changes incrementally and logically so reviewers can follow your thought process. Generic commit messages such as "add dependency," "implement file upload feature," and "address PR feedback" don’t tell much of a story and leave reviewers guessing. Why was the dependency added? What were the specific steps in creating the file uploader feature? What feedback is being addressed?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Story-Telling Commit Messages&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a toast to the demo gods, Saša demonstrated writing story-telling commits with a live coding example, creating a PR that was part of a larger feature. His example PR adds just 152 lines of code, removes 2 lines, but uses 13 thoughtful commits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While some developers might understand those 152 lines from the final diff alone, I couldn't confidently approve it without the commit story.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Breaking Down the Example&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; For instance, looking at the overall diff, I didn't understand why he added &lt;code&gt;:runtime_tools&lt;/code&gt;
      to &lt;code&gt;applications&lt;/code&gt;
      in &lt;code&gt;mix.exs&lt;/code&gt;. Following the commit narrative, it's clear this was needed for access to
      &lt;code&gt;:scheduler.get_sample()&lt;/code&gt;
      to collect the samples. Now I can research that context or ask more pointed questions.
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Iterative Process&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A huge benefit of seeing this live was witnessing the iterative process. In the compute average utilization commit, we initially saw an incorrect implementation that computed averages of all schedulers, including offline ones. When testing revealed unexpected results, Saša went back and updated both the code and the commit that originally implemented that function so the story remained coherent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A flow that I find to work well for keeping commit history clean is with fixup commits. A fixup is a small commit that’s explicitly marked to be folded into an earlier commit during an interactive rebase. When you run rebase with autosquash, Git automatically pairs each fixup with its target and tucks the changes into the right place, keeping the story coherent without manual reordering.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I sometimes experience creating merge conflicts for myself during this process. Both Saša and I agree that if it becomes too much effort to resolve the conflict, then creating a new commit is ok. Taking the time to put in extra effort to keep the commit history clean and the story coherent makes the PR easier for reviewers to understand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Value of Clean History&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keeping the commit history clean connects to advice I've heard about ensuring every commit compiles and keeps the application runnable. I used to follow this loosely, but recent experiences with git bisect emphasized to me its importance. (If you are unfamiliar with git bisect , it's worth checking out; it uses a binary search algorithm to find which commit in your project's history introduced a bug.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are a few factors that make narrowing down when and how a regression was introduced more challenging. If a commit doesn't compile, I can't isolate whether the bug first appeared there. If the bug appeared in a commit that had hundreds of lines of code changed, determining which part of the commit is the issue requires significantly more reasoning. A clean commit history with messages that tell a story makes these kinds of investigations easier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Making Review a Collaborative Success&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we present focused PRs with commits that tell clear stories, we get feedback sooner and our development cycles speed up. When reviewers understand our changes, we're more likely to receive valuable feedback instead of blanket approvals, and we're more likely to ship quality code. When our commits make sense, we can travel back in time as needed to understand how our codebase evolved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Saša's theatrical lesson, I will be more intentional about crafting commit stories. The next time you're preparing a PR, consider: Are you telling a story your reviewers can follow? Start small - maybe focus on just one aspect, like keeping PRs under that 300-line guideline or writing more descriptive commit messages. Your future reviewers (and your future debugging self) will thank you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Resources&lt;/head&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Git blame for showing which revision and author last modified each line of a file&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Git rebase for cleaning up commit history&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Git fixup for amending earlier commits&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Git bisect for finding when bugs were introduced&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45371283</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 10:35:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Wind, a Pole, and the Dragon</title><link>https://entropicthoughts.com/the-wind-a-pole-and-the-dragon</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6a4e089e8ea011d4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;The Wind, a Pole, and the Dragon&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of my favourite requests for help online comes from the shibboleth-users group, where someone Japanese used machine translation to ask about the following problem:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&lt;p&gt;At often, the goat-time install a error is vomit. To how many times like the wind, a pole, and the dragon? Install 2,3 repeat, spank, vomit blows&lt;/p&gt;14:14:01.869 - INFO [edu.internet2.middleware.shibboleth.common.config.profile.JSPErrorHandlerBeanDefinitionParser:45] Parsing configuration for JSP error handler.&lt;p&gt;Not precise the vomit but with aspect similar, is vomited concealed in fold of goat-time lumber? goat-time see like the wind, pole, and dragon? This insult to father’s stones? JSP error handler with wind, pole, dragon with intercourse to goat-time? Or chance lack of skill with a goat-time?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please apologize for your stupidity. There are a many thank you&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have long wanted to figure out exactly how this went so wrong. Some parts are fairly clear:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;vomit could come from throw (as in throwing an error) or even just output.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;lumber must clearly reference logs.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have also heard speculation that goat-time means runtime, as in the Java runtime, perhaps. This means we can already figure out how we got to “vomited concealed in fold of goat-time lumber” – it’s an error hidden in the runtime logs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I asked a few llms to assist me with the rest, and they universally think spank is an odd translation of hit, which is apparently used in Japanese to mean something like execute, and skill could be a mistranslation of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can start to put together what the message actually means.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Often when trying to install the runtime an error is thrown. uninterpretable I have tried reinstalling it three times, but when I run it an exception is thrown.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is not the exact exception but something like that. Is the real error hidden in the runtime logs? uninterpretable. uninterpretable arising due to interaction with the runtime? Or perhaps my lack of experience with the runtime?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The llms diverge on the meaning of “insult to father’s stones”. Some suggest the obvious thing, that it’d correspond to an idiomatic expression of frustration. Others seem to think it might be about “problems with the ancestral building blocks”, i.e. software dependencies. I liked that reading, but I have no idea.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New here? I apply the same weird curiosity to everything I discover. To learn something new, subscribe for weekly article summaries! If you don't like it, you can unsubscribe any time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then there’s “the wind, a pole, and the dragon.” I have yet to see anything come close to a reasonable answer. llms produce guesses referring to three parts of the configuration, variable names, dependencies, colloquialisms, descriptions of user interface, or abstract descriptions of how quickly things happen (the wind), a fixed point (a pole), and complexity/power (dragon). But again, I have no idea.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have more information, please reach out.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45371309</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 10:39:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Resurrect the Old Web</title><link>https://stevedylandev.bearblog.dev/resurrect-the-old-web/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a79450e0583082e1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Resurrect the Old Web&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently a local news station in Maine reported a story of some middle schoolers calling their friends with landline telephones. Their parents thought they were too young for cell phones and wanted to hold off on that aspect of reality, so they got an old phone from the 90s, and soon their friends also got phones. It formed schedules of calls they would make to talk to each other, even creating a phone ring of contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think I can confidently say that the majority of us aren't happy with the state of social media. Back in its early days it was fresh and exciting, a fun way to connect with your friends that might be far away, or make new friends online. It was cozy. No ads, no feeds, no endless videos. Instead it was just people, the whole reason you started in the first place. Now it's just noise and scary addicting and effective algorithms that keep you plugged in for hours on end. We build apps and products to help kill the monster, or perhaps we even delete some social media apps. Many of our friends we used to stay connected with seem so distant, as many of them too are tired and perhaps jumped off socials altogether. Well, what if I told you we could have the old web back?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In my opinion the answer is honestly pretty simple: blogs and RSS feeds. This was how it was done for years before social media came into the scene. You would find someone's blog, subscribe to their RSS feed, and anytime a new post came out it would pop up in your feed and you could read it. One important clarification is that when we say "blog" it can be pretty much whatever you want it to be. On my personal website I generally write more of my serious blogs, but on my bear blog I plan to be a bit more casual. It will be a place where I record short thoughts, ideas, musings, or cool things I find on the internet. Just sharing what I would normally share with my friends. That's what made the web great, and that's what I want to bring back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To do this, I am starting a bear blog that will have a dedicated feeds page that will have all the other blogs I'm subscribing to. The beauty is that you don't need a dedicated social network to make this work; just click on the links. Use whatever RSS reader you want! You don't have to use bear blog either, just use whatever blog you want. The key is connection. I want to point to who I follow so that you might follow them too, and hopefully create a page on your own. In some ways it's bringing back old web rings and simple networking through hyperlinks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To kick it off, here's a few blogs I'm already subscribed to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to join but not sure how, check out the video I recorded below:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Best way to keep up with your feeds is to find yourself an RSS reader! There are a lot of options out there (although admittedly a bit old), so just find it on the platform that suits you best. Feeder.co has a pretty generous free plan, and if you're a dev there's hundreds of self hosted projects to choose from like Yarr. Personally rocking NetNewsWire for MacOS and iOS, and loving it so far!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have no idea if this will amount to anything or if it's worthwhile, but I'm gonna give it a shot. The landline phones prove that we don't have to buy into the social media dopamine machine. We have autonomy, and we have the freedom to choose how we interact with each other. I want to believe we can resurrect the old web, together.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45372113</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 12:48:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Data Viz Color Palette Generator (For Charts and Dashboards)</title><link>https://www.learnui.design/tools/data-color-picker.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="32a83ff73ed5803d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Palette Generator&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Number of Colors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Background Color&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;In Context&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to Use&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use the palette chooser to create a series of colors that are visually equidistant. This is useful for many data visualizations, like pie charts, grouped bar charts, and maps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: there are two other modes besides palette mode – check out single-hue scales and divergent scales as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creating visually equidistant palettes is basically impossible to do by hand, yet hugely important for data visualizations. Why? When colors are not visually equidistant, it’s harder to (a) tell them apart in the chart, and (b) compare the chart to the key. I’m sure we’ve all looked at charts where you can hardly use the key since the data colors are so similar.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For instance, Google Analytics does a terrible job with this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s better to use use a range of hues so users can cross-reference with the key easier. It’s far simpler for our brains to distinguish, say, yellow from orange than blue from blue-but-15%-lighter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This color picker allows you to specify both endpoints of the palette. You can choose at least one to be a brand color, which gives you significant flexibility in creating a palette that will work for your visualizations, yet be customized for your brand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are a few tips for getting the best palette:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Try picking very different endpoint colors – e.g. one warm, one cool; one bright, one darker – so that your palette covers a wider range&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If you’re using a brand color for one endpoint, don’t be afraid to modify the saturation and brightness a bit if it creates a more pleasing palette. Users will recognize your brand color by its hue much far more than by it’s exact saturation/brightness.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;For data visualizations where you’re showing the strength of a single value, try using the Single Hue Palette Generator instead.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Oh, and...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;More on Color&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're new to color in UI design, I highly recommend the following resources:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The HSB Color System: A Practitioner's Primer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Color in UI Design: A Practical Framework&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gradient Generator tool, by yours truly, built to be the most fully-featured on the web 😎&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Design Hacks, my email newsletter where I send original design tips and tactics to 60,000+ of my closest friends.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyhow, I've created this to be the tool I wish I had for creating data visualization palettes. Is there another feature you'd like to see in it? Let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Single Hue Scale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Number of Colors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Modify Color Scale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brightness&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Color Intensity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Background Color&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;In Context&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to Use&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Single Hue Scale generator is most useful for visualizations where you’re showing the value of a single variable. Typically, the darker variation will represent a higher value, and a neutral color (even white) will represent a value closer to zero.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a pie chart or bar chart, size is used to distinguish higher values. But in some visualizations, the size is set and you need to rely on color. Two examples of this are show in the “In Context” section above:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A map in which size represents county size; we need to use color to distinguish the value for each county&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A week-by-week calendar in which each day is an equally sized box; we need to use color to show the value for a particular day&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here are a few tips for getting the best single hue scale:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;To transition to a flat gray endpoint, set “Color Intensity” to zero&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;To transition to a white endpoint, set “Brightness” to full and “Color Intensity” to zero&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If your color scale actually shows a variable that transitions from one end to a neutral midpoint to another end, try the Divergent Scale Generator (e.g. Republican to moderate to Democrat; hotter to same-temperature to cooler)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Divergent Color Scale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Number of Colors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Modify Midpoint Color&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brightness&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Color Intensity&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Background Color&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;In Context&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to Use&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Divergent Color Scale generator is most useful for visualizations where you’re showing a transition from (a) one extreme, through a (b) neutral middle, and finally to a (c) opposite extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most common example of this is the “how Democrat/Republican is each state in the US” chart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, the neutral midpoint is a light gray. You can change it with the "Modify Midpoint Color" sliders to be slightly darker or more colorful. For the best results, set the Color Intensity to the minimum when the two endpoint hues are significantly different – otherwise, the moderate tones will start to blend together (this will be evident in the map).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As with the other visualization styles, this will pick colors that are visually equidistant. However, if one of the two endpoint colors is significantly darker or saturated, the swatches on that side will have more color-space between them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45372286</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 13:13:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI Isn't Replacing Radiologists</title><link>https://www.worksinprogress.news/p/why-ai-isnt-replacing-radiologists</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2fd999d02d35859e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;AI isn't replacing radiologists&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Radiology combines digital images, clear benchmarks, and repeatable tasks. But demand for human radiologists is at an all-time high.&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Works in Progress is becoming a print magazine. Our first print issue, Issue 21, will land in November. If you live in the United States or the United Kingdom, you can subscribe here. If you live outside the US or UK and want to be notified as soon as subscriptions are live in your country, leave your details here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CheXNet can detect pneumonia with greater accuracy than a panel of board-certified radiologists. It is an AI model released in 2017, trained on more than 100,000 chest X-rays. It is fast, free, and can run on a single consumer-grade GPU. A hospital can use it to classify a new scan in under a second.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since then, companies like Annalise.ai, Lunit, Aidoc, and Qure.ai have released models that can detect hundreds of diseases across multiple types of scans with greater accuracy and speed than human radiologists in benchmark tests. Some products can reorder radiologist worklists to prioritize critical cases, suggest next steps for care teams, or generate structured draft reports that fit into hospital record systems. A few, like IDx-DR, are even cleared to operate without a physician reading the image at all. In total, there are over 700 FDA-cleared radiology models, which account for roughly three-quarters of all medical AI devices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radiology is a field optimized for human replacement, where digital inputs, pattern recognition tasks, and clear benchmarks predominate. In 2016, Geoffrey Hinton – computer scientist and Turing Award winner – declared that ‘people should stop training radiologists now’. If the most extreme predictions about the effect of AI on employment and wages were true, then radiology should be the canary in the coal mine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But demand for human labor is higher than ever. In 2025, American diagnostic radiology residency programs offered a record 1,208 positions across all radiology specialties, a four percent increase from 2024, and the field’s vacancy rates are at all-time highs. In 2025, radiology was the second-highest-paid medical specialty in the country, with an average income of $520,000, over 48 percent higher than the average salary in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three things explain this. First, while models beat humans on benchmarks, the standardized tests designed to measure AI performance, they struggle to replicate this performance in hospital conditions. Most tools can only diagnose abnormalities that are common in training data, and models often don’t work as well outside of their test conditions. Second, attempts to give models more tasks have run into legal hurdles: regulators and medical insurers so far are reluctant to approve or cover fully autonomous radiology models. Third, even when they do diagnose accurately, models replace only a small share of a radiologist’s job. Human radiologists spend a minority of their time on diagnostics and the majority on other activities, like talking to patients and fellow clinicians.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence is rapidly spreading across the economy and society. But radiology shows us that it will not necessarily dominate every field in its first years of diffusion — at least until these common hurdles are overcome. Exploiting all of its benefits will involve adapting it to society, and society’s rules to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Islands of automation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All AIs are functions or algorithms, called models, that take in inputs and spit out outputs. Radiology models are trained to detect a finding, which is a measurable piece of evidence that helps identify or rule out a disease or condition. Most radiology models detect a single finding or condition in one type of image. For example, a model might look at a chest CT and answer whether there are lung nodules, rib fractures, or what the coronary arterial calcium score is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For every individual question, a new model is required. In order to cover even a modest slice of what they see in a day, a radiologist would need to switch between dozens of models and ask the right questions of each one. Several platforms manage, run, and interpret outputs from dozens or even hundreds of separate AI models across vendors, but each model operates independently, analyzing for one finding or disease at a time. The final output is a list of separate answers to specific questions, rather than a single description of an image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even with hundreds of imaging algorithms approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) on the market, the combined footprint of today’s radiology AI models still cover only a small fraction of real-world imaging tasks. Many cluster around a few use cases: stroke, breast cancer, and lung cancer together account for about 60 percent of models, but only a minority of the actual radiology imaging volume that is carried out in the US. Other subspecialties, such as vascular, head and neck, spine, and thyroid imaging currently have relatively few AI products. This is in part due to data availability: the scan needs to be common enough for there to be many annotated examples that can be used to train models. Some scans are also inherently more complicated than others. For example, ultrasounds are taken from multiple angles and do not have standard imaging planes, unlike X-rays.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once deployed outside of the hospital where they were initially trained, models can struggle. In a standard clinical trial, samples are taken from multiple hospitals to ensure exposure to a broad range of patients and to avoid site-specific effects, such as a single doctor’s technique or how a hospital chooses to calibrate its diagnostic equipment.1 But when an algorithm is undergoing regulatory approval in the US, its developers will normally test it on a relatively narrow dataset. Out of the models in 2024 that reported the number of sites where they were tested, 38 percent were tested on data from a single hospital. Public benchmarks tend to rely on multiple datasets from the same hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The performance of a tool can drop as much as 20 percentage points when it is tested out of sample, on data from other hospitals. In one study, a pneumonia detection model trained on chest X-rays from a single hospital performed substantially worse when tested at a different hospital. Some of these challenges stemmed from avoidable experimental issues like overfitting, but others are indicative of deeper problems like differences in how hospitals record and generate data, such as using slightly different imaging equipment. This means that individual hospitals or departments would need to retrain or revalidate today’s crop of tools before adopting them, even if they have been proven elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The limitations of radiology models stem from deeper problems with building medical AI. Training datasets come with strict inclusion criteria, where the diagnosis must be unambiguous (typically confirmed by a consensus of two to three experts or a pathology result) and without images that are shot at an odd angle, look too dark, or are blurry. This skews performance towards the easiest cases, which doctors are already best at diagnosing, and away from real-world images. In one 2022 study, an algorithm that was meant to spot pneumonia on chest X-rays faltered when the disease presented in subtle or mild forms, or when other lung conditions resembled pneumonia, such as pleural effusions, where fluid builds up in lungs, or in atelectasis (collapsed lung). Humans also benefit from context: one radiologist told me about a model they use that labels surgical staples as hemorrhages, because of the bright streaks they create in the image.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Medical imaging datasets used for training also tend to have fewer cases from children, women, and ethnic minorities, making their performance generally worse for these demographics. Many lack information about the gender or race of cases at all, making it difficult to adjust for these issues and address the problem of bias. The result is that radiology models often predict only a narrow slice of the world,2 though there are scenarios where AI models do perform well, including identifying common diseases like pneumonia or certain tumors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problems don’t stop there. Even a model for the precise question you need and in the hospital where it was trained is unlikely to perform as well in clinical practice as it did in the benchmark. In benchmark studies, researchers isolate a cohort of scans, define goals in quantitative metrics, such as the sensitivity (the percentage of people with the condition who are correctly identified by the test) and specificity (the percentage of people without the condition who are correctly identified as such), and compare the performance of a model to the score of another reviewer, typically a human doctor. Clinical studies, on the other hand, show how well the model performs in a real healthcare setting without controls. Since the earliest days of computer-aided diagnosis, there has been a gulf between benchmark and clinical performance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, computer-aided diagnosis, effectively rudimentary AI systems, were developed to screen mammograms, or X-rays of breasts that are performed to look for breast cancer. In trials, the combination of humans and computer-aided diagnosis systems outperformed humans alone in accuracy when evaluating mammograms. More controlled experiments followed, which pointed to computer-aided diagnosis helping radiologists pick up more cancer with minimal costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FDA approved mammography computer-aided diagnosis in 1998, and Medicare started to reimburse the use of computer-aided diagnosis in 2001. The US government paid radiologists $7 more to report a screening mammogram if they used the technology; by 2010, approximately 74 percent of mammograms in the country were read by computer-aided diagnosis alongside a clinician.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But computer-aided diagnosis turned out to be a disappointment. Between 1998 and 2002 researchers analyzed 430,000 screening mammograms from 200,000 women at 43 community clinics in Colorado, New Hampshire, and Washington. Among the seven clinics that turned to computer-aided detection software, the machines flagged more images, leading to clinicians conducting 20 percent more biopsies, but uncovering no more cancer than before. Several other large clinical studies had similar findings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another way to measure performance is to compare having computerized help to a second clinician reading every film, called ‘double reading’. Across ten trials and seventeen studies of double reading, researchers found that computer aids did not raise the cancer detection rate but led to patients being called back an additional ten percent more often. In contrast, having two readers caught more cancers while slightly lowering callbacks. Computer-aided detection was worse than standard care, and much worse than another pair of eyes. In 2018, Medicare stopped reimbursing doctors more for mammograms read with computer-aided diagnosis than those read by a radiologist alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One explanation for this gap is that people behave differently if they are treating patients day to day than when they are part of laboratory studies or other controlled experiments.3 In particular, doctors appear to defer excessively to assistive AI tools in clinical settings in a way that they do not in lab settings. They did this even with much more primitive tools than we have today: one clinical trial all the way back in 2004 asked 20 breast screening specialists to read mammogram cases with the computer prompts switched on, then brought in a new group to read the identical films without the software. When guided by computer aids, doctors identified barely half of the malignancies, while those reviewing without the model caught 68 percent. The gap was largest when computer aids failed to recognize the malignancy itself; many doctors seemed to treat an absence of prompts as reassurance that a film was clean. Another review, this time from 2011, found that when a system gave incorrect guidance, clinicians were 26 percent more likely to make a wrong decision than unaided peers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Humans in the loop&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It would seem as if better models and more automation could together fix the problems of current-day AI for radiology. Without a doctor involved whose behavior might change we might expect real-world results to match benchmark scores. But regulatory requirements and insurance policies are slowing the adoption of fully autonomous radiology AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The FDA splits imaging software into two regulatory lanes: assistive or triage tools, which require a licensed physician to read the scan and sign the chart, and autonomous tools, which do not. Makers of assistive tools simply have to show that their software can match the performance of tools that are already on the market. Autonomous tools have to clear a much higher bar: they must demonstrate that the AI tool will refuse to read any scan that is blurry, uses an unusual scanner, or is outside its competence. The bar is higher because, once the human disappears, a latent software defect could harm thousands before anyone notices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Meeting that criteria is difficult. Even state-of-the-art vision networks falter with images that lack contrast, have unexpected angles, or lots of different artefacts. IDx-DR, a diabetic retinopathy screener and one of the few cleared to operate autonomously, comes with guardrails: the patient must be an adult with no prior retinopathy diagnosis; there must be two macula-centred photographs of the fundus (the rear of the eye) with a resolution of at least 1,000 times 1,000 pixels; if glare, small pupils or poor focus degrade quality, the software must self-abort and refer the patient to an eye care professional.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stronger evidence and improved performance could eventually clear both hurdles, but other requirements would still delay widespread use. For example, if you retrain a model, you are required to receive new approval even if the previous model was approved. This contributes to the market generally lagging behind frontier capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And when autonomous models are approved, malpractice insurers are not eager to cover them. Diagnostic error is the costliest mistake in American medicine, resulting in roughly a third of all malpractice payouts, and radiologists are perennial defendants. Insurers believe that software makes catastrophic payments more likely than a human clinician, as a broken algorithm can harm many patients at once. Standard contract language now often includes phrases such as: ‘Coverage applies solely to interpretations reviewed and authenticated by a licensed physician; no indemnity is afforded for diagnoses generated autonomously by software’. One insurer, Berkley, even carries the blunter label ‘Absolute AI Exclusion’.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without malpractice coverage, hospitals cannot afford to let algorithms sign reports. In the case of IDx-DR, the vendor, Digital Diagnostics, includes a product liability policy and an indemnity clause. This means that if the clinic used the device exactly as the FDA label prescribes, with adult patients, good-quality images, and no prior retinopathy, then the company will reimburse the clinic for damages traceable to algorithmic misclassification.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Today, if American hospitals wanted to adopt AI for fully independent diagnostic reads, they would need to believe that autonomous models deliver enough cost savings or throughput gains to justify pushing for exceptions to credentialing and billing norms. For now, usage is too sparse to make a difference. One 2024 investigation estimated that 48 percent of radiologists are using AI at all in their practice. A 2025 survey reported that only 19 percent of respondents who have started piloting or deploying AI use cases in radiology reported a ‘high’ degree of success.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Better AI, more MRIs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if AI models become accurate enough to read scans on their own and are cleared to do so, radiologists may still find themselves busier, rather than out of a career.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radiologists are useful for more than reading scans; a study that followed staff radiologists in three different hospitals in 2012 found that only 36 percent of their time was dedicated to direct image interpretation. More time is spent on overseeing imaging examinations, communicating results and recommendations to the treating clinicians and occasionally directly to patients, teaching radiology residents and technologists who conduct the scans, and reviewing imaging orders and changing scanning protocols.4 This means that, if AI were to get better at interpreting scans, radiologists may simply shift their time toward other tasks. This would reduce the substitution effect of AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As tasks get faster or cheaper to perform, we may also do more of them. In some cases, especially if lower costs or faster turnaround times open the door to new uses, the increase in demand can outweigh the increase in efficiency, a phenomenon known as Jevons paradox. This has historical precedent in the field: in the early 2000s hospitals swapped film jackets for digital systems. Hospitals that digitized improved radiologist productivity, and time to read an individual scan went down. A study at Vancouver General found that the switch boosted radiologist productivity 27 percent for plain radiography and 98 percent for CT within a year of going filmless. This occurred alongside other advancements in imaging technology that made scans faster to execute. Yet, no radiologists were laid off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, the overall American utilization rate per 1,000 insured patients for all imaging increased by 60 percent from 2000 to 2008. This is not explained by a commensurate increase in physician visits. Instead, each visit was associated with more imaging on average. Before digitization, the nonmonetary price of imaging was high: the median reporting turnaround time for x-rays was 76 hours for patients discharged from emergency departments, and 84 hours for admitted patients. After departments digitized, these times dropped to 38 hours and 35 hours, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Faster scans give doctors more options. Until the early 2000s, only exceptional trauma cases would receive whole-body CT scans; the increased speed of CT turnaround times mean that they are now a common choice. This is a reflection of elastic demand, a concept in economics that describes when demand for a product or service is very sensitive to changes in price. In this case, when these scans got cheaper in terms of waiting time, demand for those scans increased.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The first decade of diffusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, improvements in image interpretation have run far ahead of their diffusion. Hundreds of models can spot bleeds, nodules, and clots, yet AI is often limited to assistive use on a small subset of scans in any given practice. And despite predictions to the contrary, head counts and salaries have continued to rise. The promise of AI in radiology is overstated by benchmarks alone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multi‑task foundation models may widen coverage, and different training sets could blunt data gaps. But many hurdles cannot be removed with better models alone: the need to counsel the patient, shoulder malpractice risk, and receive accreditation from regulators. Each hurdle makes full substitution the expensive, risky option and human plus machine the default. Sharp increases in AI capabilities could certainly alter this dynamic, but it is a useful model for the first years of AI models that benchmark well at tasks associated with a particular career.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, there are industries where conditions are different. Large platforms rely heavily on AI systems to triage or remove harmful or policy-violating content. At Facebook and Instagram, 94 percent and 98 percent of moderation decisions respectively are made by machines. But many of the more sophisticated knowledge jobs look more like radiology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In many jobs, tasks are diverse, stakes are high, and demand is elastic. When this is the case, we should expect software to, at least initially, lead to more human work, not less. The lesson from a decade of radiology models is neither optimism about increased output nor dread about replacement. Models can lift productivity, but their implementation depends on behavior, institutions and incentives. For now, the paradox has held: the better the machines, the busier radiologists have become.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deena Mousa is a lead researcher at Open Philanthropy. Follow her on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few groups have started doing this, like the 2025 ‘OpenMIBOOD’ suite which explicitly scores chest-X-ray models on 14 out-of-distribution collections, but that hasn’t yet become standard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few companies and research groups are working to mitigate this, such as by training on multi-site datasets, building synthetic cases, or using self-supervised learning to reduce labeling needs, but these approaches are still early and expensive. This limitation is an important reason why AI models do not yet perform as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One study tracked 27 mammographers and compared how well each interpreted real screening films versus a standardised ‘test-set’ of the same images. The researchers found no meaningful link between a radiologist’s accuracy in the lab and accuracy on live patients; the statistical correlation in sensitivity-specificity scores was essentially zero.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45372335</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 13:19:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As many as 2M Cisco devices affected by actively exploited 0-day</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2025/09/as-many-as-2-million-cisco-devices-affected-by-actively-exploited-0-day/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f4031106c911d3ab"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As many as 2 million Cisco devices are susceptible to an actively exploited zeroday that can remotely crash or execute code on vulnerable systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cisco said Wednesday that the vulnerability, tracked as CVE-2025-20352, was present in all supported versions of Cisco IOS and Cisco IOS XE, the operating system that powers a wide variety of the company’s networking devices. The vulnerability can be exploited by low-privileged users to create a denial-of-service attack or by higher-privileged users to execute code that runs with unfettered root privileges. It carries a severity rating of 7.7 out of a possible 10.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Exposing SNMP to the Internet? Yep&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The Cisco Product Security Incident Response Team (PSIRT) became aware of successful exploitation of this vulnerability in the wild after local Administrator credentials were compromised,” Wednesday’s advisory stated. “Cisco strongly recommends that customers upgrade to a fixed software release to remediate this vulnerability.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vulnerability is the result of a stack overflow bug in the IOS component that handles SNMP (simple network management protocol), which routers and other devices use to collect and handle information about devices inside a network. The vulnerability is exploited by sending crafted SNMP packets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To execute malicious code, the remote attacker must have possession of read-only community string, an SNMP-specific form of authentication for accessing managed devices. Frequently, such strings ship with devices. Even when modified by an administrator, read-only community strings are often widely known inside an organization. The attacker would also require privileges on the vulnerable systems. With that, the attacker can obtain RCE (remote code execution) capabilities that run as root.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45372361</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 13:22:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Death rates rose in hospital ERs after private equity firms took over</title><link>https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/death-rates-rose-hospital-ers-private-equity-firms-took-study-finds-rcna233211</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2dc0956e36b12786"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After hospitals were acquired by private equity firms, patient death rates in the emergency departments rose by 13% compared with similar hospitals, according to research published this week in Annals of Internal Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The research, which compared outcomes at hospitals over a 10-year period, adds fresh evidence to previous studies showing harmful patient outcomes and higher costs among health care entities owned by profit-oriented financiers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The increased deaths in emergency departments at private equity-owned hospitals are most likely the result of reduced staffing levels after the acquisitions, which the study also measured, said Dr. Zirui Song, a co-author and associate professor of health care policy and medicine at Harvard Medical School.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After hospitals were acquired by private equity, the number of full-time employees fell by an average 11.6% compared with non-private equity facilities, the research found, and salary expenditures in the emergency departments and intensive care units declined by 18% and 16%, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Most hospital care in the country remains a face-to-face, human, labor-intensive endeavor, especially in emergency departments and ICUs,” Song said in an interview. “When human labor is cut to this extent in staffing sensitive areas of the hospital, patient harm can plausibly ensue, including mortality.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new study analyzed 1 million emergency department visits by Medicare patients at 49 private equity-owned hospitals from 2009 through 2019. The researchers compared the outcomes of those visits with more than 6 million visits at 293 matched hospitals — those of similar size and location — not acquired by private equity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The study’s co-authors, in addition to Song, are José R. Zubizarreta of Harvard University, Dr. Sneha Kannan of the University of Pittsburgh, Joseph Dov Bruch of the University of Chicago and Dr. Jennifer Stevens, director of the Center for Healthcare Delivery Science at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Song said the new research differed from previous studies on private equity’s impact, which focused on patients who were admitted to the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“There are far more patients who come into the emergency department than patients who are actually admitted into the wards of the hospital,” Song said, “so this study looks at a patient population that had not been examined in great depth before.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Private equity firms are sophisticated financial operators that buy companies, typically loading them with large amounts of debt to pay for the acquisitions. The firms hope to sell the companies for profit a few years later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The private equity industry has poured over $1 trillion into health care companies in recent years. Health care has been a focus of the financiers because it accounts for 18% of gross domestic product in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because their acquisitions add debt costs to the companies they buy, those operations must cut other expenses to offset the burden. Employees are often the first to be fired, and costs are often increased to generate higher profits. Some hospitals owned by private-equity firms sell the land under their buildings, enriching the owners but saddling the facilities with higher rent costs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dr. Robert McNamara, chairman of the department of emergency medicine at Temple University’s Lewis Katz School of Medicine, said the new research confirms what doctors in the field have long complained about: being stretched too thin by private equity owners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“When private equity comes in, they try to jack up the revenues and then, when that reaches an end point, they start slashing expenses,” McNamara said in an interview. “Instead of people just losing their jobs, you have bad patient outcomes here. Less staff equals worse outcomes.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new research on increased deaths in emergency departments at private equity-owned hospitals aligns with a 2021 study that found 11% higher mortality rates at nursing homes owned by private equity. That study, by academics at New York University, the University of Chicago and the University of Pennsylvania, concluded that lower nursing staffs and declines in compliance with care standards contributed to the increased deaths at financier-owned homes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some states are enacting laws to rein in private equity’s impact on health care. In June, Oregon enacted a law limiting the control corporations and private equity can have over health care operations. And in Indiana, a new law expands the attorney general’s powers to investigate health care transactions and mandates reporting on ownership stakes in health care entities by private equity investors and other owners.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45372442</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 13:32:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Military Was Caught Off Guard by Israeli Strike on Qatar</title><link>https://www.twz.com/air/new-info-on-how-u-s-military-was-caught-off-guard-by-israeli-strike-on-qatar</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bdc892582047f6ff"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The U.S. military was unaware of the unprecedented Israeli ballistic missile strike earlier this month on a Hamas compound in Doha, Qatar, until it was already inbound, one of its senior leaders has confirmed. The situation was further compounded by attention being focused on threats emanating from Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of the attack, there had been questions as to why the various highly advanced air defense systems and sensors, both American and Qatari, which would normally provide alert to an impending attack on Qatar, had not provided warning and defense. Now we have a better understanding of what happened from a U.S. perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can read our initial reporting on the Israeli raid on Doha on September 9 here, as well as our follow-up, which looked at the degree of damage inflicted, here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lt. Gen. Derek C. France, the commander of Air Forces Central (AFCENT) and the Combined Forces Air Component Commander for U.S. Central Command, was discussing the implications of the Israeli airstrike at the Air, Space &amp;amp; Cyber Conference in National Harbor, Maryland, today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This strike that Israel did against the Hamas target in Doha was something that we had no indications and warnings of, because our surveillance and all our attention was not put on [it],” Lt. Gen. France said. “It wasn’t something that we expected.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Qatar is a key U.S. partner in the Middle East. Al Udeid Air Base in the country is a major hub for U.S. military operations in the region, which was notably subjected to an Iranian missile barrage back in June.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I can say that we did not get a warning about this happening,” Lt. Gen. France stressed. “Our systems were the first indication that we had. And then there was discussion at some point with my counterparts in Israel, but our systems noting the attack was underway was the first indication we got.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The AFCENT boss further confirmed that “while we have exquisite systems and things that can detect a lot of different things, those things are typically focused on Iran and other things where we expect an attack to come from.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a reality we had pointed out in the aftermath of the attack, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The lack of warning of the Israeli airstrike is, Lt. Gen. France said, the major operational lesson learned. He noted “the importance of indications and warnings and having the right systems, whether that’s space-based, air-based, non-traditional, to understand those attacks as they’re happening.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lt. Gen. France’s comment about “our systems were the first indication” that some kind of attack on Qatar was in progress makes sense. The U.S. military has the ability to detect the launch of ballistic missiles globally, but tracking them during their post-boost midcourse voyage at very high altitude is a more limited capability. The Pentagon hopes to change this in the future by quickly developing and deploying a space-based tracking layer that can follow ballistic missiles during their midcourse journey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Although they knew it was happening because of those detection systems, it was from a source and a direction that we weren’t expecting,” he continued.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Speaking today, Lt. Gen. France added, “The sensing capability is there. It’s not so much a direction kind of thing. It’s what we were overall expecting to happen and having those indications of warnings that are out there.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Israeli officials said the Doha strike was carried out by 15 Israeli fighter jets, firing 10 precision munitions against a single target, the BBC reported, citing Israeli media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Israeli Air Force (IAF) fighters were over the Red Sea when they fired air-launched ballistic missiles, an unnamed U.S. defense official told the Associated Press. In this way, Israeli aircraft didn’t need to enter the airspace of any Middle East country, and the missiles arrived from a direction that the air defenses in Qatar were not focused on looking. The missiles would have also passed over Saudi Arabia at very high altitudes, likely outside the Earth’s atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ALBMs available to the IAF include an air-launched version of the Israel Aerospace Industries (IAI) LORA (Long Range Artillery), a short-range ballistic missile originally developed for surface launch. There is also the Rafael Rocks, that was developed from Israel’s line of Sparrow ballistic missile test targets. Meanwhile, the Israel Military Industries (IMI) Rampage, which is based on a guided artillery rocket, would not be relevant here due to the long ranges involved. Israel’s highly precise air-launched ballistic missiles have quickly become critical and somewhat famous weapons after their use on Iran on multiple occasions, and especially during the war between it and Israel in June.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The IAF hit a compound where negotiators for Hamas were meeting to consider a Gaza ceasefire proposal put forward by the U.S. government. The attack killed six people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to White House spokesperson Karoline Leavitt, U.S. President Donald Trump “was informed of the impending strike by his military and alerted Qatar’s leadership,” although the timeline for this remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For their part, Qatari officials claimed that they only found out about the attack after it had begun.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other than preparedness for unexpected eventualities, in terms of potential attacks, Lt. Gen. France explained that the other important lesson learned is how the U.S. military communicates and coordinates with its Qatari partners and other partners in the Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With that in mind, Lt. Gen. France said that integrated air and missile defense is one of his main areas of focus. “That we can do that in as integrated a fashion as possible with our partners in the Gulf. And that starts with interoperable equipment. So when they buy U.S. Patriot [air defense systems], and we have U.S. Patriots, the degree that we can operate efficiently together is a big part of what we’re pushing in the theater.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lt. Gen. France also said he wasn’t concerned about future U.S. military access to Qatar following Israel’s airstrike on Doha, although he admitted that “there certainly is some tension as a result of that, in my mind, goes to the importance of developing relationships and having presence that matters.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reflecting the importance of those relationships, Lt. Gen. France confirmed that he had a conversation with the Qatari Air Chief “right immediately after that happened” on September 9.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lt. Gen. France’s remarks today shed some more light on the mystery of how Israel pulled off its strike in Qatar, although there remain unresolved details. With more time, we may well learn more details about this unprecedented operation, one that succeeded in catching both the U.S. and Qatari militaries almost entirely off guard.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contact the author: thomas@thewarzone.com&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45372767</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:04:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Shiller PE Ratio</title><link>https://www.multpl.com/shiller-pe</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="d3d3d183dab07024"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Current Shiller PE Ratio: 39.79 -0.13 (-0.33%) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; 4:00 PM EDT, Wed Sep 24 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mean:&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17.28&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Median:&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16.05&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Min:&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4.78&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;(Dec 1920)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Max:&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;44.19&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;(Dec 1999)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shiller PE ratio for the S&amp;amp;P 500.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Price earnings ratio is based on average inflation-adjusted earnings from the previous 10 years, known as the Cyclically Adjusted PE Ratio (CAPE Ratio), Shiller PE Ratio, or PE 10 — FAQ.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data courtesy of Robert Shiller from his book, Irrational Exuberance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45372888</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:16:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Launch HN: Webhound (YC S23) – Research agent that builds datasets from the web</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45373008</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="354a104b23ad844a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We're the team behind Webhound (&lt;/p&gt;https://webhound.ai&lt;p&gt;), an AI agent that builds datasets from the web based on natural language prompts. You describe what you're trying to find. The agent figures out how to structure the data and where to look, then searches, extracts the results, and outputs everything in a CSV you can export.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've set up a special no-signup version for the HN community at https://hn.webhound.ai - just click "Continue as Guest" to try it without signing up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's a demo: https://youtu.be/fGaRfPdK1Sk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started building it after getting tired of doing this kind of research manually. Open 50 tabs, copy everything into a spreadsheet, realize it's inconsistent, start over. It felt like something an LLM should be able to handle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some examples of how people have used it in the past month:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Competitor analysis: "Create a comparison table of internal tooling platforms (Retool, Appsmith, Superblocks, UI Bakery, BudiBase, etc) with their free plan limits, pricing tiers, onboarding experience, integrations, and how they position themselves on their landing pages." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/c67c96a6-9d17-4c91-b9a0-ff69...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lead generation: "Find Shopify stores launched recently that sell skincare products. I want the store URLs, founder names, emails, Instagram handles, and product categories." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/b63d148a-8895-4aab-ac34-455e...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pricing tracking: "Track how the free and paid plans of note-taking apps have changed over the past 6 months using official sites and changelogs. List each app with a timeline of changes and the source for each." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/c17e6033-5d00-4e54-baf6-8dea...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Investor mapping: "Find VCs who led or participated in pre-seed or seed rounds for browser-based devtools startups in the past year. Include the VC name, relevant partners, contact info, and portfolio links for context." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/1480c053-d86b-40ce-a620-37fd...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research collection: "Get a list of recent arXiv papers on weak supervision in NLP. For each, include the abstract, citation count, publication date, and a GitHub repo if available." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/e274ca26-0513-4296-85a5-2b7b...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hypothesis testing: "Check if user complaints about Figma's performance on large files have increased in the last 3 months. Search forums like Hacker News, Reddit, and Figma's community site and show the most relevant posts with timestamps and engagement metrics." (https://www.webhound.ai/dataset/42b2de49-acbf-4851-bbb7-080b...)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first version of Webhound was a single agent running on Claude 4 Sonnet. It worked, but sessions routinely cost over $1100 and it would often get lost in infinite loops. We knew that wasn't sustainable, so we started building around smaller models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That meant adding more structure. We introduced a multi-agent system to keep it reliable and accurate. There's a main agent, a set of search agents that run subtasks in parallel, a critic agent that keeps things on track, and a validator that double-checks extracted data before saving it. We also gave it a notepad for long-term memory, which helps avoid duplicates and keeps track of what it's already seen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After switching to Gemini 2.5 Flash and layering in the agent system, we were able to cut costs by more than 30x while also improving speed and output quality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The system runs in two phases. First is planning, where it decides the schema, how to search, what sources to use, and how to know when it's done. Then comes extraction, where it executes the plan and gathers the data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It uses a text-based browser we built that renders pages as markdown and extracts content directly. We tried full browser use but it was slower and less reliable. Plain text still works better for this kind of task.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also built scheduled refreshes to keep datasets up to date and an API so you can integrate the data directly into your workflows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right now, everything stays in the agent's context during a run. It starts to break down around 1000-5000 rows depending on the number of attributes. We're working on a better architecture for scaling past that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We'd love feedback, especially from anyone who's tried solving this problem or built similar tools. Happy to answer anything in the thread.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks! Moe&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45373008</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:28:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cloudflare Email Service: private beta</title><link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/email-service/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="eed7ad5b3f10bcad"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you are building an application, you rely on email to communicate with your users. You validate their signup, notify them about events, and send them invoices through email. The service continues to find new purpose with agentic workflows and other AI-powered tools that rely on a simple email as an input or output.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And it is a pain for developers to manage. Itâs frequently the most annoying burden for most teams. Developers deserve a solution that is simple, reliable, and deeply integrated into their workflow.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Today, we're excited to announce just that: the private beta of Email Sending, a new capability that allows you to send transactional emails directly from Cloudflare Workers. Email Sending joins and expands our popular Email Routing product, and together they form the new Cloudflare Email Service â a single, unified developer experience for all your email needs.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;With Cloudflare Email Service, weâre distilling our years of experience securing and routing emails, and combining it with the power of the developer platform. Now, sending an email is as easy as adding a binding to a Worker and calling &lt;code&gt;send&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;export default {
  async fetch(request, env, ctx) {

    await env.SEND_EMAIL.send({
      to: [{ email: "[email protected]" }],
      from: { email: "[email protected]", name: "Your App" },
      subject: "Hello World",
      text: "Hello World!"
    });

    return new Response(`Successfully sent email!`);
  },
};&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email experience is user experience&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email is a core tenet of your user experience. Itâs how you stay in touch with your users when they are outside your applications. Users rely on email to inform them when they need to take actions such as password resets, purchase receipts, magic login links, and onboarding flows. When they fail, your application fails.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;That means itâs crucial that emails need to land in your usersâ inboxes, both reliably and quickly. A magic link that arrives ten minutes late is a lost user. An email delivered to a spam folder breaks user flows and can erode trust in your product. Thatâs why weâre focusing on deliverability and time-to-inbox with Cloudflare Email Service.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To do this, weâre tightly integrating with DNS to automatically configure the necessary DNS records â like SPF, DKIM and DMARC â such that email providers can verify your sending domain and trust your emails. Plus, in true Cloudflare fashion, Email Service is a global service. That means that we can deliver your emails with low latency anywhere in the world, without the complexity of managing servers across regions.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Simple and flexible for developers&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Treating email as a core piece of your application also means building for every touchpoint in your development workflow. Weâre building Email Service as part of the Cloudflare stack to make developing with email feels as natural as writing a Worker.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In practice, that means solving for every part of the transactional email workflow:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Starting with Email Service is easy. Instead of managing API keys and secrets, you can use the &lt;code&gt;Email&lt;/code&gt; binding to your &lt;code&gt;wrangler.jsonc&lt;/code&gt; and send emails securely and with no risk of leaked credentials.Â &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;You can use Workers to process incoming mail, store attachments in R2, and add tasks to Queues to get email sending off the hot path of your application. And you can use &lt;code&gt;wrangler&lt;/code&gt; to emulate Email Sending locally, allowing you to test your user journeys without jumping between tools and environments.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;In production, you have clear observability over your emails with bounce rates and delivery events. And, when a user reports a missing email, you can quickly dive into the delivery status to debug issues quickly and help get your user back on track.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Weâre also making sure Email Service seamlessly fits into your existing applications. If youâve been leaning on existing email frameworks (like React Email) to send rich, HTML-rendered emails to users, you can continue to use them with Email Service. Import the library, render your template, and pass it to the &lt;code&gt;send&lt;/code&gt; method just as you would elsewhere.Â &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;import { render, pretty, toPlainText } from '@react-email/render';
import { SignupConfirmation } from './templates';

export default {
  async fetch(request, env, ctx) {

    // Convert React Email template to html
    const html = await pretty(await render(&amp;lt;SignupConfirmation url="https://your-domain.com/confirmation-id"/&amp;gt;));

    // Use the Email Sending binding to send emails
    await env.SEND_EMAIL.send({
      to: [{ email: "[email protected]" }],
      from: { email: "[email protected]", name: "Welcome" },
      subject: "Signup Confirmation",
      html,
      text: toPlainText(html)
    });

    return new Response(`Successfully sent email!`);
  }
};&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email Routing and Email Sending: Better together&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Sending email is only half the story. Applications often need to receive and parse emails to create powerful workflows. By combining Email Sending with our existing Email Routing capabilities, we're providing a complete, end-to-end solution for all your application's email needs.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email Routing allows you to create custom email addresses on your domain and handle incoming messages programmatically with a Worker, which can enable powerful application flows such as:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Using Workers AI to parse, summarize and even label incoming emails: flagging security events from customers, early signs of a bug or incident, and/or generating automatic responses based on those incoming emails.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Creating support tickets in systems like JIRA or Linear from emails sent to &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Processing invoices sent to &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt; and storing attachments in R2.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To use Email Routing, add the &lt;code&gt;email&lt;/code&gt; handler to your Worker application and process it as needed:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;export default {
  // Create an email handler to process emails delivered to your Worker
  async email(message, env, ctx) {

    // Classify incoming emails using Workers AI
    const { score, label } = env.AI.run("@cf/huggingface/distilbert-sst-2-int8", { text: message.raw" })

    env.PROCESSED_EMAILS.send({score, label, message});
  },
};  &lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When you combine inbound routing with outbound sending, you can close the loop entirely within Cloudflare. Imagine a user emails your support address. A Worker can receive the email, parse its content, call a third-party API to create a ticket, and then use the Email Sending binding to send an immediate confirmation back to the user with their ticket number. Thatâs the power of a unified Email Service.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email Sending will require a paid Workers subscription, and we'll be charging based on messages sent. We're still finalizing the packaging, and we'll update our documentation, changelog, and notify users as soon as we have final pricing and long before we start charging. Email Routing limits will remain unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Whatâs next&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email is core to your application today, and it's becoming essential for the next generation of AI agents, background tasks, and automated workflows. We built the Cloudflare Email Service to be the engine for this new era of applications, weâll be making it available in private beta this November.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Interested in Email Sending? Sign up to the waitlist here.Â &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Want to start processing inbound emails? Get started with Email Routing, which is available now, remains free and will be folded into the new email sending APIs coming.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Weâre excited to be adding Email Service to our Developer Platform, and weâre looking forward to seeing how you reimagine user experiences that increasingly rely on emails!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45373081</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:33:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Story of DOGE, as Told by Federal Workers</title><link>https://www.wired.com/story/oral-history-doge-federal-workers/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7e60c110ece2475d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In August, months after Elon Musk left the federal government, the director of the Office of Personnel Management offered the first hard estimate of the so-called Department of Government Efficiency’s impact on the civil service. The government would likely end 2025 with about 300,000 fewer employees than it had at the start of the year, he told reporters. Most resignations were attributable to the incentives DOGE had offered the federal workforce to resign their positions. The total figure amounted to one in eight workers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, almost. In recent weeks, hundreds of the employees DOGE pushed out have reportedly been offered reinstatement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The true scope of DOGE’s attack on the federal government remains unknown. While there is no reason to think it achieved meaningful cost savings or operational efficiencies, the ramifications of building a master database to track and surveil immigrants are just beginning to be felt, and its cadre of Musk protégés and tech entrepreneurs remain embedded in agencies throughout the executive branch. The possibilities this opens up—of private takeovers of government operations, of the government embracing Silicon Valley’s ethos of moving fast and breaking things—remain open.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WIRED spoke with more than 200 federal workers across dozens of agencies to gather the most comprehensive picture yet of how the American government got to this point, and where it may go from here. Many sources requested anonymity because they fear retaliation. They told WIRED not just what has been going on inside the federal government at a time of unprecedented change—but what it’s been like to experience those changes firsthand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following is the story, in their words, of what happened when the world’s most powerful man unleashed the world’s richest one on the world’s most complex institution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I kept comparing it to a natural disaster,” one worker at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention told WIRED. “But it wasn’t natural. Just a stampede of wide-eyed, confused government employees moving files around and looking over their shoulders because they think maybe Elon was creeping behind them with a chain saw.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donald Trump established DOGE within hours of taking office on January 20, assigning it the task of “modernizing Federal technology and software to maximize governmental efficiency and productivity.” Within days, Musk’s allies and their coterie of young, inexperienced technologists were appearing in the offices of relatively unknown agencies like the General Services Administration and the Office of Personnel Management—obtaining unprecedented access to government systems and personnel files in the process. The DOGE operatives included young men like Edward “Big Balls” Coristine, Kyle Schutt, and Ethan Shaotran, all of whom would go on to work at a number of government agencies, from the Department of Education to the Social Security Administration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I met Kyle and Ethan on January 23, and I very briefly bumped into Coristine before anyone was talking about him. I would describe them all as giddy, excited, curious, passionate, and super interested in learning about and jumping in on this new thing. I was super excited too at first.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Then the next week it felt like everything shifted and suddenly they were no longer curious or asking questions or on an adventure, and instead they were just frantically running around trying to do impossible shit with no context and no flexibility and no ability to push back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I thought maybe it would turn around. But it never did.” —GSA worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The first meeting with DOGE—really the only meeting with DOGE, if I'm going to be honest—was … a virtual meeting that was 30 minutes long. In typical DOGE fashion, the government organization that we were promised unbelievable transparency on, they don't turn the cameras on, they don't tell you who they are, they don't tell you if anybody else is in the room, so you have no idea who you're talking to.” —Colin O’Brien, former head of security at the United States Institute of Peace&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We saw them immediately. They acted like new hires but a bit furtive since they were actually instructed not to share their full names with us at first.” —Technology Transformation Services (TTS) worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“My big aha moment came late, because for so long I was giving them the benefit of the doubt. These guys were young and they had a job to do, and yes, they were doing it aggressively—but again, I assumed the best. But then Ethan Shaotran went on Fox News, on Jesse Watters. He just trash-talked us pretty bad, conflating things they’d found at other agencies, basically implying we were misappropriating grant money. It made my blood boil. Ethan had to know that wasn’t true. That was it for me—there is no good faith at all.” —Federal worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The vibe they gave was ‘So, what is it that you do here?’ and ‘Why can’t AI do that?’” —TTS worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During the early weeks of the administration, emails from DOGE started showing up in federal workers’ inboxes—or at least in their spam folders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I logged on to find several emails tagged ‘External’ because DOGE just brought in their own servers and plugged them into the network. Then there were several subsequent emails from different leaders saying things like, ‘Thank you for all the phishing reports, but the emails are real and need to be followed. But also please keep reporting things that look like phishing. Except from DOGE … but probably even then. And this is totally fine and normal.’” —Contractor for the Veterans Administration&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the emails was the now infamous “Fork in the Road,” encouraging workers to be loyal or quit. It closely tracked the language of an email sent to Twitter employees not long after Musk’s takeover of the company. A subsequent follow-up was even more insulting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It was truly so idiotic and looked like it was written by a disturbed child.” —CDC employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We’re used to every little thing done by regulation, and now we’re just getting crazy emails … This is a 5-alarm fire. This is a constitutional crisis.” —Department of Labor employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“That response shocked me. We knew that this administration had little regard for professionals who choose to work for the federal government, but to state it so publicly, dripping with contempt, was truly unbelievable to me.” —General Services Administration employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Federal employees who remained were forced back to the office. Many found their workplaces increasingly hostile.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“A woman I did not know in the cubicle next to me broke down. She was literally wailing, inconsolable, because she could not get into a childcare facility she could afford on such short notice. She literally had to choose between her little child and working. Her explaining to her manager the way her child cried and begged Mommy to stay home broke me. Then, as if on cue, an email from a person whose account said they were the acting IRS commissioner arrived in our inboxes, reminding us that it was “Mental Health Awareness” month and that we can do such helpful things as “practicing gratitude” and breathing techniques to deal with stress. It also reminded us we can take time off to seek professional help … I never saw her again, and her cube is now empty.” —IRS employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Because we are part of Homeland Security, there’s always an armed guard at FEMA facilities. That’s a very standard thing. But the guys we’re used to seeing are like the contracted out, office patrol guys—they’re mall cops, to be polite about it. They sit at the desk and make sure you have ID, and that’s the extent of their policing. We have a pretty good relationship with our local guy at the front desk of our building. He’s a nice guy, he’ll walk around our office sometimes, we share our snacks with him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“One day he comes in to walk the office, like he does occasionally, and a few minutes after he passes by, another officer walks through. This time, it’s somebody we’ve never seen before, and he’s like, kitted out. He’s dressed in all black from head to toe, he’s got body armor on. He’s wearing a tactical helmet. He’s got a big gun on him, like a rifle, not like a handgun in a side pouch. He did not have a visible name tag, which is not standard at all—everybody in a federal facility is required to identify themselves at all times, and he had no individual identifying markings. The only writing on his uniform was the big yellow text on his back that said HOMELAND SECURITY.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“He was walking through the office as slowly as he could. He would pause behind you and watch what you were doing for five to 20 seconds and then move on. His entire demeanor, it was very obvious he wanted us to see him and he wanted to see us watching him. These are fucking office workers working on laptops. We’re doing spreadsheets and PowerPoints. Like, chill out, dude.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“My coworker went over [to the guard] and was like ‘Hey, welcome, can I help you with something, are we in danger? What’s the problem? The officer announces—not just to my coworker, but to as many people as can hear him—‘No, I don’t want your help, I’m just here to patrol you and to desensitize you to my presence.’ Then he just keeps on walking. That’s the only thing he’s said to us. He’s been through a couple times now and never gives anyone the time of day—never smiles, never says good morning, just walks through, dresses us all down for a few minutes, and leaves.” —FEMA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The offices were also quite literally gross—because DOGE had put a $1 spending limit on most government credit cards and didn’t make exceptions for basic necessities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The women’s restroom was out of toilet paper within a week or so of us coming back to the office. I brought this up to Facilities, like, ‘Hey, this is kind of a sanitation and dignity issue, can you hook us up with more toilet paper?’ They were like, ‘We’d love to, but we can’t purchase anything until they unfreeze the cards, and we don’t even know what the process is, because they have them sort of indefinitely frozen.’&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“For five months we were instructed to bring in our own toilet paper. I literally kept two rolls at my desk. I wish I were joking.” —FEMA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Musk and Trump were eagerly filling government agencies with their allies. At the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD), Trump installed Scott Turner, a former NFL cornerback.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“[Turner] has two primary sources of anecdotes I keep hearing: his time in the NFL—specifically that he was drafted in the last round—and his father’s time working as a shelf stocker at Safeway and how he is doing the same thing at HUD by ‘taking inventory and restocking the shelves.’ For a motivational speaker and pastor he is neither motivational nor inspirational.” —HUD employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Immigration was a major pillar of the second Trump administration. While the government made crystal clear it did not want foreigners in the country, it carved out an exception for a minority group of white South Africans in an executive order in February—a topic near and dear to Musk’s heart, as a white immigrant from South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This administration has made a complete mockery of the humanitarian side of immigration. I have interviewed parents who saw their children beheaded in front of them, I have interviewed children who saw their parents killed in front of them, I have interviewed women who have been sexually assaulted, I have interviewed children who have been sexually assaulted, I have interviewed teenagers who were beaten and threatened by their own family because they were part of the LGBTQI+ community. What has happened to these people in South Africa that warrants refugee status in the US? Nothing.” —Department of Homeland Security employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Musk said he wanted to downsize the federal workforce. What was the right size, exactly? As lean as possible. Entire agencies were gutted as tens of thousands of federal employees were subjected to reductions in force, known as RIFs. Some of these actions have been challenged in court, but the Supreme Court recently ruled that the Trump administration could continue its proposals to potentially lay off federal workers en masse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The moment everything crystallized for me was the day they came for a respected career deputy. Someone who embodied integrity and competence. His ‘crime’? Having the guts to challenge DOGE’s reckless RIF plans. One afternoon, he returned from lunch to find security waiting at his desk. No explanation, no warning—just a quiet escort out of the building while stunned colleagues looked on. Years of dedicated service reduced to a public humiliation.” —Department of Labor employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I knew what the powers that be were doing wasn't legal. So either they were incompetent and didn't know it was illegal or they knew it was illegal and didn’t care. Which one is scarier?” —CDC employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What stands out to me is how disorganized and unprofessional the GSA Reduction in Force (RIF) was. Staff were instructed to return government IDs ASAP. We lost Google Drive access immediately, and the agency put resources about our RIF on there. We were blocked from sending emails to non-GSA addresses. Even trying to email career documents to your private email address became a huge issue.” —GSA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“When the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau was first gutted, one person left their blazer in the office and was unable to get back into the building to get it. It was the only blazer they owned: They were broke, applying for jobs, and had nothing to wear to interviews because of this.” —CFPB employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On February 14, tens of thousands of federal workers lost their jobs, in an event that would become known to those impacted as the Valentine’s Day Massacre. Other workers were told they were going to receive firing letters imminently—only to wait days with no news.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“My fiancée and I had just come back from dinner. We’re getting ready to go to bed. I decide I’m just going to disconnect from social media and my email. I’m just going to turn it off … I saw I had an unread message. I was fired at 11:00, 11:30 pm. [My fiancée] looks at me, and she sees my demeanor change. [She says,] ‘That was the email, wasn't it?’” —Fired Federal Aviation Administration aeronautical information specialist&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It was Valentine’s Day and my partner planned a romantic dinner for us that I ate in a catatonic state, in my sweatpants, covered in tears.” —CDC employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On February 22, in another echo of his Twitter takeover, Musk warned that the entire federal workforce needed to write an email explaining what they’d gotten done the previous week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It was so humiliating to have to prove, ostensibly to Elon Musk—someone not in my chain of command or even a government employee—what I was doing. Not only is it none of their business what I was up to (they are not my supervisor) but they wouldn’t even understand anything I put in there anyway since it’s far too technical. I put read receipts on my first submission, and after I hadn’t gotten pinged that it had been read after two subsequent submissions, I just stopped sending them. It made me so mad that not only are they passive-aggressively insinuating I’m doing nothing, but they’re wasting tons of federal workers’ time (and taxpayer money) doing this exercise and they aren’t even opening the emails. Infuriating.” —Department of Defense employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“[Employees were responding with] emails in different languages … responding with the Constitution, and (for someone coming right back from maternity leave) responding with things such as: ‘breastfed a newborn for X number of hours, changed Y number of diapers with Z throughput, managed stakeholder input from my in-laws on best ways to burp a child.’” —VA IT worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I actually laughed pretty hard [at Musk’s email]. It’s just so ridiculous … It’s either [that or] be mad 24/7 (which some of my compatriots have decided to do), and I just don’t have the energy anymore.” —FAA air traffic controller&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On March 14, 2025, Colin O’Brien, then the head of security for the United States Institute of Peace, learned that the agency’s board had purportedly been fired. DOGE associates, including one named Nate Cavanaugh, arrived at USIP headquarters in Washington, DC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The on-duty security lieutenant called me and said, ‘Hey, DOGE is here.’ The instructions we had given were that any visit by DOGE that was unscheduled, they were not to be permitted entry. If they had a scheduled appointment, absolutely, we’d have let them in. They stayed outside for a little bit less than 30 minutes and then left.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later, O’Brien got another call from the front security desk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“They're like, ‘Hey, the FBI is here with DOGE.’ So we step outside. It was two FBI agents to our right and then four DOGE people to the left, sort of standing in a semicircle. They're dressed like college kids, sneakers and jeans that are too tight—certainly not business attire.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Our attorney asked the FBI: Why are you guys here? Do you have a court order, a warrant, anything? And they said no, and they said, ‘We're here to facilitate a cordial conversation.’ They looked embarrassed to be there, being just very honest.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The conversation lasts maybe five minutes, then the DOGE people leave with the FBI agents. I didn’t realize at the time that one of the women in the DOGE SUV had run around to the side of the building and was trying to convince one of the guards to let her in through a side door, claiming at first that it was cold and she had to go to the bathroom. Then that changed, when she was told no, to: ‘I have every right to be in a government building.’ So on one hand you have the intimidation factor of federal agents plus DOGE at your front door. And then you have this juvenile covert attempt in the back door. If she’d gotten in the door she would’ve probably called 911 and claimed false imprisonment or something.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DOGE ultimately got into the building (estimated value: $500 million; DOGE attempted to gift GSA the space but was blocked by a federal judge) and fired nearly every employee. On March 28, as staff were receiving termination notices—and finding out their health care would be cut the same day—one of O’Brien’s colleagues spied a salad in the office refrigerator with the name “Nate C” on it and promptly threw it in the trash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, DOGE was entering more agencies for the first time. Departments that rarely faced political strain, such as those that support arts and culture programs, were put under a microscope. Others, like the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, were put on ice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“No one has ever been against museums and libraries before. It seems like a really nonpolitical issue, and here we are facing a hostile takeover in real time … We were put on leave on March 31. By April 3, we were already starting to hear about grants being terminated. They were done through email, very generically, not through the official recordkeeping system, saying that they no longer met the priorities of the agencies. We initially heard about it from grantees. They were posting things publicly. On LinkedIn. On social media.” —Institute of Museum and Library Services employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“People’s livelihoods were gone, wiped out and thoroughly decimated. So many of these grantees work their entire lives to see a project, book, or exhibit come to fruition. These dreams came to a crashing and fiery end in the single hit of a button by someone who likely would never understand the true devastating impact.” —National Endowment for the Humanities employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I like to think of it as I am being slightly defiant. I’ll say ‘Although I was hired to do [certain duties] under the law, I have not been permitted to do work, so my accomplishments are limited to submitting a timesheet.’” —CFPB employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After an initial flurry of lawsuits related to DOGE access to sensitive networks, the president decided to unilaterally declare on March 20 that they could go, essentially, wherever they wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Learning about that was like getting punched in the stomach. It goes against everything our agency stands for, our mission. I have personally encouraged immigrant parents to file for benefits for their American children because those children needed it, and have promised all of them that they were safe, and that we didn’t share their information, and they trusted me. And now this administration has made a liar out of me.” —Social Security Administration employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At some agencies, that access extended to taking control of official social media accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I had to turn over access to our website and social media accounts. Ethan Shaotran asked me to turn over the login info to the website, to Facebook, Instagram, and X. I gave the passwords and usernames for those accounts. He came back later and asked for the address to log in to the WordPress account. I tried to just give the exact information they asked for because I wanted to passively resist. That’s why DOGE didn’t get access to our LinkedIn—they didn’t ask for it. The public considers these guys to be tech geniuses, but I’d say WordPress is pretty intuitive. It took them two days to take the website down.” —Federal worker&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In March, the Social Security Administration readied a plan ostensibly to combat identity theft. Under the plan, beneficiaries would not be able to verify their identity on the phone as they had in the past. Instead they’d have to use an online portal or show up in person. (About a week later, the SSA relented and began allowing the phone again.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Some elderly beneficiaries were crying on the phone, terrified that they would lose their benefits if they couldn’t figure out how to travel to an office and show us their ID. One woman was in her nineties. Another elderly couple showed up at an SSA office to prove they were alive, but it was never clear that this was necessary—no policy guidance had been issued.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We were told to be patient and wait until guidance could be provided. At one point, we were told that we would receive instructions a week AFTER the policy implementation day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In the end, the administration discovered that there wasn’t a problem with fraud in our teleclaims, something that frontline staff could’ve told them from the beginning. Less than 1 percent of claims were even flagged for further investigation. If our leaders would take the time to learn how to read the records, they might know this too.” —SSA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The concern for security apparently did not extend to DOGE affiliates themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In April, I happened to come across a partial list of employees and contractors who had not completed some of their mandatory security training. I wasn't surprised to see that DOGE-affiliated names made up more than a quarter of the list. It included [TTS director] Thomas Shedd, [Federal Acquisition Service head] Josh Gruenbaum, Ed Coristine, Luke Farritor, and Steven Davis. —Current GSA IT contractor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At AmeriCorps, DOGE called home thousands of young volunteers working on infrastructure projects or disaster relief around the country. It was chaos—a kind of chaos repeated across many agencies as spring wore on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“DOGE arrived at our agency in early April. About a week later, on Tuesday, they shut down the National Civilian Community Corps (NCCC). They wanted to bring all the members home. Members were in the literal field though, like they were in forests and on trails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The next day, 85 percent of us were placed on administrative leave. They had people booking flights for members to get home, and their computers were cut off while they were booking. It was chaos. People were just disappearing. On April 24, people started receiving RIF notices, except a bunch of them were addressed to the wrong person.” —Current AmeriCorp employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By June, Musk appeared to officially leave DOGE. With him went some key lieutenants: Steve Davis, Musk’s righthand man during the Twitter takeover and DOGE’s de facto leader; Nicole Hollander, Davis’ partner, who played a key role at the GSA; and Katie Miller, communications lead for DOGE and the wife of White House deputy chief of staff for policy Stephen Miller. Musk’s send-off had included a friendly press conference with Trump, but that fragile peace was shattered a few days later, when Musk went to war with Trump on X. It seemed like Musk’s ouster from government—and breakup with the president—was complete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“For all the talk that Trump likes teams of rivals, he doesn’t respect people who are nasty, interpersonally … I thought the cabinet secretary fights would be the end. The president was not going to tolerate him going after his cabinet secretaries, publicly or privately … The president just didn’t want that. He’s not going to tolerate that negativity. He likes all these people. These are his people. Marco’s a decade-old friend, at least, and a former competitor [with whom] he has a special comradery who he almost picked as his vice president. Peter Navarro went to jail for the guy. Took a federal charge, was found guilty, and ate it. Scott Bessent is his treasury secretary. Stuff like that was not gonna fly for very long.” —Senior Trump official&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The era of Musk’s DOGE, the flashy, so-called agency that garnered Fox News specials and had orchestrated the biggest upheaval the modern US government has ever faced, appeared to be over. But the next phase was just beginning, with DOGE’s operatives and its ethos occupying every corner of government. And the toll on federal employees still hasn't stopped.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We are in purgatory—not having enough resources to do our jobs, and not knowing what the vision is for the agency moving forward. Leadership by utter neglect.” —GSA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I am a clinical psychologist with plenty of lifetime trauma myself, but I had never actually attended therapy or seen a psychiatrist until after the inauguration. I was so upset when I first spoke to the telehealth psychiatrist that I couldn't even speak and almost had to hang up. They said that I was not the first federal employee that they'd talked to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This was the trauma that they wanted, that they planned, that they promised us. And, for once, they did a great job of delivering.” —CDC employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I’m terrified for our country and what all this means for the future. I need medication to help regulate me, because [Trump is] not going away anytime soon. And since I'm in HR, I can't get away from it. I live and breathe this during all my awake hours. If I'm not at work fielding questions from terrified employees or working with another team to terminate tons of people, family and friends are calling to see if I have any inside scoop or to check on the status of my own job.’” —Federal HR employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I’m the type of person where, like, if you push me I’ll push back. I don’t like to live in a mindset of despair and negativity. When these people do this shit, it just lights my fire. It makes me more fucking mad. This used to be the best job I’ve ever had, the best environment I’ve ever had, the best culture I’ve ever had—and they fucking ruined it. I will never ever forget how much they ruined it. I’m like, fuck these people. They can’t get me scared. I will not give them what they want. I will not just leave. I’m going to make it as difficult as possible for these fuckheads.” —FEMA employee&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let us know what you think about this article. Submit a letter to the editor at mail@wired.com.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45373102</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:36:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Accenture to 'exit' staff that cannot be retrained for age of AI</title><link>https://www.ft.com/content/a74f8564-ed5a-42e9-8fb3-d2bddb2b8675</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9e3b1951dffad9e9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;&lt;quote&gt;Accenture to ‘exit’ staff that cannot be retrained for age of AI&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Save 40% on Standard Digital&lt;/head&gt;was $540 now $319 for your first year&lt;p&gt;Save now on essential digital access to quality FT journalism on any device. Saving based on monthly annualised price.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Explore more offers.&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Trial&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then $75 per month. Complete digital access to quality FT journalism on any device. Cancel or change your plan anytime during your trial.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Premium Digital&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Complete digital access to quality FT journalism with expert analysis from industry leaders. Pay a year upfront and save 20%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FT newspaper delivered Monday-Saturday, plus FT Digital Edition delivered to your device Monday-Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Check whether you already have access via your university or organisation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Terms &amp;amp; Conditions apply&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Explore our full range of subscriptions.&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;For individuals&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discover all the plans currently available in your country&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;For multiple readers&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Digital access for organisations. Includes exclusive features and content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why the FT?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;See why over a million readers pay to read the Financial Times.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45373179</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:41:17 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>