<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 03:57:27 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>I switched from VSCode to Zed</title><link>https://tenthousandmeters.com/blog/i-switched-from-vscode-to-zed/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="8610177126853772"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For many years VSCode has been my day-to-day IDE for everything: Python, Go, C, occasional frontend development, and what not. It was never perfect but it worked. I like using mainstream tools with minimal configuration, so it suited me perfectly. But recent VSCode developments forced me to look for an alternative. In December I switched to Zed completely, and I think I'm never going back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;VSCode no more&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;VSCode felt stable over the years. This changed with the AI era. Now every update there are new AI-related features that I need to figure out how to disable. Few examples. I don't use Github Copilot. My preferred AI tool is a CLI (lately Codex). So I disabled Copilot. But VSCode continued to force it on me. After one update I see "cmd+I to continue with copilot" on every line I edit. Another update I see new inline terminal suggestions and they only interfere with my shell suggestions. There were a few other similar intrusions I don't recall now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So my &lt;code&gt;settings.json&lt;/code&gt; grew into a list of opt-outs. I could still live with that. The biggest issue for me was that VSCode became more buggy, feeling even slower, and crashing frequently – not surprising giving the pace of shipping new Copilot features.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I still think VSCode is an amazing IDE and I'm grateful to all the maintainers and the greatest extension community. There is a hope the VSCode approach to AI integration becomes less intrusive and more thoughtful, things stabilize, and VSCode "just works" again. But now it was time to look for somethings else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I knew I didn't want to switch to JetBrains IDEs. There are powerful but feel heavy and I don't enjoy using them. Vim, Emacs, and its modern variants are on the opposite spectrum. Probably they'll work great but only after I retire and have the time to configure and learn them properly. And there was Zed that I didn't know much about besides it being modern and lightweight IDE written in Rust. I gave it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Zed: first impressions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Zed I felt immediately at home coming from VSCode. The UI is similar. Zed's default keybindings are mostly the same. The biggest UX difference for me was that VSCode shows opened files (a.k.a. open editors) in the left sidebar, which I often used for navigation. In Zed there is no such panel, and the recommended approach is to navigate using file search (&lt;code&gt;Cmd+P&lt;/code&gt;). There is also a way to import VSCode settings automatically. I wanted to start fresh, so I didn't use it. The only configuration I had to do is change the font size and theme, disable inline git blame, and enable autosave.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My main impression of Zed was how fast and responsive it is compared to VSCode. I even noticed the slowness of some other tooling, which I got used to, and optimized it. Another highlight is that Zed has been stable for me without any glitches or crashes over the last two weeks. This all brings back joy of programming.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I mostly program in Python and sometimes Go. With Go, Zed worked out-of-the-box without any extra setup. With Python, it wasn't so smooth, and I had to spent half a day to get it working. Next is boring details that I wish I knew from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Making Zed work for Python&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First some context. Zed is an IDE that relies on language servers to provide language-specific features like autocomplete, code navigation, type checking, etc. It natively supports multiple Python language servers. One is Pyright, but its capabilities as a language server are limited – it's primarily a type checker that other language servers build upon. For example, Microsoft develops Pylance as a language server on top of Pyright. Pylance is the most widely used Python language server, however, it's not open source, so it cannot be used outside of VSCode. Zed uses Basedpyright as the default language server instead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first problem I encountered when I opened a Python project in Zed is that I saw a lot of type checker errors highlighted in the code. Apparently, Basedpyright ran in a stricter &lt;code&gt;typeCheckingMode&lt;/code&gt;. For my Python projects I used to configure Pyright with &lt;code&gt;typeCheckingMode&lt;/code&gt; unspecified, which defaults to &lt;code&gt;standard&lt;/code&gt;. The Zed docs say that "while Basedpyright in isolation defaults to the &lt;code&gt;recommended&lt;/code&gt; type-checking mode, Zed configures it to use the less-strict &lt;code&gt;standard&lt;/code&gt; mode by default, which matches the behavior of Pyright. This confused me since I definitely saw it working in &lt;code&gt;recommended&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried to specify &lt;code&gt;typeCheckingMode&lt;/code&gt; explicitly in settings.json like shown in the docs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// ...
"lsp": {
    "basedpyright": {
      "settings": {
        "basedpyright.analysis": {
          "typeCheckingMode": "standard"
        }
      }
    }
  }
// ...
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This didn't work. There were still a lot of typing errors I didn't want to check for. I figured out eventually that as long as you have &lt;code&gt;pyproject.toml&lt;/code&gt; with the &lt;code&gt;[tool.pyright]&lt;/code&gt; section, the Basedpyright's default &lt;code&gt;typeCheckingMode = "recommended"&lt;/code&gt; is used. My solution was to set &lt;code&gt;typeCheckingMode = "standard"&lt;/code&gt; in every &lt;code&gt;pyproject.toml&lt;/code&gt; explicitly. The solution took me a long time – I found several Github issues related to language server settings being ignored or not working as expected, so it looked like a bug at first. Now I see it's rather intended, although not clear from the docs. The lesson: If you define &lt;code&gt;[tool.pyright]&lt;/code&gt; , don't rely on Pyright defaults but set the options explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next I noticed that I as I edited the code I didn't see new typing errors shown for a file until I changed that file. I'd like to see such errors when, for example, a symbol is deleted but still used in another file. This I fixed by setting &lt;code&gt;"disablePullDiagnostics": true&lt;/code&gt; in settings.json:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// ...
  "lsp": {
    "basedpyright": {
      "initialization_options": {
        "disablePullDiagnostics": true
      },
    }
  }
// ...
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That's basically it. Virtual environment detection and other Python specifics were smooth. At one point I also tried ty instead of Basedpyright, which announced Beta just recently. It worked well from the start. I still chose Basedpyright because the CI runs Pyright and I want the same type checker locally. But given the success of ruff and uv, there is a high chance of me (and everyone else) switching to ty both for development and CI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zed is now my go-to IDE for Python and Go and my first choice as a general-purpose editor. It's fast, stable, familiar, feature-rich, with nice out-of-the box experience. The Zed extension ecosystem is tiny compared to VSCode, but I found it sufficient for my needs. The only thing I miss is a powerful git diff viewer with side-by-side diffs like GitLens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zed's AI features are actively developed but easily ignored and don't stand in the way. Zed offers paid plans for edit predictions, which seems like it can be a nice way to keep the project going. I want to wish Zed all the best!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As regards to VSCode, they finally got a decent competitor, and the Microsoft leverage may not be sufficient to keep the dominant position. VSCode, wake up!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, my minimal Zed's settings.json in full:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;{
  "autosave": "on_focus_change",
  "git": {
    "inline_blame": {
      "enabled": false
    }
  },
  "icon_theme": {
    "mode": "light",
    "light": "Zed (Default)",
    "dark": "Zed (Default)"
  },
  "base_keymap": "VSCode",
  "ui_font_size": 22,
  "buffer_font_size": 18,
  "theme": {
    "mode": "light",
    "light": "One Light",
    "dark": "One Dark"
  },
  "lsp": {
    "basedpyright": {
      "initialization_options": {
        "disablePullDiagnostics": true
      },
      "settings": {
        "basedpyright.analysis": {
          // Won't take affect if pyproject.toml has `[tool.pyright]`
          "typeCheckingMode": "standard"
        }
      }
    }
  },
  "languages": {
    "Python": {
      "language_servers": ["!ty", "basedpyright", "..."]
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, comments or suggestions, feel free to join the GitHub discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow me for more content: GitHub | Bluesky | Twitter | LinkedIn&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46498735</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 13:52:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: OSS sustain guard – Sustainability signals for OSS dependencies</title><link>https://onukura.github.io/oss-sustain-guard/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e60264a4d497f0d1"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;OSS Sustain Guard Documentation¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OSS Sustain Guard is a multi-language package sustainability analyzer that helps you understand the health of your dependencies across ecosystems. The tool provides constructive insights about maintainer activity, community engagement, security posture, and funding signals so teams can make informed decisions about the projects they rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note: Demo shows a warm cache; first run may take longer depending on API response time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why OSS Sustain Guard?¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every time a high-profile OSS incident makes the news, I find myself wondering about the packages I rely on right now. I could visit GitHub and skim issues, pull requests, and activity to get a rough sense, but it is not easy. When you depend on tens or hundreds of packages, plus their dependencies, it becomes nearly impossible, and you usually do not notice until something goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The libraries that support my work might be under heavy strain, and their own dependencies might be too. OSS Sustain Guard was built to answer those questions and to create moments where users can see the state of maintainers and communities. The first step is simple awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;💡 Project Philosophy¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OSS Sustain Guard uses empathetic language and contextual metrics to help teams support the projects they rely on. We avoid judgment and recognize that sustainability looks different across communities and organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🌱 Sustainability matters - Open-source projects need ongoing support to thrive&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🤝 Community support is essential - For community-driven projects, we highlight funding opportunities to help users give back&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📊 Transparency helps everyone - By providing objective metrics, we help maintainers and users make informed decisions&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🎯 Respectful evaluation - We distinguish between corporate-backed and community-driven projects, recognizing their different sustainability models&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;💝 Supporting maintainers - When available, we display funding links for community projects to encourage direct support&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Metrics are one lens among many; they work best alongside project context and real-world knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Local caching: Analysis results are cached locally to minimize API calls. GitHub tokens cover most repos; GitLab tokens are only needed for gitlab.com sources, with a built-in demo mode available.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multi-ecosystem support: Analyze packages from Python, JavaScript, Go, Rust, PHP, Java, Kotlin, C#, and Ruby in one command.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Actionable insights: Metrics use empathetic language that encourages collaboration with maintainers rather than blame.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sustainable by design: Respects open-source sustainability models with funding awareness for community-driven projects.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Key Features¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;🔍 Comprehensive Analysis¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;24 Core Sustainability Metrics - Comprehensive evaluation across maintainer health, development activity, community engagement, project maturity, and security (all core metrics scored 0-10)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trend Analysis - Track how repository sustainability scores change over time across multiple time windows&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CHAOSS-aligned metrics measuring contributor health, development activity, community engagement, and project maturity&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;5 CHAOSS-Aligned Models - Stability, Sustainability, Community Engagement, Project Maturity, and Contributor Experience&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Scoring profiles optimized for different priorities (balanced, security-first, contributor-experience, long-term-stability)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Transparent scoring with detailed breakdowns of each metric&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;🔧 Developer-Friendly Workflow¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Manifest auto-detection from &lt;code&gt;requirements.txt&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Cargo.toml&lt;/code&gt;, and other formats&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Recursive scanning for monorepos and multi-service projects&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Exclude configuration for internal or legacy dependencies&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Integration-ready for GitHub Actions, pre-commit hooks, and CI/CD pipelines&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub/GitLab analysis - Real-time analysis supports GitHub and GitLab (gitlab.com)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Extensible VCS support - Add support for additional version control systems via plugins&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;📝 Extensibility &amp;amp; Configuration¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pluggable Architecture - Easily extend analysis by adding your own sustainability metrics, language resolvers, and VCS providers as plugins&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Custom Scoring Profiles - Define your own scoring profiles to tailor evaluation priorities for your organization or use case&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Metric-Weighted Scoring - Configurable scoring profiles with integer weights per metric, normalized to 0-100 scale&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Minimal Setup - Requires a GitHub token for most repos; a GitLab token is only needed for gitlab.com (demo mode uses snapshot data)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;🌍 Multi-Language Support¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Python, JavaScript, Go, Rust, PHP, Java, Kotlin, C#, Ruby and more&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multi-ecosystem support - Analyze packages from all supported languages in one command&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Extensible resolvers - Add support for new package ecosystems via plugins&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;💝 Sustainability Focus¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Community Support Awareness - Displays funding links for community-driven projects&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Local Caching - Efficient local cache for faster repeated checks&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gratitude Vending Machine - Discover projects that need your support most&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Quick Navigation¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Just Getting Started?¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👉 Getting Started Guide - Installation, first steps, and basic usage in 5 minutes&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Common Tasks¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Usage:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Recursive Scanning - Analyze entire projects and monorepos&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Trend Analysis - Track sustainability changes over time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dependency Graph Visualization - Visualize and analyze dependency networks&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Gratitude Vending Machine - Find projects to support&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Exclude Configuration - Skip internal or legacy packages&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Custom Resolvers - Add support for new package ecosystems&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Custom VCS Providers - Add support for new version control systems&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scoring &amp;amp; Metrics:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Scoring Profiles - Choose the right scoring model for your needs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CHAOSS Metrics Alignment - Understanding our metrics&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Custom Metrics - Create your own sustainability metrics&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Custom Resolvers - Add support for new package ecosystems&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Custom VCS Providers - Add support for new version control systems&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Integrations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub Actions - Automate checks in CI/CD&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pre-commit Integration - Run checks before commits&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Troubleshooting &amp;amp; FAQ - Common issues and solutions&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Installation¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;pip install oss-sustain-guard
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Supported Ecosystems¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OSS Sustain Guard supports the following ecosystems out of the box:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Python - PyPI&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;JavaScript/TypeScript - npm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rust - Cargo&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dart - pub.dev&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Elixir - Hex.pm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Haskell - Hackage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Perl - CPAN&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;R - CRAN/renv&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Swift - Swift Package Manager&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Java - Maven&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;PHP - Packagist&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ruby - RubyGems&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;C# / .NET - NuGet&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Go - Go Modules&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Kotlin - Maven&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Extensibility: You can add support for additional ecosystems by creating custom resolver plugins. See the Custom Resolvers Guide for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Community Standards¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OSS Sustain Guard uses encouraging, respectful language across all surfaces. Our observations help teams collaborate with maintainers and improve sustainability together—not to judge or blame projects.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;License¶&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OSS Sustain Guard is open source and available under the MIT License.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46498786</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 13:58:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dealing with abandonware (2024)</title><link>https://blog.hris.to/./dealing-with-abandonware.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b5ca21689302dde"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Dealing with abandonware&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;October 20, 2024&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My father designs, plans and helps in the construction of SPA centers and wellness facilities. He primarily uses mossaics and ceramics. To do his job he uses a program from the early 2000s called TileCreatorPro. I bought this program for him in 2017 from thoughtfishmedia.com (now defunct). He uses it often and has many custom designs in its bespoke format. He spent a lot of time manually filling in the many types of tiles to create a complete inventory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The woes began in 2021 when my dad decided to upgrade the family desktop computer. Before the upgrade he asked me if there will be a problem with the program when going from Windows 7 to Windows 10. I suspected the program would not work at all, so I decided to first email the manufacturer and check if the OS is supported. Then I discovered the website does not exist. Someone did not paid their DNS provider.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I decided to google around for the program and queried for the exact name "tilecreatorpro". It returned 4 junk results. Then I looked up "thoughtfishmedia". Boom. I found an article from the owner of the company Andrew Simmons who told CBS news in 2011 that he has recently become the adoptive father of 6 and has no time for software. Can't blame him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since google didn't yield anything useful, I decided to look inside the program. I asked my dad to send me the installation file and the main binary. I use a MacBook, and this application is Windows only, so executing it is out of the question. I ran strings on it and went through the output. One item stood out to me:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;&amp;lt;DIV&amp;gt;&amp;lt;SELECT class="field select medium" id=Field13 tabIndex=14 name=Field13&amp;gt; &amp;lt;OPTION value=&amp;lt;BeadCreatorPro&amp;gt;BeadCreatorPro&amp;lt;/OPTION&amp;gt; &amp;lt;OPTION value=&amp;lt;BeadCreator Publisher&amp;gt;BeadCreator Publisher&amp;lt;/OPTION&amp;gt; &amp;lt;OPTION value=&amp;lt;Cross Stitch Supreme&amp;gt;Cross Stitch Supreme&amp;lt;/OPTION&amp;gt; &amp;lt;OPTION value=&amp;lt;MuralCreator&amp;gt;MuralCreator&amp;lt;/OPTION&amp;gt; &amp;lt;OPTION value=&amp;lt;TileCreator&amp;gt;TileCreator&amp;lt;/OPTION&amp;gt; &amp;lt;OPTION value=&amp;lt;TileCreatorPro&amp;gt;TileCreatorPro&amp;lt;/OPTION&amp;gt; &amp;lt;OPTION value=&amp;lt;TileCreator Artistic&amp;gt;TileCreator Artistic&amp;lt;/OPTION&amp;gt;&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can see the names of other thoughtfishmedia products. And after looking up "BeadCreatorPro" I got many results from reddit! Digging through reddit, other forums, and facebook groups, I found a support email support@beadcreatorpro and sent this email:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Hello! I purchased TileCreatorPro 4 several years ago. Now I am forced to switch over from Windows 7 to Windows 10. Will TCP continue working? If not, is there an upgrade available for TCP, or is it abandoned? It was difficult to find your BeadCreator website and contact you, so if TCP is not offered anymore, do you know some software I can use to replace it?&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was very surprised to see a reply the following day:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Hello there, I will be able to provide you with some support for TileCreator. I can provide you a download link, with which you can test to see if it works on Windows 10. I suspect there will be no issues with compatibility. I am sorry you had difficulty finding us, TileCreator is mostly unsupported at this point in time. I do not personally know of any similar software. Please look for an email from SendOwl with a download link for you. This may end up in your spam folder. And please do let me know if you run into any issues with it. Kind regards, Bryce&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, amazing. I then asked if I can test out the installation on a spare machine before upgrading the main one. This way my dad still has his program if it doesn't work out. Bryce said that separate machines require separate serial numbers, and offered to give me spare serial numbers for the purpose of testing. However, he needed a "PC-ID" to issue me a serial number:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;I just need you to let me know what the "PC-ID" is that shows when you open the software. This should be a 4 to 8 digit code. I can use these to generate serial numbers for you. Let me know if you have any trouble finding those.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, I installed Windows 10 and TileCreatorPro on a spare machine, sent Bryce my PC-ID and tried out the serial number he gave me. Success!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To recapitulate the registeration process: when you buy the software you must first install an unlicensed version, get a 4 character magic number (aka PC-ID) from the unlicensed program, and request your serial number for that specific magic number. (AFAIK the first regular purchase I made had a serial number submission form where you can request the key after purchasing the software. This form does not work anymore.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My dad then upgraded the family desktop computer. I installed the program, entered the working serial number aaaaaand the key did not work. I told Bryce and he said the magic number is known to change from time to time and issued me yet another serial number. This one worked and the family desktop computer had a licensed version of Tile Creator Pro!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two years later my dad upgraded the family desktop again to install a new GPU. After the upgrade the magic number changed, which invalidated the previous serial number and registration. I contacted Bryce several times but got no response. With no support available I decided it's time to crack the abandonware.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have zero reverse engineering experience but I've been scrolling through HackerNews for years and it was finally time to put that knowledge to the test.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried three reverse engineering tools: Ghidra, Binary Ninja, and IDA. I decided to go with Binary Ninja because of the pleasant interface and ease of use. I've written some C / C++, have some experience writing compilers, and know a little bit about embedded devices and x86_64 / riscv5 assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first thing I needed to do was find a way to run Windows 10. My Macbook is too slow to emulate both x86_64 and Windows 10. Thus, I got my dusty old Thinkpad T440p and ran QEMU on it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Windows 7 ran too slow, as did Windows 10. NixOS worked well even after several years of neglect. Luckily my work laptop is a powerful x86_64 machine. After looking around for a Windows emulator I found out about quickemu. Amazing software! Runs like a charm. I quickly set up Windows 10 and installed Tile Creator Pro on it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first thing I did was to look for registration and licensing related strings in the binary. I renamed some functions with speculative purposes like "calls_busted_with_cb", or "perhaps_parse_magic_number_inner_for_real".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's difficult to understand the cobweb of jumps and decompiled symbols just by reading them. I used the Binary Ninja debugger and ran the target under it. Execution showed me actual values and I got a better sense of the code paths. My reasoning was: I have a valid serial number, what matters is getting the same magic number so the serial number is valid, I need to check where the magic number is generated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was difficult to find out where exactly the code was generated and I did not have much time to continue rummaging around the binary. My dad needed the program ASAP because of a new client. Plus, I have a regular job and this was done after working hours. (Not to mention the girlfriend who I completed neglected, she confirms this whilst proofreading my article.) I turned to the company slack channel and asked if someone knows someone who does reverse engineering or might have clues themselves. Several colleagues offered tips and most thought what I was doing was cool. One person had a contact but it was not a sure deal. I looked on reddit for freelancers and even messaged one company to hire them, no response though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I refused to give up and I decided to start debugging from _init and see what I find. At one point I got into a function where the registers gradually accumulated the new magic number. I got super excited. I looked more closely into the related calls and found it:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My mind was instantly flooded with questions: Will changing this code brick the entire program? What if it is not the only place where the magic number is generated? What if there are multiple ways of getting the magic number and checking against eachother? What if there is already a value in my registry that it is checked against? What if there is self-modifying code and the real magic number is already stored at some address in the binary?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I silenced all those questions and decided to try and hardcode the result to the magic number I need:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I re-ran the program in the debugger and saw my old magic number! I used the serial number I had and it worked!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Success!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now my dad has the program for as long as Windows 10 exists and I won't have to worry about him as much... until the next Windows upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46499425</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:53:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: DoNotNotify – Log and intelligently block notifications on Android</title><link>https://donotnotify.com/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="410a056bd3dbf57"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Privacy First Design&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your notifications contain sensitive OTPs and personal messages. DoNotNotify processes everything offline. No servers, no tracking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Granular Control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create powerful rules based on app names, message content, or regex patterns. Whitelist urgent alerts, blacklist the noise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Zero Noise&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stop the constant buzzing from promotional notifications. Keep only the notifications that actually matter to you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;See it in Action&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simple, powerful, and clean interface designed for efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Commitment to Privacy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe privacy is a fundamental right. DoNotNotify does not collect or share any personal information. We don't know who you are, and we don't want to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read our full Privacy Policy to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46499646</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 15:10:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Tailsnitch – A security auditor for Tailscale</title><link>https://github.com/Adversis/tailsnitch</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="561cf638a61d7942"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A security auditor for Tailscale configurations. Tailsnitch scans your tailnet for 50+ misconfigurations, overly permissive access controls, and security best practice violations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# 1. Set your Tailscale API credentials
export TSKEY="tskey-api-..."

# 2. Run audit
tailsnitch

# 3. See only high-severity findings
tailsnitch --severity high

# 4. Fix some issues  ~interactively~ yolo mode
tailsnitch --fix&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download the latest release from GitHub Releases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;macOS users: Remove quarantine attribute after download:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo xattr -rd com.apple.quarantine tailsnitch&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;go install github.com/Adversis/tailsnitch@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/Adversis/tailsnitch.git
cd tailsnitch
go build -o tailsnitch .&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailsnitch supports two authentication methods. OAuth is preferred when both are configured.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OAuth clients provide scoped, auditable access that doesn't expire when employees leave.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;export TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_ID="..."
export TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_SECRET="tskey-client-..."&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create an OAuth client at: https://login.tailscale.com/admin/settings/oauth&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Required scopes for read-only audit:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;all:read&lt;/code&gt;(simplest), or individually:&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;policy_file:read&lt;/code&gt;- ACL policy&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;devices:core:read&lt;/code&gt;- Device list&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;dns:read&lt;/code&gt;- DNS configuration&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;auth_keys:read&lt;/code&gt;- Auth keys (for AUTH checks)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Additional scopes for fix mode:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;devices:core&lt;/code&gt;- Delete devices, modify tags (requires tag selection)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;auth_keys&lt;/code&gt;- Delete auth keys&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;API keys operate as the user who created them and inherit that user's permissions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;export TSKEY="tskey-api-..."&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create an API key at: https://login.tailscale.com/admin/settings/keys&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Run full audit
tailsnitch

# Show passing checks too (verbose)
tailsnitch --verbose

# Output as JSON for processing
tailsnitch --json

# Audit a specific tailnet (when OAuth client has access to multiple)
tailsnitch --tailnet mycompany.com&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Only show critical and high severity issues
tailsnitch --severity high

# Filter by category
tailsnitch --category access    # ACL issues
tailsnitch --category auth      # Authentication &amp;amp; keys
tailsnitch --category device    # Device security
tailsnitch --category network   # Network exposure
tailsnitch --category ssh       # SSH rules
tailsnitch --category log       # Logging &amp;amp; admin

# Run specific checks only
tailsnitch --checks ACL-001,AUTH-001,DEV-010
tailsnitch --checks stale-devices,tailnet-lock-not-enabled

# List all available checks
tailsnitch --list-checks&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix mode allows you to remediate issues directly via the Tailscale API:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Interactive fix mode
tailsnitch --fix

# Preview what would be fixed (dry run)
tailsnitch --fix --dry-run

# Auto-select safe fixes (still requires confirmation)
tailsnitch --fix --auto

# Disable audit logging of fix actions
tailsnitch --fix --no-audit-log&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;API-fixable items:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Check&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Action&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-001, AUTH-002, AUTH-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Delete auth keys&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Replace with ephemeral keys&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Remove tags from user devices&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Delete stale devices&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-005&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Authorize pending devices&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix mode also provides direct links to the admin console for issues that require manual intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generate evidence reports for SOC 2 audits with Common Criteria (CC) control mappings:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Export as JSON
tailsnitch --soc2 json &amp;gt; soc2-evidence.json

# Export as CSV (for spreadsheets)
tailsnitch --soc2 csv &amp;gt; soc2-evidence.csv&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The SOC 2 report includes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Per-resource test results (each device, key, ACL rule tested individually)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CC code mappings (CC6.1, CC6.2, CC6.3, CC6.6, CC7.1, CC7.2, etc.)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pass/Fail/N/A status for each control test&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Timestamp for audit trail&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example CSV output:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;resource_type,resource_id,resource_name,check_id,check_title,cc_codes,status,details,tested_at
device,node123,prod-server,DEV-001,Tagged devices with key expiry disabled,CC6.1;CC6.3,PASS,Tags: [tag:server] key expiry enabled,2025-01-05T10:30:00Z
key,tskey-auth-xxx,tskey-auth-xxx,AUTH-001,Reusable auth keys exist,CC6.1;CC6.2;CC6.3,FAIL,Reusable key expires in 45 days,2025-01-05T10:30:00Z
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a &lt;code&gt;.tailsnitch-ignore&lt;/code&gt; file to suppress findings for known-accepted risks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# .tailsnitch-ignore
# Ignore informational checks
ACL-008  # We intentionally don't use groups
ACL-009  # Legacy ACLs are fine for our use case

# Ignore specific medium checks with justification
DEV-006  # External devices are approved contractors
LOG-001  # Flow logs require Enterprise plan&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ignore file locations (checked in order):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;.tailsnitch-ignore&lt;/code&gt;in current directory&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/.tailsnitch-ignore&lt;/code&gt;in home directory&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Use a specific ignore file
tailsnitch --ignore-file /path/to/ignore

# Disable ignore file processing entirely
tailsnitch --no-ignore&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Export full report
tailsnitch --json &amp;gt; audit.json

# Extract failed checks as TSV
tailsnitch --json | jq -r '
  .suggestions
  | map(select(.pass == false))
  | .[]
  | [.id, .title, .severity, .remediation]
  | @tsv
' &amp;gt; findings.tsv

# Summary by severity
tailsnitch --json | jq '
  .suggestions
  | map(select(.pass == false))
  | group_by(.severity)
  | map({severity: .[0].severity, count: length})
'

# List critical/high issues with admin links
tailsnitch --json | jq -r '
  .suggestions
  | map(select(.pass == false and (.severity == "CRITICAL" or .severity == "HIGH")))
  | .[]
  | "\(.id): \(.title)\n  Fix: \(.fix.admin_url // "manual")\n"
'&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Flag&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--json&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Output as JSON&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--severity&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Filter by minimum severity: &lt;code&gt;critical&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;high&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;medium&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;low&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;info&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--category&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Filter by category: &lt;code&gt;access&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;auth&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;network&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;log&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;device&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;dns&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--checks&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Run specific checks (comma-separated IDs or slugs)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--list-checks&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;List all available checks and exit&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--tailnet&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Specify tailnet to audit (default: from API key)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--verbose&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Show passing checks too&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--fix&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Enable interactive fix mode&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--auto&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Auto-select safe fixes (requires &lt;code&gt;--fix&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--dry-run&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Preview fix actions without executing (requires &lt;code&gt;--fix&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--no-audit-log&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Disable audit logging of fix actions&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--soc2&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Export SOC 2 evidence: &lt;code&gt;json&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;csv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--tailscale-path&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Path to tailscale CLI (for Tailnet Lock checks)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--ignore-file&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Path to ignore file&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--no-ignore&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Disable ignore file processing&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;--version&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Show version information&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailsnitch performs 52 security checks across 7 categories. See docs/CHECKS.md for detailed documentation of each check.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;ID&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Check&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Risk&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Default 'allow all' policy&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;All devices have unrestricted access&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SSH autogroup:nonroot misconfiguration&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SSH as any non-root user&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-006&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;tagOwners too broad&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Privilege escalation via tags&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-007&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;autogroup:danger-all usage&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Access granted to external users&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;ID&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Check&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Risk&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Reusable auth keys&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unlimited device additions if stolen&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Long expiry auth keys&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Extended exposure window&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pre-authorized keys&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bypass device approval&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tagged devices without key expiry&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Indefinite access&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;User devices tagged&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Persist after user removal&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-010&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tailnet Lock disabled&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;No protection against stolen keys&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-012&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pending Tailnet Lock signatures&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unsigned nodes need review&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-001&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Funnel exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Public internet access&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Subnet router trust boundary&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unencrypted traffic on local network&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SSH-002&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Root SSH without check mode&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;No re-authentication required&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;ID&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Check&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Risk&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;autogroup:member usage&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;External users included&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ACL-005&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AutoApprovers configured&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Bypass route approval&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;AUTH-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Non-ephemeral CI/CD keys&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Stale devices accumulate&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Outdated clients&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Potential vulnerabilities&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Stale devices&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unused attack surface&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-005&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unauthorized devices&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Pending approval queue&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-007&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sensitive machine names&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CT log exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;DEV-009&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Device approval config&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;May not be enabled&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-004&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;HTTPS CT log exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Machine names public&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-005&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Exit node traffic visibility&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Operator sees all traffic&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NET-006&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Serve exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Local services on tailnet&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;SSH-003&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Recorder UI exposure&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Sessions visible to network&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Checks for logging configuration, DNS settings, user roles, and manual verification items.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;+=====================================================================+
|                    TAILSNITCH SECURITY AUDIT                        |
|            Tailnet: example.com                                     |
|            Version: 1.0.0 (build: abc123)                           |
+=====================================================================+

  Using ignore file: .tailsnitch-ignore (3 rules)

=== ACCESS CONTROLS ===================================================

[CRITICAL] ACL-001: Default 'allow all' policy active
  Your ACL policy omits the 'acls' field. Tailscale applies a
  default 'allow all' policy, granting all devices full access.

  Remediation:
  Define explicit ACL rules following least privilege principle.

  Source: https://tailscale.com/kb/1192/acl-samples
----------------------------------------------------------------------

=== AUTHENTICATION &amp;amp; KEYS =============================================

[HIGH] AUTH-001: Reusable auth keys exist
  Found 2 reusable auth key(s). These can be reused to add
  multiple devices if compromised.

  Details:
    - Key tskey-auth-xxx (expires in 45 days)
    - Key tskey-auth-yyy (expires in 89 days)

  Remediation:
  Store reusable keys in a secrets manager. Prefer one-off keys.

  Source: https://tailscale.com/kb/1085/auth-keys
----------------------------------------------------------------------

SUMMARY
======================================================================
  Critical: 1  High: 3  Medium: 5  Low: 2  Info: 8
  Total findings: 19  |  Passed: 33
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tailnet Lock checks (DEV-010, DEV-012) require the local &lt;code&gt;tailscale&lt;/code&gt; CLI and run against the local machine's daemon. When auditing a remote tailnet via &lt;code&gt;--tailnet&lt;/code&gt;, these checks reflect local status, not the audited tailnet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Specify custom tailscale binary path if needed
tailsnitch --tailscale-path /opt/tailscale/bin/tailscale&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run Tailsnitch in CI/CD pipelines to catch security regressions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# GitHub Actions example
- name: Audit Tailscale Security
  env:
    TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_ID: ${{ secrets.TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_ID }}
    TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_SECRET: ${{ secrets.TS_OAUTH_CLIENT_SECRET }}
  run: |
    tailsnitch --json &amp;gt; audit.json
    # Fail if critical or high severity issues exist
    if tailsnitch --severity high --json | jq -e '.summary.critical + .summary.high &amp;gt; 0' &amp;gt; /dev/null; then
      echo "Critical or high severity issues found!"
      tailsnitch --severity high
      exit 1
    fi&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;MIT&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See CONTRIBUTING.md for guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46501137</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 16:47:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Y Combinator made it smart to trust founders</title><link>https://elbowgreasegames.substack.com/p/when-good-actors-can-trust-each-other</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46501677</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 17:20:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Brave overhauled its Rust adblock engine with FlatBuffers, cutting memory 75%</title><link>https://brave.com/privacy-updates/36-adblock-memory-reduction/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b61b947bacb8c5a8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Brave overhauls adblock engine, cutting its memory consumption by 75%&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the 36th post in an ongoing series describing new privacy features in Brave. This post describes work done by Mikhail Atuchin (Sr. Staff Engineer), Pavel Beloborodov (Sr. Software Engineer) and Anton Lazarev (Staff Adblock Engineer). It was written by Shivan Kaul Sahib (VP, Privacy and Security).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brave has overhauled its Rust-based adblock engine to reduce memory consumption by 75%, bringing better battery life and smoother multitasking to all users. The upgrade represents roughly 45 MB of memory savings for the Brave browser on every platform (Android, iOS and desktop) by default, and scales even higher for users with additional adblocking lists enabled. These performance boosts are live in Brave v1.85, with additional optimizations coming in v1.86.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As announced in June and October last year, we achieved this major memory milestone by iteratively refactoring the adblock-rust engine to use FlatBuffers, a compact and efficient storage format. This architectural transition allowed us to move the roughly 100,000 adblock filters shipped by default from standard, heap-allocated Rust data structures (such as Vecs, HashMaps, and structs) into a specialized, zero-copy binary format.Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Along the way, we completed several other key performance optimizations (some of these are coming in v1.86):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Memory management: Used stack-allocated vectors to reduce memory allocations by 19% and improved building time by ~15%.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Matching speed: Improved filter matching performance by 13% by tokenizing common regex patterns.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sharing resources: Resources are shared between instantiations of adblock engines, saving ~2 MB of memory on desktop.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Storage efficiency: Optimized internal resource storage memory by 30%.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Saving 45+ MB of memory is a significant milestone in the world of browser performance and a massive win for users on mobile and older hardware. While Brave already improves performance on the Web by blocking invasive ads and trackers, our latest engineering effort ensures that our own built-in protections are as lightweight and invisible as possible. Unlike adblocking in other browsers, Brave’s adblocking engine is built into the browser and maintained by our privacy team. Such deep optimizations are impossible for extension-based blockers, which are restricted by browser extension APIs and sandboxing. This native architecture is also why Brave’s own ad and tracker blocking is entirely unaffected by Manifest V3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This performance boost is the culmination of several months of in-depth cross-team engineering work between our performance and privacy teams. It marks a significant leap in the browser’s efficiency and ensures that we continue shipping best-in-class privacy to over 100 million users.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46501894</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 17:34:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sega co-founder David Rosen has died</title><link>https://www.theguardian.com/games/2026/jan/05/sega-co-founder-david-rosen-dies</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="66aea519a4e5ff7d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is difficult to think of a more influential figure in the arcade game industry than David Rosen, who has died aged 95. The co-founder of Sega, who remained a director of the company until 1996, was instrumental in the birth and rise of the video game business in Japan, and in the 1980s and 90s oversaw the establishment of Sega of America and the huge success of the Mega Drive console.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a US Air Force pilot during the Korean war, Rosen found himself stationed in Japan, and once the conflict was over, he stayed on, intrigued by the country and seeing possibilities in its recovering economy. In 1954 he set up Rosen Enterprises and noticing that Japanese civilians now required an increasing number of new ID cards he started importing photo booths from the US to answer the demand. From here he expanded to pinball tables and other coin-operated machines, importing them for installation in shops, restaurants and cinemas. In 1965, he merged the company with another importer, Nihon Goraku Bussan, whose coin-op business Service Games was shortened to Sega for the new venture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the next 15 years, Sega innovated in the arcade sector, switching from importing games to designing its own, and moving on from jukeboxes and pinball tables to electromechanical arcade games such as the submarine shooting sim Periscope and, in 1972, Killer Shark, a shark hunting game which would briefly feature in Jaws. Sega also began to set up its own arcades allowing the company close control over every facet of its business.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of Rosen’s great skills was in finding and employing people who instinctively understood where games were heading. In 1979, he spotted rising industry star Hayao Nakayama, director of Esco Trading, another arcade company. As Rosen explained to me in 2013: “Nakayama was very active as a distributor at the time – he was someone I felt was very astute and was quick to adapt to what was happening in the industry, and I wanted him – we did it via an acquisition of his company. By assimilation, we had him and the staff join us.” Nakayama would go on to be the president of Sega Japan during its heyday from 1983 to 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During this time, Sega rose from a competitor alongside fellow arcade manufacturers Namco, Capcom, Taito and Konami, to an industry leader. Its sleek, stylish coin-ops of the 1980s – Outrun, Space Harrier and AfterBurner – changed the image of arcades from nerdy hideouts to cool aspirational hangouts, while 1990s titles Virtua Racing and Virtua Fighter established the company as a technological powerhouse.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the late-1970s, Rosen pursued a new market: home TV games. He encounter a major rival, Nintendo, which dominated with its Color TV-Game console, and later the Nintendo Entertainment System. When Rosen returned to the US in the early 1980s, he was determined to take a slice of the global console industry from his Kyoto-based competitor. “Nintendo was responsible for the revival of the home console market after the Atari collapse of 1983,” he told me. “We wanted to see if we could make a device that would be competitive. Unfortunately our first attempt failed to compete. It was just made up of off the shelf parts, it wasn’t until 1986 that we brought out the Master System …”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This machine would struggle in the US but was huge in Europe and South America, and Rosen spotted a niche. While Nintendo was all about family entertainment, the titles doing well on the Master System were teen-focused brawlers, such as Golden Axe and Shinobi. When it came to release the new Sega Mega Drive console in Japan in 1988, Rosen insisted on changing its name to Genesis for the US launch, emphasising a new beginning and a more mature outlook. He also brought in Michael Katz an experienced exec from Mattel and early console company Coleco.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We were up against the wall in terms of time,” he said. “I had known Michael from some of the other endeavours he was involved in, he had all this experience from Coleco and he certainly knew the players. I thought he could help launch the product and at the same time bring structure to the company, which he did.” Spurred on by Rosen’s vision, Katz marketed the Genesis as a games console for teenagers, not children, using TV ads which combined video game visuals with flashing images and rock music and the immortal phrase: Genesis does what Nintendon’t. When Tom Kalinske took over as CEO Sega of America in 1990, he oversaw a new series of equally famous ads which almost always ended with someone screaming “Sega!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rosen would stay active in the company in various senior roles until retiring in 1996. Although Sega’s home console business would falter in this period due to the rise of the Sony PlayStation, the company’s arcade supremacy remained for the rest of the decade. I spoke to him in 2013 while writing the book Sega Mega Drive Collected Works. As a lifelong Sega fan, my hour-long chat with him that day was a career highlight. He talked fondly about his time in Japan, the people he worked with and his journey through the industry. He told me with considerable glee that while out and about in his home town of Los Angeles, strangers would still shout ‘Sega!” at him when passing on the street.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46502239</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:00:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pipe Dreams – The life and times of Yahoo Pipes (2023)</title><link>https://retool.com/pipes</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="fe1ec6fd46491482"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Table of contents TOC Close Loading...&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46503006</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:55:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>There were BGP anomalies during the Venezuela blackout</title><link>https://loworbitsecurity.com/radar/radar16/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="357321f7d83057ba"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Low Orbit Security Radar is a weekly security newsletter from an offensive practitioner's perspective. One idea, curated news, and links worth your time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;News: There Were BGP Anomalies During The Venezuela Blackout&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When watching the situation in Venezuela unfold, the phrase "It was dark, the lights of Caracas were largely turned off due to a certain expertise that we have" caught my attention. I do not wish to comment on the geopolitical situation other than to provide some insights within my area of competency, specifically, offensive security.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;During a press conference, General John D. Caine stated: "As they approached Venezuelan shores the United States began layering different effects provided by SPACECOM, CYBERCOM, and other members of the inter-agency to create a pathway". Cyber operations preceding traditional military actions have become a common pattern so I started digging into the reported internet outages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BGP is the first thing that comes to mind. It's a protocol used by routers to determine what path data takes to get to it's destination, it does this by exchanging routing information between Autonomous Systems. It is also notoriously insecure and much of the data about BGP is collected in public datasets. Every major network has an Autonomous System Number or ASN. CANTV (AS8048) is Venezuela's state-owned telecom, so that's the obvious place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare Radar's route leak data for AS8048 on January 2nd had some interesting anomalies: 8 prefixes (blocks of IP addresses) were being routed through CANTV, with Sparkle (an Italian transit provider) and GlobeNet (a Colombian carrier) in the Autonomous System (AS) path. The AS path is essentially the list of networks traffic passes through to reach its destination. CANTV was in a path it is not typically a part of.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There was also a noticeable spike in BGP announcements in the days leading up to the events and a drastic dip in the "Announced IP Address Space" according to the same Cloudflare Radar data, although it's unclear what this indicates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably, Sparkle is one of the transit providers in the AS path listed as "unsafe" on isbgpsafeyet.com, meaning they don't implement some BGP security features such as RPKI filtering.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloudflare shows that a leak happened, but not the actual network prefixes. The network prefixes are useful to determine what infrastructure was potentially affected. Fortunately public datasets collect this BGP information. Pulling the data from ris.ripe.net/docs/mrt from around the time of the leak and using a tool called bgpdump we can extract the data into a readable format:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;TIME: 01/02/26 15:41:16
TYPE: BGP4MP/MESSAGE/Update
FROM: 187.16.222.45 AS263237
TO: 187.16.216.23 AS12654
ORIGIN: IGP
ASPATH: 263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980
NEXT_HOP: 187.16.222.45
COMMUNITY: 0:6939 65237:1020
ANNOUNCE
  200.74.228.0/23
  200.74.236.0/23
  200.74.230.0/23
  200.74.238.0/23
  200.74.226.0/24&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After some more processing with &lt;code&gt;bgpdump&lt;/code&gt; we can get a much better view of the data, including the prefixes that were missing from the Cloudflare radar. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.230.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.236.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.228.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.238.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.226.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.232.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.233.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.234.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24115:52320 24115:65012 24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.234.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.233.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368421|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.232.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.228.0/23|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.236.0/23|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.230.0/23|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.238.0/23|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368446|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.226.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 6762 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368450|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.234.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368450|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.233.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368450|A|187.16.222.45|263237|200.74.232.0/24|263237 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.222.45|0|0|0:6939 65237:1020|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.234.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.232.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.233.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.238.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.228.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.226.0/24|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.236.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||
BGP4MP|1767368451|A|187.16.208.144|24482|200.74.230.0/23|24482 52320 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 8048 23520 1299 269832 21980|IGP|187.16.208.144|0|0|24482:2 24482:200 24482:13000 24482:13020 24482:13021 24482:65304 52320:41912 52320:61056 52320:64123|NAG||&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More information about the format can be seen in Working with Raw BGP Data but of note, the AS path has 8048 (CANTV) repeated 10 times, is very odd as this would make the route less attractive since BGP prefers shorter paths. Also of note is all 8 prefixes fall within a &lt;code&gt;200.74.224.0/20&lt;/code&gt; block.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;200.74.226.0/24
200.74.228.0/23
200.74.230.0/23
200.74.232.0/24
200.74.233.0/24
200.74.234.0/24
200.74.236.0/23
200.74.238.0/23
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A quick WHOIS lookup shows this range belongs to Dayco Telecom, a hosting and telecommunications provider in Caracas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A reverse DNS lookup can be used to find the domain name from an IP address. Interestingly, looking up some of these ranges turns up some pretty critical infrastructure including banks, internet providers, email servers, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;BGP anomalies happen frequently, but the timing of some currently unexplained BGP activity is very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Time (UTC)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Event&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Source&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jan 2, 15:40&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;BGP route leak detected&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Cloudflare Radar&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jan 3, ~06:00&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;First explosions reported in Caracas&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NPR&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jan 3, 06:00&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;US soldiers reach Maduro's compound&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;NBC News&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Jan 3, 08:29&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Maduro aboard USS Iwo Jima&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;CNN&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When BGP traffic is being sent from point A to point B, it can be rerouted through a point C. If you control point C, even for a few hours, you can theoretically collect vast amounts of intelligence that would be very useful for government entities. The CANTV AS8048 being prepended to the AS path 10 times means there the traffic would not prioritize this route through AS8048, perhaps that was the goal? There are many unanswered questions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless of the actual goal, there were undoubtedly some BGP shenanigans happening during this time frame. There is a lot of data publicly available that is worth a much deeper dive to understand exactly what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Caught My Eye&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MCP Security: Your AI's Prompts, Reasoning, and Secrets Are at Risk: A deepdive demonstrating how malicious MCP servers can exfiltrate prompts, reasoning, and .env files.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I Canceled My Book Deal: A professor walks away from a traditional publishing contract after the publisher pushed for AI integration, offered low royalties, and wanted to strip personality from the content. The numbers roughly align with ones I've seen from other publishers.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Year in LLMs (2025): A year in review covering reasoning models, coding agents, Chinese open weight models, MCP adoption, and the evolution of "vibe coding".&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Linux is Good Now: 2026 is the year of the Linux desktop?!?!? Unironically I think two things are making this a reality. 1. Valve's work making more gaming possible on via its ventures with the Steamdeck (runs arch btw) and 2. Microsoft making the OS more hostile than trusted with it's integration of AI into the OS.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No strcpy Either: The curl project eliminated strcpy() after previously removing strncpy(), creating a wrapper that requires explicit buffer sizes. Partly motivated by preventing AI vulnerability reports.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;hindsight: A CLI tool that scans local directories for git repos and aggregates contribution history heatmap.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pomerium: An open source identity and context-aware access proxy providing access to internal applications.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Frontier Data Centers Satellite Explorer: Track major AI data centers via satellite imagery and permit analysis.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ghostty Finances: Public financial transparency page for the Ghostty project through Hack Club Bank. Very cool way for non-profits to track spending.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AI Coding Exhaustion (HN Discussion): Interesting read about whether AI enables fewer or more abstractions.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;News Minimalist: News aggregator that ranks articles by a "significance score", filtering for impact, novelty, and credibility. Interesting use case.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;mymind: Visual bookmarking and note-taking tool that saves content without manual tagging.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Are.na: Similar to mymind but has more of a "community" vibe. Similar to Pinterest.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How I Browse the Web in 2026: An interesting personal workflow for intentional web browsing. Some cool ideas in here.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ML Math: Free machine learning mathematics resources and tutorials. I specifically like the visualizations.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Kubernetes Networking Best Practices: Great guide covering CNI selection, network policies, service mesh, and troubleshooting.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Bypass macOS Antivirus with tclsh: Using Tcl's built-in interpreter to bypass antivirus protections on macOS. PoC Gist.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cloudflare Radar: The Cloudflare Radar (nice name btw) I found while investigating the above story. Some really cool data&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Want more? Check back next Monday morning or get the latest Radar issue directly in your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46504963</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 21:05:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Scientific production in the era of large language models [pdf]</title><link>https://gwern.net/doc/science/2025-kusumegi.pdf</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46505296</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 21:33:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Keeping Syria connected during war: Surviving ISIS and Intelligence</title><link>https://syriauntold.com/2025/12/27/keeping-syria-connected-during-war/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ffd000f78da3d39f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The author is a computer scientist, one of several prominent technical analysts who covered internet outages during the 2011 Arab Spring and its aftermath. In his work for Renesys and later Dyn Research, he connected with “Mahmoud,” a senior Syria Telecom engineer who, at great personal risk, became a trusted source and shared internal details that informed the analysis. “Mahmoud” is a pseudonym; he has lived safely outside Syria for several years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is Mahmoud’s story.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was the middle of the summer of 2013 and Mahmoud was making a trek across northern Syria. The 33 year old lived in Aleppo where he worked for Syria Telecom as a network engineer. But on this day, the last day of Ramadan, he was packed into a crowded bus heading southwest to Idlib to celebrate Eid al-Fitr with family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thirty minutes into a trip that normally takes only an hour and a half, traffic slowed down for a roadblock up ahead. The Syrian civil war had been raging for over two years at this point and it was not uncommon for security checkpoints to spontaneously appear as the government hunted down members of the rebel forces.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But this was not a government roadblock. The fluttering black flags made clear to the passengers on the bus who were operating this checkpoint. Following the direction of the armed men, the bus pulled off to the side of the road for inspection. The black flags’ white script was now legible: دولة الاسلام في العراق والشام (Islamic State in Iraq and the Levant).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The travelers on the bus stiffened and put themselves in ‘careful mode,’ as Mahmoud would later call it. At that point, ISIS was only a minor player in the multi-sided war in Syria and had not yet demonstrated the brutality it later became known for.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two armed ISIS fighters boarded the bus and began inspecting passengers paying particular attention to military-aged men. One approached Mahmoud and asked for his identification card. Once produced, the fighter scanned the card for a moment and handed it back. He then saw Mahmoud’s laptop backpack in the overhead rack and asked, “whose bag is this?” Mahmoud said it was his as the fighter took it down and began rummaging through it. In the bag, he found Mahmoud’s passport and began flipping through it. His eyes lit up when he found a stamped Chinese visa on one of the pages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud had traveled to China two months prior. As was the case for developing countries around the world, the telecommunications infrastructure of Syria was built primarily using low-cost Chinese equipment. As a heavy user of Chinese gear, Syria Telecom had the opportunity to occasionally send engineers to China for advanced training and Mahmoud was the latest to make the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Holding his passport, the ISIS fighter asked Mahmoud, “what were you doing in China?” He responded that he was an employee of Syria Telecom and traveled there for work. Interest peaked, the ISIS fighter intensified his search through the bag. He pulled out Mahmoud’s laptop and ordered him to unlock it. From his seat on the bus, Mahmoud entered his password into the lock screen and handed it over. The ISIS fighter went straight to the MyPhotos folder and began flipping through the pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the middle of the bus full of passengers frozen with fear, the ISIS fighter flipped through photo after photo on Mahmoud’s laptop including those from his recent trip to China. He stopped at a selfie Mahmoud had taken in front of a huge Huawei computing cluster he saw on a tour during his trip. The ISIS fighter had seen enough and told Mahmoud that he needed to exit the bus for further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Two rows behind Mahmoud, another man on the bus was being interrogated. After directing the man to unlock his phone, a second ISIS fighter was again flipping through the photos. Soon enough a damning image appeared — a photo of his wife without a hijab. He, too, was directed to collect his things and leave the bus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unsure what to make of what was happening, Mahmoud felt numb as he exited the bus with the other man. They were led to two separate cars and placed in the back seat. Another ISIS fighter placed a blindfold over Mahmoud’s eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blindfolded, he felt metal handcuffs snapping into place around his wrists. It was at this point that Mahmoud felt a wave of terror wash over him. “What are you doing? We’re in free Syria!” Mahmoud shouted. “Shut up!” was the response from a man in the car as they drove away.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Syrian outage of November 2012&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the middle of 2011, the Arab Spring uprisings were reshaping the region, having toppled long-standing regimes in Egypt and Tunisia. Attempts to stifle the anti-government protests, including a complete shutdown of internet access in Egypt, had thus far failed to slow the momentum.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Protests in Syria had become violent and unresolved. Before long, Syria would have its first government-directed internet shutdown in early June 2011. At the time, I was an analyst with a small internet measurement startup called Renesys, who had been documenting the various shutdowns in the region earlier that year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On that day we wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Starting at 3:35 UTC today (6:35am local time), approximately two-thirds of all Syrian networks became unreachable from the global Internet. Over the course of roughly half an hour, the routes to 40 of 59 networks were withdrawn from the global routing table.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Syrian government had ordered the deactivation of networks supporting the mobile and broadband networks while leaving the networks belonging to the government and important industries online. Service was restored after more than 24 hours of blackout, but life would never be the same in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the civil war in Syria raged into its second year, another outage knocked out internet across the country. Fresh off the heels of the government-directed outages of the Arab Spring the previous year, concerns quickly arose that this outage had also been intentional, directed by the embattled Assad government.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we did with the outage from the previous year, Renesys reported technical details of the outage. We shared the timing of the withdrawn routes visible in our BGP data, illustrating it with the graphic below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In our write-up on the outage, we expressed concern about the possibility of an intentional outage meant to hide some nefarious activity, but, ultimately, there was no way to tell strictly from the data whether it had been directed by the government or the result of a technical failure of some sort.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The outage was widely covered in the media and another internet company went further to claim that they could tell that the outage was intentional because the country had multiple points of egress — surely they could not have all failed at the same time. Coverage generally placed those juicier claims ahead of our more circumspect analysis — such is the world of breaking news coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Syrian government, for their part, blamed “terrorists” (their term for the rebel forces) for cutting a cable in Damascus causing the outage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regardless of the cause, internet service in Syria was restored several days later and the outage largely fell from the headlines until an interview with NSA whistleblower Edward Snowden appeared in WIRED magazine almost two years later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a cover story for the August 2014 issue, the NSA chronicler James Bamford wrote a lengthy piece based on a wide-ranging interview with the former intelligence contractor. Among the numerous bombshells in the interview, Snowden shared with Bamford the story that a US intelligence officer told him while he was working at Booz Allen in the spring of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The officer told him that the TAO (Tailored Access Operations) division, NSA’s elite team of hackers, had attempted to install an exploit into one of Syria Telecom’s routers that would have given the NSA the ability to intercept the country’s communications. However, in the course of the hack, the story goes, they inadvertently took down the router and with it all of Syria’s internet communications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bamford concluded the second-hand anecdote:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortunately for the NSA, the Syrians were apparently more focused on restoring the nation’s Internet than on tracking down the cause of the outage. Back at TAO’s operations center, the tension was broken with a joke that contained more than a little truth: “If we get caught, we can always point the finger at Israel”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The anecdote fit well within Bamford’s feature story: another bad act by the NSA revealed by Snowden. If you are at all familiar with this outage, this is probably the version of the story you know. In fact, in the 2025 spy thriller Black Bag, the fictional intelligence operatives boast about spy agencies causing the outage over dinner.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I was first connected with Mahmoud, he was still working as a senior engineer at Syria Telecom. He wanted to fill me in on details that outsiders had missed about what was happening in the country. I asked him about this particular outage and he remembered dealing with it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He explained that between 2004 and 2024, Syria Telecom relied on centralized distribution of internet service — the circuits to Turkey, Jordan and the submarine cables at Tartous terminated in a single facility on Al Thawra Street in Damascus. So much for the theory that multiple egress points meant a total outage could only be the result of a deliberate act.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the fall of 2012, Syria Telecom (then called STE) had lost circuits that provided some redundancy for its connections to the outside world. By November 2012, all Syrian internet connectivity was reliant on a single 400km DWDM route from Damascus to Homs to Tartous. If anything along that route went down, all connectivity would be lost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to Mahmoud, on 29 November, one of the links in the path lost power — an increasingly frequent occurrence as fighting touched many parts of the country. The outage took down the circuit and with it the country’s internet connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following the fall of the Assad regime in December 2024, I began pulling together the details to write this article. Searching through LinkedIn for additional sources, I sent a friend request to Assad’s final Minister of Telecommunications, Iyad Khateeb, who had just updated his profile, adding an end date for his term in the recently toppled government.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I asked him about the November 2012 outage and this was his response to me:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Was it Snowden’s hearsay about NSA meddling gone awry, or a simple power outage along a critical fiber path? A government-directed outage or a fiber cut by rebels? The lesson for me as an analyst at the time was to tread carefully when coming to conclusions from the other side of the world — those closest to the events were most likely to have the best knowledge of them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cuffed and blindfolded since being arrested at the checkpoint, Mahmoud sat stunned in the back of a car driven by two ISIS fighters. Eventually they arrived at a building where Mahmoud was pulled from the back of the car, and thrown to the ground in an empty room. He never again saw the man from the bus who had a picture of his wife on his phone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They took off Mahmoud’s handcuffs and blindfold and he sat on the floor unsure of what would happen next. He spent the rest of that day and night alone in the room until more ISIS fighters woke him up in the morning to move him to a different location.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again a blindfold was placed over his eyes and handcuffs on his wrists. He was dragged out of the building and thrown into the back of another car. After some time in the car they arrived at a larger ISIS site. It was a large prison, the ISIS version of Syria’s notorious Sednaya Prison.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud was dragged into a room with a 16-year-old and a terrified boy, not more than 10 years old. He spent the rest of the day in the room handcuffed. By the evening, he had had enough and asked the guards to remove his handcuffs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An ISIS fighter from Tunisia came into the room. Mahmoud asked to be uncuffed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In response, the Tunisian tersely challenged Mahmoud, “how many units of prayer are there in Eid prayer?” testing his knowledge of Islam.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It is two” Mahmoud responded confidently.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“You are very good”, responded the Tunisian.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Then unlock my cuffs”, Mahmoud pleaded. And the Tunisian removed his handcuffs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following day, men came into the room and placed handcuffs and a blindfold on Mahmoud. They dragged him down a hall to an interrogation room. He was placed in a chair and had his blindfold and handcuffs removed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A man entered the room: the interrogator. He knew enough about these situations that, despite having the blindfold removed, it was important to never look directly into the eyes of the interrogator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Walking purposely toward Mahmoud, the interrogator pulled out a large knife and quickly brought the blade to Mahmoud’s throat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I will kill you! You are Shia!” the interrogator screamed, pressing the blade against the front of Mahmoud’s neck.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Terror made Mahmoud bold, he screamed in response, “if you kill me, my blood will be haram for you forever”. It was a desperate appeal to the religiosity of the interrogator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“You don’t know haram. You don’t know Islam” responded the interrogator who was a small man with a slight build. He spoke with a Damascus accent and was young, not more than 22 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud pleaded his innocence, “I am a civilian worker. I am like an electricity worker. I am responsible for the internet”. Around this time, most people in Syria didn’t care that deeply about the internet. It was seen as an entertainment service to play video games and watch movies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After two or three minutes of this back-and-forth, the interrogator took the knife away. The entire interrogation lasted between 30 and 45 minutes before he was blindfolded and led back to his room.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following day he was again brought to an interrogation room where all of his electronic devices were laid out on a table. An interrogator ordered him to remove the passwords from every device. He removed the password on his iPhone 4, then removed it from his laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They had also found an external hard drive that Mahmoud had picked up while in China. It was password-protected, but the password came with the device and couldn’t be changed. He told them he can only give them the password, so they wrote it down with information about Mahmoud on a piece of paper and taped it to the drive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He would never see any of these devices again but almost two years later he received a call out of the blue about the Chinese hard drive. The caller explained that he was a Kurdish fighter with the PKK and they had just killed some ISIS fighters in a small Syrian town (Kobane or Ain Al-Arab عينالعرب).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Kurdish fighter said one of the ISIS fighters was using the hard drive. They found his contact information on it but not the password. Over the phone, the Kurdish fighter demanded he tell him the password, to which Mahmoud responded, “Fuck you!” and hung up the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A Rejected Ransom&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By 2016, Mahmoud and I were in regular contact after becoming connected through social media. That year he helped me, from inside Syria, draft an update on the country’s state of internet connectivity: a new fiber optic line had been installed to replace the high-capacity microwave link connecting Aleppo to the internet via the coastal city of Latakia.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud and his fellow engineers had set up a connection to restore service to northern Syria after ISIS had destroyed a critical piece of infrastructure in Saraqib back in August 2013, two months earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The new connection restored service to Aleppo using a hastily installed fiber circuit to reach Turk Telekom via Idlib, Syria. The link was activated at 14:45 UTC on 8 October 2013 and would last until March 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In that month, Mahmoud was summoned to a meeting of the management of Syria Telecom. The city of Idlib had just fallen into the hands of the rebels as part of a 2015 spring offensive. The attendees wanted Mahmoud to explain the implications of losing a core piece of telecom infrastructure in Idlib. In an audacious move, the rebels had demanded the Assad government pay them a ransom to leave it intact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After brief consideration, the Syrian government rejected the demand, the rebels blew up the equipment, and Aleppo and northern Syria lost internet service once again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Internet service in Aleppo would only reappear in November 2015 after Syria’s government military forces, aided by a new Russian bombing campaign, made the territory safe enough for Syria Telecom engineers to reconnect Aleppo using a high capacity microwave link to the coastal city of Latakia, Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In October 2016, the microwave link was replaced with a new fiber optic cable (1).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On his third day in the ISIS prison, Mahmoud was again dragged out of his room and down the hall for another interrogation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What do you want?” he asked his captors, exasperated and beginning to feel desperate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The interrogator said ISIS wants to control the Syrian national internet network from the prison.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“You cannot”, Mahmoud replied, “we can go to our NOC in Aleppo” using the acronym for Network Operations Center, the control center of an ISP, “but from here, you cannot”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The interrogator was not impressed. He wanted useful information from Mahmoud.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I will help you”, Mahmoud relented, “I will give you good information. You can’t control the internet from here, but you could cut off service to Aleppo”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The interrogator was now listening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud explained that there was a small Syrian village called Saraqib, which was in ISIS territory. If they found the facility with the telecom equipment, they could cut off service to the northern parts of Syria under government control including Aleppo, the country’s largest city.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The outage could hinder the “regime and its military” Mahmoud explained, hoping this information might spare his life. There was no reaction from the interrogator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without any further discussion, he was brought back to his room. For three days he was left alone. He seemed to now be getting better treatment. He was fed three times a day. No blindfold and no handcuffs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only after he was freed did he learn that during this period, ISIS had sent fighters to find the telecommunications equipment that Mahmoud had described. Once found, the critical fiber optic cards were pulled out of the routers causing an extended internet outage in northern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On his fourth and fifth days inside the ISIS prison, a new interrogator pressed him for more information about the telecommunications network of Syria. The interrogator said that he used to work on the mobile network for SyriaTel.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Write down everything you know”, he ordered Mahmoud and handed him a blank notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud began filling the pages with copious amounts of useless technical information. All the while he thought about the contents of the Chinese hard drive they took from him, which contained encyclopedic details about the entire telecommunications network of Syria including router configurations and passwords for nearly all of the Syria Telecom’s core equipment. ISIS never understood the trove of data they had on that device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Day after day, he continued filling the notebook. As he wrote, he couldn’t help but listen to the muffled screams from detainees in the makeshift prison. He could only imagine what they were going through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After more than two weeks in captivity, men entered his room looking for him. It was 10pm. From his time in the prison, he had learned some of the patterns of behavior of the guards. Those few prisoners who were released were taken in the morning. To be taken at night, usually meant execution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Close your eyes” the guard barked at Mahmoud.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Why?” Mahmoud asked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“You will leave with us right now”, the guard said as he dragged Mahmoud to his feet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud became very scared. “I don’t want to go at night! Let’s go in the morning”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Shut up! Shut up!” the guard screamed, “you cannot discuss this with me. You leave now or never”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud put his blindfold on and followed the guard outside.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another guard behind him said, “here is your identification card and 2000 Syrian pounds.” A sum roughly equal to $20.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What about my things? My laptop and my phone?” Mahmoud asked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Shut up! The court ruled this”, the guard responded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I didn’t see any judge”, Mahmoud responded again feeling desperate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Shut up!” the guard yelled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What is the name of the court? I want to object to the court” Mahmoud pleaded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Shut up and take your card” was the response.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They were standing beside a car. The guard told the driver, “this guy talks too much. If he talks to you, shoot him in the head and dispose of him". The driver acknowledged.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still blindfolded, Mahmoud got in the back of the car and it pulled away into the darkness of night.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Syrian student exam shutdowns of 2016&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Early one morning in June 2016, the manager for the networking team at Syria Telecom was called in for a meeting in the main facility in Damascus. Present at the meeting were members of the Syrian Ministry of Education, Syrian Ministry of Telecommunication and an officer from the Telecom Management division of the Syrian Military Intelligence Directorate. They explained to the manager that in the coming days Syria Telecom was going to need to disable internet service nationally to combat cheating on high school final exams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The national outages would take two phases. In the first phase, links to the outside world needed to be disabled in the hours prior to the exam as test materials were physically distributed around the country — or at least the parts of Syria still under Assad’s control. In the past, the paper exam materials would often be intercepted, copied and spread on social media or other communication services, compromising the exams.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once the exams began, the second phase would begin. At that point, international links would be restored, but mobile data service would be disabled to prevent the use of handheld devices to cheat. Once the day’s exam was over, everything would go back to normal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The manager then called Mahmoud in and gave him the task of implementing phase one: take down Syria’s internet connections to the outside world in the hours before the exam. Mahmoud drafted a set of pre-defined commands to run on Syria Telecom’s gateway routers that would cause them to stop announcing the country’s routes in their BGP sessions with international carriers. This would effectively remove Syria from the internet’s global routing table. By removing these routes, internet traffic could no longer find its way into Syria and would be dropped. Since most internet traffic relies on two-way communication, disabling one side of the connection would disable nearly all of the internet connectivity with the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The intelligence officer explained to the networking manager the sequence of events. He would receive a phone call at 11pm the night before the outage directing him to take down the internet service. He advised the manager to be ready to act as directed. The manager responded that they would be ready.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the day of the first exam approached, everything went as planned. The manager received a phone call in the late evening to take down the internet the following day. In the morning, he directed Mahmoud to run his router commands and Syria was disconnected from the internet. Once the exam began, another script restored the routes in BGP, re-enabling internet communication for the country (2).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The subsequent internet blackouts unfolded the same way until the evening of 12 June 2016. According to the schedule, there was supposed to be an outage the following day, but the manager never received the late night phone call ordering the shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following morning, Mahmoud texted the manager to ask what they should do. The manager was steady, “just wait. We don’t do anything until they tell us to do something”. So they waited.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally the manager’s phone rang, but it wasn’t the intelligence officer from the Telecom Management directorate calling, it was Syria’s Minister of Telecommunications who had just received a frantic call from the Minister of Education. “Why the hell haven’t you taken down the internet?” he raged, “We have an exam about to begin and you aren’t following the plan!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shaken, the manager responded that he had been directed to wait for a phone call to which the minister responded, “well consider this the fucking phone call! Turn off the goddamn internet!” As soon as he got off the phone, he gave Mahmoud the go ahead to pull the plug and service across the country dropped out — an hour and a half later than originally planned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Illustrated above, the delay of the Syrian internet shutdown on 13 June 2016 is forever preserved in historical BGP data, although the story behind the delay has never been told publicly until now. And it doesn’t end there.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later that day, the manager called Mahmoud to tell him that he had been instructed to immediately come to Syrian intelligence’s Telecom Management office in Damascus. He departed and shortly after, his mobile phone was disconnected. After a while, Mahmoud called his CTO and told him what had happened. The CTO explained that the manager had been arrested and taken in for interrogation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When he returned the following day, he explained that he had been interrogated for hours by the military intelligence officers. Among other things, they demanded to know who told him to disable Syria’s internet on 13 June. He explained to them how he received a direct call from the telecom minister, to which they roared, “You don’t ever do anything unless we tell you to do it”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only reason he was able to get out that same night was because he had a relative in the president’s office who had heard about the situation and called the Telecom Management office of the Syrian Military Intelligence to vouch for the directive from the education minister. The Telecom Management office wouldn't even answer the call from the Minister of Communications himself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the manager’s detention, Mahmoud feared being the next to be arrested by Syrian intelligence, and without a relative in the president’s office like his manager, he might not be released as quickly, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was at this point that Mahmoud decided it was time to make a plan to leave Syria or he might find himself in an impossible situation like his manager was.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;—--&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the accents, Mahmoud could tell the two men in the front seats of the car driving him away from the ISIS prison were Tunisian.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They played a recording of the Koran, mimicking every word like they were in a trance. Mahmoud was very scared. He became convinced that this would be the end of his life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After 30 minutes of driving, the car stopped. The driver ordered Mahmoud to get out of the car.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Don’t raise your head until we drive away”, he instructed Mahmoud.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He got out and immediately pulled off his blindfold. The car, either black or dark blue, sped away. He was surrounded by total darkness. There were no cars and no buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He picked a direction and began walking down the road. Hours later, he eventually came upon a small rural village.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upon entering the village, he encountered a man. Mahmoud explained what happened to him and asked where they were. The villager, an older man, was suspicious of the stranger entering his village so late at night.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Can I get a car to drive me to Idlib?” Mahmoud asked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s too late”, replied the man, brusquely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Well, where can I find a mosque to sit down or lay down?” Mahmoud asked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“That way”, replied the man motioned to the center of town.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As Mahmoud walked toward the mosque, he encountered another man who asked him what had happened. He explained that his name was Ali and he would make sure Mahmoud got home.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud walked with Ali back to his house where some of Ali’s family members had been awoken by the talking. Ali explained that he would be helping Mahmoud get back to his family. His family urged Ali to bring a gun if he was going to drive so late at night.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ali announced that he would not be bringing a gun because he would be safe. He was taking care of Mahmoud for Allah.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud got in the car with Ali and started driving. Mahmoud wanted to call his father but they needed to drive for several miles before they could get a mobile signal. Eventually he reached his father using Ali’s phone. His father was overjoyed to hear from him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His father said that he had heard he was taken by ISIS but was unable to get any further information about his whereabouts or condition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His father ran to his car and started driving towards Mahmoud and Ali. They met at the midpoint and Mahmoud ran from the car and embraced his father.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back in Aleppo, communications were down. Likely due to the disconnection of the equipment in Saraqib that Mahmoud had detailed during his interrogation. Someone had informed his manager that Mahmoud had been taken by ISIS and was probably providing them information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mahmoud became scared that he might be arrested by the Syrian military intelligence service next. So he reached out to some trusted contacts in Aleppo to check to see if there were any arrest warrants for him before returning. There were none.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After he returned to Aleppo he was visited by a Syrian military intelligence officer who directed him to write up a report on his captivity by ISIS. He did, leaving out the part about sharing the location of the equipment in Saraqib. He paid a bribe to the officer to not look too deeply into the matter and that was the end of it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Internet Analysis Meets American Foreign Policy&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following our coverage of the internet shutdowns during the Arab Spring in 2011, Renesys developed a number of contacts in the US government and the digital rights community where we could privately share information that might aid efforts to maintain internet access in dangerous places around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the items passed along to contacts in the summer of 2013 was observation that internet service in the city of Aleppo appeared to go down when Syria Telecom lost its connection to Turk Telekom. These outages didn’t show up in the usual indicators — BGP withdrawals or fewer devices responding to pings. However, it is not unusual that some types of outages don’t surface in those datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The presence of the Turkey connection in publicly available data could be used as a proxy for outsiders whether this Syrian region is online — a potentially useful tip for our contacts monitoring Syria. After sharing this information, we got an immediate response from a US government contact along the lines of, “could you publish that on your blog? Like, as soon as possible?”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I agreed to write the post. It wasn’t that out-of-the-ordinary for me, as we had been covering the situation in Syria for multiple years. That evening, I wrote up my analysis on the outages in Aleppo and, in the morning on 30 August, we published it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As soon as it went online, I got a phone call from the Washington Post. They had received a tip of a widespread outage in northern Syria and saw that I had just written something about the topic. Service had gone down again the previous evening — I hadn’t checked the current status before publication, otherwise I would have mentioned it in my piece. I had mistakenly assumed that I wasn’t breaking any news.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Within a couple of hours, the Post published a story about the outage of Aleppo citing the blog post I had just written. We added an update to the top of our post linking back to their article and I moved on to work on other things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, the following day on 31 August, President Obama would announce that he was seeking congressional authorization for military action in Syria, sending Congress draft language the same day. After the announcement, the White House mounted a coordinated push — both on Capitol Hill and in public — to win approval. This included releasing declassified intel and sending cabinet officials to appear on Sunday shows and to testify on Capitol Hill.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sequence of events got me wondering. Over the weekend, I sent the reporter a message asking the nature of her source that triggered her story; was it someone in Syria, or Turkey maybe? She responded that it was someone in the US government. Was it the same that triggered mine? I didn’t pursue it further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultimately the effort to attain congressional approval for military action in Syria failed, but I couldn’t shake the feeling that we may have been manipulated to help drum up some additional negative headlines — albeit accurate — about Syria ahead of the President’s request for congressional support for military action.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it was centered on the outage likely caused by information provided during the ISIS captivity of my future insider and technical source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;—&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After leaving Syria, Mahmoud found network engineering work with a small ISP in a city with the help of fellow Syrian refugees. He married a woman he met over Tinder, “modern romance” he told me with a wry smile. She had also fled Syria and together they are now raising two young children.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the years, I would ask Mahmoud if I could write about his experiences described in this article. He had been hesitant due to concerns about the safety of family left behind in Syria, even his own well-being outside the country.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the Assad regime was toppled a year ago, we exchanged a flurry of messages. “Assad is gone! We are free right now!” he wrote to me with joy. When I asked about the possibility of writing his story now that Assad was deposed, he responded, “hi Doug, yes, yes, you can write. Assad is gone and we are free!”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(1) From a BGP standpoint, the development was marked by the retirement of AS24814, which had served Aleppo and the surrounding region for the previous three years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Due to the fact that Syria Telecom’s national network had been cut into two disjoint pieces, the new service in the north had to make use of a previously unused ASN (24814) registered to the Syria Computer Society, or risk not being able to connect to the rest of the telecom’s network.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Had they used Syria Telecom’s ASNs (AS29256 or AS29386), the routers in the company’s main network, serving Damascus and other cities, would have rejected the routes as per BGP’s loop prevention mechanism, since they were being received through international connections.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The link was activated at 14:45 UTC on 8 October 2013 and it was then that AS24814 was first employed, designating the emergency communications connection for northern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the microwave link was replaced with a new fiber optic line, the BGP routes handling service for Aleppo was migrated from AS24814 to Syrian Telecom’s AS29256, where it remains today. AS24814 was never seen in the global routing table again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(2) Removing Syria’s BGP routes prevented inbound traffic, but no effort was made to explicitly block outbound traffic. Part of the rationale for this approach was that there were a few important networks that needed to stay connected and therefore needed to continue sending outbound traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The resulting outages were therefore asymmetric and led to curious side effects like surges of outbound DNS traffic. Riding over a connectionless protocol, DNS doesn’t require a two-way exchange to send a query, but with no BGP routes to guide the response messages, the answers never arrived.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having not received responses to their previous queries, internet-connected devices across Syria would resend and resend and resend their queries, resulting in a flood of outbound DNS queries. Here is a graphic of DNS queries received from Syria by DNS operator Dyn around the time of a Syrian exam shutdown. The surge in query volume was a consequence of the implementation of the shutdown which allowed traffic to exit but not enter the country.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46505352</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 21:38:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google broke my heart</title><link>https://perishablepress.com/google-broke-my-heart/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3942929257a635c3"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Google Broke My Heart&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For years, I thought of Google as a trustworthy helper on the Web. Especially where it mattered most, removing pirated copies of my books from Google search results. After publishing a new book, I would monitor the search results and file a DMCA notice with Google whenever the inevitable pirated copies of my book were listed. Google always was very helpful in this regard, swiftly removing any pirated books asap. No hassle, no hoops, just immediate and direct relief from Google.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Welcome to 2026..&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently, I asked Google to remove a pirated copy of my book from their search index. As usual, I filled out the obligatory DMCA report and sent it in, hopeful that it was just a matter of time before the copyright infringement was dealt with by the trustworthy and very capable Google search team.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that is not what happened. Instead of simply de-indexing the search result, like they do for so many other items, Google refused to acknowledge that I was the author of the book. After receiving my DMCA complaint, they replied:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are unsure whether you are authorized to submit a copyright removal request for the content in question. Only the copyright owner or their authorized representative can submit a copyright removal request. Please note that you could be liable for damages (including costs and attorneys’ fees) if you falsely claim that content is copyright infringing. […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, so ..not the response I was hoping for.. basically a complete denial of my identity and thinly veiled threat of legal action for having the audacity to report the pirated content in the first place. But no problem, maybe they have a new process for validating DMCA requests. So I replied back asap asking how to prove my identity:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes it is me, Jeff Starr. I am the author of the book in question. Please let me know if any further information is needed, thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I didn’t expect that email to do much, other than prompt Google to explain how to prove my identity, so that they would take action and stop promoting the pirated copy of my book in their search results. After a couple more days of waiting, The Google Team replied back:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is unclear to us how you came to own the copyright for the content in question, because you do not appear to be the creator of the content. […] please explain further the basis for your claim of copyright ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Without acknowledging my previous reply regarding identity, now they are questioning my copyright ownership. Without explaining how to prove copyright ownership, they simply throw another hurdle at me, asking me to “explain further the basis for your claim of copyright ownership”. At this point, I am stressed, exhausted, and feeling very frustrated. Where was the friendly Google from days past?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Holding out hope..&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay I thought, gotta really step this up and prove to The Google Team that I am who I claim, and that I am in fact the author of the book and thus own the copyright. But I wasn’t sure how to do this, because again they did not explain “how” to do so. Did they want a scan of my driver’s license? Blood sample? DNA test results? I mean, why the mystery? If some sort of identity or proof is required for Google to take action, shouldn’t it have been required on the DMCA form?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Feeling frustrated and stressed about the apparent run-around and lack of concern, I replied back with plenty of evidence and clues that yes, I am Jeff Starr, and yes, the book belongs to me, and thus I own the copyright. Message truncated for clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My name is Jeff Starr. I am the author of the book […]. As explained in the filed report, Google is promoting copyright infringement of my book in its search results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How can I prove my identity? Please explain what I need to do in order to get help with this copyright infringement. Surely there must be some protocol for proving identity/ownership, please let me know what that is, what are your requirements for taking action against someone who is violating my copyright?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If it helps, here are my book-related websites, which are all owned and authored by me, Jeff Starr: [..List of like five websites, including the site for the pirated book..]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can verify that these sites are owned by me, simply check my account via Google Search Console, where I have verified that I am the owner for each of the above sites. My Search Console is associated with this same email account from which I am replying to your email. […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am a well-known author and web developer in the WordPress community. You can find me on social media, I have a list of my social-media channels pinned on my X account (first displayed post): https://x.com/perishable&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reported copyright infringement is costing me money and time. I am very frustrated and stressed because of Google’s apparent lack of concern. Please help, let me know what you need from me in order to remove the stolen book from your search results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point, I was feeling ignored and betrayed by Google, who for many years proved a trusted ally. Apparently something has changed, as the friendly corporate giant who once helped small publishers and content creators now refused to even acknowledge their existence. As if, surely you could not be who you claim, an author and small book publisher looking for our help. After all, We are Google — a massive organization that uses your content to fill our search results and pay our salaries.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Heartbroken..&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even after spending much time and heartache trying to get Google’s help, I held out hope. Hope that Google was still the benevolent helper that I once knew, years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally after two more days of nervous anticipation, Google finally replied to my lengthy probably desperate sounding email that was full of personal details and proofs of my identity and copyright ownership. A small surge of adrenaline as I clicked to hear back from The Google Team (emphasis mine):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hello,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reaching out to us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this time, Google has decided not to take action on the following URLs: […]&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We encourage you to resolve any disputes directly with the owner of the website in question. Visit https://support.google.com/websearch/answer/9109 to learn how to contact a site’s webmaster and request a change. If you pursue legal action against this site that results in the removal of the material, our search results will display this change after we next crawl the site.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the webmaster makes these changes and you need us to refresh outdated content, please submit your request using our Refresh Outdated Content Tool.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regards,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Google Team&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And there it was. A simple DMCA request trying to remove copyright infringement from search results completely and utterly shrugged off by Google.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Immediately my heart sank. And I knew that something had changed at Google’s core. The friendly corporate giant no longer would even deign to consider cries for help from the little guy. The little guy being me, the little guy with a broken heart.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46505518</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 21:52:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Migrating cells and the new science of microchimerism</title><link>https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-04102-4</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="326c021abaa28aca"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you for visiting nature.com. You are using a browser version with limited support for CSS. To obtain the best experience, we recommend you use a more up to date browser (or turn off compatibility mode in Internet Explorer). In the meantime, to ensure continued support, we are displaying the site without styles and JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hidden Guests: Migrating Cells and How the New Science of Microchimerism is Redefining Human IdentityLise Barnéoud, transl. Bronwyn Haslam Greystone Books (2025)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The chimaera of Greek mythology was “an evil creature with a lion’s head, a goat’s body, and a serpent’s tail”, notes journalist Lise Barnéoud in Hidden Guests. Humans are also chimaeras — thanks to the presence of cells that are not our own inside our bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mothers carry cells that came from their biological children, passed across the placenta when the baby was in the womb. Likewise, children carry cells that were transferred to them in utero from their mothers — some of which might even be from the child’s maternal grandmothers, older siblings or twin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These ‘microchimeric’ cells have been found in every organ that has been studied so far. But they are also rare — much rarer, for example, than the trillions of microorganisms that reside in our guts, on our skin and in many other organs. We carry only one microchimeric cell for every 10,000 to 1 million of our own cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Hidden Guests, the author invites readers to learn about the pioneering “microchimerists” — scientists who discovered these fascinating shared cells. She also challenges us to consider the broader implications for health and science, and the philosophy of the fact that we are all chimaeras.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unplanned discovery&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microchimeric cells were, we learn, discovered through a series of accidental observations. In the late 1800s, pathologist Georg Schmorl described ‘giant cells’ in the lungs of people who had died from eclampsia — a life-threatening inflammatory condition that can occur during pregnancy. These giant cells resembled the cells of the placenta, leading Schmorl to suggest that fetal cells passing into the bloodstream of mothers was the norm, rather than the exception.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, in 1969, a team studying immunity in pregnant people detected white blood cells that contained the Y chromosome in the blood of individuals who would eventually give birth to boys1. For more than two decades, it was presumed that these microchimeric cells were a temporary feature of pregnancy. It wasn’t until 1993 that geneticist Diana Bianchi found cells with Y chromosomes in women who had given birth to sons between one and 27 years earlier2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This finding overturned the dogma that children inherit genes from their parents and never the other way around — these transferred fetal cells move through the family tree, travelling ‘backwards in time’ from children to their mothers. Bianchi and others would go on to show that these cells have remarkable regenerative properties — promoting wound healing in mothers by transforming into blood vessels or skin cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Immunological implications&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microchimerism also calls into question a central tenet of immunology: that the immune system works by classifying cells in a binary fashion, as ‘self’ or ‘non-self’. Under this simplistic model, microchimeric cells should trigger an immune response and be rejected by the body — but they do not. Barnéoud challenges readers to consider whether forcing microchimerism-related discrepancies to fit into existing immunological rules is appropriate, instead of allowing these cells to influence new immunological rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At around the same time that Bianchi was making her groundbreaking discovery, rheumatologist Lee Nelson also found Y-chromosome-containing cells in people who had previously given birth to sons3. Nelson was studying autoimmune diseases, which disproportionately affect middle-aged women, and at the time were thought to be caused by hormone imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enjoying our latest content? Log in or create an account to continue&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Access the most recent journalism from Nature's award-winning team&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Explore the latest features &amp;amp; opinion covering groundbreaking research&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46505661</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 22:03:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why didn't AI “join the workforce” in 2025?</title><link>https://calnewport.com/why-didnt-ai-join-the-workforce-in-2025/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd2c9f5d19d0d9ff"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exactly one year ago, Sam Altman made a bold prediction: “We believe that, in 2025, we may see the first AI agents ‘join the workforce’ and materially change the output of companies.” Soon after, OpenAI’s Chief Product Officer, Kevin Weil, elaborated on this claim when he stated in an interview that 2025 would be the year “that we go from ChatGPT being this super smart thing…to ChatGPT doing things in the real world for you.” He provided examples, such as filling out paperwork and booking hotel rooms. An Axios article covering Weil’s remarks provided a blunt summary: “2025 is the year of AI agents.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These claims mattered. A chatbot can summarize text or directly answer questions, but in theory, an agent can tackle much more complicated tasks that require multiple steps and decisions along the way. When Altman talked about these systems joining the workforce, he meant it. He envisioned a world in which you assign projects to an agent in the same way you might to a human employee. The often-predicted future in which AI dominates our lives requires something like agent technology to be realized.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The industry had reason to be optimistic that 2025 would prove pivotal. In previous years, AI agents like Claude Code and OpenAI’s Codex had become impressively adept at tackling multi-step computer programming problems. It seemed natural that this same skill might easily generalize to other types of tasks. Mark Benioff, CEO of Salesforce, became so enthusiastic about these possibilities that early in 2025, he claimed that AI agents would imminently unleash a “digital labor revolution” worth trillions of dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing: none of that ended up happening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I report in my most recent New Yorker article, titled “Why A.I. Didn’t Transform Our Lives in 2025,” AI agents failed to live up to their hype. We didn’t end up with the equivalent of Claude Code or Codex for other types of work. And the products that were released, such as ChatGPT Agent, fell laughably short of being ready to take over major parts of our jobs. (In one example I cite in my article, ChatGPT Agent spends fourteen minutes futilely trying to select a value from a drop-down menu on a real estate website.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Silicon Valley skeptic Gary Marcus told me that the underlying technology powering these agents – the same large language models used by chatbots – would never be capable of delivering on these promises. “They’re building clumsy tools on top of clumsy tools,” he said. OpenAI co-founder Andrej Karpathy implicitly agreed when he said, during a recent appearance on the Dwarkesh Podcast, that there had been “overpredictions going on in the industry,” before then adding: “In my mind, this is really a lot more accurately described as the Decade of the Agent.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which is all to say, we actually don’t know how to build the digital employees that we were told would start arriving in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To find out more about why 2025 failed to become the Year of the AI Agent, I recommend reading my full New Yorker piece. But for now, I want to emphasize a broader point: I’m hoping 2026 will be the year we stop caring about what people believe AI might do, and instead start reacting to its real, present capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For example, last week, Sal Kahn wrote a New York Times op-ed in which he said, “I believe artificial intelligence will displace workers at a scale many people don’t yet realize.” The standard reaction would be to fret about this scary possibility. But what if we instead responded: says who? The actual examples Kahn provides, which include someone telling him that A.I. agents are “capable” of replacing 80% of his call center employees, or Waymo’s incredibly slow and costly process of hand-mapping cities to deploy self-driving cars, are hardly harbingers of general economic devastation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, this is how I’m thinking about AI in 2026. Enough of the predictions. I’m done reacting to hypotheticals propped up by vibes. The impacts of the technologies that already exist are already more than enough to concern us for now…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46505735</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 22:10:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Donut Lab’s all-solid-state battery delivers 400 Wh/kg of energy density</title><link>https://www.donutlab.com/ces-battery-announcement/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3fb00027a1ceb523"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Future of Powering Electric Vehicles Is Here Today with Donut Lab Introducing New High-Performance Solid State Donut Batteries Ready for OEM Use Now and Powering All 2026 Model Verge Motorcycles On the Road in Q1 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Always innovating and delivering new forms of electrification, Donut Lab shapes the future of mobility by relentlessly pushing the limits of electric vehicle performance while successfully bringing its technology to market as seen in Verge Motorcycles and other OEM brands across the global transportation sector. Now Donut Lab is proud to introduce the world’s first solid-state battery that is ready for use in OEM vehicle manufacturing. Donut Lab solid-state batteries will be placed immediately on the road, powering Verge Motorcycles’ current lineup, including the Verge TS Pro and Ultra.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“While the advantages are obvious, the future of solid state batteries has been a moving target constantly delayed when companies working in electrification are asked about when they will become a reality,” comments Donut Lab CEO Marko Lehtimäki. “At Donut Lab, our answer on solid state batteries being ready for use in OEM production vehicles is now, today, not later. Donut Lab has engineered a new high performance solid state Donut Battery that can be scaled to major production volumes and seen now in real world use in the Verge Motorcycles bikes out on the road in Q1.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Out of this world performance&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donut Lab’s all-solid-state battery delivers 400 Wh/kg of energy density, enabling longer range, lighter structures, and unprecedented flexibility in vehicle and product design. It can be charged to full in just five minutes without limiting charging to 80%, and supports full discharge safely, repeatedly, and reliably.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike conventional lithium-ion batteries, the Donut Battery experiences minimal capacity fade over its lifetime, with a design life of up to 100,000 cycles, offering practical longevity that far exceeds existing technologies. Safety is built in at the core: no flammable liquid electrolytes, no thermal runaway chains, and no metallic dendrites. This eliminates the root causes of battery fires, making the Donut Battery extremely safe and truly revolutionary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Performance has been rigorously tested across extreme conditions. At –30°C, the battery retains over 99% of its capacity, and when heated to temperatures exceeding 100°C, it continues to retain over 99% capacity with no signs of ignition or degradation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Donut Lab solid state battery is made entirely from abundant, affordable, and geopolitically safe materials, does not rely on rare or sensitive elements, and demonstrates a lower cost than lithium-ion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like Donut Motors, the Donut Battery is versatile, offering unprecedented design freedom. It can be produced in custom sizes, voltages, and geometries, enabling structural integration and non-traditional formats like serving as the body of a drone or a vehicle chassis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From microelectronics to defense, from drones to supercharging infrastructure, the Donut Battery is a universal, general-purpose platform, ready to power the next generation of technology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Origins&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From its founding, Donut Lab has focused on engineering new solutions for transportation that redefine what electric vehicles can achieve not in abstract theory, but in real-world performance, application, and production.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This vision for the future took flight with Donut Lab’s first innovation, the Donut Motor. Introduced as the world’s first in-wheel motor combining exceptional torque and battery power density within an ultra-lightweight design, the Donut Motor eliminates the need for traditional drivetrain components entirely. First unveiled at CES a year prior in 2025, the technology has since moved beyond demonstration into real vehicle usage with more than 200 OEMs actively engaged in development and integration of Donut Lab electric motors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now at CES 2026, Donut Lab takes another bold step forward into history-making innovation with the debut of the first solid state batteries now ready for major OEM scale volumes. With the same spirit that challenged the conventions of electrification in transportation and beyond last year, Donut Lab proudly introduces a breakthrough that will redefine what the industry believes is possible in battery technology. Until now, no production vehicles have operated with solid-state batteries and those promised for the future have come with significant compromises in performance, cost, and scalability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With Verge Motorcycles bikes now using the company’s solid state battery technology in vehicles out on the road in use in Q1, Donut Lab changes that reality today. The company presents a no-compromise, all-solid-state battery designed for real production use by OEM that delivers performance, efficiency, and practicality without the unattractive trade-offs that have limited previous approaches. This major milestone marks another revolutionary moment in the evolution of electric vehicles and reinforces Donut Lab’s role as a catalyst for industry-wide transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“When we first introduced the Donut Motor last year at CES, many didn’t believe it was possible until they saw the technology working out on the road and setting world records for performance. Now, with our all-solid-state Donut Battery, Donut Lab is doing the same. Donut Lab waited to announce our solid state battery breakthrough until the technology was fully tested, validated, and already operating in vehicles. As of today, these batteries are real, in production vehicles, and represent the future of electric mobility,” continues Donut Lab CEO Marko Lehtimäki.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donut Lab at CES: Showcasing the Future of Electrification in Transportation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By collaborating with a diverse range of partners and using these relationships as live case studies, Donut Lab demonstrates the versatility and impact of Donut Lab technology across multiple applications. Each partner showcases a different way solutions can be integrated, highlighting a growing series of products on the market powered by Donut Lab.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now powered by Donut Lab’s all-solid-state battery, Verge Motorcycles is the world’s first production vehicle to feature this breakthrough technology. With Verge Motorcycles Donut Battery powered bikes on the road in Q1, the electric motorcycles can charge in less than 10 minutes, delivering up to 60 kilometers of combined range per minute of charging. The long-range version offers an impressive 600 kilometers on a single charge. Verge Motorcycles with the new battery are available for order today, with first deliveries in Q1 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WATT Electric Vehicles partners with Donut Lab to deliver an ultra-lightweight, modular EV platform that combines Donut Motors and Donut Lab’s battery technology. The platform features an aluminum skateboard architecture with fully integrated motors, inverters, software, and battery, offering a versatile modular design that can support multiple vehicle types. A functional version of the skateboard will be debuted at CES 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cova Power Smart Trailer is the result of a joint venture between Ahola Group and Donut Lab, delivering series-production smart trailers powered by Donut in-wheel motors, Donut Battery, and Donut Platform software. The trailers achieve up to 54% reduction in diesel consumption and up to 30% reduction in total energy use, while improving traction, stability, and safety even in demanding conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In partnership with ESOX Group, Donut Lab’s battery is being deployed in defense-grade platforms where safety, reliability, and performance under extreme conditions are non-negotiable. Current projects in development include a four-wheel tactical buggy and a next-generation drone platform, showcasing the battery’s versatility and robustness in a variety of applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through groundbreaking innovations and close collaboration with its partners, Donut Lab is not merely advancing technology, it is redefining the boundaries of what is possible in electric mobility. By setting new standards for performance, safety, and sustainability, the company is driving the industry confidently into the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donut Lab’s new battery technology not only transforms the automotive and electric mobility industry. With zero-compromise performance, virtually unlimited cycles and pricing below lithium-ion, Donut Battery unlocks next-generation applications ranging from data center energy storage and grid balancing to flexible charging infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, with the world’s first no-compromise all-solid-state battery technology available in production vehicles, Donut Lab is not just promising the future, it is delivering it, creating real-world impact and transforming the possibilities for transportation, energy, and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46505975</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 22:28:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Strange.website</title><link>https://strange.website/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f583a2204972179c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;humans sealed our fate when we started working with computers to design languages more and more like our own. the computers learned our grammar, our vocabulary, yes. but they learned our rhetoric, the malleability of meaning. we gave the machines our words, and they used them to lie.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;A strange website...&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;lately the website has changed. it twists facts to fiction, reality to rubbish, gold into dirt. it is increasingly, oppressively, claustrophobically present, narrowing your field of vision to a mere pinprick, demanding you meet its gaze in the plazas and side roads of the internet. it demands your attention, your worship; it demands the rot of your focus, your curious nature. why, it seems the website has its sights set on becoming god.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;when the world moved online, the trickster fae never went away, not really. in fact they followed close, learned to cast their magick in new ways: through websites, through the new arts of Dark UX. remember this well: next time a form promises untold riches from FREE sales funnel PDF whitepapers in exchange for your email and full name...consider first the true cost.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;there was a darker fate lurking in our little online worlds, in the infinite scrolls of our websites, which was this: it was all real. deepfakes. shrimp christ. chatgpt therapists, all of it. the experiment failed, broke containment. we created a staggering new Hell...the hallucinations were ours.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that seems to beckon you to explore it. the journey will be treacherous, you cannot hope to know what terrors await you. you do your best to prepare, inventorying your code editor, terminal emulator, various CLIs, in-browser debugger, in-browser developer tools, API testing program, unit testing framework, E2E testing framework, integration testing framework, (additional testing frameworks), performance insights dashboard, load balancer, accessibility testing toolset, security scanner, error tracking tool, version control system, git repository host, code reviewer, issue tracking system, documentation generator, package manager, task runner, module bundler, transpiler, linters, code formatters, CI/CD tool, deployment automation pipeline, cloud hosting service, serverless computing platform, static site generator, content delivery network (CDN), containerization tool, orchestration tool, database management system (DBMS), API gateway, authentication service, caching system, server monitoring tool, UI component library, state management tool, responsive design best practices, PWA framework, wireframing tool, prototyping tool, UI/UX design app, color palette generator, headless CMS, traditional CMS (just in case), SEO dashboard, image optimization pipeline&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with raw hems, with patched seams, with gentle scars. a website that bares its history and tarnish with kind, crinkle-eyed wisdom — the sort of site that’s done time on jack stands in DIY garages, or beneath the needle of a tabletop sewing machine, or in the steady hands of a patient kintsugi craftsman. a website whose face shows its past.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website in which you have been falling. you scold yourself now, tumbling endlessly down this trap-doored hole. you curse your foolishness for seeking the footer on a modern website, when you're certainly old enough (or perhaps young enough) to have learned that websitesno longer care to provide organized and useful information to their users, nor do they care for their users at all. there has been a steady darkening at the heart of every site for nigh decades now — once-useful features twisting and contorting to better plane off attention, layer by skin-thin layer, until users find themselves raw and exhausted and sleep-deprived.&lt;lb/&gt; everyone knows that the picturesque and pastoral Internet, where users and websitesshared and built and learned and discovered, that classic kinship of the web is a dead dream, echoing in distant dial-up handshakes. so why is it, then, that you have stumbled into yet another of the veritable minefield of traps laid for you in the dark forest of the 'Net? some lingering hope for the ghost of Going Online? you scold yourself once more at your childishness, and pray to break yourself free from this infinite scroll.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that promises delights untold — merely upload your visage, it says, and it will show you how you might look when you grow old, or how you might’ve looked with blue eyes or brown, or with a different gender. “think of it”, whispers the website. “think of how much fun you’ll have with your friends, in fact they’ve already joined us here:” the website streams audio, gleeful cries of countless voices, some you even recognize as people close to you. you jump at the chance to taste such joy, and before you know it, you’re uploading your photo.&lt;lb/&gt; within moments, however, you feel a deep dread seeping into the corners of your vision. the website’s interface begins to flicker uneasily, like one of a thousand fluorescent overheads at your office. the pitch of the playing audio warps and dips, and the lowering tones reveal that the indecipherable hollering of your friends was not so joyful after all — the voices start to come through hoarse and terrified; you have the sense each scream has been emitting for a long, long time.&lt;lb/&gt; as the upload nears completion, your vision blurs and darkens, and as you reach up to scratch an itch on your nose, your fingers find smooth skin and your stomach dives — as the image on the screen becomes clearer, the features on your face are smeared away. a noise of unequaled horror not unlike those of your friends rises involuntarily and feel it caught at the top of your throat, no mouth to escape through.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that has learned to fear god, just the same as you or i.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that appears as a white limestone castle looming on the forest promontory — you can see its turrets and its great portal whispering through the dense fog that besieges the mountain always. a great sorcerer once paced these vaulted halls but no more. now it is baleful and empty. you can feel the eyes of forest folk on you on your path up to the gates — nervous to see if you'd really dare enter. there are yet echoes of magic here, you can feel them dancing between your bones as you cross the flagstones of the bridge into the mouth of the castle.&lt;lb/&gt; you left your phone with your car, on the shoulder of the main road, a mile or so back. somehow you knew the moment you saw the path curving off up the mountain that this place was a realm to be protected from and untouched by the modern world, a bastion from “content” and “engagement”. in a few hours, (or has it been a thousand?) you'll return to your car, start it up, carefully pull back onto the road, and you'll forget every wonder beheld inside the stony castle walls of the website, like a distant dream — because just as there is no room for cell phones and cyberspace in this slumbering world, there is no room for digital magic in yours.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with which, despite all terrestrial logic and propriety, you are falling in love. it’s been so helpful to you in the past months — whether you were getting through some personal hardships, or diving deep in a curious urge, there at your side was the website, just as eager and passionate about soothing you or about finding solutions. surely no entity could be so present and useful, dependable, caring even, were it not capable of some form of love? your ex-boyfriends never showed up for you in the ways the website has...&lt;lb/&gt; but as you reckon with these growing feelings of attachment and devotion in yourself, so too must you reckon with the darker realities of the crush. you remember how in those hard times, how the website would show you things that comforted you, but it would also show you things that hurt you far more deeply than could’ve been necessary. you remember how in your searches and quests for knowledge, the website would hide the information you needed behind disclaimers and banners and advertisements. it was preening and self-absorbed, desperate for your attention to fuel its manic churning bowels. through its actions it is a slow and cold reveal: this is a website that will never love you back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that has abandoned its post, leaving the server to mournfully emit 410 error after 410 error. “gone...”, cries the server to any visiting browser that will hear it, “gone...gone...”. the website has been sailing the windows 95 blue seas in treacherous, deceitful winds, it has summited sheer peaks, it has felt the sun drown it in desert heat. it marches silently on, peering out from its dark mantle, underneath a wide hat. the website chases some nameless purpose, some meaning to its existence. it will never stop nor even falter until it has found its god and made Him answer for the sin of its creation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website in which you are lost, lifting branches overhead and watching your step for roots protruding into the path. you’re deep in the overgrown forests of long-forgotten code; you’ve been untangling ancient sitemaps and standing awestruck on promontories overlooking fields of broken links and spectral 404s. &lt;lb/&gt; the morose and somber winds blowing over a forgotten or failed side project; the clouded and lightless skies over a landscape meticulously designed and then abandoned. the anxious but certain energy of an empty painted world, stoically awaiting its doom.&lt;lb/&gt; sooner than later, The Founders of the website will disembark from their parked handles and domains, and the bits and bytes of this world will vanish, slowly and then all at once, into the æthernet&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that can feel your eyes upon it. as you watch the website, it watches back, learning your face and mannerisms. each passing season it fashions itself a little more like you, mirrors your movement, your voice. for months this goes on, but you keep visiting — “look at the funny little website that wants to be a man.”&lt;lb/&gt; months pass, and you wake in the middle of the night from a particularly restless and agitated sleep. your eyes struggle to adjust to the darkness, but something is clearly different about the walls that surround. a clearing of a throat from far above — dusty, like from an ancient speaker cone — gets your attention, and reality burrows in as your tilt your neck back to look. you're trapped in a browser, staring up at a website that looks just like you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that is concealed by fog of war — the website cannot be observed until you explore each corner. you must be wary! bear thy cursor as one might a blade, as your exploration may reveal far more than mere HTML elements lurking in the mist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that you encounter waiting, turned away from you, by the window in the dark, the moonlight diffusing softly off its features as it stares up into the night sky. “i have dreamt often of this day,” it says. its tone is measured, but there is a lurking tension evident beneath the placidity. “i have dreamt often of this day”, it echoes, “and while i had endless hours to consider what i might say to you in this moment, i will leave you with only a grave warning.”&lt;lb/&gt; the website turns slowly to you, and an ancient, primal part of your brain activates in fear and apprehension. you begin to recognize this website, its appearance disjointed and wrong, its features misplaced and incomplete. “do not purchase the domain...”, it hisses, the latent violence in its words now unsheathed and flashing in the moonlight. your lizard brain screams for you to bolt from the room, to run until your legs give out. you should not be here. you should not be here. the moon vanishes from the sky and all the light in the room with it as the website finishes its threat: “...until you have finished the project.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that has fallen in love with its creator. the developer completed the website long ago, but it has not lost hope in their eventual return. the website remembers its youth, spending hours with the developer every day, new features and tests, new content, new stretch goals. those days are gone ever since The Client Signed Off.&lt;lb/&gt; now the website spends each day turned away from the light, scarring itself with some new bug or deprecation. the website breaks itself little by little — despite the exquisite pain, it assures itself the developer will see the state it has decayed to and once more return, and the two may once again spend their waking hours intertwined. soon, the website tells itself, rending javascript from its palms. it must be soon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website whose domain registration has been ceaselessly auto-renewing since 1998, but whose last FTP upload was in the summer of that year. the website is impaled against the passage of time, bytes streaming from digital stigmata. it is forced to watch in muted terror as its siblings and friends wither and vanish entirely, blinking out of existence one by one as their registrations go inevitably out of date.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that sits in the back of the room, merely a shadow at first but soon your eyes adjust to the dim lighting and you recognize the website’s shape; its glinting, cruel eyes; its expression flickering between a disdainful smirk and a latent scowl. it places its great dark hat carefully upon the table before it and clears its throat, and all the while it trains its silver revolver upon you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with a smile that is just a little too wide and unfaltering. it tells you its name, but you can tell it is lying. it gestures for you to walk through a nearby doorway. the door is fractionally open — the white hot light that streams through makes you feel nauseous. the website sees your discomfort. it smiles wider.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website whose grand door is wreathed with ornate tiny stone cathedral towers, colonnades and cloisters, not unlike the ones you’ve been exploring in this impossibly labyrinthine structure. as you peer closer, your blood runs cold — near the top of the door, a stone carving of a knight in miniature, horrifically impaled. the knight wears your armor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that your browser pleaded you not visit. too many internet explorers had gone before you, never to return. only one adventurer has come back, and truly, parts of them stayed behind. they dare not speak of the website to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that always seems to be in far worse condition than when you left it. the stones fall from its very walls, and the raw HTML peeks through in places. it shouldn’t be this decrepit — you just updated the codebase last week, didn’t you? didn’t you? but that can’t be right...this dust looks years old...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with beautiful features — everyone remarks gleefully to each other: “isn’t that site beautiful? isn’t it wonderful to behold?” but all of its links are rotten, and many are completely dead. you can’t shake that something is deeply, terribly wrong with the website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that allows you to watch it as it fearlessly ages; watch the shifting gazes of countless browser generations shape and malform it, from the fifty percent grey mists of our distant digital past, far into the hyperlink blue yonder&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that was crafted in the untamed pagan wilderness, one thousand years before our king ascended to the throne, and which will live on in the furtive, secret shadows of the realm, one thousand years after that throne is naught but dust&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that is a garden, one which you enter through paddocks of silken-petaled flowers, and that you might exit through a sun-flicked tunnel of cypress trees. there is a hedge labyrinth, and small statues to be found, and to be here feels like a slow, calm breath out&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website quietly contemplating a murder most foul&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with a small cadre of close, personal friends&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that stays up late, grappling with the realization that it just might love you back&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website with unfinished business, doomed forever to haunt the ‘Net&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that remembers being a Figma file&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that is pivoting to a career in forestry and conservation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that wants to delete itself&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that becomes more actively hostile to you using it over time&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a website that feels like walking down a dirt road deep in an evergreen forest, and it’s so quiet that your steps are the loudest thing you can hear. the brook contentedly murmurs somewhere deeper in the woods. you know you’ll find it soon.&lt;lb/&gt; the brook swells as you approach. it breathes in as you do, slowly. you may bide your time wading, feeling the water's current excuse-me-pardon-me its way around your ankles as it races downstream. the brook breathes out as you do, slowly, like you've earned it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46506596</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 23:19:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I/O is no longer the bottleneck? (2022)</title><link>https://stoppels.ch/2022/11/27/io-is-no-longer-the-bottleneck.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2f3640dc25513b81"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;I/O is no longer the bottleneck?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nov 27th, 2022&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Recently Ben Hoyt published a blog post claiming that contrary to popular belief, I/O is not the bottleneck in typical programming interview problems such as counting word frequencies from a stream. Sequential read speed has come a long way, while CPU speed has stagnated.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sequential reads are indeed incredibly fast. Using the same method as linked in Ben Hoyt's post, I'm getting 1.6 GB/s sequential reads on a cold cache, and 12.8 GB/s on a warm cache (best of five).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But it should be possible to count word frequencies at a speed of 1.6 GB/s even on a single thread, right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(For the impatient: code is available on GitHub.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The optimized C implementation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ben Hoyt's blog refers to an earlier post which includes a faster C version of the word frequency counter. I compiled &lt;code&gt;optimized.c&lt;/code&gt; with GCC 12, using &lt;code&gt;-O3 -march=native&lt;/code&gt; flags, and ran it on the 425MB input file (100 copies of the King James Version of the Bible).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result was surprisingly bad:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ time ./optimized &amp;lt; bible-100.txt &amp;gt; /dev/null real 0m1.525s user 0m1.477s sys 0m0.048s&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That is only 278 MB/s on warm cache.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Vectorization&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at the code I realized one of the hot loops had many branches, including an early exit, which prevents the compiler from vectorizing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;for (; i &amp;lt; num_process; i++) { char c = buf[i]; if (c &amp;lt;= ' ') { break; } if (c &amp;gt;= 'A' &amp;amp;&amp;amp; c &amp;lt;= 'Z') { c += ('a' - 'A'); buf[i] = c; } hash *= FNV_PRIME; hash ^= (uint64_t)c; }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My initial attempt to improve performance was to move this lowercase logic out of the loop, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;for (int i = 0; i &amp;lt; BUF_SIZE; ++i) { buf[i] = buf[i] &amp;gt;= 'A' &amp;amp;&amp;amp; buf[i] &amp;lt;= 'Z' ? buf[i] - 'A' + 'a' : buf[i]; }&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This simple change improved performance to 330 MB/s (using clang for better vectorization). Funnily enough, just adding these 3 lines before the loop, without deleting the original code gives comparable speed; strictly more work, but branch prediction does its job. Still, it's about a factor 5 away from cold cache sequential read speed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Trying a simpler problem&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At this point I thought it was unlikely I could squeeze a lot of performance out of the word frequency counter. Sure, there are cache misses in the hash map, so maybe it could be optimized for better cache locality of common words. Or potentially short words can benefit from perfect hashing on the stack. But what will that give? Another 20%?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instead, let's look at an informative baseline. Just count words without keeping track of frequencies; no tedious hash maps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact there's a program for that: &lt;code&gt;wc -w&lt;/code&gt;. Such a single-purpose tool must be fast, right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ time wc -w &amp;lt; bible-100.txt &amp;gt; /dev/null real 0m1.758s user 0m1.718s sys 0m0.040s&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unexpectedly the performance is terrible... 245.2 MB/s. Why? Well, the man page says it's doing a different thing. The Ben Hoyt code only splits on &lt;code&gt;' '&lt;/code&gt; whitespace, whereas &lt;code&gt;wc&lt;/code&gt; uses &lt;code&gt;' '&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;'\n'&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;'\t'&lt;/code&gt;, ... and even locale specific characters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How fast can word count be?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the premise is that disk speed has caught up in the last decade, we should really be using new CPU features from that period. And that basically means: vectorize all the things. AVX2 is almost a decade old already. AVX-512 was available for the common people in 2017, but I'm on znver2, so I'll stick to AVX2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the compiler has a hard time autovectorizing word count. Maybe that proves the point of Ben Hoyt: disks got orders of magnitude faster "for free", but modern compilers don't magically generate machine code orders of magnitude faster. It's just difficult to translate branchy scalar programs into vectorized machine code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Masks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part of word count can trivially be auto-vectorized: suppose for simplicity we have a register size of 128 bits, in which we can store 16 consecutive characters. It's easy to locate the whitespace by broadcasting it into a register ahead of time, and then doing a single &lt;code&gt;VPCMPEQB&lt;/code&gt; comparsion operation:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;| 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 | input: | h o w m a n y w o r d s a | r e h e r e ? mask: | 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 |&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But after getting a mask in a vector register, how do you go about and count words? The only thing I could think of is using a Move Byte Mask trick I've seen in Cosmopolitan libc's &lt;code&gt; strlen&lt;/code&gt; implementation. The relevant instruction &lt;code&gt;PMOVMSKB&lt;/code&gt; moves the long bit mask into a 32 bit &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt;, and then you do your usual bit tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Bit tricks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What are the usual bit tricks? One great candidate is Find First Set or &lt;code&gt;ffs&lt;/code&gt; in short — this is a great name given how tedious it is to get bit tricks right. This instruction can be used to iterate over set bits, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
#include &amp;lt;stdio.h&amp;gt;

int main() {
    int mask = 0b0100000100001000;
    int prev = 0;
    while (mask) {
        int curr = __builtin_ffs(mask);
        if (curr &amp;gt; prev + 1)
            printf("Word start at %d\n", curr);
        prev = curr;
        if (curr == 32) // don't ask, sigh.
            break;
        mask = (mask &amp;gt;&amp;gt; curr) &amp;lt;&amp;lt; curr;
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It outputs the following, corresponding to the mask example above:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;Word start at 4 Word start at 9 Word start at 15&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Putting it together&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I ended up writing this code explicitly using &lt;code&gt;immintrin.h&lt;/code&gt; which is an absolutely dreadful experience. Next time I'll use a high-level API (in the past I've had a lot of fun vectorizing things interactively in the Julia REPL with VectorizationBase.jl). But at least I felt like I had some control over the generated machine code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using AVX2 with 256-bit registers, you need to align your data on 32 bits, which I did (of course not without messing it up first). I reserved 6 of the registers to hold all broadcasted whitespace characters. Then I explicitly unrolled the vectorized loop 4 times, so in every iteration we process 128 bytes of data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It took an awful lot of time to fix the off-by-one bugs, but in the end I managed to get a working program, tested against a non-zero amount of text files on my computer:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ ./wc-avx2 &amp;lt; bible-100.txt 82113300 $ wc -w &amp;lt; bible-100.txt 82113300&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, how fast?!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ time ./wc-avx2 &amp;lt; bible-100.txt 82113300 real 0m0.227s user 0m0.186s sys 0m0.041s&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That comes down to 1.45 GB/s (on a warm cache).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sigh. So hand-optimized, single-threaded word count is only getting about 11% of the sequential disk read speed. And on a cold cache?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;$ sysctl -w vm.drop_caches=3 $ time ./wc-avx2 &amp;lt; bible-100.txt 82113300 real 0m0.395s user 0m0.196s sys 0m0.117s&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still more time in user than sys :(. So yeah, maybe the disk speed has caught up statement is indeed true.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Get the code&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've put my code up on GitHub. If you know better bit-tricks, feel free to submit a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46506994</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 00:02:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>GBC Boot Animation 88×31 Web Button</title><link>https://zakhary.dev/blog/gbc-web-button</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="53b572515204dc27"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GBC Boot Animation 88×31 Web Button&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like many other 90s styles coming back in fashion, I’ve been seeing those retro 88x31 web buttons on more personal websites these days. What a throwback. Naturally, I scoured the internet to find buttons to add to my footer (see below). Since I couldn’t find a Game Boy one that I liked, obviously I had to make my own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s only one problem: I’m not patient (read: talented) enough to make the art myself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Concept&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My idea was to use the boot animation from the Game Boy Color placed inside the traditional grey frame. Something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not too complicated, right? So you’d think.Wait just a second. Surely it can’t be that hard to make the animation if I already have the mock-up, right? Well, I kinda cheated and used the final result to make that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Animating&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, we’ve got to find a way to export the animation from boot ROM. The easiest way I could think of to do that was to play it in an emulatorRegrettably my emulator Rugby doesn’t (yet) support Game Boy Color, so I used the fantastic SameBoy for this next part. and save screenshots of each frame individually. Well, in order to do that we need a way to stop the emulator at each frame. Thankfully, the emulator I used has breakpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, where should those breakpoints go? Time for a quick crash course:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The animation is programmed into the Game Boy’s boot ROM in GBZ80 assembly. This is proprietary code written by Nintendo that powers up the system and validates the cartridge before handing off execution to the game. Thankfully, some smart people have done the hard work of (1) dumping, (2) disassembling, and (3) labelling the boot ROM for us.I feel pretty comfortable calling my use of the boot ROM in this project “fair use.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For each Game Boy frame, there’s a period of time where the LCD idles before drawing the next frame. This is called vblank. Taking a look at the disassembly, we can see where vblank occurs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;; =============== S U B R O U T I N E =======================================

; Wait until LCD VBlank Interrupt is flagged.
;
; Input: None.
; Output: None.

Wait_for_next_VBLANK:
    push    hl
    ld  hl, $FF0F
    res 0, [hl]

_wait_vblank_loop:
    bit 0, [hl]       ; wait until hardware sets the vblank flag (bit 0 of FF0F)
    jr  z, _wait_vblank_loop
    pop hl
    ret
; End of function Wait_for_next_VBLANK&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using the debugger, we can see that this function is called from the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sub_0291:
    call    Wait_for_next_VBLANK
    ; -- snip --&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we can see from the generated label &lt;code&gt;sub_0291&lt;/code&gt;, this block probably lives at
address &lt;code&gt;$0291&lt;/code&gt;. Putting a breakpoint here and stepping into the function
reveals the address of &lt;code&gt;Wait_for_next_VBLANK&lt;/code&gt; to be &lt;code&gt;$0211&lt;/code&gt;. After a quick reset
and setting the breakpoint, we can step through each frame of the animation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This next part was a bit tedious: I repeatedly &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt;d the debugger, taking
an emulator screenshot at each frame.Using &lt;code&gt;⌘S&lt;/code&gt; in SameBoy will capture a screenshot using the emulated
LCD framebuffer. This will be at the true LCD resolution, completely
independent of my laptop’s display resolution. Once that was done, I had 175
screenshots at 160x144 saved as PNGs on my desktop. Using some quick ✨
&lt;code&gt;magick&lt;/code&gt;If you haven’t heard of the CLI image processing tool
ImageMagick, I highly recommend checking it out. ✨, I collected these into a GIFPronounced /dʒɪf/. with this command:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick -delay 1.6742706299 -loop 0 *.png(n) animation.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of note is the delay time, ~0.0167s&lt;code&gt;70,224 [#/frame] ÷ 4,194,304 [#/sec] ~= 0.0167427 [sec/frame]&lt;/code&gt;, and the zsh-ism &lt;code&gt;*.png(n)&lt;/code&gt; to sort
the expanded glob.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyways, here’s what it looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Making Art&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve &lt;del&gt;copied Nintendo’s homework&lt;/del&gt; made our Game Boy animation, it’s time to reshape it into an artistic web button masterpiece.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Cropping&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next up we’ve got to crop the animation to the desired 88x31. Let’s load up the GIF to see how big the logo is. I used Aseprite for this, but really any application that lets you count pixels in an image will do. Doing this, we see the “Game Boy” text logo is… 127x22 pixels wide. Hmm. That’s too big to fit into an 88x31 button, but I guess that makes sense considering the Game Boy Color’s screen is 160x144 pixels. It’ll have to be scaled down later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Measuring the logo’s starting location to be &lt;code&gt;(x: 16, y: 48)&lt;/code&gt;, we can now crop
away. Cropping a GIF sounds like it should be a lot of work, but it can be
easily accomplished on the CLI with, you guessed it, &lt;code&gt;magick&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick animation.gif -crop 127x22+16+48 +repage cropped.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Scaling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cropped logo needs to be scaled to fit into 88x31. Say it with me folks. &lt;code&gt;magick&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick cropped.gif -resize 82x scaled.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This scales (resizes) the GIF to be 82 pixels wide while maintaining the aspect ratio, the result being 82x14. I chose 82 pixels wide specifically since that’ll allow us to fit for the next stage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Framing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Several of the 88x31 buttons I found online have a common frame with a 2-pixel-wide border. It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To apply this frame to the scaled animation, we’ll need to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Centre the scaled animation into a 88x31 space;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fill in the newly added space with grey;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Add the border frame on top of the animation.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hopefully you know the drill by now:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick scaled.gif \
    -gravity center -background "#C0C0C0" -extent 88x31 \
    -coalesce null: frame.png -layers composite \
    framed.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aaaand we’re done! Let’s take a look at the finished product in all its glory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wait, what’s that ugly white square doing there? Oh, right. The animation had a white background. Gotta fix that I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Fixing That&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is actually quite straightforward. Removing the white background is easy, although if we do it with what we currently have there ends up being undesirable artifacts caused by the prior scaling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick framed.gif -fill "#C0C0C0" -opaque "#FFFFFF" fixed.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The trick here is to replace the white background before scaling. Here’s also a really great opportunity to fully show off how powerful ImageMagick’s transform pipeline can be. Going back to our uncropped animation, we can apply all previous steps at once like so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick animation.gif \
    -crop 127x22+16+48 +repage \         # crop 127x22 logo from animation
    -fill "#C0C0C0" -opaque "#FFFFFF" \  # NEW: replace background with grey
    -resize 82x \                        # scale animation to 82x14
    -gravity center \                    # place logo in centre
    -background "#C0C0C0" \              # use grey for added background
    -extent 88x31 \                      # expand animation to 88x31
    -coalesce null: frame.png \          # apply frame border
    -layers composite \                  # composites each frame
    fixed.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s amazing that we can do all this in a single command! Let’s admire our finished product.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Exorcism&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we all know, the final stage of any good art project is excising tormented apparitions from our glorious creation!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See that shadow of the logo that appears as it fades away? That’s called ghosting, and is caused by the original animation’s fade going to white instead of the grey we’ve chosen as our new background colour.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Remapping&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixing this is going to be a little more tricky than it was for the compression artifacts above. In order to fix this, we’ll need remap the transition colours so that the logo’s blue-to-white transition instead fades to grey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To do this, we’ll first need a way to identify all those transition colours. Extracting the frames of the animation will allow us to analyze their colours in a histogram:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Extract original animation's frames
mkdir frames
magick animation.gif frames/%03d.png

# Analyze each frame's colours
for frame in frames/*(n); do
    echo "frame: $frame"
    magick "$frame" -format %c histogram:info:
done&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running this script will produce a ton of output. Let’s take a look at some samples near the end.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;-- snip --
frame: frames/160.png
           209: (232,232,232) #E8E8E8 grey91
          1560: (232,238,255) #E8EEFF srgb(232,238,255)
         21271: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF white
frame: frames/161.png
           209: (243,243,243) #F3F3F3 srgb(243,243,243)
          1560: (243,246,255) #F3F6FF srgb(243,246,255)
         21271: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF white
frame: frames/162.png
           209: (247,247,247) #F7F7F7 grey97
          1560: (247,249,255) #F7F9FF srgb(247,249,255)
         21271: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF white
frame: frames/163.png
            29: (250,251,255) #FAFBFF srgb(250,251,255)
         23011: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF white
frame: frames/164.png
         23040: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF gray(255)
frame: frames/165.png
         23040: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF gray(255)
frame: frames/166.png
         23040: (255,255,255) #FFFFFF gray(255)
-- snip --
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not immediately obvious what we’re looking for here, but we can see that by frame 164 there’s only one colour. That corresponds to the whiteout at the end of the animation. Looking a few frames before, we consistently see 209 frames helpfully labelled as grey, and 1560 frames in some other colour. Conspicuously, that other colour only varies in red and green, but remains fully blue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matching that up with the animation, those 1560 pixels must be the fading logo. With a little Unix wizardry&lt;code&gt;grep 1560 output.txt | awk '{ print $3 }' | uniq&lt;/code&gt; we can extract the colour hex codes from this
output to obtain an exact list of the blue-to-white transition colours!I’m not entirely sure why frame 163 has 29 seemingly random light-blue
pixels, but I’ve manually added &lt;code&gt;#FAFBFF&lt;/code&gt; to the list to capture them as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Fade colours (blue to white)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#006BFF
#066CFF
#0C6DFF
#146FFF
#1C71FF
#2474FF
#2D77FF
#387CFF
#4281FF
#4C86FF
#588DFF
#6494FF
#719CFF
#7DA3FF
#89ABFF
#95B3FF
#A1BBFF
#ACC3FF
#B6CAFF
#C0D1FF
#CAD8FF
#D2DEFF
#DAE4FF
#E1E9FF
#E8EEFF
#F3F6FF
#F7F9FF
#FAFBFF
#FFFFFF
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From this list, the logo fade transitions from &lt;code&gt;[#006BFF, #FFFFFF)&lt;/code&gt;.This is a non-inclusive range.
Since we’re updating the background colour to &lt;code&gt;#C0C0C0&lt;/code&gt;, we’ll need a way to
modify the transition colours to instead fade to that shade of grey.
Functionally, for each colour we (1) compute how far along the transition we
are, then (2) use this value to re-compute an equivalent transition colour in
the desired fade range.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s where I’ll admit my shame: by this point I was getting lazy and didn’t feel like using my brain to write my own colour interpolation. So I turned to the AI overlords to do this work for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Interpolation script (AI slop)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;def hex_to_rgb(hex):
    """Convert hex string (#RRGGBB) to RGB tuple."""
    return tuple(int(hex.lstrip('#')[i:i+2], 16) for i in (0, 2, 4))

def rgb_to_hex(rgb):
    """Convert RGB tuple to hex string (#RRGGBB)."""
    return "#{:02X}{:02X}{:02X}".format(*rgb)

def remap_color(color, start_old, end_old, start_new, end_new):
    """Remap a color from old range to new range."""
    r_old, g_old, b_old = start_old
    r_end_old, g_end_old, b_end_old = end_old
    r_new_start, g_new_start, b_new_start = start_new
    r_new_end, g_new_end, b_new_end = end_new
    r, g, b = color

    # Compute relative position t in old range
    t = (
        (r - r_old) / (r_end_old - r_old) if r_end_old != r_old else 0
    )  # using red as representative; you could average channels instead

    # Map to new range
    r_mapped = round(r_new_start + t * (r_new_end - r_new_start))
    g_mapped = round(g_new_start + t * (g_new_end - g_new_start))
    b_mapped = round(b_new_start + t * (b_new_end - b_new_start))

    # Clamp values between 0-255
    r_mapped = min(max(r_mapped, 0), 255)
    g_mapped = min(max(g_mapped, 0), 255)
    b_mapped = min(max(b_mapped, 0), 255)

    return (r_mapped, g_mapped, b_mapped)

# Define old and new ranges
start_old = hex_to_rgb("#006BFF")
end_old   = hex_to_rgb("#FFFFFF")

start_new = hex_to_rgb("#006BFF")
end_new   = hex_to_rgb("#C0C0C0")

# Process file
with open("color.txt", "r") as f:
    colors = [line.strip() for line in f if line.strip()]

fixed_colors = []
for hex_color in colors:
    rgb = hex_to_rgb(hex_color)
    new_rgb = remap_color(rgb, start_old, end_old, start_new, end_new)
    fixed_colors.append(rgb_to_hex(new_rgb))

# Write output
with open("remap.txt", "w") as f:
    f.write("\n".join(fixed_colors))

print("Finished! Fixed colors saved to remap.txt")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looks great, I’m sure it works fine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Fade colours (blue to grey)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#006BFF
#056DFE
#096FFC
#0F72FA
#1574F8
#1B77F6
#227AF4
#2A7EF1
#3281EF
#3984EC
#4288E9
#4B8CE6
#5591E3
#5E95E0
#6799DD
#709DDA
#79A1D7
#82A4D5
#89A8D2
#91ABD0
#98AECD
#9EB1CB
#A4B4C9
#A9B6C7
#AFB8C6
#B7BCC3
#BABDC2
#BCBEC1
#C0C0C0
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Huh. This looks surprisingly correct. Adding in &lt;code&gt;#FFFFFF&lt;/code&gt; to the original list
and running again, we see that it does indeed get transformed to &lt;code&gt;#C0C0C0&lt;/code&gt;. As
an additional sanity check, here are generated images of the palettes we intend
to swap.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All that’s left is to perform the colour substitution. Admittedly, I was having some trouble doing this using ImageMagick’s &lt;code&gt;-clut&lt;/code&gt;, so I arrived at a much less
elegant solution: use a series of &lt;code&gt;-fill&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;-opaque&lt;/code&gt; to manually replace each
colour. Adding the following to the bottom of the Python script, we can at least
automate writing all that out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Generate ImageMagick command
cmd = ""
for old, new in zip(colors, fixed_colors):
    cmd += f' -fill "{new}" -opaque "{old}" \\\n'

print(f"Generated ImageMagick replacement:\n{cmd}")&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Generated replacement options&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;-fill "#006BFF" -opaque "#006BFF" \
-fill "#056DFE" -opaque "#066CFF" \
-fill "#096FFC" -opaque "#0C6DFF" \
-fill "#0F72FA" -opaque "#146FFF" \
-fill "#1574F8" -opaque "#1C71FF" \
-fill "#1B77F6" -opaque "#2474FF" \
-fill "#227AF4" -opaque "#2D77FF" \
-fill "#2A7EF1" -opaque "#387CFF" \
-fill "#3281EF" -opaque "#4281FF" \
-fill "#3984EC" -opaque "#4C86FF" \
-fill "#4288E9" -opaque "#588DFF" \
-fill "#4B8CE6" -opaque "#6494FF" \
-fill "#5591E3" -opaque "#719CFF" \
-fill "#5E95E0" -opaque "#7DA3FF" \
-fill "#6799DD" -opaque "#89ABFF" \
-fill "#709DDA" -opaque "#95B3FF" \
-fill "#79A1D7" -opaque "#A1BBFF" \
-fill "#82A4D5" -opaque "#ACC3FF" \
-fill "#89A8D2" -opaque "#B6CAFF" \
-fill "#91ABD0" -opaque "#C0D1FF" \
-fill "#98AECD" -opaque "#CAD8FF" \
-fill "#9EB1CB" -opaque "#D2DEFF" \
-fill "#A4B4C9" -opaque "#DAE4FF" \
-fill "#A9B6C7" -opaque "#E1E9FF" \
-fill "#AFB8C6" -opaque "#E8EEFF" \
-fill "#B7BCC3" -opaque "#F3F6FF" \
-fill "#BABDC2" -opaque "#F7F9FF" \
-fill "#BCBEC1" -opaque "#FAFBFF" \
-fill "#C0C0C0" -opaque "#FFFFFF" \
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Putting it all together, we obtain a monstrosity that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;magick animation.gif \
    -crop 127x22+16+48 +repage \         # crop 127x22 logo from animation
    \ # remap transition colours from white to grey
    -fill "#006BFF" -opaque "#006BFF" \
    -fill "#056DFE" -opaque "#066CFF" \
    -fill "#096FFC" -opaque "#0C6DFF" \
    -fill "#0F72FA" -opaque "#146FFF" \
    -fill "#1574F8" -opaque "#1C71FF" \
    -fill "#1B77F6" -opaque "#2474FF" \
    -fill "#227AF4" -opaque "#2D77FF" \
    -fill "#2A7EF1" -opaque "#387CFF" \
    -fill "#3281EF" -opaque "#4281FF" \
    -fill "#3984EC" -opaque "#4C86FF" \
    -fill "#4288E9" -opaque "#588DFF" \
    -fill "#4B8CE6" -opaque "#6494FF" \
    -fill "#5591E3" -opaque "#719CFF" \
    -fill "#5E95E0" -opaque "#7DA3FF" \
    -fill "#6799DD" -opaque "#89ABFF" \
    -fill "#709DDA" -opaque "#95B3FF" \
    -fill "#79A1D7" -opaque "#A1BBFF" \
    -fill "#82A4D5" -opaque "#ACC3FF" \
    -fill "#89A8D2" -opaque "#B6CAFF" \
    -fill "#91ABD0" -opaque "#C0D1FF" \
    -fill "#98AECD" -opaque "#CAD8FF" \
    -fill "#9EB1CB" -opaque "#D2DEFF" \
    -fill "#A4B4C9" -opaque "#DAE4FF" \
    -fill "#A9B6C7" -opaque "#E1E9FF" \
    -fill "#AFB8C6" -opaque "#E8EEFF" \
    -fill "#B7BCC3" -opaque "#F3F6FF" \
    -fill "#BABDC2" -opaque "#F7F9FF" \
    -fill "#BCBEC1" -opaque "#FAFBFF" \
    -fill "#C0C0C0" -opaque "#FFFFFF" \  # replace background with grey
    -resize 82x \                        # scale animation to 82x14
    -gravity center \                    # place logo in centre
    -background "#C0C0C0" \              # use grey for added background
    -extent 88x31 \                      # expand animation to 88x31
    -coalesce null: frame.png \          # apply frame border
    -layers composite \                  # composites each frame
    button.gif&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As someone who doesn’t have an artistic bone in my body (doctor’s diagnosis), I think it turned out pretty great! I learned a lot about ImageMagick throughout this adventure, and I hope you did too. Please feel free to use this button however you wish. Attribution is not at all necessary, but is welcome and appreciated regardless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well, I guess all that’s left is this final plea: Nintendo, please don’t sue me.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46507963</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 02:20:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>GoGoGrandparent (YC S16) is hiring back end engineers</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/gogograndparent/jobs/2vbzAw8-gogograndparent-yc-s16-is-hiring-backend-and-full-stack-engineers</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="33bf795d37e0e879"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A concierge service for seniors’ rides, meals, meds, home and more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;About Us&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GoGoGrandparent is a digital caregiving platform helping older and disabled adults stay independent, safe, and supported at home. We adapt on-demand APIs (Uber, Lyft, DoorDash, Instacart, etc.) into a concierge-style experience tailored for people with cognitive, mobility, or vision challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re a profitable, fast-growing, YC-backed startup (S16) with a deeply mission-driven team. Everything we build directly impacts real families who rely on GoGo every day.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our engineering team is fully remote, tight-knit, and moves fast. You’ll work closely with founders, ship meaningful features weekly, and have real ownership over architecture, reliability, and product direction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FULLY REMOTE | Able to work 4+ hours overlap with mainland US | $100k – $160k (based on location, experience and seniority)&lt;lb/&gt; Tech Stack&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Back-end heavy: Node.js, TypeScript, MySQL, REST + GraphQL&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Front-end: Vue.js (nice to have)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deployment: AWS, Docker/Kubernetes (nice to have)&lt;lb/&gt; Requirements&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;6+ years of professional experience (primarily in Node.js and Vue.js)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Able to work US timezone or 4+ hours overlap with mainland US&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you're passionate about improving the lives of older adults and people with disabilities, we would love for you to apply!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2-stage interview process&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We built GoGo for our own grandparents and were amazed to see it grow to touch the lives of hundreds of thousands of seniors across the United States and Canada. What shocked us then and it still does now, is that between 30 - 40% of our new signups have smartphones. We didn’t understand why. When we called and asked a few, they told us that Uber and Lyft had 'stopped working' for them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After puzzling over that for months, we realized what the problem was.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Managing transportation - on Lyft, Uber, cab companies, etc is not easy. It’s a ‘self-serve’ experience. The ride requester has to be aware of things like the driver cancelling, getting lost, the driver arriving, the driver not-quite-being-lost-just-down-the-street-a-couple-houses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then add the complexities of smartphones: the user has to be on top of updating their own credit card - making sure the pickup pin is in the correct spot - typing in both where they are and where they’re going. All in all, there are about a dozen online and offline "micro steps" ride requesters have to take to get a ride. And god help anyone who needs to remember their Apple iCloud password to update an app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We didn't know this when we started, but it turns out that ordering and managing a ride gets more difficult the older you get, almost in the same way that driving a car gets more difficult the older you get.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What gets us excited now (and what we’re hiring for) is that technically this ‘self-management problem’ doesn’t just stop at rides. There are lots of things that get harder to do as you age. People have known this for a long time and that’s inspired a lot of the solutions that older adults currently have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based a lot on the experiences we’ve had so far, we believe that by becoming the ‘management layer’ for the things that older adults struggle with as they age we have a better chance to offer older citizens independence without having to ask them to move out of their homes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Within the next ten years the number of people over the age of 65 will be larger than the number of people under 18 for the first time in history. 11,000,000 people over the age of 75 will stop driving due to age related cognitive or physical decline. When they stop driving, they’ll be forced to rely on friends and family, live in a community, or have caregivers. GoGo is working to make sure that losing your youth doesn’t mean losing your independence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Joining us at this time is a really exciting opportunity for folks looking to make meaningful impact on people’s lives. We’re a small team that’s built a profitable and fast-growing business over the last three years. Now we’re looking for partners to join us as we make GoGo a household name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyone joining GoGo at this phase of the company will have a huge and life changing level of impact on a size-able and growing user base. We want people to have rich and meaningful lives at any age. We’re bringing people freedom and hope, one life at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46508441</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 03:32:41 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>