<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 20:12:01 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>How we lost communication to entertainment</title><link>https://ploum.net/2025-12-15-communication-entertainment.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="6d901f930c208a99"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How We Lost Communication to Entertainment&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;by Ploum on 2025-12-15&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;All our communication channels are morphed into content distribution networks. We are more and more entertained but less and less connected.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I did a controversial blog post about Pixelfed hurting the Fediverse. I defended the theory that, in a communication network, you hurt the trust in the whole network if you create clients that arbitrarily drop messages, something that Pixelfed is doing deliberately. It gathered a lot of reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I originally wrote this post, nearly one year ago, I thought that either I was missing something or Dansup, Pixelfed’s creator, was missing it. We could not both be right. But as the reactions piled in on the Fediverse, I realised that such irreconcilable opinions do not arise only from ignorance or oversight. It usually means that both parties have vastly different assumptions about the world. They don’t live in the same world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Two incompatible universes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started to see a pattern in the two kinds of reactions to my blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were people like me, often above 40, who like sending emails and browsing old-fashioned websites. We think of ActivityPub as a "communication protocol" between humans. As such, anything that implies losing messages without feedback is the worst thing that could happen. Not losing messages is the top priority of a communication protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then there are people like Dansup, who believe that ActivityPub is a content consumption protocol. It’s there for entertainment. You create as many accounts as the kinds of media you want to consume. Dansup himself is communicating through a Mastodon account, not a Pixelfed one. Many Pixelfed users also have a Mastodon account, and they never questioned that. They actually want multiple accounts for different use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the Fediverse threads, nearly all the people defending the Pixelfed philosophy posted from Mastodon accounts. They usually boasted about having both a Mastodon and a Pixelfed account.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A multiplicity of accounts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To me, the very goal of interoperability is not to force you into creating multiple accounts. Big Monopolies have managed to convince people that they need one account on each platform. This was done, on purpose, for purely unethical reasons in order to keep users captive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That brainwash/marketing is so deeply entrenched that most people cannot see an alternative anymore. It looks like a natural law: you need an account on a platform to communicate with someone on that platform. That also explains why most politicians want to "regulate" Facebook or X. They think it is impossible not to be on those platforms. They believe those platforms are "public spaces" while they truly are "private spaces trying to destroy all other public spaces in order to get a monopoly."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People flock to the Fediverse with this philosophy of "one platform, one account", which makes no sense if you truly want to create a federated communication protocol like email or XMPP.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But Manuel Moreale cracked it for me: the Fediverse is not a communication network. ActivityPub is not a communication protocol. The spec says it: ActivityPub is a protocol to build a "social platform" whose goal is "to deliver content."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;The ActivityPub protocol is a decentralised social networking protocol based upon the ActivityStreams 2.0 data format. It provides a client to server API for creating, updating and deleting content, as well as a federated server-to-server API for delivering notifications and content. (official W3C definition of ActivityPub)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;No more communication&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But aren’t social networks also communication networks? That’s what I thought. That’s how they historically were marketed. That’s what we all believed during the "Arab Spring."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But that was a lie. Communication networks are not profitable. Social networks are entertainment platforms, media consumption protocols. Historically, they disguised themselves as communication platforms to attract users and keep them captive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The point was never to avoid missing a message sent from a fellow human being. The point was always to fill your time with "content."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We dreamed of decentralised social networks as "email 2.0." They truly are "television 2.0."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They are entertainment platforms that delegate media creation to the users themselves the same way Uber replaced taxis by having people drive others in their own car.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what was created as "ride-sharing" was in fact a way to 1) destroy competition and 2) make a shittier service while people producing the work were paid less and lost labour rights. It was never about the social!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The lost messages&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My own interpretation is that social media users don’t mind losing messages because they were raised on algorithmic platforms that did that all the time. They don’t see the point in trusting a platform because they never experienced a trusted means of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that I write it, it may also explain why instant messaging became the dominant communication medium: because if you don’t receive an immediate answer, you don’t even trust the recipient to have received your messages. In fact, even if the message was received, you don’t even trust the recipient's attention span to remember the message.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiple studies have confirmed that we don’t remember the vast majority of what we see while doomscrolling. While the "view" was registered to increase statistics, we don’t have the slightest memory of most of that content, even after only a few seconds. It thus makes sense not to consider social media as a means of communication at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s no need for a reliable communication protocol if we assume that human brains are not reliable enough to handle asynchronous messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s not Dansup who is missing something. It is me who is unadapted to the current society. I understand now that Pixelfed was only following some design decisions and protocol abuses fathered by Mastodon. Pixelfed was my own "gotcha" moment because I never understood Instagram in the first place, and, in my eyes, Pixelfed was no better. But if you take that route, Mastodon is no better than Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many reactions pointed, justly, that other Fediverse tools such as PeerTube, WriteFreely, or Mobilizon were just not displaying messages at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I didn’t consider it a big problem because they never pretended to do it in the first place. Nobody uses those tools to follow others. There’s no expectation. Those platforms are "publish only." But this is still a big flaw in the Fediverse! Someone could, using autocompletion, send a message pinging your PeerTube address and you will never see it. Try autocomplete "@ploum" from your Mastodon account and guess which suggestion is the only one that will send me a valid notification!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a more positive note, I should give credit to Dansup for announcing that Pixelfed will soon allow people to optionally "not drop" text messages.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How we lost email&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I cling to asynchronous reliable communications, but those are disappearing. I use email a lot because I see it as a true means of communication: reliable, asynchronous, decentralised, standardised, manageable offline with my own tools. But many people, even barely younger than me, tell me that email is "too formal" or "for old people" or "even worse than social network feeds."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And they are probably right. I like it because I’ve learned to use it. I apply a strong inbox 0 methodology. If I don’t reply or act on your email, it is because I decided not to. I’m actively keeping my inbox clean by sharing only disposable email addresses that I disable once they start to be spammed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But for most people, their email inbox is simply one more feed full of bad advertising. They have 4 or 5 digit unread count. They scroll through their inbox like they do through their social media feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Boringness of communications&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The main problem with reliable communication protocols? It is a mostly solved problem. Build simple websites, read RSS feeds, write emails. Use IRC and XMPP if you truly want real-time communication. Those are working and working great.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And because of that, they are boring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Communications protocols are boring. They don’t give you that well-studied random hit of dopamine. They don’t make you addicted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They don’t make you addicted which means they are not hugely profitable and thus are not advertised. They are not new. They are not as shiny as a new app or a new random chatbot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The problem with communication protocols was never the protocol part. It’s the communication part. A few sad humans never wanted to communicate in the first place and managed to become billionaires by convincing the rest of mankind that being entertained is better than communicating with other humans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;As long as I’m not alone&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We believe that a communication network must reach a critical mass to be really useful. People stay on Facebook to "stay in touch with the majority." I don’t believe that lie anymore. I’m falling back to good old mailing lists. I’m reading the Web and Gemini while offline through Offpunk. I also handle my emails asynchronously while offline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Offpunk, an offline-first command-line browser (offpunk.net)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;There Is No Content on Gemini (ploum.net)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I may be part of an endangered species.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter. I made peace with the fact that I will never get in touch with everyone. As long as there are people posting on their gemlogs or blogs with RSS feeds, as long as there are people willing to read my emails without automatically summarising them, there will be a place for those who want to simply communicate. A protected reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are welcome to join!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Illustration of a message board piled with messages by David Revoy (CC By 4.0)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Illustration of animal meeting at an intersection with messages by David Revoy (CC By 4.0)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m Ploum, a writer and an engineer. I like to explore how technology impacts society. You can subscribe by email or by rss. I value privacy and never share your adress.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I write science-fiction novels in French. For Bikepunk, my new post-apocalyptic-cyclist book, my publisher is looking for contacts in other countries to distribute it in languages other than French. If you can help, contact me!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46404848</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 20:15:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Liberating Bluetooth on the ESP32</title><link>https://exquisite.tube/w/mEzF442Q4hUXnhQ8HmfZuq</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bf6f84981497afad"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems JavaScript is either blocked or disabled in your web browser. We totally get that. However, this page will not work without it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are concerned about the security and privacy (or lack thereof) of JavaScript web applications, you might want to review the source code of the instance you are trying to access, or look for security audits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are sorry but it seems that PeerTube is not compatible with your web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please try with the latest version of Mozilla Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you think this is a mistake, please report it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46406098</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 22:37:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Functional programming and reliability: ADTs, safety, critical infrastructure</title><link>https://blog.rastrian.dev/post/why-reliability-demands-functional-programming-adts-safety-and-critical-infrastructure</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="99767a096f092704"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why Reliability Demands Functional Programming: ADTs, Safety, and Critical Infrastructure&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In banking, telecom, and payments, reliability is not a nice to have. It is table stakes. The most reliable systems I have worked on reduce entire classes of bugs before the code even runs. Functional programming and Algebraic Data Types (ADTs) let you push correctness into the type system, so illegal states cannot be constructed in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What you will learn&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How invalid states show up in real systems and why they cause costly incidents&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How ADTs encode business rules so the compiler enforces them&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How pattern matching and exhaustiveness checks turn refactors into safe edits&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Practical modeling patterns for banking and telecom domains in TypeScript and OCaml&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A migration playbook that juniors and mid-levels can apply today&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Functional programming&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Algebraic data type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tagged union or sum type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Product type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pattern matching&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Immutable object&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pure function&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;High availability&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;1) Reliability starts at the type system&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most production incidents are not due to complex algorithms. They are due to the code entering a state that should never have been possible. If you have been on call, you have seen variants of these:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Magic strings: &lt;code&gt;"paypal"&lt;/code&gt;sneaks into a system that only supports&lt;code&gt;Cash&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Card&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Pix&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Nulls: a function expects an email and receives &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;in a path you forgot to guard&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Conflicting booleans: an account is both &lt;code&gt;isActive = true&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;isSuspended = true&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Incomplete lifecycles: a transaction is marked &lt;code&gt;Pending&lt;/code&gt;and then jumps to&lt;code&gt;Reversed&lt;/code&gt;without an associated&lt;code&gt;Settled&lt;/code&gt;record&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Functional programming helps by modeling the domain with types that make invalid states unrepresentable. Pure functions and immutability keep behavior predictable and testable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;2) ADTs in practice: sums and products&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Product types combine fields, think "and". Sum types choose one of several cases, think "or". Together they model your domain rules.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Product type example&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type user = {
  id    : int;
  name  : string;
  email : string option;  (* Some "[email protected]" or None *)
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type User = Readonly&amp;lt;{
  id: number;
  name: string;
  email?: string; // we will improve this with Option next
}&amp;gt;;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Sum type example&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type payment =
  | Cash
  | Card of string   (* last 4 digits *)
  | Pix  of string
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript discriminated union
type Payment =
  | { kind: "cash" }
  | { kind: "card"; last4: string }
  | { kind: "pix"; key: string };
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With this shape, &lt;code&gt;"paypal"&lt;/code&gt; cannot exist as a &lt;code&gt;Payment&lt;/code&gt;. The compiler refuses the value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;3) Pattern matching and exhaustiveness&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you pattern match on a sum type, the compiler can force you to handle every variant. If you later add a new case, every non exhaustive match becomes a compilation error or warning. This is how refactors become safe by default.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
let describe_payment = function
  | Cash -&amp;gt; "Paid in cash"
  | Card last4 -&amp;gt; "Card ••••" ^ last4
  | Pix key -&amp;gt; "Pix " ^ key
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
const assertNever = (x: never): never =&amp;gt; { throw new Error(`Unhandled variant: ${JSON.stringify(x)}`) }

function describePayment(p: Payment): string {
  switch (p.kind) {
    case "cash":  return "Paid in cash"
    case "card":  return `Card ••••${p.last4}`
    case "pix":   return `Pix ${p.key}`
    default:      return assertNever(p)
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a new &lt;code&gt;Crypto&lt;/code&gt; method and both code bases will point out every place you must update.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;4) Failure scenarios and their type driven fixes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;4.1 Banking example: double settlement and reconciliation drift&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incident story&lt;lb/&gt; A payout worker retries on network timeouts and calls &lt;code&gt;settle()&lt;/code&gt; twice. The table allows &lt;code&gt;pending = false&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;settled = true&lt;/code&gt; twice with the same ledger id. Reconciliation finds duplicates and accounting needs a manual fix.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why it happened&lt;lb/&gt; State is spread across booleans and strings. The database does not express the lifecycle. The application code does, but only by convention and tests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix with ADTs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type failure_reason =
  | InsufficientFunds
  | ComplianceHold
  | NetworkError of string

type txn_state =
  | Pending
  | Settled  of string       (* ledger_id *)
  | Failed   of failure_reason
  | Reversed of string       (* original_ledger_id *)

type txn = {
  id           : string;
  amount_cents : int;
  state        : txn_state;
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type FailureReason =
  | { kind: "insufficientFunds" }
  | { kind: "complianceHold" }
  | { kind: "networkError"; message: string }

type TxnState =
  | { kind: "pending" }
  | { kind: "settled"; ledgerId: string }
  | { kind: "failed"; reason: FailureReason }
  | { kind: "reversed"; originalLedgerId: string }

type Txn = Readonly&amp;lt;{
  id: string
  amountCents: number
  state: TxnState
}&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transitions become total functions. You can return a &lt;code&gt;Result&lt;/code&gt; when a transition is not allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type 'a result = Ok of 'a | Error of string

let settle (t: txn) (ledger_id: string) : txn result =
  match t.state with
  | Pending -&amp;gt; Ok { t with state = Settled ledger_id }
  | Settled _ -&amp;gt; Error "already settled"
  | Failed _ -&amp;gt; Error "cannot settle a failed transaction"
  | Reversed _ -&amp;gt; Error "cannot settle a reversed transaction"
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;  = { _tag: "Ok"; value: T }
type Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Err"; error: E }
type Result&amp;lt;T, E&amp;gt; = Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; | Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt;
const Ok = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Result&amp;lt;T, never&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Ok", value })
const Err = &amp;lt;E&amp;gt;(error: E): Result&amp;lt;never, E&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Err", error })

function settle(t: Txn, ledgerId: string): Result&amp;lt;Txn, string&amp;gt; {
  switch (t.state.kind) {
    case "pending":  return Ok({ ...t, state: { kind: "settled", ledgerId } })
    case "settled":  return Err("already settled")
    case "failed":   return Err("cannot settle a failed transaction")
    case "reversed": return Err("cannot settle a reversed transaction")
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now the illegal transitions are blocked by construction. Test coverage still matters, but the shape of the model prevents a class of bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Refactor safety&lt;lb/&gt; When product adds &lt;code&gt;Chargeback&lt;/code&gt;, the compiler highlights every match that ignores it. You cannot ship with a half handled lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;type TxnState =
  | { kind: "pending" }
  | { kind: "settled"; ledgerId: string }
  | { kind: "failed"; reason: FailureReason }
  | { kind: "reversed"; originalLedgerId: string }
  | { kind: "chargeback"; networkRef: string } // new
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Every &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; on &lt;code&gt;TxnState&lt;/code&gt; now requires a &lt;code&gt;chargeback&lt;/code&gt; branch. This is free guidance from the compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;4.2 Telecom example: ghost billing and incomplete sessions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incident story&lt;lb/&gt; The call detail record pipeline generates billing events whenever it sees a &lt;code&gt;Connected&lt;/code&gt; event. Under jitter and retries, some sessions never receive &lt;code&gt;Completed&lt;/code&gt;. The billing system charges based on the wrong boundary and customers complain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why it happened&lt;lb/&gt; The call lifecycle is implicit across many services. A connected session with no end was still billable because there was no type that separated non billable states from billable ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix with ADTs&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type drop_reason = Network | Busy | Timeout

type call =
  | Dialing   of int                   (* at_ms *)
  | Connected of int                   (* started_ms *)
  | Dropped   of drop_reason * int     (* reason, at_ms *)
  | Completed of int * int             (* started_ms, ended_ms *)

let billable_seconds = function
  | Completed (start_ms, end_ms) -&amp;gt; max 0 (end_ms - start_ms) / 1000
  | _ -&amp;gt; 0
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type DropReason = "network" | "busy" | "timeout"

type Call =
  | { kind: "dialing";   atMs: number }
  | { kind: "connected"; startedMs: number }
  | { kind: "dropped";   reason: DropReason; atMs: number }
  | { kind: "completed"; startedMs: number; endedMs: number }

const billableSeconds = (c: Call): number =&amp;gt; {
  switch (c.kind) {
    case "completed": return Math.max(0, (c.endedMs - c.startedMs) / 1000)
    default:          return 0
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now a connected but never completed call cannot produce a billable duration. The shape forbids the bug.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;4.3 Config parsing example: hidden NaN and partial failures&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incident story&lt;lb/&gt; A cache TTL is stored in an environment variable. Someone sets &lt;code&gt;CACHE_TTL_SECS=30s&lt;/code&gt;. In JavaScript, &lt;code&gt;Number("30s")&lt;/code&gt; yields &lt;code&gt;NaN&lt;/code&gt; and your code treats it as zero, disabling caching in production.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fix with Result types&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type 'a result = Ok of 'a | Error of string

let parse_int (s: string) : int result =
  try Ok (int_of_string s) with _ -&amp;gt; Error "invalid int"

let load_ttl () : int option =
  match Sys.getenv_opt "CACHE_TTL_SECS" with
  | None -&amp;gt; None
  | Some s -&amp;gt;
    match parse_int s with
    | Ok n -&amp;gt; Some n
    | Error _ -&amp;gt; None  (* or propagate the error *)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
const parseIntR = (s: string): Result&amp;lt;number, "invalid-int"&amp;gt; =&amp;gt;
  /^-?\d+$/.test(s) ? Ok(Number(s)) : Err("invalid-int")

function loadTtl(): Option&amp;lt;number&amp;gt; {
  const raw = process.env.CACHE_TTL_SECS
  if (!raw) return None
  const parsed = parseIntR(raw)
  return parsed._tag === "Ok" ? Some(parsed.value) : None
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ambiguity disappears. The code must handle absence and parse errors explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;5) Options and Results as first class tools&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do not use &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; to mean "maybe". Do not throw exceptions for expected errors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Option or Maybe&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
type user = { id: int; email: string option }

let send_mail (u: user) =
  match u.email with
  | Some e -&amp;gt; (* send e *) ()
  | None   -&amp;gt; ()
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type None = { _tag: "None" }
type Some&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Some"; value: T }
type Option&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; = None | Some&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;
const None: None = { _tag: "None" }
const Some = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Option&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Some", value })

const map = &amp;lt;A, B&amp;gt;(o: Option&amp;lt;A&amp;gt;, f: (a: A) =&amp;gt; B): Option&amp;lt;B&amp;gt; =&amp;gt;
  o._tag === "Some" ? Some(f(o.value)) : None
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Result or Either&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
let result_map f = function
  | Ok x -&amp;gt; Ok (f x)
  | Error e -&amp;gt; Error e
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;  = { _tag: "Ok"; value: T }
type Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Err"; error: E }
type Result&amp;lt;T, E&amp;gt; = Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; | Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt;
const Ok  = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Result&amp;lt;T, never&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Ok", value })
const Err = &amp;lt;E&amp;gt;(error: E): Result&amp;lt;never, E&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Err", error })
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These types make the happy path and the error path equally explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;6) Immutability and why it simplifies reasoning&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mutable shared state is a common source of heisenbugs under concurrency. Prefer immutable data and pure functions. When you need to update, create a new value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
let set_email (u: user) (e: string option) : user =
  { u with email = e }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type User = Readonly&amp;lt;{ id: number; name: string; email: Option&amp;lt;string&amp;gt; }&amp;gt;

const setEmail = (u: User, email: Option&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;): User =&amp;gt;
  ({ ...u, email })
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your tests become simple. Given the same inputs, the function returns the same output.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;7) Smart constructors and newtypes to protect units and invariants&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Numbers are not self describing. Create types that carry meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml *)
module Cents : sig
  type t
  val make : int -&amp;gt; t            (* reject negatives *)
  val add  : t -&amp;gt; t -&amp;gt; t
end = struct
  type t = Cents of int
  let make x = if x &amp;lt; 0 then invalid_arg "negative cents" else Cents x
  let add (Cents a) (Cents b) = Cents (a + b)
end
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript
type Brand&amp;lt;K, T&amp;gt; = K &amp;amp; { __brand: T }

type Cents = Brand&amp;lt;number, "Cents"&amp;gt;
const Cents = (n: number): Cents =&amp;gt; {
  if (!Number.isInteger(n) || n &amp;lt; 0) throw new Error("invalid cents")
  return n as Cents
}

type Millis = Brand&amp;lt;number, "Millis"&amp;gt;
const Millis = (n: number): Millis =&amp;gt; n as Millis

const price: Cents = Cents(500)
// const wrong: Cents = Millis(500)  // type error
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You stop mixing milliseconds with seconds or dollars with cents by accident.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;8) Pure core, effectful shell&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep the domain logic pure and push IO to the edges. This makes unit tests cheap and fast.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml, pure core *)
let authorize_payment (amount: Cents.t) (balance: Cents.t) : bool =
  amount &amp;lt;= balance  (* assume a comparison helper inside the module *)

(* impure shell *)
let run () =
  let amount = Cents.make 500 in
  let balance = Cents.make 1200 in
  if authorize_payment amount balance then
    (* call database and payment gateway here *) ()
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript, pure core
const authorizePayment = (amount: Cents, balance: Cents): boolean =&amp;gt; {
  return (amount as unknown as number) &amp;lt;= (balance as unknown as number)
}

// effectful shell
async function run() {
  const amount = Cents(500)
  const balance = Cents(1200)
  if (authorizePayment(amount, balance)) {
    // perform DB writes or API calls here
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;9) Migration playbook&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start small and make continuous progress. Here is a practical order for a team new to these ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replace pairs of booleans with a sum type&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Before: &lt;code&gt;{ isActive: boolean; isSuspended: boolean }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;After: &lt;code&gt;type AccountState = { kind: "active" } | { kind: "suspended" } | { kind: "closed" }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Before: &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replace string enums with discriminated unions&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Avoid free form strings like &lt;code&gt;"pending" | "settled" | "failed" | string&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Avoid free form strings like &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replace nullable fields with Option&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;OCaml &lt;code&gt;string option&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;TypeScript &lt;code&gt;Option&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;or a stricter domain specific union&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OCaml &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replace thrown control flow with Result&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Reserve exceptions for truly unexpected situations&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Introduce newtypes or branded types for units and ids&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Prevent mixing &lt;code&gt;Millis&lt;/code&gt;with&lt;code&gt;Seconds&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;Cents&lt;/code&gt;with&lt;code&gt;Dollars&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Prevent mixing &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Enforce exhaustiveness&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;OCaml already warns&lt;/item&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;TypeScript: discriminated unions, &lt;code&gt;assertNever&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;strictNullChecks&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;noImplicitReturns&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Add guard rails in CI&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
          &lt;item&gt;Treat TypeScript non exhaustive switches and OCaml warnings as errors&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Smells to look for&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multiple booleans that can be true at the same time&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Strings that travel far before being validated&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Functions that sometimes return a value and sometimes throw&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Types that carry numbers without units&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;10) Performance and ergonomics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pattern matching compiles to simple branches. Discriminated unions in TypeScript are just plain objects. The main cost you will feel is validation at the boundaries in smart constructors. This is a trade worth making. The compiler then protects the interior of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reliability is designed. With Algebraic Data Types, pattern matching, Option and Result, immutability, and smart constructors, you encode domain rules directly in your types. Illegal states cannot compile. This is why industries that cannot afford failure, such as banking and telecom, gravitate to functional ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you work on code that touches money, minutes, or public availability, adopt these patterns now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Model workflows with sum types, not conflicting flags&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use Option and Result instead of nullable and throwable APIs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Keep a pure core with effects at the edges&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Brand units and identifiers&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enforce exhaustiveness during code review and in CI&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your on call shifts will be quieter, and your users will notice the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Further reading&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Functional programming&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Algebraic data type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Tagged union or sum type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Product type&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pattern matching&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Immutable object&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Pure function&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;High availability&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Appendix: paste ready helpers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;// TypeScript Option and Result
export type None = { _tag: "None" }
export type Some&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Some"; value: T }
export type Option&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; = None | Some&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;
export const None: None = { _tag: "None" }
export const Some = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Option&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Some", value })

export type Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;  = { _tag: "Ok"; value: T }
export type Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt; = { _tag: "Err"; error: E }
export type Result&amp;lt;T, E&amp;gt; = Ok&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; | Err&amp;lt;E&amp;gt;
export const Ok  = &amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(value: T): Result&amp;lt;T, never&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Ok", value })
export const Err = &amp;lt;E&amp;gt;(error: E): Result&amp;lt;never, E&amp;gt; =&amp;gt; ({ _tag: "Err", error })

export const assertNever = (x: never): never =&amp;gt; { throw new Error(`Unhandled variant: ${JSON.stringify(x)}`) }
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;(* OCaml Option and Result helpers *)
let option_map f = function
  | None -&amp;gt; None
  | Some x -&amp;gt; Some (f x)

let option_value ~default = function
  | None -&amp;gt; default
  | Some x -&amp;gt; x

let result_map f = function
  | Ok x -&amp;gt; Ok (f x)
  | Error e -&amp;gt; Error e
&lt;/code&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46406901</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 00:05:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Replacing JavaScript with Just HTML</title><link>https://www.htmhell.dev/adventcalendar/2025/27/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3e52da19219ff136"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can also use other input types:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;label for="quantity"&amp;gt;Quantity&amp;lt;/label&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that, at the time of this writing, Firefox was limited to only textual-based input types, so no &lt;code&gt;date&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;time&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;range&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;color&lt;/code&gt; for now... :-(&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also note that, at the time of this writing, there are limitations on mobile, and accessibility concerns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;popover&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;popovertarget&lt;/code&gt; attributes can replace the traditional JS-driven modal/popover/overlay:&lt;lb/&gt;CodePen: Modal / Popover&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An &lt;code&gt;auto&lt;/code&gt; popover (default) can be "light dismissed" (clicking outside of it or hitting the &lt;code&gt;esc&lt;/code&gt; key). Opening an &lt;code&gt;auto&lt;/code&gt; automatically closes any other &lt;code&gt;auto&lt;/code&gt; popovers that were open. Clicking the &lt;code&gt;button&lt;/code&gt; a second time will close the one it opened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button popovertarget="pop-auto"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;hint&lt;/code&gt; popover can also be "light dismissed". It does not close other &lt;code&gt;hint&lt;/code&gt; popovers when opened. Clicking the &lt;code&gt;button&lt;/code&gt; a second time will close the one it opened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button popovertarget="pop-hint"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that, at the time of this writing, Firefox and all iOS varieties do not support &lt;code&gt;hint&lt;/code&gt; popovers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;manual&lt;/code&gt; popover can not be "light dismissed". It does not close other &lt;code&gt;manual&lt;/code&gt; popovers when opened. Clicking the &lt;code&gt;button&lt;/code&gt; a second time will close the one it opened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button popovertarget="pop-manual"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;Learn more about the opening and closing dialogs and popovers in the previously-published âControlling dialogs and popovers with the Invoker Commands API".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;popover&lt;/code&gt; page&lt;p&gt;The above Modal / Popover functionality can also be used to create an offscreen navigation that requires no JS:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CodePen: Offscreen Content&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button popovertarget="menu"&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code&gt;#menu {&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;I use a &lt;code&gt;nav&lt;/code&gt; element to give it semantic value, but you can use any HTML element (&lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;section&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;aside&lt;/code&gt;, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;popover&lt;/code&gt; defaults to &lt;code&gt;position: fixed&lt;/code&gt; per the User Agent Stylesheet, and is simply pushed off screen when closed, and pulled back onscreen when it is open. Note that &lt;code&gt;margin: 0&lt;/code&gt; is required if you want to override the User Agent center-alignment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clicking outside of the above menu closes it. You can force the panel to stay open, requiring a manual/explicit close, by using &lt;code&gt;popover="manual"&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can also add a &lt;code&gt;backdrop&lt;/code&gt; pseudo element and style it as you wish:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;#menu::backdrop {&lt;/code&gt;&lt;p&gt;While we all love the power and flexibility JS provides, we should also respect it, and our users, by limiting its use to what it needs to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is so much more that has changed in recent years, including a ton of options that CSS now covers. If you are now hungry for more, have a look at [my longer article that covers those as well](https://aarontgrogg.com/blog/2023/05/31/replace-js-with-no-js-or-lo-js-options/.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy reducing!&lt;lb/&gt;Atg&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Web Developer / Performance Optimization Specialist&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blog: aarontgrogg.com&lt;lb/&gt;BlueSky: aarontgrogg.bsky.social&lt;lb/&gt;Mastodon: mastodon.social/@aarontgrogg&lt;lb/&gt;LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/aarontgrogg&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46407337</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 01:07:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fathers’ choices may be packaged and passed down in sperm RNA</title><link>https://www.quantamagazine.org/how-dads-fitness-may-be-packaged-and-passed-down-in-sperm-rna-20251222/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f66c934f689e0b5b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;How Dad’s Fitness May Be Packaged and Passed Down in Sperm RNA&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The standard sperm-meets-egg story posits that sperm cells are hardly more than bundles of shrink-wrapped DNA with tails. Their mission is simple: Deliver a father’s genes into a mother’s egg for sexual reproduction. Just about all other aspects of a developing embryo, including its cellular and environmental components, have nothing to do with dad. Those all come from mom.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But nearly two decades of studies from multiple independent labs threaten to rewrite that story. They suggest that dad’s gametes shuttle more than DNA: Within a sperm’s minuscule head are stowaway molecules, which enter the egg and convey information about the father’s fitness, such as diet, exercise habits and stress levels, to his offspring. These non-DNA transfers may influence genomic activity that boots up during and after fertilization, exerting some control over the embryo’s development and influencing the adult they will become.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The findings, so far largely described in mouse models, could end up changing the way we think about heredity. They suggest “that what we do in this life affects the next generation,” said Qi Chen, a reproductive and developmental biologist at the University of Utah Medical School who is among the pioneers of this research. In other words: What a father eats, drinks, inhales, is stressed by or otherwise experiences in the weeks and months before he conceives a child might be encoded in molecules, packaged into his sperm cells and transmitted to his future kid. The researchers have largely zeroed in on RNA molecules, those short-lived copies of DNA that reflect genetic activity at a given time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a tantalizing notion. But the mechanistic details — how experience is encoded, how it’s transferred from sperm to egg, and whether and how it affects a developing embryo — are not easy to unpack, especially given the challenges of conducting research in human subjects. For this reason, and because of the potentially textbook-rewriting implications of the findings, researchers, including those spearheading the work, are cautious about overselling their results.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It’s still very hand-wavy,” said the epigeneticist Colin Conine of the University of Pennsylvania Perelman School of Medicine and Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, who has been trying to uncover the mechanics of how sperm RNA can contribute nongenetic information to progeny. Some elements of the story are clear, he said: Researchers have significant evidence that the environment can regulate sperm RNAs, that these molecules transmit traits to offspring and that they can regulate embryonic development after fertilization. “We just don’t have really any understanding of how RNAs can do this, and that’s the hand-wavy part,” Conine said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But evidence keeps piling up. Most recently, in November 2025, a comprehensive paper published in Cell Metabolism traced the downstream molecular effects of a father mouse’s exercise regimen on sperm microRNAs that target genes “critical for mitochondrial function and metabolic control” in a developing embryo. The researchers found many of those same RNAs overexpressed in the sperm of well-exercised human men.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This study shows that paternal exercise can confer benefits — enhanced endurance and metabolic health — to offspring,” said Chen, who was not involved in the study. “It’s a powerful reminder that many sperm-mediated epigenetic effects are deeply adaptive in nature.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The possibility that a previously undocumented avenue of inheritance is at play is too important to ignore. That’s why the researchers are now hunkering down in their labs to trace out the molecular processes that would have to operate for a father’s here-and-now experience to be transferred as developmental instructions to his partner’s egg.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Epigenetic Avenues&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In most animals, a sperm cell is tiny compared to an egg cell. In humans, an egg contains 10 million times the volume of a sperm and contributes most cellular components — nutrition, cytoplasm, mitochondria and other organelles, the molecular machinery to make proteins, and more — to a zygote (a newly fertilized egg that hasn’t started dividing). Plus, a mother provides the environment within which an embryo and then fetus develops and grows. As a result, the effect of a mother’s health on her children has long been scrutinized, including at the molecular level. But over the past 15 years or so, the evidence for some kind of non-DNA inheritance of paternal experience has also been strengthening.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“There are many different labs that have done diet and stress studies, and typically the readouts of those in the next generation are either metabolism or behavioral changes,” Conine said. Feed a male mouse a high-fat or low-protein diet, or take him away from his mom when he is young, and his offspring will inherit traits, such as changes in mitochondrial function, related to those environmental conditions. These traits aren’t necessarily detrimental. For instance, mouse fathers exposed to nicotine sire male pups with livers that are good at disarming not just nicotine but cocaine and other toxins as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a survival logic here, said Oliver Rando, an epigeneticist at the University of Massachusetts Chan Medical School who led the nicotine study. It’s reasonable to expect that offspring will experience an environmental context similar to that of their parents. Biologically priming them for those conditions could therefore help them survive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“You might think of this as a way to tell your kids something useful for them so that they can be better at dealing with the world they inherit,” said Rando, a father of two boys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But logic does not make the story true. That’s why Chen, Rando, Conine and other researchers have been working to uncover the mechanistic components of dad-based epigenetic heredity to add to what is already known about these processes in mothers. “Epigenetics” refers to heredity processes that do not change the DNA sequences of genes, but rather involve when and to what degree genes are expressed and made into functional proteins. Epigeneticists focus on the molecular biology that unfolds around genomic and chromosomal frameworks that can switch genes on and off in response to internal and external cues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This kind of differential gene expression is central to some of biology’s greatest wonders — for example, the fact that all cells in the human body have the same DNA, and yet brain cells differ dramatically from liver, skin and blood cells. Some cues that trigger changes in gene expression are programmed into DNA, while others come from the environment — for example, a dearth of calories or nutrients due to food deprivation, or rising cortisol levels due to stressors such as the absence of parental care. These conditions affect the kinds of metabolites and other molecules circulating in our bodies, which influences what kinds of reactions and genomic processes cells can carry out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some molecules involved in epigenetic processes, such as methyl or acetyl groups, interface directly with DNA or bind to proteins attached to DNA. These actions loosen up or batten down portions of the genome and are akin to opening or closing doors to specific genes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RNA molecules — flexible, ephemeral versions of DNA sequences — can also intervene in gene expression. But because they are relatively short-lived, sometimes surviving mere minutes or hours before degrading, they have been overlooked as epigenetic regulators. Since the 1990s, their roles have been clarified, as has their longevity: Certain RNAs can survive for weeks or longer. Some RNAs (such as long noncoding RNAs, or lncRNAs) regulate gene expression by modifying DNA or its proteins. Others, known as microRNAs, alter or repress other RNAs, including those that would otherwise be translated into proteins; this discovery was awarded the 2024 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could sperm carry RNA or other molecules that then participate in epigenetic processes in the embryo? It seemed plausible to some researchers, but it would take a whole lot of experimental work to put the pieces together.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Package of RNA&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are three core questions that biologists need to resolve to confirm that sperm cells transmit epigenetic inheritance. The first is how a father’s body physically encodes lived experience, such as stress, diet, exercise or nicotine use, in the form of molecules — for example, as RNAs circulating in blood that reflect gene expression in tissues. The next centers on how molecularly encoded experience could make its way into sperm cells. The third traces how those signals in sperm could become epigenetic vectors during and after fertilization to specify observable traits, known as phenotypes, in offspring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a series of studies beginning in 2012, Qi Chen started answering all three questions. In what he describes as one of the most serendipitous discoveries of his career, his team at the Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing used sequencing techniques to inventory the short RNA molecules present in mice sperm cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They were shocked to see a subset of the RNAs drastically increasing in concentration as sperm cells matured, and then crowding into the sperm heads with DNA. This same class of RNAs was abundant in the blood serum of various vertebrates, ranging from fish to humans, they found. All of this pointed to the possibility that information-carrying molecules were being transferred into the reproductive cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It got even more interesting when Chen, who moved to the U.S. academic circuit in 2015, and his team collected sperm RNAs from male mice fed different diets. The RNA assemblages in mice reared on high-fat foods differed dramatically from those in mice that were fed normal diets. And when the researchers injected the RNAs from the sperm of the fat-eating mice into a zygote, some of the male offspring showed metabolic issues associated with a high-fat diet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The experiments hinted at a seemingly heretical possibility, Chen said: that “certain acquired traits during paternal exposure can be ‘memorized’ in the sperm and inherited by the offspring.” After characterizing a pathway that regulates sperm RNAs, in 2019 Chen dubbed this channel of heredity the “sperm RNA code,” which he suggested “programs the metabolic health of offspring.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He wasn’t the only one to become fixated on this idea. Around the same time, in an article published in Developmental Cell in 2018, Rando’s team reported the use of biochemical techniques to characterize where and when RNAs are packaged into sperm cells and how those RNAs might change during this process. They were trying to answer the question: “What tissue could be responsible for choosing what to tell sperm to tell kids?” he said. One logical place to start looking was the epididymis. Within this tubular organ attached to the back of the testicle, sperm cells undergo a maturation process, taking about one to two weeks in most mammalian species, before they become ready for fertilization.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rando’s data showed that sperm cells gain almost all their small RNAs when they are in the epididymis. Using techniques for tracking specific RNA molecules, the scientists observed RNAs getting packaged into virus-size capsules, called epididymosomes, which shuttled the molecules into sperm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“This shows how small RNAs can get trafficked between the body’s nonreproductive cells, like those in the epididymis, and germline cells,” such as sperm, Rando said. “The epididymis has been emerging as a key location for paternal effects. Certainly the epididymis has to be taken seriously as a potential sensor of the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Molecular Snapshot&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By “sensor of the world,” Rando is referring to the first stage of a presumed paternal-effects mechanism — when a male’s body translates a lived condition, such as a high-fat diet, rigorous exercise or toxin exposure, into molecular signals. The epididymis then provides a route for the second step, packaging those signals for the next generation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is also where investigations by Isabelle Mansuy come in. At the University of Zurich and the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology Zurich, she studies the molecular and cellular mechanisms of epigenetic inheritance in mammals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;© Philippe Rossier / Ringier Media Switzerland&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In one line of her research, she focuses on processes that transmit the molecular effects of traumatic stress to subsequent generations by focusing on extracellular vesicles (EVs) that circulate in blood. Shed by almost every type of cell in the body, including in the epididymis (the epididymosomes are EVs), they carry a diversity of molecular cargo, such as RNAs, proteins, lipids and metabolites. Because EVs circulate in blood just about anywhere in the body and can cross cell membranes, they provide a potential means to transfer molecules and the biological cues they carry between bodily tissues and reproductive cells. Notably, RNAs tend to survive longer when packaged in EVs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mansuy creates trauma in mice by subjecting the animals to conditions such as restraint or maternal separation when they are young. Then she searches for molecular changes in reproductive cells that could cause similar consequences of trauma to manifest in the children or even grandchildren of the animals who directly endure it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She’s shown that traumatic stress alters metabolic pathways, especially those that involve lipids, in exposed male mice and their offspring. She has also found a similar metabolic profile in humans who experienced high stress in childhood. In mice, some of the metabolic changes remained discernible through five generations — a rare data-backed finding for epigenetic inheritance cascading through generations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dennis Kunkel Microscopy/Science Source&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In March 2025, in a preprint uploaded to biorxiv.org, Mansuy and colleagues reported that EVs in mice can transport certain RNAs, metabolites and lipids linked to early-life stress from circulating blood to sperm, with consequences for offspring. The offspring produced by these sperm cells had stress-related metabolic dysfunction as adults and bore the stress signatures in their own sperm RNA. “These changes imply a mechanistic link between sperm RNA modifications and phenotypic features in the offspring,” Mansuy’s team concluded in their paper, which has not yet been peer-reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Phenotypic Translation&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perhaps the trickiest step to understand is how sperm-borne molecules could influence an adult’s observable traits. In one form of experiment, researchers extract all the sperm RNA from mice that have been raised under stressful or health-altering conditions. Those isolated RNAs are then injected into a zygote. Pups that emerge usually “get the dad’s phenotypes,” Conine said, suggesting that the RNAs alone confer traits from dad to offspring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But how? During early development, epigenetic processes reign. As one fertilized cell divides into two, and those cells divide again, and so on, one set of DNA instructions is dynamically and repeatedly reprogrammed. The growing body specializes into different cell types and is sculpted into a sequence of increasingly complex forms. It’s possible, then, that early epigenetic alterations to the genome could have significant downstream effects on an adult.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Research out of Conine’s lab, published in 2024, showed that sperm microRNAs alter gene expression in mouse embryos. Experiments like these, he said, support the idea that offspring can inherit paternal traits via the transfer of non-DNA molecular stowaways in sperm.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The recent Cell Metabolism paper took this idea a step further by tracing a mechanism by which this can happen. A team of more than two dozen Chinese researchers focused on the epigenetic transmission of exercise benefits, homing in on a set of microRNAs that reprogram gene expression in the early embryo. These changes ultimately result in skeletal muscle adaptations in adult offspring that enhance exercise endurance. The researchers found that well-exercised mice had more of these microRNAs in their sperm than sedentary mice did. When these microRNAs were transferred into zygotes, the adults they grew into were more physically fit, with more mitochondria in skeletal muscle and higher endurance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But how did the molecules generate the exercise-positive phenotype? In experiments, the researchers found that the microRNAs suppressed a particular protein, which had the effect of boosting genes related to mitochondrial activity and metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Intriguingly, the sperm of physically trained male humans also hosted higher levels of many of the same microRNAs than those of untrained cohorts. “This cross-species conservation suggests a potential role for these sperm mi[cro]RNAs in intergenerational exercise adaptations in humans,” the researchers wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The First Draft&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The notion that a father’s lived experience can become recorded by his body, transmitted to his gametes and relayed to his offspring is no longer as outlandish as it once seemed. Many researchers in the field are willing to float speculative visions of what could be going on, even as they acknowledge that gaps remain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Our hypothesis is that the epididymis ‘sees’ the world and alters the small RNAs it produces in response,” Rando said. “These RNAs are then delivered to the zygote upon fertilization and control early gene regulation and development to shape offspring health and disease.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conine speculates that once certain RNAs make their way into the egg, they trigger “a cascade of changes in developmental gene expression that then leads to these phenotypes” of the father showing up in the next generation. Remarkably, this unfolds even though the sheer volume of the sperm’s contents is so much less than an egg’s contents, including the relative amounts of RNA.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The full picture of how paternal experience and behavior might epigenetically influence offspring is not nearly in hand. Researchers are currently piecing the story together, one experiment at a time, rather than proving out every step sequentially in the same set of organisms. One of the gaps is in the characterization of what RNA and perhaps other epigenetic factors do in the zygote to modify genomic activity as it unfolds during development, Mansuy said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We are still blind men describing for the first time different parts of the same elephant,” Chen said. “The underlying mechanism is almost certainly an orchestra of a sperm RNA code and factors beyond that.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Confirming the findings in humans would take enormous effort, but it would be key to turning these findings in mice into “informed medical advice,” Chen said. This would require well-controlled experiments following multiple generations, tracking diet, exercise, aging and environmental exposures, while also using advanced tools to decode sperm-packaged molecules — and then looking for strong correlations between the molecular and phenotypic data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even amid the uncertainties, researchers are cautiously moving forward as they learn to believe the results of their own experiments. If they’re right, they will have discovered a new fact of life, Rando said. When he thinks about his two boys, he wonders what he might have done differently when he was younger, before they were born, that might have tweaked his RNA profile in ways that would affect them today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We don’t know enough yet to develop guidance like that,” Rando said. “Maybe we will get there.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46407502</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 01:33:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dialtone – AOL 3.0 Server</title><link>https://dialtone.live/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46408192</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 03:40:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Calendar</title><link>https://neatnik.net/calendar/?year=2026</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="5ff9519dbc2b8b32"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;👋 Hello! If you print this page, you’ll get a nifty calendar that displays all of the year’s dates on a single page. It will automatically fit on a single sheet of paper of any size. For best results, adjust your print settings to landscape orientation and disable the header and footer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take in the year all at once. Fold it up and carry it with you. Jot down your notes on it. Plan things out and observe the passage of time. Above all else, be kind to others.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Looking for 2026? Here you go!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2026&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Jan&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Feb&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Mar&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Apr&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;May&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Jun&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Jul&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Aug&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Sep&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Oct&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Nov&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Dec&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4 F&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;7 M&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;8 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;9 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;11 F&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;12 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;13 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;14 M&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;15 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;16 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;17 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;18 F&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;19 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;20 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;21 M&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;22 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;23 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;24 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;25 F&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;26 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;27 S&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;28 M&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;29 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="12"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 W&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 W&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 T&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 F&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 M&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 S&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;31 T&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46408613</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 05:02:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Growing up in “404 Not Found”: China's nuclear city in the Gobi Desert</title><link>https://substack.com/inbox/post/182743659</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46408988</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 06:43:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hungry Fat Cells Could Someday Starve Cancer</title><link>https://www.ucsf.edu/news/2025/01/429411/how-hungry-fat-cells-could-someday-starve-cancer-death</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3348413b9eaeeb1b"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Liposuction and plastic surgery aren’t often mentioned in the same breath as cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But they are the inspiration for a new approach to treating cancer that uses engineered fat cells to deprive tumors of nutrition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers at UC San Francisco used the gene editing technology CRISPR to turn ordinary white fat cells into “beige” fat cells, which voraciously consume calories to make heat. The work is funded by the National Institute of Health (NIH).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then, they implanted them near tumors the way plastic surgeons inject fat from one part of the body to plump up another. The fat cells scarfed up all the nutrients, starving most of the tumor cells to death. The approach even worked when the fat cells were implanted in mice far from the sites of their tumors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The approach's reliance on a common procedure could speed its use as a new form of cellular therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We already routinely remove fat cells with liposuction and put them back via plastic surgery,” said Nadav Ahituv, PhD, director of the UCSF Institute for Human Genetics and professor in the Department of Bioengineering and Therapeutic Sciences. He is the senior author of the paper, which appears Feb. 4 in Nature Biotechnology. “These fat cells can be easily manipulated in the lab and safely placed back into the body, making them an attractive platform for cellular therapy, including for cancer.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; Cold therapy sparks a new idea&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ahituv and his post-doc at the time, Hai Nguyen, PhD, were aware of studies that showed exposure to cold could suppress cancer in mice. One experiment even showed it could help a patient with non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Scientists concluded that the cancer cells were starving because the cold was activating brown fat cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But cold therapy isn’t a viable option for cancer patients with fragile health. So, Ahituv and Nguyen turned to the idea of using beige fat, wagering that they could engineer it to burn enough calories, even in the absence of cold, to deprive tumors of the fuel they needed to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nguyen, who is the first author of the paper, used CRISPR to activate genes that are dormant in white fat cells but are active in brown fat cells, in the hopes of finding the ones that would transform the white fat cells into the hungriest of beige fat cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A gene called UCP1 rose to the top. Nguyen grew UCP1 beige fat cells and cancer cells in a “trans-well” petri dish. The cancer cells were on the bottom and the fat cells were above them in separate compartments that kept the cells apart but forced them to share nutrients. The results were shocking.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In our very first trans-well experiment, very few cancer cells survived. We thought we had messed something up – we were sure it was a mistake,” Ahituv recalled. “So, we repeated it multiple times, and we kept seeing the same effect.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The beige fat cells held sway over two different types of breast cancer cells, as well as colon, pancreatic and prostate cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No fat cells: Actively-multiplying cancer cells (pink) are seen in a mouse predisposed to develop breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fat cells are added: When fat cells were implanted in the breast, far fewer cancer cells were able to multiply.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Cancer is no match for hungry fat&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the researchers still didn’t know if the beige fat cells would work in a more realistic context. So, they turned to fat organoids, which are coherent clumps of cells grown in a dish, to see if they could beat tumor cells when they were implanted next to tumors in mice. The approach worked against breast cancer, as well as pancreatic and prostate cancer cells. The cancer cells starved as the fat cells gobbled up all the available nutrients.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once implanted into mice that were genetically predisposed to develop cancer, the beige fat cells were so powerful that they suppressed pancreatic and breast tumors. Beige fat even worked when it was implanted far away from the breast cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To see how the fat cells would work in human tissue, Ahituv and Nguyen teamed up with Jennifer Rosenbluth, MD, PhD, a breast cancer specialist at UCSF. Rosenbluth had amassed a library of breast cancer tissue from mastectomies containing both fat cells and cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Because the breast has a lot of fat, we could get fat from the same patient, modify the fat and grow it in a single trans-well experiment with that patient’s own breast cancer cells,” Ahituv said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These same-patient beige fat cells outcompeted breast cancer cells in petri dishes – and when they were implanted together in mouse models.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Knowing that cancers have preferred diets, the researchers engineered fat just to eat certain nutrients. Certain forms of pancreatic cancer, for example, rely on uridine when glucose is scarce. So, they programmed the fat cells to eat just uridine, and they easily outcompeted the pancreatic cancer cells. This suggested that fat could be adapted to any cancer’s dietary preferences.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A new approach to living cell therapy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fat cells have many advantages when it comes to living cell therapies, according to Ahituv. They are easy to obtain from patients. They grow well in the laboratory and can be engineered to express different genes and take on different biological roles. And they behave well once they are put back into the body, not straying from the location where they’re implanted and playing nice with the immune system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s a conclusion supported by decades of plastic surgery.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“With fat cells, there’s less interaction with the environment, so there’s very little worry of the cells leaking out into the body, where they might cause problems,” Ahituv said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fat cells can also be programmed to emit signals or carry out more complicated tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And their ability to defeat cancer even when they are not right next to tumors could prove invaluable for treating hard-to-reach cancers like glioblastoma, which affects the brain, as well as many other diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We think these cells could also be designed to sense glucose in the bloodstream and release insulin, for diabetes, or suck up iron in diseases where there’s excessive iron like hemochromatosis,” Ahituv said. “The sky’s the limit for these fat cells.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;A pioneering scientist is lost too soon&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The discovery of how hungry fat cells could suppress cancer began in 2021, when Hai Nguyen, PhD, joined Ahituv’s lab. Nguyen had years of experience working with fat cells in the laboratory. But he wasn’t aware of their cancer-fighting potential until an experiment pitting engineered beige fat cells against cancer cells tipped them off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazed at how the beige fat was able to starve the tumors, they tested the engineered cells against all sorts of cancers in the lab. The project grew to include other scientists and cancer specialists at UCSF and across the country, offering a proof of principle that the approach could work against a wide range of cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nguyen moved to UT Austin to start his own lab in January 2024 but passed away suddenly in November before he could finish the final experiments. The paper, of which he is the first author, is dedicated to him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Hai was one of the most amazing post-docs I’ll ever have and a great friend,” Ahituv said. “We are heartbroken. He has left us with this incredible gift of a technology that could truly change lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;A pioneering scientist is lost&lt;lb/&gt; too soon&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The discovery of how hungry fat cells could suppress cancer began in 2021, when Hai Nguyen, PhD, joined Ahituv’s lab. Nguyen had years of experience working with fat cells in the laboratory. But he wasn’t aware of their cancer-fighting potential until an experiment pitting engineered beige fat cells against cancer cells tipped them off.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Amazed at how the beige fat was able to starve the tumors, they tested the engineered cells against all sorts of cancers in the lab. The project grew to include other scientists and cancer specialists at UCSF and across the country, offering a proof of principle that the approach could work against a wide range of cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nguyen moved to UT Austin to start his own lab in January 2024 but passed away suddenly in November before he could finish the final experiments. The paper, of which he is the first author, is dedicated to him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Hai was one of the most amazing post-docs I’ll ever have and a great friend,” Ahituv said. “We are heartbroken. He has left us with this incredible gift of a technology that could truly change lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;lb/&gt; Authors: In addition to Ahituv, Nguyen, and Rosenbluth, other UCSF authors include Kelly An, Yusuke Ito, Bhushan N. Kharbikar, PhD, Rory Sheng, Breanna Paredes, MS, Elizabeth Murray, Kimberly Pham, Michael Bruck, Xujia Zhou, MS, PhD, Cassidy Biellak, Aki Ushiki, PhD, Mai Nobuhara, MS, Daniel A. Bernards, PhD, Mark Jesus M. Magbanua, PhD, Laura A. Huppert, MD, Heinz Hammerlindl, PhD, Laura Esserman, MD, MBA, Tejal A. Desai, PhD, and Sook Wah Yee, MPharm. For all authors see the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Funding: The work was funded in part by the UCSF Sandler Program for Breakthrough Biomedical Research, the UCSF Living Therapeutics Initiative, the National Institutes of Health (1R01DK124769, 1R01CA283826) and the California Institute for Regenerative Medicine. Ahituv is a cofounder and on the scientific advisory board of Regel Therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disclosures: Ahituv receives funding from BioMarin Pharmaceutical Incorporate. Ahituv has filed a patent application covering embodiments and concepts disclosed in the manuscript. For all funding and disclosures see the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46409928</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 10:04:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Last Year on My Mac: Look Back in Disbelief</title><link>https://eclecticlight.co/2025/12/28/last-year-on-my-mac-look-back-in-disbelief/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="26bce657dc5791ff"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If someone had told me 12 months ago what was going to happen this past year, I wouldn’t have believed them. Skipping swiftly past all the political, economic and social turmoil, I come to the interface changes brought in macOS Tahoe with Liquid Glass. After three months of strong feedback during beta-testing, I was disappointed when Tahoe was released on 15 September to see how little had been addressed. When 26.1 followed on 3 November it had only regressed, and 26.2 has done nothing. Here I summarise my opinions on where Tahoe’s overhaul has gone wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;What goes round&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Almost all the content displayed in windows is best suited to rectangular views. Images, video, webpages and other text crave areas bounded by right angles. Gentle rounding on the corners, as in Sequoia, is fine, but the significantly increased radius enforced in Tahoe is a misfit. This either leads to cropping of contents, or reduction in size of the view and wasted space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cropping is misleading, as seen in this enlarged view of a thumbnail image in the Finder’s Gallery view, compared to the larger version shown below. The thumbnail misrepresents what’s in the original.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among Apple’s claims for this new look is greater consistency. But two windows in the same app, both created using SwiftUI, can’t even share a common radius, as shown below in Providable running in macOS 26.2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Out of control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tahoe has also increased the size of its controls, without using that to improve their clarity. The best way to see that is in my Mallyshag demo app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This looks good in Sequoia above, but becomes a mess in Tahoe (below) because of its changed control dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those three buttons are significantly wider, so now overlap one another and are wider than the text box below. The user sees no benefit to this, though, as the text within the controls is identical.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Iconoclasm&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;App icons need to be both distinguishable and readily recalled. The first ensures that we can tell one from another, and relies on all the visual cues we can muster, including colours, form and content. Tahoe enforces a rule that everything in the icon must be fitted inside its uniform square with rounded corners, so restricting cues to colours and contents. As a result, the icons of many bundled and other Apple apps have become harder to distinguish in a crowded Dock. Some, including Apple’s Developer app and the App Store, are indistinguishable, while others have degenerated into vague blotches.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Above are most of the apps bundled in Sequoia, and below are those in Tahoe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Whiteout&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In real life, whiteouts are dangerous because they’re so disorienting. There’s no horizon, no features in the landscape, and no clues to navigation. We see and work best in visual environments that are rich in colour and tonal contrasts. Tahoe has continued a trend for Light Mode to be bleached-out white, and Dark Mode to be a moonless night. Seeing where controls, views and contents start and end is difficult, and leaves them suspended in the whiteout.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In light mode, with default transparency, tool icons and text are clearly distinguished tonally, as are some controls including buttons and checkboxes. However, text entry fields are indistinguishable from the background, and there’s a general lack of demarcation, particularly between controls and the list view below.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Wet-on-wet&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This technique is used in watercolours to merge layers of colour diffusely, and the best description of some of the results of transparency in Liquid Glass. My examples speak for themselves, and are drawn first from Apple’s own design for System Settings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transparency of the Search box at the top of the sidebar on the left renders it incomprehensible when it’s underlaid by scrolled navigational content.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although the view title Keyboard remains readable, bleed-through of underlying colours is confusing, distracting and aesthetically upsetting.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My next examples show the same window in Providable with a selected list row being scrolled up behind what used to be a window title bar.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With the window in focus, the selection colour overwhelms the traffic light controls and window title, which should read Drop Files. This also draws attention to the limited width necessary to accommodate rectangular content in a window with excessively rounded corners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Out of focus the selected row is less overwhelming, but traffic lights and title have dissipated in grey blur.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m sure that, in the right place and time, transparency effects of Liquid Glass can be visually pleasing. Not only is this the wrong time and place, but those with visual impairment can no longer remove or even reduce these effects, as the Reduce Transparency control in Accessibility settings no longer reduces transparency in any useful way. That was one of the regressions in 26.1 that hasn’t been addressed in 26.2.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Summary&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;macOS Tahoe’s visual interface:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fits largely rectangular contents into windows with excessively rounded corners.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enlarges controls without any functional benefit.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Results in app icons being more uniform, thus less distinguishable and memorable.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fails to distinguish tools, controls and other interface elements using differences in tone, so making them harder to use.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Makes a mess where transparent layers are superimposed, and won’t reduce transparency when that’s needed to render its interface more accessible.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Maybe this is because I’m getting older, but that gives me the benefit of having experienced Apple’s older interfaces, with their exceptional quality and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That was little more than a decade ago, in 2014. Not that I want to turn the clock back, but it would be really helpful if I could read clearly what’s on my display once again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46409969</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 10:12:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Learn computer graphics from scratch and for free</title><link>https://www.scratchapixel.com</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="94021bf895f5cbe4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These lessons are structured to introduce 3D rendering concepts in a beginner-friendly order. Unlike most resources, we start with hands-on results before diving into theory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This section is dedicated to explaining the mathematical theories and tools used in creating images and simulations with a computer. It's not intended as a starting point, but rather as a reference to be consulted when these topics are mentioned in lessons from other sections.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46410210</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 11:08:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Building a macOS app to know when my Mac is thermal throttling</title><link>https://stanislas.blog/2025/12/macos-thermal-throttling-app/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="25dc742d3b2ac9ec"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Building a macOS app to know when my Mac is thermal throttling&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head class="block cursor-pointer bg-neutral-100 py-1 ps-5 text-lg font-semibold text-neutral-800 dark:bg-neutral-700 dark:text-neutral-100 lg:hidden"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the story about how I built MacThrottle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been very happy with my M2 MacBook Air for the past few years. However, when using an external display, especially a very demanding one like a 4K 120Hz display, I’ve noticed it started struggling more. Since it lacks fans, you can’t hear it struggling, but you can feel it as everything becomes very slow or unresponsive: that’s when thermal throttling kicks in.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I know it’s thermal throttling because I can see in iStat Menus that my CPU usage is 100% while the power usage in watts goes down.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s even more obvious with MX Power Gadget: You can see the power usage and frequency of the performance core dropping, as usage keeps being 100%:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve also hit thermal throttling with my work MacBook Pro. It’s the 14" M4 Max variant, which is the worst variant because the thermal envelope of the 14" is too small for the max output for the M4 Max. On my previous 14" M1 Pro MacBook Pro, I’ve never even heard the fans in 3 years…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That being said, I still love Apple Silicon for the performance and power usage, it’s still a dramatic improvement over the Intel days. 🫶&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyway, I wanted to know: is there a way to tell if the Apple Silicon SoC is thermal throttling, that is not based on heuristics like in my screenshot?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Getting the thermal state programmatically #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This was a wilder ride than I expected. It’s possible to know programmatically if the Mac is throttled, because macOS exposes this in various but inconsistent ways.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The approach that Apple recommends is to use &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo.thermalState&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;Foundation&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ swift -e 'import Foundation; print(["nominal", "fair", "serious", "critical"][ProcessInfo.processInfo.thermalState.rawValue])'
nominal
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sounds good, right? However, I knew that another tool could provide this information, though it needed root: &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ sudo powermetrics -s thermal

Password:
Machine model: Mac14,2
OS version: 25B78
Boot arguments:
Boot time: Sun Nov 23 10:19:29 2025



*** Sampled system activity (Wed Dec 17 09:48:34 2025 +0100) (5001.07ms elapsed) ***



**** Thermal pressure ****

Current pressure level: Nominal


*** Sampled system activity (Wed Dec 17 09:48:39 2025 +0100) (5001.25ms elapsed) ***



**** Thermal pressure ****

Current pressure level: Nominal
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(yes the output has that many newlines)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both report the pressure level to be “nominal”, they must be the same…right?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After running a few stress tests &lt;code&gt;stress-ng --cpu 0 -t 600&lt;/code&gt;, I started to see the two values diverge!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For some reason, the granularity is different between &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo.thermalState&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt;. They have a different amount of possible states and they don’t line up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is my empirical experience:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo.thermalState&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;nominal&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;nominal&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;fair&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;moderate&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;fair&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;heavy&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I never managed to hit these states, so I don’t know if they match, but they’re technically defined:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo.thermalState&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;
          &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;serious&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;trapping&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;critical&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;sleeping&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In practice, when my Mac starts getting hot, from the &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt; perspective it goes into &lt;code&gt;moderate&lt;/code&gt;, and when it starts throttling, it goes into &lt;code&gt;heavy&lt;/code&gt;. The problem is that with &lt;code&gt;ProcessInfo&lt;/code&gt;, both are covered by the &lt;code&gt;fair&lt;/code&gt; state, so it’s not really useful to know when the Mac is actually throttling. ☹️&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought maybe this was an iOS vs macOS thing? But Apple references it in the macOS docs as well. Maybe it was more consistent on Intel Macs?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon this article from Dave MacLachlan, a Googler working on Apple stuff, from 2020. I learned that there are other CLI tools to get thermal data, but they don’t seem to work on my Apple Silicon MacBook:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜ sudo thermal levels
Thermal levels are unsupported on this machine.
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜ sudo pmset -g thermlog
Note: No thermal warning level has been recorded
Note: No performance warning level has been recorded
Note: No CPU power status has been recorded
^C
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the most interesting thing I learned is that the data &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt; shows is actually coming from &lt;code&gt;thermald&lt;/code&gt;. And &lt;code&gt;thermald&lt;/code&gt; writes the current thermal pressure to the Darwin notification system (&lt;code&gt;notifyd&lt;/code&gt;)!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜ notifyutil -g com.apple.system.thermalpressurelevel

com.apple.system.thermalpressurelevel 0
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The various levels are defined in &lt;code&gt;OSThermalNotification.h&lt;/code&gt; according to the article. Indeed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ xcrun --sdk macosx --show-sdk-path
/Applications/Xcode.app/Contents/Developer/Platforms/MacOSX.platform/Developer/SDKs/MacOSX26.2.sdk
➜  ~ SDK="$(xcrun --sdk macosx --show-sdk-path)"
➜  ~ find "$SDK/usr/include" -name 'OSThermalNotification.h'
/Applications/Xcode.app/Contents/Developer/Platforms/MacOSX.platform/Developer/SDKs/MacOSX26.2.sdk/usr/include/libkern/OSThermalNotification.h
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ head -n 52 "/Applications/Xcode.app/Contents/Developer/Platforms/MacOSX.platform/Developer/SDKs/MacOSX26.2.sdk/usr/include/libkern/OSThermalNotification.h"
/*
 * Copyright (c) 2007 Apple Inc. All rights reserved.
 *
 * @APPLE_LICENSE_HEADER_START@
 *
 * This file contains Original Code and/or Modifications of Original Code
 * as defined in and that are subject to the Apple Public Source License
 * Version 2.0 (the 'License'). You may not use this file except in
 * compliance with the License. Please obtain a copy of the License at
 * http://www.opensource.apple.com/apsl/ and read it before using this
 * file.
 *
 * The Original Code and all software distributed under the License are
 * distributed on an 'AS IS' basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER
 * EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, AND APPLE HEREBY DISCLAIMS ALL SUCH WARRANTIES,
 * INCLUDING WITHOUT LIMITATION, ANY WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
 * FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE, QUIET ENJOYMENT OR NON-INFRINGEMENT.
 * Please see the License for the specific language governing rights and
 * limitations under the License.
 *
 * @APPLE_LICENSE_HEADER_END@
 */

#ifndef _OSTHERMALNOTIFICATION_H_
#define _OSTHERMALNOTIFICATION_H_

#include &amp;lt;_bounds.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;sys/cdefs.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;Availability.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;TargetConditionals.h&amp;gt;

_LIBC_SINGLE_BY_DEFAULT()

/*
**  OSThermalNotification.h
**
**  Notification mechanism to alert registered tasks when device thermal conditions
**  reach certain thresholds. Notifications are triggered in both directions
**  so clients can manage their memory usage more and less aggressively.
**
*/

__BEGIN_DECLS

/* Define pressure levels usable by OSThermalPressureLevel */
typedef enum {
#if TARGET_OS_OSX || TARGET_OS_MACCATALYST
        kOSThermalPressureLevelNominal = 0,
        kOSThermalPressureLevelModerate,
        kOSThermalPressureLevelHeavy,
        kOSThermalPressureLevelTrapping,
        kOSThermalPressureLevelSleeping
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The funny thing is that &lt;code&gt;OSThermalNotification.h&lt;/code&gt; is barely referenced anywhere, there are only three pages of Google results. It seems to be used in Bazel for example. That post was a big help.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s great about this approach is that it doesn’t require root! I can subscribe to the notification system for the &lt;code&gt;com.apple.system.thermalpressurelevel&lt;/code&gt; event to get the (good) thermal state!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is a snippet to get it in Swift:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import Foundation

@_silgen_name("notify_register_check")
private func notify_register_check(
  _ name: UnsafePointer&amp;lt;CChar&amp;gt;, _ token: UnsafeMutablePointer&amp;lt;Int32&amp;gt;
) -&amp;gt; UInt32
@_silgen_name("notify_get_state")
private func notify_get_state(_ token: Int32, _ state: UnsafeMutablePointer&amp;lt;UInt64&amp;gt;) -&amp;gt; UInt32
@_silgen_name("notify_cancel")
private func notify_cancel(_ token: Int32) -&amp;gt; UInt32

let notifyOK: UInt32 = 0
let name = "com.apple.system.thermalpressurelevel"

var token: Int32 = 0
let reg = name.withCString { notify_register_check($0, &amp;amp;token) }
guard reg == notifyOK else { fatalError("notify_register_check failed: \(reg)") }
defer { _ = notify_cancel(token) }

var state: UInt64 = 0
let got = notify_get_state(token, &amp;amp;state)
guard got == notifyOK else { fatalError("notify_get_state failed: \(got)") }

let label =
  switch state {
  case 0: "nominal"
  case 1: "moderate"
  case 2: "heavy"
  case 3: "trapping"
  case 4: "sleeping"
  default: "unknown(\(state))"
  }

print("\(state) \(label)")
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prints:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ swift thermal.swift
0 nominal
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that I had a useful value to work with, it was time to build the app.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Building MacThrottle #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Armed with Opus 4.5, I set out to build a little menu bar app where I could see, at a glance, if my Apple Silicon die was trying to save itself from crossing 110°C. I called it MacThrottle.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I built a simple SwiftUI app for the menu bar that shows me the status in a superbly original thermometer icon. The thermometer is filled depending on the thermal state, and its color changes from green to red. I have like 20 menu bar icons and they’re all monochromatic, so the color in the thermometer is very subtle to keep things consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The app is a simple SwiftUI app. Apple provides a scene called MenuBarExtra to render a menu bar control. It was simpler than I expected! To make it a pure menu bar app with no dock icon, you just need to set &lt;code&gt;LSUIElement&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;Info.plist&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;First approach: root helper for &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt; #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I explained the various approaches to get the thermal pressure level in the previous section. But when I was building the app, I discovered later on that &lt;code&gt;thermald&lt;/code&gt; was publishing the thermal state to &lt;code&gt;notifyd&lt;/code&gt;. So at first, I thought I had to use &lt;code&gt;powermetrics&lt;/code&gt; to get useful thermal state changes. Since that unfortunately requires root access, the app needed root access too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To reduce the scope of what runs as root, I did not run the app itself as root. Instead, the app does not work by default, but it gives you the option to install a helper. It does this through an AppleScript &lt;code&gt;with administrator privileges&lt;/code&gt; to prompt for access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The helper is just a bash script run as a launchd daemon:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ cat /Library/LaunchDaemons/com.macthrottle.thermal-monitor.plist
&amp;lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE plist PUBLIC "-//Apple//DTD PLIST 1.0//EN" "http://www.apple.com/DTDs/PropertyList-1.0.dtd"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;plist version="1.0"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;dict&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;key&amp;gt;Label&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;string&amp;gt;com.macthrottle.thermal-monitor&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;key&amp;gt;ProgramArguments&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;array&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;string&amp;gt;/usr/local/bin/mac-throttle-thermal-monitor&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/array&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;key&amp;gt;RunAtLoad&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;true/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;key&amp;gt;KeepAlive&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;true/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dict&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/plist&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;➜  ~ cat /usr/local/bin/mac-throttle-thermal-monitor
#!/bin/bash
OUTPUT_FILE="/tmp/mac-throttle-thermal-state"

while true; do
    THERMAL_OUTPUT=$(powermetrics -s thermal -n 1 -i 1 2&amp;gt;/dev/null | grep -i "Current pressure level")

    if echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "sleeping"; then
        PRESSURE="sleeping"
    elif echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "trapping"; then
        PRESSURE="trapping"
    elif echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "heavy"; then
        PRESSURE="heavy"
    elif echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "moderate"; then
        PRESSURE="moderate"
    elif echo "$THERMAL_OUTPUT" | grep -qi "nominal"; then
        PRESSURE="nominal"
    else
        PRESSURE="unknown"
    fi

    echo "{\"pressure\":\"$PRESSURE\",\"timestamp\":$(date +%s)}" &amp;gt; "$OUTPUT_FILE"
    chmod 644 "$OUTPUT_FILE"
    sleep 10
done
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The bash script writes the thermal state to a file every few seconds and the app reads it every few seconds!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Using the &lt;code&gt;thermald&lt;/code&gt; IPC notifications #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once I discovered I could use the notification system without elevated privileges, I replaced the helper by code in the app to read the value from the notification system directly. Much simpler 🎉&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Temperature and fans #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wanted to show the temperature and fan speed (when supported) in a little graph in the menu bar app. This would allow me to correlate the thermal state with increased temperature, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Again, there are multiple APIs to read the temperature. First, I started using an undocumented API from IOKit, but I realised I was getting ~80ºC max, while iStat Menus or MX Power Gadget would show &amp;gt;100ºC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stats, the open source alternative to iStat Menus, helped me use the SMC instead and get the correct values. But the SMC is a much more unstable API because each SoC has different keys to access the temperature data:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;private let m1Keys = ["Tp01", "Tp05", "Tp09", "Tp0D", "Tp0H", "Tp0L", "Tp0P", "Tp0X", "Tp0b"]
private let m2Keys = ["Tp01", "Tp05", "Tp09", "Tp0D", "Tp0X", "Tp0b", "Tp0f", "Tp0j"]
private let m3Keys = ["Tf04", "Tf09", "Tf0A", "Tf0B", "Tf0D", "Tf0E", "Tf44", "Tf49", "Tf4A", "Tf4B"]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though the M3 keys seem to work on my M4 Max work MacBook Pro…&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I ended up using SMC first to get the accurate temperature and fall back to IOKit if SMC doesn’t work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Graph in the menu bar #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the graph, I wanted a compact visualization that would show me the thermal history at a glance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The graph packs three layers of information:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Colored background segments for each thermal state (green for nominal, yellow for moderate, orange for heavy, red for critical)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A solid line for CPU temperature with a dynamic Y-axis that adjusts to actual values&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A dashed cyan line for fan speed percentage (on Macs that have fans)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I didn’t want to spend too much time making a super fancy graph system. Since it polls every two seconds, the graph gets very busy after a while. So I decided to keep it down to 10 minutes, since the thermal state history is mostly interesting short-term.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also added hover tooltips using &lt;code&gt;onContinuousHover&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the system was under load, I noticed the graph hovering was not very smooth on my 120Hz display. I found out I can add &lt;code&gt;.drawingGroup&lt;/code&gt; to my SwiftUI canvas to use GPU rendering!. Indeed, I added it, and it was smooth again.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Adding macOS notifications #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also added notifications so I get alerted when the state changes, in case I miss the menu bar icon. It can alert on specific state transitions, and optionally on recovery. This is useful to know when it’s time to kill a VS Code instance or a Docker container!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s true that I usually already notice when the Mac is getting slow, but sometimes the Mac gets slow when it’s swapping heavily. At least now I know when it’s just too hot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Launching the app at Login #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Of course, I want the app to start automatically now, since it works so well!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I expected that I would need to write &lt;code&gt;.plist&lt;/code&gt; again, but no, it’s extremely easy to prompt the user to add a “login item” as macOS calls it, using &lt;code&gt;SMAppService&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;SMAppService.mainApp.register()    // enable auto-start
SMAppService.mainApp.unregister()  // disable auto-start
SMAppService.mainApp.status == .enabled  // check current state
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to use it #&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since I don’t have an Apple Developer account, I can’t notarize the app, so installing it from the releases is going to require a few extra clicks in &lt;code&gt;Privacy and Security&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And for Macs that disallow it entirely, building from source with Xcode is the only way. I added instructions in the README.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hope this is useful to someone else!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46410402</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 11:51:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Langfuse (YC W23) Is Hiring in Berlin, Germany</title><link>https://langfuse.com/careers</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a8cdb519cd720a6d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Building Langfuse&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Join the team building the leading open-source LLM engineering platform&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;View Open Positions →&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While LLMs improve a lot, we don’t see enough applications in production. Building these applications requires a new workflow of continuous monitoring and evaluation that we enable with Langfuse (learn more about our mission).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are seeing strong traction (see metrics below), thus it is the right time to grow the team to build out our backend systems, product, and how we communicate with developers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are backed by Lightspeed, General Catalyst, Y Combinator, and angels. We are growing fast (see metrics below) and work with some of the best AI teams such as Samsara, Twilio, Khan Academy, and Rocket Money.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If complex technical problems &amp;amp; great developer experiences excite you, we’d love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;– Marc, Clemens, Max and the Langfuse team&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Team&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Marc Klingen, @marcklingen, GitHub, Linkedin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Max Deichmann, @maxdeichmann, GitHub, Linkedin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Clemens Rawert, @rawert, GitHub, Linkedin&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Marlies Mayerhofer, @marliessophie, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hassieb Pakzad, @hassiebpakzad, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Steffen Schmitz, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Jannik Maierhöfer, @jmaierhoefer, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Felix Krauth, @felixkrrr, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Akio Nuernberger, @AkioNuernberger, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Nimar Blume, @nimarblu, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Michael Froehlich, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Valeriy Meleshkin, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Lotte Verheyden, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Leonard Wolters, GitHub, LinkedIn&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Curious to build with us?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are excited about delivering exceptional open-source developer experiences alongside an insanely motivated team that ships, reach out!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Read our Handbook&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We publicly document our core principles and processes at Langfuse to align as a team, maintain transparency with our community, and help you determine if you’d enjoy working here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Main Chapters&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;More Links&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The handbook contains many more resources that define how we do things. These might be interesting to you:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Open Source&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Almost everything we do is public. Get a glimpse of our work here:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Videos/Podcasts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you prefer watching videos or listening to podcasts to get an impression, here are some suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Public Metrics&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Langfuse is the most widely adopted LLM Engineering platform with 19,719 GitHub stars, 23.1M+ SDK installs per month, and 6M+ Docker pulls. Trusted by 19 of the Fortune 50 and 63 of the Fortune 500 companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Work with us&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Curious to build with us?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are excited about delivering exceptional open-source developer experiences alongside an insanely motivated team that ships, reach out!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46410449</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 12:00:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ask HN: Best Podcasts of 2025?</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46411500</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9611195abab66adb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Rest is Politics, Leading, Philosophize This and Stratechery (paid) are the podcasts that stood out the most in 2025. Curious what other HNers listen to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the "Michael Hobbes Podcast Universe" this year. He's a reporter who is now making entertaining podcasts debunking claims in the media/zeitgeist. I appreciate that he takes a pragmatic approach -- to paraphrase something he said: "There's probably an impact on kids having so much screen time, but this data you're citing doesn't show what you're claiming."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I learn a lot listening to the Money Stuff podcast.¹ The newsletter² is also great but I don’t always have time to read every one. I also really enjoy Why Is This Happening.³ Chris Hayes really shines as an interviewer and policy wonk when he’s not in the cable news format. While Ezra Klein seems to be leaning into Democratic Party whisperer, Hayes is leaning into policy nerdity that I miss from Vox-era Klein.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The podcast started as a sequel to Mike Duncan's classic The History of Rome, and in my opinion surpassed it. Where THoR eventually falls into the narrative trap of turning into "The Lives of Roman Emperors", THoB spends a lot of time talking about economic, demographic, societal, and technological changes within the Empire and the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Extremely recommended if you want a proper history podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I enjoyed Shell Game, which explores using voice agents in ever more personal situations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The specifics of the journey are going to date quickly given the speed of AI development. But the shape of the journey and the dilemmas posed are going to be relevant for a lot longer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been a fan of The Ezra Klein Show for years - whatever your thoughts of his personal politics, he’s a fantastic interviewer, and I think he does a great job at both helping define and then interrogating the strongest construction of his guest’s beliefs. He’s not a soft interviewer, but he’s genuinely trying to understand his guest, and I’ve learned a ton about how people who I disagree with view the world.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;His podcast has gotten a lot worse over the years. It feels over-produced now and he doesnt have a lot of interesting guests on anymore. 90% of it is useless policy wonks no one has heard of pumping their latest shitty book no one will read.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Sullivan (Dish Cast) is doing a much better job and isnt associated with a main stream media org.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Klein is a smart liberal journalist and Sullivan is a smart conservative journalist. They both get guests from think tanks/mainstream media/academia. They both book guests that are on book tours. The distinction you're making is not really true.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- "Complex Systems with Patrick McKenzie (patio11)"&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- My First Million (www.mfmpod.com). I just don't know why, but for some reason I stopped listening to them in the past 2 months, but rest of the year I was really enjoying their content. Even older ones.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- Pivot and Prof G, mostly because of Scott Galloway. I really like him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- Under The Influence with Terry O'Reilly. Amazingly good. Very fun to listen to and almost always brings joy and help me learn something new.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;- All In, can't say I'm still enjoying this. It's way too political these days. But it's still something I listen to occasionally. When I listen I usually end up skipping half of the content to find something I like.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Startups For The Rest Of Us is a great for bootstrappers or other non-VC-backed founders. I find that even episodes that are not specifically relevant to the work I'm doing are good to listen to because they may bring ideas to the surface in helpful ways.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My favourite podcast right now is Let's Learn Everything, three science geeks taking turns to explain things to each other. In a standard episode, there's a deep dive into a science topic, followed by a lighter miscellaneous segment. Special episodes, such as the yearly HaLearnDays or the occasional guest episode, take a different format.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The three all have science degrees, and do proper research for their deep dives. This is a podcast which comes with supporting citations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'll have to give this a shot. I am a scientist and have never found a good science podcast ever. I think its because the topic doesn't lend itself as well to the format; papers are hard to digest and communicate in an entertaining way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A micro recommendation for This Week in Virology (TWiV). Essentially a journal club for virology papers, I think they nail the conversational/technical balance that’s so hard to get right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Incidentally, TWiV changed my life. I was working as a cabinet maker with no college degree when I gave it a shot, on a whim. The host’s refusal to shy away from technical depth convinced me that I could learn hard things. 10 years I have a biochemistry degree and work in machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I would have put Coder Radio on this list but ever since Mike took over without Chris the show has lost its appeal for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And sadly, there are no more Jupiter Broadcasting shows left without crypto or mostly inside baseball.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Anyone know of shows in the category of two or three lads discussing computing, coding, devops, but in the style of two older guys crumudging that everything used to be better in the old days?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks. I didn't realize Dan Carlin was still producing new episodes. Ten years ago I was enthralled by his series on the Persian Empire and then I forgot about him.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Rest is History is good, depending on the topic. Both guests have a bit of bias which you have to sort of take into account, not that different from The Rest is Politics. Mishal Husain has a new podcast on Bloomberg TV which so far was excellent. Also from Bloomberg TV, Big Take is often interesting. I still enjoy Lex Fridman, again depending on the guest. Dwarkesh Patel same shit as Lex, but he pretends he knows something about AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I've really been enjoying Complex Systems with Patrick McKenzie (patio11) of HN fame. Additionally: Odd Lots, Money Stuff, Chat with Traders (hit or miss, some guests are not great).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Came here to say this! Complex Systems is not the best for me but it's for sure the new content I found this year. I find myself listening and sometimes pausing to search to learn more about what he is talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Call me simple or provincial, but I really enjoyed "Good Hang" from Amy Poehler. It's a breezy interview with interesting people (doesn't hurt that I'm a long-time SNL fan).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Acquired (Long episodes about companies, recents include: coca-cola, trader joe's &amp;amp; alphabet) Dwarkesh Podcast (Inquisitive curious host, mostly "AGI" related) Conversations with Tyler (Wide ranging, polymath host, distinctive, hard to describe style) The Marginal Revolution Podcast (Tyler cowen &amp;amp; Alex Tabbarok discussing economics) Sharp Tech with Ben Thompson (you sort of mentioned) The Morning Meeting (US Politics mostly. Neutral tone, informative, forward looking i.e. what will happen next not who is bad etc)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46411500</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 14:57:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Designing Predictable LLM-Verifier Systems for Formal Method Guarantee</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02080</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="e89c2c0b05c79c88"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Computer Science &amp;gt; Artificial Intelligence&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Submitted on 30 Nov 2025 (v1), last revised 16 Dec 2025 (this version, v2)]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Title:The 4/$δ$ Bound: Designing Predictable LLM-Verifier Systems for Formal Method Guarantee&lt;/head&gt;View PDF HTML (experimental)&lt;quote&gt;Abstract:The integration of Formal Verification tools with Large Language Models (LLMs) offers a path to scale software verification beyond manual workflows. However, current methods remain unreliable: without a solid theoretical footing, the refinement process acts as a black box that may oscillate, loop, or diverge. This work bridges this critical gap by developing an LLM-Verifier Convergence Theorem, providing the first formal framework with provable guarantees for termination in multi-stage verification pipelines. We model the interaction not as a generic loop, but as a sequential absorbing Markov Chain comprising four essential engineering stages: \texttt{CodeGen}, \texttt{Compilation}, \texttt{InvariantSynth}, and \texttt{SMTSolving}. We prove that for any non-zero stage success probability ($\delta &amp;gt; 0$), the system reaches the \texttt{Verified} state almost surely. Furthermore, because of the sequential nature of the pipeline, we derive a precise latency bound of $\mathbb{E}[n] \leq 4/\delta$. We stress-tested this prediction in an extensive empirical campaign comprising over 90,000 trials. The results match the theory with striking consistency: every run reached verification, and the empirical convergence factor clustered tightly around $C_f\approx 1.0$, confirming that the $4/\delta$ bound accurately mirrors system behavior rather than serving as a loose buffer. Based on this data, we identify three distinct operating zones -- marginal, practical, and high-performance -- and propose a dynamic calibration strategy to handle parameter drift in real-world environments. Together, these contributions replace heuristic guesswork with a rigorous architectural foundation, enabling predictable resource planning and performance budgeting for safety-critical software.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Submission history&lt;/head&gt;From: Pierre Dantas [view email]&lt;p&gt;[v1] Sun, 30 Nov 2025 22:19:09 UTC (459 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v2] Tue, 16 Dec 2025 22:28:30 UTC (491 KB)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Current browse context: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;cs.AI&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h3"&gt;References &amp;amp; Citations&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; export BibTeX citation Loading... &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Bibliographic and Citation Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Bibliographic Explorer (What is the Explorer?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Connected Papers (What is Connected Papers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Litmaps (What is Litmaps?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; scite Smart Citations (What are Smart Citations?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Code, Data and Media Associated with this Article&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; alphaXiv (What is alphaXiv?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CatalyzeX Code Finder for Papers (What is CatalyzeX?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; DagsHub (What is DagsHub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Gotit.pub (What is GotitPub?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Hugging Face (What is Huggingface?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Papers with Code (What is Papers with Code?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ScienceCast (What is ScienceCast?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Demos&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Recommenders and Search Tools&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt; Influence Flower (What are Influence Flowers?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; CORE Recommender (What is CORE?) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;arXivLabs: experimental projects with community collaborators&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;arXivLabs is a framework that allows collaborators to develop and share new arXiv features directly on our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both individuals and organizations that work with arXivLabs have embraced and accepted our values of openness, community, excellence, and user data privacy. arXiv is committed to these values and only works with partners that adhere to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have an idea for a project that will add value for arXiv's community? Learn more about arXivLabs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46411539</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 15:02:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Global Memory Shortage Crisis: Market Analysis</title><link>https://www.idc.com/resource-center/blog/global-memory-shortage-crisis-market-analysis-and-the-potential-impact-on-the-smartphone-and-pc-markets-in-2026/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bb723c998ebaa7c8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In late 2025, the global semiconductor ecosystem is experiencing an unprecedented memory chip shortage with knock-on effects for the device manufacturers and end users that could persist well into 2027. DRAM prices have surged significantly as demand from AI data centers continues to outstrip supply, creating a supply/demand imbalance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IDC was monitoring the memory situation as we prepared our November device forecasts, and we factored them into the update. The situation, however, has become more acute since publishing, and we feel it’s important we address the situation. Although we are maintaining our official forecasts as the situation is still evolving, we will offer here two downside risk scenarios that may play out in two critical markets: Smartphones and Personal Computers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s causing the shortage? The memory market is at an unprecedented inflexion point, with demand materially outpacing supply. For an industry that has long been characterized by boom-and-bust cycles, this time is different. The rapid expansion of AI infrastructure and workloads is exerting significant pressure on the memory ecosystem. These AI workloads require large amounts of memory, and the shortage, in part, is driven by a reallocation of manufacturing capacity away from consumer electronics toward high-margin memory solutions to support AI. Instead of expanding conventional DRAM and NAND used in smartphones, PCs, and other consumer electronics, major memory makers have shifted production toward memory used in AI data centers, such as high-bandwidth (HBM) and high-capacity DDR5. This has restricted the supply of general-purpose memory modules and driven up prices across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI servers and enterprise environments require far more memory per system than consumer devices, so the AI build-out is pulling a disproportionate share of global capacity and creating shortages, as suppliers prioritize orders from hyperscalers and OEMs building AI servers. That dynamic has left less DRAM available for consumer devices, exacerbating price pressure in a tight market.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, this is not just a cyclical shortage driven by a mismatch in supply and demand, but a potentially permanent, strategic reallocation of the world’s silicon wafer capacity. For decades, the production of DRAM and NAND Flash for smartphones and PCs was the primary driver for production. Today, that dynamic has inverted. The voracious demand for HBM by hyperscalers, such as Microsoft, Google, Meta and Amazon, has forced the three biggest memory manufacturers (Samsung Electronics, SK Hynix, and Micron Technology) to pivot their limited cleanroom space and capital expenditure towards higher margin enterprise-grade components. This is a zero-sum game: every wafer allocated to an HBM stack for an Nvidia GPU is a wafer denied to the LPDDR5X module of a mid-range smartphone or the SSD of a consumer laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a result, IDC expects 2026 DRAM and NAND supply growth be below historical norms at 16% year-on-year and 17% year-on-year, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Crisis in the Devices Market&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The result of this supply/demand imbalance is twofold: DRAM and NAND/SSD prices have risen sharply in recent months, and the availability of these components is limited, forcing device manufacturers to navigate a fluid situation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Potential Smartphone Market Impact&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The global smartphone market, particularly Android manufacturers, is facing a threat in 2026. The industry’s decade-long trend of democratizing specs by bringing flagship features to affordable smartphones is reversing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cost structure of a smartphone is heavily dependent on the memory used. For a mid-range device, memory can represent 15-20% of the total bill of materials (BOM), while for a high-end flagship device, it is around 10-15%. As memory prices continue to surge, OEMs will likely have to raise prices significantly, cut specifications or both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Different Vendors, Different Impacts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The impact of the shortage is highly asymmetric, creating winners and losers on supply chain resilience and vertical integration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Manufacturers, whose business is mainly in the low end of the market, are likely to suffer significantly. The business models of vendors such as TCL, Transsion, Realme, Xiaomi, Lenovo, Oppo, Vivo, Honor or Huawei are based on thin margins. This increase in cost will hit their margins substantially, and they will have no other option but to pass the cost (or part) to end users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the high end of the market, Apple and Samsung face pressure but are structurally hedged. Its cash reserves and long-term supply agreements allow it to secure memory supply 12-24 months in advance. On the other hand, new flagship models in 2026 will likely have no RAM upgrades, sticking to 12GB for Pro models rather than increasing to 16GB. It is also unlikely that current models will see the same price erosion seen after the introduction of the latest model.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The cumulative effect of these pressures is a potential contraction in the global smartphone market alongside an increase in average selling prices (ASP). In 2026, in our moderate downside scenario, we could see the market contract by 2.9%. In our pessimistic downside scenario, it could be as bad as 5.2%. The severity of each scenario depends on how long this situation lasts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the same time, smartphone ASPs could rise by 3% to 5% in the moderate scenario, or by 6% to 8% in the pessimistic scenario. These price rises will be significantly higher in the low end of the market, where margins are extremely tight, and OEMs will have to pass the cost to end users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But regardless of the severity of the scenario, longer replacement cycles are likely to occur in markets with rising costs causing lower purchasing power. By contrast, in more mature markets, consumers are likely to rely on financing and instalment plans to absorb higher prices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While there could be significant downside risk to volumes in 2026, we expect 4Q25 to outperform our earlier projections as vendors stocked channels ahead of price increases.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Impact to the PC Market&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the smartphone market is facing pressure, the PC market is bracing for disruption. The timing of the memory shortage creates a perfect storm for the PC industry, colliding with the Microsoft Windows 10 end-of-life refresh cycle and the AI PC marketing push.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PC vendors are signalling broad price increases as cost pressures intensify into H2 2026. Lenovo, Dell, HP, Acer and ASUS have warned clients of tougher conditions ahead, confirming 15-20% hikes and contract resets as an industry-wide response.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PC vendors with larger shipment volumes should be better positioned to navigate current supply constraints, enabling them to capture market share from smaller and regional brands. Regardless of how much the total market size may be impacted, we expect vendor market shares to shift in favor of the largest vendors armed with inventory and greater leverage with suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;White box as well as lower tier (often local) vendors, on the other hand, will bear the greatest burden of the shortage, and that would include DIY systems, oftentimes built by gamers. That in turn represents an opportunity for large OEMs to gain share from smaller assemblers in the gaming space by positioning pre-built systems as offering higher value.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Impact on AI PC&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The shortage threatens to derail the industry’s growth narrative around AI PC. IDC defines the AI PC as any PC with an NPU. Crucially, these devices tend to have more RAM (Microsoft’s Copilot+ PCs require a minimum of 16GB). As more small language models and large language models move on device, memory becomes even more important, with many higher-end systems shifting toward 32GB or higher. Just as the industry is seeing a need to add more RAM, it has become prohibitively expensive to do so, even if they can get supply. This will result in higher prices, lower margins, or a potential downmix in the amount of RAM in new systems at the worst possible time for this to occur.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As with smartphones, IDC is not changing its official PC forecast. Here again, we offer two potential scenarios for 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the more moderate downside scenario, we could see the PC market contract by 4.9% compared with a 2.4% year-on-year decline in the November forecast. Under a more pessimistic scenario, the decline could deepen to 8.9%. The severity of each scenario will largely depend on how long the current supply constraints persist through 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Under these downside scenarios, PC average selling prices would likely rise, increasing by 4% to 6% in a moderate scenario, and by 6% to 8% in a pessimistic scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As with smartphones, channels are building inventory in advance to mitigate the impact of further price increases in the months ahead, which is expected to support stronger-than-expected forecast performance in Q4 2025, relative to the November outlook.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What began as an AI infrastructure boom has now rippled outward, with tightening memory supply, inflating prices, and reshaping product and pricing strategies across both consumer and enterprise devices. As the industry adjusts to this new reality, the smartphone and PC markets are bracing for a period of higher costs, altered product roadmaps, and slower volume growth. The severity and duration of the shortage will be determined by how quickly production capacity can expand and how effectively demand rebalances across segments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For consumers and enterprises alike, this signals the end of an era of cheap, abundant memory and storage, at least in the medium term. The year 2026 is shaping up to be one in which technology becomes more expensive, driven by supply constraints rather than demand growth.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46411902</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 15:51:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>tc-ematch(8) extended matches for use with "basic", "cgroup" or "flow" filters</title><link>https://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man8/tc-ematch.8.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a601e349e52939e4"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;NAME | SYNOPSIS | MATCHES | CAVEATS | EXAMPLE &amp;amp; USAGE | AUTHOR | COLOPHON&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row/&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
ematch(8)                         Linux                         ematch(8)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;ematch - extended matches for use with "basic", "cgroup" or "flow" filters&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;tc filter add .. basic match EXPR .. flowid .. EXPR := TERM [ { and | or } EXPR ] TERM := [ not ] { MATCH | '(' EXPR ')' } MATCH := module '(' ARGS ')' ARGS := ARG1 ARG2 ..&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;cmp Simple comparison ematch: arithmetic compare of packet data to a given value. cmp( ALIGN at OFFSET [ ATTRS ] { eq | lt | gt } VALUE ) ALIGN := { u8 | u16 | u32 } ATTRS := [ layer LAYER ] [ mask MASK ] [ trans ] LAYER := { link | network | transport | 0..2 } meta Metadata ematch meta( OBJECT { eq | lt |gt } OBJECT ) OBJECT := { META_ID | VALUE } META_ID := id [ shift SHIFT ] [ mask MASK ] meta attributes: random 32 bit random value loadavg_1 Load average in last 5 minutes nf_mark Netfilter mark vlan Vlan tag sk_rcvbuf Receive buffer size sk_snd_queue Send queue length A full list of meta attributes can be obtained via # tc filter add dev eth1 basic match 'meta(list)' nbyte match packet data byte sequence nbyte( NEEDLE at OFFSET [ layer LAYER ] ) NEEDLE := { string | c-escape-sequence } OFFSET := int LAYER := { link | network | transport | 0..2 } u32 u32 ematch u32( ALIGN VALUE MASK at [ nexthdr+ ] OFFSET ) ALIGN := { u8 | u16 | u32 } ipset test packet against ipset membership ipset( SETNAME FLAGS ) SETNAME := string FLAGS := { FLAG [, FLAGS] } The flag options are the same as those used by the iptables "set" match. When using the ipset ematch with the "ip_set_hash:net,iface" set type, the interface can be queried using "src,dst (source ip address, outgoing interface) or "src,src" (source ip address, incoming interface) syntax. ipt test packet against xtables matches ipt( [-6] -m MATCH_NAME FLAGS ) MATCH_NAME := string FLAGS := { FLAG [, FLAGS] } The flag options are the same as those used by the xtable match used. canid ematch rule to match CAN frames canid( IDLIST ) IDLIST := IDSPEC[IDLIST] IDSPEC := { âsffâ CANID | âeffâ CANID } CANID := ID[:MASK] ID, MASK := hexadecimal number (i.e. 0x123)&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;The ematch syntax uses '(' and ')' to group expressions. All braces need to be escaped properly to prevent shell commandline from interpreting these directly. When using the ipset ematch with the "ifb" device, the outgoing device will be the ifb device itself, e.g. "ifb0". The original interface (i.e. the device the packet arrived on) is treated as the incoming interface.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;# tc filter add .. basic match ... # 'cmp(u16 at 3 layer 2 mask 0xff00 gt 20)' # 'meta(nfmark gt 24)' and 'meta(tcindex mask 0xf0 eq 0xf0)' # 'nbyte("ababa" at 12 layer 1)' # 'u32(u16 0x1122 0xffff at nexthdr+4)' Check if packet source ip address is member of set named bulk: # 'ipset(bulk src)' Check if packet source ip and the interface the packet arrived on is member of "hash:net,iface" set named interactive: # 'ipset(interactive src,src)' Check if packet matches an IPSec state with reqid 1: # 'ipt(-m policy --dir in --pol ipsec --reqid 1)'&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;The extended match infrastructure was added by Thomas Graf.&lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;
       This page is part of the iproute2 (utilities for controlling
       TCP/IP networking and traffic) project.  Information about the
       project can be found at 
       â¨http://www.linuxfoundation.org/collaborate/workgroups/networking/iproute2â©.
       If you have a bug report for this manual page, send it to
       netdev@vger.kernel.org, shemminger@osdl.org.  This page was
       obtained from the project's upstream Git repository
       â¨https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/network/iproute2/iproute2.gitâ© on
       2025-08-11.  (At that time, the date of the most recent commit
       that was found in the repository was 2025-08-08.)  If you discover
       any rendering problems in this HTML version of the page, or you
       believe there is a better or more up-to-date source for the page,
       or you have corrections or improvements to the information in this
       COLOPHON (which is not part of the original manual page), send a
       mail to man-pages@man7.org

iproute2                      6 August 2012                     ematch(8)
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pages that refer to this page: tc(8), tc-basic(8), tc-bpf(8), tc-cgroup(8), tc-flow(8)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46412327</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 16:43:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A "Prime" View of HN</title><link>https://dosaygo-studio.github.io/prime-news/index.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="33615c5ebc84496"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ζ Hacker News Prime new | past | posts | mersenne | germain | fermat | palindrome | p k | 2 | 4 | 6 | 8 | 10 | 12 | e≤k² | e&amp;lt;√p | submit login Pure Math | Deterministic | API | Security | Legal | Apply to ζ | Contact Search:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46412549</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 17:12:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Deathbed Advice/Regret</title><link>https://hazn.com/deathbed-regret</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3435999908c30219"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;On deathbed advice/regret&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;A common social media trope is posting advice from people on their deathbed. Usually about things they didn't do. "I should've been more there for my loved ones" is a classic tune, "I should've cared less about what other people think" is another hit, usually culminating in the banger conclusion of "I should've done [a super specific personal thing like opening up a hobbyist store or buying a house in their favorite hinterland]."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't value this kind of advice much, it's too cheap. Just like complaining is just so cheap. Maybe there are good reasons at the time to not tackle the thing they are regretting, or they were too whiny in the first place to do transformative things. I think that's my biggest problem with deathbed regrets, it feels like time-travelled whining about your life situation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When chronic whiners annoy you — those who love non-stop complaining more than solving — mention that their complaint just became a top deathbed regret candidate. Or you can be polite and internalize that you are probably gonna hear about the same person on their deathbed advising the exact opposite of what they're doing now. That way you can be just like me and whine about other people's whining.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So yeah I don't value regrets packaged as advice, especially from people who never acted on their advice — a.k.a. people on their deathbed. "The uncaught fish is always a big fish" is the appropriate Turkish saying1 that captures my mood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Better advice comes from things people actually did. This is fundamentally because advice doesn't work that well, but being a role model does.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, "be less on social media" is another advice/regret I am sure will be on people's lips on their deathbeds. I'm sure because I hear it a lot. People are aware of this regret pre-deathbed and free to act on it now. Or they can just post on social media about deathbed regrets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Related&lt;/p&gt;Write me: [email protected] ☺️&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46412578</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 17:15:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Remembering Lou Gerstner</title><link>https://newsroom.ibm.com/2025-12-28-Remembering-Lou-Gerstner</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f8dd935902cb38d"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;All press releases&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Remembering Lou Gerstner&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following is the text of an email sent today to all IBM employees by Chairman and CEO Arvind Krishna:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IBMers,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am saddened to share that Lou Gerstner, IBM’s Chairman and CEO from 1993 to 2002, passed away yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lou arrived at IBM at a moment when the company’s future was genuinely uncertain. The industry was changing rapidly, our business was under pressure, and there was serious debate about whether IBM should even remain whole. His leadership during that period reshaped the company. Not by looking backward, but by focusing relentlessly on what our clients would need next.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of Lou’s earliest signals as CEO has become part of IBM lore. Early on, he stopped a long internal presentation and said, simply, “Let’s just talk.” The message was clear: less inward focus, more real discussion, and much closer attention to customers. That mindset would define his tenure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lou believed one of IBM’s central problems was that we had become optimized around our own processes, debates, and structures rather than around client outcomes. As he later put it, the company had lost sight of a basic truth of business: understanding the customer and delivering what the customer actually values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That insight drove real change. Meetings became more direct. Decisions were grounded more in facts and client impact than in hierarchy or tradition. Innovation mattered if it could translate into something clients would come to rely on. Execution in the quarter and the year mattered, but always in service of longer-term relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lou made what may have been the most consequential decision in IBM’s modern history: to keep IBM together. At the time, the company was organized into many separate businesses, each pursuing its own path. Lou understood that clients didn’t want fragmented technology—they wanted integrated solutions. That conviction shaped IBM’s evolution and reestablished our relevance for many of the world’s largest enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lou also understood that strategy alone would not be enough. He believed lasting change required a shift in culture—in how people behave when no one is watching. What mattered was what IBMers valued, how honestly they confronted reality, and how willing they were to challenge themselves and each other. Rather than discard IBM’s long-standing values, he pushed the company to renew them to meet the demands of a very different era.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have my own memory of Lou from the mid-1990s, at a small town hall with a few hundred people. What stood out was his intensity and focus. He had an ability to hold the short term and the long term in his head at the same time. He pushed hard on delivery, but he was equally focused on innovation: doing work that clients would remember, not just consume.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lou stayed engaged with IBM long after his tenure ended. From my first days as CEO, he was generous with advice—but always careful in how he gave it. He would offer perspective, then say, “I’ve been gone a long time—I’m here if you need me.” He listened closely to what others were saying about IBM and reflected it back candidly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That neutral, experienced voice mattered to me, and I was fortunate to learn from Lou on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lou was direct. He expected preparation. He challenged assumptions. But he was deeply committed to building a company that could adapt—culturally as much as strategically—without losing its core values.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lou’s impact extended well beyond IBM. Before joining the company, he had already built an extraordinary career—becoming one of the youngest partners at McKinsey &amp;amp; Company, later serving as president of American Express and CEO of RJR Nabisco. After IBM, he went on to chair The Carlyle Group and devoted significant time and resources to philanthropy, particularly in education and biomedical research. A native of Long Island, NY, Lou earned his undergraduate degree from Dartmouth and an MBA from Harvard, and he remained deeply devoted to his family throughout his life. Lou was preceded in death by his son Louis Gerstner III.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We will hold a celebration in the new year to reflect on Lou’s legacy and what his leadership enabled at IBM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My thoughts are with Lou’s wife Robin, his daughter Elizabeth, his grandchildren and extended family, as well as his many friends, colleagues, and people around the world who were shaped by his leadership and his work.&lt;lb/&gt; Media contact:&lt;lb/&gt; IBM Press Room&lt;lb/&gt; ibmpress@us.ibm.com &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46413365</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 18:43:54 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>