<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 17:14:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Interview with RollerCoaster Tycoon's Creator, Chris Sawyer (2024)</title><link>https://medium.com/atari-club/interview-with-rollercoaster-tycoons-creator-chris-sawyer-684a0efb0f13</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46130335</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 04:32:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Researchers Find Microbe Capable of Producing Oxygen from Martian Soil</title><link>https://scienceclock.com/microbe-that-could-turn-martian-dust-into-oxygen/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a38e904b38a1646a"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we talk about the possibility of humans living on Mars, one of the biggest challenges is not the rockets or the habitats, but something far more basic: how to breathe. Carrying oxygen tanks across space is not practical for long-term survival. This is where a tiny microbe might make a huge difference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scientists have been studying an extremophile, a type of microorganism that can survive in very harsh environments. This particular one is known as Chroococcidiopsis. It has shown the ability to grow on materials that are similar to Martian soil, and in the process, it produces oxygen. That means if it can be cultivated in future Mars colonies, it could support human breathing needs directly on the Red Planet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Researchers tested this by using soil that mimics Martian regolith. The results were promising. The bacteria did not just survive, it actively thrived, pulling nutrients from the soil and releasing oxygen as part of its natural process. What makes it even more interesting is that it does not require rich Earth-like soil to function. Even in the limited resources available on Mars, it can manage to carry out its work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also Read: Mars Ice Could Preserve Traces of Ancient Life, Study Suggests&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The experiments also showed that these microbes can survive extreme conditions such as radiation and low pressure that would normally be deadly to most life. Even when their DNA was damaged by radiation, they were able to repair it after rehydration and continue functioning normally, with no lasting increase in mutations. This resilience is what defines them as extremophiles, organisms that have evolved to survive where most others cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For space scientists and planners, this is a big step. If humans ever build bases on Mars, they will need systems that can provide oxygen without constant resupply from Earth. Carrying oxygen would be costly and dangerous, while producing it locally would make settlements more realistic. A living system using microbes might offer a natural and renewable source.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This does not mean the problem is solved. There are still challenges ahead. One is how to grow these organisms at scale in Martian conditions. Another is how to protect them and keep them productive in an environment that is far more unstable than Earth. But the fact that they can survive in laboratory simulations of Mars is an important first step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is also a wider question. If such microbes can survive on Mars-like conditions, does that mean life could exist elsewhere in the solar system? Extremophiles on Earth already show us that life can adapt to the most unlikely places — from boiling hot springs to the depths of ice. This experiment adds to the evidence that life is resilient and flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For now, the practical focus remains on human needs. Space agencies and researchers are interested in creating closed-loop systems where food, water, and oxygen can all be recycled and produced on site. Using microbes for oxygen production could become one part of that system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is too early to say whether this specific cyanobacterium will be the final answer. But it shows a direction for research and gives hope that we may not need to carry every breath of oxygen from Earth. Instead, we may be able to “farm” our oxygen directly on another planet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Story Source: Universe Today&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46130907</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 06:34:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zig quits GitHub, says Microsoft's AI obsession has ruined the service</title><link>https://www.theregister.com/2025/12/02/zig_quits_github_microsoft_ai_obsession/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="8e14b4d14f364afe"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Zig quits GitHub, says Microsoft's AI obsession has ruined the service&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Zig prez complains about 'vibe-scheduling' after safe sleep bug goes unaddressed for eons&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Foundation that promotes the Zig programming language has quit GitHub due to what its leadership perceives as the code sharing site's decline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The drama began in April 2025 when GitHub user AlekseiNikiforovIBM started a thread titled “safe_sleep.sh rarely hangs indefinitely.” GitHub addressed the problem in August, but didn’t reveal that in the thread, which remained open until Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The code uses 100 percent CPU all the time, and will run forever&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That timing appears notable. Last week, Andrew Kelly, president and lead developer of the Zig Software Foundation, announced that the Zig project is moving to Codeberg, a non-profit git hosting service, because GitHub no longer demonstrates commitment to engineering excellence.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One piece of evidence he offered for that assessment was the “safe_sleep.sh rarely hangs indefinitely” thread.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Most importantly, Actions has inexcusable bugs while being completely neglected," Kelly wrote. "After the CEO of GitHub said to 'embrace AI or get out', it seems the lackeys at Microsoft took the hint, because GitHub Actions started 'vibe-scheduling' – choosing jobs to run seemingly at random. Combined with other bugs and inability to manually intervene, this causes our CI system to get so backed up that not even master branch commits get checked."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Older and deeper&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kelly’s gripe seems justified, as the bug discussed in the thread appears to have popped up following a code change in February 2022 that users flagged in prior bug reports.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The code change replaced instances of the posix "sleep" command with a "safe_sleep" script that failed to work as advertised. It was supposed to allow the GitHub Actions runner – the application that runs a job from a GitHub Actions workflow – to pause execution safely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The bug in this 'safe sleep' script is obvious from looking at it: if the process is not scheduled for the one-second interval in which the loop would return (due to $SECONDS having the correct value), then it simply spins forever," wrote Zig core developer Matthew Lugg in a comment appended to the April bug thread.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"That can easily happen on a CI machine under extreme load. When this happens, it's pretty bad: it completely breaks a runner until manual intervention. On Zig's CI runner machines, we observed multiple of these processes which had been running for hundreds of hours, silently taking down two runner services for weeks."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fix was merged on August 20, 2025, from a separate issue opened back in February 2024. The related bug report from April 2025 remained open until Monday, December 1, 2025. A separate CPU usage bug remains unresolved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Microsoft appears to move on from its most loyal 'customers' – Contoso and Fabrikam&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;UK gov blames budget leak on misconfigured WordPress plugin, server&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Google Antigravity vibe-codes user's entire drive out of existence&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OpenAI cuts off Mixpanel after analytics leak exposes API users&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jeremy Howard, co-founder of Answer.AI and Fast.AI, said in a series of social media posts that users’ claims about GitHub Actions being in a poor state of repair appear to be justified.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"The bug," he wrote, "was implemented in a way that, very obviously to nearly anyone at first glance, uses 100 percent CPU all the time, and will run forever unless the task happens to check the time during the correct second."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I can't see how such an extraordinary collection of outright face-palming events could be made&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He added that the platform-independent fix for the CPU issue proposed last February lingered for a year without review and was closed by the GitHub bot in March 2025 before being revived and merged.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;"Whilst one could say that this is just one isolated incident, I can't see how such an extraordinary collection of outright face-palming events could be made in any reasonably functioning organization," Howard concluded.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GitHub did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While Kelly has gone on to apologize for the incendiary nature of his post, Zig is not the only software project publicly parting ways with GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, Rodrigo Arias Mallo, creator of the Dillo browser project, said he's planning to move away from GitHub owing to concerns about over-reliance on JavaScript, GitHub's ability to deny service, declining usability, inadequate moderation tools, and "over-focusing on LLMs and generative AI, which are destroying the open web (or what remains of it) among other problems."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Codeberg, for its part, has doubled its supporting membership since January, going from more than 600 members to over 1,200 as of last week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GitHub has not disclosed how many of its users pay for its services presently. The code hosting biz had "over 1.3 million paid GitHub Copilot subscribers, up 30 percent quarter-over-quarter," Microsoft CEO Satya Nadella said on the company's Q2 2024 earnings call.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Q4 2024, when GitHub reported an annual revenue run rate of $2 billion, GitHub Copilot subscriptions accounted for about 40 percent of the company's annual revenue growth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nadella offered a different figure during Microsoft's Q3 2025 earnings call: "we now have over 15 million GitHub Copilot users, up over 4X year-over-year." It's not clear how many GitHub users pay for Copilot, or for runner scripts that burned CPU cycles when they should have been sleeping. ®&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46131406</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 07:52:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Anthropic reportedly preparing for $300B IPO</title><link>https://vechron.com/2025/12/anthropic-hires-wilson-sonsini-ipo-2026-openai-race/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3b1ce32d7bba0f70"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;San Francisco-based Anthropic has asked Wilson Sonsini Goodrich &amp;amp; Rosati to begin work on an initial public offering (IPO) that could take place as early as 2026, the Financial Times reported this week.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The move positions the company, best known for its Claude chatbot, to reach the stock market ahead of rival OpenAI and would test investors’ willingness to fund large, loss-making artificial-intelligence labs. People familiar with the plans cautioned that discussions with investment banks remain informal and that no underwriting line-up has been chosen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wilson Sonsini, which advised Anthropic on its multibillion-dollar investment agreements with Amazon and Google, has previously guided Google, LinkedIn and Lyft to market.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a statement, an Anthropic spokesperson said: “We have not made any decisions about when, or even whether, to go public.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The IPO preparations coincide with a private fundraising round that could value Anthropic above $300 billion. Microsoft and Nvidia have jointly committed $15 billion to that round, according to the Financial Times, while Anthropic has pledged to spend $30 billion on Microsoft’s cloud platform over the next four years. A previous funding round this autumn pegged the company at roughly $183 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chief executive Dario Amodei has told investors that annualised revenue could rise to $26 billion next year, triple this year’s run-rate, as the customer base expands beyond 300,000 businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Internal changes aimed at satisfying public-market requirements are already under way. Last year Anthropic hired Airbnb’s former head of corporate finance, Krishna Rao, as chief financial officer and has since worked through governance, accounting and disclosure checklists, one source said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OpenAI, valued at about $500 billion after a recent share sale, is conducting similar early-stage work but chief financial officer Sarah Friar said last month that a listing is “not in the near-term plan.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both companies face the challenge of forecasting profits while spending heavily on model training and infrastructure. Anthropic recently announced a $50 billion build-out of data centres in Texas and New York and plans to triple its global workforce.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46132531</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 09:53:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Are we repeating the telecoms crash with AI datacenters?</title><link>https://martinalderson.com/posts/are-we-really-repeating-the-telecoms-crash-with-ai-datacenters/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2932f0575a46cc69"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Are we really repeating the telecoms crash with AI datacenters?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I keep hearing the AI datacentre boom compared to the 2000s telecoms crash. The parallels seem obvious - billions in infrastructure spending, concerns about overbuilding, warnings of an imminent bubble. But when I actually ran the numbers, the fundamentals look completely different.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I'm not here to predict whether there will or won't be a crash or correction. I just want to look at whether the comparison to telecoms actually holds up when you examine the history in a bit more detail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Actually Happened in the Telecoms Crash&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let me start with what the 2000s telecoms crash actually looked like, because the details matter. Firstly, there was massive capex - between 1995 and 2000 somewhere like $2 trillion was spent laying 80-90 million miles of fiber. Inflation adjusted, this is over $4trillion, or close to $1trillion/year in 2025 dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By 2002 only 2.7% of this fibre was used.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How did this happen? A catastrophic supply and demand miscalculation past the pure securities fraud involved in many of the companies. Telecom CEOs claimed internet traffic was doubling every 3-4 months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But in reality, traffic was doubling roughly every 12 months. That's a 4x overestimate of demand growth, which compounds each year. This false assumption drove massive debt-financed overbuilding. If you overestimate 4x a year for 3 years, by the end of your scenario you are 256x out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even worse for these companies, enormous strides were made on the optical transceivers, allowing the same fibre to carry 100,000x more traffic over the following decade. Just one example is WDM multiplexing, allowing multiple carriers to be multiplexed on the same physical fibre line. In 1995 state of the art was 4-8 carriers. By 2000, it was 128. This alone allowed a 64x increase in capacity with the same infrastructure. Combined with improvements in modulation techniques, error correction, and the bits per second each carrier could handle, the same physical fibre became exponentially more capable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key dynamic: supply improvements were exponential while demand was merely linear. While some physical infrastructure needed to be built, there was enormous overbuilding that could mostly be serviced by technology improvements on the same infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;AI Infrastructure: A Different Story&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike fibre optics in the 1990s, GPU performance per watt improvements are actually slowing down:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2015-2020 Period:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Performance per watt improved significantly with major architectural changes&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Process nodes jumped from ~20nm to 7nm (major efficiency gains)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Introduction of Tensor Cores and specialized AI hardware&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2020-2025 Period:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ML hardware energy efficiency improves ~40% annually&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Performance per watt improvements slowing compared to previous era&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Process nodes: improvements slowed dramatically with EUV being a requirement at sub 5nm wavelengths.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More tellingly, GPU TDPs (power consumption) are rising dramatically:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;V100 (2017): 300W&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A100 (2020): 400W&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;H100 (2022): 700W&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;B200 (2024): 1000-1200W&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the opposite of what happened in telecoms. We're not seeing exponential efficiency gains that make existing infrastructure obsolete. Instead, we're seeing semiconductor physics hitting fundamental limits.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The B200 from NVidia also requires liquid cooling - which means most datacentres designed for air cooling need to be completely retrofitted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Demand Growth Is Actually Accelerating&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The telecoms crash happened partly because demand was overestimated by 4x. What does AI demand growth look like?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traditional LLM Usage: ChatGPT averages 20+ prompts per user per day. Extended conversations can reach 3,000-4,000 tokens cumulative, though many users treat it like Google - short "searches" with no follow-up, consuming surprisingly few tokens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Agent Usage (Anthropic research):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Basic agents: 4x more tokens than chat&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Multi-agent systems: 15x more tokens than chat&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Coding agents: 150,000+ tokens per session (multiple sessions daily)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're looking at a fundamentally different demand curve - if anything, people are underestimating how much agents will consume. The shift from chat to agents represents a 10x-100x increase in token consumption per user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We're not even there yet, and infrastructure is already maxed out, with AI infrastructure running at very high utilization rates. Major providers still experience peak-time capacity issues. The problem isn't unused infrastructure sitting idle; it's infrastructure struggling to meet current demand. One major hyperscaler told me they still have capacity issues at peak times causing free tier users to have high error rates.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Datacenter CapEx: Evolution, Not Revolution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another important piece of context that gets missed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-AI Growth (2018-2021):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Combined Amazon/Microsoft/Google capex: $68B (2018) → $124B (2021)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;81% growth over 3 years&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Annual growth rate: ~22%&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Driven by cloud migration, pandemic acceleration, streaming&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI Boom (2023-2025):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2023: $127B&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2024: $212B (67% growth year-over-year)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;2025 projected: $255B+ (Amazon $100B, Microsoft $80B, Alphabet $75B)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While it's no doubt a huge amount of capex going into this rollout; it's not quite as dramatic as some news stories make out. I have no doubt that now any datacentre related capex is being rebranded as "AI", even if it's just 'boring' old compute, storage and network not being directly used for AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why Forecasting Is Nearly Impossible&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's where I think the comparison to telecoms becomes both interesting and concerning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Lead Time Problem:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Datacenters take 2-3 years to build&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GPU orders have 6-12 month lead times&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Can't adjust capacity in real-time to match demand&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Prisoner's Dilemma:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Underestimating demand = terrible user experience + losing to competitors&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Overestimating demand = billions in wasted capex (that might just get used slower)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Given the choice, rational players overbuild - because wasting some capex is infinitely better than losing the "AI wars"&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Forecasting Challenge:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Imagine you're planning datacenter capacity right now for 2027. You need to make billion-dollar decisions today based on what you think AI usage will look like in three years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's scenario one: agent adoption is gradual. Some developers use Claude Code daily. A few enterprises deploy internal agents. Customer service stays mostly human with AI assist. You need maybe 3-4x your current infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's scenario two: agents go mainstream. Every developer has an always-on coding agent consuming millions of tokens per session. Enterprises deploy agents across operations, finance, legal, sales. Customer service becomes 80% agentic with humans handling escalations. You need 30-50x your current infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both scenarios are completely plausible. Nobody can tell you which one is right. But you have to commit billions in capex NOW - datacenters take 2-3 years to build, GPU orders have 6-12 month lead times.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But here's the really insidious part: even if you're directionally right, small errors compound massively. Let's say you're confident agents are going mainstream and you need roughly 50x growth over 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If actual demand is 40x, you've overbuilt by 25% - billions in excess capacity. If actual demand is 60x, you've underbuilt by 20% - your service degrades and you lose market share.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You're trying to hit a moving target in the dark, and the margin of error is measured in tens of billions of dollars and thousands of megawatts of power infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you build for scenario one and scenario two happens, your service degrades to unusable, users revolt, and you lose the AI wars to competitors who bet bigger. If you build for scenario two and scenario one happens, you've got billions in underutilized datacenters burning cash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which mistake would you rather make?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is where the telecoms comparison makes sense: given those choices, rational players overbuild. The difference is what happens to that overcapacity.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Key Differences&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let me put this in a table:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Factor&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Telecoms (1990s-2000s)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;AI Datacenters (2020s)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Supply improvements&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Exponential (100,000x capacity increase)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Slowing (69%→44% annual perf/watt gains)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Demand growth&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Overestimated 4x&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Potentially underestimated (agent transition)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Utilization&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;95% dark fiber (genuine overcapacity)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Very high - many providers still experiencing peak time scale problems&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Technology curve&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Making infrastructure obsolete&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Hitting semiconductor physics limits&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="3"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Power consumption&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Decreasing&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Increasing (300W → 1200W)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Infrastructure lifespan&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Decades (fiber doesn't degrade)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Years (refreshed as better hardware arrives)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The telecoms crash happened because exponential supply improvements met linearly growing (and overestimated) demand, with infrastructure that would last decades sitting unused.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI datacenters are facing slowing supply improvements meeting potentially exponentially growing demand. And crucially, because GPU efficiency improvements are slowing down, today's hardware retains value for longer - not shorter - than previous generations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What About a Short-Term Correction?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could there still be a short-term crash? Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scenarios that could trigger a correction:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. Agent adoption hits a wall&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enterprises might discover that production agent deployments are harder than demos suggest. Hallucinations in high-stakes workflows, regulatory concerns around autonomous AI systems, or implementation complexity could slow adoption dramatically. If the agent future takes 5-7 years instead of 2-3, there's a painful gap where billions in infrastructure sits waiting for demand to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, given the explosion in usage for software engineering and other tasks, I suspect this is highly unlikely. You can already use Claude Code for non engineering tasks in professional services and get very impressive results without any industry specific modifications, so I have no doubt there is going to be very high adoption of agents in all kinds of areas.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2. Financial engineering unravels&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These datacenter buildouts are heavily debt-financed. If credit markets seize up, interest rates spike further, or lenders lose confidence in AI growth projections, the financing model could collapse. This wouldn't be about technical fundamentals - it would be good old-fashioned financial panic, similar to what happened in telecoms when the debt markets froze, but with one key difference - a lot of the key players (Microsoft, Google, Meta, Oracle) are extremely cash flow positive, which definitely wasn't the case in the 2000s fibre boom. The pure datacentre players though are at risk - who don't have a money printing main business to backstop the finance - no doubt about that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3. Efficiency breakthroughs change the math&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Model efficiency could improve faster than expected. Or we could see a hardware breakthrough: custom ASICs that are 10x more efficient than GB200s for inference workloads. Either scenario could make current buildouts look excessive. I actually think this is the biggest risk - and this is exactly what happened in the fibre boom. So far, I'm not seeing signs of this though. While specialist ASICs are becoming available, they hit their impressive speed by having huge wafers, which isn't a huge efficiency game (yet).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Key Difference From Telecoms:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if there's a correction, the underlying dynamics are different. Telecoms built for demand that was 4x overestimated, then watched fiber optic technology improvements make their infrastructure obsolete before it could be utilized. The result: 95% of fiber remained permanently dark.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AI datacenters might face a different scenario. If we build for 50x growth and only get 30x over 3 years, that's not "dark infrastructure" - that's just infrastructure that gets utilized on a slower timeline than expected. Unlike fiber optic cable sitting in the ground unused, GPU clusters still serve production workloads, just at lower capacity than planned.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And unlike telecoms where exponential technology improvements made old infrastructure worthless, GPU efficiency improvements are slowing. A GB200 deployed today doesn't become obsolete when next year's chip arrives - because that chip is only incrementally better, not 100x better. With process node improvements slowing down, current generation hardware actually retains value for longer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A correction might mean 2-3 years of financial pain, consolidation, and write-downs as demand catches up to capacity. But that's fundamentally different from building infrastructure for demand that never materializes while technology makes it obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Real Risk: Timing, Not Direction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think the real question isn't whether we need massive AI infrastructure - the agent transition alone suggests we do. The question is timing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If enterprises take 5 years to adopt agents at scale instead of 2 years, and hyperscalers have built for the 2-year scenario, you could see a 2-3 year period of overcapacity and financial pain. That might be enough to trigger a correction, layoffs, and consolidation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But unlike telecoms, that overcapacity would likely get absorbed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The telecom fibre mostly stayed dark because technology outpaced it and demand never materialized. AI infrastructure might just be early, not wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are we repeating the telecoms crash with AI datacenters? The fundamentals suggest not, but that doesn't mean there won't be bumps.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The key insight people miss when making the telecoms comparison: telecoms had exponential supply improvements meeting linear demand, with 4x overestimated growth assumptions. AI has slowing supply improvements potentially meeting exponential demand growth from the agent transition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The risks are different:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Telecoms: Built too much infrastructure that became completely obsolete by supply-side technology improvements&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AI: Might build too much too fast for demand that arrives slower than expected&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But the "too much" in AI's case is more like "3 years of runway instead of 1 year" rather than "95% will never be used."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I could be wrong. Maybe agent adoption stalls, maybe model efficiency makes current infrastructure obsolete, maybe there's a breakthrough in GPU architecture that changes everything. But when I look at the numbers, I don't see the same setup as the telecoms crash.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fundamentals are different. That doesn't mean there won't be pain, consolidation, or failures. But comparing this to 2000s telecoms seems like the wrong mental model for what's actually happening.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46133141</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 11:14:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The "Mad Men" in 4K on HBO Max Debacle</title><link>http://fxrant.blogspot.com/2025/12/the-mad-men-in-4k-on-hbo-max-debacle.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="212590f1136290f9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Reader warning: there's gonna be a lot of pretend puke photos in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you've fired up HBO Max recently, you've probably seen that one of the most influential and prestigious television series of all time was to premiere in 4K on the streaming service. The show's first four seasons were shot on film, and the final three were shot digitally on the Alexa, but the run of the series was mastered in 1080p HD. HBO Max has been touting this 4K "restoration" of the series, produced by Lionsgate TV. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The highly anticipated 4K debut of the show was to be one of HBO Max' crown jewels of television history. It looks like it might initially serve as a cautionary tale of quality control when it comes to restorations and the technical process of bringing shows to streaming.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, &lt;/p&gt;Paul Haine was the first to notice something weird&lt;p&gt; going on with HBO Max' presentation. In one of season one's most memorable moments, Roger Sterling barfs in front of clients after climbing many flights of stairs. As a surprise to Paul, you can clearly see the pretend puke hose (that is ultimately strapped to the back side of John Slattery's face) in the background, along with two techs who are modulating the flow. Yeah, you're not supposed to see that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It appears as though this represents the original photography, unaltered before digital visual effects got involved. Somehow, this episode (along with many others) do not include all the digital visual effects that were in the original broadcasts and home video releases. It's a bizarro mistake for Lionsgate and HBO Max to make and not discover until after the show was streaming to customers.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear that this is a separate issue than the "reframed original film negative for 16:9" issue that has plagued many restorations that have left viewers scratching their heads. In those cases, the shows were originally shot on film and presented in 1.33-to-1 aspect ratio, but for their HD restorations the studio decided that their shows should fill the HD frame at the 16:9 aspect ratio, so portions of the negative, previously unseen and NOT intended for broadcast, were now suddenly visible, &lt;/p&gt;sometimes leading to ridiculous images that were never meant to be seen by audiences&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;example from "Friends" in HD, look at screen right&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;example from "Seinfeld" in HD&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Reframing old shows to fit a new aspect ratio is antithetical to the spirit of media restoration, and cheapens the future of our shared culture. The folks at the studios who insist on hobbling their most classic television shows are really bad at their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;But that's NOT what is going on with "Mad Men", since the show was mastered in 16:9 to begin with. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;I decided to help illustrate the changes&lt;p&gt; by diving in and creating images that might do better than words. The first thing I noticed is that, at least for season one, the episode titles and order were totally jumbled. The puke episode is "Red in the Face", not "Babylon".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;update 12/2/25: The season one episodes are being updated live on HBO Max to their correct positions and titles. The corrected title:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I lined up the Blu-ray edition of the episode with the current HBO Max episode:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The fun thing about this restoration mistake is that now we, the audience, get to see exactly how many digital visual effects were actually used in a show like "Mad Men", which most would assume did not have any digital effects component. In this shot, not only were the techs and hose removed, but the spot where the pretend puke meets Slattery's face has some clever digital warping to make it seem like the flow is truly coming from his mouth (as opposed to it appearing through a tube inches from his mouth, on the other side of his face).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;A Twitter user noticed&lt;p&gt; that the post-production screwups are not exclusive to season one, so I fired up my comparison machine to illustrate it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In this case, visual effects was used to obscure the fact that the show was filmed in 2000's era Los Angeles, not in 1960's New York City. Every sign was altered, and period-appropriate garbage NYC garbage cans were also added to each side of the frame.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;update 12/3/25: Another comparison below. When you fire up the first episode of the first season on HBO Max, right after the now-iconic opening titles, you might wonder why the music plays against black for a few beats. Well, that's because you're missing some titles that should appear on screen.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You should be seeing the text: "Mad Men: A term coined int he late 1950's to describe the advertising executives of Madison Avenue. They coined it." However, like the visual effects examples above, these graphics do not appear in the HBO Max version.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46133422</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 11:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>You Can't Fool the Optimizer</title><link>https://xania.org/202512/03-more-adding-integers</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a429e90ffa511a5c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Written by me, proof-read by an LLM. &lt;lb/&gt;Details at end.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sometimes you’ll step through code in a debugger and find a complex-looking loop… that executes as a single instruction. The compiler saw through the obfuscation and generated the obvious code anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider this assortment of highly questionable unsigned addition routines1 - for variety, here compiled for ARM (unlike yesterday’s addition example).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite these all being very different ways of returning &lt;code&gt;x + y&lt;/code&gt;, the compiler sees through it all and recognises that it’s just a single &lt;code&gt;add w0, w1, w0&lt;/code&gt;2 instruction. Even the recursive &lt;code&gt;add_v4&lt;/code&gt; - which calls itself - gets optimised down to the same single instruction3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The compiler’s ability to recognise patterns and replace them with efficient alternatives - even when the code is pretty obfuscated - is a superpower. It lets programmers choose how to write their code that’s intention-revealing (not like these contrived examples, obviously!) and leave the code generation up to the compiler, knowing that most of the time it’ll do the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So how does the compiler spot these patterns? Is it maintaining a database of “silly ways to add numbers”? Not quite. Internally, it translates your code into an intermediate representation - a simplified, abstract form that’s easier to analyse. When the compiler sees the while loop in &lt;code&gt;add_v3&lt;/code&gt;, it transforms it into something like “increment y by x, then return y”, which it then recognises as mathematically equivalent to “return x + y”. This process of converting different code patterns into a standard, canonical form is what lets the compiler treat them all identically. By the time code generation happens, all four functions look the same to the optimiser4.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This pattern recognition is remarkably robust - the compiler will happily optimise code you’d never want to write in the first place. Throughout this series we’ll see how far this canonicalisation can take us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See the video that accompanies this post.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post is day 3 of Advent of Compiler Optimisations 2025, a 25-day series exploring how compilers transform our code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This post was written by a human (Matt Godbolt) and reviewed and proof-read by LLMs and humans.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Support Compiler Explorer on Patreon or GitHub, or by buying CE products in the Compiler Explorer Shop.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thanks to long-term Compiler Explorer Patron Greg Baker for this example. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ARM supports three operands, so you should read this as &lt;code&gt;w0 = w1 + w0&lt;/code&gt;. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll cover tail-call optimisation and how it enables this later in the series. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can “Open in Compiler Explorer” the example above and then experiment with the “Opt Pipeline Viewer” to see some of the ways the compiler is doing this. ↩&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Matt Godbolt is a C++ developer living in Chicago. He works for Hudson River Trading on super fun but secret things. He is one half of the Two's Complement podcast. Follow him on Mastodon or Bluesky.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46133622</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 12:14:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Helldivers 2 devs slash install size from 154GB to 23GB</title><link>https://www.tomshardware.com/video-games/pc-gaming/helldivers-2-install-size-slashed-from-154gb-to-just-23gb-85-percent-reduction-accomplished-by-de-duplicating-game-data-an-optimization-for-older-mechanical-hard-drives</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="fd9ddd9e0f821ea9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Helldivers 2 devs slash install size from 154GB to 23GB, thanks to the help of PC port veterans — ditching HDD optimization, 85% size reduction accomplished by de-duplicating game data&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PC players can now opt into a slim version that’s 85% smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's no surprise to see modern AAA games occupying hundreds of gigabytes of storage these days, especially if you are gaming on a PC. But somehow, Arrowhead Game Studios, the developers behind the popular co-op shooter Helldivers 2, have managed to substantially cut the game’s size by 85%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As per a recent post on Steam, this reduction was made possible with support from Nixxes Software, best known for developing high-quality PC ports of Sony’s biggest PlayStation titles. The developers were able to achieve this by de-duplicating game data, which resulted in bringing the size down from ~154GB to just ~23GB, saving a massive ~131GB of storage space.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originally, the game’s large install size was attributed to optimization for mechanical hard drives since duplicating data is used to reduce loading times on older storage media. However, it turns out that Arrowhead’s estimates for load times on HDDs, based on industry data, were incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With their latest data measurements specific to the game, the developers have confirmed the small number of players (11% last week) using mechanical hard drives will witness mission load times increase by only a few seconds in worst cases. Additionally, the post reads, “the majority of the loading time in Helldivers 2 is due to level-generation rather than asset loading. This level generation happens in parallel with loading assets from the disk and so is the main determining factor of the loading time.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a promising development and a nudge to other game developers to take some notes and potentially make an effort in saving precious storage space for PC gamers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One can access the ‘slim’ version of Helldivers 2 by opting in to the latest beta update via Steam, which is said to functionally offer the same experience as the legacy versions, apart from its smaller installation size. All progression, war contributions, and purchases are also expected to be carried over to the new slim version. There's also the option to opt out of the beta at any time in case there are any potential issues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Follow Tom's Hardware on Google News, or add us as a preferred source, to get our latest news, analysis, &amp;amp; reviews in your feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get Tom's Hardware's best news and in-depth reviews, straight to your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kunal Khullar is a contributing writer at Tom’s Hardware. He is a long time technology journalist and reviewer specializing in PC components and peripherals, and welcomes any and every question around building a PC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;hotaru251&lt;/header&gt;i mean...its 2025...almost 2026 just accept that HDD for gaming is not gonna cut it. You can buy a 500GB ssd for sub $50.Reply&lt;lb/&gt;Don't be like the windows OS and drag dead weight (32bit x86) that holds you back.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;Gururu&lt;/header&gt;Having the option is key. I wonder if every other +100GB game has the same accommodations.Reply&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;gggplaya&lt;/header&gt;If you're a pc gamer in 2025, you should SSD's should be minimum spec for all AAA titles. I bought a 256GB SATA SSD for $20 years ago. You can get 256GB Sata SSD's on ebay for $15 now. I mean common, it's cheaper than most AAA titles. Even consoles are SSD only now.Reply&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;teeejay94&lt;/header&gt;Reply&lt;quote/&gt;Just accept that you can't get 12TB for 300$ on a SSD 💯 SSDs are also garbage for long term storage.hotaru251 said:i mean...its 2025...almost 2026 just accept that HDD for gaming is not gonna cut it. You can buy a 500GB ssd for sub $50.&lt;lb/&gt;Don't be like the windows OS and drag dead weight (32bit x86) that holds you back.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;deadcat27&lt;/header&gt;This is maddening to say the least. Just to sell a few more copies of a title, devs and publishers are wasting space on my storage which is crazy expensive per gb so that I can subsidize other players because they are too cheap or ill-informed to have proper modern hardware. I can't imagine what this has cost the rest of us and it's doubtful that this de-gigafication has anything to do with the user experience but rather the file transfer and hosting fees for the publishers. This 11% is the same group that creates a troubleshooting post/ticket about how their game runs poorly on their PC and when prompted for more detailed system info they reply simply, "It's a Windows PC."Reply&lt;lb/&gt;Over a decade ago, in 2011-12, I was playing WoW installed on Sandisk CZ80 because my system drive, a crucial m4 64gb, wasn't big enough to handle the OS and wow. I think even as a USB stick its TP and RA was way way faster than the standard hdd at the time and that 64gb was way less than $100. It wasn't anything special, just a i3-2120 and a gt560 and I bet that whole system cost ~$5-600ish and likely outperformed many of its contemporaries simply because it was using sata ssd and a USB flash drive. I can't imagine if I had used that system with just a hdd.&lt;lb/&gt;This nonsense is directly related to how some titles still have a forced pre-roll when starting up to allow for a hdd to load the game as if its a console while my system had the whole thing loaded before the pre-roll even displayed on my screen. This inconvenience only cost me 20 seconds of my life and not expensive nand though.&lt;lb/&gt;Just think. A modern W11 install fully configured after its trimming might only be around 25-35gb (ymmv). If the all game space we needed could get reduced like this we could all be using 100% SLC drives rather than a single game needlessly taking up most of it with current designs !&lt;lb/&gt;Ugh!&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;header&gt;gggplaya&lt;/header&gt;Replyteeejay94 said:Just accept that you can't get 12TB for 300$ on a SSD 💯 SSDs are also garbage for long term storage.&lt;lb/&gt;No one is saying for long term storage, just for gaming.&lt;lb/&gt;It's not fair that we need to take up 154GB of SSD space instead of 23GB just to accomodate the 11% of the player base that refuse to get an SSD for games.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46134178</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:20:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Congressional lawmakers 47% pts better at picking stocks</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w34524</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3ab211afd411b7b0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;"Captain Gains" on Capitol Hill&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Working Paper 34524 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; DOI 10.3386/w34524 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Issue Date &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using transaction-level data on US congressional stock trades, we find that lawmakers who later ascend to leadership positions perform similarly to matched peers beforehand but outperform them by 47 percentage points annually after ascension. Leaders’ superior performance arises through two mechanisms. The political influence channel is reflected in higher returns when their party controls the chamber, sales of stocks preceding regulatory actions, and purchase of stocks whose firms receiving more government contracts and favorable party support on bills. The corporate access channel is reflected in stock trades that predict subsequent corporate news and greater returns on donor-owned or home-state firms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt; Copy CitationShang-Jin Wei and Yifan Zhou, ""Captain Gains" on Capitol Hill," NBER Working Paper 34524 (2025), https://doi.org/10.3386/w34524.Download Citation&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46134443</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:50:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>GSWT: Gaussian Splatting Wang Tiles</title><link>https://yunfan.zone/gswt_webpage/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ea89769d8f9682b6"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;GSWT: Gaussian Splatting Wang Tiles&lt;/head&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Abstract&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) has shown strong capability in reconstructing and rendering photorealistic 3D scenes with high efficiency. However, extending 3DGS to synthesize large-scale or infinite terrains from a single captured exemplar—remains an open challenge. In this paper, we propose a tile-based framework that addresses this problem. Our method builds on Wang Tiles, where each tile encodes a local field of Gaussians with boundary constraints to ensure seamless transitions. This enables stochastic yet continuous tiling of Gaussian fields over arbitrary surfaces, allowing for procedural generation of expansive terrains with high spatial diversity. Furthermore, we introduce several rendering optimizations tailored to the unique characteristics of 3DGS Wang tiles, achieving real-time rendering of large-scale 3DGS terrains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pipeline&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given multi-view images of an exemplar scene, our goal is to construct Gaussian Splatting Wang Tiles (GSWT) that can be tiled on arbitrary surfaces and rendered in real time with our novel GSWT renderer. An overview of the entire pipeline is illustrated below. We begin by reconstructing the 3DGS exemplar at multiple LODs. For each level, we generate a set of Wang Tiles by sampling the edge and center patches and applying a semantic-aware graph cut algorithm. Prior to rendering, we pre-sort each tile for efficient sort-free splatting, and during runtime, we perform tiling on the fly, allowing efficient GSWT-based terrain synthesis and rendering.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (a) Given the input images, we construct the exemplar multiple times with different Level of Detail (LOD). &lt;lb/&gt; (b) We construct the tile set and preprocess it before rendering. &lt;lb/&gt; (c) The surface is tiled at run-time on the worker thread, while the main thread renders each frame. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Full Demo&lt;/head&gt;TBD&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;BibTeX&lt;/head&gt;&lt;code&gt;@inproceedings{Zeng:2025:gswt,
  author = {Zeng, Yunfan and Ma, Li and Sander, Pedro V.},
  title = {GSWT: Gaussian Splatting Wang Tiles},
  year = {2025},
  publisher = {Association for Computing Machinery},
  booktitle = {SIGGRAPH Asia 2025 Conference Papers},
  location = {Hong Kong, China},
  series = {SA '25}
}&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46134991</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:40:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mapping Every Dollar of America's $5T Healthcare System</title><link>https://healthisotherpeople.substack.com/p/an-abominable-creature</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46135008</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:42:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Microsoft lowers AI software growth targets</title><link>https://finance.yahoo.com/news/microsoft-lowers-ai-software-sales-141531121.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="af1729197ed28dcf"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dec 3 (Reuters) - Multiple divisions at Microsoft (MSFT) have lowered sales growth targets for certain artificial intelligence products after many sales staff missed goals in the fiscal year that ended in June, The Information reported on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is rare for Microsoft to lower quotas for specific products, the report said, citing two salespeople in the Azure cloud unit. The division is closely watched by investors as it is the main beneficiary of Microsoft's AI push.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shares of one of the biggest winners of the AI boom due to its early bet on ChatGPT-maker OpenAI fell nearly 3%, but pared losses after CNBC reported, citing Microsoft, that it has not lowered sales targets. The stock was last down 1.5%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft did not immediately respond to a Reuters request for comment. Reuters could not independently verify the report from The Information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;WORRIES OVER AI BUBBLE&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lower sales growth goals for its AI products are likely to fans fears about real-world adoption of the technology as investors fear the frenzy driving up valuations has turned into a bubble. An MIT study from earlier this year had found that only about 5% of AI projects advance beyond the pilot stage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Information report said Carlyle Group last year started using Copilot Studio to automate tasks such as meeting summaries and financial models, but cut its spending on the product after flagging Microsoft about its struggles to get the software to reliably pull data from other applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The report shows the industry was in the early stages of adopting AI, said D.A. Davidson analyst Gil Luria. "That does not mean there isn't promise for AI products to help companies become more productive, just that it may be harder than they thought."&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;U.S. tech giants are under investor pressure to prove that their hefty investments in AI infrastructure are generating returns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;RECORD SPENDING&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft reported a record capital expenditure of nearly $35 billion for its fiscal first quarter in October and warned that spending would rise this year. Overall, U.S. tech giants are expected to spend around $400 billion on AI this year.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The companies have said the outlay is necessary to overcome supply constraints that have hobbled their ability to capitalize on AI demand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft has predicted it would remain short on AI capacity at least until the end of its current fiscal year in June 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The spending has so far paid off for the Satya Nadella-led company as revenue at its Azure cloud-computing unit grew 40% in the July-September period, outpacing expectations. Its fiscal second-quarter forecast was also above estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46135388</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:11:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why are my headphones buzzing whenever I run my game?</title><link>https://alexene.dev/2025/12/03/Why-do-my-headphones-buzz-when-i-run-my-game.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f6e835137dac0b9f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Why are my headphones buzzing whenever I run my game?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Background&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am working on an isometric game inspired from Gnomoria, RimWorld, Dwarf Fortress, etc. It uses my own simple engine (with rust and wgpu-rs). Whenever I started my game, my headphones were buzzing. I could play Fortnite, Overwatch or any other game and that doesn’t cause my headphones to buzz. It’s only my game.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it’s really annoying, as you might imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why can I play Overwatch and Fortnite fine, while my isometric game makes my headset buzz? I had a fairly decent CPU, a 3090RTX card, 32GB RAM and USB audio through a MODI 2 DAC. Nothing out of this world, but nothing too bad. One important detail here is that the power to the MODI device comes from an USB port in my computer. This was the first clue, I tried other ports with no change in results (headphones still buzzed).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initially, I started to think it’s some sort of power-use related issue, because maybe my PSU was getting old, or had daemons in it. However, I still couldn’t explain why my tiny game was causing more chaos than say big games that send significantly more work at my PC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I noticed is that when it didn’t render anything, nothing buzzed (I run tests with rendering disabled). So that eliminated any sort of CPU work causing it. Let’s take a look at what the GPU does.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The pipeline&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The game has a simple graphics pipeline. I use WebGPU (more precisely wgpu-rs) and do some compute work to select visible entities, then use draw indirect to draw those entities. In the end, my render pipeline also outputs two things: the buffer that ends up on screen and a “picking texture”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A picking texture is a very simple idea. As the name says, it’s used to handle picking in the game, when you click somewhere on the screen (e.g. to select an unit), I use this texture to know what you clicked on. Instead of colors, every object instance writes their EntityID to this texture. Then, when you click the mouse, you check what id is in the pixel under the mouse position.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of a frame, I copy that picking texture back to RAM (from GPU memory), to check it against mouse positions in case of a click.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t ideal as transfers from GPU-&amp;gt;CPU memory take time, but it works and is way simpler to implement and debug than casting a ray through the scene:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;So why does rendering make my headphones buzz?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we have a picture of how the rendering in my game works, time to debug it. We know it’s something to do with the GPU work, but what can possibly cause this? As the trace above shows, my GPU is not under heavy load.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As I was stuck and had no idea on what can be a likely issue, I proceeded to then disable parts of my rendering pipeline (first the compute, then the rendering, then transferring the picking texture). When I skipped downloading the picking texture the buzzing was fully gone. What was confusing in this process is that disabling parts of the pipeline, somehow made the buzzing a lower volume and less noticeable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To be sure it was the picking texture download, I also issued the download every 250ms and noticed the noise is almost gone. Increasing the frequency on how often we download it to RAM, increased the buzzing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So at this point I had a likely source, but no idea why things would interfere in ways to what I assumed was the power to my MODI device. Through a bunch of discussion with other graphics engineers, someone suggested it may be due to the fact that I full on hit the GPU with tons of work, then pause the GPU to wait for that picking texture to transfer, then turn it back on 100% for the next frame.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That explanation is plausible and also likely as I further on proceeded to supply power to my MODI device from another source that’s not my PC and the buzzing was gone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now that we know this, all was left is to fix it. In hindsight, the solution is obvious. There’s no need to download the whole texture each frame, just the part of the picking texture that’s under the mouse. So I implemented that and it worked and buzzing is gone. As a bonus, now it’s also not visible at all on the GPU trace.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46135627</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:30:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>VA staff flag dangerous errors in Oracle-built electronic health record</title><link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/investigations/2025/12/03/veterans-administration-va-hospitals-health/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3dceb20b68ac9f9c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the eve of a major expansion, a multibillion-dollar project to upgrade the computer systems of all Department of Veterans Affairs hospitals is beset with problems, according to some medical staff who already use it. Critical patient notes disappear. Prescriptions log the wrong dosages. One nurse said the system incorrectly listed one of her patients as dead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;23 min&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This story was produced through a partnership between The Washington Post and The Spokesman-Review.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46135661</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:32:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Critical Security Vulnerability in React Server Components</title><link>https://react.dev/blog/2025/12/03/critical-security-vulnerability-in-react-server-components</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bc2bbf4cc953e9c2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Critical Security Vulnerability in React Server Components&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;December 3, 2025 by The React Team&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is an unauthenticated remote code execution vulnerability in React Server Components.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We recommend upgrading immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On November 29th, Lachlan Davidson reported a security vulnerability in React that allows unauthenticated remote code execution by exploiting a flaw in how React decodes payloads sent to React Server Function endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if your app does not implement any React Server Function endpoints it may still be vulnerable if your app supports React Server Components.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This vulnerability was disclosed as CVE-2025-55182 and is rated CVSS 10.0.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vulnerability is present in versions 19.0, 19.1.0, 19.1.1, and 19.2.0 of:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Immediate Action Required&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A fix was introduced in versions 19.0.1, 19.1.2, and 19.2.1. If you are using any of the above packages please upgrade to any of the fixed versions immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If your app’s React code does not use a server, your app is not affected by this vulnerability. If your app does not use a framework, bundler, or bundler plugin that supports React Server Components, your app is not affected by this vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Affected frameworks and bundlers&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some React frameworks and bundlers depended on, had peer dependencies for, or included the vulnerable React packages. The following React frameworks &amp;amp; bundlers are affected: next, react-router, waku, @parcel/rsc, @vitejs/plugin-rsc, and rwsdk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We will update this post with upgrade instructions on how to upgrade as they become available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Hosting Provider Mitigations&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have worked with a number of hosting providers to apply temporary mitigations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You should not depend on these to secure your app, and still update immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Vulnerability overview&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;React Server Functions allow a client to call a function on a server. React provides integration points and tools that frameworks and bundlers use to help React code run on both the client and the server. React translates requests on the client into HTTP requests which are forwarded to a server. On the server, React translates the HTTP request into a function call and returns the needed data to the client.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An unauthenticated attacker could craft a malicious HTTP request to any Server Function endpoint that, when deserialized by React, achieves remote code execution on the server. Further details of the vulnerability will be provided after the rollout of the fix is complete.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Update Instructions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Next.js&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All users should upgrade to the latest patched version in their release line:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install next@15.0.5   // for 15.0.x&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are on Next.js 14.3.0-canary.77 or a later canary release, downgrade to the latest stable 14.x release:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install next@14&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See the Next.js changelog for more info.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;React Router&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are using React Router’s unstable RSC APIs, you should upgrade the following package.json dependencies if they exist:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install react@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Expo&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upgrade to the latest &lt;code&gt;react-server-dom-webpack&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install react@latest react-dom@latest react-server-dom-webpack@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Redwood SDK&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ensure you are on rwsdk&amp;gt;=1.0.0-alpha.0&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the latest beta version:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install rwsdk@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upgrade to the latest &lt;code&gt;react-server-dom-webpack&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install react@latest react-dom@latest react-server-dom-webpack@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;See Redwood docs for more migration instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Waku&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upgrade to the latest &lt;code&gt;react-server-dom-webpack&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install react@latest react-dom@latest react-server-dom-webpack@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;@vitejs/plugin-rsc&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upgrade to the latest RSC plugin:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install react@latest react-dom@latest @vitejs/plugin-rsc@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;react-server-dom-parcel&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update to the latest version:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install react@latest react-dom@latest react-server-dom-parcel@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;react-server-dom-turbopack&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update to the latest version:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install react@latest react-dom@latest react-server-dom-turbopack@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;
      &lt;code&gt;react-server-dom-webpack&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update to the latest version:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;npm install react@latest react-dom@latest react-server-dom-webpack@latest&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Timeline&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;November 29th: Lachlan Davidson reported the security vulnerability via Meta Bug Bounty.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;November 30th: Meta security researchers confirmed and began working with the React team on a fix.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;December 1st: A fix was created and the React team began working with affected hosting providers and open source projects to validate the fix, implement mitigations and roll out the fix&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;December 3rd: The fix was published to npm and the publicly disclosed as CVE-2025-55182.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Attribution&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you to Lachlan Davidson for discovering, reporting, and working to help fix this vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46135784</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:43:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MinIO is now in maintenance-mode</title><link>https://github.com/minio/minio/commit/27742d469462e1561c776f88ca7a1f26816d69e2</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="37a3c795b9d7e61e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;main&gt;
            &lt;turbo-frame&gt;
              &lt;div&gt;
                &lt;react-app&gt;
                  &lt;div&gt;
                    &lt;div&gt;
                      &lt;div&gt;
                        &lt;div&gt;
                          &lt;div&gt;
                            &lt;div&gt;
                              &lt;div&gt;
                                &lt;h2&gt;File tree&lt;/h2&gt;
                                &lt;div&gt;
                                  &lt;div&gt;
                                    &lt;div&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;Expand file tree&lt;/span&gt;
                                      &lt;button/&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;Collapse file tree&lt;/span&gt;
                                      &lt;h2&gt;1 file changed&lt;/h2&gt;
                                      &lt;p&gt;+14&lt;/p&gt;
                                      &lt;p&gt;-0&lt;/p&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;lines changed&lt;/span&gt;
                                    &lt;/div&gt;
                                  &lt;/div&gt;
                                &lt;/div&gt;
                              &lt;/div&gt;
                            &lt;/div&gt;
                          &lt;/div&gt;
                          &lt;div&gt;
                            &lt;div&gt;
                              &lt;div&gt;
                                &lt;div&gt;
                                  &lt;div&gt;
                                    &lt;div&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;Expand file tree&lt;/span&gt;
                                      &lt;button/&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;Collapse file tree&lt;/span&gt;
                                      &lt;h2&gt;1 file changed&lt;/h2&gt;
                                      &lt;p&gt;+14&lt;/p&gt;
                                      &lt;p&gt;-0&lt;/p&gt;
                                      &lt;span&gt;lines changed&lt;/span&gt;
                                    &lt;/div&gt;
                                  &lt;/div&gt;
                                  &lt;div&gt;
                                    &lt;div&gt;
                                      &lt;div&gt;
                                        &lt;table&gt;
                                          &lt;thead&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;th&gt;Original file line number&lt;/th&gt;
                                              &lt;th&gt;Diff line number&lt;/th&gt;
                                              &lt;th&gt;Diff line change&lt;/th&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                          &lt;/thead&gt;
                                          &lt;tbody&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;
                                                    &lt;span&gt;# &lt;span&gt;Maintenance Mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;**&lt;/span&gt;This project is currently under maintenance and is not accepting new changes.&lt;span&gt;**&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;4&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;5&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; The codebase is in a maintenance-only state&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;6&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; No new features, enhancements, or pull requests will be accepted&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;7&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; Critical security fixes may be evaluated on a case-by-case basis&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;8&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; Existing issues and pull requests will not be actively reviewed&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;9&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; Community support continues on a best-effort basis through &lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;Slack&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://slack.min.io&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;10&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;11&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;For enterprise support and actively maintained versions, please see &lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;MinIO AIStor&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://www.min.io/product/aistor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;12&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;13&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;
                                                    &lt;span&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;14&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;span&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;15&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;
                                                    &lt;span&gt;# &lt;span&gt;MinIO Quickstart Guide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                                                  &lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;16&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;p/&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                            &lt;tr&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;17&lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                              &lt;td&gt;
                                                &lt;code&gt;
                                                  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;![&lt;/span&gt;Slack&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://slack.min.io/slack?type=svg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://slack.min.io&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;![&lt;/span&gt;Docker Pulls&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://img.shields.io/docker/pulls/minio/minio.svg?maxAge=604800&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://hub.docker.com/r/minio/minio/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;![&lt;/span&gt;license&lt;span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://img.shields.io/badge/license-AGPL%20V3-blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;https://github.com/minio/minio/blob/master/LICENSE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                                                &lt;/code&gt;
                                              &lt;/td&gt;
                                            &lt;/tr&gt;
                                          &lt;/tbody&gt;
                                        &lt;/table&gt;
                                      &lt;/div&gt;
                                    &lt;/div&gt;
                                  &lt;/div&gt;
                                &lt;/div&gt;
                                &lt;svg&gt;
                                  &lt;defs/&gt;
                                &lt;/svg&gt;
                              &lt;/div&gt;
                            &lt;/div&gt;
                          &lt;/div&gt;
                        &lt;/div&gt;
                      &lt;/div&gt;
                    &lt;/div&gt;
                  &lt;/div&gt;
                &lt;/react-app&gt;
              &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;/turbo-frame&gt;
          &lt;/main&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;svg/&gt;
        &lt;button&gt;
          &lt;svg/&gt;
        &lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;p&gt; You can’t perform that action at this time. &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;template&gt;
        &lt;details&gt;
          &lt;details-dialog&gt;
            &lt;button&gt;
              &lt;svg/&gt;
            &lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;/details-dialog&gt;
        &lt;/details&gt;
      &lt;/template&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46136023</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 16:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>RCE Vulnerability in React and Next.js</title><link>https://github.com/vercel/next.js/security/advisories/GHSA-9qr9-h5gf-34mp</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="9b77f64ed15ff8f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;RCE in React Server Components&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Package&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Affected versions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;gt;=14.3.0-canary.77, &amp;gt;=15, &amp;gt;=16&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Patched versions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v16.0.7, v15.5.7, v15.4.8, v15.3.6, v15.2.6, v15.1.9, v15.0.5&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Description&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A vulnerability affects certain React packages1 for versions 19.0.0, 19.1.0, 19.1.1, and 19.2.0 and frameworks that use the affected packages, including Next.js 15.x and 16.x using the App Router. The issue is tracked upstream as CVE-2025-55182.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fixed in:&lt;lb/&gt; React: 19.0.1, 19.1.2, 19.2.1&lt;lb/&gt; Next.js: 15.0.5, 15.1.9, 15.2.6, 15.3.6, 15.4.8, 15.5.7, 16.0.7&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vulnerability also affects experimental canary releases starting with 14.3.0-canary.77. Users on any of the 14.3 canary builds should either downgrade to a 14.x stable release or 14.3.0-canary.76.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All users of stable 15.x or 16.x Next.js versions should upgrade to a patched, stable version immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1 The affected React packages are:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;react-server-dom-parcel&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;react-server-dom-turbopack&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;react-server-dom-webpack&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46136026</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 16:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Critical RCE Vulnerabilities in React and Next.js</title><link>https://www.wiz.io/blog/critical-vulnerability-in-react-cve-2025-55182</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd2ab75fcb139341"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CVE-2025-55182 (React) and CVE-2025-66478 (Next.js) are critical unauthenticated RCE vulnerabilities in the React Server Components (RSC) “Flight” protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default configurations are vulnerable – a standard Next.js app created with create-next-app and built for production can be exploited with no code changes by the developer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exploitation requires only a crafted HTTP request and has shown near-100% reliability in testing. The flaw stems from insecure deserialization in the RSC payload handling logic, allowing attacker-controlled data to influence server-side execution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Immediate patching is required. Hardened releases for React and Next.js are available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wiz Research data shows 39% of cloud environments contain vulnerable instances.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Technical Details&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A critical vulnerability has been identified in the React Server Components (RSC) "Flight" protocol, affecting the React 19 ecosystem and frameworks that implement it, most notably Next.js. Assigned CVE-2025-55182 (React) and CVE-2025-66478 (Next.js), this flaw allows for unauthenticated remote code execution (RCE) on the server due to insecure deserialization. The vulnerability exists in the default configuration of affected applications, meaning standard deployments are immediately at risk. Due to the high severity and the ease of exploitation, immediate patching is required.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To maintain ecosystem safety while patches are applied, we are currently withholding specific details; the details provided here are intended solely to assist defenders in prioritizing remediation and understanding the risk. We will be updating this blog with additional information as it comes to light.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What are CVE-2025-55182 and CVE-2025-66478?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CVE-2025-55182 is a critical unauthenticated remote code execution (RCE) vulnerability in the react-server package used by React Server Components (RSC).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CVE-2025-66478 is the corresponding RCE vulnerability in Next.js, which inherits the same underlying flaw through its implementation of the RSC “Flight” protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The vulnerability fundamentally resides in the react-server package and its handling of the RSC "Flight" protocol. It is characterized as a logical deserialization vulnerability where the server processes RSC payloads in an unsafe manner. When a server receives a specially crafted, malformed payload, it fails to validate the structure correctly. This allows attacker-controlled data to influence server-side execution logic, resulting in the execution of privileged JavaScript code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In our experimentation, exploitation of this vulnerability had high fidelity, with a near 100% success rate and can be leveraged to a full remote code execution. The attack vector is unauthenticated and remote, requiring only a specially crafted HTTP request to the target server. It affects the default configuration of popular frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wiz Research data: what’s the risk to cloud environments?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to Wiz data, 39% of cloud environments have instances vulnerable to CVE-2025-55182 and/or CVE-2025-66478.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which products are affected?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vulnerable product&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Patched release&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;React: 19.0, 19.1, 19.2&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;19.0.1, 19.1.2, and 19.2.1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next.js: 14.3.0-canary, 15.x, and 16.x (App Router)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any framework or library bundling the react-server implementation is likely affected. This includes, but is not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next.js&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Vite RSC plugin&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parcel RSC plugin&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;React Router RSC preview&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RedwoodSDK&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Waku&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which actions should security teams take?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1. Upgrade React and dependencies to the hardened versions (see above). This is the only definitive mitigation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2. if you are using other RSC-enabled frameworks (Redwood, Waku, etc.), check their official channels for updates regarding the bundled react-server version and update immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modern code runs in complex and distributed cloud environments. Wiz SAST meets this complexity by correlating code flaws with real cloud context–including where workloads run, what they can access, and how exposed they are.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46136067</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 16:03:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Steam Deck lead reveals Valve is funding ARM compatibility of Windows games</title><link>https://frvr.com/blog/news/steam-deck-lead-reveals-valve-is-funding-arm-compatibility-of-windows-games-to-expand-pc-gaming-and-release-ultraportables-in-the-future/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="84de38730d022cfe"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For over a decade, Steam company Valve’s biggest goal has been bringing Windows games to Linux. While that goal is almost complete with the massive success of Proton compatibility on Steam Deck and the upcoming Steam Machine, the company has also been secretly pushing to bring Windows games to ARM devices.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In an interview with The Verge, Steam Deck and SteamOS lead Pierre-Loup Griffais revealed that Valve has been secretly funding Fex, an open-source project to bring Windows games to ARM, for almost a decade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In 2016, 2017, there was always an idea we would end up wanting to do that,” the SteamOS lead said, and that’s when the Fex compatibility layer was started, because we knew there was close to a decade of work needed before it would be robust enough people could rely on it for their libraries. There’s a lot of work that went into that.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Griffais explained that the project pushes to “reduce barriers for users not having to worry about what games run”. With Windows games running on ARM, a large number of Steam games are able to run on a significant number of additional devices including low-power laptops, tablets and even phones (hopefully) without issue.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While Griffais didn’t confirm specific devices that Valve is working on, the SteamOS lead explained that they’re “excited” about creating potential ARM-based devices. “I think that it paves the way for a bunch of different, maybe ultraportables, maybe more powerful laptops being ARM-based and using different offerings in that segment,” he said. “Handhelds, there’s a lot of potential for ARM, of course, and one might see desktop chips as well at some point in the ARM world.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But why ARM? The Steam Deck lead explained that the hardware offers more efficiency at lower power compared to other options. While the current hardware in the Steam Deck and other handhelds can run at low-wattage, they’re simply less efficient at lower-power than hardware designed specifically to run at that spec.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“There’s a lot of price points and power consumption points where Arm-based chipsets are doing a better job of serving the market,” they said. “When you get into lower power, anything lower than Steam Deck, I think you’ll find that there’s an ARM chip that maybe is competitive with x86 offerings in that segment.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We’re pretty excited to be able to expand PC gaming to include all those options instead of being arbitrarily restricted to a subset of the market,” they continued.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valve is currently working on an ARM version of SteamOS using “the same exact OS components, the same exact Arch Linux base, all the same updater, all the same technologies,” Griffais said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“When you’re looking at SteamOS on Arm, you’re really looking at the same thing,” he continued. “Instead of downloading the normal Proton that’s built for x86 and targets x86 games, it will also be able to download a Proton that’s Arm-aware, that has a bulk of its code compiled for Arm and can also include the Fex emulator.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of this is to give players a choice. While Windows games are built for Windows, they don’t necessarily need to be played on Windows. Valve has already proven how effective this can be with some games Windows running via Proton performing better due to the lack of Windows bloat.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, there are issues. Some games have compatibility problems out of the box, and modern multiplayer games with anti-cheat simply do not work through a translation layer, something Valve hopes will change in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s all fantastic work though, and it gives players a chance to break away from Windows without losing much, if anything, when shifting ecosystems. For decades, Windows has dominated the PC space, and it likely still will for a long while, but now there’s actually space for alternatives to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve already seen massive adoption of SteamOS via the Steam Deck, but with Bazzite now shifting petabytes of ISOs every month, there’s definitely an urge to move away from Windows, at least on the handheld side.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46136901</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 17:00:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rocketable (YC W25) is hiring a founding engineer to automate software companies</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/rocketable/jobs/CArgzmX-founding-engineer-automation-platform</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="355ab05ec9c6afb0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You've been watching the AI capability curve. You've done the mental math. You know where this is going.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;While most people are still debating whether LLMs can "really" reason, you're thinking about what happens when agents replace entire functions, when systems can debug themselves, when software can operate without humans touching it.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We're building that future. Right now. With real companies.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Premise&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rocketable acquires profitable SaaS companies and transforms them into fully autonomous systems. No human operators. No engineering team shipping features. No support staff answering tickets. Just AI running the entire business.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This sounds crazy to most people, but the trajectory is obvious if you're paying attention. Within a few years, the question won't be "can AI run a software company?" It will be "why would a human?"&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you think we're wrong, don't apply. If you think we're early, let's talk.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Role&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;You'll be the architect of the platform that makes this possible.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Starting point: A live SaaS company. Revenue. Customers. All the messy reality of a business that currently requires humans to operate.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Week 4: Your agent swarm handles first-line customer support. A meta-layer analyzes every human intervention—not just logging it, but learning from it. Why did a human need to step in? How do we eliminate that trigger?&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Week 12: Hours of autonomous operation. Agents creating specialized sub-agents. The system building its own tools when it hits capability gaps. Performance metrics tracking toward superhuman baselines.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Beyond: Each new acquisition stress-tests your abstractions. Different tech stacks. Different domains. Different edge cases. The platform either generalizes or we start over and rebuild until it does.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Filter&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Apply if:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You believe full automation for software companies isn't just possible, it's inevitable (and you want to be the one building it).&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You'd rather fail at something unprecedented than succeed at something incremental.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You want to work on the hardest version of the problem, not the safe version that gets you acqui-hired in 18 months.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Don't apply if:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You think "human in the loop" is a permanent design pattern, not a temporary constraint.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You're uncomfortable with the societal implications of what we're building. (We think about them. We just don't let them paralyze us.)&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;You're optimizing for a good story for your next job, not for a decade of building something durable.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Technical Requirements&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This isn't a research role. You need to ship production systems.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Systems (5+ years): You've scaled production systems to 100K+ DAU. You understand distributed architectures deeply (microservices, event-driven systems, message queues). Full-stack fluency from frontend to infrastructure. TypeScript and Python preferred.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;AI/ML: Hands-on LLM integration (OpenAI, Anthropic, Google). You treat prompt and context engineering as an engineering discipline with version control, evals, and systematic optimization. You've built systems to measure AI performance. Bonus points for self-improving systems, RL, RLHF.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Infrastructure: Kubernetes. Docker with real security understanding. Infrastructure as Code. Cloud platforms (GCP or AWS preferred). CI/CD that doesn't suck. Observability that helps you debug distributed systems. Security fundamentals.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Setup&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Founder: Alan Wells. Ex-Cruise, ex-Uber ATG. 10+ years of experience building AI/ML products that sense, predict, and act in mission-critical applications.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Funding: $6.5M seed from Y Combinator, True Ventures, Bloomberg Beta, Indie.vc, and others. Capital for 3+ acquisitions.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;Team philosophy: Small by design. In-person 5 days/week (San Francisco default, Marin County possible).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Bet&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rocketable is a bet that AI capabilities will continue accelerating. That autonomous systems will outperform human-operated ones. That the companies who figure this out first will have a compounding advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We might be wrong. But if we're right, you'll have built the infrastructure that runs a new kind of company. This is the highest-leverage engineering work that exists right now.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;That's the trade. Interested? Apply here.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;More about Rocketable:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46136918</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 17:01:18 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>