<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 06:50:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Why haven't quantum computers factored 21 yet?</title><link>https://algassert.com/post/2500</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7135b1ea033e1ef8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In 2001, quantum computers factored the number 15. It’s now 2025, and quantum computers haven’t yet factored the number 21. It’s sometimes claimed this is proof there’s been no progress in quantum computers. But there’s actually a much more surprising reason 21 hasn’t been factored yet, which jumps out at you when contrasting the operations used to factor 15 and to factor 21.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The circuit (the series of quantum logic gates) that was run to factor 15 can be seen in Figure 1b of “Experimental realization of Shor’s quantum factoring algorithm using nuclear magnetic resonance”:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The important cost here is the number of entangling gates. This factoring-15 circuit has 6 two-qubit entangling gates (a mix of CNOT and CPHASE gates). It also has 2 Toffoli gates, which each decompose into 6 two-qubit entangling gates. So there’s a total of 21 entangling gates in this circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, for comparison, here is a circuit for factoring 21. Sorry for rotating it, but I couldn’t get it to fit otherwise. Try counting the Toffolis:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Here’s an OPENQASM2 version of the circuit, so you can test it produces the right distribution if you’re inclined to do so.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In case you lost count: this circuit has 191 cnot gates and 369 Toffoli gates, implying a total of 2405 entangling gates. That’s 115x more entangling gates than the factoring-15 circuit. The factoring-21 circuit is more than one hundred times more expensive than the factoring-15 circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I ask people to guess how many times larger the factoring-21 circuit is, compared to the factoring-15 circuit, there’s a tendency for them to assume it’s 25% larger. Or maybe twice as large. The fact that it’s two orders of magnitude more expensive is shocking. So I’ll try to explain why it happens.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Quick aside: the amount of optimization that has gone into this factoring-21 circuit is probably unrepresentative of what would be possible when factoring big numbers. I think a more plausible amount of optimization would produce a circuit with 500x the cost of the factoring-15 circuit… but a 100x overhead is sufficient to make my point. Regardless, special thanks to Noah Shutty for running expensive computer searches to find the conditional-multiplication-by-4-mod-21 subroutine used by this circuit.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Where does the 100x come from?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A key background fact you need to understand is that the dominant cost of a quantum factoring circuit comes from doing a series of conditional modular multiplications under superposition. To factor an $n$-bit number $N$, Shor’s algorithm will conditionally multiply an accumulator by $m_k = g^{2^k} \pmod{N}$ for each $k &amp;lt; 2n$ (where $g$ is a randomly chosen value coprime to $N$). Sometimes people also worry about the frequency basis measurement at the end of the algorithm, which is crucial to the algorithm’s function, but from a cost perspective it’s irrelevant. (It’s negligible due by an optimization called “qubit recycling”, which I also could have used to reduce the qubit count of the factoring-21 circuit, but in this post I’m just counting gates so meh).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are three effects that conspire to make the factoring-15 multiplications substantially cheaper than the factoring-21 multiplications:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;All but two of the factoring-15 multiplications end up multiplying by 1.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The first multiplication is always ~free, because its input is known to be 1.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The one remaining factoring-15 multiplication can be implemented with only two CSWAPs.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s consider the case where $g=2$. In that case, when factoring 15, the constants to conditionally multiply by would be:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print([pow(2, 2**k, 15) for k in range(8)])
[2, 4, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, notice that the last six constants are 1. Multiplications by 1 can be implemented by doing nothing. So the factoring-15 circuit is only paying for 2 of the expected 8 multiplications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Second, notice that the first conditional multiplication (by 2) will either leave the accumulator storing 1 (when its control is off) or storing 2 (when its control is on). This can be achieved much more cheaply by performing a controlled xor of $1 \oplus 2 = 3$ into the accumulator.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Third, notice that the only remaining multiplication is a multiplication by 4. Because 15 is one less than a power of 2, multiplying by 2 modulo 15 can be implemented using a circular shift. A multiplication by 4 is just two multiplications by 2, so it can also be implemented by a circular shift. This is a very rare property for a modular multiplication to have, and here it reduces what should be an expensive operation into a pair of conditional swaps. (If you go back and look at the factoring-15 circuit at the top of the post, the 2 three-qubit gates are being used to implement these two conditional swaps.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may worry that these savings are specific to the choice of $g=2$ and $N=15$. And they are in fact specific to $N=15$. But they aren’t specific to $g=2$. They occur for all possible choices of $g$ when factoring 15.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For contrast, let’s now consider what happens when factoring 21. Using $g=2$, the multiplication constants would be:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;  print([pow(2, 2**k, 21) for k in range(10)])
[2, 4, 16, 4, 16, 4, 16, 4, 16, 4]
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is going to be a lot more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, there’s no multiplications by 1, so the circuit has to pay for every multiplication instead of only a quarter. That’s a ~4x relative cost blowup vs factoring 15. Second, although the first-one’s-free trick does still apply, proportionally speaking it’s not as good. It cheapens 10% of the multiplications rather than 50%. That’s an extra ~1.8x cost blowup vs factoring 15. Third, the multiplication by 4 and 16 can’t be implemented with two CSWAPs. The best conditionally-multiply-by-4-mod-21 circuit that I know is the one being used in the diagram above, and it uses 41 Toffolis. These more expensive multiplications add a final bonus ~20x cost blowup vs factoring 15.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Aside: multiplication by 16 mod 21 is the inverse of multiplying by 4 mod 21, and the circuits are reversible, so multiplying by 16 uses the same number of Toffolis as multiplying by 4.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These three factors (multiplying-by-one, first-one’s-free, and multiplying-by-swapping) explain the 100x blowup in cost of factoring 21, compared to factoring 15. And this 100x increase in cost explains why no one has factored 21 with a quantum computer yet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another contributor to the huge time gap between factoring 15 and factoring 21 is that the 2001 factoring of 15 was done with an NMR quantum computer. These computers were known to have inherent scaling issues, and in fact it’s debated whether NMR computers were even properly “quantum”. If the 2001 NMR experiment doesn’t count, I think the actually-did-the-multiplications runner-up is a 2015 experiment done with an ion trap quantum computer (discussed by Scott Aaronson at the time).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet another contributor is the overhead of quantum error correction. Performing 100x more gates requires 100x lower error, and the most plausible way of achieving that is error corection. Error correction requires redundancy, and could easily add a 100x overhead on qubit count. Accounting for this, I could argue that factoring 21 will be ten thousand times more expensive than factoring 15, rather than “merely” a hundred times more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are papers that claim to have factored 21 with a quantum computer. For example, here’s one from 2021. But, as far as I know, all such experiments are guilty of using optimizations that imply the code generating the circuit had access to information equivalent to knowing the factors (as explained in “Pretending to factor large numbers on a quantum computer” by Smolin et al). Basically: they don’t do the multiplications, because the multiplications are hard, but the multiplications are what make it factoring instead of simpler forms of period finding. So I don’t count them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is unfortunately a trickle of bullshit results that claim to be quantum factoring demonstrations. For example, I have a joke paper in this year’s sigbovik proceedings that cheats in a particularly silly way. More seriously, I enjoyed “Replication of Quantum Factorisation Records with an 8-bit Home Computer, an Abacus, and a Dog” making fun of some recent egregious papers. I also recommend Scott Aaronson’s post “Quantum computing motte-and-baileys”, which complains about papers that benchmark “variational” factoring techniques while ignoring the lack of any reason to expect them to scale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because of the large cost of quantum factoring numbers (that aren’t 15), factoring isn’t yet a good benchmark for tracking the progress of quantum computers. If you want to stay abreast of progress in quantum computing, you should be paying attention to the arrival quantum error correction (such as surface codes getting more reliable as their size is increased) and to architectures solving core scaling challenges (such as lost neutral atoms being continuously replaced).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45082587</guid></item><item><title>F-Droid site certificate expired</title><link>https://gitlab.com/fdroid/fdroid-website/-/issues/883</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7857cdff5f9f3c6f"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Skip to content GitLab Menu Why GitLab Pricing Contact Sales Explore Why GitLab Pricing Contact Sales Explore Sign in Get free trial Site certificates expired "Your connection isn't private" I got error when access f-droid.org on Edge and Chrome To upload designs, you'll need to enable LFS and have an admin enable hashed storage. More information&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45082595</guid></item><item><title>“This telegram must be closely paraphrased before being communicated to anyone”</title><link>https://history.stackexchange.com/questions/79371/this-telegram-must-be-closely-paraphrased-before-being-communicated-to-anyone</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2e9509d36c2fa0d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It appears that it was US military communications doctrine to not send the exact same message twice using different encryption ("none" counting as one type of encryption), and the term of art for changing a message to avoid that was indeed "paraphrase".&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I managed to dig up a US Army document on Cryptology from roughly that era that appears to discuss paraphrasing. The document in question is Department of the Army Technical Manual TM 32-220(pdf), dated 1950, titled "BASIC CRYPTOGRAPHY". It apparently supersedes previous documents TM-484 from March 1945 and TM 11-485 from June 1944. It would probably be more ideal to look at them, since they are closer to the time you are interested in, but I was not able to find them online.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Here's what this declassified manual had to say about "paraphrasing", from Chapter 7, in the section Fundamental Rules of Cryptographic Security, section 84, subsection b, rule 3 (titled "Text of messages")&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;(a) Never repeat in the clear the identical text of a message once sent in cryptographic form, or repeat in cryptographic form the text of a message once sent in the clear. Anything which will enable an alert enemy to compare a given piece of plain text with a cryptogram that supposedly contains this plain text is highly dangerous to the safety of the cryptographic system. Where information must be given out for publicity, or where information is handled by many persons, the plain text version should be very carefully paraphrased before distribution, to minimize the data an enemy might obtain from an accurate comparison of the cryptographic text with the equivalent, original plain text. To paraphrase a message means to rewrite it so as to change its original wording as much as possible without changing the meaning of the message. This is done by altering the positions of sentences in the message, by altering the positions of subject, predicate, and modifying phrases or clauses in the sentence, and by altering as much as possible the diction by the use of synonyms and synonymous expressions. In this process, deletion rather than expansion of the wording of the message is preferable, because if an ordinary message is paraphrased simply by expanding it along its original lines, an expert can easily reduce the paraphrased message to its lowest terms, and the resultant wording will be practically the original message. It is very important to eliminate repeated words or proper names, if at all possible, by the use of carefully selected pronouns; by the use of the words "former," "latter," "first-mentioned," "second-mentioned"; or by other means. After carefully paraphrasing, the message can be sent in the other key or code.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;(b) Never send the literal plain text or a paraphrased version of the plain text of a message which has been or will be transmitted in cryptographed form except as specifically provided in appropriate regulations&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;(emphasis mine)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In fact the allies would have have known intimately about how this was possible, because this is one of the ways they ended up decrypting the stronger German Enigma cipher. Captured machines using simpler ciphers were used to break those simpler ciphers. The fact that the Germans were encrypting the exact same messages in both ciphers meant the allies could know (for those messages) what both the unencrypted and encrypted messages were, which allowed them to decrypt the stronger cyphers as well, or quickly figure out what today's code was.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Though Enigma had some cryptographic weaknesses, in practice it was German procedural flaws, operator mistakes, failure to systematically introduce changes in encipherment procedures, and Allied capture of key tables and hardware that, during the war, enabled Allied cryptologists to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45082731</guid></item><item><title>Survey: a third of senior developers say over half their code is AI-generated</title><link>https://www.fastly.com/blog/senior-developers-ship-more-ai-code</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="67c0a117eb3142e8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Vibe Shift? Senior Developers Ship nearly 2.5x more AI Code than Junior Counterparts&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Content Marketing Manager&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fastlyâs July 2025 survey of 791 developers found a notable difference in how much AI-generated code is making it into production. About a third of senior developers (10+ years of experience) say over half their shipped code is AI-generated â nearly two and a half times the rate reported by junior developers (0â2 years of experience), at 13%.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;âAI will bench test code and find errors much faster than a human, repairing them seamlessly. This has been the case many times,â one senior developer said. A junior respondent noted the trade-offs: âItâs always hard when AI assumes what Iâm doing and thatâs not the case, so I have to go back and redo it myself.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Senior developers were also more likely to say they invest time fixing AI-generated code. Just under 30% of seniors reported editing AI output enough to offset most of the time savings, compared to 17% of juniors. Even so, 59% of seniors say AI tools help them ship faster overall, compared to 49% of juniors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Senior Developers Are More Optimistic About AI Saving Time&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just over 50% of junior developers say AI makes them moderately faster. By contrast, only 39% of more senior developers say the same. But senior devs are more likely to report significant speed gains: 26% say AI makes them a lot faster, double the 13% of junior devs who agree.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One reason for this gap may be that senior developers are simply better equipped to catch and correct AIâs mistakes. They have the experience to recognize when code âlooks rightâ but isnât. That makes them more confident at using AI tools efficiently, even for high-stakes or business-critical code. By contrast, junior developers may not fully trust their ability to spot errors, which can make them more cautious about relying on AI, or more likely to avoid using it in production at all.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That tracks with how much AI-generated code actually makes it into production. Among junior devs, just 13% say over half of their shipped code is AI-generated. By contrast, 32% of senior developers say the same, suggesting that more experienced engineers are not only using AI more aggressively, but are also trusting it more in production environments. This is surprising given growing concerns about âvibe codingâ introducing vulnerabilities into applications.Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Perception vs. Reality&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Nearly 1 in 3 developers (28%) say they frequently have to fix or edit AI-generated code enough that it offsets most of the time savings. Only 14% say they rarely need to make changes. And yet, over half of developers still feel faster with AI tools like Copilot, Gemini, or Claude.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fastlyâs survey isnât alone in calling AI productivity gains into question. A recent randomized controlled trial (RCT) of experienced open-source developers found something even more striking: when developers used AI tools, they took 19% longer to complete their tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This disconnect may come down to psychology. AI coding often feels smooth: code autocompletes with a few keystrokes. This gives the impression of momentum, but the early speed gains are often followed by cycles of editing, testing, and reworking that eat into any gains. This pattern is echoed both in conversations we've had with Fastly developers and in many of the comments we received in our survey.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One respondent put it this way: âAn AI coding tool like GitHub Copilot greatly helps my workflow by suggesting code snippets and even entire functions. However, it once generated a complex algorithm that seemed correct but contained a subtle bug, leading to several hours of debugging.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another noted: âThe AI tool saves time by using boilerplate code, but it also needs manual fixes for inefficiencies, which keep productivity in check.â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yet, AI still seems to improve developer job satisfaction. Nearly 80% of developers say AI tools make coding more enjoyable. For some, itâs about skipping grunt work. For others, it might be the dopamine rush of code on demand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;âIt helps me complete a task that Iâm stuck with. It allows me to find the answers necessary to finish the task,â one survey respondent says.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enjoyment doesnât equal efficiency, but in a profession wrestling with burnout and backlogs, that morale boost might still count for something.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;The Hidden Cost of AI Coding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fastlyâs survey also explored developer awareness of green codingâthe practice of writing energy-efficient softwareâ and the energy cost behind AI coding tools. The practice of green coding goes up sharply with experience. Just over 56% of junior developers say they actively consider energy use in their work, while nearly 80% among mid- and senior-level engineers consider this when coding.Â&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developers are very aware of the environmental cost of AI tools: roughly two-thirds of developers across all experience levels said they know that these tools can carry a significant carbon footprint. Only a small minority (under 8% even at the most junior levels) were completely unaware. Altogether, the data suggests that sustainability is increasingly embedded in developer culture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Methodology&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This survey was conducted by Fastly from July 10 to July 14, 2025, with 791 professional developers. All respondents confirm that writing or reviewing code is a core part of their job. The survey is distributed in the US and quality-controlled for accuracy, though, as with all self-reported data, some bias is possible.Â&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45083635</guid></item><item><title>Jujutsu for everyone</title><link>https://jj-for-everyone.github.io/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="97d01e5b68f7a9ce"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a tutorial for the Jujutsu version control system. It requires no previous experience with Git or any other version control system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, most Jujutsu tutorials are targeted at experienced Git users, teaching them how to transfer their existing Git skills over to Jujutsu. This tutorial is my attempt to fill the void of beginner learning material for Jujutsu. If you are already experienced with Git, I recommend Steve Klabnik's tutorial instead of this one.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This tutorial requires you to work in the terminal. Don't worry, there's a chapter covering some terminal basics in case you're not 100% comfortable with that yet. The commands I tell you to run will often only work on Unix-like operating systems like Linux and Mac. If you're on Windows (and can't switch to Linux), consider using WSL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to read this tutorial&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The tutorial is split into levels, which are the top-level chapters in the sidebar. The idea is that once you complete a level, you should probably put this tutorial away for a while and practice what you've learned. Once you're comfortable with those skills, come back for the next level.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is one exception to this: If you're here because you need to collaborate with other people, you should complete the levels 1 and 2 right away.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's an overview of the planned levels:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Level&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Description&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;The bare minimum to get started. This is only enough for the simplest use cases where you're working alone. For example, students who track and submit their homework with a Git repository can get by with only this.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;The bare minimum for any sort of collaboration. Students who are working on a group project and professional software developers need to know this. Going further is highly recommended, but you can take a break after this.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;3&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Basic problem solving skills like conflict resolution and restoring files from history. Without this knowledge, it's only a matter of time until you run into trouble. Completing this level is comparable to the skill level of the average software developer.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;4&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;History rewriting skills. These will allow you to iterate toward a polished version history, which pays dividends long-term. Some projects require you to have these skills in order to meet their quality standards.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;5&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Productivity boosters, advanced workflows, lesser-known CLI functions and a little VCS theory. Completing this level means you have mastered Jujutsu.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;6&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Additional topics that only come up in specific situations: tags, submodules, workspaces etc. Consider skimming the list of topics and come back once you have an actual need for it.&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only a few levels are complete right now, the rest are on the way.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Reset your progress&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Throughout the tutorial, you will build an example repository. Later chapters depend on the state of previous ones. Losing the state of the example repo can therefore block you from making smooth progress. This might happen for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You use the example repo for practice and experimentation.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You switch to a different computer or reinstall the OS.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;You intentionally delete it to clean up your home directory.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The tutorial is updated significantly while you're taking a break.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To solve this problem, there is a script which automates the task of resetting your progress to the start of any chapter. To identify the chapter you want to continue with, the script expects a keyword as an argument. Each chapter includes its precise reset command at the beginning, so you can easily copy-paste it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The script is not complicated, you can verify that it's not doing anything malicious. Basically, it's just the list of commands I tell you to run manually. For convenience, it's included in the expandable text box below. You can also download the script here and then execute it locally once you have inspected it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head class="admonition-title"&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Source of reset script&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Source of reset script&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#!/usr/bin/env bash
set -euxo pipefail

if [ "${1:-x}" = "x" ] ; then
    echo "Please provide the chapter keyword as the first argument."
    exit 1
fi
chapter="$1"

function success() {
    set +x
    echo "✅✅✅ Reset script completed successfully! ✅✅✅"
    exit 0
}

# Ensure existing user configuration does not affect script behavior.
export JJ_CONFIG=/dev/null

rm -rf ~/jj-tutorial

if ! command -v jj &amp;gt; /dev/null ; then
    echo "ERROR: Jujutsu doesn't seem to be installed."
    echo "       Please install it and rerun the script."
    exit 1
fi

if [ "$chapter" = initialize ] ; then success ; fi

mkdir -p ~/jj-tutorial/repo
cd ~/jj-tutorial/repo
jj git init --colocate

jj config set --repo user.name "Alice"
jj config set --repo user.email "alice@local"
jj describe --reset-author --no-edit

if [ "$chapter" = log ] ; then success ; fi

if [ "$chapter" = make_changes ] ; then success ; fi

echo "# jj-tutorial" &amp;gt; README.md
jj log -r 'none()' # trigger snapshot

if [ "$chapter" = commit ] ; then success ; fi

jj commit --message "Add readme with project title

It's common practice for software projects to include a file called
README.md in the root directory of their source code repository. As the
file extension indicates, the content is usually written in markdown,
where the title of the document is written on the first line with a
prefixed \`#\` symbol.
"

if [ "$chapter" = remote ] ; then success ; fi

git init --bare ~/jj-tutorial/remote
jj git remote add origin ~/jj-tutorial/remote
jj bookmark create main --revision @-
jj git push --bookmark main --allow-new

if [ "$chapter" = clone ] ; then success ; fi

cd ~
rm -rf ~/jj-tutorial/repo
jj git clone --colocate ~/jj-tutorial/remote ~/jj-tutorial/repo
cd ~/jj-tutorial/repo
jj config set --repo user.name "Alice"
jj config set --repo user.email "alice@local"
jj describe --reset-author --no-edit

if [ "$chapter" = github ] ; then success ; fi

if [ "$chapter" = update_bookmark ] ; then success ; fi

printf "\nThis is a toy repository for learning Jujutsu.\n" &amp;gt;&amp;gt; README.md
jj commit -m "Add project description to readme"

jj bookmark move main --to @-

jj git push

if [ "$chapter" = branch ] ; then success ; fi

echo "print('Hello, world!')" &amp;gt; hello.py

jj commit -m "Add Python script for greeting the world

Printing the text \"Hello, world!\" is a classic exercise in introductory
programming courses. It's easy to complete in basically any language and
makes students feel accomplished and curious for more at the same time."

jj git clone --colocate ~/jj-tutorial/remote ~/jj-tutorial/repo-bob
cd ~/jj-tutorial/repo-bob
jj config set --repo user.name Bob
jj config set --repo user.email bob@local
jj describe --reset-author --no-edit

echo "# jj-tutorial

The file hello.py contains a script that greets the world.
It can be executed with the command 'python hello.py'.
Programming is fun!" &amp;gt; README.md
jj commit -m "Document hello.py in README.md

The file hello.py doesn't exist yet, because Alice is working on that.
Once our changes are combined, this documentation will be accurate."

jj bookmark move main --to @-
jj git push

cd ~/jj-tutorial/repo
jj bookmark move main --to @-
jj git fetch

if [ "$chapter" = show ] ; then success ; fi

if [ "$chapter" = merge ] ; then success ; fi

jj new main@origin @-

jj commit -m "Merge code and documentation for hello-world"
jj bookmark move main --to @-
jj git push

if [ "$chapter" = ignore ] ; then success ; fi

cd ~/jj-tutorial/repo-bob

tar czf submission_alice_bob.tar.gz README.md

echo "
## Submission

Run the following command to create the submission tarball:

~~~sh
tar czf submission_alice_bob.tar.gz [FILE...]
~~~" &amp;gt;&amp;gt; README.md

echo "*.tar.gz" &amp;gt; .gitignore

jj file untrack submission_alice_bob.tar.gz

jj commit -m "Add submission instructions"

if [ "$chapter" = rebase ] ; then success ; fi

jj bookmark move main --to @-
jj git fetch
jj rebase --destination main@origin
jj git push

if [ "$chapter" = more_bookmark ] ; then success ; fi

cd ~/jj-tutorial/repo

echo "for (i = 0; i &amp;lt; 10; i = i + 1):
    print('Hello, world!')" &amp;gt; hello.py

jj commit -m "WIP: Add for loop (need to fix syntax)"

jj git push --change @-

if [ "$chapter" = navigate ] ; then success ; fi

jj git fetch
jj new main

if [ "$chapter" = undo ] ; then success ; fi

echo "print('Hallo, Welt!')" &amp;gt;&amp;gt; hello.py
echo "print('Bonjour, le monde!')" &amp;gt;&amp;gt; hello.py

jj commit -m "code improvements"

jj undo

jj commit -m "Print German and French greetings as well"

jj undo
jj undo
jj undo

jj redo
jj redo
jj redo

if [ "$chapter" = track ] ; then success ; fi

cd ~ # move out of the directory we're about to delete
rm -rf ~/jj-tutorial/repo
jj git clone --colocate ~/jj-tutorial/remote ~/jj-tutorial/repo
cd ~/jj-tutorial/repo

# roleplay as Alice
jj config set --repo user.name "Alice"
jj config set --repo user.email "alice@local"
jj describe --reset-author --no-edit

echo "print('Hallo, Welt!')" &amp;gt;&amp;gt; hello.py
echo "print('Bonjour, le monde!')" &amp;gt;&amp;gt; hello.py
jj commit -m "Print German and French greetings as well"

jj bookmark move main -t @-
jj git push

jj bookmark track 'glob:push-*@origin'

if [ "$chapter" = conflict ] ; then success ; fi

jj new 'description("WIP: Add for loop")'

echo "for _ in range(10):
    print('Hello, world!')" &amp;gt; hello.py

jj commit -m "Fix loop syntax"

jj new main @-

echo "for _ in range(10):
    print('Hello, world!')
    print('Hallo, Welt!')
    print('Bonjour, le monde!')" &amp;gt; hello.py

jj commit -m "Merge repetition and translation of greeting"
jj bookmark move main --to @-
jj git push

if [ "$chapter" = abandon ] ; then success ; fi

jj commit -m "Experiment: Migrate to shiny new framework"
jj git push --change @-
jj new main
jj commit -m "Experiment: Improve scalability using microservices"
jj git push --change @-
jj new main
jj commit -m "Experiment: Apply SOLID design patterns"
jj git push --change @-
jj new main

jj abandon 'description("Experiment")'

jj git push --deleted

if [ "$chapter" = restore ] ; then success ; fi

rm README.md
jj show &amp;amp;&amp;gt; /dev/null

jj restore README.md

jj restore --from 'description("Fix loop syntax")' hello.py

jj commit -m "Remove translations"
jj bookmark move main --to @-
jj git push

if [ "$chapter" = complete ] ; then success ; fi

set +x
echo "Error: Didn't recognize the chapter keyword: '$chapter'."
exit 1
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Stay up to date&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both this tutorial and Jujutsu are still evolving. In order to keep your Jujutsu knowledge updated, subscribe to releases of the tutorial's GitHub repo. You will be notified of important changes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A new level becomes available.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;An existing level is changed significantly.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I especially intend to keep this tutorial updated as new version of Jujutsu come out with features and changes that are relevant to the tutorial's content. I consider this tutorial up-to-date with the latest version of Jujutsu (&lt;code&gt;0.32&lt;/code&gt;) as of August 2025.
If that's more than a couple months in the past, I probably stopped updating this tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can subscribe to these updates by visiting the GitHub repo and clicking on "Watch", "Custom" and then selecting "Releases".&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Help make this tutorial better&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you find a typo, you can suggest a fix directly by clicking on the "edit" icon in the top-right corner. If you have general suggestions for improvement, please open an issue. I am also very interested in experience reports, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Do you have any frustrations with Jujutsu which the tutorial did not help you overcome?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Was there a section that wasn't explained clearly? (If you didn't understand something, it's probably the tutorial's fault, not yours!)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Did you complete a level but didn't feel like you had the skills that were promised in the level overview?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Is there something missing that's not being taught but should?&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Do you feel like the content could be structured better?&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thank you for helping me improve this tutorial!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What is version control and why should you use it?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will assume you're using version control for software development, but it can be used for other things as well. For example, authoring professionally formatted documents with tools like Typst. The source of this tutorial is stored in version control too!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What these scenarios have in common is that a large body of work (mostly in the form of text) is slowly being expanded and improved over time. You don't want to lose any of it and you want to be able to go back to previous states of your work. Often, several people need to work on the project at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A general-purpose backup solution can keep a few copies of your files around. A graphical document editor can allow multiple people to edit the text simultaneously. But sometimes, you need a sharper knife. Jujutsu is the sharpest knife available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why Jujutsu instead of Git?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Git is by far the most commonly used VCS in the software development industry. So why not use that? Using the most popular thing has undeniable benefits. There is lots of learning material, lots of people can help you with problems, lots of other tools integrate with it etc. Why make life harder on yourself by using a lesser-known alternative?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's my elevator pitch:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Jujutsu is compatible with Git. You're not actually losing anything by using Jujutsu. You can work with it on any existing project that uses Git for version control without issues. Tools that integrate with Git mostly work just as well with Jujutsu.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Jujutsu is easier to learn than Git. (That is, assuming I did a decent job writing this tutorial.) Git is known for its complicated, unintuitive user interface. Jujutsu gives you all the functionality of Git with a lot less complexity. Experienced users of Git usually don't care about this, because they've paid the price of learning Git already. (I was one of these people once.) But you care!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Jujutsu is more powerful than Git. Despite the fact that it's easier to learn and more intuitive, it actually has loads of awesome capabilities for power users that completely leave Git in the dust. Don't worry, you don't have to use that power right away. But you can be confident that if your VCS-workflow becomes more demanding in the future, Jujutsu will have your back. This is not a watered-down "we have Git at home" for slow learners!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learning Jujutsu instead of Git as your first VCS does have some downsides:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When talking about version control with peers, they will likely use Git-centric vocabulary. Jujutsu shares a lot of Git's concepts, but there are also differences. Translating between the two in conversation can add some mental overhead. (solution: convince your peers to use Jujutsu 😉)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Jujutsu is relatively new and doesn't cover 100% of the features of Git yet. When you do run into the rare problem where Jujutsu doesn't have an answer, you can always fall back to use Git directly, which works quite seamlessly. Still, having to use two tools instead of one is slightly annoying. I plan to teach such Git features in this tutorial in later levels. The tutorial should be a one-stop-shop for all Jujutsu users.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The command line interface of Jujutsu is not yet stable. That means in future versions of Jujutsu, some commands might work a little differently or be renamed. I personally don't think this should scare you away. Many people including me have used Jujutsu as a daily driver for a long time. Whenever something did change, my reaction was usually: "Great, that was one of the less-than-perfect parts of Jujutsu! Now it's even more intuitive than before!" Consider subscribing to GitHub releases of this tutorial. You will be notified if new versions of Jujutsu change something in a way that's relevant to what you learned in this tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite some downsides, I think the benefits are well worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45083952</guid></item><item><title>10-20x Faster LLVM -O0 Back-End (2020)</title><link>https://discourse.llvm.org/t/tpde-llvm-10-20x-faster-llvm-o0-back-end/86664</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7670c85cc80273d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;5 years ago, @nikic wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;quote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I can’t say a 10% improvement is making LLVM fast again, we would need a 10x improvement for it to deserve that label.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We recently open-sourced TPDE and our fast LLVM baseline back-end (TPDE-LLVM), which is 10-20x faster than the LLVM -O0 back-end with similar runtime performance and 10-30% larger code size. We support a typical subset of LLVM-IR and only target x86-64 and AArch64. Posting this here, as this might be interesting for the LLVM community – questions/comments welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Data on SPEC CPU 2017 (x86-64, compile-time speedup and code size relative to LLVM 19 -O0 back-end):&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;table&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Benchmark&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right" role="head"&gt;Comp-Time O0 IR&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right" role="head"&gt;Code Size O0 IR&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right" role="head"&gt;Comp-Time O1 IR&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right" role="head"&gt;Code Size O1 IR&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;600.perl&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;11.39x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.27x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;15.06x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;0.97x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;602.gcc&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;12.54x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.32x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;17.55x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.01x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;605.mcf&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;9.72x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.27x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;12.47x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;0.92x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;620.omnetpp&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;21.46x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.24x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;26.49x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.03x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;623.xalanc&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;18.99x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.24x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;24.80x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;0.98x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;625.x264&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;10.52x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.26x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;15.19x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;0.97x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;631.deepsjeng&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;9.60x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.25x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;17.56x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;0.97x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;641.leela&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;21.44x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.24x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;18.36x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;0.95x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;657.xz&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;10.95x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.30x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;15.15x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;0.92x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
          &lt;row&gt;
            &lt;cell&gt;geomean&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;13.34x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;1.27x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;17.58x&lt;/cell&gt;
            &lt;cell style="text-align:right"&gt;0.97x&lt;/cell&gt;
          &lt;/row&gt;
        &lt;/table&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Results for AArch64 are similar (a bit higher speedups due to GlobalISel). Obviously, on optimized IR LLVM’s optimizing back-ends fare much better in terms of run-time (~2x better) and code size (~2x better), but we don’t intend to compete there.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;How Does It Work?&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See this paper. In essence, we do three passes: one IR cleanup/preparation pass, one analysis pass (loop+liveness), and one codegen pass, which performs lowering, regalloc, and machine code encoding in combination.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Features &amp;amp; Future Plans&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Currently, the goal is to support typical Clang O0/O1 IR, so there are a lot of unsupported features. Flang code often works, but sometimes misses some floating-point operations. Rust code works in principle, but some popular crates use illegal (=not natively supported) vector types, which are not implemented yet. (Legalizing vector types/operations is very annoying.)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Besides some more IR features, our current plans include: DWARF support (we already have some prototype) and better register allocation than “spill everything”. If someone provides sufficient motivation, other big items are non-ELF platforms, non-small-PIC code models, and other targets.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Speculatively Answered Questions&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;How to use TPDE-LLVM?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The LLVM back-end is usable as a library (e.g., for JIT compilation, also usable with ORC JIT), as &lt;code&gt;llc&lt;/code&gt;-like tool, and can be integrated in Clang (needs a patch, plugins can’t provide a custom back-end right now). Some more details here.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Why not make LLVM faster?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We did, LLVM 18-&amp;gt;20 got 18% faster on x86-64. I think that another 10-20% might be reasonable to achieve, but I’d expect going beyond that to require deeper changes. Even when doing this, a 10x speedup is unlikely to be achievable.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Which changes to LLVM-IR could allow even faster compilation?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;No &lt;code&gt;ConstantExpr&lt;/code&gt; inside functions. These are hard to handle, so before compilation, we rewrite them to instructions – by iterating over all instruction operands to find such constants (and also walk through constant aggregates).&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;No arbitrarily-sized struct/array values. The only (IMHO) valid reason for struct/array values inside functions are arguments (e.g. AArch64 HFA/HVA) and multiple return values, but there’s no point in loading a &lt;code&gt;[6000 x {i32, i64}]&lt;/code&gt;. (We currently have quadratic runtime in the number of elements per value.)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not directly related to performance, but would make things easier:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;No direct access to thread-local globals (see e.g. the proposal here). We cannot easily generate a function call at arbitrary places, so we rewrite all accesses to use the intrinsic.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;No arbitrary bit-width arithmetic. &lt;code&gt;i260&lt;/code&gt; doesn’t work well already, yet Clang occasionally generates this (bitfield structs) – we don’t support multi-word integers other than &lt;code&gt;i128&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Random “Fun” Facts&lt;/head&gt;
      &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;We currently use 4 padding bytes in &lt;code&gt;Instruction&lt;/code&gt; to store instruction numbers, as there is no field to store auxiliary data.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;PHINode::getIncomingValForBlock&lt;/code&gt; causes quadratic compile-time for blocks with many predecessors. Thus, for blocks with &amp;gt;1k predecessors (happens for auto-generated code), we sort incoming entries by block pointer and use binary search.&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;llvm::successors&lt;/code&gt; is slow, so we collect and cache successors once. (This could be changed, &lt;code&gt;SwitchInst&lt;/code&gt; should store blocks together instead of interleaved with &lt;code&gt;ConstantInt&lt;/code&gt;. Maybe even make &lt;code&gt;SwitchInst&lt;/code&gt; store &lt;code&gt;uint64_t&lt;/code&gt;s instead of arbitrary-width integer?)&lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;item&gt;We track the performance of &lt;code&gt;tpde-llc&lt;/code&gt; (similar to LLVM c-t-t), but ~90% (77-95%) of the time is spent in bitcode parsing…&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45084111</guid></item><item><title>Launch HN: VibeFlow (YC S25) – Web app generator with visual, editable workflows</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45084759</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="334ac65b00c5ecf8"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi HN! We’re Alessia and Elia, the founders of VibeFlow (&lt;/p&gt;https://vibeflow.ai&lt;p&gt;). VibeFlow lets semi-technical people (i.e. people with some technical skill but who are not professional programmers) build full-stack web apps from natural language prompts, while making the underlying business logic clear and editable as a visual workflow. Demo video: &lt;/p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-CwWd3-b1JI&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem we’re trying to solve: today, people who want to build apps without coding often have to stitch together multiple tools, e.g. using Lovable for the frontend, n8n for workflows, and Supabase for the database. That creates data silos and leaves builders with fragile apps that break in production, don’t scale, and aren’t safe. We saw YouTube tutorials teaching people how to duct-tape these together just to get a functional app running. As engineers building no-code tools, we realized that people wanted the power of AI-generated UIs but also the ability to see and control their backend workflows and data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our solution is to generate the whole app at once, and represent it as a visual workflow. Users describe what they want in English (“I need a chat widget with an AI agent”) and VibeFlow generates both the interface and the logic. That logic shows up as a workflow graph they can edit visually or by giving new instructions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We use Convex (https://www.convex.dev/) as backend. The generation of the backend code is fully deterministic, we map workflow graphs to code templates. This makes deployments predictable and avoids the hallucinated, black-box code you often get from AI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Workflow representation: the logic is a directed graph where each node can be customized. We currently support CRUD operations and agent components. Any changes to the graph compiles directly back into code, so you always own the underlying logic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Frontend: generated via AI and directly linked to workflow outputs, so it always stays in sync with the business logic. Changes to the frontend can be made through a chat interface.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Semi-technical builders can create maintainable apps (not opaque “magic”), and technical folks can still inspect the code and architecture. Compared to Bubble/Webflow, the interface is simpler; compared to Zapier, the workflows have an output code; and compared to AI coding assistants, you get an automatic backend plugged in with no black-box.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can try it here: https://app.vibeflow.ai/. The demo video is https://youtu.be/-CwWd3-b1JI We'd love to hear from the HN community, whether you're a builder who's struggled with stitching tools together, a developer who's seen the pain points in no-code platforms, or someone curious about where AI-powered app generation is heading - we're eager for your thoughts!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45084759</guid></item><item><title>When the sun will literally set on what's left of the British Empire</title><link>https://oikofuge.com/sun-sets-on-british-empire/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b5391f99f8aa9fdb"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A while ago I treated you to a dissertation entitled “Does The Sun Set On The British Empire?”, and concluded that it doesn’t. The UK’s widely scattered overseas territories, sparse though they are, mean that the sun is still always shining, somewhere in the world, over British territory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most important territories in maintaining this late-empire sunlight are the Pitcairn Islands, in the Pacific, and the British Indian Ocean Territory, in the Indian Ocean. To illustrate that, I offered the sunlight chart below, showing how Pitcairn and BIOT catch the sunlight when it’s dark in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In fact, as my map at the head of this post shows, BIOT is pivotal. There, I’ve plotted the distribution of light and darkness, across the globe, at 02:15 Greenwich Mean Time, during the June solstice of 2024.*&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And here’s the situation at the December solstice:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Just after the sun sets in Pitcairn, it’s dark over every British territory except BIOT.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m revisiting the situation because the UK government has announced plans to hand over sovereignty of the Chagos Archipelago, which houses BIOT, to Mauritius. The announcement was made in October 2024, but the original agreement has now been contested by a new government in Mauritius. And the situation is further complicated by the fact that BIOT houses a large US military base on the island of Diego Garcia, so the new Trump administration also has a say in the process. (Meanwhile, the unfortunate Chagossians, evicted from their homeland in 1968 to make way for the military base, have so far been given no voice in the negotiations.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The current proposal suggests that the military base would be maintained under a long-term lease agreement, in which case British sovereignty would be lost, and BIOT would cease to exist. At that point, the role of easternmost British territory would fall to the Sovereign Base Areas (SBAs), in Cyprus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The SBAs are worth a few paragraphs, both because they’re relatively obscure, and because their existence, as sovereign military territories, perhaps has some slight relevance to how the situation on Diego Garcia might play out, should the Trump administration raise strong objections to the current plan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The SBAs came into existence when Cyprus gained its independence from the UK in 1960. Under the Treaty of Establishment, the UK retained sovereignty over about 250 square kilometres of the island, in two separate areas—the Western Sovereign Base Area of Akrotiri, and the Eastern Sovereign Base Area of Dhekelia. These have extremely complicated boundaries, designed to avoid Cypriot settlements while including British military establishments. The Eastern SBA contains three Cypriot enclaves—the towns of Ormideia and Xylotymbou, and the area surrounding the Dhekelia power station (which is crossed by a British road). It also features a long northward extension along the road to the village of Ayios Nikolaos, which now houses a signals intelligence unit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And the whole border situation became even more complicated after the Turkish invasion of Cyprus in 1974, which has left the island traversed by a UN buffer zone. British territory, including the Ayios Nikolaos road, forms part of the buffer zone. Elsewhere, the Turkish-controlled town of Kokkina has its very own buffer zone. Here’s an overview map, followed by some detail of the SBAs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Interestingly, the British military settlements within the SBAs are referred to as cantonments, a military term which, to me at least, has something of a colonial ring to it, given its association with British rule in India.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The relevance, here, to the current situation of Diego Garcia, is because the UK government made plans to hand the SBAs back to Cyprus in 1974, but were persuaded to retain sovereignty by the USA, which valued access to signals intelligence in the Eastern Mediterranean, as well as a convenient location from which to fly, among other things, U2 spy planes. The difference, of course, is that the Cypriot government appears to have been compliant with that arrangement, whereas it seems unlikely, at time of writing, that the Mauritians would agree to such a deal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ll see how it goes. Meanwhile, I’ve plotted another sunrise/sunset graph, showing how sunlight is handed off between the two key players in the absence of BIOT:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(For my sunlight calculation, I’ve plugged in the latitude and longitude of the easternmost part of the Eastern SBA—Ayios Nikolaos.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s close—in June there’s less than an hour when it’s dark in both Pitcairn and the SBAs. But, if BIOT goes, when the sun sets on Pitcairn, it will also set on (what’s left of) the British Empire.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;* I haven’t plotted British Antarctic Territory, because territorial claims in Antarctica are in abeyance under the Antarctic Treaty.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45084913</guid></item><item><title>Use One Big Server (2022)</title><link>https://specbranch.com/posts/one-big-server/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="dfdab7597d822fd7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Use One Big Server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lot of ink is spent on the "monoliths vs. microservices" debate, but the real issue behind this debate is about whether distributed system architecture is worth the developer time and cost overheads. By thinking about the real operational considerations of our systems, we can get some insight into whether we actually need distributed systems for most things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have all gotten so familiar with virtualization and abstractions between our software and the servers that run it. These days, "serverless" computing is all the rage, and even "bare metal" is a class of virtual machine. However, every piece of software runs on a server. Since we now live in a world of virtualization, most of these servers are a lot bigger and a lot cheaper than we actually think.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Meet Your Server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a picture of a server used by Microsoft Azure with AMD CPUs. Starting from the left, the big metal fixture on the left (with the copper tubes) is a heatsink, and the metal boxes that the copper tubes are attached to are heat exchangers on each CPU. The CPUs are AMD's third generation server CPU, each of which has the following specifications:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;64 cores&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;128 threads&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;~2-2.5 GHz clock&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Cores capable of 4-6 instructions per clock cycle&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;256 MB of L3 cache&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In total, this server has 128 cores with 256 simultaneous threads. With all of the cores working together, this server is capable of 4 TFLOPs of peak double precision computing performance. This server would sit at the top of the top500 supercomputer list in early 2000. It would take until 2007 for this server to leave the top500 list. Each CPU core is substantially more powerful than a single core from 10 years ago, and boasts a much wider computation pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Above and below each CPU is the memory: 16 slots of DDR4-3200 RAM per socket. The largest capacity "cost effective" DIMMs today are 64 GB. Populated cost-efficiently, this server can hold 1 TB of memory. Populated with specialized high-capacity DIMMs (which are generally slower than the smaller DIMMs), this server supports up to 8 TB of memory total. At DDR4-3200, with a total of 16 memory channels, this server will likely see ~200 Gbps of memory throughput across all of its cores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In terms of I/O, each CPU offers 64 PCIe gen 4 lanes. With 128 PCIe lanes total, this server is capable of supporting 30 NVMe SSDs plus a network card. Typical configurations you can buy will offer slots for around 16 SSDs or disks. The final thing I wanted to point out in this picture is in the top right, the network card. This server is likely equipped with a 50-100 Gbps network connection.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The Capabilities of One Server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One server today is capable of:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Serving video files at 400 Gbps (now 800 Gbps)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;1 million IOPS on a NoSQL database&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;70k IOPS in PostgreSQL&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;500k requests per second to nginx&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Compiling the linux kernel in 20 seconds&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Rendering 4k video with x264 at 75 FPS&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among other things. There are a lot of public benchmarks these days, and if you know how your service behaves, you can probably find a similar benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The Cost of One Server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a large hosting provider, OVHCloud, you can rent an HGR-HCI-6 server with similar specifications to the above, with 128 physical cores (256 threads), 512 GB of memory, and 50 Gbps of bandwidth for $1,318/month.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Moving to the popular budget option, Hetzner, you can rent a smaller server with 32 physical cores and 128 GB of RAM for about â¬140.00/month. This is a smaller server than the one from OVHCloud (1/4 the size), but it gives you some idea of the price spread between hosting providers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In AWS, one of the largest servers you can rent is the m6a.metal server. It offers 50 Gbps of network bandwidth, 192 vCPUs (96 physical cores), and 768 GB of memory, and costs $8.2944/hour in the US East region. This comes out to $6,055/month. The cloud premium is real!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A similar server, with 128 physical cores and 512 GB of memory (as well as appropriate NICs, SSDs, and support contracts), can be purchased from the Dell website for about $40,000. However, if you are going to spend this much on a server, you should probably chat with a salesperson to make sure you are getting the best deal you can. You will also need to pay to host this server and connect it to a network, though.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In comparison, buying servers takes about 8 months to break even compared to using cloud servers, and 30 months to break even compared to renting. Of course, buying servers has a lot of drawbacks, and so does renting, so going forward, we will think a little bit about the "cloud premium" and whether you should be willing to pay it (spoiler alert: the answer is "yes, but not as much as the cloud companies want you to pay").&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Thinking about the Cloud&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The "cloud era" began in earnest around 2010. At the time, the state of the art CPU was an 8-core Intel Nehalem CPU. Hyperthreading had just begun, so that 8-core CPU offered a whopping 16 threads. Hardware acceleration was about to arrive for AES encryption, and vectors were 128 bits wide. The largest CPUs had 24 MB of cache, and your server could fit a whopping 256 GB of DDR3-1066 memory. If you wanted to store data, Seagate had just begun to offer a 3 TB hard drive. Each core offered 4 FLOPs per cycle, meaning that your 8-core server running at 2.5 GHz offered a blazing fast 80 GFLOPs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The boom in distributed computing rode on this wave: if you wanted to do anything that involved retrieval of data, you needed a lot of disks to get the storage throughput you want. If you wanted to do large computations, you generally needed a lot of CPUs. This meant that you needed to coordinate between a lot of CPUs to get most things done.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since that time began, the size of servers has increased a lot, and SSDs have increased available IOPS by a factor of at least 100, but the size of mainstream VMs and containers hasn't increased much, and we still use virtualized drives that perform more like hard drives than SSDs (although this gap is closing).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;One Server (Plus a Backup) is Usually Plenty&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are doing anything short of video streaming, and you have under 10k QPS, one server will generally be fine for most web services. For really simple services, one server could even make it to a million QPS or so. Very few web services get this much traffic - if you have one, you know about it. Even if you're serving video, running only one server for your control plane is very reasonable. A benchmark can help you determine where you are. Alternatively, you can use common benchmarks of similar applications, or tables of common performance numbers to estimate how big of a machine you might need.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Tall is Better than Wide&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you need a cluster of computers, if one server is not enough, using fewer larger servers will often be better than using a large fleet of small machines. There is non-zero overhead to coordinate a cluster, and that overhead is frequently O(n) on each server. To reduce this overhead, you should generally prefer to use a few large servers than to use many small servers. In the case of things like serverless computing, where you allocate tiny short-lived containers, this overhead accounts for a large fraction of the cost of use. On the other extreme end, coordinating a cluster of one computer is trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Big Servers and Availability&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The big drawback of using a single big server is availability. Your server is going to need downtime, and it is going to break. Running a primary and a backup server is usually enough, keeping them in different datacenters. A 2x2 configuration should appease the truly paranoid: two servers in a primary datacenter (or cloud provider) and two servers in a backup datacenter will give you a lot of redundancy. If you want a third backup deployment, you can often make that smaller than your primary and secondary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, you may still have to be concerned about correlated hardware failures. Hard drives (and now SSDs) have been known to occasionally have correlated failures: if you see one disk fail, you are a lot more likely to see a second failure before getting back up if your disks are from the same manufacturing batch. Services like Backblaze overcome this by using many different models of disks from multiple manufacturers. Hacker news learned this the hard way recently when the primary and backup server went down at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are using a hosting provider which rents pre-built servers, it is prudent to rent two different types of servers in each of your primary and backup datacenters. This should avoid almost every failure mode present in modern systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Use the Cloud, but don't be too Cloudy&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A combination of availability and ease of use is one of the big reasons why I (and most other engineers) like cloud computers. Yes, you pay a significant premium to rent the machines, but your cloud provider has so much experience building servers that you don't even see most failures, and for the other failures, you can get back up and running really quickly by renting a new machine in their nearly-limitless pool of compute. It is their job to make sure that you don't experience downtime, and while they don't always do it perfectly, they are pretty good at it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hosting providers who are willing to rent you a server are a cheaper alternative to cloud providers, but these providers can sometimes have poor quality and some of them don't understand things like network provisioning and correlated hardware failures. Also, moving from one rented server to a larger one is a lot more annoying than resizing a cloud VM. Cloud servers have a price premium for a good reason.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, when you deal with clouds, your salespeople will generally push you towards "cloud-native" architecture. These are things like microservices in auto-scaling VM groups with legions of load balancers between them, and vendor-lock-in-enhancing products like serverless computing and managed high-availability databases. There is a good reason that cloud salespeople are the ones pushing "cloud architecture" - it's better for them!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The conventional wisdom is that using cloud architecture is good because it lets you scale up effortlessly. There are good reasons to use cloud-native architecture, but serving lots of people is not one of them: most services can serve millions of people at a time with one server, and will never give you a surprise five-figure bill.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Why Should I Pay for Peak Load?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One common criticism of the "one big server" approach is that you now have to pay for your peak usage instead of paying as you go for what you use. Thus, serverless computing or fleets of microservice VMs more closely align your costs with your profit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, since all of your services run on servers (whether you like it or not), someone in that supply chain is charging you based on their peak load. Part of the "cloud premium" for load balancers, serverless computing, and small VMs is based on how much extra capacity your cloud provider needs to build in order to handle their peak load. You're paying for someone's peak load anyway!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This means that if your workload is exceptionally bursty - like a simulation that needs to run once and then turn off forever - you should prefer to reach for "cloudy" solutions, but if your workload is not so bursty, you will often have a cheaper system (and an easier time building it) if you go for few large servers. If your cloud provider's usage is more bursty than yours, you are going to pay that premium for no benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This premium applies to VMs, too, not just cloud services. However, if you are running a cloud VM 24/7, you can avoid paying the "peak load premium" by using 1-year contracts or negotiating with a salesperson if you are big enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Generally, the burstier your workload is, the more cloudy your architecture should be.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;How Much Does it Cost to be Cloudy?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being cloudy is expensive. Generally, I would anticipate a 5-30x price premium depending on what you buy from a cloud company, and depending on the baseline. Not 5-30%, a factor of between 5 and 30.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here is the pricing of AWS lambda: $0.20 per 1M requests + $0.0000166667 per GB-second of RAM. I am using pricing for an x86 CPU here to keep parity with the m6a.metal instance we saw above. Large ARM servers and serverless ARM compute are both cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Assuming your server costs $8.2944/hour, and is capable of 1k QPS with 768 GB of RAM:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;1k QPS is 60k queries per minute, or 3.6M queries per hour&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Each query here gets 0.768 GB-seconds of RAM (amortized)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replacing this server would cost about $46/hour using serverless computing&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The price premium for serverless computing over the instance is a factor of 5.5. If you can keep that server over 20% utilization, using the server will be cheaper than using serverless computing. This is before any form of savings plan you can apply to that server - if you can rent those big servers from the spot market or if you compare to the price you can get with a 1-year contract, the price premium is even higher.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you compare to the OVHCloud rental price for the same server, the price premium of buying your compute through AWS lambda is a factor of 25&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are considering renting a server from a low-cost hosting provider or using AWS lambda, you should prefer the hosting provider if you can keep the server operating at 5% capacity!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also, note that the actual QPS number doesn't matter: if the $8.2944/hour server is capable of 100k QPS, the query would use 100x less memory-time, meaning that you would arrive at the same 5.5x (or 25x) premium. Of course, you should scale the size of the server to fit your application.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Common Objections to One Big Server&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you propose using the one big server approach, you will often get pushback from people who are more comfortable with the cloud, prefer to be fashionable, or have legitimate concerns. Use your judgment when you think about it, but most people vastly underestimate how much "cloud architecture" actually costs compared to the underlying compute. Here are some common objections.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;But if I use Cloud Architecture, I Don't Have to Hire Sysadmins&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes you do. They are just now called "Cloud Ops" and are under a different manager. Also, their ability to read the arcane documentation that comes from cloud companies and keep up with the corresponding torrents of updates and deprecations makes them 5x more expensive than system administrators.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;But if I use Cloud Architecture, I Don't Have to Do Security Updates&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yes you do. You may have to do fewer of them, but the ones you don't have to do are the easy ones to automate. You are still going to share in the pain of auditing libraries you use, and making sure that all of your configurations are secure.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;But if I use Cloud Architecture, I Don't Have to Worry About it Going Down&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The "high availability" architectures you get from using cloudy constructs and microservices just about make up for the fragility they add due to complexity. At this point, if you use two different cloud regions or two cloud providers, you can generally assume that is good enough to avoid your service going down. However, cloud providers have often had global outages in the past, and there is no reason to assume that cloud datacenters will be down any less often than your individual servers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remember that we are trying to prevent correlated failures. Cloud datacenters have a lot of parts that can fail in correlated ways. Hosting providers have many fewer of these parts. Similarly, complex cloud services, like managed databases, have more failure modes than simple ones (VMs).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;But I can Develop More Quickly if I use Cloud Architecture&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then do it, and just keep an eye on the bill and think about when it's worth it to switch. This is probably the strongest argument in favor of using cloudy constructs. However, if you don't think about it as you grow, you will likely end up burning a lot of money on your cloudy architecture long past the time to switch to something more boring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;My Workload is Really Bursty&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cloud away. That is a great reason to use things like serverless computing. One of the big benefits of cloud architecture constructs is that the scale down really well. If your workload goes through long periods of idleness punctuated with large unpredictable bursts of activity, cloud architecture probably works really well for you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;What about CDNs?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It's impossible to get the benefits of a CDN, both in latency improvements and bandwidth savings, with one big server. This is also true of other systems that need to be distributed, like backups. Thankfully CDNs and backups are competitive markets, and relatively cheap. These are the kind of thing to buy rather than build.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;A Note On Microservices and Monoliths&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thinking about "one big server" naturally lines up with thinking about monolithic architectures. However, you don't need to use a monolith to use one server. You can run many containers on one big server, with one microservice per container. However, microservice architectures in general add a lot of overhead to a system for dubious gain when you are running on one big server.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you experience growing pains, and get close to the limits of your current servers, today's conventional wisdom is to go for sharding and horizontal scaling, or to use a cloud architecture that gives you horizontal scaling "for free." It is often easier and more efficient to scale vertically instead. Using one big server is comparatively cheap, keeps your overheads at a minimum, and actually has a pretty good availability story if you are careful to prevent correlated hardware failures. It's not glamorous and it won't help your resume, but one big server will serve you well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45085029</guid></item><item><title>Eternal Struggle</title><link>https://yoavg.github.io/eternal/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="57c9d1e55408cc08"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;change background&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45086020</guid></item><item><title>What to do with C++ modules?</title><link>https://nibblestew.blogspot.com/2025/08/we-need-to-seriously-think-about-what.html</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45086210</guid></item><item><title>Lunar soil machine developed to build bricks using sunlight</title><link>https://www.moondaily.com/reports/Lunar_soil_machine_developed_to_build_bricks_using_sunlight_999.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="769b71fb3ab40f48"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Developed by the Deep Space Exploration Laboratory (DSEL) in Hefei, Anhui province, the system functions as a 3D printing device powered by concentrated solar heat. It employs a parabolic reflector to gather solar radiation, which is then funneled through fiber optic bundles. At the focus point, light intensity exceeds 3,000 times the standard level, reaching temperatures over 1,300 C to melt lunar regolith.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;According to senior engineer Yang Honglun, the machine uses no additives - relying entirely on lunar soil. The bricks produced are dense and robust, suitable not only for shelter construction but also for roads and platforms on the lunar surface.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The project spanned two years of research and development. Key challenges included transporting and melting variable lunar soil compositions and achieving efficient solar energy transmission. To address this, the team created multiple types of simulated lunar soil for extensive trials.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While the technology is a milestone, Yang emphasized that lunar soil bricks alone cannot sustain pressure in the moon's vacuum and low-gravity environment. Instead, the bricks will act as protective layers over pressure-retaining habitat modules made of rigid and inflatable structures.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He outlined a broader vision for lunar construction involving brick manufacturing, modular component integration, and structural validation under true lunar surface conditions. These efforts aim to enable full-scale surface construction supported by automated robots and the brick-making device.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This development aligns with China's plans for the International Lunar Research Station (ILRS), a joint venture with 17 countries and over 50 research bodies. Scheduled in two phases, ILRS will establish a base in the lunar south pole region by 2035, with expansions in the 2040s.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In preparation, Chinese astronauts aboard the nation's space station will expose simulated lunar bricks - delivered by the Tianzhou 8 cargo spacecraft in November 2024 - to space conditions. These experiments will assess thermal durability, mechanical integrity, and radiation shielding to inform future lunar base construction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Related Links&lt;lb/&gt; Deep Space Exploration Laboratory&lt;lb/&gt; Mars News and Information at MarsDaily.com&lt;lb/&gt;Lunar Dreams and more&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Subscribe Free To Our Daily Newsletters&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Subscribe Free To Our Daily Newsletters&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45086238</guid></item><item><title>Installing UEFI Firmware on ARM SBCs</title><link>https://interfacinglinux.com/2025/08/25/edk2-uefi-for-the-rock-5-itx/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="37ccd15999b9bcce"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I am a huge fan of my Rock 5 ITX+. It wraps an ATX power connector, a 4-pin Molex, PoE support, 32 GB of eMMC, front-panel USB 2.0, and two Gen 3×2 M.2 slots around a Rockchip 3588 SoC that can slot into any Mini-ITX case. Thing is, I never put it in a case because the microSD slot lives on the side of the board, and pulling the case out and removing the side panel to install a new OS got old with a quickness.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I originally wanted to rackmount the critter, but adding a deracking difficulty multiplier to the microSD slot minigame seemed a bit souls-like for my taste. So what am I going to do? Grab a microSD extender and hang that out the back? Nay! I’m going to neuralyze the SPI flash and install some Kelvin Timeline firmware that will allow me to boot and install generic ARM Linux images from USB.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At least, that’s the plan 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;EDK2 RK3588&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EDK2-RK3588 is a UEFI firmware implementation based on EDK2 for various RK3588 boards. It delivers a PC-like, standardised boot experience, supporting multiple operating systems, such as Windows, Linux, BSD, and VMware ESXi. At least, that’s what it says on the tin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, I could write the EDK2 firmware to a microSD and try before you buy. Welp, that’s not going to work on the Rock 5 ITX+ because it’s a wee bit, what’s a polite way to put this, special. Not only does the microSD trick not work, it also refuses to let me boot the EDK2 firmware from eMMC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time to break out the neuralyzer!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;ARMBIAN&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To pull off this roundabout feat of engineering, I first need to boot the Rock 5 ITX+ to a desktop, and there is exactly one correct answer to that problem: Armbian 25.2.2 Noble Gnome with kernel 6.1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once booted to the desktop, it’s time to crack open a copy of Chromium, head over to the EDK2-RK3588 GitHub page, and download the latest rock-5-itx UEFI release.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Remember the “specialness” I talked about earlier? Yeah, the Rock 5 ITX+ exposes the SPI flash as a standard 17 MB block device, meaning I can flash the UEFI image with GNOME Disks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Granted, I’m still flashing the SPI, so I had to remind myself not to freak out when it seized up at the start, then proceeded to write the image at the speed of smell. The whole process ended up taking about a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All that’s left to do at this point is power down the system, pop out the microSD, and reapply the electrons. Saying a prayer to an elder deity is optional but highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;UEFI BOOT&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After a mild panic attack, I realised the EDK2 boot screen only shows up on when connected to the first HDMI output. I was finally greeted by a Radxa splash screen, and tapping Escape got me into the setup menu.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a gang of settings to play around with, but for the time being I’m only focused on one, ACPI / Device Tree.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s located in Device Manager &amp;gt; Rockchip Platform Configuration &amp;gt; ACPI / Device Tree. Here I could tell the Rock 5 ITX+ to boot using ACPI, Device Tree, or both.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I decided to keep the Config Table Mode set to both, with Device Tree Configuration set to Mainline, and DTB override and firmware fixups enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;GENERIC ARM LINUX&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The whole point of this experiment was to be able to download generic ARM images for any distribution and install them as I would on my x86-64 desktop PC. The thing is, there’s a miniboss hiding in plain sight on the EDK2-RK3588 GitHub page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Basically, if I want a hardware-accelerated desktop (or anything else), I’m going to need a distribution shipping with kernel 6.15+, and while that might seem comical to anyone reading from the future, Debian 13 was released this week and it’s rocking 6.12.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The kernel 6.15+ requirement rules out the current releases of Armbian, openSUSE, Ubuntu, and Fedora. Thankfully, both Ubuntu (Daily) and Fedora (Rawhide) have bleeding-edge builds, so I’m crossing my pinky toes, hoping that one of them works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;FEDORA RAWHIDE&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you haven’t heard of Rawhide, it’s bleeding-edge Fedora, aimed at advanced users, testers, and anyone trying to shove Fedora onto an ARM SBC running EDK2 firmware in the glorious year of his noodly appendage, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Out of the gate, Fedora was being fussy, requiring me to switch the Config Table to Device Tree just to get a display. Even then, it took a reboot (or two) before finally gracing me with display output.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once I defeated GRUB, it was smooth sailing. Pick a language, select the installation drive, agree to murderate some databits, and exit to the desktop. All that’s left to do is power off the system, remove the flash drive, and reapply the electrons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the reboot, I was greeted by a non-functioning GNOME desktop. Well, it wasn’t completely broken, as I could wiggle the mouse pointer, and that is how things remained until Mr 🙁 showed up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the superpowers you develop while working with ARM SBCs is the ability to get up and walk away in case it’s having an extended think, knowing the solution is simply to wait it out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After however long it took me to make a cup of tea, I came back to a task failed successfully and was finally able to complete the setup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A quick poke around the GNOME Control Center revealed that networking, power, and display options were intact and operational.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then I clicked on sound. I’m going to assume this is solvable by enabling some third-party repository, but that’s for someone else to figure out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;UBUNTU 25.10&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve talked an egregious amount of smack about Ubuntu over the decades, 73.6% of it deserved, but credit where it’s due: they’ve put serious time and energy into making their desktop work on both ARM and RISC-V.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So I wasn’t terribly surprised that GRUB appeared after I reset the EDK2 firmware to its defaults, followed by the installer’s splash screen.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have installed Ubuntu before, there is nothing of note here. Like Fedora, it offered the option to install the system on NVMe or eMMC, along with settings to enable third-party repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another rummage in the GNOME Control Center revealed that networking, power, and display options were intact and operational. Unlike Fedora, Ubuntu dispelled the myth that sound does not work on Linux. At least on ARM, out of the box… on a bleeding edge distro.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also want to point out that Vulkan worked on both Ubuntu 25.10 and Fedora Rawhide. The open-source drivers still have some catching up to do, but they are most certainly getting there and are more than enough to provide a smooth desktop experience.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;NETBSD?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I also grabbed a copy of NetBSD daily, and it booted right up. I didn’t bother trying to install it, but it picked up the ethernoodles, so you could probably get up to, something?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;VERDICT&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This all started because I wanted to put the Rock 5 ITX+ into a rackmount case and have a way to swap out the OS without pulling it from the rack and fiddling with the SD card. And yes, while writing this, all I can think about is how long it will take for someone to point out the existence of SD card extenders in the YouTube comments.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I won’t fault them for doing so. A simple SD extender plus a little arts and crafts with a Dremel would have been my solution if I needed a working fix yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But I really wanted to see where EDK2 RK3588 stands, since Collabora is hard at work upstreaming support for the RK3588 to the Linux kernel, and that’s going to be the SoC where everything JustWorks™ in a year or so.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right now, EDK2 + RK3588 isn’t there yet, but it’s not that far off either. It’s the worst of all states, kinda works if you squint a little. The big hangup is kernel 6.15, but that only matters if you need HDMI output with hardware acceleration. Building a headless fileserver? You’re already good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It looks like the Rock 5 ITX+ has escaped the rack, for now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;PRODUCT LINKS&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All the links in this article go directly to the sources they reference. There are no affiliate links and no backlinks to unrelated articles because I absolutely loathe how common that has become. If you want to support Interfacing Linux, you can use the affiliate links listed below or join the Patreon.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Radxa ROCK 5 ITX+: https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_olkG93p&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;IN WIN PC Case: https://amzn.to/3JrTKk5&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some posts contain affiliate links. If you click on an affiliate link and later make a purchase, I may receive a small commission.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have questions about your Linux setup? Ask in the forums.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45086346</guid></item><item><title>Best practices for dealing with human waste in the great outdoors</title><link>https://theconversation.com/how-to-poop-outdoors-in-a-way-that-wont-harm-the-environment-and-other-hikers-262426</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="76d016db2ae1c71c"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re one of the 63 million Americans who went hiking last year, chances are you’ve found yourself needing to go, with no toilet in sight.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Aside from personal inconvenience, why is this such a big deal?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Human fecal contamination is a public health concern in natural areas. Pathogens in human poop can remain active for a long time – over a year in outdoor environments – meaning that waste left behind today can cause severe gastrointestinal disease and other sicknesses for future visitors. Fecal waste can enter waterways after storms or snowmelt, harming water quality. Finally, it can be upsetting – or at the least, unpleasant – to encounter someone else’s poop and used toilet paper in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As a researcher and a Ph.D. candidate who study human impacts on parks and protected areas, we have been thinking quite a lot about poop and ways people can tread more lightly on the landscape. Our focus is on Leave No Trace, an environmental education framework – created by an organization with the same name – that helps people implement minimal-impact practices in the outdoors.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Poop is causing problems in parks and protected areas&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the Appalachian Trail and Mount Everest – known as Sagarmatha in Nepali – to national parks in Norway and Aotearoa – known as New Zealand to English speakers, researchers have documented the negative impacts our bodily wastes are causing in the sensitive environments where we seek recreation and restoration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Colorado, the problem has gotten so bad that land managers have decided to take action. In the Eagle-Holy Cross District of the White River National Forest, for example, the U.S. Forest Service now requires visitors to take their human waste out with them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Best practices for dealing with your poo in the great outdoors&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of us – Derrick Taff – works as a science adviser to Leave No Trace, an organization that has educated outdoor recreationists on this issue for more than 30 years and has provided concrete guidance based on scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first rule of thumb is to avoid the possibility of contamination entirely by not leaving waste in natural areas to begin with. Toilet facilities are regarded as the most effective method to reduce human waste in the backcountry. If there’s a toilet at the trailhead, use it before you head out.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Current research we’re doing in Grand Teton National Park in Wyoming and San Isabel National Forest in Colorado confirms that hikers prefer to use trailhead toilets when they’re available.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But as anyone who’s been out in the woods is aware, remote wilderness areas do not necessarily offer such infrastructure. Access for maintenance and waste removal costs are major barriers for land management agencies considering installing backcountry toilets.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then there’s the very real likelihood that even when trailhead facilities do exist, you may be far away when nature calls. In our own research, pending publication, we surveyed hikers on Colorado’s Mount Elbert. Up to 70% of those needing to poop ended up doing so in the backcountry despite the presence of a trailhead toilet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Issues develop because hikers aren’t prepared&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This issue may persist because people aren’t aware of the current rules. In our soon-to-be-published study of Grand Teton hikers, 66% of backcountry trail visitors reported that they had not received any information on how to dispose of human waste in the park.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other reasons why people may not follow the rules are because they may consider them onerous or unimportant.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Research shows that clear, actionable messaging including relevant environmental and moral appeals does make a difference in shifting people’s behaviors in the outdoors. Although individual choices may seem inconsequential, they add up to big impacts in the aggregate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to poop in the backcountry&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So what to do when there really is no potty? Leave No Trace advises us of two main options.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first is to dig a little pit, commonly called a cat hole, and deposit your poop in there. Can’t aim? No worries – Just poop next to the hole and scoop it in afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The use of cat holes is recommended in areas where it’s possible to dig roughly the length of your hand deep in the soil, where moist ground indicates that material buried there will decompose, and where digging is not likely to disturb fragile environments. Make sure you’re about 70 steps away from any water source, trail or campsite to avoid water contamination and reduce the likelihood that someone else will accidentally come upon your waste.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can typically leave toilet paper in a cat hole, but check local regulations and carry it out in a sealed bag if not. Never leave wet wipes behind. They don’t biodegrade.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outdoor companies are now making lightweight trowels designed for digging cat holes in the backcountry. But there are also places where it’s difficult if not impossible to dig a cat hole because of snow, frozen ground, shallow soil or exposed bedrock, or where leaving human waste in the outdoors is not recommended due to environmental conditions. These typically include high-mountain zones above tree line, alpine environments inhabited by delicate and slow-growing flora, and deserts and other arid places characterized by low soil moisture.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In places like this, it’s best to remove all poop and toilet paper and dispose of it in a proper location such as a trash can at the trailhead or even back at your home. Before you recoil in horror, remember that dog owners do this with their pets’ waste when on a walk.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wag bags – short for waste aggregation and gelling – are used to pack out poop. Wag bag kits typically include an inner and an outer bag as well as a drying agent to prevent odor and leakage. Our current research, as well as a recent study of Norwegian park users, has demonstrated that people are willing to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our study found that among people who defecated while on a hike to the summit of Mount Elbert, 30% used a wag bag to carry their waste off the mountain, and 87% expressed willingness to use one on future trips.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These results suggest that people are willing to do the right thing when given the proper tools and information, and that it’s possible to effectively teach people how to care for our wild spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45086440</guid></item><item><title>We should have the ability to run any code we want on hardware we own</title><link>https://hugotunius.se/2025/08/31/what-every-argument-about-sideloading-gets-wrong.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f58638d75127bfe5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sideloading has been a hot topic for the last decade. Most recently, Google has announced further restrictions on the practice in Android. Many hundreds of comment threads have discussed these changes over the years. One point in particular is always made: âI should be able to run whatever code I want on hardware I ownâ. I agree entirely with this point, but within the context of this discussion itâs moot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;âI should be able to run whatever code I want on hardware I ownâ&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When Google restricts your ability to install certain applications they arenât constraining what you can do with the hardware you own, they are constraining what you can do using the software they provide with said hardware. Itâs through this control of the operating system that Google is exerting control, not at the hardware layer. You often donât have full access to the hardware either and building new operating systems to run on mobile hardware is impossible, or at least much harder than it should be. This is a separate, and I think more fruitful, point to make. Apple is a better case study than Google here. Appleâs success with iOS partially derives from the tight integration of hardware and software. An iPhone without iOS is a very different product to what we understand an iPhone to be. Forcing Apple to change core tenets of iOS by legislative means would undermine what made the iPhone successful.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You shouldnât take away from this that I am some stalwart defender of the two behemoths Apple and Google, far from it. However, our critique shouldnât be of the restrictions in place in the operating systems they provide â rather, it should focus on the ability to truly run any code we want on hardware we own. In this context this would mean having the ability and documentation to build or install alternative operating systems on this hardware. It should be possible to run Android on an iPhone and manufacturers should be required by law to provide enough technical support and documentation to make the development of new operating systems possible. If you want to play Playstation games on your PS5 you must suffer Sonyâs restrictions, but if you want to convert your PS5 into an emulator running Linux that should be possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45087396</guid></item><item><title>A Linux version of the Procmon Sysinternals tool</title><link>https://github.com/microsoft/ProcMon-for-Linux</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="a010c81b3ca44182"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Process Monitor (Procmon) is a Linux reimagining of the classic Procmon tool from the Sysinternals suite of tools for Windows. Procmon provides a convenient and efficient way for Linux developers to trace the syscall activity on the system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OS: Ubuntu 18.04 lts&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;cmake&lt;/code&gt;&amp;gt;= 3.14 (build-time only)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;libsqlite3-dev&lt;/code&gt;&amp;gt;= 3.22 (build-time only)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please see installation instructions here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please see build instructions here.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Usage: procmon [OPTIONS]
   OPTIONS
      -h/--help                Prints this help screen
      -p/--pids                Comma separated list of process IDs to monitor
      -e/--events              Comma separated list of system calls to monitor
      -c/--collect [FILEPATH]  Option to start Procmon in a headless mode
      -f/--file FILEPATH       Open a Procmon trace file
      -l/--log FILEPATH        Log debug traces to file&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following traces all processes and syscalls on the system:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo procmon&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following traces processes with process id 10 and 20:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo procmon -p 10,20&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following traces process 20 only syscalls read, write and open at:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo procmon -p 20 -e read,write,openat&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following traces process 35 and opens Procmon in headless mode to output all captured events to file &lt;code&gt;procmon.db&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo procmon -p 35 -c procmon.db&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The following opens a Procmon &lt;code&gt;tracefile&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;procmon.db&lt;/code&gt;, within the Procmon TUI:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;sudo procmon -f procmon.db&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Ask a question on Stack Overflow (tag with ProcmonForLinux)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Request a new feature on GitHub&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Vote for popular feature requests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;File a bug in GitHub Issues&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are interested in fixing issues and contributing directly to the code base, please see the document How to Contribute, which covers the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;How to build and run from the source&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The development workflow, including debugging and running tests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Coding Guidelines&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Submitting pull requests&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please see also our Code of Conduct.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Copyright (c) Microsoft Corporation. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Licensed under the MIT License.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45087748</guid></item><item><title>Lewis and Clark marked their trail with laxatives</title><link>https://offbeatoregon.com/2501d1006d_biliousPills-686.077.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="b4199d0d24278264"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h4"&gt;ASTORIA, CLATSOP COUNTY; 1800s:&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Lewis and Clark marked their trail with laxatives&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;Audio version is not yet available&lt;/head&gt;
          &lt;head&gt;By Finn J.D. John&lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;“Some people have stated that the Lewis and Clark Expedition would have been better off if they had taken a trained physician along to care for the numerous problems that they encountered. I totally disagree,” says physician and historian David Peck. “I think a trained physician would have been overly confident and possibly would have been much more aggressive in their treatment of illnesses, often times to the detriment of the patient.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;In lieu of a trained physician, the Corps of Discovery’s leaders got some basic medical training, along with a bag full of the tools of allopathic intervention: lancets for bleeding patients, blister powder for inducing “heat,” opium products for relieving pain and inducing sleep â and purgatives.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Those purgatives are the heroes of our story today. They came in the form of beefy pills, about four times the size of a standard aspirin tablet, which Rush called “Dr. Rush’s Bilious Pills.” They contained about 10 grains of calomel and 10 to 15 grains of jalap.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Jalap, the powdered root of a Mexican variety of morning glory, is a natural laxative of considerable power.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And calomel ... ah, calomel. Calomel was the wonder drug of the age. Its chemical name is mercury chloride. In large doses (and they don’t get much larger than 10 grains, or 20 if a fellow takes two of them, as Dr. Rush recommended!) it functions as a savage purgative, causing lengthy and productive sessions in the outhouse and leaving a patient thoroughly depleted and hopefully in full restoration of his bile balance.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Calomel also was the only thing known to be effective against syphilis, which was always an issue with military outfits. Whether picked up from a friendly lady in a waterfront St. Louis “sporting house” before the journey, or from an equally friendly Native lady met along the way, syphilis went with soldiers like ice cold milk with an Oreo cookie.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;When symptoms broke out, the patient would be dosed with “thunder clappers” and slathered with topical mercury ointments until he started salivating ferociously, which was a symptom of mild mercury poisoning but at the time was considered a sure sign that the body was purging the sickness out of itself.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And yes, a few of the men did end up needing treatment for syphilis. But everyone in the party needed a good laxative âon the regularâ (sorry about that). Week after week, hunting parties went out and brought back animals to eat. The explorers lived on almost nothing but meat.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;And this low-fiber diet had predictable results.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;It had another result, too, which was less predictable â although highly convenient for later historians. The fact is, mercury chloride is only slightly soluble in human digestion. Plus, the reason it works is, it irritates the tissues of the digestive tract severely, causing the body to expel it just as fast as it possibly can before more damage can be done. So, most of the calomel in any given “bilious pill” gets blown out post-haste in the ensuing “purge.”&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Then, once out of the body and in the earth, it lasts literally for centuries without breaking down or dissolving away.&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;So as Lewis and Clark and their crew made their way across the continent, and across Oregon, they were unknowingly depositing a trail of heavy-metal laxatives along the way â a trail that historians and scientists have been able to detect and use to document almost their every, uh, movement.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45087815</guid></item><item><title>Show HN: Spotilyrics – See synchronized Spotify lyrics inside VS Code</title><link>https://github.com/therepanic/spotilyrics</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="2926fc790a54ede9"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📌 Live lyrics sync with your Spotify playback.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🎨 Lyrics colors auto-themed from album cover (via &lt;code&gt;colorthief&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🖥️ Smooth side panel view – code on the left, lyrics on the right.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🔑 Simple one-time login using your own Spotify Client ID.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🚪 Quick logout command to reset session.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open VS Code → Extensions → search&lt;/p&gt;&lt;code&gt;spotilyrics&lt;/code&gt;or install from VS Code Marketplace.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Run the command:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;Show Spotify Lyrics via Spotilyrics
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Go to Spotify Developer Dashboard.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create an app → copy Client ID.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Important: set the Redirect URI for your app to: &lt;code&gt;http://127.0.0.1:8000/callback&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Run the &lt;code&gt;Show Spotify Lyrics via Spotilyrics&lt;/code&gt;command.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Paste your Client ID in the panel and log in.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Enjoy synced lyrics while coding! 🎶&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;ℹ️ Why? – To respect Spotify API rate limits, you need your own ID.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Show Spotify Lyrics via Spotilyrics&lt;/code&gt;(&lt;code&gt;spotilyrics.lyrics&lt;/code&gt;) – open synced lyrics panel.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;Logout from Spotilyrics&lt;/code&gt;(&lt;code&gt;spotilyrics.logout&lt;/code&gt;) – clear session and re-auth when needed.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Spotify Web API&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;LRClib for lyrics with timing&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;colorthief for cover-based theme&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;TypeScript + VS Code WebView&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is licensed as Unlicensed.&lt;lb/&gt; Feel free to use, hack, and remix it – but no warranties 😉&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Made with ❤️ by therepanic. Code hard, vibe harder 🎧 &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45087905</guid></item><item><title>Nintendo Switch 2 Dock USB-C Compatibility</title><link>https://www.lttlabs.com/blog/2025/08/30/nintendo-switch-2-dock</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45087971</guid></item><item><title>What Is Complexity in Chess?</title><link>https://lichess.org/@/Toadofsky/blog/what-is-complexity/pKo1swFh</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f5839fd03a7eda7"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pacto Visual&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h1"&gt;What is Complexity?&lt;/head&gt;If we all knew, we would all be masters.&lt;p&gt;May 2020 an interesting proposal was suggested.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I provided some constructive criticism on research paper A Metric of Chess Complexity by FM David Peng, as well as constructive criticism on the codebase used to validate this experiment. For many months I have refrained from further comment, and although code has not progressed, two things have:&lt;lb/&gt;1. Public interest in "complexity" as determined by ACPL (yuck).&lt;lb/&gt;2. Lichess has a blogging platform where I can properly address deficiencies in the research method and control the conversation which I start.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;... so the time has come for me to share my remaining criticisms of this ambitious project. Previously I had shared some easier-to-address criticisms while privately I shared Peng's suggestion with the Lichess team.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;The Golden Goose&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Such a feature has the potential to revolutionize chess and would be invaluable to any chess website. Some specific applications include generating non-tactical puzzles (imagine tactics trainer for positional chess puzzles), creating chess computers that play with human personalities, and identifying concepts that are key to improvement at any rating level."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Science is a window for us to learn more about the world around us. Marketing is about selling ideas to an audience. This statement, if true, would have already garnered interest by both scientists and business people, who by exerting a modicum of effort could easily develop and sell products based upon them. Further, if true, this could also inspire a black market of cheating software to help players identify the risk associated with cheating in particular positions. Peng's paper makes many similar promises to the above, so this raises the level of scrutiny I take to the rest of the paper.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Propositions&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper specifies complexity in two different propositions:&lt;lb/&gt;a) Complexity is a 1-dimensional, transferable (teachable to a neural network) metric based upon centipawn loss as determined by some version(s) of Stockfish with or without a neural network.&lt;lb/&gt;b) By definition, complexity can be used in real time to determine how difficult a position is.&lt;lb/&gt;While some people's intuitions may support the notion that these propositions support or complement each other, I am unconvinced; regardless, it takes more than intuition to create useful tools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Logic&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even if the above axioms were true, how many of these conclusions are logically valid?&lt;lb/&gt;1. Non-tactical puzzles could be generated by identifying challenging positions (as opposed to the current method which is based upon positions where the solution is superior in evaluation to other variations).&lt;lb/&gt;2. The current model for puzzle ratings (based upon "elo") takes many attempts to establish an initial puzzle rating.&lt;lb/&gt;3. Holistic opening preparation can be automated by software, making players understand openings rather than memorize them.&lt;lb/&gt;4. Interesting positions for books are the same as difficult positions, which are the same as complex positions.&lt;lb/&gt;5. By identifying positions which are difficult for low-rated players and easy for high-rated players, one could develop training materials to help players understand common key concepts.&lt;lb/&gt;6. By identifying positions which are difficult for low-rated players and easy for high-rated players, one could develop a diagnostic chess exam which identifies a player's rating and identifies key concepts for improvement.&lt;lb/&gt;7. Large databases contain additional tagged information, such as time control, which would produce significant insight into which positions can be played intuitively. Large databases also indicate player ratings and therefore somehow complexity can be used to identify unique strategies useful for playing at a rating advantage or disadvantage.&lt;lb/&gt;8. Chess players have human personalities.&lt;lb/&gt;9. Opening systems can be devised around an opponent's tendency to seek or to avoid complexity.&lt;lb/&gt;10. Chess players are likely to make errors in difficult positions, unlike engines, and therefore a complexity metric would be an invaluable tool.&lt;lb/&gt;11. Spectating (and honestly, post-game analysis) of top chess games could be enriched by displaying complexity information related to each position, informing spectators who otherwise look at engine evaluations and variations &amp;amp; jump to conclusions.&lt;lb/&gt;12. Complexity varies by variant; for example blitz and correspondence have different complexities for identical positions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, conclusion#11 is valid and others require further research. Anyway, on to Peng's research...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Neural Networks&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper nearly predates efforts by DeepMind, the Leela Chess Zero team, and the Stockfish team which resulted in development of Stockfish-NNUE. We could not have anticipated such rapid developments! Many chess players had opinions that AlphaZero and Leela played much more human-like moves than traditional engines, in much the same manner that decades prior world champion Kasparov was astounded that Deep Blue played human-like sacrifices. Whatever conclusions are drawn may need to be updated since both Stockfish evaluations without NNUE, and Stockfish-NNUE evaluations, have rapidly changed (complementing Stockfish search changes and search parameter changes).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Endgame Scaling&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stockfish evaluations in the middlegame are capped at 10 and in the endgame are capped at 100. As such, it seems unreasonable to deviate from prior research indicating the need for a sigmoid to normalize evaluations before classifying example input moves as blunders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Board Representation&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doing original research allows liberties in methods and models, although considerations offered here differ from those announced and discussed in public interviews by DeepMind's CEO. While I don't fully agree with DeepMind's emphasis on asymmetry and castling rights, I do question the need for an extra bit for White/Black to move. For example, the positions after 1. c3 e5 2. c4 (Black to move) and after 1. e4 c5 (White to move) should have the same relative evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Evaluation Skewness&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is ample prior research about ranking moves. In fact, Peng's research here is predicated on a notion that traditional engines sometimes indicate to spectators that two moves are equally good, despite one resulting in a more difficult position than the other. We cannot be fully certain that players in fact played the best moves, as this is the very concept we are trying to figure out how to measure! Regardless, we have to start somewhere, and this seems like a good first attempt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;head rend="h4"&gt;Summary&lt;/head&gt;&lt;p&gt;I could further nitpick... I criticize because I am impressed and I care about this subject. I am further impressed that results were split by "elo," leading to a discovery that some positions are difficult for all players, whereas some positions are more difficult for lower-rated players than for higher-rated players.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other possible improvements could involve:&lt;lb/&gt;* Obtain segmented Stockfish evaluations (material, pawn structure, etc.) and WDL statistics&lt;lb/&gt;* Obtain Stockfish-NNUE evaluations and WDL predictions&lt;lb/&gt;* Model checks in sample input&lt;lb/&gt;* Model log(time remaining) in sample input&lt;lb/&gt;* Maybe bootstrap models based upon known pawn concepts&lt;lb/&gt;* Maybe include some human versus engine games. Some bots such as Boris-Trapsky and TurtleBot have personalities!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the suggestion and someday I hope to see Lichess.org or some other site implement a complexity metric before cheaters do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Photo credit: Pacto Visual&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45089256</guid></item></channel></rss>